<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HAE171650F2124A1ABEE65567237EE824" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 3402 IH: Calling Card Consumer Protection
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-08-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 3402</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20070803">August 3, 2007</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000179">Mr. Engel</sponsor> (for
			 himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000443">Mr. Ferguson</cosponsor>, and
			 <cosponsor name-id="T000326">Mr. Towns</cosponsor>) introduced the following
			 bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee
			 on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To require accurate and reasonable disclosure of the
		  terms and conditions of prepaid telephone calling cards and
		  services.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HC289361AAC004ECE9DC6EE63D98E83A4" style="OLC">
		<section id="HA111D80D826041F5BD3441E597151C72" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Calling Card Consumer Protection
			 Act</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="HFBEBFAA0262349718F70913CE7A13EAF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text>
			<paragraph id="H04904BCFB9F340BF9390FE81E4A7381C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the prepaid
			 telephone calling card industry in the United States is plagued by fraudulent
			 and deceptive business practices; and</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCAC83ED2469B45A5A4372DBFA3DB117B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the necessary protections relating to
			 prepaid telephone calling cards must ensure that all advertising is truthful,
			 accurate, and reasonably discloses the terms and conditions of prepaid
			 telephone calling cards and prepaid telephone calling services.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="HB85B2BBA5E02492592A58E6F220332AB"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">As used in this Act, the following
			 definition apply:</text>
			<paragraph id="HDE680D9985B84E69931E2135BA04E077"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>prepaid telephone calling
			 service provider</term> means any entity, corporation, company, association,
			 firm, partnership, or person providing prepaid telephone calling service to the
			 public using its own, or a resold telecommunications network or voice over
			 Internet technology.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H5A312999FA3F4C86BBFCDF61A476FF00"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>prepaid telephone calling service</term> or <quote>service</quote> means
			 any prepaid telecommunications service that allows consumers to originate calls
			 through a local, long distance or toll-free access number and authorization
			 code, whether manually or electronically dialed. Such term shall not include
			 any service that provides access to a wireless telecommunications service
			 account wherein the purchaser has a pre-existing relationship with the wireless
			 service provider or establishes a carrier-customer relationship via the
			 purchase of the object.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H910BB0A6C6CC4FB5824F443C259015ED"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>prepaid telephone calling
			 card</term> or <term>card</term> means any right of use purchased for a sum
			 certain that contains an access number and authorization code that enables a
			 consumer to use a prepaid telephone calling service. Such rights of use may be
			 embodied on a card or other physical object or may be purchased by an
			 electronic or telephonic means through which the purchaser obtains access
			 numbers and authorization codes that are not physically located on a card, its
			 packaging, an Internet website, or other promotional materials. Such term shall
			 not include cards or other rights of use that provide access to—</text>
				<subparagraph id="H3E17AC73480148598301B825847CC511"><enum>(A)</enum><text>telecommunications
			 service wherein the card or other rights of use and telecommunications service
			 are provided for free or at no additional charge as a promotional item
			 accompanying a product or service purchased by a consumer; or</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6264B51550F14C0BAFEBA3936DD29B65"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a wireless
			 telecommunications service account wherein the purchaser has a pre-existing
			 relationship with the wireless service provider or establishes a
			 carrier-customer relationship via the purchase of the object.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD9E81F147F04E2CA93FBA81CA3FBCD7"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>prepaid telephone calling
			 card distributor</term> means any entity, corporation, company, association,
			 firm, partnership, or person that purchases prepaid telephone calling cards
			 from a prepaid telephone calling card provider or distributor and sells,
			 re-sells, issues, or distributes such cards to one or more distributors of such
			 cards or to one or more retail sellers of such cards. Such term shall not
			 include any retail merchants or sellers of prepaid telephone calling cards
			 exclusively engaged in point-of-sale transactions with end-user
			 customers.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="HE9F6BEB3AE994D988744CB6170146363"><enum>4.</enum><header>Required
			 disclosures of prepaid telephone calling cards or services</header>
			<subsection id="HC8C8B2DE161C478389F15E193B9141DA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Required
			 disclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any prepaid
			 telephone calling service provider or prepaid telephone calling card
			 distributors shall disclose the following information relating to the terms and
			 conditions of the prepaid telephone calling card or service:</text>
				<paragraph id="H285E030789AE4DD6B1DB4610F696247C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total value in dollars or the number of
			 calling minutes available of the prepaid telephone calling card or service at
			 the time of purchase.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H9018BB7344A94DAF8478F95D008EA567"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of any and all terms and
			 conditions pertaining to, and associated with, the use of the prepaid telephone
			 calling service and prepaid telephone calling card, including all fees,
			 limitations on the use of minutes available, and surcharges and applicable
			 policies relating to refund, recharge, decrement, and expiration.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HC48BC6A3923A4CD4849CA301145849E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The name of the prepaid telephone calling
			 service provider.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H7AD75B25D6134506A3F1B79F2F9ECF8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The prepaid
			 telephone calling service provider’s customer service telephone number and
			 hours of service.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H1C3C72D52E814BEAA1708EE7CC004DC4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Location of
			 disclosure and language requirement</header>
				<paragraph id="HE4501D8D12E0461299B28BB653D8E459"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Clear and
			 conspicuous</header>
					<subparagraph id="HAE359553C60E4A7784CC4916D7BBC3F9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Cards</header><text>In
			 the case of a prepaid telephone calling card, the disclosures required under
			 subsection (a) shall be printed in plain English language in a clear and
			 conspicuous location on the prepaid telephone calling card or its packaging. If
			 the card is enclosed in opaque packaging, such disclosures shall be printed on
			 the outside packaging of the card.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC40C807B43A84F3D9CB94C643B6D7991"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Online
			 services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a
			 prepaid telephone calling service that consumers access and purchase via the
			 Internet, the disclosures required under subsection (a) shall be displayed in
			 plain English language in a clear and conspicuous location on the Internet site
			 that the consumer must access prior to purchasing such service.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36F44D32F45047169BBA732F9EC7EEB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Advertising and
			 other promotional material</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The disclosures required under subsection
			 (a) shall also be printed on any advertising for the prepaid telephone calling
			 card or service, including on any signs for display by retail merchants, any
			 promotional emails, any Internet site used to promote such card or service, and
			 on any other promotional material.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H595A394211224864845BBA3CC4940091"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign
			 languages</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a language other
			 than English is predominantly used on a prepaid telephone calling card, its
			 packaging, or in point of sale advertising, or promotional material of a
			 prepaid telephone calling card or prepaid telephone calling service, then the
			 disclosures required by this section shall be disclosed in that language on
			 such card, packaging, advertisement, or promotional material.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H46B89BB779A64F8B8482C5CEC096E700"><enum>5.</enum><header>Unlawful conduct
			 related to prepaid telephone calling cards</header>
			<subsection id="H917F6D7845A74695B8BFA6532276D125"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Undisclosed fees
			 and charges</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be
			 unlawful for any prepaid telephone calling service provider or prepaid
			 telephone calling card distributor to assess any fee associated with the
			 prepaid telephone calling card or prepaid telephone calling service, or impose
			 any charge for any permitted use of the prepaid telephone calling card or
			 prepaid telephone calling service if such fee or charge is not disclosed as
			 required under section 4.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HCF0E5158DB224B6DA344C8E0CE76B2B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Minutes as
			 promoted and advertised</header>
				<paragraph id="HB023E369A4444414A012951DC5EFFF4F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Service
			 provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful
			 for any prepaid telephone calling service provider to provide fewer minutes
			 than the number of minutes promoted or advertised on any prepaid telephone
			 calling card, any point of sale material relating to such card or the other
			 advertising related to any prepaid telephone calling card or service. Any
			 limitation on the period of time for which the displayed, promoted, or
			 advertised minutes will be available to the customer shall be conspicuously
			 displayed on the card, packaging, and promotional material that lists the
			 minutes, consistent with section 4(b).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H5AA7FDB5635143FCB13F7C7C51004696"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Distributor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful for any prepaid
			 telephone calling card distributor to distribute any prepaid telephone calling
			 card that the distributor knows that the prepaid telephone calling card
			 provides fewer minutes than the number of minutes promoted or advertised on any
			 prepaid telephone calling card, any point of sale material relating to such
			 card, any voice prompt indicating the number of minutes available, or other
			 advertising relating to any prepaid telephone calling card or service. Any
			 limitations on the period of time for which the displayed, promoted, or
			 advertised minutes will be available to the customer shall be conspicuously
			 displayed on the card, packaging, and promotional material that lists the
			 minutes, consistent with section 4(b).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE49B2D56F9E64F83A7168BF0DB758652"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Minutes Promoted
			 and Advertised Through Voice Prompts</header>
				<paragraph id="H2C4A26D82BE64D798FA570E18B3F1B93"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Service
			 provider</header><text>It shall be unlawful for any prepaid telephone calling
			 service provider to provide fewer minutes than the number of minutes promoted
			 or advertised through any voice prompt given to a customer at the time the
			 customer places a call to a dialed destination with the prepaid telephone
			 calling card or service.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H2537058664F2470F00E907AEA96AEC2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Distributor</header><text>It
			 shall be unlawful for any prepaid telephone calling card distributor to
			 distribute prepaid telephone calling cards that it knows provide fewer minutes
			 than the number of minutes promoted or advertised through any voice prompt
			 given to a customer at the time the customer places a call to a dialed
			 destination with the prepaid telephone calling card or service.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB29C5D4E794F4179A23237803F979944"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Expiration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Unless a different expiration date is
			 clearly disclosed pursuant to the disclosure requirements under section 4, it
			 shall be unlawful for any prepaid telephone calling service provider or prepaid
			 telephone calling card distributor to provide, issue, resell, or distribute a
			 prepaid telephone calling card or service that expires—</text>
				<paragraph id="HD9AB82AFFE634EFE8B00F17272D2B957"><enum>(1)</enum><text>after a period of
			 less than 1 year from the date on which such card or service is first used;
			 or</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H52C57AEF09B04794BC72883232117B27"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of a
			 prepaid telephone calling card or service that permits the consumer to purchase
			 additional usage minutes or add additional value to the card or service, after
			 a period of less than 1 year from the date on which the consumer last purchased
			 additional usage minutes or added additional value to the card or
			 service.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7D6F5DD03E144ECEAFC3858878E2C405"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Charges for
			 unconnected calls</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be
			 unlawful for any prepaid telephone calling service provider or service to
			 assess any fee or charge for any unconnected telephone call. For purposes of
			 this subsection, a telephone call shall not be considered connected if the
			 person placing the call receives a busy signal or if the call is
			 unanswered.</text>
			</subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H838C1D701A894A40B7EA5CD6FA165FA"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Liability</header><text>Liability
			 under this section may not be avoided by stating that the displayed, promoted,
			 or advertised minutes are subject to fees or charges, or by utilizing other
			 disclaimers or limitations.</text>
			</subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H2F0D9698886A4B23AFF18879ACF05CB1"><enum>6.</enum><header>Enforcement by
			 the Federal Trade Commission</header>
			<subsection commented="no" id="H3CF4CA9E71214E11AC9077EF003D177C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Unfair and
			 deceptive act or practice</header><text>A violation of section 4 or 5 shall be
			 treated as a violation of a rule defining an unfair or deceptive act or
			 practice prescribed under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the Federal Trade Commission
			 Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>).</text>
			</subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H57F0F39C5AD3407BA7782883EF9D0220"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authority of the
			 Commission</header><text>The Federal Trade Commission shall enforce this Act in
			 the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction as though
			 all applicable terms and provisions of the Federal Trade Commission Act were
			 incorporated into and made a part of this Act.</text>
			</subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H8142078C7D9A45118076F8F6A25CE883"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rulemaking
			 authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may
			 issue regulations to carry out this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HCEE773ADD5E64807893D36DE5EB31EA3"><enum>7.</enum><header>State
			 enforcement</header>
			<subsection id="HF0776342973A47F5AD7BA2917B0755EC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 General</header>
				<paragraph id="H7974A723BA794071BDB0E74EBBB01E42"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Civil
			 actions</header><text>In any case in which the attorney general of a State has
			 reason to believe that an interest of the residents of that State has been or
			 is threatened or adversely affected by the engagement of any person in a
			 practice that is prohibited under this Act, the State, as parens patriae, may
			 bring a civil action on behalf of the residents of that State in a district
			 court of the United States of appropriate jurisdiction, or any other court of
			 competent jurisdiction—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H5D17E2F33CFF40628100492E6D14444D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to enjoin that
			 practice;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8DECBE9D21E64D5382413F7D32792D85"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to enforce
			 compliance with this Act;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA674E169CD7A4EE180E92282FD22C232"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to obtain damage,
			 restitution, or other compensation on behalf of residents of the State ;
			 or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1E79DD9E6DBF45D1BDCC35B555159E00"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to obtain such
			 other relief as the court may consider to be appropriate.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H72C8352CD358423EA9FFDCB7CD313919"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice to
			 F.T.C</header>
					<subparagraph id="HC333BAC073154CD8BB1800501137A771"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Before filing an action under paragraph (1), the attorney
			 general of a State shall provide to the Commission—</text>
						<clause id="HC02690CA4E214573B56DC7C3230006B7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>written notice of
			 the action ; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="HD90CBA4E731B4AE9A15496DC56E6604F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a
			 copy of the complaint for the action.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE0EB09070CCE4BF9932FA17B1EEACCE4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exemption</header>
						<clause id="H51323BB105F9479D856D83171BD00F4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply with respect to the
			 filing of an action by an attorney general of a State under this subsection, if
			 the attorney general of a State determines that it is not feasible to provide
			 the notice described in that subparagraph before the filing of the
			 action.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H5821553CF62E4B28888700BD5926D30"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>In
			 an action described in clause (i), the attorney general of a State shall
			 provide notice and a copy of the complaint to the Commission at the same time
			 as the attorney general files the action.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBF7AF891D79C40AA99003841E92CA433"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Intervention by
			 F.T.C</header>
				<paragraph id="H715C0EDD303D411600FC00C982876193"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>On receiving notice under subsection (a)(2), the
			 Commission shall have the right to intervene in the action that is the subject
			 of the notice.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H0D58F821965144969D3997B95C93B5C3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effect of
			 intervention</header><text>If the Commission intervenes in an action under
			 subsection (a), it shall have the right—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HA9CE5A8F98DA45E0AADD93FD47B28681"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to be heard with
			 respect to any matter that arises in that action ; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5FA335A2D1A24BB58E59B5CEFA48CBF8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to file a petition
			 for appeal.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H90C7DA26F83D4115826FE249F2E3FD3E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>For
			 purposes of bringing any civil action under subsection (a), nothing in this Act
			 shall be construed to prevent an attorney general of a State from exercising
			 the powers conferred on the attorney general by the laws of that State—</text>
				<paragraph id="H1C78416D5CF0440690E381E4316787C8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to conduct
			 investigations;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H7B1542E9FF1D4CDC8996706BB9EA400"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to
			 administer oaths or affirmations; or</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H804D292C3CE841549166E80087C3B16"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to
			 compel the attendance of witnesses or the production of documentary and other
			 evidence.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H37370DC793024F44B62DFFC73F1BF1D6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Action by the
			 commission may preclude state action</header><text>In any case in which an
			 action is instituted by or on behalf of the Commission for violation of this
			 Act, no State may, during the pendency of that action , institute an action
			 under subsection (a) against any defendant named in the complaint in that
			 action for violation of that section.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H0320F2151B364A6B0022A5002E8E91B7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Venue; Service
			 of Process</header>
				<paragraph id="HC969CE3D2BD54D08BA91EAC157D32466"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Venue</header><text>Any
			 action brought under subsection (a) may be brought in the district court of the
			 United States that meets applicable requirements relating to venue under
			 <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/28/1391">section 1391</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H3FA78DF8EB324F68A270A6C490F6B100"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Service of
			 process</header><text>In an action brought under subsection (a), process may be
			 served in any district in which the defendant—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HFCF8D7F6B36F4555A4CC8C714195F83E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is an inhabitant;
			 or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B9854881936495B90F21F58D7058FC9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may be
			 found.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


