<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7DDAA8F7AC424EDB8B1072F755459776" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>108th CONGRESS</congress>
<session>2d Session</session>
<legis-num>H. R. 4600</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20040616">June 16, 2004</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="U000031">Mr. Upton</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M000133">Mr. Markey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000213">Mr. Barton of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000355">Mr. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000657">Mr. Boucher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000459">Mr. Terry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000326">Mr. Towns</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000110">Mr. John</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000179">Mr. Engel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000572">Mr. Rogers of Michigan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001203">Mr. Buyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001036">Mrs. Capps</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000784">Mr. Wynn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000309">Mr. Gordon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000210">Mr. Gillmor</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000410">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001228">Mrs. Bono</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000822">Mr. Stearns</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000323">Mr. Pickering</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000114">Mr. Davis of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001135">Mr. Burr</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000364">Mr. Shimkus</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000544">Mr. Gonzalez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend section 227 of the Communications Act of 1934 to clarify the prohibition on junk fax transmissions.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H9AA32C96A7134B2D8DBC616136D07700" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7939304A76344E6886FA4E4272432117" section-type="section-one" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Junk Fax Prevention Act of 2004</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H2A692C50B9CC4365B3B2429C6F007375"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on fax transmissions containing unsolicited advertisements</header> 
<subsection id="H152968F6FC63479387D046D9DA52CC9C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>Subparagraph (C) of section 227(b)(1) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/227">47 U.S.C. 227(b)(1)(C)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFA037646F1B844A6A73404E4DF3130C1" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="HE935B6EDE10448C284DE6460B396F8A6"><enum>(C)</enum><text> to use any telephone facsimile machine, computer, or other device to send, to a telephone facsimile machine, an unsolicited advertisement—</text> 
<clause id="H21CA76AE0AC64687A94B2C90C077D200"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to a person who has made a request to such sender that complies with the requirements under paragraph (2)(D), not to send future unsolicited advertisements to a telephone facsimile machine; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HCCDAE058EE9E463A9CD434D017791B26"><enum>(ii)</enum><text> to a person not described in clause (i), unless—</text> 
<subclause id="HAFBDF265F4AD463DB13700F2503313CD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the sender has an established business relationship (which term, for purposes of this subclause, shall have the meaning given the term in section 64.1200 of the Commission’s regulations, as in effect on January 1, 2003, except that such term shall include a relationship between a person or entity and a business subscriber subject to the same terms applicable under such section to a relationship between a person or entity and a residential subscriber) with such person; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H7EEAE2F2D3734DBB98B1555DAF003B2E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the unsolicited advertisement contains a conspicuous notice on the first page of the unsolicited advertisement that—</text> 
<item id="HA3A84229A87F4EF4A541A35F34CF592C"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>states that the recipient may make a request to the sender of the unsolicited advertisement not to send any future unsolicited advertisements to such telephone facsimile machine and that failure to comply, within the shortest reasonable time, as determined by the Commission, with such a request meeting the requirements under paragraph (2)(D) is unlawful;</text></item> 
<item id="H264D62443FD54C999E111D69B8FB4F0"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>sets forth the requirements for a request under paragraph (2)(D); and</text></item> 
<item id="H96708CEBBB0E48EFB6AEB9DFFC8C1F51"><enum>(cc)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes a domestic contact telephone and facsimile number for the recipient to transmit such a request to the sender, neither of which may be a number for a pay-per-call service (as such term is defined in section 228(i)); any number supplied shall permit an individual or business to make a do-not-fax request during regular business hours; or</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3A08F1A71D3D4CDA87B08FEFAF4EEC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Request to opt-out of future unsolicited advertisements</header><text>Paragraph (2) of section 227(b) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/227">47 U.S.C. 227(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2A946AF6741D4B6182A8DC6CBF00D5D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9EA10E92018C4F0F9B88ED9EE7A474EF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H61AA581FA9874B5794F777F2849D35CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraphs:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2AA6409F5D9F4B7BAE3EB04801BA484D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="H14984BB12DBF44A7A08D811C55AB20F1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shall provide, by rule, that a request not to send future unsolicited advertisements to a telephone facsimile machine complies with the requirements under this subparagraph only if—</text> 
<clause id="H795A4CC431B84F6FB0DF1BD63B27746F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the request identifies the telephone number of the telephone facsimile machine to which the request relates;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1354163F771E42B19F55C2EE615ED100"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the request is made to the telephone or facsimile number of the sender of such an unsolicited advertisement provided pursuant to paragraph (1)(C)(ii)(II)(cc) or by any other method of communication as determined by the Commission; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB28315F4C5B942AAAAE4C3BEC151C84"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the person making the request has not, subsequent to such request, provided express invitation or permission to the sender, in writing or otherwise, to send such advertisements to such person at such telephone facsimile machine; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4DE40DFA91574E6D975C3DA0BE15200"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may, in the discretion of the Commission and subject to such conditions as the Commission may prescribe, allow professional trade associations that are tax-exempt nonprofit organizations to send unsolicited advertisements to their members in furtherance of the association’s tax-exempt purpose that do not contain the notice required by paragraph (1)(C)(ii)(II), except that the Commission may take action under this subparagraph only by regulation issued after notice and opportunity for public comment in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/553">section 553</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, and only if the Commission determines that such notice is not necessary to protect the right of the members of such trade associations to make a request to their trade associations not to send any future unsolicited advertisements.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3275827EB7914E9B8C9D06C2C8324C72"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Unsolicited advertisement</header><text>Paragraph (4) of section 227(a) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/227">47 U.S.C. 227(a)(4)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>, in writing or otherwise</quote> before the period at the end.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4FCFBC8F39084369913608ADE99F78E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Federal Communications Commission shall issue regulations to implement the amendments made by this section.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HF07BF3E43B7A4246A436FD6CAB6029D6" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>3.</enum><header> FCC annual report regarding junk fax enforcement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 227 of the Communications Act of 1934 (47 U. S.C. 227) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H5F8F6152930A4ACB958962AD137860E" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HE32B516FAC784D99A131E8A9F275D943"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Junk Fax Enforcement Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall submit a report to the Congress for each year regarding the enforcement of the provisions of this section relating to sending of unsolicited advertisements to telephone facsimile machines, which shall include the following information:</text> 
<paragraph id="HE1303BB53F164E47BD6EA7FB087485A4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of complaints received by the Commission during such year alleging that a consumer received an unsolicited advertisement via telephone facsimile machine in violation of the Commission’s rules.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3DE445A0706E4533950401E50303513D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of such complaints received during the year on which the Commission has taken action.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF819010DD1EE424CAC929255DDDA6BB9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The number of such complaints that remain pending at the end of the year.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB6AA70C0CB64461A905809F46F437149"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of citations issued by the Commission pursuant to section 503 during the year to enforce any law, regulation, or policy relating to sending of unsolicited advertisements to telephone facsimile machines.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAC1131A0675A4E249C66B9782B3F5F3F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The number of notices of apparent liability issued by the Commission pursuant to section 503 during the year to enforce any law, regulation, or policy relating to sending of unsolicited advertisements to telephone facsimile machines.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE732C5BCDBDE4E07BDECE39E47996D62"><enum>(6)</enum><text>For each such notice—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H77FE0C6E306D43799F8DC9DBDD56D100"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount of the proposed forfeiture penalty involved;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC0820DA341F449899704458E98A0D3B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the person to whom the notice was issued;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAA37F92ACE1E4A6E9F6D6BBF162105CF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the length of time between the date on which the complaint was filed and the date on which the notice was issued; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H86D9F8F86636448588A05BBB1D893458"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the status of the proceeding.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H421868C9076B4162B3E86735CD7058A6"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The number of final orders imposing forfeiture penalties issued pursuant to section 503 during the year to enforce any law, regulation, or policy relating to sending of unsolicited advertisements to telephone facsimile machines.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD514E2FF2B99489084FEC39C4E052C55"><enum>(8)</enum><text>For each such forfeiture order—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H48099EE1CC6A4AC190BAB3A79F28E62C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount of the penalty imposed by the order;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H23ECBDBDEACE4C02B43FD7B14E36D8F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the person to whom the order was issued;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H499804F57042409CB82D1D8959D0AD68"><enum>(C)</enum><text>whether the forfeiture penalty has been paid; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H376E20A83AB047B797FBFAE459D6EC78"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the amount paid.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H84D778D7489E4D16B727D0112BB5323F"><enum>(9)</enum><text>For each case in which a person has failed to pay a forfeiture penalty imposed by such a final order, whether the Commission referred such matter to the Attorney General for recovery of the penalty.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE0DEC532EACF4526B759CBBC2B13530"><enum>(10)</enum><text>For each case in which the Commission referred such an order to the Attorney General—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H579AF63FBE9945E49432978213C147FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of days from the date the Commission issued such order to the date of such referral;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE8F760780A8E4CC4941CB07D832302B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whether the Attorney General has commenced an action to recover the penalty, and if so, the number of days from the date the Commission referred such order to the Attorney General to the date of such commencement; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H313806D1711845F1B7A68C22F0778E2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>whether the recovery action resulted in collection of any amount, and if so, the amount collected.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HE58FAC82D7D94C70B41182ECC6720062"><enum>4.</enum><header>GAO study of junk fax enforcement</header> 
<subsection id="HC877BD54A3EE45A7A385F2921E52D6CE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study regarding complaints received by the Federal Communications Commission concerning unsolicited advertisements sent to telephone facsimile machines, which shall determine—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF70E835BCBCB4E1CAC9CB824202401D2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number and nature of such complaints;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9EFE84E9515B475D8CD374E0AF87D9B1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of such complaints that result in final agency actions by the Commission;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF42370ECE73D4137AD805C07639281A3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the length of time taken by the Commission in responding to such complaints;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCFBCAAD620144897A0FBB621B718BF6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the mechanisms established by the Commission to receive, investigate, and respond to such complaints;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H510C38865F1949B0A9DD1D2871A5F7C1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the level of enforcement success achieved by the Commission and the Attorney General regarding such complaints;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7E3D8F1BFEE3405F97FA0850357EAAFF"><enum>(6)</enum><text>whether complainants to the Commission are adequately informed by the Commission of the responses to their complaints; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6305C19830E4418E8DDFF2153B028943"><enum>(7)</enum><text>whether additional enforcement measures are necessary to protect consumers, including recommendations regarding such additional enforcement measures.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB1FED7955519452E00A2F1E392C030C0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional enforcement remedies</header><text>In conducting the analysis and making the recommendations required under paragraph (7) of subsection (a), the Comptroller General shall specifically examine—</text> 
<paragraph id="H061445989F6D45F9A711AA3045A845A0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the adequacy of existing statutory enforcement actions available to the Commission;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H32950C2CDB34414F8700412E96656E94"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the adequacy of existing statutory enforcement actions and remedies available to consumers;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD4558180E2EE482297F5A54B95212EC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the impact of existing statutory enforcement remedies on senders of facsimiles;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2C860E42BC7B4C31AAD940C63CF3E9AA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>whether increasing the amount of financial penalties is warranted to achieve greater deterrent effect; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA17F54922DD04DC9B08F7C4E07213C2C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>whether establishing penalties and enforcement actions for repeat violators or abusive violations similar to those established by section 4 of the CAN–SPAM Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/7703">15 U.S.C. 7703</external-xref>) would have a greater deterrent effect.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H34B4FFC716E5460ABE91F38FC152F01"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit a report on the results of the study under this section to Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 



