<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H6388C316D52840789C1FB347BC9591BB" public-private="public">
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>112th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 3016</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20110922">September 22, 2011</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001252">Mr. Barrow</sponsor> introduced
			 the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed
			 Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on
			 <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name>, for a
			 period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for
			 consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the
			 committee concerned</action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To direct the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of
		  Veterans Affairs to jointly operate the Federal Recovery Coordination Program,
		  and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H9810D032A5AC4A27966FEC95EBF51530" style="OLC">
		<section id="H0A58C5448BD24397A9759B78D42C8F59" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Joint operation of Federal
			 Recovery Coordination Program</header>
			<subsection id="H5D5C912C726240ACA858E6D8632D8992"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal Recovery
			 Coordination Program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In
			 carrying out the Federal Recovery Coordination Program (in this section
			 referred to as the <term>Program</term>), the Secretary of Defense and the
			 Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall ensure that—</text>
				<paragraph id="HE2EED41CBB5A4F44AF8906E82C27A0FB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the program is operated jointly by the
			 Secretaries;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H5F6CAAC20D4F42B480B7028E598881BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the administration of the Program is not
			 delegated to an individual outside the respective office of each
			 Secretary;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H0170529B97A946B483A8D10B7C573AC1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the program
			 assists—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H4375EBA8D67443A9ACA92464D95A4FE2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">members of the Armed Forces with severe or
			 catastrophic injuries or illnesses who are unlikely to return to active duty
			 and will most likely be medically separated under chapter 61 of title 10,
			 United States Code; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H134BE12DF5944EA0AD730F17CF1758B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>members of the
			 Armed Forces and veterans whose individual circumstances (including illness,
			 injury, mental health, family situation, and unique benefit needs) are
			 determined by the Secretary concerned to cause difficulties to the member or
			 veteran in transitioning to civilian life;</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA44378E4C2C464F96422D7721FEE6C6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in referring
			 members and veterans described in paragraph (3) to the Program, the Secretary
			 of each military department and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs makes such
			 referrals at the earliest time feasible, including by the date that is 180 days
			 before the last day of the month in which a member is expected to be retired or
			 separated from the Armed Forces; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H2760CC24425945FB8290EA2566B59CD1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each department and agency of the Federal
			 Government, including the Department of Defense and the Department of Veterans
			 Affairs, provides a Federal Recovery Coordinator of the Program with the
			 information, coordination, and cooperation necessary for the Coordinator to
			 assist members and veterans participating in the Program, including the maximum
			 amount of information, coordination, and cooperation available to allow the
			 Coordinator to—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H540AE57CC1D549B38A9063611B450645"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure the efficient recovery, transition,
			 and reintegration of such members and veterans;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30DBBF95AA19468088B62EB27DC6618F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>act as a liaison
			 between such members and veterans and the team of care providers and other
			 personnel involved with the recovery, transition, and reintegration of the
			 member or veteran, regardless of whether such team is under the Secretary of
			 Defense or the Secretary of Veterans Affairs; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBD15DD02FFD455E9CCDC11E060D7066"><enum>(C)</enum><text>work closely with
			 case and care-management programs that assist such members and veterans.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A4B6CBFF2474C2EA690FBDC4CBAE810"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Plan and
			 memorandum of understanding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of
			 the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of
			 Veterans Affairs shall—</text>
				<paragraph id="H3B23AD639D914F2DBACC5C72A398C89E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">jointly develop a plan to carry out
			 subsection (a);</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H3B3F77B9F5CD47599D199556D98CAAF2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>enter into a
			 memorandum of understanding to jointly carry out the plan beginning 90 days
			 after the date on which the memorandum is entered into; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H406FA88B059E4AA982FF9870C1AE8A43"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">jointly submit to the appropriate
			 congressional committees such plan and memorandum.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0B01D60D353E4093AEA28FFE2D841063"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date on
			 which the memorandum of understanding under paragraph (2) of subsection (b)
			 goes into effect, the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans
			 Affairs shall jointly submit to the appropriate congressional committees a
			 report describing and evaluating the implementation of such memorandum and plan
			 under paragraph (1) of such subsection.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HF8D4C0E29E484FA68E74FF4E96A65A60"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Appropriate
			 congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term
			 <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the following:</text>
				<paragraph id="H0E226E270B1C46FA8018EE17387D1BD4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Committees on
			 Armed Services of the House of Representatives and Senate.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H3E767CE44C0348F796FE9850FFA49E3E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Committees on
			 Veterans' Affairs of the House of Representatives and Senate.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>
