<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HD3BA2726E4FA45EFAEFCAB36746A04FF" public-private="public">
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>111th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 1327</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20090305">March 5, 2009</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000339">Mr. Frank of
			 Massachusetts</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B000410">Mr.
			 Berman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, and
			 <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the
			 following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial
			 Services</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To authorize State and local governments to direct
		  divestiture from, and prevent investment in, companies with investments of
		  $20,000,000 or more in Iran’s energy sector, and for other
		  purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H47F47C3369F040D7AE328CA1DADAF26C" style="OLC">
		<section id="H96E977A02C354E7899164D6D4046E398" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Iran Sanctions Enabling Act of
			 2009</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H4AA28DDF66B14675A22C688B6F20BFE4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds as follows:</text>
			<paragraph id="HF51B9C22D7D144F88B0780F005EF25F3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>There is an
			 increasing interest by States, local governments, educational institutions, and
			 private institutions to seek to disassociate themselves from companies that
			 directly or indirectly support the Government of Iran’s efforts to achieve a
			 nuclear weapons capability.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HAD4517602A4542F9A2E27D603778B781"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Policy makers and
			 fund managers may find moral, prudential, or reputational reasons to divest
			 from companies that accept the business risk of operating in countries that are
			 subject to international economic sanctions or that have business relationships
			 with countries, governments, or entities with which any United States company
			 would be prohibited from dealing because of economic sanctions imposed by the
			 United States.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H12CCC40251D3409C83482E0DA7A51380"><enum>3.</enum><header>Authority of
			 State and local governments to divest from certain companies invested in Iran’s
			 energy sector</header>
			<subsection id="H8C8F618DCAF840D3994BEEF537A5A08D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Statement of
			 policy</header><text>It is the policy of the United States to support the
			 decision of State governments, local governments, and educational institutions
			 to divest from, and to prohibit the investment of assets they control in,
			 persons that have investments of more than $20,000,000 in Iran’s energy
			 sector.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H960A3896268C40EBBBEF3EF22063E125"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authority To
			 divest</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a State or
			 local government may adopt and enforce measures that meet the requirements of
			 subsection (d) to divest the assets of the State or local government from, or
			 prohibit investment of the assets of the State or local government in, any
			 person that the State or local government determines, using credible
			 information available to the public, engages in investment activities in Iran
			 described in subsection (c).</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HBD7E6D22F3544A4D93885D1A72DAAE4A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Investment
			 activities in Iran described</header><text>A person engages in investment
			 activities in Iran described in this subsection if the person—</text>
				<paragraph id="H870D0F39B0574B7293F386F676703B4A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has an investment
			 of $20,000,000 or more—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H445788FE1C82427095FDA465E34D9E46"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the energy
			 sector of Iran; or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H56E90AA9BE094CE0BF440F8BF9B6CC2D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in a person that
			 provides oil or liquified natural gas tankers, or products used to construct or
			 maintain pipelines used to transport oil or liquified natural gas, for the
			 energy sector in Iran; or</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4949E91BA18B4B8380D698C5DEAE2BE6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is a financial
			 institution that extends $20,000,000 or more in credit to another person, for
			 45 days or more, if that person will use the credit to invest in the energy
			 sector in Iran.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7181ABAC786844359E3702ABD8FF6D8A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The
			 requirements referred to in subsection (b) that a measure taken by a State or
			 local government must meet are the following:</text>
				<paragraph id="H619C5E12AC7640248F1E99CAD94118CE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The State or local government shall provide
			 written notice to each person to whom the State or local government, as the
			 case may be, intends to apply the measure, of such intent.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HBFE52719161B485383EECE31ED15EEBA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The measure shall apply to a person not
			 earlier than the date that is 90 days after the date on which the person
			 receives the written notice required by paragraph (1).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H607C8265125F4403AB34E118C960D1D0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Opportunity for
			 hearing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The State or local
			 government shall provide each person referred to in paragraph (1) with an
			 opportunity to demonstrate to the State or local government, as the case may
			 be, that the person does not engage in investment activities in Iran described
			 in subsection (c). If the person demonstrates to the State or local government
			 that the person does not engage in investment activities in Iran described in
			 subsection (c), the measure shall not apply to the person.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H425A238B2A444649B54C93A78362D48A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Sense of the
			 Congress on avoiding erroneous targeting</header><text>It is the sense of the
			 Congress that a State or local government should not adopt a measure under
			 subsection (b) with respect to a person unless the State or local government
			 has made every effort to avoid erroneously targeting the person and has
			 verified that the person engages in investment activities in Iran described in
			 subsection (c).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H03AB481D858D4263BCF97E7681413615"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Notice to
			 Department of Justice</header><text>Not later than 30 days after adopting a
			 measure pursuant to subsection (b), a State or local government shall submit to
			 the Attorney General of the United States a written notice which describes the
			 measure.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H4D9FB7DA602C42EA865B63CA60F78259"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Nonpreemption</header><text>A
			 measure of a State or local government authorized under subsection (b) is not
			 preempted by any Federal law or regulation.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HBE8C99FE7C4945D38DBD7EFA34431CE7"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In
			 this section:</text>
				<paragraph id="HE63B1E3E912C415CA4EEE8D0DAEBDAE1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Investment</header><text>The
			 <quote>investment</quote> of assets, with respect to a State or local
			 government, includes—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HD08D5FF534854874AD073C79B18630B6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a commitment or
			 contribution of assets;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17167BA70E1F4570AECFCD784F4DBD8C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a loan or other
			 extension of credit; or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A802AF41440402688F6E6AE067EAD2E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the entry into or
			 renewal of a contract for goods or services.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEAEFAC3C5AD48CFB0E76DADBF3801A7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assets</header>
					<subparagraph id="H432229B13D2F455C9F201BBEBC2728ED"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the term
			 <term>assets</term> refers to public monies and includes any pension,
			 retirement, annuity, or endowment fund, or similar instrument, that is
			 controlled directly or indirectly by a State or local government.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7174CFA6F3BD482689D1CCDB78242731"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The
			 term <term>assets</term> does not include employee benefit plans covered by
			 title I of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (29 U.S.C. 1001
			 et seq.).</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H894D953ED5D94BEA9595C627F27A0052"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Effective
			 date</header>
				<paragraph id="H1AB9E735303E484CA9596EDDD0E7C410"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), this section shall
			 apply to measures adopted by a State or local government before, on, or after
			 the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HF007B26519F7400B90BE5A85CFAB96F7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice
			 requirements</header><text>Subsections (d) and (e) apply to measures adopted by
			 a State or local government on or after the date of the enactment of this
			 Act.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7631EC62ACC4499E98E926DFAA1DC5A1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Safe harbor for
			 changes of investment policies by asset managers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 13(c)(1) of the Investment Company
			 Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a–13(c)(1)) is amended by inserting before the period
			 the following: <quote>or engage in investment activities in Iran described in
			 section 3(c) of the Iran Sanctions Enabling Act of 2009</quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H3F462550DD724D41A59C34A5E0E4BB85"><enum>5.</enum><header>Sense of Congress
			 regarding certain ERISA plan investments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that a fiduciary
			 of an employee benefit plan, as defined in section 3(3) of the Employee
			 Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (29 U.S.C. 1002(3)), may divest plan
			 assets from, or avoid investing plan assets in, any person the fiduciary
			 determines engages in investment activities in Iran described in section 3(c)
			 of this Act, without breaching the responsibilities, obligations, or duties
			 imposed upon the fiduciary by section 404 of the Employee Retirement Income
			 Security Act of 1974 (29 U.S.C. 1104), if—</text>
			<paragraph id="HE8BC1320D38F4BCC8FA2E44748796D72"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the fiduciary
			 makes such determination using credible information that is available to the
			 public; and</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H4FFCA4653D084E3BBE0D6B08EE81A878"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such divestment or
			 avoidance of investment is conducted in accordance with section 2509.94–1 of
			 title 29, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the day before the date
			 of the enactment of this Act).</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H886EF338059346D894FB82B5AABA6DBC"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title:</text>
			<paragraph id="HB46E69920BB748D18FD0E42E67B823BF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Energy
			 sector</header><text>The term <term>energy sector</term> refers to activities
			 to develop petroleum or natural gas resources or nuclear power.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HF217285021964521B3186B653925BB8F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Financial
			 institution</header><text>The term <term>financial institution</term> has the
			 meaning given that term in section 14(5) of the Iran Sanctions Act of 1996
			 (Public Law 104–172; 50 U.S.C. 1701 note).</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HC21AE4D784454B18820E660FF662B38F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Iran</header><text>The
			 term <term>Iran</term> includes any agency or instrumentality of Iran.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HF16E9B0A1A43442E9CBC38F0BA470571"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Person</header><text>The
			 term <term>person</term> means—</text>
				<subparagraph id="H133DB7A513E24E0798BDF377BD7FE157"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a natural person,
			 corporation, company, business association, partnership, society, trust, or any
			 other nongovernmental entity, organization, or group;</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18545EB48DF44F0D8FA86D7011E73367"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any governmental
			 entity or instrumentality of a government, including a multilateral development
			 institution (as defined in section 1701(c)(3) of the International Financial
			 Institutions Act (22 U.S.C. 262r(c)(3))); and</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2760921092141B6A322047001190B47"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any successor,
			 subunit, parent company, or subsidiary of any entity described in subparagraph
			 (A) or (B).</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE93F14ABEE4745B7BC0B33C31AEC7C29"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State</header><text>The
			 term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of
			 Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands,
			 Guam, American Samoa, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana
			 Islands.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H845808DFD46B44E3BCF9A7A6E6CBBF97"><enum>(6)</enum><header>State or local
			 government</header><text>The term <term>State or local government</term>
			 includes—</text>
				<subparagraph id="HF60BC81F6B1B4CF591A4A5119946965A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any State and any
			 agency or instrumentality thereof;</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9B8A77462454B0286736D6086EAC8E8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any local
			 government within a State, and any agency or instrumentality thereof;</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC588A59397E54177A8ABB990CDB461E8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other
			 governmental instrumentality; and</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52EB9D6FC1594ED5A1A0A112FA9CD849"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any public
			 institution of higher education within the meaning of the Higher Education Act
			 of 1965 (20 U.S.C. 1001 et seq.).</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H8FF7A5451AFF4E18B6C77120F1C7884C"><enum>7.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act shall terminate 30 days after the
			 date on which the President has certified to the Congress that—</text>
			<paragraph id="H182BC4AF11D54CF5B0C63720169A2E45"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Government of
			 Iran has ceased providing support for acts of international terrorism and no
			 longer satisfies the requirements for designation as a state-sponsor of
			 terrorism for purposes of section 6(j) of the Export Administration Act of
			 1979, section 620A of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, section 40 of the
			 Arms Export Control Act, or any other provision of law; or</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H38792B9D7D424C23A753D4E2CC31A6C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Iran has ceased
			 the pursuit, acquisition, and development of nuclear, biological, and chemical
			 weapons and ballistic missiles and ballistic missile launch technology.</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body>
</bill>
