<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H7038A653D62A4CF888D2C55E90B1E474" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 1315 RH: Amend the title so as to read: </dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-03-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code> 
<calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 168</calendar> 
<congress display="yes">110th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 1315</legis-num> 
<associated-doc display="yes" role="report">[Report No. 110–266]</associated-doc> 
<current-chamber display="yes">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070305">March 5, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001037">Ms. Herseth</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HVR00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<action> 
<action-date>July 27, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc>Reported with amendments, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc> 
<action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to provide specially adaptive housing assistance to certain disabled members of the Armed Forces residing temporarily in housing owned by a family member.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body changed="deleted" committee-id="HVR00" id="H477143EE41A5439999AF54FE032F2C41" reported-display-style="strikethrough" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H790BD2AAAC30413393CE615539A4E9A7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Provision of specially adaptive housing assistance to disabled members of the Armed Forces residing temporarily in housing owned by a family member</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/2102A">Section 2102A</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7E1E05A0D1684B45AB575957EE1E5C6E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (d) and (e) as subsections (e) and (f), respectively; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB0FEE0EE4C7B4E939B30FF391346A6C6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (c) the following new subsection (d):</text> 
<quoted-block changed="deleted" committee-id="HVR00" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE64C5C4235434D259CAC120077A06051" reported-display-style="strikethrough" style="USC"> 
<subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6FEFC64BB87C40FA9D66BFB829B2F438"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Assistance for members of the Armed Forces</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may provide assistance under subsection (a) to a member of the Armed Forces serving on active duty who is suffering from a disability described in subsection (a)(2) or (b)(2) of section 2101 of this title if such disability is the result of an injury incurred or disease contracted in or aggravated in the line of duty in the active military, naval, or air service. Such assistance shall be provided to the same extent as assistance is provided under subsection (a) to veterans eligible for assistance under that subsection and subject to the limitation under subsection (c).</text> </subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></section>
</legis-body> 
<legis-body changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" display-enacting-clause="no-display-enacting-clause" id="HC7282394F4A24DE688DC0000B85C79BD" reported-display-style="italic" style="OLC"> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H685A792282D042E284F0C591DD0230C0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans’ Benefits Improvement Act of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text> </section>
<section id="H68C9276643B94A84BE6601C691E12EFA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Provision of specially adaptive housing assistance to disabled members of the Armed Forces residing temporarily in housing owned by a family member</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/2102A">Section 2102A</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7AC7C0E3356F48B98BC5514F22450587"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (d) and (e) as subsections (e) and (f), respectively; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE938D055B4094A30BACDF0120900C420"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (c) the following new subsection (d):</text> 
<quoted-block changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF8DC14A7E73748F18636D740242F105C" reported-display-style="italic" style="USC"> 
<subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE15F3142BFB47C4B25EA78EA477B61F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Assistance for members of the Armed Forces</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may provide assistance under subsection (a) to a member of the Armed Forces serving on active duty who is suffering from a disability described in subsection (a)(2) or (b)(2) of section 2101 of this title if such disability is the result of an injury incurred or disease contracted in or aggravated in line of duty in the active military, naval, or air service. Such assistance shall be provided to the same extent as assistance is provided under subsection (a) to veterans eligible for assistance under that subsection and subject to the limitation under subsection (c).</text> </subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></section>
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE53F0A763AD14A2BB5BE30AC23F60259" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Extension of period of mortgage foreclosure protection under Servicemembers Civil Relief Act</header> 
<subsection id="H49895A123EED49EC87E28FE9B532864"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Extension to 6 months</header><text>Subsection (c) of section 303 of the Servicemembers Civil Relief Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/50/533">50 U.S.C. App. 533(c)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>90 days</quote> and inserting <quote>180 days</quote>.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H39DDBD4B95044DA788E68CEB4F83AA2F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Extension of period of interest rate limitation</header><text>Such section is further amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H13CD78E6A6A648188137B96D599BB209" reported-display-style="italic" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H2506A4BF5B6646F0AAE9C771D006E625"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Applicability of interest rate limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 207 shall apply with respect to an obligation described in subsection (a) during the 180-day period beginning on the last day of the period of the servicemember’s military service in the same manner that section applies with respect to such an obligation during the period of the servicemember’s military service.</text> </subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection>
<subsection id="HAACB3545796A48CDB7ECB47196ED1848"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsections (a) and (b) shall apply with respect to any person performing a period of military service (as such term is defined in section 101(2) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/50/511">50 U.S.C. App. 511(2)</external-xref>)) that begins on or after the date that is 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text> </subsection></section>
<section id="H4A37387DAB3B423595BA8600C6C93986" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Visual impairment and orientation and mobility professionals education assistance program</header> 
<subsection id="H1C062C9E07EC48F8AC34CBFB7D658EDB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/76">Chapter 76</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subchapter:</text> 
<quoted-block changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE3512CAAC8D54AEC93EA4E489AAD0A2" reported-display-style="italic" style="USC"> 
<subchapter id="HC60D71F721D84E8A936225D4298082C4"><enum>VIII</enum><header>Visual Impairment and Orientation and Mobility Professionals Scholarship Program</header> 
<section id="HA2CAA30F7D3848BE83CF5298959B7BE2"><enum>7691.</enum><header>Authority for program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">As part of the Educational Assistance Program and subject to the availability of appropriations for such purpose, the Secretary shall carry out a scholarship program under this subchapter. The program shall be known as the Department of Veterans Affairs Visual Impairment and Orientation and Mobility Professionals Scholarship Program (hereinafter in this subchapter referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>). The purpose of the Program is to increase the supply of qualified blind rehabilitation specialists for the Department and the Nation.</text> </section>
<section id="HD746F409BAE24E7389181CCF69456012"><enum>7692.</enum><header>Eligibility; agreement</header> 
<subsection id="H39411F5531B347260013740032259341"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to participate in the Program, an individual must be accepted for enrollment or enrolled (as described in section 7602 of this title) as a full-time or part-time student in a field of education or training described in subsection (b).</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HFCD3B81EB59E45EC00C603F971B3861"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualifying fields of education or training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A field of education or training described in this subsection is education or training leading to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6E21FEDF43C44D96ADD88DB61C58ADC6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a degree or certificate in visual impairment or orientation and mobility, or a dual degree or certification in both such areas; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H73C33F71B069463CA182BB086C46EBBE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>appointment or retention in a position under section 7401 of this title.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H62BFACB30D5A4DA5AC367314DE1E839F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Agreement</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4DB6778A366C49579634002B73C76248"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An agreement between the Secretary and a participant in the Program shall (in addition to the requirements set forth in section 7604 of this title) include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" id="H8A3251F124144F5AAC9BE5425D9C54AF" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Secretary’s agreement to provide the participant with a scholarship under the Program for a specified number (from one to three) of school years during which the participant pursues a course of education or training described in subsection (b) that meets the requirements set forth in section 7602(a) of this title.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" id="H3F14080E780E44E996323579988F1200" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The participant’s agreement to serve as a full-time employee in the Veterans Health Administration for a period of three years (hereinafter in this subchapter referred to as the <quote>period of obligated service</quote>) during the six-year period beginning on the date the participant completes the education or training and receives a degree or certificate described in subsection (b)(1).</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" id="HB4D968CD7D98476D86AB17BEEB2E6387" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The participant’s agreement to serve under subparagraph (B) in a Department facility selected by the Secretary.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph changed="added" commented="no" committee-id="HVR00" id="H3F7B85EB77C04D11814870F3223BEE0" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In a case in which an extension is granted under section 7673(c)(2) of this title, the number of years for which a scholarship may be provided under the Program shall be the number of school years provided for as a result of the extension.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph changed="added" commented="no" committee-id="HVR00" id="HBC7CC5A4446144E592406BC9ED46BBEF" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In the case of a participant who is a part-time student, the period of obligated service shall be reduced in accordance with the proportion that the number of credit hours carried by such participant in any such school year bears to the number of credit hours required to be carried by a full-time student in the course of training being pursued by the participant, but in no event to less than one year.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section>
<section commented="no" id="HD02A4C048B034417AED3EC211226FD86"><enum>7693.</enum><header>Scholarship</header> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HAA63BAD723CA44EDBDC8FBF7598F3BA7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Scholarship</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A scholarship provided to a participant in the Program for a school year shall consist of payment of the tuition (or such portion of the tuition as may be provided under subsection (b)) of the participant for that school year and payment of other reasonable educational expenses (including fees, books, and laboratory expenses) for that school year.</text> </subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HB36AA6BEDBAA4BBE86907949364EF990"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amounts</header><text>The total amount of the scholarship payable under subsection (a)—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H1E5A0858E5444C16AA00CCEDDA079CCF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of a participant in the Program who is a full-time student, may not exceed $15,000 for the equivalent of one year of full-time coursework; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H541030A24D244AFEABE7DAFFE5D3DF10"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of a participant in the Program who is a part-time student, shall bear the same ratio to the amount that would be paid under paragraph (1) if the participant were a full-time student in the course of education or training being pursued by the participant as the coursework carried by the participant to full-time coursework in that course of education or training.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HB54F09CEB0974D878EBFFCC9E3C917E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitations on period of payment</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H22739B228A384E44A2650079A9C4CA6B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The maximum number of school years for which a scholarship may be paid under subsection (a) to a participant in the Program shall be six school years.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph changed="added" commented="no" committee-id="HVR00" id="H389DCE6B70544A4589B44B039A71FD6" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A participant in the Program may not receive a scholarship under subsection (a) for more than the equivalent of three years of full-time coursework.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HB7972B83C2984D349863ECD72F4B4F7E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Payment of educational expenses by educational institutions</header><text>The Secretary may arrange with an educational institution in which a participant in the Program is enrolled for the payment of the educational expenses described in subsection (a). Such payments may be made without regard to subsections (a) and (b) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/3324">section 3324</external-xref> of title 31.</text> </subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H256D26B1A8154FAF0068F0ED72A839D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Full-time coursework</header><text>For purposes of this section, full-time coursework shall consist of the following:</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H1446394B5F524835805C9F2197685B54"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the case of undergraduate coursework, 30 semester hours per undergraduate school year.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H5692A3C487B1456882B588223FAD5231"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In the case of graduate coursework, 18 semester hours per graduate school year.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section>
<section commented="no" id="H4E4BA18F2A524B24B4525895B8D9547E"><enum>7694.</enum><header>Obligated service</header> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HC1FBD4951E31410BA7222933719DBEEE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each participant in the Program shall provide service as a full-time employee of the Department for the period of obligated service provided in the agreement of the participant entered into under section 7604 of this title. Such service shall be provided in the full-time clinical practice of such participant’s profession or in another health-care position in an assignment or location determined by the Secretary.</text> </subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H05CD7A6B955A45569935C19E87478B06"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Determination of service commencement date</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8E8728AB26E5449F9D74CB756E5BF201"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Not later than 60 days before a participant’s service commencement date, the Secretary shall notify the participant of that service commencement date. That date is the date for the beginning of the participant’s period of obligated service.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph changed="added" commented="no" committee-id="HVR00" id="H0B82BE86B85C46F8A077F89E3118F91C" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(2)</enum><text>As soon as possible after a participant’s service commencement date, the Secretary shall—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HA160887D582F4AD8B4BB80E9A54E7416"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of a participant who is not a full-time employee in the Veterans Health Administration, appoint the participant as such an employee; and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H385004C07FC54EF78C2D003942CF2FE4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a participant who is an employee in the Veterans Health Administration but is not serving in a position for which the participant’s course of education or training prepared the participant, assign the participant to such a position.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph changed="added" commented="no" committee-id="HVR00" id="HB996C18AA11E4351B3C3B6A520591CE9" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(3)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9533DBE9EFD340C38B84972DE7589563"><enum>(A)</enum><text>In the case of a participant receiving a degree from a school of medicine, osteopathy, dentistry, optometry, or podiatry, the participant’s service commencement date is the date upon which the participant becomes licensed to practice medicine, osteopathy, dentistry, optometry, or podiatry, as the case may be, in a State.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph changed="added" commented="no" committee-id="HVR00" id="H1339833B239447DBB6A8FF00397C76F2" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In the case of a participant receiving a degree from a school of nursing, the participant’s service commencement date is the later of—</text> 
<clause commented="no" id="H01D78253A4004FA98200038E6097CAF8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the participant’s course completion date; or</text> </clause>
<clause commented="no" id="H885DE964E728497CB6184DC3B4D08ECA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the date upon which the participant becomes licensed as a registered nurse in a State.</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph changed="added" commented="no" committee-id="HVR00" id="H05602694CF9044ABB0FA6C00D932724C" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a participant not covered by subparagraph (A) or (B), the participant’s service commencement date is the later of—</text> 
<clause commented="no" id="H747C63F1B09743D8A1EC6FB771757E88"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the participant’s course completion date; or</text> </clause>
<clause commented="no" id="H08EA32E8055E4E98AE2FDC2C1FCB1659"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the date the participant meets any applicable licensure or certification requirements.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph changed="added" commented="no" committee-id="HVR00" id="HC153C4EC01A4473580E80024792D5D6D" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Secretary shall by regulation prescribe the service commencement date for participants who were part-time students. Such regulations shall prescribe terms as similar as practicable to the terms set forth in paragraph (3).</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H60929A9CFE394842B2F9261405D90052"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Commencement of obligated service</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7FCA217537804101AA677640003EE69F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), a participant in the Program shall be considered to have begun serving the participant’s period of obligated service—</text> 
<subparagraph changed="added" commented="no" committee-id="HVR00" id="H68B4C7490AA940A0A1CC000040341569" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(A)</enum><text>on the date, after the participant’s course completion date, on which the participant (in accordance with subsection (b)) is appointed as a full-time employee in the Veterans Health Administration; or</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph changed="added" commented="no" committee-id="HVR00" id="H91ED3FBF691D49D4BC03EE34CD1F5061" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if the participant is a full-time employee in the Veterans Health Administration on such course completion date, on the date thereafter on which the participant is assigned to a position for which the participant’s course of training prepared the participant.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph changed="added" commented="no" committee-id="HVR00" id="H82C1C4D6FB8B451A94E49535185C362E" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A participant in the Program who on the participant’s course completion date is a full-time employee in the Veterans Health Administration serving in a capacity for which the participant’s course of training prepared the participant shall be considered to have begun serving the participant’s period of obligated service on such course completion date.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H89116ED8F36444DF9F2D1268B017314C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Course completion date defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>course completion date</quote> means the date on which a participant in the Program completes the participant’s course of education or training under the Program.</text> </subsection></section>
<section commented="no" id="HD4E115B0935A4E9A8D608B00A4E9288"><enum>7695.</enum><header>Repayment for failure to satisfy requirements of agreement</header> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HC945D068A7B64FFAB347B38C319793A7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An individual who receives educational assistance under this subchapter shall repay to the Secretary an amount equal to the unearned portion of such assistance if the individual fails to satisfy the requirements of the agreement entered into under section 7604 of this title, except in circumstances authorized by the Secretary.</text> </subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H45CFAF1CFC8845EE8603C90066729D6C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amount of repayment</header><text>The Secretary shall establish, by regulations, procedures for determining the amount of the repayment required under this subsection and the circumstances under which an exception to the required repayment may be granted.</text> </subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H3808E12B00834030B22BDFC9F088F284"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Waiver or suspension of compliance</header><text>The Secretary shall prescribe regulations providing for the waiver or suspension of any obligation of an individual for service or payment under this subchapter (or an agreement under this subchapter) whenever noncompliance by the individual is due to circumstances beyond the control of the individual or whenever the Secretary determines that the waiver or suspension of compliance is in the best interest of the United States.</text> </subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HB009B704D53C43F9945615B617984082"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Obligation as debt to United States</header><text>An obligation to repay the Secretary under this section is, for all purposes, a debt owed the United States. A discharge in bankruptcy under title 11 does not discharge a person from such debt if the discharge order is entered less than five years after the date of the termination of the agreement or contract on which the debt is based.</text> </subsection></section></subchapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection>
<subsection id="HA8D89E3186394E59B600AD99B1547DB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The tables of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the items relating to subchapter VII the following new items:</text> 
<quoted-block changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB9FA8A7893E948B2813F253608725D80" reported-display-style="italic" style="USC"> 
<toc changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" regeneration="no-regeneration" reported-display-style="italic"> 
<toc-entry level="subchapter">SUBCHAPTER VIII—Visual Impairment and Orientation and Mobility Professionals Scholarship Program</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">7691. Authority for program.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">7692. Eligibility; agreement.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">7693. Scholarship.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">7694. Obligated service.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">7695. Repayment for failure to satisfy requirements of agreement.</toc-entry> </toc> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection>
<subsection id="HFC772AC1B9964BA7AC67A4B60098F9E9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Such chapter is further amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H955AF41F5BB84C689F3CD9E41B7B9B70"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 7601(a)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFB80F9720A434395BDD6349DD795EAA3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5D17A39D89DF4A3780DFBCF5D2C748C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9F5793B34BFE4BB48B87C269B439846D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4D21ACE7CCAB4B4AA7FAAD85B85B73C6" reported-display-style="italic" style="USC"> 
<paragraph id="H96F4DCF839F7434DA048BCE8EE579B9E"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Visual Impairment and Orientation and Mobility Professionals Scholarship Program provided for in subchapter VIII of this chapter.</text> </paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6D50820FDA934679BDEE8039036B32C5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 7602—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H75255454DC6645ED8EC2D7BAA3EECDE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1)—</text> 
<clause id="H0D4D48D604B54CFFA1015C4086D1AC91"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or VI</quote> and inserting <quote>VI, or VIII</quote>; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="H292C91D0BC474D0D8BEED69F1EEDFAF3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or for which a scholarship may be awarded under subchapter VI of this chapter</quote> and inserting <quote>for which a scholarship may be awarded under subchapter VI of this chapter, or for which a scholarship may be awarded under subchapter VIII of this chapter</quote>; and</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H89F835C187CA4348B9C9A1C8CDA0196"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>or VI</quote> and inserting <quote>VI, or VIII</quote>;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H63C2FD416FCF48CE8CA3F394B2A89041"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 7603(a)(1), by striking <quote>or VI</quote> and inserting <quote>VI, or VIII</quote>; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5FB0779E2F2947B58C9500B0AB7FC110"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 7604, by striking <quote>or VI</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>VI, or VIII</quote>.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H67855B725E7447910082A7B3AA99BD6D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall implement subchapter VIII of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/76">chapter 76</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, as added by section 1, not later than six months after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text> </subsection></section>
<section id="H3FB4A30949C84085A2AFE90770E9F3E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Veterans’ reemployment rights report improvement</header> 
<subsection id="H0D7CB8C618094558865120AC6787391F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Additional report requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/4332">Section 4332</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB7134C1F15EC4923AA39995F1247FE00"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The Secretary shall</quote> and inserting <quote>(a) <header-in-text level="subsection" style="USC">Report required.—</header-in-text>The Secretary shall</quote>;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H777C826788B34BCDA4C0D1560048F05D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (4) through (6) as paragraphs (5) through (7), respectively, and inserting after paragraph (3) the following new paragraph (4):</text> 
<quoted-block changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB8ECEB35A0A04F789F17A71F700640D0" reported-display-style="italic" style="USC"> 
<paragraph id="HA8933C87F28B4D738D5920B800D904CF"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of cases reviewed by the Secretary of Defense under the National Committee for Employer Support of the Guard and Reserve of the Department of Defense during the fiscal year for which the report is made.</text> </paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB4321F75BE1C486AB4BA4672615DE200"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>or (3)</quote> and inserting <quote>(3), or (4)</quote>;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H19AC369376DD4804A006217E8204E79F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (7), as so redesignated, as paragraph (8), and inserting after paragraph (6) the following new paragraph (7):</text> 
<quoted-block changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H41D02CE5F3214EC8A8888132D6E6DC73" reported-display-style="italic" style="USC"> 
<paragraph id="H48FBE7B1D2D2444E84BC00D025E2AB2F"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An indication of which of the cases reported on pursuant to paragraphs (1), (2), (3), and (4) are disability-related.</text> </paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H572FA6D4548E49B08DE23E6C5522C690"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsections:</text> 
<quoted-block changed="added" committee-id="HVR00" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB9D0CD6868EA460C9DAF6873BA04AEE6" reported-display-style="italic" style="USC"> 
<subsection id="HA8CD6E6ED5494ED1B03DC07C9D2610BC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Uniform categorization of data</header><text>The Secretary shall coordinate with the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, the Attorney General, and the Special Counsel to ensure that the information required to be submitted as part of the report under subsection (a) is categorized in a uniform way.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H181DEDDDE2C849D0BA2CC03E4EEE86BB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Provision of information</header><text>The Secretary shall provide the information contained in the report required under subsection (a) to the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, the Attorney General, and the Special Counsel.</text> </subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE6617C091E0548009EBADDB392D6E806"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to a report submitted after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text> </subsection></section>
<section id="H5D5E701F1AFB47D8A6C5AA8BA5AF25C9" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Increase in number of members of Advisory Committee on Veterans Employment, Training, and Employer Outreach</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/4110">Section 4110(c)(1)</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>15</quote> and inserting <quote>16</quote>.</text> </section>
</legis-body><official-title-amendment>Amend the title so as to read: <quote>A bill to amend title 38, United States Code, to make certain improvements in the benefits provided to veterans under laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, and for other purposes.</quote>.</official-title-amendment> 
<endorsement display="yes"> 
<action-date>July 27, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc>Reported with amendments, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc> </endorsement> 
</bill> 


