<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H57AF073C68814BA78B54582EA7FE16BC" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 2818 EH: Veterans’ Epilepsy Treatment Act of 2008</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">110th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 2818</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to provide for the establishment of epilepsy centers of excellence in the Veterans Health Administration of the Department of Veterans Affairs.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="H5B337F21D6F94589836C13C2504C6ED6" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5819627E00BB45029F34D191000956B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans’ Epilepsy Treatment Act of 2008</short-title></quote>.</text> </section>
<section id="H55F58BC84D5F43EBA9CB555D69B65C9D" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Epilepsy centers of excellence</header> 
<subsection id="HEA45AE16E5D045789E377910A5E5253"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement for establishment of epilepsy centers of excellence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/73">chapter 73</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H317111CCFE6847C5B4BF42AC9F9B9CDD" style="USC">
<section id="H22876943F3B14329BBCDC0414845EDB0"><enum>7330A.</enum><header>Epilepsy centers of excellence</header> 
<subsection id="HD78C7B034E2F4675A598CEB35E90A55D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation of centers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall designate an epilepsy center of excellence at each of the 5 centers designated under section 7327.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H44C213FD8AE44FF8B7C57234FBB1B5BE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Expert clinical and research staff</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each center designated under subsection (a) shall employ such expert clinical and research staff, including board certified neurologists and neurosurgeons, as may be necessary to ensure that such center is capable of serving as a center of excellence in research, education, and clinical care activities in the diagnosis and treatment of epilepsy, including post-traumatic epilepsy.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HB172540D93764FD394EFF33B6EB966F0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements and operation of centers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each center designated under subsection (a) shall function as a center for—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA94DB947E23D47339F636B83ABFD4B94"><enum>(1)</enum><text>research on the diagnosis, treatment, and long-term effects of epilepsy, including epilepsy developed as a result of combat, in order to support the provision of services for such diagnosis and treatment in accordance with the most current information on epilepsy;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC9DD62A260214D3CBF00594590D230AC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the development of evidence-based methodologies for treating individuals with epilepsy;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H16ADA6CD521B46E40073EC41C079B354"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the continuous and consistent coordination of care from the point of referral throughout the diagnostic and treatment process and ongoing follow-up after return to home and community;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBDCD11B2EF254904B6906596A1FDD080"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the development of a national system of coordinated care for veterans with epilepsy, including the development and maintenance of a national network of Department health care personnel with an interest and expertise in the care and treatment of epilepsy and the establishment of a referral system and procedure within each Veterans Integrated Service Network;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0AAD3516188745629778685F0404D889"><enum>(5)</enum><text>assist in the expansion, where appropriate, of the utilization of telehealth technology, including exploring the use of such technology to develop, transmit, monitor, and review neurological diagnostic tests and other applicable uses of telehealth technology for the diagnosis, care, and treatment of veterans with epilepsy; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFF5456A146CE40D79CA56354D07BEF0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the dissemination of educational materials and research regarding diagnosis, care, and treatment of epilepsy, throughout the Department.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H503FA4EF02814F4AA49801B2C8CCE026"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>In order to assist the Secretary in carrying out this section, the Secretary shall designate a national coordinator for epilepsy programs who shall report to the official responsible for neurology at the Veterans Health Administration and shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBFF5AB04830343ECAFBFDBD03DD19726"><enum>(1)</enum><text>supervise the operation of the centers designated under this section;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFE9F18B574804C34BBC756899E5CD89E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinate and support the national network of Department health care professionals with an interest and expertise in the care and treatment of epilepsy;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCE4B9F7181BE4841A58FABA4C702B44"><enum>(3)</enum><text>ensure that the education and research mission of such centers is being accomplished; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9A8B280BD1944C5592D2C74E50D9D237"><enum>(4)</enum><text>conduct regular evaluations of such centers to ensure compliance with the requirements of this section.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H49A16E6C52DA43338F0079B919C3DC5F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2009 through 2013.</text> </subsection></section> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection>
<subsection id="H5F01CF49ADFC4F52AB67B08BDD77CF15"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 7330 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0FCC6377BFCC4E9184A6264DF85E5415" style="OLC">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">7330A. Epilepsy centers of excellence.</toc-entry> </toc> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection></section>
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20080624" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives June 24, 2008.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 


