<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HBD8C19058DA54CB78A10C320FD392EFC" public-private="public">
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>112th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 169</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20110105">January 5, 2011</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000822">Mr. Stearns</sponsor>
			 introduced the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’
			 Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to include
		  on the main page of the Internet website of the Department of Veterans Affairs
		  a hyperlink to the VetSuccess Internet website and to publicize such Internet
		  website.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H8A7A6F0A6DA448F18AC7EF74E32ABB16" style="OLC">
		<section id="H6892F7B1E09E4D7D9115E9FF774F33A4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Promotion of the VetSuccess
			 Internet website</header>
			<subsection id="HCED08F1ABBBD4F7EB1CBBB98318A5E20"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Inclusion of
			 hyperlink</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60
			 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans
			 Affairs shall include on the main page of the Internet website of the
			 Department of Veterans Affairs a new hyperlink with a drop-down menu entitled
			 <quote>Veterans Employment</quote>. The drop-down menu shall include a direct
			 hyperlink to the VetSuccess Internet website, the USA Jobs Internet website,
			 the Job Central website, and any other appropriate employment Internet
			 websites, as determined by the Secretary, especially such websites that focus
			 on jobs for veterans.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H1F9A0A56DDAE46A99F2C9FDE6BF0029D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Advertisement of
			 Internet website</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to
			 the availability of appropriations for such purpose, the Secretary of Veterans
			 Affairs shall, in accordance with section 532 of title 38, United States Code,
			 purchase advertising in national media outlets for the purpose of promoting
			 awareness of the VetSuccess Internet website to veterans.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H88A2EE1B7F1A4E44BE94A6218C830073"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Outreach to
			 veterans of Operation Iraqi Freedom and Operation Enduring
			 Freedom</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct outreach
			 to veterans of Operation Iraqi Freedom and Operation Enduring Freedom to inform
			 such veterans of the VetSuccess Internet website.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HB08A7E1400564371953CBD5BE0567E9B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>VetSuccess
			 Internet website defined</header><text>In this section, the term
			 <quote>VetSuccess Internet website</quote> means www.vetsuccess.gov or any
			 successor Internet website maintained by the Department of Veterans
			 Affairs.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>
