<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H8CE240D0F6374001A8769EFB28C1EE2" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 5579 IH: Emergency Mortgage Loan Modification
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2008-03-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>2d Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 5579</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20080311">March 11, 2008</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000243">Mr. Castle</sponsor> (for
			 himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000008">Mr. Kanjorski</cosponsor>) introduced
			 the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial
			 Services</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To remove an impediment to troubled debt restructuring on
		  the part of holders of residential mortgage loans, and for other
		  purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HF6158F5F6B4D4D50B7D776F324C24027" style="OLC">
		<section id="HF571323888F948C9BD315797105388AB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Emergency Mortgage Loan Modification
			 Act of 2008</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H1BC77EC62A824283B54791B0899FD348"><enum>2.</enum><header>Safe harbor for
			 qualified loan modifications or workout plans for certain residential mortgage
			 loans</header>
			<subsection id="H7B1418D7CE3743DCB8855B2BBB26267"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Standard for loan
			 modifications or workout plans</header><text>Absent specific contractual
			 provisions to the contrary—</text>
				<paragraph id="HBDB6A17B914A48B6A8C400EA6E303218"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the duty to
			 maximize, or to not adversely affect, the recovery of total proceeds from
			 pooled residential mortgage loans is owed by a servicer of such pooled loans to
			 the securitization vehicle for the benefit of all investors and holders of
			 beneficial interests in the pooled loans, in the aggregate, and not to any
			 individual party or group of parties; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HFA132447D9DD4A79995735C01E0CFCC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a
			 servicer of pooled residential mortgage loans shall be deemed to be acting on
			 behalf of the securitization vehicle in the best interest of all investors and
			 holders of beneficial interests in the pooled loans, in the aggregate, if for a
			 loan that is in payment default under the loan agreement or for which payment
			 default is imminent or reasonably foreseeable, the loan servicer makes
			 reasonable and documented efforts to implement a modification or workout plan
			 or, if such efforts are unsuccessful or such plan would be infeasible, engages
			 in other loss mitigation, including accepting a short payment or partial
			 discharge of principal, or agreeing to a short sale of the property, to the
			 extent that the servicer reasonably believes the modification or workout plan
			 or other mitigation actions will maximize the net present value to be realized
			 on the loan over that which would be realized through foreclosure.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9142E75D131141668E88BB65C13FDDBF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Safe
			 harbor</header><text>Absent specific contractual provisions to the contrary, a
			 servicer of a residential mortgage loan that acts in a manner consistent with
			 the duty set forth in subsection (a), shall not be liable for entering into a
			 qualified loan modification or workout plan, to—</text>
				<paragraph id="H96B4C8C1E0134EFB96B16281AB76D35"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any person, based
			 on that person’s ownership of a residential mortgage loan or any interest in a
			 pool of residential mortgage loans or in securities that distribute payments
			 out of the principal, interest and other payments in loans on the pool;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H033D720FD4AD419583E8166178B76C18"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any person who is
			 obligated to make payments determined in reference to any loan or any interest
			 referred to in paragraph (1); or</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HA050C9404FF94212A6C43386A7C2C73"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any person that insures any loan or any
			 interest referred to in paragraph (1) under any law or regulation of the United
			 States or any law or regulation of any State or political subdivision of any
			 State.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF2F886F500B44C9D93007014BBE07607"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of
			 construction</header><text>No provision of this section shall be construed as
			 limiting the ability of a servicer to enter into loan modifications or workout
			 plans other than qualified loan modification or workout plans.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H23083864ED164C079396831E6B591852"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For
			 purposes of this section, the following definitions shall apply:</text>
				<paragraph id="HBA6C409B69A14D319802644662741BA4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Qualified loan
			 modification or workout plan</header><text>The term <quote>qualified loan
			 modification or workout plan</quote> means a modification or plan that—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HBD1758EA0EAA41C0A7647867004EDF3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is scheduled to
			 remain in place until the borrower sells or refinances the property, or for at
			 least 5 years from the date of adoption of the plan, whichever is
			 sooner;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22CDDBA773C84CF9802DDECE7E8D37"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not provide for
			 a repayment schedule that results in negative amortization at any time;
			 and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H81EBFA58FC8045739D07D4A426734FF0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>does not require
			 the borrower to pay additional points and fees.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFAB737B326A47DD81E69CCA0590D566"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Residential
			 mortgage loan defined</header><text>The term <quote>residential mortgage
			 loan</quote> means a loan that is secured by a lien on an owner-occupied
			 residential dwelling.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H144C673D88E24BD2B4F2ABCC462DAB6E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Securitization
			 vehicle</header><text>The term <quote>securitization vehicle</quote> means a
			 trust, corporation, partnership, limited liability entity, special purpose
			 entity, or other structure that—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HEF97BB624C524B63B553B225A453B4C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is the issuer, or
			 is created by the issuer, of mortgage pass-through certificates, participation
			 certificates, mortgage-backed securities, or other similar securities backed by
			 a pool of assets that includes residential mortgage loans; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C1C9774189D47BFA5B5D086279B9697"><enum>(B)</enum><text>holds such
			 loans.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5EE1C87F4CAD4ED890B6BBC4898B23FD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Effective
			 period</header><text>This section shall apply only with respect to qualified
			 loan modification or workout plans initiated prior to January 1, 2011.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


