<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H10EAF138A5124EAFA7C4CFC656FF006D" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 5622 IH: To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to carry out
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2008-03-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>2d Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 5622</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20080313">March 13, 2008</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001247">Ms. Ginny Brown-Waite of
			 Florida</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’
			 Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to carry out
		  a pilot program to establish standards of access to care for veterans seeking
		  health care from certain Department of Veterans Affairs medical facilities, and
		  for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HCF0F07BDC7304B468EB4076626CF501F" style="OLC">
		<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H695D63D74A694DB586FACD18360304AE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote>Veterans
			 Timely Access to Health Care Act</quote>.</text>
		</section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5F4FBC2612FC49619985D444FF2D9FAC" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Veterans
			 Affairs pilot program on access to medical care</header>
			<subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC8ED2D910FE345DDB9ABC450F0E2EB47"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Pilot
			 Program</header><text>During the five-year period beginning on the date of the
			 enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct a pilot
			 program under which the Secretary shall ensure that for each veteran seeking
			 primary care from a covered medical facility, the standard for access to care,
			 determined from the date on which the veteran contacts the Department seeking
			 an appointment until the date on which a visit with a primary-care provider is
			 completed, is 30 days.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H2DB68F3CCE0749EF9EE2D21536E81CB8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered
			 facility</header><text>For purposes of the pilot program under this section, a
			 covered medical facility is a medical facility of the Department of Veterans
			 Affairs in Veterans Integrated Service Network 8.</text>
			</subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAAB772589E904F4799A49EADC7331C78"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Review of
			 performance</header><text>The Secretary shall periodically review the
			 performance of covered medical facilities compared to the standard established
			 under subsection (a). The Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’
			 Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives an annual report providing
			 an assessment of the Department’s performance in meeting that standard.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HE8C8E039CF344898BCE00974F433E37"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Provision of care at non-Department
			 facilities</header>
				<paragraph id="HC64304CB333C463EB940080664D57E55"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Provision of
			 care</header><text>Effective on the first day of the first fiscal year
			 beginning after the date of the enactment of this section, in a case in which
			 the Secretary is unable to meet the standard for access to care under
			 subsection (a) with respect to a veteran enrolled in the patient enrollment
			 system of the Department of Veterans Affairs under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1705">section 1705,</external-xref> of title 38,
			 United States Code, the Secretary shall use the authority of section 1703(a) of
			 that title to furnish health care and services for that veteran in a
			 non-Department facility. In any such case—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HCBD24B03BAF44DC1909EA4B446CAFD94"><enum>(A)</enum><text>payments by the Secretary may not
			 exceed the reimbursement rate for similar outpatient services paid by the
			 Secretary of Health and Human Services under part B of the medicare program (as
			 defined in section 1781(d)(4)(A) of that title); and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93281AE0F8A5490FBC4C8D15375DE27D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the non-Department facility may not
			 bill the veteran for any difference between the facility’s billed charges and
			 the amount paid by the Secretary under paragraph (1).</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H967F9BA73D584DE181C036FC90E333C3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Veteran choice to receive care at
			 Department facility</header><text>A veteran for whom the Secretary furnishes
			 health care or services at a non-Department facility under paragraph (1) may,
			 after 30 days of receiving such care or services at the non-Department
			 facility, choose to receive such care or services from a Department facility,
			 if available. If a veteran so chooses, the veteran shall submit to the
			 Secretary notice in writing of that choice.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HACBC2B2E2A2340DFB2274C2B35BF2271"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Continuity of
			 care</header><text>For the purpose of providing for continuity of care, the
			 Secretary shall develop a form to be used by veterans to authorize the
			 Secretary to obtain any records created in connection with the veteran’s
			 receipt of care from a non-Department facility.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HB1EA220241DA433C9101146BAFB700B1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Quarterly reports</header>
				<paragraph id="HA6226973F9CB4F2F98057BE7CB7D052D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>Not later
			 than 60 days after the end of a calendar-year quarter, the Secretary of
			 Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the
			 Senate and House of Representatives a report for that calendar-year quarter on
			 the experience of the Department during the quarter covered by the report with
			 respect to waiting times for veterans seeking appointments at a covered
			 facility.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC0754AAB784A424FB257D91383DF707"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>Each report
			 under subparagraph (A) shall include—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H1316A666123243B9ACF7690037F12659"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the total number of veterans
			 waiting by the following categories:</text>
						<clause id="HF5E427DF52AA4306A08E1ED4D700EF73"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Those waiting under 30 days for scheduled
			 appointments.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H2FEEB85F21D34C6B94BF2F781B0011C2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Those waiting over 30 days but less than
			 60 days.</text>
						</clause><clause id="HB99694851814460881CE9DE08107DB16"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Those waiting over 60 days but less
			 than 4 months.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H6BDC2D1A4D964EA1858CEFDA7F78C7"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Those waiting over 4 months but who
			 cannot be scheduled within 6 months.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H336132DAD34D4A469494CCE63250DC93"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Any remaining veterans who cannot be
			 scheduled, with the reasons therefor.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA88D09759C1D4D87A23D6BE8B38646D7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For each category set forth in
			 subparagraph (A), distinctions between—</text>
						<clause id="HB3A70F2AA1644C01AF553F73E6DFE4A8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>waiting times for primary care and
			 specialty care; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H4F03D3EF980447A582B50819D81220DB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>waiting times for veterans who are newly
			 enrolled versus those who were enrolled before October 1, 2001.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3FC62D6E2CF24B93A6CEDA10804BF731"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The number of veterans who have
			 enrolled in the Department of Veterans Affairs health care system but have not
			 since such enrollment sought care at a Department medical facility.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A8438CDFAAE48C4A7459C0096F780EE"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The
			 authority to conduct a pilot program under this section shall terminate on the
			 date that is five years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


