<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9571AC3BD056426CA6F61162EF2FAC22" public-private="public" stage-count="1"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">112th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 1633</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To establish a temporary prohibition against revising any national ambient air quality standard applicable to coarse particulate matter, to limit Federal regulation of nuisance dust in areas in which such dust is regulated under State, tribal, or local law, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="H230E394DD5F04665A89627C30BE9BCC3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7868670122F74F6F827213C761B84972" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Farm Dust Regulation Prevention Act of 2011</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H695E08FD223A4C4DB326315F4BFC45AC" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Temporary prohibition against revising any national ambient air quality standard applicable to coarse particulate matter</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Before the date that is one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency may not propose, finalize, implement, or enforce any regulation revising the national primary ambient air quality standard or the national secondary ambient air quality standard applicable to particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter greater than 2.5 micrometers under section 109 of the Clean Air Act (42 U.S.C. 7409).</text> </section> 
<section id="H9CA27328A56148F2B7F92B94F99E29DF"><enum>3.</enum><header>Nuisance dust</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part A of title I of the Clean Air Act (42 U.S.C. 7401 et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCE1B83BA61C04E6D83A07BBCFCB1DF70" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H647CA3C7E5404A6CA9E12231F7E6F91D"><enum>132.</enum><header>Regulation of nuisance dust primarily by State, tribal, and local governments</header> 
<subsection id="H448B2F495AF14591A4066937645063E3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (b), this Act does not apply to, and references in this Act to particulate matter are deemed to exclude, nuisance dust.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H2B0BE5C346D2424CABF4A7013D5B4A30"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (a) does not apply with respect to any geographic area in which nuisance dust is not regulated under State, tribal, or local law insofar as the Administrator, in consultation with the Secretary of Agriculture, finds that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7581EDE790564556BCF1ED9740619F6D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">nuisance dust (or any subcategory of nuisance dust) causes substantial adverse public health and welfare effects at ambient concentrations; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H49984060767B45FC95FE4E21F808EA2D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the benefits of applying standards and other requirements of this Act to nuisance dust (or such subcategory of nuisance dust) outweigh the costs (including local and regional economic and employment impacts) of applying such standards and other requirements to nuisance dust (or such subcategory).</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA173892302844770B112FC485FE29D3C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section—</text> 
<paragraph id="HDB9B9BB573B747A8BE3B4528916EE1ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>nuisance dust</quote> means particulate matter that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD92C4B8D9CA541F2B08D3965DC1DA426"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is generated primarily from natural sources, unpaved roads, agricultural activities, earth moving, or other activities typically conducted in rural areas;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7CED16F3888640DC982F2E918721440F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consists primarily of soil, other natural or biological materials, or some combination thereof;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAAB7D8258C75411EA8E5FFBAEDA700EB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is not emitted directly into the ambient air from combustion, such as exhaust from combustion engines and emissions from stationary combustion processes; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1298FE0F4FEE4B34A44038101F8660D1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is not comprised of residuals from the combustion of coal; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H18CF5D7358974CA4940B08794BEA702D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>nuisance dust</quote> does not include radioactive particulate matter produced from uranium mining or processing.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section>
<section id="H030B770BD4174AD1AE5BDB9EF9B7273A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of the Congress that the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency should implement an approach to excluding so-called <quote>exceptional events</quote>, or events that are not reasonably controllable or preventable, from determinations of whether an area is in compliance with any national ambient air quality standard (NAAQS) applicable to coarse particulate matter that—</text>
<paragraph id="H1D4836BCA9EA4252B2B65B4D914644D0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>maximizes transparency and predictability for States, tribes, and local governments; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAC00F12569AF45AA8CE46033C5A74351"><enum>(2)</enum><text>minimizes the regulatory and cost burdens States, tribes, and local governments bear in excluding such events.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H8A19DF2445E54B88898BEE70494C77C8"><enum>5.</enum><header>Impacts of EPA regulatory activity on employment and economic activity in the agriculture community</header>
<subsection id="HBFC74888533D40D6BEDC24E41EE1BDD5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Analysis of impacts of actions on employment and economic activity in the agriculture community</header>
<paragraph id="HF2F3D3165E4348CD82457B022B652FCE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Analysis</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before taking a covered action, the Administrator shall analyze the impact, disaggregated by State, of the covered action on—</text>
<subparagraph id="H7F7CEC062DFC4DFEAC62637104FE8F40"><enum>(A)</enum><text>employment levels in the agriculture industry; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HABC5F76CFA9E4938B725AF3C381B94B2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>agricultural economic activity, including estimated job losses and decreased economic activity related to agriculture.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB4001FF67D7947B5AD3EE4DB54CFCCF9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Economic models</header>
<subparagraph id="H60BFFAB1DB8C4CFCB9D5D1A143CA36F1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Administrator shall utilize the best available economic models.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1AEA60E0404743BA84C0158324E848DE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Annual GAO report</header><text>Not later than December 31 of each year, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report on the economic models used by the Administrator to carry out this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7E9BB39B13314E02922CF618AABA97F7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Availability of information</header><text>With respect to any covered action, the Administrator shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H6F9973C4FC3247C4B6CB84744DF4851B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>post the analysis under paragraph (1) as a link on the main page of the public Internet Web site of the Environmental Protection Agency;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD5FB78272D9B4454AC335BA56501A8B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>request the Secretary of Agriculture to post the analysis under paragraph (1) as a link on the main page of the public Internet Web site of the Department of Agriculture; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCD7B6E5D700946E7BA19992CE2B24A01"><enum>(C)</enum><text>request that the Governor of any State experiencing more than a de minimis negative impact post such analysis in the Capitol of such State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H86AA5FA326FD415A881C91607A677BEE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public hearings</header>
<paragraph id="H6896A5524D334603932900197858C84B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Administrator concludes under subsection (a)(1) that a covered action will have more than a de minimis negative impact on agricultural employment levels or agricultural economic activity in a State, the Administrator shall hold a public hearing in each such State at least 30 days prior to the effective date of the covered action.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H737014EA2E324403B9AF76823E38349A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Time, location, and selection</header><text>A public hearing required under paragraph (1) shall be held at a convenient time and location for impacted residents. In selecting a location for such a public hearing, the Administrator shall give priority to locations in the State that will experience the greatest number of job losses.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1C911C9F4C1E46DF85E56F552BCCEE4E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>If the Administrator concludes under subsection (a)(1) that a covered action will have more than a de minimis negative impact on agricultural employment levels or agricultural economic activity in any State, the Administrator shall give notice of such impact to the State’s Congressional delegation, Governor, and Legislature at least 45 days before the effective date of the covered action.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H797B4EE447274BDA8828E7F8B2564FA7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the following definitions apply:</text>
<paragraph id="H12EE75E7CFBB400FA71CDA6B2455B9AE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H685668C3282E4DE28664B28F76CE1F45"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered action</header><text>The term <quote>covered action</quote> means any of the following actions taken by the Administrator under the Clean Air Act (42 U.S.C. 7401 et seq.) relating to agriculture and the national primary ambient air quality standard or the national secondary ambient air quality standard for particulate matter:</text>
<subparagraph id="H0DFDC75A1990487DA336D8A61B1F75B6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Issuing a regulation, policy statement, guidance, response to a petition, or other requirement.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEA83372A2B33443BA12A34087003BAB4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Implementing a new or substantially altered program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA808ECE7C5C741C996FC07C749B4F5AD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>More than a de minimis negative impact</header><text>The term <quote>more than a de minimis negative impact</quote> means the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="H5DA123904DDC41678435DA9543296EDC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>With respect to employment levels, a loss of more than 100 jobs related to the agriculture industry. Any offsetting job gains that result from the hypothetical creation of new jobs through new technologies or government employment may not be used in the job loss calculation.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H64B2ECECCC0F487C83160BE24BEC741D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>With respect to economic activity, a decrease in agricultural economic activity of more than $1,000,000 over any calendar year. Any offsetting economic activity that results from the hypothetical creation of new economic activity through new technologies or government employment may not be used in the economic activity calculation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20111208" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives December 8, 2011.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Karen L. Haas,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation> 
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement> 
</bill> 
