<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1753C8FAF2924A36BAEC00A2BFDA8FC4" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 1534 IH: Mercury Export Ban Act of 2007</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-03-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
<session>1st Session</session>
<legis-num>H. R. 1534</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070315">March 15, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000357">Mr. Allen</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To prohibit the sale, distribution, or transfer of mercury, to prohibit the export of mercury, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HA5176107FC254A6288F83FDCDC66E873" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H44AD1DB9757C4E2A87C89146F333C100" section-type="section-one" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Mercury Export Ban Act of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HAA9787DDAB6E4EFCA9B71FB508EFD00" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H92338D969E1C4100801480917FC9FEC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>mercury is highly toxic to humans, ecosystems, and wildlife;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB841EB64CAE14E119FA62CE6AEC8FF12"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as many as 10 percent of women in the United States of childbearing age have mercury in the blood at a level that could put a baby at risk;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBE1D8FB41FCF4C2F812FF526001500E3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>as many as 630,000 children born annually in the United States are at risk of neurological problems related to mercury;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDCA29C21876B45099BDF402B5D00E3EA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the most significant source of mercury exposure to people in the United States is ingestion of mercury-contaminated fish;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6E25EF877023466E947717DBD15744E6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Environmental Protection Agency reports that, as of 2004—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEB502E59DFA647B2B821EC9E31EC22C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>44 States have fish advisories covering over 13,000,000 lake acres and over 750,000 river miles;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9D3C8DF9CB8749AF9C78A46455FB716"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in 21 States the freshwater advisories are statewide; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9ECCA016D2B747F58D9F9375902BA87D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in 12 States the coastal advisories are statewide;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H741B1708AD1242C79F3C964E2333749F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the long-term solution to mercury pollution is to minimize global mercury use and releases to eventually achieve reduced contamination levels in the environment, rather than reducing fish consumption since uncontaminated fish represents a critical and healthy source of nutrition worldwide;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2225AD6B821B4AF7BCF3725DBF9DDF50"><enum>(7)</enum><text>mercury pollution is a transboundary pollutant, depositing locally, regionally, and globally, and affecting water bodies near industrial sources (including the Great Lakes) and remote areas (including the Arctic Circle);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7F572C36D77049228D7308849728E790"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the free trade of mercury on the world market, at relatively low prices and in ready supply, encourages the continued use of mercury outside of the United States, often involving highly dispersive activities such as artisinal gold mining;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H96904999E339401FA016B4FA2B4C4CBB"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the intentional use of mercury is declining in the United States as a consequence of process changes to manufactured products (including batteries, paints, switches, and measuring devices), but those uses remain substantial in the developing world where releases from the products are extremely likely due to the limited pollution control and waste management infrastructures in those countries;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H740525885AD34DDDAB8E7812055BC7CD"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the member countries of the European Union collectively are the largest source of mercury exports globally;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF093D73513F24C7E8EF899402427F2CB"><enum>(11)</enum><text>the European Commission has proposed to the European Parliament and to the Council of the European Union a regulation to ban exports of mercury from the European Union by 2011;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF7836CE5CFCF44E3B20067D3F7B2EE85"><enum>(12)</enum><text>the United States is a net exporter of mercury and, according to the United States Geological Survey, exported 506 metric tons of mercury more than the United States imported during the period of 2000 through 2004; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HACC6421DD83D4C31B43F1243FBD0A765"><enum>(13)</enum><text>banning exports of mercury from the United States will have a notable affect on the market availability of mercury and switching to affordable mercury alternatives in the developing world.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H681DC5D57E8E4B58AAD9F154023B1230"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on sale, distribution, or transfer of mercury</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6 of the Toxic Substances Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/2605">15 U.S.C. 2605</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC31C14B2F2044A3D856BE0F29CB95859" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H1BF0D21173F145E9A6BC521553E3B61B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Mercury</header> 
<paragraph id="H0FA5F74ADBF84696BD1396A396E54BB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition on sale, distribution, or transfer of mercury by Federal agencies</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), effective beginning on the date of enactment of this subsection, no Federal agency shall convey, sell, or distribute to any other Federal agency, any State or local government agency, or any private individual or entity any elemental mercury under the control or jurisdiction of the Federal agency.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H84B8A1C3F1E943E1A4B7552475C21200"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to a transfer between Federal agencies of elemental mercury for the sole purpose of facilitating storage of mercury to carry out this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HFB14791A1C9E495D996F19A83B223F00"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibition on export of mercury</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 12 of the Toxic Substances Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/2611">15 U.S.C. 2611</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE964BE5C0AB54F09A065D41FA553BFA2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a) by striking <quote>subsection (b)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsections (b) and (c)</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3B2E9F8E9973440C8D01B134AC21D9D8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8FD0869566F34E25B8FA0E44253D086" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H5B841CBEDFAC49CA86F122EC00A4146B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition on export of mercury</header> 
<paragraph id="H573D2A52B3414944B2CC2D52C2385AA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>Effective January 1, 2010, the export of elemental mercury from the United States is prohibited.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H157FA875FF80447D9BD742DA0500432E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inapplicability of subsection (<enum-in-header>a</enum-in-header>)</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply to this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDECC23FA789246F7B0BDD474F22D783C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report to congress on mercury compounds</header> 
<subparagraph id="H5E3C4F799ED14535AB3205BEBE932E1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Mercury Export Ban Act of 2007</short-title>, the Administrator shall publish and submit to Congress a report on mercuric chloride, mercurous chloride or calomel, mercuric oxide, and other mercury compounds, if any, that may currently be used in significant quantities in products or processes. Such report shall include an analysis of—</text> 
<clause id="HD83469E3743B463400EB5F1629F1A3A5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the sources and amounts of each of the mercury compounds produced annually in the United States or imported into the United States;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HAA5916EB98B740BAAD94D422C2ABD08D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the purposes for which each of these compounds are used domestically, the amount of these compounds currently consumed annually for each purpose, and the estimated amounts to be consumed for each purpose in 2010 and beyond;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8818488B792C43999B58544DEABDAFA6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the sources and amounts of each mercury compound exported from the United States annually in each of the last three years;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB1D4BEF51E674F97AFE0E4B06F5BD091"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the potential for these compounds to be processed into elemental mercury after export from the United States; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HCB3FC7BA00F244069CF050D362FE66A9"><enum>(v)</enum><text>other information that Congress should consider in determining whether to extend the export prohibition to include one or more of these mercury compounds.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB7ED4580F8AB427DA3CD9CF6BBDCDBFF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Procedure</header><text>For the purpose of preparing the report under this paragraph, the Administrator may utilize the information gathering authorities of this title, including sections 10 and 11, except that subsection (b)(2) of section 11 shall not apply to activities under this subparagraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H68F233BFAD9B4C0A0026AB8C943082A4"><enum>5.</enum><header>Excess Mercury Storage Advisory Committee</header> 
<subsection id="H8A148397B6724F1C83208343A59F04D9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title I of the Toxic Substances Control Act is amended by adding at the end the following new section: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFFF57E4A7FB2449AA1C303FDD4684584" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="HCEA1CD12C9D04B3D8EC24EDDFD00D04F" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>32.</enum><header>Excess Mercury Storage Advisory Committee</header> 
<subsection id="H0DBF0D47139043940010C9E737D34546"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established an advisory committee, to be known as the <quote>Excess Mercury Storage Advisory Committee</quote> (referred to in this section as the <term>Committee</term>).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H71222329B5C042CCA5E0B92CF1BFABD6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header> 
<paragraph id="H03F97D14E22F43FD86E23B95EA9D00FD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Committee shall be composed of 9 members, of whom—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H30C0EB601B654E2DA4CD9F631E5B4F19"><enum>(A)</enum><text>2 members shall be jointly appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives and the Majority Leader of the Senate—</text> 
<clause id="HECBDE34557004E47A22B6918A8B80013"><enum>(i)</enum><text>1 of whom shall be designated to serve as Chairperson of the Committee; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H43B03CDACDC6434000EE0260FC809060"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>1 of whom shall be designated to serve as Vice-Chairperson of the Committee;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0B794BB787AA4FCD8D45B1AB6DA1600"><enum>(B)</enum><text>1 member shall be the Administrator;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE8BE9D6DA8BD427983C21C840783D9CD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>1 member shall be the Secretary of Defense;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA8ADB1CA63C84344A494FA47A17EAF9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>1 member shall be a representative of State environmental agencies;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCCB6E280421847B9944D1B00AA67A5DD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>1 member shall be a representative of State attorneys general;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4CEDDEB66EB842CE94013000C00044E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>1 member shall be a representative of the chlorine industry;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE7518E92A32F472EBA13037F8CCEFB1"><enum>(G)</enum><text>1 member shall be a representative of the mercury waste treatment industry; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD8EAB20393D44678A50059D6D8E26764"><enum>(H)</enum><text>1 member shall be a representative of a nonprofit environmental organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3A1D1930F6724F86A94EB6473296529E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appointments</header><text>Not later than 45 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator, in consultation with the appropriate congressional committees, shall appoint the members of the Committee described in subparagraphs (D) through (H) of paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDE6BCA5CE5D84829BCC404C24927F1D5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Initial meeting</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which all members of the Committee have been appointed, the Committee shall hold the initial meeting of the Committee.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7FC9470DBCDE4922A01958F1D40700C8" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Committee shall meet at the call of the Chairperson.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA7B71EF42C254CB4AE3F00633E995754"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A majority of the members of the Committee shall constitute a quorum.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAD5D14EE19FE4F13AD4592905163BA86"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, the Committee shall submit to Congress a report describing the findings and recommendations of the Committee, if any, relating to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4431EE7CB26C455AB312D847E23026B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the environmental, health, and safety requirements necessary to prevent—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA0F1325F17E0405CB1CE49E97C1EBFD2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the release of elemental mercury into the environment; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEB3E3A180C6948D485A81518A05D1FB1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>worker exposure from the storage of elemental mercury;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2F71F09EB91041938460D49766E4F13E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the estimated annual cost of storing elemental mercury on a per-pound or per-ton basis;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDC977F19587E4571A5AD82549191FD4B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for the 40-year period beginning on the date of submission of the report, the optimal size, number, and other characteristics of Federal facilities required to store elemental mercury under current and anticipated jurisdictions of each Federal agency;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H389DB12CB85E4CCEB1A0C7B0382DCC1B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the estimated quantity of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8476B1E66EB740F39CBF6568E3D44467"><enum>(A)</enum><text>elemental mercury that will result from the decommissioning of mercury cell chlor-alkali facilities in the United States; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEAD70D778506457485640300F9D49132"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other supplies that may require storage to carry out this Act;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2E1C71E76BF04A8EA7514C4E00497782"><enum>(5)</enum><text>for the 40-year period beginning on the date of submission of the report, the estimated quantity of elemental mercury generated from the recycling of unwanted products and other wastes that will require storage to comply with the export prohibitions under this Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7C1CD96AE6C846F78948527E18285752"><enum>(6)</enum><text>any legal, technical, economic, or other barrier that may prevent the private sector from storing elemental mercury produced by the private sector during the 40-year period beginning on the date of submission of the report, including a description of measures to address the barriers;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8476851E667246D18E4B3B2D84436E1B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the advantages and disadvantages of consolidating the storage of mercury produced by public and private sources under the management of the public or private sector;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H20CDB3894515425E8DEB143D04DBD2C2"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the optimal plan of the Committee for storing excess mercury produced by public and private sources; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H12B1649E22E645B4B0549277B3BCDA2"><enum>(9)</enum><text>additional research, if any, required to determine a long-term disposal option for the storage of excess mercury.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9E73ACEEB29D41B78800DAF22F24F7E7"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Compensation of members</header> 
<paragraph id="HDEA0D81F23AB4B53A5BC63AE888214FB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header> 
<subparagraph id="H975C3B55EC1B49A7B0F1850362CE99E1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Non-federal employees</header><text>A member of the Committee who is not an officer or employee of the Federal Government shall be compensated at a rate equal to the daily equivalent of the annual rate of basic pay prescribed for level V of the Executive Schedule under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/5316">section 5316</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, for each day (including travel time) during which the member is engaged in the performance of the duties of the Committee.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H061BEE6CE6E246FD92EA1C921BEE623E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Federal employees</header><text>A member of the Committee who is an officer or employee of the Federal Government shall serve without compensation in addition to the compensation received for the services of the member as an officer or employee of the Federal Government.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1E5E95E36D7B4D7F8E75D7003FA42835" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Travel expenses</header><text>A member of the Committee shall be allowed travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, at rates authorized for an employee of an agency under subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, while away from the home or regular place of business of the member in the performance of the duties of the Committee.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB2377D54C14547099B302B009DB3CAE"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Staff and funding</header><text>The Administrator shall provide to the Committee such funding and additional personnel as are necessary to enable the Committee to perform the duties of the Committee.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBF77140B5F5C460F835EDBAF298799E2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Committee shall terminate 180 days after the date on which the Committee submits the report of the Committee under subsection (f).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD5823A7E8EC744759647BCFA1B290042"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents amendment</header><text>The table of contents of the Toxic Substances Control Act is amended by adding after the item relating to section 31 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H437993CE10624FE29F8BFEF498BCEB14" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 32. Excess Mercury Storage Advisory Committee.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


