<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF1B3749DF8684E9A00E0F53104C7E8F6" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 5632 IH: To prohibit the importation of certain low-level radioactive waste into the United States.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2008-03-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 5632</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20080313">March 13, 2008</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000309">Mr. Gordon of Tennessee</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000413">Mr. Whitfield of Kentucky</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001142">Mr. Matheson</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To prohibit the importation of certain low-level radioactive waste into the United States.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H06D38851741345ECBF6979AB6D86ED92" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB7D6859B73AE48F4B896202C813821DF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Prohibition of importation</header> 
<subsection id="H03D39A1054754A978114EE1EAD92D49F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Chapter 8 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2111">42 U.S.C. 2111 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="other" id="H1D30B1ED04E24AC7B7C7989326B4942E" display-inline="no-display-inline" other-style="nuclear"> 
<section id="HD50DE1C8362F4D949BBD5D440028342E"><enum>85.</enum><header>Importation of low-level radioactive waste</header> 
<subsection id="H3F7966473A044C53A37F290314915D53"><enum>a.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection b. or c., the Commission shall not issue a license authorizing the importation into the United States of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0204012B3D434C228CECE3772E72B2F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>low-level radioactive waste (as defined in section 2 of the Low-Level Radioactive Waste Policy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2021b">42 U.S.C. 2021b</external-xref>)); or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE6DF6F8FE3A141BB989049691987BA08"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">specific radioactive waste streams exempted from regulation by the Commission under section 10 of the Low-Level Radioactive Waste Policy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2021j">42 U.S.C. 2021j</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H124DF19966504D7FBEC8B490D6839E63"><enum>b.</enum><text>Subsection a. shall not apply to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5952AAE5E65E4BD091A400D731C2353C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">low-level radioactive waste being returned to a United States Government or military facility which is authorized to possess the material; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAEB5C3B662C54E00A1FCEBEDEAEFB31"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">low-level radioactive waste resulting from the use in a foreign country of nuclear material obtained by the foreign user from an entity in the United States that is being returned to the United States for management and disposal.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB20EEC5594C54AB7A71EE70472D8C27D"><enum>c.</enum><text>The President may waive the prohibition under this section and authorize the grant of a specific license to import materials prohibited under subsection a., under the rules of the Commission, only after a finding that such importation would meet an important national or international policy goal, such as the use of waste for research purposes. Such a waiver must specify the policy goal to be achieved, how it is to be achieved, and the amount of material to be imported.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H911DC6253EC84493BC261F4B90CCC805"><enum>d.</enum><text>A license not permitted under this section that was issued before the date of enactment of this section may continue in effect according to its terms, but may not be extended or amended with respect to the amount of material permitted to be imported.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA5C3BAC7F8B54C43988405C7B2880246"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents amendment</header><text>The table of contents for the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 is amended by inserting at the end of the items relating to chapter 8 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2FDA51E800CB4C73AF5C5DB08D1B427" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 85. Importation of low-level radioactive waste.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


