<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="HAC001C4F095844B4BF7C39CD6792DD23" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>109 HR 3043 RH: Zero Downpayment Pilot Program Act of 2006</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2006-07-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code> 
<calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 326</calendar> 
<congress display="yes">109th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3043</legis-num> 
<associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 109-571]</associated-doc> 
<current-chamber display="yes">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20050623">June 23, 2005</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000462">Mr. Tiberi</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00" added-display-style="italic">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20060717">July 17, 2006</action-date> 
<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc> 
<action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction> 
<action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on June 23, 2005</action-instruction> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development to carry out a pilot program to insure zero-downpayment mortgages for one-unit residences.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HBA00" reported-display-style="italic" id="HDCC61A2BC1DF444492AD281CF2C03674"> 
<section changed="added" id="H15FEA4F11F7C4E23908EDCA221F9ABA3" section-type="section-one" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Zero Downpayment Pilot Program Act of 2006</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section changed="added" id="H418EA2E006014D9A8CB8974C991460CD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pilot program for insurance for zero-downpayment mortgages</header> 
<subsection changed="added" id="H6BF2394CF9904DEAA4B8641757E07205"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Mortgage insurance authority</header><text>Section 203 of the <act-name parsable-cite="NHA">National Housing Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1709">12 U.S.C. 1709</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after subsection (k) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="National Housing Act" id="HD8851CBEFB2A447F87FD5D817551CBA5"> 
<subsection changed="added" id="H32CAEEDAB5984835B42CE290D5F2D637"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Zero-Downpayment mortgages pilot program</header> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="H0EEDB1E471054C88B752115CE3E4200"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Insurance authority</header><text>The Secretary may insure, and commit to insure, under this subsection any mortgage that meets the requirements of this subsection and, except as otherwise specifically provided in this subsection, of subsection (b).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="HE0CE9F001C084229A948A970E85C465C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible single family property</header><text>To be eligible for insurance under this subsection, a mortgage shall involve a property upon which there is located a dwelling that is designed principally for a 1- to 3-family residence and that, notwithstanding subsection (g), is to be occupied by the mortgagor as his or her principal residence, which shall include—</text> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="HEE711AC6F47E4504855D7CD626AB001B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a 1-family dwelling unit in a multifamily project and an undivided interest in the common areas and facilities which serve the project;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="HBAE89E5B38634902B2A7FA5404DB6647"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a 1-family dwelling unit of a cooperative housing corporation the permanent occupancy of the dwelling units of which is restricted to members of such corporation and in which the purchase of such stock or membership entitles the purchaser to the permanent occupancy of such dwelling unit; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="HCEEA4F59D3D54A2799BEF91662161300"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a manufactured home that meets such standards as the Secretary has established for purposes of subsection (b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="HA598A7890BE94665993B66E14B88C2F9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Maximum principal obligation</header> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="HAE835AC317534BB9BBE1168C9BBFB7AD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>To be eligible for insurance under this subsection, a mortgage shall involve a principal obligation in an amount not in excess of 100 percent of the appraised value of the property plus any initial service charges, appraisal, inspection and other fees in connection with the mortgage as approved by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="H3CC686EF21704968ACAE181E685B7E2F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inapplicability of other loan-to-value requirements</header><text>A mortgage insured under this subsection shall not be subject to subparagraph (B) of paragraph (2) of subsection (b) or to the matter in such paragraph that follows such subparagraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="HB692FDDDC21B430889EBE9FE08985846"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible mortgagors</header><text>The mortgagor under a mortgage insured under this subsection shall meet the following requirements:</text> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="H44DBF6FEFF884EEA8C470666C3E5DFD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>First-time homebuyer</header><text>The mortgagor shall be a first-time homebuyer. The program for mortgage insurance under this subsection shall be considered a Federal program to assist first-time homebuyers for purposes of section 956 of the <act-name parsable-cite="CGNHA">Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12713">42 U.S.C. 12713</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="HB04B21C845104234A0CB6B4341C16214"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Counseling</header> 
<clause changed="added" id="H8EBD991809DD46D49EFD015B20DCCC07"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>The mortgagor shall have received counseling, prior to application for the loan involved in the mortgage, by a third party (other than the mortgagee) who is approved by the Secretary, with respect to the responsibilities and financial management involved in homeownership. Such counseling shall be provided to the mortgagor on an individual basis by a representative of the approved third party counseling entity, and shall be provided in person to the maximum extent practicable.</text></clause> 
<clause changed="added" id="H1B298ACB316E43CB9B6C6C073E3C9DA1"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Topics</header><text>Such counseling shall include providing to, and discussing with, the mortgagor—</text> 
<subclause changed="added" id="HBF9DD629889F4A7EA4247510723472B1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>information regarding homeownership options other than a mortgage insured under this subsection, other zero- or low-downpayment mortgage options that are or may become available to the mortgagor, the financial implications of entering into a mortgage (including a mortgage insured under this subsection), and any other information that the Secretary may require; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause changed="added" id="HF627578C24184CBD9700F651C295CDBD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a document that sets forth the amount and the percentage by which a property subject to a mortgage insured under this subsection must appreciate for the mortgagor to recover the principal amount of the mortgage, the costs financed under the mortgage, and the estimated costs involved in selling the property, if the mortgagor were to sell the property on each of the second, fifth, and tenth anniversaries of the mortgage.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause changed="added" id="H99CA728A5E4245B2B372968368A91819"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>2- and 3-family residences</header><text>In the case of a mortgage involving a 2- or 3-family residence, such counseling shall include (in addition to the information required under clause (ii)) information regarding real estate property management.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="H16FE27F6432844D6A4FB3DB500441FF2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Option for notice of foreclosure prevention counseling availability</header> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="H02D51F8958D0494E8B8F786FE4E3EC1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Option</header><text>To be eligible for insurance under this subsection, the mortgagee shall provide mortgagor, at the time of the execution of the mortgage, an optional written agreement which, if signed by the mortgagor, allows, but does not require, the mortgagee to provide notice described in subparagraph (B) to a housing counseling entity that has agreed to provide the notice and counseling required under subparagraph (C) and is approved by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="H1021A99964CB47C3824EF8F874732284"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notice to counseling agency</header><text>The notice described in this subparagraph, with respect to a mortgage, is notice, provided at the earliest time practicable after the mortgagor becomes 60 days delinquent with respect to any payment due under the mortgage, that the mortgagor is so delinquent and of how to contact the mortgagor. Such notice may only be provided once with respect to each delinquency period for a mortgage.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="H0C5B554CBF6145CFB4D35F949444DD23"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Notice to mortgagor</header><text>Upon notice from a mortgagee that a mortgagor is 60 days delinquent with respect to payments due under the mortgage, the housing counseling entity shall at the earliest time practicable notify the mortgagor of such delinquency, that the entity makes available foreclosure prevention counseling that may assist the mortgagor in resolving the delinquency, and of how to contact the entity to arrange for such counseling.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="H61CF8C6C3EC943578F02B4DD8D63EE15"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Ability to cure</header><text>Failure to provide the optional written agreement required under subparagraph (A) may be corrected by sending such agreement to the mortgagor not later than the earliest time practicable after the mortgagor first becomes 60 days delinquent with respect to payments due under the mortgage. Insurance provided under this subsection may not be terminated and penalties for such failure may not be prospectively or retroactively imposed if such failure is corrected in accordance with this subparagraph.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="HF165DF2A64794F2984DD46B5D4CB315E"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Penalties for failure to provide agreement</header><text>The Secretary may establish and impose appropriate penalties for failure of a mortgagee to provide the optional written agreement required under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="HFC57C4ACDC1D47FE835B129D98989BEC"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Limitation on liability of mortgagee</header><text>A mortgagee shall not incur any liability or penalties for any failure of a housing counseling entity to provide notice under subparagraph (C).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="HBFD4327BEFB84C3F91ECB84CF19718F8"><enum>(G)</enum><header>No private right of action</header><text>This paragraph shall not create any private right of action on behalf of the mortgagor.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="HACEFEA65EED54932A514B4E6D0B49582"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Delinquency period</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>delinquency period</term> means, with respect to a mortgage, a period that begins upon the mortgagor becoming delinquent with respect to payments due under the mortgage and ends upon the first subsequent occurrence of such payments under the mortgage becoming current or the property subject to the mortgage being foreclosed or otherwise disposed of.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="H7C7E4D1D96E84C3BBF7B12FDD68B38A2"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Inapplicability of downpayment requirement</header><text>A mortgage insured under this subsection shall not be subject to paragraph (9) of subsection (b) or any other requirement to pay on account of the property, in cash or its equivalent, any amount of the cost of acquisition.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="H5FE8C6E3FA0A41F28CDB9C0831BA0045"><enum>(7)</enum><header>MMIF monitoring</header><text>In conjunction with the credit subsidy estimation calculated each year pursuant to the <act-name parsable-cite="FCRA90">Federal Credit Reform Act of 1990</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/661">2 U.S.C. 661 et seq.</external-xref>), the Secretary shall review the program performance for mortgages insured under this subsection and make any necessary adjustments, which may include altering mortgage insurance premiums subject to subsection (c)(2), adjusting underwriting standards, and limiting the availability of mortgage insurance under this subsection, to ensure that the Mutual Mortgage Insurance Fund shall continue to generate a negative credit subsidy.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="HB65F382EE3404221A4E30542B200BE18"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Underwriting</header><text>For a mortgage to be eligible for insurance under this subsection:</text> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="H1A4B88D0C6A34877AEE78C31E3BFD200"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The mortgagor’s credit and ability to pay the monthly mortgage payments shall have been evaluated using the Federal Housing Administration’s Technology Open To Approved Lenders (TOTAL) Mortgage Scorecard, or a similar standardized credit scoring system approved by the Secretary, and in accordance with procedures established by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="H687C77987F464023B6F186905C542EA3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Multi-unit properties</header><text>In the case of a mortgage involving a property upon which there is located a dwelling that is designed principally for a 2- or 3-family residence, the mortgagor meets such additional underwriting standards as the Secretary may establish.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="H42801924B57E4FE4AD583885DDE5B0E0"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Approval of mortgagees</header><text>To be eligible for insurance under this subsection, a mortgage shall have been made to a mortgagee that meets such criteria as the Secretary shall establish to ensure that mortgagees meet appropriate standards for participation in the program authorized under this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="HCB6C8787FCAE4DDD831CC111ECD267A9"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Disclosure of incremental costs</header> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="H47F57EAAC086492EB3C178C6CD5F2717"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Required disclosure</header><text>For a mortgage to be eligible for insurance under this subsection, the mortgagee shall provide to the mortgagor, at the time of the application for the loan involved in the mortgage, a written disclosure, as the Secretary shall require, that specifies the effective cost to a mortgagor of borrowing the amount by which the maximum amount that could be borrowed under a mortgage insured under this subsection exceeds the maximum amount that could be borrowed under a mortgage insured under subsection (b), based on average closing costs with respect to such amount, as determined by the Secretary. Such cost shall be expressed as an annual interest rate over the first 5 years of a mortgage.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="H150C074E72434416A361625CD4CFA870"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The disclosure required under this paragraph may be provided in conjunction with the notice required under subsection (f).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="H7B00238AC2B5471392B5841F51CDFD5E"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Loss mitigation</header> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="HA19786545C574A24B5A1009825C0E1B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon the default of any mortgage insured under this subsection, the mortgagee shall engage in loss mitigation actions for the purpose of providing an alternative to foreclosure to the same extent as is required of other mortgages insured under this title pursuant to the regulations issued under section 230(a).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="HDB6932A6A0094B23839C01A2B5751C79"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Annual reporting</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the end of each fiscal year, the Secretary shall submit a report to the Congress that compares the rates of default and foreclosure during such fiscal year for mortgages insured under this subsection, for single-family mortgages insured under this title (other than under this subsection), and for mortgages for housing purchased with assistance provided under the downpayment assistance initiative under section 271 of the <act-name parsable-cite="CGNHA">Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12821">42 U.S.C. 12821</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="HAE8494FED8574763B2832F641B196CA6"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Additional requirements</header><text>The Secretary may establish any additional requirements for mortgage insurance under this subsection as may be necessary or appropriate.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="H01A4126333D4408885646DAA9837A12E"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Pilot program limitations</header> 
<subparagraph id="H2DD6D42D6E7F4A519FC195BF277068D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Annual</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In any fiscal year, the aggregate number of mortgages insured under this subsection may not exceed 10 percent of the aggregate number of mortgages and loans insured by the Secretary under this title during the preceding fiscal year.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3F07D7E584B54C6B8E898756F1D8D000"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Term of program</header><text>The aggregate number or mortgages insured under this subsection may not exceed 50,000.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="HCD750675C35648EF93F01F9C67C82778"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Program suspension</header> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="H22B458A8AF5045DCAECBB3AFF88439A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (C), the authority under paragraph (1) to insure mortgages shall be suspended if at any time the claim rate described in subparagraph (B) exceeds 3.5 percent. A suspension under this subparagraph shall remain in effect until such time as such claim rate is 3.5 percent or less.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="H868D7EEBAD464E4F9FFCDFCC1709805D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>FHA TOTAL single-family annual claim rate</header><text>The claim rate described in this subparagraph, for any particular time, is the ratio of the number of claims during the 12 months preceding such time on mortgages on 1- to 4-family residences insured pursuant to this title to the number of mortgages on such residences having such insurance in force at that time.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph changed="added" id="HCC658C85EE32447DBC573D6DCAC39B00"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>A suspension under subparagraph (A) shall not preclude the Secretary from endorsing or insuring any mortgage that was duly executed before the date of such suspension.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="HC0903D8207164B250019050800B6E02"><enum>(15)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>No mortgage may be insured under this subsection after September 30, 2010, except that the Secretary may endorse or insure any mortgage that was duly executed before such date.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="H87F6C3E27CA547418FAD30E95C17E912"><enum>(16)</enum><header>GAO reports</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall submit a report to the Congress not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this subsection, and annually thereafter, regarding the performance of mortgages insured under this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph changed="added" id="H49C06B5F5C014502B39E29734E2034FF"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The Secretary may implement this subsection on an interim basis by issuing an interim rule, except that the Secretary shall solicit public comments upon publication of such interim rule and shall issue a final rule implementing this subsection after consideration of the comments submitted.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection changed="added" id="H6D23CE5961314CEEAD2FC07E9B0056C5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Mortgage insurance premiums</header><text>The second sentence of subparagraph (A) of section 203(c)(2) of the <act-name parsable-cite="NHA">National Housing Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1709">12 U.S.C. 1709(c)(2)(A)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>In</quote> and inserting <quote>Except with respect to a mortgage insured under subsection (l), in</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection changed="added" id="H656711F9F3394DA700A9D34EAF634626"><enum>(c)</enum><header>General insurance fund</header><text>Section 519(e) of the <act-name parsable-cite="NHA">National Housing Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1735c">12 U.S.C. 1735c(e)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and 203(i)</quote> and inserting <quote>, 203(i), and 203(l)</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCE759EC93C4F47BB8D81D889075015A0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>GAO study of expanded or extended program</header><text>If at any time authority to insure mortgages under section 203(l) of the National Housing Act (as added by subsection (a) of this section) is—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6B520183FA0643069C985FFFA7B247CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>expanded to more than 50,000 mortgages, or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H86B70367530241BB9C0072A682005FFC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>extended to a date after September 30, 2010, including any permanent extension of such authority,</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study of the financial soundness, at such time, of the Mutual Mortgage Insurance Fund and the effects of such expansion or extension on such financial soundness, and shall submit a report to the Congress regarding the conclusions of such study not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of the law providing for such expansion or extension. </continuation-text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
<endorsement display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20060717">July 17, 2006</action-date> 
<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement> 
</bill> 


