<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H91FDAE66010B434FA918345902AC7E3E" public-private="public">
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>111th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 3045</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20090625">June 25, 2009</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Waters</sponsor> (for
			 herself, <cosponsor name-id="F000339">Mr. Frank of Massachusetts</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="B001234">Mr. Baca</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001232">Mrs.
			 Biggert</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial
			 Services</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To reform the housing choice voucher program under
		  section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H68B1AF584EF5412F94FEA748BAE574EB" style="OLC">
		<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA55B048EFF0B4F50BD2CC726BB01E027" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title and table of
			 contents</header>
			<subsection id="H955FFD8272AD42F58899A656445DA431"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short
			 title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited
			 as the <quote><short-title>Section 8 Voucher Reform Act of
			 2009</short-title></quote>.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HEC2ECDF6862C4307921B33A0DC7FE77C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of
			 contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
				<toc container-level="legis-body-container" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration">
					<toc-entry idref="HA55B048EFF0B4F50BD2CC726BB01E027" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title and table of contents.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H63F4E0F9D9AB439686A6FC584CD39DEA" level="section">Sec. 2. Inspection of dwelling units.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HB19D2C8A3FD645098A7AB42E1AF07ABA" level="section">Sec. 3. Rent reform and income reviews.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H1067D041ADFE4A56B48566D33C1D866E" level="section">Sec. 4. Eligibility for assistance based on assets and
				income.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HD0298447E029444FA7C823420DF83A4E" level="section">Sec. 5. Targeting assistance to low-income working
				families.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H3364B6DCABD14F23AA53E57E25FDED99" level="section">Sec. 6. Voucher renewal funding.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H1E55D68635FB41AE8A17BCAE98DCD38A" level="section">Sec. 7. Administrative fees.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HC4379E968A8945E5B4EDC5BBE0D4B483" level="section">Sec. 8. Homeownership.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HC423EDFA62FC4D30BCCA065DF8C2BE02" level="section">Sec. 9. PHA reporting of rent payments to credit reporting
				agencies.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HDCC920FD53B74E57B2AFBD5E74A082FA" level="section">Sec. 10. Performance assessments.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H835B51D401804C28B60579255287EC4D" level="section">Sec. 11. PHA project-based assistance.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H892F10A56091470E9582D69CD909DE00" level="section">Sec. 12. Rent burdens.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H05BEB1A8C7524EE988207182262C1C4C" level="section">Sec. 13. Establishment of fair market rent.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H55EFFB887985415A9F0A06CEAC228142" level="section">Sec. 14. Screening of applicants.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HBF27ED3BD77B4B05A84881030B5A6A2F" level="section">Sec. 15. Enhanced vouchers.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H4BC8E2A110344F17AE3A6D5B9BF444AF" level="section">Sec. 16. Demonstration program waiver authority.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFB3C1ECAFB3944418DDAE8D9FC438593" level="section">Sec. 17. Authorization of appropriations.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H043D3A7152D547DCBA08010717AD024B" level="section">Sec. 18. Agency authority for utility payments in certain
				circumstances.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H3221B45F14924DED933E0981B3D5B71A" level="section">Sec. 19. Project-based preservation vouchers.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HBA3BEEF31054412C864E10F2DC7FF6C7" level="section">Sec. 20. Effect of foreclosure on section 8
				tenancies.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H099CAB1340CB470C9242B6FB78F6CE65" level="section">Sec. 21. Study to identify obstacles to using vouchers in
				federally subsidized housing projects.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H836A18F868D1480FA7306C671BD0FC34" level="section">Sec. 22. Interagency Council on Homelessness.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H23B00AC18B1147A0B920B5DB5B0A331C" level="section">Sec. 23. Housing innovation program.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H699B311EBF234320BEB31FEEE73FC82B" level="section">Sec. 24. Effective date.</toc-entry>
				</toc>
			</subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H63F4E0F9D9AB439686A6FC584CD39DEA" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Inspection of dwelling
			 units</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8(o)(8) of the
			 United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(8)) is amended—</text>
			<paragraph id="H623E5EA7A33148D1A96FEBD9848FF21A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking
			 subparagraph (A) and inserting the following new subparagraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE856FDBE364C43E486FB6F49F568C08B" style="OLC">
					<subparagraph id="H6F1202AE932F4AE18D45B30D0284D63F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial
				inspection</header>
						<clause id="H9EA58BC6BC884DF497DC04D47BAEC18A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text>For each dwelling unit for which a housing assistance
				payment contract is established under this subsection, the public housing
				agency (or other entity pursuant to paragraph (11)) shall inspect the unit
				before any assistance payment is made to determine whether the dwelling unit
				meets the housing quality standards under subparagraph (B), except as provided
				in clause (ii) or (iii) of this subparagraph.</text>
						</clause><clause commented="no" id="HAAFD814227E2490293A594AF01FCB9EB"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Correction of
				non-life threatening conditions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any dwelling unit that is
				determined, pursuant to an inspection under clause (i), not to meet the housing
				quality standards under subparagraph (B), assistance payments may be made for
				the unit notwithstanding subparagraph (C) if failure to meet such standards is
				a result only of non-life threatening conditions. A public housing agency
				making assistance payments pursuant to this clause for a dwelling unit shall,
				30 days after the beginning of the period for which such payments are made,
				suspend any assistance payments for the unit if any deficiency resulting in
				noncompliance with the housing quality standards has not been corrected by such
				time, and may not resume such payments until each such deficiency has been
				corrected.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H526B30377F164848AC271D92471F9DA3"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Use of
				alternative inspection method for interim period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any property that within the
				previous 12 months has met the requirements of an inspection that qualifies as
				an alternative inspection method pursuant to subparagraph (E), a public housing
				agency may authorize occupancy before the inspection under clause (i) has been
				completed, and may make assistance payments retroactive to the beginning of the
				lease term after the unit has been determined pursuant to an inspection under
				clause (i) to meet the housing quality standards under subparagraph
				(B).</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0D53B607904743B7B15B14300F55CBCC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating
			 subparagraph (E) as subparagraph (H); and</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HBDF7E9BC656A44A186E0D4B137B636E8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking
			 subparagraph (D) and inserting the following new subparagraphs:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7B1D1C210B5D499591945EBC91D9E56E" style="OLC">
					<subparagraph id="H862735397F17416280A1A699ACA2068F"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Biennial
				inspections</header>
						<clause id="HC6EBE00A6D674CD1A491AE2DE8B2759A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each public housing agency providing
				assistance under this subsection (or other entity, as provided in paragraph
				(11)) shall, for each assisted dwelling unit, make inspections not less often
				than biennially during the term of the housing assistance payments contract for
				the unit to determine whether the unit is maintained in accordance with the
				requirements under subparagraph (A).</text>
						</clause><clause id="HCC5E5452906F42B7A4E1F2551AE2C750"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Use of
				alternative inspection method</header><text>The requirement under clause (i)
				may be complied with by use of inspections that qualify as an alternative
				inspection method pursuant to subparagraph (E).</text>
						</clause><clause id="H9644111A52884F3C81A6AC2BE6AA296D"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Records</header><text>The
				agency (or other entity) shall retain the records of the inspection for a
				reasonable time and shall make the records available upon request to the
				Secretary, the Inspector General for the Department of Housing and Urban
				Development, and any auditor conducting an audit under section 5(h).</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H479C1684060E47768F1170E9FAD75A24"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Alternative
				inspection method</header><text>An inspection of a property shall qualify as an
				alternative inspection method for purposes of this subparagraph if—</text>
						<clause id="H287BEAD649744C728783CDB51500C808"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the inspection was
				conducted pursuant to requirements under a Federal, State, or local housing
				assistance program (including the HOME investment partnerships program under
				title II of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (42 U.S.C.
				12721 et seq.) and the low-income housing tax credit program under section 42
				of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986); and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H77B9E7DD62024497BA27CC86D196B6BB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>pursuant to such
				inspection, the property was determined to meet the standards or requirements
				regarding housing quality or safety applicable to units assisted under such
				program, and, if a non-Federal standard was used, the public housing agency has
				certified to the Secretary that such standards or requirements provide the same
				protection to occupants of dwelling units meeting such standards or
				requirements as, or greater protection than, the housing quality standards
				under subparagraph (B).</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC4DBA68EB9D841EE8B1D3D4649830FE5"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Interim
				inspections</header><text>Upon notification to the public housing agency, by a
				family on whose behalf tenant-based rental assistance is provided under this
				subsection or by a government official, that the dwelling unit for which such
				assistance is provided does not comply with the housing quality standards under
				subparagraph (B), the agency shall inspect the dwelling unit—</text>
						<clause id="HB9F7191391804856AD23D53790D273E3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in
				the case of any condition that is life-threatening, within 24 hours after
				receipt of such notice; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H9D336C4A46024220876744E3B6587CAE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of
				any condition that is not life-threatening, within 15 days after receipt of
				such notice.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40DBCD960F194CC786FB66FDEAB45BB0"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Enforcement of
				housing quality standards</header>
						<clause id="HA498B24E0EE74A1A8D4EF6EC034B2003"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Determination of
				noncompliance</header><text>A dwelling unit that is covered by a housing
				assistance payments contract under this subsection shall be considered, for
				purposes of subparagraphs (D) and (F), to be in noncompliance with the housing
				quality standards under subparagraph (B) if—</text>
							<subclause id="H9D27EE6267EE4735BE1CD364DAACF617"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the public housing
				agency or an inspector authorized by the State or unit of local government
				determines upon inspection of the unit that the unit fails to comply with such
				standards;</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H915C2FD5BCE446CEA5AF5C734070B15F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the agency or
				inspector notifies the owner of the unit in writing of such failure to comply;
				and</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="HE1E165B9225B4CD1B83BBDFB4C448CC0"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the failure to
				comply is not corrected—</text>
								<item id="HCD33A354CEB4482DBA66720EA92D0DA8"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in
				the case of any such failure that is a result of life-threatening conditions,
				within 24 hours after such notice has been provided; and</text>
								</item><item id="HB5A640CF6909448C9B8400F8A9F6EF86"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in
				the case of any such failure that is a result of non-life threatening
				conditions, within 30 days after such notice has been provided or such other
				reasonable longer period as the public housing agency may establish.</text>
								</item></subclause></clause><clause id="H8BE4165B51394DC286DC7365ED112AE8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Withholding of
				assistance amounts during correction</header><text>The public housing agency
				may withhold assistance amounts under this subsection with respect to a
				dwelling unit that does not comply with housing quality standards under
				subparagraph (B) as determined pursuant to an inspection conducted under
				subparagraph (D) or (F). If the unit is brought into compliance with such
				housing quality standards during the periods referred to in clause (i)(III),
				the public housing agency shall recommence assistance payments and may use any
				amounts withheld during the correction period to make assistance payments
				relating to the period during which payments were withheld.</text>
						</clause><clause id="HF20FF10A806B4C03951DDA8592865910"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Abatement of
				assistance amounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The public
				housing agency shall abate all of the assistance amounts under this subsection
				with respect to a dwelling unit that is determined, pursuant to subparagraph
				(G)(i), to be in noncompliance with housing quality standards under
				subparagraph (B). Upon completion of repairs by the public housing agency or
				the owner sufficient so that the dwelling unit complies with such housing
				quality standards, the agency shall recommence payments under the housing
				assistance payments contract to the owner of the dwelling unit.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H1D41EDA13DC34170BD55558AD9A1C988"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Use of abated
				assistance to pay for repairs</header>
							<subclause id="H5B683215A91D4CE5AC92B4D280E31E7B"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The public housing agency may use such
				amounts abated to make repairs to the dwelling unit or to contract to have
				repairs made, except that a contract to make repairs may not be entered into
				with the inspector for the dwelling unit referred to in clause (i)(I).</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H4B8D4533AC5F45A2BF20BB319C370C47"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Abated
				funds</header><text>For purposes of this clause, abated amounts may include an
				amounts withheld during the correction period described in clause (ii) of this
				subparagraph with respect to a dwelling unit that is subsequently determined
				under clause (i) to be in noncompliance with housing quality standards.</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H385F7126BEEE4E4A864AF2BBD1525EBA"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Limitation of
				liability of public housing agencies</header><text>A public housing agency that
				uses its authority under this clause shall not, if the agency accomplishes the
				work through a contractor that is licensed, bonded, and insured in amounts and
				with coverage as required by the Secretary, be liable for any injury or damages
				that may result to persons or to any property owned by the tenant or
				owner.</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause id="H4FB847CC9C9E4A4BA84E3C4E72000FDC"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>If
				a public housing agency providing assistance under this subsection abates
				rental assistance payments pursuant to clause (iii) with respect to a dwelling
				unit, the agency shall, upon commencement of such abatement—</text>
							<subclause id="H3E298DAADED34653AE3AB02520754237"><enum>(I)</enum><text>notify the tenant
				and the owner of the dwelling unit that—</text>
								<item id="HEFCD9A5206B5428E857D9C081468184F"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>such abatement
				has commenced; and</text>
								</item><item id="HB7814BB2A9364CAA9539BDE0351D063C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>if
				the dwelling unit is not brought into compliance with housing quality standards
				within 60 days after the effective date of the determination of noncompliance
				under clause (i) or such reasonable longer period as the agency may establish,
				the tenant will have to move; and</text>
								</item></subclause><subclause id="H4F013F12DDDD4F97BB77A6431FCA9CA2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>issue the tenant
				the necessary forms to allow the tenant to move to another dwelling unit and
				transfer the rental assistance to that unit.</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause id="H2B893254F07744B7AD08D4799DBE1E3B"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Protection of
				tenants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An owner of a
				dwelling unit may not terminate the tenancy of any tenant because of the
				withholding or abatement of assistance pursuant to this subparagraph. During
				the period that assistance is abated pursuant to this subparagraph, the tenant
				may terminate the tenancy by notifying the owner.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H042D73AC7EDD447A91FDDD195B31D495"><enum>(vii)</enum><header>Termination of
				lease or assistance payments contract</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If assistance amounts under this section
				for a dwelling unit are abated pursuant to clause (iii) and the owner does not
				correct the noncompliance within 60 days after the effective date of the
				determination of noncompliance under clause (i), or such other reasonable
				longer period as the public housing agency may establish, and the agency does
				not use its authority under clause (iv), the agency shall terminate the housing
				assistance payments contract for the dwelling unit.</text>
						</clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8A28BD46C4634EB1AA88FA824A420BE9"><enum>(viii)</enum><header>Relocation</header>
							<subclause id="HE399F760F0F94261A6B80FF91028FBC1"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Lease of new
				unit</header><text>The agency shall provide the family residing in such a
				dwelling unit a period of 90 days or such longer period as is necessary to
				lease a new unit, beginning upon termination of the contract, to lease a new
				residence with tenant-based rental assistance under this section.</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H8A4BA9332732423DAFFFF8B92EEB192A"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Availability of
				public housing units</header><text>If the family is unable to lease such a new
				residence during such period, the public housing agency shall, at the option of
				the family, provide such family a preference for occupancy in a dwelling unit
				of public housing owned or operated by the agency that first becomes available
				for occupancy after the expiration of such period.</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="HC0C2E3DF3F4D40FE8122B83FF0D2B4FE"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Assistance in
				finding unit</header><text>The public housing agency shall provide reasonable
				assistance to the family in finding a new residence, including use of up to two
				months of any assistance amounts abated pursuant to clause (iii) for costs
				directly associated with relocation of the family to a new residence, which may
				include moving expenses and security deposits. The agency may require that a
				family receiving assistance for a security deposit shall remit, to the extent
				of such assistance, the amount of any security deposit refunds made by the
				owner of the dwelling unit for which the lease was terminated.</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause id="H13617DC0E1CF4B6A95D6E959DC914954"><enum>(ix)</enum><header>Tenant-caused
				damages</header><text>If a public housing agency determines that any damage to
				a dwelling unit that results in a failure of the dwelling unit to comply with
				housing quality standards under subparagraph (B), other than any damage
				resulting from ordinary use, was caused by the tenant, any member of the
				tenant’s household, or any guest or other person under the tenant’s control,
				the agency may waive the applicability of this subparagraph, except that this
				clause shall not exonerate a tenant from any liability otherwise existing under
				applicable law for damages to the premises caused by such tenant.</text>
						</clause><clause id="HD975296728CD497DB816BF659A959794"><enum>(x)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>This
				subparagraph shall apply to any dwelling unit for which a housing assistance
				payments contract is entered into or renewed after the date of the
				effectiveness of the regulations implementing this
				subparagraph.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB19D2C8A3FD645098A7AB42E1AF07ABA" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Rent reform and income
			 reviews</header>
			<subsection id="H22D8C4B43CC64BA1AA07548CD9ACE576"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Rent for public
			 housing and section 8 programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3 of the United States Housing Act
			 of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437a) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H651C3C3F6926433D8087E315B0BDBFD2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (a)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H6593E694F0594AAC9C1CC97385848A72"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)
			 by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Low-income
			 occupancy requirement and rental payments</header-in-text>.—</quote> after
			 <quote>(1)</quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6250F91E13A440F4BFBBE12F0E462ECE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph
			 (1)—</text>
						<clause id="H35748F9FC5984A26928DDCBEFE4061F2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by
			 striking <quote>paragraph (2)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraphs (2) and
			 (3)</quote>; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H83B3FCFEC1AD42259830CBEA899526BD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by
			 striking <quote>paragraph (3)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraph
			 (4)</quote>;</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF8FEB30826CD4DC99D401446A8FAA629"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph
			 (2)(A)(i), by striking <quote>paragraph (3)</quote> and inserting
			 <quote>paragraph (4)</quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF5DD82E492284EBD8DECCB8F24562892"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by redesignating
			 paragraphs (3), (4), and (5) as paragraphs (4), (5), and (6),
			 respectively;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19DD8349125B4E37AF26DCAC2267F7B2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by inserting after
			 paragraph (2) the following new paragraph:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6DE7080A8A7A45FBABA10E993F7CA943" style="OLC">
							<paragraph id="H67A850EDEFD64C0E8977CF9B3AC63EFF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>PHA authority to
				establish alternative rents</header>
								<subparagraph id="H5EE0A8CEFEC54D019A8BB2F6151E9B7F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Rent flexibility
				for public housing</header><text>Subject to the requirements under subparagraph
				(B), a public housing agency may establish for public housing—</text>
									<clause id="H522E50B3E7314014A0D1CC714C58B053"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a
				tenant rent structure in which—</text>
										<subclause id="H4E2E173EECBF4AC395D299BE63FDEFD6"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the public housing agency establishes,
				based on the rental value of the unit, as determined by the public housing
				agency, a ceiling rent for each dwelling unit that it owns and operates;
				and</text>
										</subclause><subclause id="HB5FCBA1AA1804240BA1C5759FF8EB6E5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>such ceiling rent
				is adjusted periodically on the basis of an inflation index or a recalculation
				of the rental value of the unit (which may be recalculated by unit or by
				building);</text>
										</subclause></clause><clause id="HEF1C38FF4EB54DAAA4EA82B2AEEA0792"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an income-tiered
				tenant rent structure in which the amount of rent a family shall pay is set and
				distributed on the basis of broad tiers of income and such tiers and rents are
				adjusted on the basis of an annual cost index except that families shall not be
				offered a rent lower than the rent corresponding to their income tier;
				or</text>
									</clause><clause id="H545E30DEF277491C9F9D7D06F6DE35FB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a tenant rent
				structure in which the amount of rent a family shall pay is based on a
				percentage of family income, except that lower percentages may apply only with
				respect to earned income; such a rent structure may provide for an amount of
				rent based on a calculation of earned income that provides for disregard of a
				higher percentage or higher dollar amount, or both, than provided for in
				paragraph (8)(B).</text>
									</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB091F32A251146EBA660C0E159325343"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Notwithstanding
				the authority provided under subparagraph (A), the amount paid for rent
				(including the amount allowed for tenant-paid utilities) by any family for a
				dwelling unit in public housing may not exceed the amount determined under
				subsection (a)(1) of this section. The Secretary shall issue regulations and
				establish procedures for public housing agency calculations and documentation
				as are necessary to ensure compliance with this subparagraph.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4EEA7A8C128A4F8380D3E68C4E40ADF6"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Elderly families
				and disabled families</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this
				Act, this paragraph shall not apply to elderly families and disabled
				families.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9EC71D586437452D8B1C81413A337196"><enum>(F)</enum><text>by adding at the
			 end the following new paragraphs:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H643E932C95A44703AA0A05C773F19F52" style="OLC">
							<paragraph id="H913B327726A04B03A99FA4266F44E8A8"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Reviews of
				family income</header>
								<subparagraph id="H8B70807F6B1A426C9D61A1816907A28C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Frequency</header><text>Reviews
				of family income for purposes of this section shall be made—</text>
									<clause id="HA8B2E05BD8294D46A68ABC42F9193153"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in
				the case of all families, upon the initial provision of housing assistance for
				the family;</text>
									</clause><clause id="H932F1F84B90A49939098EB19204B6A7B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">annually thereafter, except as provided in
				subparagraph (B)(i);</text>
									</clause><clause id="HCA16989DD73A443DAEAEB034999928C6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>upon the request
				of the family, at any time the income or deductions (under subsection (b)(5))
				of the family change by an amount that is estimated to result in a decrease of
				$1,200 (or such lower amount as the public housing agency or owner may, at the
				option of the agency or owner, establish) or more in annual adjusted income;
				and</text>
									</clause><clause id="H0A681705C29B4FEDA4C2527507248298"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at any time the income or deductions (under
				subsection (b)(5)) of the family change by an amount that is estimated to
				result in an increase of $1,200 or more in annual adjusted income, except that
				any increase in the earned income of a family shall not be considered for
				purposes of this clause (except that earned income may be considered if the
				increase corresponds to previous decreases under clause (iii)), except that a
				public housing agency or owner may elect not to conduct such review in the last
				three months of a certification period.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H11C9823B6E0F4A498151D4A959F17418"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Fixed-income
				families</header>
									<clause id="HCAD8D4D84B5C469CB8434EB3160F047B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Self
				certification and 3-year review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any family described in
				clause (ii), after the initial review of the family’s income pursuant to
				subparagraph (A)(i), the public housing agency or owner shall not be required
				to conduct a review of the family’s income pursuant to subparagraph (A)(ii) for
				any year for which such family certifies, in accordance with such requirements
				as the Secretary shall establish, that the income of the family meets the
				requirements of clause (ii) of this subparagraph and that the sources of such
				income have not changed since the previous year, except that the public housing
				agency or owner shall conduct a review of each such family’s income not less
				than once every 3 years.</text>
									</clause><clause id="H19E9A2813E43425EA999DCF384BF65F2"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Eligible
				families</header><text>A family described in this clause is a family who has an
				income, as of the most recent review pursuant to subparagraph (A) or clause (i)
				of this subparagraph, of which 90 percent or more consists of fixed income, as
				such term is defined in clause (iii).</text>
									</clause><clause id="HF5408B4CB6E54560A3E69748C958A709"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Fixed
				income</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <term>fixed
				income</term> includes income from—</text>
										<subclause id="HD8896A42418F43A99BEF6E917F99D359"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the supplemental
				security income program under title XVI of the Social Security Act, including
				supplementary payments pursuant to an agreement for Federal administration
				under section 1616(a) of the Social Security Act and payments pursuant to an
				agreement entered into under section 212(b) of Public Law 93–66;</text>
										</subclause><subclause id="H7C2EF8D9790E4C9CAB6CDE405E1CA2A3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Social Security
				payments;</text>
										</subclause><subclause id="H33EC2D8203184D4C969A09CBBDE26254"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Federal, State,
				local and private pension plans; and</text>
										</subclause><subclause id="H3304FEE117D84A0A8805F04FA912A18F"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>other periodic
				payments received from annuities, insurance policies, retirement funds,
				disability or death benefits, and other similar types of periodic receipts that
				are of substantially the same amounts from year to year.</text>
										</subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC2F2B8339ED4FCEBB14F724333DA157"><enum>(C)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Reviews of family
				income for purposes of this section shall be subject to the provisions of
				section 904 of the Stewart B. McKinney Homeless Assistance Amendments Act of
				1988.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFF3B5777AD3452AA8C3AD1C6603BF04"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Calculation of
				income</header>
								<subparagraph id="H67ABDD192FBD4BD8BEDBB54491A93BD9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Use of current
				year income</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining
				family income for initial occupancy or provision of housing assistance pursuant
				to clause (i) of paragraph (7)(A) or pursuant to reviews pursuant to clause
				(iii) or (iv) of such paragraph, a public housing agency or owner shall use the
				income of the family as estimated by the agency or owner for the upcoming
				year.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74953E28D67443DABAB18D2D5852DA23"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Use of prior
				year income</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining
				family income for annual reviews pursuant to paragraph (7)(A)(ii), a public
				housing agency or owner shall, except as otherwise provided in this paragraph,
				use the income of the family as determined by the agency or owner for the
				preceding year, taking into consideration any redetermination of income during
				such prior year pursuant to clause (iii) or (iv) of paragraph (7)(A).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1959EBCAC654D1D8DF3C76676AB8EBE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Inflationary
				adjustment for fixed income families</header>
									<clause id="HA650DC6AAEE74519A890644A3E1955AF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In any year in which
				a public housing agency or owner does not conduct a review of income for any
				family described in clause (ii) of paragraph (7)(B) pursuant to the authority
				under clause (i) of such paragraph to waive such a review, such family’s prior
				year’s income determination shall, subject to clauses (ii) and (iii), be
				adjusted by applying an inflationary factor as the Secretary shall, by
				regulation, establish.</text>
									</clause><clause id="H5140473617DF42B4944AE63A4EDDAB9C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exemption from
				adjustment</header><text>A public housing agency or owner may exempt from an
				adjustment pursuant to clause (i) any income source for which income does not
				increase from year to year.</text>
									</clause><clause id="HD6E5AA3B073F41A4AD0B4EADE29DDE1D"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Applicability
				of inflationary factor</header><text>The inflationary factor adjustment
				referred to in clause (i) shall not be made with respect to the first year
				after the year in which housing is occupied or housing assistance is initially
				provided for a family.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H49BE35F54C584EC38CC9D7552C9A0676"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Other
				income</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining the
				income for any family based on the prior year’s income, with respect to prior
				year calculations of income not subject to subparagraph (B), a public housing
				agency or owner may make other adjustments as it considers appropriate to
				reflect current income.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H62DF3404A11846C3A50AE5B6387DB1D5"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Safe
				harbor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A public housing
				agency or owner may, to the extent such information is available to the public
				housing agency or owner, determine the family’s income prior to the application
				of any deductions based on timely income determinations made for purposes of
				other means-tested Federal public assistance programs (including the program
				for block grants to States for temporary assistance for needy families under
				part A of title IV of the Social Security Act, a program for Medicaid
				assistance under a State plan approved under title XIX of the Social Security
				Act, and the food stamp program as defined in section 3(h) of the Food Stamp
				Act of 1977). The Secretary shall, in consultation with other appropriate
				Federal agencies, develop procedures to enable public housing agencies and
				owners to have access to such income determinations made by other means-tested
				Federal programs that the Secretary determines to have comparable reliability.
				Exchanges of such information shall be subject to the same limitations and
				tenant protections provided under section 904 of the Stewart B. McKinney
				Homeless Assistance Act Amendments of 1988 (42 U.S.C. 3544) with respect to
				information obtained under the requirements of section 303(i) of the Social
				Security Act (42 U.S.C. 503(i)).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD47193E4250B4A51B9BEB70532308F5E"><enum>(F)</enum><header>PHA and owner
				compliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A public housing
				agency or owner may not be considered to fail to comply with this paragraph or
				paragraph (7) due solely to any de minimus errors made by the agency or owner
				in calculating family
				incomes.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H095AD1BBB7C3434C88DF4516AC935993"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking
			 subsections (d) and (e); and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HAF772A8615904A5F95BFBF2045444521"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating
			 subsection (f) as subsection (d).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6CA4EBB734AC45EB83A883C0625CA3B8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Income</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3(b) of the United States Housing
			 Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437a(b)) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="HD896797CA9424CDD89CF64F766B70F0C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking
			 paragraph (4) and inserting the following new paragraph:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1CCE7F1D4F8448EF9AEAB6621A366425" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="H1D5F048C270646C8A056E3A389DF3270"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Income</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>income</term> means, with
				respect to a family, income received from all sources by each member of the
				household who is 18 years of age or older or is the head of household or spouse
				of the head of the household, plus unearned income by or on behalf of each
				dependent who is less than 18 years of age, as determined in accordance with
				criteria prescribed by the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of
				Agriculture, subject to the following requirements:</text>
							<subparagraph id="HA257E78EA390446BBCA4B5B187538D18"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Included
				amounts</header><text>Such term includes recurring gifts and receipts, actual
				income from assets, and profit or loss from a business.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE9531A0E16BE40F59AE491574BE62DF5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Excluded
				amounts</header><text>Such term does not include—</text>
								<clause id="HE903F91906804555BFA2E4CFA53F1062"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any imputed return
				on assets;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HBA7658077E3E421F95E742B89125E208"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any amounts that would be eligible for
				exclusion under section 1613(a)(7) of the Social Security Act (42 U.S.C.
				1382b(a)(7)); and</text>
								</clause><clause id="H8B91044F8B864904999EF0743267E4A9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>deferred
				disability benefits from the Department of Veterans Affairs that are received
				in a lump sum amount or in prospective monthly amounts.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H916EAA35EF2243F7B711FE3642A20435"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Earned income of
				students</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such term does not
				include earned income of any dependent earned during any period that such
				dependent is attending school on a full-time basis or any grant-in-aid or
				scholarship amounts related to such attendance used for the cost of tuition or
				books.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H297D31072D174853B31E714A2C9D0AD8"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Educational
				savings accounts</header><text>Income shall be determined without regard to any
				amounts in or from, or any benefits from, any Coverdell education savings
				account under section 530 of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 or any qualified
				tuition program under section 529 of such Code.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB178039E9CC45B3BFEB17D453DF72BB"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Other
				exclusions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such term shall
				not include other exclusions from income as are established by the Secretary or
				any amount required by Federal law to be excluded from consideration as income.
				The Secretary may not require a public housing agency or owner to maintain
				records of any amounts excluded from income pursuant to this
				subparagraph.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HBBE8D3D9C43A4773BE511D31F2A0A88C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking
			 paragraph (5) and inserting the following new paragraph:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H27394983A28D425083986DB354BEDA15" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="HF440CC4350DE4F59BF77A7DA86FFF3A3"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Adjusted
				income</header><text>The term <term>adjusted income</term> means, with respect
				to a family, the amount (as determined by the public housing agency or owner)
				of the income of the members of the family residing in a dwelling unit or the
				persons on a lease, after any deductions from income as follows:</text>
							<subparagraph id="H0E8F8B48029E46F698583EB25BC6190C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Earned income
				disregard</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An amount equal to
				10 percent of the lesser of—</text>
								<clause id="H665878BDEDC046E2AE31E8BA0FF43627"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the family’s
				earned income; or</text>
								</clause><clause id="HE979433B83B5434B9C3668EED670C954"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>$9,000, except
				that such amount shall be adjusted annually by applying to such amount (as it
				may have been previously adjusted) an inflationary factor as the Secretary
				shall, by regulation, establish and except that for purposes of adjusted income
				determinations each year such amount shall be established by rounding the
				amount calculated down to the next lowest multiple of $1,000.</text>
								</clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">The
				deduction under this subparagraph shall not be considered in determining
				adjusted income for the purposes of section 16 (relating to eligibility for
				assisted housing and income mix).</continuation-text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC62EB18AFCCB4CAF8F20E06E5CFA9464"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Elderly and
				disabled families</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$725 in the
				case of any family that is an elderly family or a disabled family.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H226979194F2D49CBB183346488663C70"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Dependents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any family that includes a
				member or members who—</text>
								<clause id="H312B3D1E15594963B4809BFEEEA773EF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are less than 18
				years of age or attending school or vocational training on a full-time basis;
				or</text>
								</clause><clause id="H3E3759ACA1F742599A9147936BF5067E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is a person with disabilities who is 18
				years of age or older and resides in the household,</text>
								</clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">$500
				for each such member.</continuation-text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB555C24DAB1B488DA741550EB77C0AFF"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Child
				care</header><text>The amount, if any, that exceeds 10 percent of annual family
				income that is used to pay for unreimbursed child care expenses, which shall
				include child care for preschool-age children, for before- and after-care for
				children in school, and for other child care necessary to enable a member of
				the family to be employed or further his or her education.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DAC71B19C1246DAABC543B7AEA422B1"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Health and
				medical expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount,
				if any, by which 10 percent of annual family income is exceeded by the sum
				of—</text>
								<clause id="HBB093BC7D526420F92F912A742FDDE72"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in
				the case of any elderly or disabled family, any unreimbursed health and medical
				care expenses; and</text>
								</clause><clause id="HFF5EBC4D8D644557AC579BFB08724E6E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any unreimbursed
				reasonable attendant care and auxiliary apparatus expenses for each handicapped
				member of the family, to the extent necessary to enable any member of such
				family to be employed.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE6C31DA8CE84857AD28CD4FF19B971D"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Permissive
				deductions</header><text>Such additional deductions as a public housing agency
				may, at its discretion, establish, except that the Secretary shall establish
				procedures to ensure that such deductions do not materially increase Federal
				expenditures.</text>
							</subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">The
				Secretary shall annually calculate the amounts of the deductions under
				subparagraphs (B) and (C), as such amounts may have been previously calculated,
				by applying an inflationary factor as the Secretary shall, by regulation,
				establish, except that the actual deduction determined for each year shall be
				established by rounding such amount to the next lowest multiple of
				$25.</continuation-text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCD6546CD6F0547A6B32765345CB6E843"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Housing choice
			 voucher program</header><text>Paragraph (5) of section 8(o) of the United
			 States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(5)) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H189A6D50D65147AB95E46A9EAFC53630"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the paragraph
			 heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Annual review</header-in-text></quote> and inserting
			 <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Reviews</header-in-text></quote>;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H1BBDE734C0C04E71846D4DF3CAA7E0B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph
			 (A)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H1F4AFAC6E03946928B963A7D5971EA5E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>the provisions of</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraphs (7) and (8) of
			 section 3(a) and to</quote>; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB993D225F50A438BB320EBAF09E040F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>and shall be conducted upon the initial provision of housing assistance
			 for the family and thereafter not less than annually</quote>; and</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8FC385CA725742A5977B7FC128DC517C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subparagraph
			 (B), by striking the second sentence.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H43306B7A09BC473F930DA391D01D06F9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Enhanced voucher
			 program</header><text>Section 8(t)(1)(D) of the United States Housing Act of
			 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(t)(1)(D)) is amended by striking <quote>income</quote>
			 each place such term appears and inserting <quote>annual adjusted
			 income</quote>.</text>
			</subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6A349B82AA7542DFB4A3C1966ACD9EBB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Project-based
			 housing</header><text>Paragraph (3) of section 8(c) of the United States
			 Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(c)(3)) is amended by striking the last
			 sentence.</text>
			</subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3DB29E5DD50C48E7B01AFCDE25155ADC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Impact on public
			 housing revenues</header>
				<paragraph id="HE98E283ECCCB4845B9EB9C60E897D7A9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Adjustments to
			 operating formula</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the
			 Secretary of Housing and Urban Development determines that the application of
			 the amendments made by this section results in a material and disproportionate
			 reduction in the rental income of certain public housing agencies during the
			 first year in which the amendments made by this section are implemented, the
			 Secretary may make appropriate adjustments in the formula income for such year
			 of those agencies experiencing such a reduction.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HEE4DF728A0D0424C8F6DB0C1433B20F2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>HUD reports on
			 revenue and cost impact</header><text>In each of the first two years after the
			 first year in which the amendments made by this section are implemented, the
			 Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall submit a report to Congress
			 identifying and calculating the impact of changes made by the amendments made
			 by this section and sections 4 and 5 of this Act on the revenues and costs of
			 operating public housing units, the voucher program for rental assistance under
			 section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937, and the program under such
			 section 8 for project-based rental assistance. If such report identifies a
			 material reduction in the net income of public housing agencies nationwide or a
			 material increase in the costs of funding the voucher program or the
			 project-based assistance program, the Secretary may include in such report
			 recommendations for legislative changes to reduce or eliminate such a
			 reduction.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H00290C3671CC46FEA738F3B661034500"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Effective
			 date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect during
			 the first calendar year after regulations or notice has been adopted to
			 implement such amendments, except that the Secretary may delay such effective
			 date by one year upon a determination that such delay is necessary for public
			 housing agencies and owners to make the necessary changes to comply with such
			 amendments.</text>
			</subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1067D041ADFE4A56B48566D33C1D866E" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Eligibility for
			 assistance based on assets and income</header>
			<subsection id="HB567271E6114410DB8A2424FBC0C9501"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Assets</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 16 of the United States Housing Act
			 of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437n) is amended by inserting after subsection (d) the
			 following new subsection:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3D2BB6DDBEC542978ECA79A76667516F" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H7A968C953C8544F0A2FE3CD9AD760E53"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Eligibility for
				assistance based on assets</header>
						<paragraph id="HB6755B39E747492BBAF8C291A5BAD43B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Limitation on
				assets</header><text>Subject to paragraph (3) and notwithstanding any other
				provision of this Act, a dwelling unit assisted under this Act may not be
				rented and assistance under this Act may not be provided, either initially or
				at each recertification of family income, to any family—</text>
							<subparagraph id="H773221CC8CB94ECC9FF297178B40E34C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whose net family assets exceed $100,000, as
				such amount is adjusted annually by applying an inflationary factor as the
				Secretary considers appropriate; or</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H38072DE4F4714C82B8D1522E22EF2740"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who has a present
				ownership interest in, a legal right to reside in, and the effective legal
				authority to sell, real property that is suitable for occupancy as a residence,
				except that the prohibition under this subparagraph shall not apply to—</text>
								<clause id="H6BF4A2BBDCC9467B94A17CD0BA325E22"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any property for
				which the family is receiving assistance under this Act;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H5DDE6806423B47A291E7833DF5352435"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any person that
				is a victim of domestic violence; or</text>
								</clause><clause id="H586B58D64CC348D8AA42341D360943D4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any family that
				is making a good faith effort to sell such property.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE038166A55CE42B8A3DC44703713ABF8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Net family
				assets</header>
							<subparagraph id="H4C0218C24FB243A887B6906B674062AA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this
				subsection, the term <term>net family assets</term> means, for all members of
				the household, the net cash value of all assets after deducting reasonable
				costs that would be incurred in disposing of real property, savings, stocks,
				bonds, and other forms of capital investment. Such term does not include
				interests in Indian trust land, equity accounts in homeownership programs of
				the Department of Housing and Urban Development, or Family Self Sufficiency
				accounts.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD224D4BDC41E44A38C9CA91CE0B48A55"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>Such
				term does not include—</text>
								<clause id="H3D90FACB98F64524A3318D8A383E419F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the value of
				personal property, except for items of personal property of significant value,
				as the Secretary may establish or the public housing agency may
				determine;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H7634286F9F404A4DA251B9F124C3E133"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the value of any
				retirement account;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H65B8E8890341429E9D1250E118C7FDFC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>real property
				for which the family does not have the effective legal authority necessary to
				sell such property;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HC570FBECE8CF49CE8FFBC1B793B93303"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any amounts
				recovered in any civil action or settlement based on a claim of malpractice,
				negligence, or other breach of duty owed to a member of the family and arising
				out of law, that resulted in a member of the family being disabled;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HFEE08E3F6FB042468A3E350D5F9CDB9F"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the value of any Coverdell education
				savings account under section 530 of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 or any
				qualified tuition program under section 529 of such Code; and</text>
								</clause><clause id="HF93E1170B0A84B278136440106666352"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>such other
				exclusions as the Secretary may establish.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H159D41FF1AA8420D875B9D15129DCF65"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Trust
				funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In cases in which a
				trust fund has been established and the trust is not revocable by, or under the
				control of, any member of the family or household, the value of the trust fund
				shall not be considered an asset of a family if the fund continues to be held
				in trust. Any income distributed from the trust fund shall be considered income
				for purposes of section 3(b) and any calculations of annual family income,
				except in the case of medical expenses for a minor.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H292CA3FFE6E544BB8DC40D800F13D11D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Self-certification</header>
							<subparagraph id="H100BC1CAFB2D49198EFA35F5CCC44F41"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Net family
				assets</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A public housing
				agency or owner may determine the net assets of a family, for purposes of this
				section, based on a certification by the family—</text>
								<clause id="HEE454A5BADE0427098D74CC05C1FC5BA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that the net
				assets of such family do not exceed $50,000; or</text>
								</clause><clause id="H3D262E0F937E4B8C9AA4A37B1F0AC26F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>of the amounts
				reported by the family at the time the agency or owner reviews the family’s
				income.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3DFC098F11CB4B7986C9672CFE73189E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No current real
				property ownership</header><text>A public housing agency or owner may determine
				compliance with paragraph (1)(B) based on a certification by the family that
				such family does not have any current ownership interest in any real property
				at the time the agency or owner reviews the family’s income.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1B0A78050BE4744B1A34CDA9B66F0C3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Standardized
				forms</header><text>The Secretary may develop standardized forms for the
				certifications referred to in subparagraphs (A) and (B).</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9F9F4E296E04BFFA81535E8E77D94DA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Compliance for
				public housing dwelling units</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When recertifying family income with
				respect to families residing in public housing dwelling units, a public housing
				agency may, in the discretion of the agency and only pursuant to a policy that
				is set forth in the public housing agency plan under section 5A for the agency,
				choose not to enforce the limitation under paragraph (1).</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="HCCAA946E9C2D4E818E7D9782C842EC7F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Elderly and
				disabled families</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When
				recertifying the income of an elderly or disabled family residing in a dwelling
				unit assisted under this Act, a public housing agency or owner may choose not
				to enforce the limitation under paragraph (1) or may establish exceptions to
				such limitation based on eligibility criteria, but only pursuant to a policy
				that is set forth in the public housing agency plan under section 5A for the
				agency or under a policy adopted by the owner. Eligibility criteria for
				establishing exceptions may provide for separate treatment for elderly and
				disabled families and may be based on different factors, such as age, income,
				the ability of the family to find suitable alternative housing, and whether
				supportive services are being provided.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H4A06F5272E3645F6A293C69B6500C49E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Authority to
				delay evictions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case
				of a family residing in a dwelling unit assisted under this Act who does not
				comply with the limitation under paragraph (1), the public housing agency or
				project owner may delay eviction or termination of the family based on such
				noncompliance for a period of not more than 6
				months.</text>
						</paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HF216E391487544CB95D6B2F55BE0D284"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Income</header><text>The
			 United States Housing Act of 1937 is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H4C347C22E23B4055AA41D406B33821E7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 3(a)(1)
			 (42 U.S.C. 1437a(a)(1)), by striking the first sentence and inserting the
			 following: <quote>Dwelling units assisted under this Act may be rented, and
			 assistance under this Act may be provided, whether initially or at time of
			 recertification, only to families who are low-income families at the time such
			 initial or continued assistance, respectively, is provided, except that
			 families residing in dwelling units as of the date of the enactment of the
			 Section 8 Voucher Reform Act of 2009 that, under agreements in effect on such
			 date of enactment, may have incomes up to 95 percent of local area median
			 income shall continue to be eligible for assistance at recertification as long
			 as they continue to comply with such income restrictions. When recertifying
			 family income with respect to families residing in public housing dwelling
			 units, a public housing agency may, in the discretion of the agency and only
			 pursuant to a policy that is set forth in the public housing agency plan under
			 section 5A for the agency, choose not to enforce the prohibition under the
			 preceding sentence. When recertifying family income with respect to families
			 residing in dwelling units for which project-based assistance is provided, a
			 project owner may, in the owner’s discretion and only pursuant to a policy
			 adopted by such owner, choose not to enforce such prohibition. In the case of a
			 family residing in a dwelling unit assisted under this Act who does not meet
			 the requirements under the first sentence of this paragraph or the requirements
			 under section 8(o)(4), the public housing agency or project owner may delay
			 eviction or termination of the family based on such noncompliance for a period
			 of not more than 6 months.</quote>;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HD68E7E4D07F64FBDAA6E1B94C03C4849"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 8(o)(4)
			 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(4)), by striking the matter preceding subparagraph (A) and
			 inserting the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H60167018CA1C4F2DA2D92357BC5E3B96" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="HBEA06006CD7748C5A13A03212E64374F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible
				families</header><text>Assistance under this subsection may be provided,
				whether initially or at each recertification, only pursuant to subsection (t)
				to a family eligible for assistance under such subsection or to a family who at
				the time of such initial or continued assistance, respectively, is a low-income
				family that is—</text>
						</paragraph><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H95FFEFD87B7743A591906B9E3D44678A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 8(c)(4) (42 U.S.C. 1437f(c)(4)),
			 by striking <quote>at the time it initially occupied such dwelling unit</quote>
			 and inserting <quote>according to the restrictions under section
			 3(a)(1)</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD0298447E029444FA7C823420DF83A4E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Targeting
			 assistance to low-income working families</header>
			<subsection id="HDD298FDC7E2E4B639F69F4EA7DCCC19C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Vouchers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 16(b)(1) of the United States
			 Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437n(b)(1)) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H86EF5189D20B4C70A973B2D23E7EBD7A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting after
			 <quote>do not exceed</quote> the following: <quote>the higher of (A) the
			 poverty line (as such term is defined in section 673 of the Omnibus Budget
			 Reconciliation Act of 1981 (42 U.S.C. 9902), including any revision required by
			 such section) applicable to a family of the size involved, or (B)</quote>;
			 and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H63EE1A66648B4036B165C84631BCA8E0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting
			 before the period at the end the following: <quote>; and except that clause (A)
			 of this sentence shall not apply in the case of public housing agencies located
			 in Puerto Rico or any other territory or possession of the United
			 States</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0A435B1ED6B645968D321D72997AA958"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public
			 housing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 16(a)(2)(A)
			 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437n(a)(2)(A)) is
			 amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H9235044519B543B586EB9D322A4C3668"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting after
			 <quote>do not exceed</quote> the following: <quote>the higher of (i) the
			 poverty line (as such term is defined in section 673 of the Omnibus Budget
			 Reconciliation Act of 1981 (42 U.S.C. 9902), including any revision required by
			 such section) applicable to a family of the size involved, or (ii)</quote>;
			 and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H33758E16D6D5485199A365A74E5C33B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting
			 before the period at the end the following: <quote>; and except that clause (i)
			 of this sentence shall not apply in the case of projects located in Puerto Rico
			 or any other territory or possession of the United States</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H218C6901018B4DDEAC34A3F20D963B75"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Project-based
			 section 8 assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section
			 16(c)(3) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437n(c)(3)) is
			 amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="HA916287155904172BBC728F82C66F428"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting after
			 <quote>do not exceed</quote> the following: <quote>the higher of (A) the
			 poverty line (as such term is defined in section 673 of the Omnibus Budget
			 Reconciliation Act of 1981 (42 U.S.C. 9902), including any revision required by
			 such section) applicable to a family of the size involved, or (B)</quote>;
			 and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HF55F68C7566B4F0F9085FAC79A0A6D90"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting
			 before the period at the end the following: <quote>; and except that clause (A)
			 of this sentence shall not apply in the case of projects located in Puerto Rico
			 or any other territory or possession of the United States</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3364B6DCABD14F23AA53E57E25FDED99" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Voucher renewal
			 funding</header>
			<subsection id="HCD311144054647F7B1AB7E071FEDF32D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42
			 U.S.C. 1437f) is amended by striking subsection (dd) and inserting the
			 following new subsection:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFD0C22B764C941C4A776907159E13DCA" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H3B3A5E0C079F4C6DB640B2BDBC192AFB"><enum>(dd)</enum><header>Tenant-based
				vouchers</header>
						<paragraph id="H88306F6CC8F1453CA111DB0983040338"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization of
				appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are
				authorized to be appropriated, for each of fiscal years 2010 through 2014, such
				sums as may be necessary for tenant-based assistance under subsection (o) for
				the following purposes:</text>
							<subparagraph id="H294826D839644819B71F318DCBB26B61"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To renew all
				expiring annual contributions contracts for tenant-based rental
				assistance.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H464DE72311804A0589EE73386CF85ED5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>To provide
				tenant-based rental assistance for—</text>
								<clause id="HBBE9B58724634CBB9B88129C89035EF7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>conversion of
				section 23 projects to assistance under this section;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HC7950D8029CC4496A9E690817A5FFD82"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the family
				unification program under subsection (x) of this section;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HB76AA9B55B8A4249A41B885FBFB5465F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>relocation of
				witnesses in connection with efforts to combat crime in public and assisted
				housing pursuant to a request from a law enforcement or prosecution
				agency;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HDAF0331D735E49D1B2E06AE7AF5DDD69"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>enhanced vouchers
				authorized under subsection (t) of this section;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HB232BEFCF7684D8AB4CEAB7F1BBD2CDA"><enum>(v)</enum><text>relocation or
				replacement in connection with the HOPE VI program under section 24;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H9CCB3ED2E5C6466889508C9B83A11B3E"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>demolition or
				disposition of public housing units pursuant to section 18 of the United States
				Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437p);</text>
								</clause><clause id="H131625ECFC4C43468C1F4308F13C813F"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>mandatory
				conversions of public housing to vouchers, pursuant to section 33 of the United
				States Housing Act of 1937, respectively (42 U.S.C. 1437z–5);</text>
								</clause><clause id="H05ABF47E606D4F998797D83F1CC54F83"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">voluntary conversions of public housing to
				vouchers, pursuant to section 22 of the United States Housing Act of 1937,
				respectively (42 U.S.C. 1437t);</text>
								</clause><clause id="HFD619A89CE73489B8E02730C4F3D92DF"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>vouchers
				necessary to comply with a consent decree or court order;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HE7B07CA8EA444CB2B36C7C3D249CC2FE"><enum>(x)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">tenant protection vouchers in connection
				with dwelling units that cease to receive project-based assistance under
				subsection (b), (c), (d), (e), or (v) of this section;</text>
								</clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H882250275276466A80BE9CBDC496DF88"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>relocation and
				replacement vouchers in connection with public housing units that are
				demolished or disposed of pursuant to eminent domain, pursuant to a
				homeownership program, or in connection with a mixed finance development method
				under section 35 or otherwise;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HF0B37DEA3EDC4109B481E85C3FD670F2"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>vouchers used
				for the preservation of public housing units not included in the operating
				formula under section 9(e)(2) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42
				U.S.C. 1437g(e)(2));</text>
								</clause><clause id="HA30CE48455D24DA195EF3571DC5B8AB8"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>emergency
				voucher assistance for the protection of victims of domestic violence, dating
				violence, sexual assault, or stalking;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H43160B3ACC394EB39F1D8900034EE298"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>tenant
				protection vouchers in connection with the foreclosure or disposition of
				multifamily housing subject to a mortgage insured and subsidized under the
				National Housing Act; and</text>
								</clause><clause id="H193630796F1446E9A8FF83983C1A670E"><enum>(xv)</enum><text>tenant protection
				assistance, including replacement and relocation assistance.</text>
								</clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">Subject
				only to the availability of sufficient amounts provided in appropriation Acts,
				the Secretary shall provide tenant-based rental assistance in connection with
				all dwelling units that cease to be available as assisted housing as a result
				of clauses (i), (iv), (v), (vi), (vii), (x), (xi), and (xiv).</continuation-text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H82B66FF6F87E45A7BABD6100EE641EB3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Allocation of
				renewal funding among public housing agencies</header>
							<subparagraph id="H29EFBFB5F9BC46F795A1B9FFFD438352"><enum>(A)</enum><text>From amounts
				appropriated for each year pursuant to paragraph (1)(A), the Secretary shall
				provide renewal funding for each public housing agency—</text>
								<clause id="H618D77E296384C0F967448ED8884C01C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">based on leasing and cost data from the
				preceding calendar year, as adjusted by an annual adjustment factor to be
				established by the Secretary, which shall be established using the smallest
				geographical areas for which data on changes in rental costs are annually
				available;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H4ECF32E59D60404EAF26F9E68E23D4AE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by making any adjustments necessary to
				provide for the first-time renewal of vouchers funded under paragraph (1)(B)
				and of any incremental vouchers funded in previous years;</text>
								</clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H32ED9E1858C74DBEBA7984AC798F7AB1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by making any adjustments necessary for
				full year funding of vouchers moved into and out of the jurisdiction of the
				public housing agency in the prior calendar year pursuant to portability
				procedures under subsection (r)(2); and</text>
								</clause><clause id="H8ED56A6AE1DA49BF8BD349B7A67C7A4F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by making such
				other adjustments as the Secretary considers appropriate, including adjustments
				necessary to address changes in voucher utilization rates and voucher costs
				related to natural and other major disasters.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H999F05FBB07F481F929BC13C87721FE3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Leasing and cost
				data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of
				subparagraph (A)(i), leasing and cost data shall be calculated annually by
				using the average for the preceding calendar year. Such leasing and cost data
				shall be adjusted to include vouchers that were set aside under a commitment to
				provide project-based assistance under subsection (o)(13) and to exclude
				amounts funded through advances under paragraph (3). Such leasing and cost data
				shall not include funds not appropriated for tenant-based assistance under
				section 8(o), unless the agency’s funding was prorated in the prior year and
				the agency used other funds to maintain vouchers in use.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFB3A5A7E62D145E9B0967F01EC2E5231"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Overleasing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of determining allocations
				under subsection (A)(i), the leasing rate calculated for the prior calendar
				year may exceed an agency’s authorized voucher level, except that such
				calculation shall not utilize a leasing rate in excess of 103 percent of the
				leasing rate in the year preceding such prior year (after making appropriate
				adjustments for incremental and new enhanced vouchers) which results from the
				use of accumulated amounts, as referred to in the last sentence of paragraph
				(4)(A).</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51A3AC584DCB4BFAA1A0C304F9ED35AD"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Moving to work;
				housing innovation program</header><text>Notwithstanding subparagraphs (A) and
				(B), each public housing agency participating in any year in the moving to work
				program or the housing innovation program under section 37 of this Act shall be
				funded pursuant to its agreement under such program and shall be subject to any
				pro rata adjustment made under subparagraph (F)(i).</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13238E337DE342C0B8AFEA4B15F8F895"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Unreimbursed
				portability costs</header><text>The Secretary may reimburse public housing
				agencies for increased costs related to portability incurred during the prior
				year that were not reimbursed pursuant to paragraph (4)(B)(i).</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H538C960EC0E8470490343CBE9274EF80"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Pro rata
				allocation</header>
								<clause id="H57734DB2B83B4ABF9C360C2460803AE0"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Insufficient
				funds</header><text>To the extent that amounts made available for a fiscal year
				are not sufficient to provide each public housing agency with the full
				allocation for the agency determined pursuant to subparagraphs (A) and (D), the
				Secretary shall reduce such allocation for each agency on a pro rata basis,
				except that renewal funding of enhanced vouchers under section 8(t) shall not
				be subject to such proration.</text>
								</clause><clause id="HE35459BC8AA34AA4923F49F6A7FF27E8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Excess
				funds</header><text>To the extent that amounts made available for a fiscal year
				exceed the amount necessary to provide each housing agency with the full
				allocation for the agency determined pursuant to subparagraphs (A) and (D),
				such excess amounts shall be used for the purposes specified in paragraph
				(4)(B).</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2CA40801E4D14BAEA92227FBCB386DA7"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Prompt funding
				allocation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary
				shall allocate all funds under this subsection for each year before the latter
				of (i) February 15, or (ii) the expiration of the 45-day period beginning upon
				the enactment of the appropriations Act funding such renewals.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5BAEACA50608471EA35F1BB1B42964D2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Advances</header>
							<subparagraph id="HACADB6E12DAC4D18826FE072D4011358"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>During
				the last 3 months of each calendar year, the Secretary shall provide amounts
				out of any appropriations made pursuant to paragraph (1) for the fiscal year
				beginning on October 1 of that calendar year to any public housing agency, at
				the request of the agency, in an amount up to two percent of the allocation for
				the agency for such calendar year, subject to subparagraph (C).</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A6B67AA1269478A8D9A346345C8F9F5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Use</header><text>Amounts
				advanced under subparagraph (A) may be used to pay for additional voucher
				costs, including costs related to temporary overleasing.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3D3DA9B0AF064EFB804580052C88B0E6"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Use of prior
				year amounts</header><text>During the last 3 months of a calendar year, if
				amounts previously provided to a public housing agency for tenant-based
				assistance for such year or for previous years remain unobligated and available
				to the agency—</text>
								<clause id="HC2D1A9B9D6934C079C0C0E325B922B20"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the agency shall
				exhaust such amounts to cover any additional voucher costs under subparagraph
				(B) before amounts advanced under subparagraph (A) may be so used; and</text>
								</clause><clause id="H91D2E69F65024A849EBAEAA0D65E960B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amount that may be advanced under
				subparagraph (A) to the agency shall be reduced by an amount equal to the total
				of such previously provided and unobligated amounts.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07AB9BF960084038B4735A79C6C400F6"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Repayment</header><text>Amounts
				advanced under subparagraph (A) in a calendar year shall be repaid to the
				Secretary in the subsequent calendar year by offsetting the amounts made
				available for such agency for such subsequent calendar year pursuant to
				allocation under paragraph (2) by an amount equal to the amount so advanced to
				the agency.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AEEE45ACE8640E7888179DD744AFA2D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Offset</header>
							<subparagraph id="H18F9C099DA764551ACC77C9A30BD1782"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall
				offset, from amounts provided under the annual contributions contract for a
				public housing agency for a calendar year, all accumulated amounts allocated
				under paragraph (2) and from previous years that are unused by the agency at
				the end of each calendar year, except for an amount not less than 6 percent of
				such amount allocated to the agency pursuant to paragraph (2) for the preceding
				calendar year. Notwithstanding any other provision of law, each public housing
				agency may retain all amounts not offset under this subparagraph, and may use
				such amounts for all authorized purposes.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88B97DB3B3B34C0DA7C85D4FA335AC6A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reallocation</header><text>Not
				later than the latter of April 1 of each calendar year or 75 days after the
				enactment of an appropriations Act providing funding for voucher renewal costs,
				the Secretary shall, from amounts available pursuant to paragraph (2)(E) and
				from any other available amounts appropriated for such purpose—</text>
								<clause id="H87C0CBF2C0B541D1AD3ED2FC4FA743C3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>set aside and
				subsequently make available such amounts as the Secretary considers likely to
				be needed, when combined with funds from a central fund or any other source of
				funds appropriated or made available for such purpose, to reimburse public
				housing agencies for increased costs related to portability and family
				self-sufficiency activities pursuant to section 23(h) during such year;
				and</text>
								</clause><clause id="HE620AEDE9C0B43F98614FF7788ABAC84"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reallocate all remaining amounts among
				public housing agencies, with priority given based on the extent to which an
				agency has utilized the amount allocated under paragraph (2) for the agency to
				serve eligible families and the relative need for additional voucher assistance
				for use only to increase voucher leasing
				rates.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H0A7153AA88E54AD08808E155537268DF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Portability</header><text>The
			 Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall, not later than the expiration
			 of the 6-month period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, issue
			 a proposed rule for comment to modify the regulations governing the
			 responsibilities of public housing agencies in cases in which families assisted
			 with tenant-based assistance under section 8 of the United States Housing Act
			 of 1937 exercise their right to move to a different jurisdiction under the
			 Secretary’s regulations regarding portability procedures (24 C.F.R. 982.355),
			 to eliminate, or minimize to the greatest extent feasible consistent with
			 available funding, billing between agencies and administrative barriers to
			 families’ choices of where to reside, without undermining the ability of public
			 housing agencies to serve their waiting lists. The Secretary shall finalize
			 regulations modifying such portability procedures in accordance with this
			 subsection not later than the expiration of the 12-month period beginning upon
			 the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H325331D0B0394339869D2EF7CB384403"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Vouchers for
			 persons with disabilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The
			 Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall develop and issue, to public
			 housing agencies that have received voucher assistance under section 8(o) for
			 non-elderly disabled families pursuant to appropriations Acts for fiscal year
			 1997 and fiscal years thereafter, guidance to ensure that, to the maximum
			 extent practicable, such vouchers continue to be provided upon turnover to
			 qualified non-elderly disabled families.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H1E55D68635FB41AE8A17BCAE98DCD38A"><enum>7.</enum><header>Administrative
			 fees</header>
			<subsection id="HE6ACA7B939174EDAB65886135D35767C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8(q) of the
			 United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(q)) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H3DAF033A48664CA8B1ADEB5808BE5B02"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph
			 (1)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HEC675E6D48DE48CAAAA9595D4D4C9C78"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking
			 subparagraphs (B) and (C) and inserting the following new subparagraphs:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H829788E92F0749BDA6115A6AD6C6F124" style="OLC">
							<subparagraph id="HA3F69498CAB148F4B23876C1E9C6B649"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Calculation</header><text>The
				fee under this subsection shall—</text>
								<clause id="HF6ABD6C13F6147C3BCB520DB8A1B31A4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be
				payable to each public housing agency for each month for which a dwelling unit
				is covered by an assistance contract;</text>
								</clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCAEB1FA311C845B88D88E799B9D2599E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be based on a per-unit fee, which shall be
				based on the per-unit fee payable to the agency in fiscal year 2003 and updated
				for each subsequent year as specified in subsection (iv), or on such formula
				which the Secretary may, by regulation, establish using a per-unit fee
				structure which shall provide for the payment of the full cost of administering
				vouchers, and which may include performance incentives consistent with
				subsection (o)(21);</text>
								</clause><clause id="H4C65CB22F4674C5385CDB3FC28A3CBB9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>include an
				amount for the cost of issuing a voucher to new participants;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HC0E983AC0D6A449EB700E2D4872BD585"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>be updated each
				year using an index of changes in wage and benefit data or other objectively
				measurable data that reflect the costs of administering the program for such
				assistance, as determined by the Secretary; and</text>
								</clause><clause id="HA23CFEBF0C304CEEAC0E7E9EC5B0BBAF"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include an amount for the cost of family
				self-sufficiency coordinators, as provided in section 23(h)(1).</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53C65E30356240B896BA4844A374F9B7"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>The
				Secretary shall cause to be published in the Federal Register the fee rate for
				each geographic area.</text>
							</subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8F71A80BA3F41DDAF7FB5BBF11B2B54"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking
			 subparagraph (E) and inserting the following new subparagraph;</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4AC508681D9B48B9B567E6C4892CAF44" style="OLC">
							<subparagraph id="H0BC03906E43F47499351150141F03BCF"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Fee for
				agency-owned units</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The
				Secretary shall establish a fee for dwelling units owned by a public housing
				agency that reflects reasonable costs of administration, which shall take into
				consideration the third-party inspection and rent determination expenses
				incurred in compliance with the requirements of subsection
				(o)(11).</text>
							</subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA15229E3675543619426E1F078C75469"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4),
			 by striking <quote>1999</quote> and inserting <quote>2010</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB257351379114D41ADA044F4757CC71F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Administrative
			 fees for family self-sufficiency program costs</header><text>Subsection (h) of
			 section 23 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437u(h)) is
			 amended by striking paragraph (1) and inserting the following new
			 paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H187C49FA97224E3B9AB8C79A97FF6C90" style="OLC">
					<paragraph id="H34FD71C091C945A7A717C575CAEB276D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Section 8
				fees</header>
						<subparagraph id="H28E767AE933A4D1082B0E53DA6900433"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a fee under section 8(q)
				for the costs incurred in administering the self-sufficiency program under this
				section to assist families receiving voucher assistance through section
				8(o).</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA36078F76264391BB5A7820F47B94AC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Eligibility for
				fee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The fee shall provide
				funding for family self-sufficiency coordinators as follows:</text>
							<clause id="HF2D989A7483C44A5BBA8231B5B5E0111"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Base
				fee</header><text>A public housing agency serving 25 or more participants in
				the family self-sufficiency program under this section shall receive a fee
				equal to the costs of employing one full-time family self-sufficiency
				coordinator. An agency serving fewer than 25 such participants shall receive a
				prorated fee.</text>
							</clause><clause id="H64D6594EB23B4C61A3F8A2771D41A0B7"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Additional
				fee</header><text>An agency that meets minimum performance standards shall
				receive an additional fee sufficient to cover the costs of employing a second
				family self-sufficiency coordinator if the agency has 75 or more participating
				families, and a third such coordinator if it has 125 or more participating
				families.</text>
							</clause><clause id="H44D9C87742FF4CFF946FA2B77CAA5898"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Previously
				funded agencies</header><text>An agency that received funding from the
				Department of Housing and Urban Development for more than three such
				coordinators in any of fiscal years 1998 through 2009 shall receive funding for
				the highest number of coordinators funded in a single fiscal year during that
				period, provided they meet applicable size and performance standards.</text>
							</clause><clause id="HC71A6FEFD42442498AE348106900DD7F"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Initial
				year</header><text>For the first year in which a public housing agency
				exercises its right to develop an family self-sufficiency program for its
				residents, it shall be entitled to funding to cover the costs of up to one
				family self-sufficiency coordinator, based on the size specified in its action
				plan for such program.</text>
							</clause><clause id="HC49A660B249345DD8895A49D8B52C31F"><enum>(v)</enum><header>State and
				regional agencies</header><text>For purposes of calculating the family
				self-sufficiency portion of the administrative fee under this subparagraph,
				each administratively distinct part of a State or regional public housing
				agency shall be treated as a separate agency.</text>
							</clause><clause id="H86D39BE5FF274AEFBEE05ED38CB315EC"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Determination
				of number of coordinators</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In
				determining whether a public housing agency meets a specific threshold for
				funding pursuant to this paragraph, the number of participants being served by
				the agency in its family self-sufficiency program shall be considered to be the
				average number of families enrolled in such agency’s program during the course
				of the most recent fiscal year for which the Department of Housing and Urban
				Development has data.</text>
							</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8447519E33847D3A06F3E9588AA4BDB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Proration</header><text>If
				insufficient funds are available in any fiscal year to fund all of the
				coordinators authorized under this section, the first priority shall be given
				to funding one coordinator at each agency with an existing family
				self-sufficiency program. The remaining funds shall be prorated based on the
				number of remaining coordinators to which each agency is entitled under this
				subparagraph.</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F40BC6910184A99BC9A4D2B3BCDADC9"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Recapture</header><text>Any
				fees allocated under this subparagraph by the Secretary in a fiscal year that
				have not been spent by the end of the subsequent fiscal year shall be
				recaptured by the Secretary and shall be available for providing additional
				fees pursuant to subparagraph (B)(ii).</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2A7FA026662544F8827AB0F6D6D9611B"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Performance
				Standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within six months
				after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, the Secretary shall publish
				a proposed rule specifying the performance standards applicable to funding
				under clauses (ii) and (iii) of subparagraph (B). Such standards shall include
				requirements applicable to the leveraging of in-kind services and other
				resources to support the goals of the family self-sufficiency program.</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC15B92D6F53423C830CFB5E80AD3E26"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Data
				collection</header><text>Public housing agencies receiving funding under this
				paragraph shall collect and report to the Secretary, in such manner as the
				Secretary shall require, information on the performance of their family
				self-sufficiency programs.</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25C594DD76824EE182E69565BE4BF6A5"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall conduct a formal and
				scientific evaluation of the effectiveness of well-run family self-sufficiency
				programs, comparing outcomes of families participating in such programs with
				families who are not, using random assignment of participants to the extent
				practicable. Not later than the expiration of the 4-year period beginning upon
				the enactment of this paragraph, the Secretary shall submit an interim
				evaluation report to the Congress. Not later than the expiration of the 8-year
				period beginning upon such enactment, the Secretary shall submit a final
				evaluation report to the Congress. There is authorized to be appropriated
				$10,000,000 to carry out the evaluation under this subparagraph.</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H996DEDB652D84E82B10834E11962E884"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Incentives for
				innovation and high performance</header><text>The Secretary may reserve up to
				10 percent of the amounts made available for administrative fees under this
				paragraph to provide support to or reward family self-sufficiency programs that
				are particularly innovative or highly successful in achieving the goals of the
				program.</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H4BD75D80421140B787A10185FD32ADA0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Repeal</header><text>Section
			 202 of the Departments of Veterans Affairs and Housing and Urban Development,
			 and Independent Agencies Appropriations Act, 1997 (42 U.S.C. 1437f note; Public
			 Law 104–204; 110 Stat. 2893) is hereby repealed.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HC4379E968A8945E5B4EDC5BBE0D4B483"><enum>8.</enum><header>Homeownership</header>
			<subsection id="H3BE8D95D134A4CA1806E4F0CF4E27925"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Section 8
			 homeownership downpayment program</header><text>Section 8(y)(7) of the United
			 States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(y)(7)) is amended by striking
			 subparagraphs (A) and (B) and inserting the following new subparagraphs:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD6D07B875F96469C839A5304014A5174" style="OLC">
					<subparagraph id="HCF7F466570584AC990BC4B85C33AD736"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the
				provisions of this paragraph, in the case of a family on whose behalf rental
				assistance under section 8(o) has been provided for a period of not less than
				12 months prior to the date of receipt of downpayment assistance under this
				paragraph, a public housing agency may, in lieu of providing monthly assistance
				payments under this subsection on behalf of a family eligible for such
				assistance and at the discretion of the agency, provide a downpayment
				assistance grant in accordance with subparagraph (B).</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE38F52C0244044D7AF89C1736A5EDE9F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Grant
				requirements</header><text>A downpayment assistance grant under this
				paragraph—</text>
						<clause id="H5BB37C62F2CC401B846610ACA33CE9BF"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be used by the family only as a
				contribution toward the downpayment and reasonable and customary closing costs
				required in connection with the purchase of a home;</text>
						</clause><clause id="H44DED787439C40DEAEA9F0ABD772D262"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall be in the
				form of a single one-time grant; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H9FE364AFD7D841948E1A3696E1BE979B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>may not exceed
				$10,000.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19DA21E1412A44F4B60ADE46905D3715"><enum>(C)</enum><header>No effect on
				obtaining outside sources for downpayment assistance</header><text>This Act may
				not be construed to prohibit a public housing agency from providing downpayment
				assistance to families from sources other than a grant provided under this Act,
				or as determined by the public housing
				agency.</text>
					</subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HCCF8FA156FD34F2C9B5B69F0242ADDDD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of vouchers
			 for manufactured housing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8(o)(12) of the United States
			 Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(12)) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="HFD2CF87183B247FF827E7CFB7EDED8AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph
			 (A), by striking the period at the end of the first sentence and all that
			 follows through “of” in the second sentence and inserting “and rents”;
			 and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H625A085109A4439AB83A25248D0746F3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph
			 (B)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H71A80B5C78EE47F2A2766952DD3EEC9A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (i), by
			 striking <quote>the rent</quote> and all that follows and inserting the
			 following: “rent shall mean the sum of the monthly payments made by a family
			 assisted under this paragraph to amortize the cost of purchasing the
			 manufactured home, including any required insurance and property taxes, the
			 monthly amount allowed for tenant-paid utilities, and the monthly rent charged
			 for the real property on which the manufactured home is located, including
			 monthly management and maintenance charges.”;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F8188E865994A28A1B4CDA46C010F50"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking clause
			 (ii); and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D802E491A9948AF85576B7020A352BE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in clause
			 (iii)—</text>
						<clause id="H56321EFBAB464C06B4BD5DAE4C0C173B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by
			 inserting after the period at the end the following: “If the amount of the
			 monthly assistance payment for a family exceeds the monthly rent charged for
			 the real property on which the manufactured home is located, including monthly
			 management and maintenance charges, a public housing agency may pay the
			 remainder to the family, lender or utility company, or may choose to make a
			 single payment to the family for the entire monthly assistance amount.”;
			 and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H0131913FD19C4E63A275535A8C53EE34"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by
			 redesignating such clause as clause (ii).</text>
						</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC423EDFA62FC4D30BCCA065DF8C2BE02"><enum>9.</enum><header>PHA reporting of
			 rent payments to credit reporting agencies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3 of the United States Housing Act
			 of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437a), as amended by the preceding provisions of this Act,
			 is further amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA384BB37230A410D8989D048C81492FE" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="HAAE33E6255CD4BE2913A2DC203E734B6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>PHA reporting of
				rent payments to credit reporting agencies</header>
					<paragraph id="H60EA62597D8C4382A1217384CD4AA534"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent that a family receiving
				tenant-based housing choice vouchers under section 8 by a public housing agency
				agrees in writing to reporting under this subsection, the public housing agency
				may submit to consumer reporting agencies described in section 603(p) of the
				Fair Credit Reporting Act (15 U.S.C. 1681a) information regarding the past rent
				payment history of the family with respect to the dwelling unit for which such
				assistance is provided.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H3697CB0C5F2946F685910E34AFEBBE8E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Format</header><text>The
				Secretary, after consultation with consumer reporting agencies referred in
				paragraph (1), shall establish a system and format to be used by public housing
				agencies for reporting of information under such paragraph that provides such
				information in a format and manner that is similar to other credit information
				submitted to such consumer reporting agencies and is usable by such
				agencies.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDCC920FD53B74E57B2AFBD5E74A082FA" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>10.</enum><header>Performance
			 assessments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8(o) of
			 the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)) is amended by adding
			 at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H010320EDB6004183A760F27F35049F30" style="OLC">
				<paragraph id="HE3708201C30D45D2A4C2EE77B7981CB4"><enum>(21)</enum><header>Performance
				assessments</header>
					<subparagraph id="HF4BC87CA11634CD4941829A250F38EC1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The
				Secretary shall, by regulation, establish standards and procedures for
				assessing the performance of public housing agencies in carrying out the
				programs for tenant-based rental assistance under this subsection and for
				homeownership assistance under subsection (y).</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD4D66A5A5454B67A93CF37015748C90"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The
				standards and procedures under this paragraph shall provide for assessment of
				the performance of public housing agencies in the following areas:</text>
						<clause id="HF639C7C5BA3349D884460618DB77AAC3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Extent to which
				dwelling units comply with housing quality standards, including compliance with
				inspection requirements.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H5CFE44B7E0524CF2BDBD7877CB086FA8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Extent of
				utilization of assistance amounts provided to the agency and of authorized
				vouchers, using appropriate adjustments for vouchers set aside to meet
				commitments under paragraph (13).</text>
						</clause><clause id="H506F4777A7A140D196FD7737F3F717ED"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Timeliness and
				accuracy of reporting by the agency to the Secretary.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H87E5EBE5C27C42059A140644BE39A59C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Effectiveness in
				carrying out policies that result in deconcentration of poverty.</text>
						</clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1785408B5B324EFA9E7D1A5AC16C12CC"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Reasonableness of rent burdens, consistent
				with public housing agency responsibilities under section
				8(o)(1)(E)(iii).</text>
						</clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H99C2BAE328884C6891C6DB2C5934928D"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Accurate calculations of rent, utility
				allowances, and subsidy payments.</text>
						</clause><clause id="HA56F87D06CD34082B86D376425A9FF0D"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Effectiveness in
				carrying out family self-sufficiency activities.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H3632E9AA1FB94072BC0F76B5D0E566E5"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Timeliness of
				actions related to landlord participation.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H678FDE9DED9541489B7EAA45E04F11EE"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Compliance with
				targeting requirements under section 16(b).</text>
						</clause><clause id="H6CC705307CBA4AFBB06401C8265BCCCF"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Such other areas
				as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H542A3C1310E948AA9CA61D2D2ED4B871"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Biennial
				assessment</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of
				this paragraph, and at least every 2 years thereafter, the Secretary, using the
				standards and procedures established under this paragraph, shall—</text>
						<clause id="H0BA04D1ED252422898BB55E780B0DD12"><enum>(i)</enum><text>conduct an
				assessment of the performance of each public housing agency carrying out a
				program referred to in subparagraph (A);</text>
						</clause><clause id="H9F51E7793B194FABBD5093808C32B43B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>make such
				assessment available to the public housing agency and to the public via the
				website of the Department of Housing and Urban Development; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="HD568342AA78845A6BDE14E1933C5CD66"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>submit a report
				to Congress regarding the results of each such assessment.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H808664381DD64DBDBE984F9BB1D07768"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>When
				implemented, the performance assessment standards and procedures under this
				paragraph shall supercede the Section 8 Management Assessment Program of the
				Secretary then in
				effect.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H835B51D401804C28B60579255287EC4D" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>11.</enum><header>PHA project-based
			 assistance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8(o)(13) of
			 the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(13)) is
			 amended—</text>
			<paragraph id="H8FB8B11D34BB47E1AC3EACEB30CC8BE1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking
			 subparagraph (B) and inserting the following new subparagraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H12368FD7199D4073B39A526696B7493F" style="OLC">
					<subparagraph id="H7AE20F52350A41EE87BDB4AEDD84F39B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Percentage
				limitation</header>
						<clause id="H023FB73FD8B44CC0870ADD78EF51B683"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to clause
				(ii), not more than 25 percent of the funding available for tenant-based
				assistance under this section that is administered by the agency may be
				attached to structures pursuant to this paragraph.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H3D71EAEB14C54C4996EED222845B539E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>An
				agency may attach up to an additional 5 percent of the funding available for
				tenant-based assistance under this section to structures pursuant to this
				paragraph for dwelling units that house individuals and families that meet the
				definition of homeless under section 103 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless
				Assistance Act (42 U.S.C. 11302), that provide supportive housing to persons
				with disabilities, or that are located in areas where vouchers under this
				subsection are difficult to use, as specified in subparagraph (D)(ii)(II). The
				Secretary may, by regulation, establish additional categories for the exception
				under this clause.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;
				</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA80DE67B821F43D49EFFF8A2A1814467"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking
			 subparagraph (D) and inserting the following new subparagraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBA5B31C21F7F47C69A40A13B3D560B7E" style="OLC">
					<subparagraph id="H8EB1FC6746FD47849696D203110873F3"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Income mixing
				requirement</header>
						<clause id="HB3ADD043114B447892884F40B41B794E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in
				clause (ii), not more than the greater of 25 dwelling units or 25 percent of
				the dwelling units in any project may be assisted under a housing assistance
				payment contract for project-based assistance pursuant to this paragraph. For
				purposes of this subparagraph, the term <term>project</term> means a single
				building, multiple contiguous buildings, or multiple buildings on contiguous
				parcels of land.</text>
						</clause><clause id="HA1AEE5313205424FB7A7AE923C7874BE"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exceptions</header>
							<subclause id="H2195274D569946D7AA4CBA3C54F646BE"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Certain
				housing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The limitation under
				clause (i) shall not apply in the case of assistance under a contract for
				housing consisting of single family properties, or for dwelling units that are
				specifically made available for households comprised of elderly families,
				disabled families, and families receiving comprehensive supportive services for
				special needs populations, such as individuals who were formerly homeless. For
				purposes of the preceding sentence, the term <term>single family
				properties</term> means buildings with no more than four dwelling units.</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H43A9F9BA028A421885275F47B212C756"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Certain
				areas</header>
								<item id="H0A4365999B434666A7A428CFBC33517D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to areas in which fewer than
				75 percent of families issued vouchers become participants in the program, the
				public housing agency has established the payment standard at 110 percent of
				the fair market rent for all census tracts in the area for the previous six
				months, the public housing agency has requested a higher payment standard, and
				the public housing agency grants an automatic extension of 90 days (or longer)
				to families with vouchers who are attempting to find housing, clause (i) shall
				be applied by substituting <quote>40 percent</quote> for <quote>25
				percent</quote>; and</text>
								</item><item commented="no" id="HBBB763507E364617A14070BF2615F7FC"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to census tracts with a
				poverty rate of 20 percent or less, clause (i) shall be applied by substituting
				<quote>50 percent</quote> for <quote>25 percent</quote> and the Secretary may,
				by regulation, establish additional
				conditions.</text>
								</item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HA2A11324204048DDA0A0EE84AE6403E2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subparagraph
			 (J)—</text>
				<subparagraph id="HB5D71AC74E0142B69526DF74F1CE1FC8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking the fifth and sixth sentences
			 and inserting the following: <quote>A public housing agency may establish and
			 utilize procedures for maintaining site-based waiting lists under which
			 applicants may apply directly at, or otherwise designate to the public housing
			 agency, the project or projects in which they seek to reside, except that all
			 applicants on the waiting list of an agency for assistance under this
			 subsection shall be permitted to place their names on such separate list. All
			 such procedures shall comply with title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964, the
			 Fair Housing Act, and other applicable civil rights laws. The owner or manager
			 of a structure assisted under this paragraph shall not admit any family to a
			 dwelling unit assisted under a contract pursuant to this paragraph other than a
			 family referred by the public housing agency from its waiting list, or a family
			 on a site-based waiting list that complies with the requirements of this
			 subparagraph. A public housing agency shall disclose to each applicant all
			 other options in the selection of a project in which to reside that are
			 provided by the public housing agency and are available to the
			 applicant.</quote>; and</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22A52811BD4F45878198A7AFA2992849"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after the third sentence the
			 following new sentence: <quote>Any family who resides in a dwelling unit
			 proposed to be assisted under this paragraph, or in a unit to be replaced by a
			 proposed unit to be assisted under this paragraph shall be given an absolute
			 preference for selection for placement in the proposed unit, if the family is
			 otherwise eligible for assistance under this subsection.</quote>; and</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD8A93729ED054895A42F304530A2CB31"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the
			 end the following new subparagraphs:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9AA67787A58348A5931CB126B8980DF9" style="OLC">
					<subparagraph id="H6FB978C263E04C5D95DC42CA82D3654C"><enum>(N)</enum><header>Structure owned
				by agency</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, as part of
				an initiative to improve, develop, or replace a public housing site, a public
				housing agency may attach assistance to an existing, newly constructed, or
				rehabilitated structure in which the agency has an ownership interest without
				following a competitive process, but only if the agency includes such
				initiative in its public housing agency plan approved under section 5A and the
				units that receive such assistance will not receive assistance under section 9.
				The preceding sentence may not be construed to limit the ability of a public
				housing agency to attach assistance to structures under other applicable
				law.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6BE3F83F8E349A797D00CA49FDE1F12"><enum>(O)</enum><header>Leases and
				tenancy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assistance provided
				under this paragraph shall be subject to the provisions of paragraph (7),
				except that subparagraph (A) of such paragraph shall not apply. Notwithstanding
				any other provision of law, for the term of the contract under this paragraph,
				the owner may terminate tenancy only for serious or repeated violations of the
				terms and conditions of the lease or for violation of applicable law.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4346242FA39A4BB0BF4E3B5C1C232DFC"><enum>(P)</enum><header>Allowable
				transfers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A public housing
				agency may transfer a portion of its vouchers and related budget authority to a
				public housing agency that administers a program under this subsection in
				another jurisdiction located in the same or a contiguous metropolitan area or
				county.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8FFA5234567542E881339CFA6EE91C66"><enum>(Q)</enum><header>Rent
				flexibility</header><text>If a dwelling unit assisted under this paragraph also
				receives funding from either of the funds established under section 1138 or
				1339 of the Federal Housing Enterprises Financial Safety and Soundness Act of
				1992 (12 U.S.C. 4568, 4569), the rent for the unit, if agreed upon by both the
				public housing agency and the owner, may be established at an amount that is
				less than would otherwise be permitted under paragraphs (1)(B) or (10)(A) of
				this
				section.</text>
					</subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H892F10A56091470E9582D69CD909DE00"><enum>12.</enum><header>Rent
			 burdens</header>
			<subsection id="HBA08950B8BFB49D98839A060EB1646FA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reviews</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8(o)(1) of the United States
			 Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(1)) is amended by striking subparagraph
			 (E) and inserting the following new subparagraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H28E03F41C30544AE8EA893F2DD8465E9" style="OLC">
					<subparagraph id="H7A469D8A15854378AF7EC7D2B8E711BD"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Reviews</header>
						<clause id="H30C9F2652F06448DB15DB2F94756CD54"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Rent
				burdens</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall
				monitor rent burdens and submit a report to the Congress annually on the
				percentage of families assisted under this subsection, occupying dwelling units
				of any size, that pay more than 30 percent of their adjusted incomes for rent
				and such percentage that pay more than 40 percent of their adjusted incomes for
				rent. Using information regularly reported by public housing agencies, the
				Secretary shall provide public housing agencies, on an annual basis, a report
				with the information described in the first sentence of this clause, and may
				require a public housing agency to modify a payment standard that results in a
				significant percentage of families assisted under this subsection, occupying
				dwelling units of any size, paying more than 30 percent of their adjusted
				incomes for rent. In implementing the requirements of this clause, the
				Secretary shall separate out calculations and consideration of families whose
				rent contributions are calculated under section 3(a)(3) and clauses (ii) and
				(iii) of paragraph (2)(A) of this subsection.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H4371AE7F6B454B0B975B2BA6672DA89D"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Concentration
				of poverty</header><text>The Secretary shall submit a report to the Congress
				annually on the degree to which families assisted under this subsection in each
				metropolitan area are clustered in lower rent, higher poverty areas, which
				shall include reporting of data by race and ethnicity, and how, and the extent
				to which, greater geographic distribution of such assisted families could be
				achieved, including by increasing payment standards for particular communities
				within such metropolitan areas.</text>
						</clause><clause id="HD2975266DD6E4AFF8E5D5952EA123037"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Public housing
				agency responsibilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each
				public housing agency shall make publicly available the information on rent
				burdens provided by the Secretary pursuant to clause (i), and, for agencies
				located in metropolitan areas, the information on concentration provided by the
				Secretary pursuant to clause (ii). If a public housing agency has a high degree
				of concentration of poverty, as determined under a standard to be developed by
				the Secretary in accordance with clause (ii), or if the percentage of families
				paying more than 40 percent of their adjusted net income exceeds a percentage
				level, to be established by the Secretary, the public housing agency shall
				adjust the payment standard to eliminate excessive rent burdens within a
				reasonable time period or explain its reasons for not making such adjustment.
				The Secretary may not deny the request of a public housing agency to set a
				payment standard up to 120 percent of the fair market rent to eliminate
				excessive rent burdens in accordance with the preceding sentence, except on the
				basis that an agency has not demonstrated that its request meets these
				criteria. If a request of a public housing agency has not been denied or
				approved with 45 days after the request is made, the request shall be
				considered to have been
				approved.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H0C0E24FDB5A84A76A761AD3D2DFC5325"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public housing
			 agency plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 5A(d)(4)
			 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437c–1(d)(4)) is amended
			 by inserting before the period at the end the following: “, including the
			 report with respect to the agency furnished by the Secretary pursuant to
			 section 8(o)(1)(E) concerning rent burdens and, if applicable, geographic
			 concentration of voucher holders, any changes in rent or other policies the
			 public housing agency is making to address excessive rent burdens or
			 concentration, and if the public housing agency is not adjusting its payment
			 standard, its reasons for not doing so”.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H7DC8EE237A0547A2B35CD26CF6F02CE7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rent burdens for
			 persons with disabilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subparagraph (D) of section 8(o)(1) is
			 amended by inserting before the period at the end the following: “, except that
			 a public housing agency may establish a payment standard of not more than 120
			 percent of the fair market rent where necessary as a reasonable accommodation
			 for a person with a disability, without approval of the Secretary. A public
			 housing agency may seek approval of the Secretary to use a payment standard
			 greater than 120 percent of the fair market rent as a reasonable accommodation
			 for a person with a disability”.</text>
			</subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H05BEB1A8C7524EE988207182262C1C4C"><enum>13.</enum><header>Establishment of
			 fair market rent</header>
			<subsection id="HFCCCFD92B1544C15977C349BBE591B9C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Paragraph (1) of section 8(c) of the United States
			 Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(c)(1)) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="HAE127E766BD44EEB85DD79F9B4DCE3A2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting
			 <quote>(A)</quote> after the paragraph designation;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H334C09D173D2464CB7E37CD162403088"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking the
			 seventh, eighth, and ninth sentences; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H4421970ADB6D4DDDA2BA6AD73F74DF61"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the
			 end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6C7E05F1598048F687AC82762A48B18E" style="OLC">
						<subparagraph id="HE995D848C9F84A8EA5FEA5CCDED39649" indent="up2"><enum>(B)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H46A4A859FF304704832670BCA20AB568"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall define market areas for
				purposes of this paragraph in areas sufficiently distinct as is
				necessary—</text>
								<subclause id="H0570F3913A5C47188CE0924CCE8DAE6E" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to establish fair market rentals that
				accurately reflect typical rental costs of units suitable for occupancy by
				persons assisted under this section in communities in metropolitan and
				non-metropolitan areas (including low poverty areas); and</text>
								</subclause><subclause id="H5C6D88E9140444C7BA1A806C362E7A5A" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to avoid concentration of voucher
				holders;</text>
								</subclause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="clause">while taking
				into consideration the factors specified in clause (ii).</continuation-text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF2D31A8107A94293BDBB7F2705DE8CED" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The factors specified in this clause
				are—</text>
								<subclause id="HD6D5354FAA66431686F11C7C0F5C05EC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the efficient administration of the
				program by public housing agencies and the administrative costs of the
				Secretary of establishing additional areas;</text>
								</subclause><subclause id="H447AA28DA1E64AADBD072254D8B7AEC9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the availability of data for a
				sufficient number of dwelling units to establish accurate fair market rentals;
				and</text>
								</subclause><subclause id="H3C753C318070425785ABB2FD194403AA"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the ability of public housing
				agencies to adjust the payment standard to more accurately reflect typical
				rental costs.</text>
								</subclause></clause><clause id="H65C2EC2A0D2A47E1B8A2CBCF5AA32F27" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The Secretary shall establish
				procedures to permit a public housing agency to request the establishment of a
				separate market areas for either all or contiguous parts of the areas under the
				jurisdiction of such agency. The Secretary shall consider and approve any such
				request using the criteria established in clause (i) and the considerations
				under clause (ii).</text>
							</clause><clause id="H1BFE15D1176440D98A215AD4EBBC6263" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The Secretary shall not reduce the
				fair market rental in a market area as a result of a change in the percentile
				of the distribution of market rents used to establish the fair market
				rental.</text>
							</clause><clause id="HCC36654B1C0A4278A371E65FB29E923B" indent="up1"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall phase in large
				increases or decreases in the fair market rentals that result from changes in
				market area boundaries or other methodological changes that do not reflect
				actual year-to-year trends in rents by limiting such increases or decreases to
				not more than 5 percent each
				year.</text>
							</clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1C44E1DA25AD45FB8B2B006EF133446C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Payment
			 standard</header><text>Subparagraph (B) of section 8(o)(1) of the United States
			 Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(1)(B)) is amended by inserting before
			 the period at the end the following: <quote>, except that no public housing
			 agency shall be required as a result of a reduction in the fair market rental
			 to reduce the payment standard applied to a family continuing to reside in a
			 unit for which the family was receiving assistance under this section at the
			 time the fair market rental was reduced</quote>.</text>
			</subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H55EFFB887985415A9F0A06CEAC228142"><enum>14.</enum><header>Screening of
			 applicants</header>
			<subsection id="HAB4FBBD2243D4D0FB6980E1EFC6069AC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subparagraph (B) of
			 section 8(o)(6) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (1437f(o)(6)(B)) is
			 amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="HF52D3812E3BC4EA08E9B72733D25C2EA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>(B) <header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">Selection of
			 tenants</header-in-text>.—Each</quote> and inserting the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4206478862F247D3B1052F8FFFC681E4" style="OLC">
						<subparagraph id="H8713A2C999474B95A793DBA666DFFECE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Selection of
				tenants</header>
							<clause id="HA6AF1816EF484B6F8F4A82CF94954F66"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Function of
				owner</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each</text>
							</clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H2DB6503A84C04D5DB223D30821B8BEAC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the first
			 sentence, by striking <quote>unit)</quote> and inserting
			 <quote>unit</quote>;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H8AA3196655CF419D98007B600F854ABF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>In addition</quote> and inserting the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCEAF00CA573F44C9AF28A9779B8E06FC" style="OLC">
						<clause id="HBAEE5AA60BBD4D0B9211BD67A987540E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Screening</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In
				addition</text>
						</clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H3514D56D9BEF4CF08606E1AFC89F35D2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after
			 <quote>establish.</quote> the following: <quote>A public housing agency’s
			 elective screening shall be limited to criteria that are directly related to an
			 applicant’s ability to fulfill the obligations of an assisted lease and shall
			 consider mitigating circumstances related to such applicant. The requirements
			 of the preceding sentence shall not limit the ability of a public housing
			 agency to deny assistance based on an applicant’s criminal background or any
			 other permissible grounds for denial under subtitle F of title V of the Quality
			 Housing and Work Responsibility Act of 1998 (42 U.S.C. 13661 et seq.; relating
			 to safety and security in public and assisted housing), subject to the
			 procedural requirements of this section. Any applicant or participant
			 determined to be ineligible for admission or continued participation to the
			 program shall be notified of the basis for such determination and provided,
			 within a reasonable time after the determination, an opportunity for an
			 informal hearing on such determination at which mitigating circumstances,
			 including remedial conduct subsequent to the conduct that is the basis of such
			 determination, shall be considered.</quote>; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H6729FCF2339E4F999894E218201088F4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by adding at the
			 end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF62689E0C273446F832F2B2235DACD7C" style="OLC">
						<clause id="HDB975B7F554843A798CAA3BB9B3BE7AA"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Existing
				assisted families</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Families
				being provided enhanced vouchers pursuant to subsection (t), families receiving
				assistance under this Act that are subsequently provided tenant-based
				assistance pursuant to subsection (dd)(1)(B), and families residing in
				multifamily housing subject to a mortgage insured under the National Housing
				Act that are provided tenant-based assistance pursuant to subsection
				(dd)(1)(B)(xiv) of this section shall not be considered new applicants under
				this paragraph and shall not be subject to elective re-screening by a public
				housing
				agency.</text>
						</clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB25982CA799C4354A88EFA2E6BEDF965"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Leases and
			 tenancy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subparagraph (E) of
			 section 8(o)(7) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C.
			 1437f(o)(7)(E)) is amended by inserting <quote>termination or</quote> after
			 <quote>any</quote> the last place such term appears.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H228848A777B942EE8044029D4E5C5341"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Denials of
			 admission</header><text>Section 576 of the Quality Housing and Work
			 Responsibility Act of 1998 (42 U.S.C. 13661) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H246C7F8D0CBB49FEBAD6BFE351D40B81"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (b)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H0D960E2085E04E3EA7D2A860E733492D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking
			 paragraph (2);</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11E5D076006840089EA617C793F953F7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph
			 (1)—</text>
						<clause id="H9836BAEA520B4B88BB9E66185E868186"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in
			 subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>, based on documented evidence that is
			 credible and objective,</quote> after <quote>determines</quote>;</text>
						</clause><clause id="H1236EDA87C5E4873986B9BA4D9DC711C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in
			 subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>that it has reasonable</quote> and all
			 that follows through <quote>by other residents</quote> and inserting <quote>,
			 based on documented evidence that is credible and objective, is a chronic
			 abuser of alcohol, and who is not currently participating in a supervised
			 alcohol rehabilitation program</quote>; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="HF7848367F5F447CBA7BDD1098B37A90A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by
			 redesignating subparagraphs (A) and (B) (as so amended) as paragraphs (1) and
			 (2) and realigning such paragraphs, as so redesignated, so as to be indented 2
			 ems from the left margin; and</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B12730057F04984A002E2583B3C03B1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking the
			 subsection designation and all that follows through
			 <quote>Notwithstanding</quote> in paragraph (1) and inserting the
			 following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6610D8FA596F4DAE80D5C0496C4976C4" style="OLC">
							<subsection id="HADDAF88824C744E69AA6295BEC96F0E2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ineligibility of
				illegal drug users and alcohol abusers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding</text>
							</subsection><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H51F8874E15BA42489EE303C4B4FCC345"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (c)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H67575249B89740FD820C82A89889D48C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the section
			 heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">certain</header-in-text></quote> before <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">criminal</header-in-text></quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E08E11BB9304D0EA28E4E03485FB571"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the matter that
			 precedes paragraph (1)—</text>
						<clause id="H6062C6BCE21D4242AE558433E6D446BF"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>, based on documented
			 evidence that is credible and objective,</quote> after
			 <quote>determines</quote>;</text>
						</clause><clause id="H91445EF5ACCC4A78ADA285A241A36421"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by
			 striking <quote>a reasonable time</quote> and inserting <quote>the 5-year
			 period</quote>; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H2CA50245B27149C291935465FC796FA4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by
			 striking <quote>or other criminal activity</quote>;</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H34371CF70EE34DBC9DB2827A46654AB4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (2),
			 by striking <quote>reasonable</quote> each place such term appears and
			 inserting <quote>5-year</quote>; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBFF7534874494B4EBE02C121B5634A8D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by adding after
			 and below paragraph (2) the following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6DD2CF4BC5F748C299FAEC0CDD73E783" style="OLC">
							<quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="subsection">No denial
				of admission may be made pursuant to this subsection based on a misdemeanor
				conviction or activity which is of a misdemeanor nature unless such denial is
				based on a pattern of
				activity.</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBF27ED3BD77B4B05A84881030B5A6A2F"><enum>15.</enum><header>Enhanced
			 vouchers</header>
			<subsection id="H04792977FFD04F8E8BEF0CFC6B92967F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Qualification;
			 election To remain in unit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8(t)(1) of the United States
			 Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(t)(1)(B)) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H716B9D8A72B741859E56D3ACA9CB22E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the matter
			 preceding subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>and shall not require that the
			 family requalify under the selection standards for a public housing agency in
			 order to be eligible for such assistance</quote> before the comma; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H71E89CDB2F7F4DEBAF0F761119410073"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking
			 subparagraph (B) and inserting the following new subparagraph:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H86407DACEDDA40808D7E10A2F1832967" style="OLC">
						<subparagraph id="HDABAC600177A4A7886C600FA962A457B"><enum>(B)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC0409C2EE1794527A105A0B7A145E06B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the assisted family may
				elect to remain in the same project in which the family was residing on the
				date of the eligibility event for the project regardless of unit and family
				size standards normally used by the administering public housing agency (except
				that tenants may be required to move to units of appropriate size if available
				on the premises), and the owner of the unit shall accept the enhanced voucher
				and terminate the tenancy only for serious or repeated violation of the terms
				and conditions of the lease or for violation of applicable law; and</text>
							</clause><clause id="HDF6163908A8A47BAA9E7D989A9243394" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if, during any period the family
				makes such an election and continues to so reside, the rent for the dwelling
				unit of the family in such project exceeds the applicable payment standard
				established pursuant to subsection (o) for the unit, the amount of rental
				assistance provided on behalf of the family shall be determined using a payment
				standard that is equal to the rent for the dwelling unit (as such rent may be
				increased from time-to-time), subject to paragraph (10)(A) of subsection (o)
				and any other reasonable limit prescribed by the Secretary, except that a limit
				shall not be considered reasonable for purposes of this subparagraph if it
				adversely affects such assisted
				families;</text>
							</clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB8C4169179A340C39B652D1FDEE5156B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Provision to
			 residents of assisted multifamily projects upon termination date</header>
				<paragraph id="H6AB4A87C2112452CAE41871AC6E95AED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon the termination date for each assisted
			 multifamily housing project, to the extent that amounts for assistance under
			 this paragraph are provided in advance in appropriation Acts, the Secretary of
			 Housing and Urban Development shall make enhanced voucher assistance under
			 section 8(t) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(t))
			 available on behalf of each family described in paragraph (2).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H6A47ECA69956446C9859326D49442908"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>A
			 family described in this paragraph is a family who—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H9B72CF9B91C143AE968D7B507DAABA9D"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4DA19C85422A4B028DF3892029CFBEAE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is a low-income family;
			 or</text>
						</clause><clause id="H095B6BC7C7BE49688A91549EA1DDA824" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is a moderate-income family that
			 is—</text>
							<subclause id="H8FAD68595F7C4D589B075942618D02E6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an elderly family (as such term is used
			 in section 3(b) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C.
			 1437a(b));</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H479128010763429694F785AB71FAF1E5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a disabled family (as such term is used
			 in section 3(b) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437a(b));
			 or</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="HFD5383C84AA146CEB1A640DDD8089AC7"><enum>(III)</enum><text>residing in a low-vacancy area (as
			 determined by the Secretary); and</text>
							</subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0FD443B01F0C40B8B2A9A523D3C6AFF5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>on such
			 termination date, is residing in a dwelling unit of the project that—</text>
						<clause id="H169AE813329142ADB740DF765BB06B77"><enum>(i)</enum><text>immediately before
			 such termination date was assisted under the multifamily housing subsidy
			 program for the project; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H01AD9E9875BE46FAB63501B0FF60598B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is
			 not assisted after such termination date under section 8 of such Act.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8C635C2F07C455B993F62A415EFE261"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligibility
			 event</header><text>Section 8(t)(2) of the United States Housing Act of 1937
			 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(t)(2)) is amended by adding after the period at the end the
			 following new sentence: “Such term includes, with respect to an assisted
			 multifamily housing project (as such term is defined in section 15(b) of the
			 <short-title>Section 8 Voucher Reform Act of
			 2009</short-title>), the occurrence of the termination date for the
			 project.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H54FD957668144B47833D1C78C46B5BFC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For
			 purposes of this subsection, the following definitions shall apply:</text>
					<subparagraph id="H0A103057BB6F4B67A12378826E73ECF9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Assisted
			 multifamily housing property</header><text>The term <term>assisted multifamily
			 housing property</term> means a multifamily housing project for which
			 assistance is provided under a multifamily housing subsidy program.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B23945E90B94970A3B9E7057A642512"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Low-income
			 family</header><text>The term <term>low-income family</term> has the meaning
			 given such term in section 3(b) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42
			 U.S.C. 1437a(b)).</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H891782675D534170912182641BD4A17C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Moderate-income
			 family</header><text>The term <term>moderate-income family</term> has the
			 meaning given such term in section 229 of the Low-Income Housing Preservation
			 and Resident Homeownership Act of 1992 (12 U.S.C. 4119).</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22B184B4B75745429820E79020189DF4"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Multifamily
			 housing subsidy program</header><text>The term <term>multifamily housing
			 subsidy program</term> means—</text>
						<clause id="H708FFAB1842E46768E35A0EB72E78867"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the
			 below-market interest rate mortgage insurance program under section 221(d)(3)
			 of the National Housing Act (12 U.S.C. 1715l(d)(3)); and</text>
						</clause><clause id="HAFC1EF748ED244B59E53ABEBC372F5A0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the
			 program for interest reduction payments under section 236 of the National
			 Housing Act (12 U.S.C. 1715z–1).</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47A2C35CAB0C4F08B934C997F7D8586A"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Termination
			 date</header><text>The term <term>termination date</term> means, with respect
			 to an assisted multifamily housing property, the date that—</text>
						<clause id="H04D9B59555674ACBA048D778CF0A463B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the
			 mortgage for the property that is insured under the below-market interest rate
			 program under section 221(d)(3) of the National Housing Act, or for which
			 interest reduction payments are made under section 236 of such Act, matures;
			 and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H69C40CE4DD2D46D3A2A54D4D984EF13D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the
			 affordability restrictions applicable to the property because of assistance for
			 the property pursuant to a multifamily housing subsidy program terminate with
			 respect to the property.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFC26AF71EFEF4D72AC79C3DE48011A11"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The
			 Secretary may issue any regulations necessary to carry out this
			 subsection.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4BC8E2A110344F17AE3A6D5B9BF444AF"><enum>16.</enum><header>Demonstration
			 program waiver authority</header>
			<subsection id="H8122B401C64E44E785A785B5B4A92675"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority To
			 enter into agreements</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law,
			 the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development may enter into such agreements
			 as may be necessary with the Social Security Administration and the Secretary
			 of Health and Human Services to allow for the participation, in any
			 demonstration program described in subsection (c), by the Department of Housing
			 and Urban Development and the use under such program of housing choice vouchers
			 under section 8(o) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C.
			 1437f(o)).</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HDFD343671D664DDE81D04CF416C63B88"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiver of income
			 requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of
			 Housing and Urban Development may, to extent necessary to allow rental
			 assistance under section 8(o) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 to be
			 provided on behalf of persons described in subsection (c) who participate in a
			 demonstration program described in such subsection, and to allow such persons
			 to be placed on a waiting list for such assistance, partially or wholly
			 disregard increases in earned income for the purpose of rent calculations under
			 section 3 for such persons.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HF33DFFC58CB8494FA98E648D5D786F10"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Demonstration
			 programs</header><text>A demonstration program described in this subsection is
			 a demonstration program of a State that provides for persons with significant
			 disabilities to be employed and continue to receive benefits under programs of
			 the Department of Health and Human Services and the Social Security
			 Administration, including the program of supplemental security income benefits
			 under title XVI of the Social Security Act, disability insurance benefits under
			 title II of such Act, and the State program for medical assistance (Medicaid)
			 under title XIX of such Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFB3C1ECAFB3944418DDAE8D9FC438593" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>17.</enum><header>Authorization of
			 appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is
			 authorized to be appropriated for fiscal year 2010 the amount necessary to
			 provide public housing agencies with incremental assistance under section 8(o)
			 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)) sufficient to
			 assist 150,000 incremental dwelling units in such fiscal year, for—</text>
			<paragraph id="H42884D67E77347AB8F1ACB80E8905E2A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>tenant-based
			 assistance; and</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H1A135F58083C48D8AC6BA1C35BC09F7F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>project-based
			 voucher assistance for extremely low-income families, in conjunction
			 with—</text>
				<subparagraph id="HFD7DBCE853564670ADEF78F9DB7AFAE5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">funding from either of the funds
			 established under section 1138 or 1339 of the Federal Housing Enterprises
			 Financial Safety and Soundness Act of 1992 (12 U.S.C. 4568, 4569);</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57B2936A0F46497E8C7D9DAB7376EA90"><enum>(B)</enum><text>low-income housing
			 tax credits provided under section 42 of the Internal Revenue Code of
			 1986;</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBADACBAD1FF84FFEBB378A4DC1752309"><enum>(C)</enum><text>amounts provided
			 under the community development block grant program under title I of the
			 Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (42 U.S.C. 5301 et seq.) and the
			 HOME investment partnerships program under title II of the Cranston-Gonzalez
			 National Affordable Housing Act (42 U.S.C. 12721 et seq.); and</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23903B49C2E8420F9C550FB2D121C135"><enum>(D)</enum><text>State and local
			 affordable housing funds and programs.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H043D3A7152D547DCBA08010717AD024B"><enum>18.</enum><header>Agency authority
			 for utility payments in certain circumstances</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8(o) of the United States Housing
			 Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)), as amended by the preceding provisions of
			 this Act, is further amended by adding at the end the following new
			 paragraph:</text>
			<quoted-block id="HE907D29B60064359BFAB822EA3F528FE" style="OLC">
				<paragraph id="HA29635E7082342C2B4B4DD39429F323E"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Authority of
				public housing agencies to make direct payments for utilities when owner fails
				to pay</header>
					<subparagraph id="H771E5527E84E4D3881E740A1370B918A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text>If the owner has failed to pay for utilities that are the
				responsibility of the owner under the lease or applicable law, the public
				housing agency is authorized to utilize subsidy payments otherwise due the
				owner to pay for continued utility service to avoid hardship to program
				participants.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02FF5C3F510E4BB096D34C299EE02C20"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>Before
				making utility payments as described in subparagraph (A), the public housing
				agency shall take reasonable steps to notify the owner that it intends to make
				payments to a utility provider in lieu of payments to the owner, except prior
				notification shall not be required in any case in which the unit will be or has
				been rendered uninhabitable due to the termination or threat of termination of
				service, in which case the public housing agency shall notify the owner within
				a reasonable time after making such
				payment.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="H3221B45F14924DED933E0981B3D5B71A"><enum>19.</enum><header>Project-based
			 preservation vouchers</header>
			<subsection id="HC37DE24CF93244A4A35887D5FAD0C7A0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Enhanced
			 vouchers</header><text>Section 8(t) of the United States Housing Act of 1937
			 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(t)) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="HE72A02270E504AE79A569750819D44BF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating
			 paragraph (4) as paragraph (5); and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HF3FDB1C0EE50465CA6CAB6726A80327D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after
			 paragraph (3) the following new paragraph:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA4D1D408331F405289D07F68A7307220" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="H2A8DD596A809493684E7F7BB969197D4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Preservation
				project-based voucher assistance</header><text>Notwithstanding any other
				provision of law, in the case of a multifamily housing project with respect to
				which an eligibility event occurs or has occurred, project-based voucher
				assistance may be provided in accordance with subsection (o)(13)(P) in lieu of
				enhanced voucher assistance under this subsection. Such project-based voucher
				assistance shall not be subject to the provisions of this subsection, except as
				otherwise specifically provided in subsection
				(o)(13)(P).</text>
						</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD5980D51516E496590F4FE7FB64E884A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>PHA
			 project-based voucher assistance</header><text>Paragraph (13) of section 8(o)
			 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(13)), as amended
			 by the preceding provisions of this Act, is further amended by adding at the
			 end the following new subparagraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H00C175038DD044A3B130E44E3FB16C2A" style="OLC">
					<subparagraph id="H299A6FF1D34C4CFB9C028AC37B0EACD9"><enum>(P)</enum><header>Preservation
				assistance</header>
						<clause id="H636B288732BF4D15ACF8276B49A144B4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Project-based voucher assistance under this
				paragraph shall be made available in accordance with this subparagraph for
				multifamily housing projects for which an eligibility event (as such term is
				defined in subsection (t)) occurs or has occurred and for which enhanced
				voucher assistance would otherwise be, or has been, provided under subsection
				(t). Any such assistance shall be in lieu of enhanced voucher assistance under
				subsection (t) for tenants residing in the project and shall be provided by the
				Secretary to a public housing agency.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H2433AD583460409F8E8AC7B6C05D8209"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Request and
				provision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the owner of a
				multifamily housing project makes a request for project-based voucher
				assistance pursuant to this subparagraph for the project to a public housing
				agency that administers a program for assistance under subsection (o) for a
				jurisdiction within which the project is located, a contract for assistance
				under this subparagraph shall be provided with respect to the project, subject
				to clause (v).</text>
						</clause><clause id="H3614C8DC01AE410DA88D993F323581F8"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Timing,
				coverage, and unit rents</header>
							<subclause id="H2248AF859D504FA2B4A4CE4158B9E7E4"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Request made
				before eligibility event</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In
				the case of a contract for assistance under this subparagraph with respect to a
				project that is requested prior to the occurrence of the eligibility event, the
				contract for assistance shall be provided, subject to clause (v), upon the
				occurrence of the eligibility event. Such contract shall cover all dwelling
				units in the project for which enhanced voucher assistance under subsection (t)
				would otherwise be provided.</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="HFCF5581B913D4464A7C00F9657A4175C"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Request made
				after issuance of enhanced vouchers</header><text>In the case of a contract for
				assistance under this subparagraph with respect to a project that is requested
				after the issuance of enhanced vouchers under subsection (t) for the project,
				the contract shall be provided, subject to clause (v), as soon as possible.
				Such contract shall cover all dwelling units in the project that are occupied
				by tenants receiving such enhanced voucher assistance at the time the contract
				is effective.</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H75F53A02CD14496E880C52504F0A1C58"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Coverage of
				additional dwelling units</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At
				the request of the owner of a multifamily housing project for which a contract
				for assistance is to be provided under this subparagraph, the public housing
				agency may contract with the owner for project-based voucher assistance under
				this subparagraph to cover additional dwelling units, if the public housing
				agency determines that such additional assistance is necessary or desirable to
				further the purposes reflected in clause (v).</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H41766FD3277F4DBB8930B0193EDB9036"><enum>(IV)</enum><header>Approval of
				higher rents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the request
				of the owner of a multifamily housing project for a contract for assistance
				under this subparagraph to establish rents at levels above those permitted by
				subparagraph (H), a public housing agency that has made the determinations
				required by clause (v) may request, and the Secretary may approve, higher unit
				rents if necessary to preserve housing opportunities that further the purposes
				of clause (v).</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause id="H4263CB76D0564A648DCB5917486719EE"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Projects in
				multiple PHA jurisdictions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If
				the Secretary has not entered into a contract with a public housing agency to
				provide enhanced voucher assistance under subsection (t) for the project at the
				time the owner of a multifamily housing project requests assistance under this
				subparagraph, and the project is located within the jurisdiction for the
				program under subsection (o) of more than one public housing agency, in
				determining which agency will administer such assistance, the Secretary
				shall—</text>
							<subclause id="H8A01FD1FFFCC42E2B5C18430C6E2069D"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consider the ratio of the number of
				vouchers to be awarded under this subparagraph and of other project-based
				vouchers administered under this paragraph to the total number of vouchers
				administered by an agency; and</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H077FD837874A40AD8733E62096BFEE62"><enum>(II)</enum><text>among other
				factors, provide preference to an agency for which the total number of
				project-based vouchers administered under this paragraph, including vouchers to
				be awarded pursuant to this subparagraph, would not exceed 50 percent of the
				total number of all vouchers to be administered by the agency after such
				award.</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause id="H8DCB3D35A02E487E99891E44D33ACF7C"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Required
				determinations</header><text>As a condition of entering into a contract
				pursuant to this subparagraph, the public housing agency shall have determined,
				before entering into such contract that—</text>
							<subclause id="HFD31DB3FC4624AD195A25FEE548F5BA6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the housing to be
				assisted under the contract is economically viable; and</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H47B4F65BA2C3482DA30E15AAF25F71F6"><enum>(II)</enum><item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H61CCEC653FC8416180A6A65F2FC82653"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>there is a significant
				demand for the housing;</text>
								</item><item id="HC430958EAF054F4F885639B9EA2C0D83" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the housing will contribute to a
				community revitalization plan or to deconcentrating poverty and expanding
				housing and economic opportunities; or</text>
								</item><item id="H248B3F1C70B84278878024294B5D44AE" indent="up1"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the continued affordability of the
				housing otherwise is an important asset to the community.</text>
								</item></subclause></clause><clause id="HE10E150868DE4B8BAB19EECD50614EAF"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Inapplicability
				of goals</header><text>Subparagraph (C) shall not apply to a housing assistance
				payment contract pursuant to this subparagraph.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H0486B8465F774B659838EFC5E3ABFF2A"><enum>(vii)</enum><header>Disregard of
				assistance under percentage limitation</header><text>Amounts provided pursuant
				to this subparagraph shall not be considered for purposes of calculating the
				limitation under subparagraph (B).</text>
						</clause><clause id="HF5766FB49D32460CB64CA9CE0839FD30"><enum>(viii)</enum><header>Inapplicability
				of income-mixing requirement</header><text>Subparagraph (D) shall not apply
				with respect to a housing assistance payments contract pursuant to this
				subparagraph.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H12CCB204836143999697B7CB07945B10"><enum>(ix)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>Subject
				only to clause (iii) and notwithstanding any other provision of law, any family
				residing in a multifamily housing project on the date of the eligibility event
				for the project who would otherwise be eligible for enhanced voucher assistance
				under subsection (t) shall be eligible for project-based voucher assistance
				pursuant to this
				subparagraph.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section><section id="HBA3BEEF31054412C864E10F2DC7FF6C7"><enum>20.</enum><header>Effect of
			 foreclosure on section 8 tenancies</header>
			<subsection id="H08477C154F0144ACB743F67435BB373D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Use of rental
			 assistance amounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section
			 8(o)(7) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(7)(F)), as
			 amended by section 703 of division A of Public Law 111–22 (123 Stat. 1661), is
			 amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H310D1BB1D1E142D3833F9B31B53A056E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph
			 (F), by inserting after <quote>occupied unit,</quote> the
			 following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7307D4FF692A4F749CA56D37368A452D" style="OLC">
						<text>and if a public housing agency is
			 unable to make payments under the contract to the immediate successor in
			 interest after foreclosure, due to action or inaction by the successor in
			 interest, including the rejection of payments or the failure of the successor
			 to maintain the unit in compliance with paragraph (8), or an inability to
			 identify the successor, the agency may use funds that would have been used to
			 pay the rental amount on behalf of the family—</text><clause id="H22E6B62FBB6C429A8D368A065E8D8DAC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to
				pay for utilities that are the responsibility of the owner under the lease or
				applicable law, after taking reasonable steps to notify the owner that it
				intends to make payments to a utility provider in lieu of payments to the
				owner, except prior notification shall not be required in any case in which the
				unit will be or has been rendered uninhabitable due to the termination or
				threat of termination of service, in which case the public housing agency shall
				notify the owner within a reasonable time after making such payment; or</text>
						</clause><clause id="H7795A292A9D74C70BB0BC67B15E9A2DB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for the family’s
				reasonable moving costs, including security deposit
				costs.</text>
						</clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HE64D52EDC30B4E039495FB7D899CA32A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>except that this provision and the provisions related to foreclosure in
			 subparagraph (C) shall not</quote> in subparagraph (F) and inserting the
			 following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4A4637CCA98A4A6FA1D4C047F8C45537" style="OLC">
						<quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="paragraph">The
				provisions related to foreclosure in subparagraphs (C) and
				(F)</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H405386D3AEC54B13BAB697EB00584205"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in the matter
			 after and below subparagraph (F), as amended by paragraph (2) of this
			 subsection, by adding after the period at the end the following: <quote>For
			 purposes of subparagraphs (C) and (F), the term <term>immediate successor in
			 interest</term> includes a purchaser who purchases a property from an immediate
			 successor in interest.</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8E9F003469CC468786AB6FB755B9A333"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>Section
			 704 of division A of the Helping Families Save Their Homes Act (Public Law
			 111–22; 123 Stat. 1662) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="HDB8E70881B0F412A8AB69FB0A018FD45"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>This title, and any amendments made by this title are</quote> and
			 inserting <quote>Section 702 is</quote>; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H27B5BFB0A0AA407991ABB9AC1882FA1B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>this title</quote> and inserting <quote>such section</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H099CAB1340CB470C9242B6FB78F6CE65"><enum>21.</enum><header>Study to
			 identify obstacles to using vouchers in federally subsidized housing
			 projects</header>
			<subsection id="HD6E8C10F819B47678FECFD413CCF7085"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The
			 Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study of (1) the
			 housing voucher program authorized under section 8(o) of the United States
			 Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)), and (2) other federally subsidized
			 housing programs, to determine whether any statutory, regulatory, or
			 administrative provisions of the housing voucher program or of other federally
			 subsidized housing programs, or policies and practices of housing owners or
			 public housing agencies or other agencies, may have the effect of making
			 occupancy by voucher holders in federally subsidized housing projects more
			 difficult to obtain than occupancy by non-voucher holders. In conducting the
			 study required under this subsection the Comptroller General shall determine if
			 any gaps exist in the statute, regulations, or administration of the housing
			 voucher program or of other federally subsidized housing programs and policies
			 and practices of housing owners or public housing agencies or other agencies
			 that, if addressed, could eliminate or reduce obstacles to voucher holders in
			 seeking occupancy in federally subsidized housing projects. Such study shall
			 include data on the use of housing vouchers in federally subsidized housing
			 projects.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H25FB048E7A564DF9B55060910795CDB5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>As
			 used in this section, the term <term>federally subsidized housing
			 projects</term> includes projects assisted pursuant to the HOME investment
			 partnerships program under title II of the Cranston-Gonzalez National
			 Affordable Housing Act (42 U.S.C. 12721 et seq.) and those projects receiving
			 the benefit of low-income housing credits under section 42 of the Internal
			 Revenue Code of 1986 (26 U.S.C. 42).</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H9C9AF97B09CA41A098184723406DA57D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not
			 later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller
			 General shall report to Congress the findings from the study required under
			 subsection (a) and any recommendations for statutory, regulatory, or
			 administrative changes.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H836A18F868D1480FA7306C671BD0FC34" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>22.</enum><header>Interagency Council
			 on Homelessness</header>
			<subsection id="H1B0054D688224531994B1A9F4EE3B730"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Technical
			 correction</header><text>Section 202(e) of the McKinney-Vento Homeless
			 Assistance Act (42 U.S.C. 11312), as amended by section 1004 of Public Law
			 111–22, is amended by striking <quote>Chairman</quote> and inserting
			 <quote>Chairperson</quote>.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HF076B27D5D7F461D8E5D523AC21AADFE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>Section
			 203 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (42 U.S.C. 11313), as amended
			 by section 1004 of Public Law 111–22, is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H4D9C2795ADEC4580B9F5AA3BACF3CF4A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (a)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H0FFD084B5265498B80D3647C95EDF8FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating paragraphs (6) through
			 (13) as paragraphs (9), and (16), respectively;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D8736E8A9D543C2929A3A10E5230A0D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1),
			 by inserting <quote>which shall set forth actions to accomplish the goal of
			 ending homelessness,</quote> after <quote>National Strategic Plan to End
			 Homelessness,</quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF9DE19167DD4CF48DF111ED8BCC5BBD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (3),
			 by inserting before the semicolon at the end the following: <quote>and ensure
			 that related programs and activities to assist homeless individuals of Federal
			 agencies are coordinated with each other</quote>; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32A1DF33621F42DAA5AD6C4AF526918D"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after paragraph (5) the
			 following new paragraphs:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDBC696D6FD3149BBB2C7AF3DA15B0CB6" style="OLC">
							<paragraph id="H83CE7027155C423A86409949F9EE0BCA"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">make recommendations, in the reports
				submitted pursuant to subsection (c) on—</text>
								<subparagraph id="H333D6C5B760D49209E36FFB7511881C1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>long-term goals
				for the Congress to reduce homelessness; and</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBE54E19BA85468E80390C11F332F1D0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>legislative
				strategies for the Congress to achieve such goals;</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFD5057AE8404706ADBC642D11926019"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evaluate the Federal role in interacting
				and coordinating with State and local entities that address
				homelessness;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H3BBC9C86F3614DFA9961B2C5F914AD09"><enum>(8)</enum><text>conduct research
				and develop methods—</text>
								<subparagraph id="H22844AC76B3748F0847EBB86DD20FF57"><enum>(A)</enum><text>through
				consultation with State and local agencies, to improve coordination between the
				Council and Federal agencies in existence upon the date of enactment of the
				<short-title>Interagency Council on Homelessness Reform
				Act of 2009</short-title> that specifically deal with homelessness; and</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H886C916A36CF4FC1938A0242152A6CEF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to minimize the
				period during which individuals remain
				homeless;</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H61112FF231614E01B8F460329CA9F8F5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c),
			 by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAEBD24274E854B8B93BB634FFF47AA67" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="HE2B90528C5104AC9A84DCF4D5FFDF9E2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Biennial
				report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Council shall
				prepare and transmit to the President and the Congress a biennial report
				detailing the efforts of the Council to address homelessness.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H9FB9BD9366844F71B197CDE71150794F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Public
				availability</header><text>The Council shall make each report submitted to the
				Congress pursuant to paragraph (1), (2), or (3) of this subsection, and the
				national plan and updates of such plan submitted pursuant to paragraph (1) of
				subsection (a), publicly available, including through posting on a World Wide
				Web site maintained by the
				Council.</text>
						</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2F1A7A5CC04F415FA5D666F5D5FD05D6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of
			 appropriations</header><text>Section 208 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless
			 Assistance Act (42 U.S.C. 11318), as amended by section 1004 of Public Law
			 111–22, is amended by striking <quote>fiscal years 2011</quote> and inserting
			 <quote>each of fiscal years 2011 through 2015</quote>.</text>
			</subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H23B00AC18B1147A0B920B5DB5B0A331C" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>23.</enum><header>Housing innovation
			 program</header>
			<subsection id="HB532AD76E7FF4C488E62E60D2B74633C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of
			 program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title I of the United
			 States Housing Act of 1937 (42 U.S.C. 1437 et seq.) is amended by adding at the
			 end the following new section:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0061AFE6848A4B12BD1D0C01A5722329" style="OLC">
					<section id="H663C5BE54356430793401C60F75050C8"><enum>37.</enum><header>Housing
				innovation program</header>
						<subsection id="HC9AB53D5430547068E540D0B364CA545"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The
				purpose of the program under this section is to establish a demonstration
				program under which public housing agencies are given the flexibility to
				design, and the Secretary is given the responsibility to evaluate, innovative
				approaches to providing housing assistance that—</text>
							<paragraph id="H092AFD3AA17A492180F9053BFAF2B585"><enum>(1)</enum><text>increase housing
				opportunities for low-, very low-, and extremely low-income families, including
				modernizing, rehabilitating, reconfiguring, or replacing public housing at risk
				of physical deterioration or obsolescence, developing additional affordable
				housing, providing supportive housing, and increasing the number of families
				receiving tenant-based rental assistance;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H39B4EB242A7741188FECCDC56BE516D6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide financial
				incentives and other support mechanisms to families to obtain employment and
				increase earned income, and achieve economic self-sufficiency, while protecting
				very low- and extremely low-income families from increased rent burdens;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H3D2E05FABFB245318B5EDC6462BD648A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>utilize funds in a
				more effective or cost-efficient manner, including achieving energy,
				administrative, and other cost savings;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HAC846E129FB44A20B698827F5EB610B7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>leverage other
				Federal, State, and local funding sources, including the low-income housing tax
				credit program, to expand and preserve affordable housing opportunities,
				including public housing;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HE969C25F21CB49ACBDD28DCDA887BD8F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>test alternative
				rent-setting policies to determine whether rent determinations can be
				simplified and administrative cost savings can be realized while protecting
				extremely low- and very low-income families from increased rent burdens;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H918167B6E5F2421E82B729903F5E0AC3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>are subject to
				rigorous evaluation to test the effectiveness of such innovative approaches;
				and</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H0941CA54F7024E27AEC0C70C02D1EF97"><enum>(7)</enum><text>are developed with
				the support of the local community and with the substantial participation of
				affected residents.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H65ED1D4214974ACCB4B857B9642977D3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program
				authority</header>
							<paragraph id="H941697D4B12C4C38A67557B6F3822BFF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Scope</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall carry out a housing
				innovation demonstration program under this section under which the Secretary
				may designate such number of public housing agencies to participate in the
				housing innovation demonstration program as may be necessary, in conjunction
				with agencies approved for continued program participation pursuant to
				subsection (c), to demonstrate the effectiveness of the priority strategies
				identified in subsection (d)(2). The Secretary may also designate such number
				of additional agencies to participate in the program under the terms of
				subsection (i) as may be necessary to demonstrate other innovative strategies
				as the Secretary or applicants may propose.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HE3B99181DBD54ABC866BA2861AE881FB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may carry out the housing
				innovation program under this section only during the 10-year period beginning
				on the date of the enactment of the Section 8 Voucher Reform Act of
				2009.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8E848F964F71459C8885C8922F546562"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Participation of
				existing MTW agencies</header>
							<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8B4D8309A8384698A7477C28C757EAB4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Existing MTW
				agencies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the
				requirements of paragraph (2), all existing MTW agencies shall be designated to
				participate in the program.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HE180D5C49B5A4322A0E440A83CDB6DA8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conditions of
				participation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary
				shall approve and transfer into the housing innovation program under this
				section each existing MTW agency that the Secretary determines is not in
				default under such agreement and which the Secretary also determines is meeting
				the goals and objectives of its moving to work plan. Any agency that has been
				audited by the Inspector General of the Department of Housing and Urban
				Development shall demonstrate compliance with the program rules that the
				Inspector General determined were not being complied with by such agency. Any
				agency approved for transfer into the housing innovation program may, at its
				option, be subject to the provisions of this paragraph, in lieu of an agreement
				currently in place with the Secretary for participation in the Moving to Work
				program. Each agency shall, within two years after the date of the enactment of
				the Section 8 Voucher Reform Act of 2009, make changes to its policies that
				were implemented before such date of enactment in order to comply with the
				requirements of this section.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB98953FBD95E487FA7C0A5EE7AB43DA0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Additional
				agencies</header>
							<paragraph id="H2107515C32BC46C7875C475D0925B020"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Proposals;
				selection process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition
				to agencies participating in the program pursuant to subsection (c), the
				Secretary shall, within 12 months after such date of enactment, select public
				housing agencies to participate in the program pursuant to a competitive
				process that meets the following requirements:</text>
								<subparagraph id="H4D1823772EDC4759A23235B3BF304DF0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any public housing agency may be selected
				to participate in the program, except that not more than 5 agencies that are
				near-troubled under the public housing assessment system and/or section 8
				management assessment program may be selected, and except that any agency that
				is a troubled agency under either such assessment program or for which the
				Secretary has hired an alternative management entity for such agency or has
				taken possession of all or any part of such agency’s public housing program
				shall not be eligible for participation. Any near-troubled public housing
				agency participating in the program shall remain subject to the requirements of
				this Act governing tenant rent contributions, eligibility, and continued
				participation, and may not adopt policies described in subsection (e)(4)
				(relating to rents and requirements for continued occupation and
				participation).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1919304F614C4EBAAB55C8F6A989C084"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The process provides, to the extent
				possible based on eligible agencies submitting applications and taking into
				account existing MTW agencies participating pursuant to subsection (c), for
				representation among agencies selected of agencies having various
				characteristics, including both large and small agencies, agencies serving
				urban, suburban, and rural areas, and agencies in various geographical regions
				throughout the United States, and which may include the selection of agencies
				that only administer the voucher program under section 8(o).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF04ADB6913DF49DB9C4FD96330FAD86D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any agency
				submitting a proposal under this paragraph shall have provided notice to
				residents and the local community, not later than 30 days before the first of
				the two public meetings required under subparagraph (D).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0FF61A4DC23241809F86B4DEBE34DB5D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The agency
				submitting a proposal shall hold two public meetings to receive comments on the
				agency’s proposed application, on the implications of changes under the
				proposal, and the possible impact on residents.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H641EE74FA16D4654B42BB43B2A6EA52E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The process
				includes criteria for selection, as follows:</text>
									<clause id="H74656DB758F748589C5B63DD4D32970F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The extent to
				which—</text>
										<subclause id="HD91378E57C0645BF9B52FC0A59E3F10E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>if proposal is for
				the purpose of carrying out the priority strategy under subsection (d)(2)(A),
				the proposal is likely to achieve the purposes of increasing housing
				opportunities for low-, very low-, and extremely low-income families, including
				modernizing, rehabilitating, reconfiguring, or replacing public housing at risk
				of physical deterioration or obsolescence, developing additional affordable
				housing, providing supportive housing, or increasing the number of families
				receiving tenant-based rental assistance, or a combination of these
				purposes;</text>
										</subclause><subclause id="H4CAC6364373B4243A28CD067AF9F069E"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the proposal is for the purpose of
				carrying out the priority strategy under subsection (d)(2)(B), the proposal is
				likely to achieve the purposes of families obtaining employment, increasing
				earned income, or achieving economic self-sufficiency, while protecting
				extremely low- and very low-income families from increased rent burdens;
				or</text>
										</subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H61C1D24086C343A89BA401683455C236"><enum>(III)</enum><text>if the proposal
				is for the purpose of carrying out an innovative strategy pursuant to the last
				sentence of subsection (b)(1), the proposal is likely to achieve the goals and
				objectives of such strategy.</text>
										</subclause></clause><clause id="H97038ED170644506ADD96584BD9203A4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The extent to
				which the proposal generally identifies statutory provisions and existing rules
				and regulations that impede achievement of the goals and objectives of the
				proposal and an explanation of why a waiver of such statutory provisions,
				rules, and regulations is necessary to achieve such goals and
				objectives.</text>
									</clause><clause id="HC935FC558F3E4D3585E7A55CA71BEC1C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The extent to
				which the agency has a successful history of implementing or has expertise in
				strategies similar to those set forth in the agency’s proposal.</text>
									</clause><clause id="HCAAFD26B35194627A84FB2CAEFD1A1CE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The extent of
				commitment and funding for carrying out the proposal by local and State
				government agencies and nonprofit organizations, including the provision of
				additional funding and other services, and the extent of support for the
				proposal by residents, resident advisory boards, and members of the local
				community.</text>
									</clause><clause id="H1D2B2B4E9FBE460389A0228BAF4C8A66"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Such other factors
				as the Secretary may establish, in consultation with participating agencies and
				agencies interested in participating in the program, program stakeholders, and
				any entity conducting evaluations pursuant to subsection (f), which may include
				the extent to which the proposal is likely to result in utilization of funds in
				a more effective or cost-efficient manner, including achieving energy,
				administrative, and other cost savings.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A6B82D58CA94DA095F8522E6762ADE3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority
				strategies</header><text>For purposes of the first sentence of paragraph
				(b)(1), the following are priority strategies:</text>
								<subparagraph id="HDCDC1777AAB84349BD38C0EE4C1E9601"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Increasing
				housing opportunities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A
				strategy of development of increasing housing opportunities for low-, very
				low-, and extremely low-income families, including modernizing, rehabilitating,
				reconfiguring, or replacing public housing at risk of physical deterioration or
				obsolescence, developing additional affordable housing, providing supportive
				housing, or increasing the number of families receiving tenant-based rental
				assistance, or a combination of these purposes.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC2A534BB1944F14AF17DDF9A7E83086"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Rent reforms and
				family self-sufficiency</header><text>A strategy to implement rent reforms and
				other self-sufficiency incentives or resources, which shall be designed to help
				families obtain employment, increase their earned income, or achieve economic
				self-sufficiency, while protecting extremely low- and very low-income families
				from increased rent burdens.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H615BBDDFBCDF452CBBAC4EFC3957BBDA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contract
				amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After selecting
				agencies under this subsection, the Secretary shall promptly amend the
				applicable annual contributions contracts of such agencies to provide
				that—</text>
								<subparagraph id="H130FC9C656FE4E1687C96AA591E35C9E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>subject to
				subparagraph (B), such agencies may implement only such policies and activities
				that are necessary to carry out the priority strategy or innovative strategy or
				strategies included in the application for participation in the program,
				without specifying such policies and activities in such amendment and without
				negotiating or entering into any other agreements with the Secretary specifying
				such policies and activities; and</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF78224A8C57F423AB33BAC36825F791E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the activities to
				be implemented by an agency under the program in a given year shall be
				described in and subject to the requirements of the annual plan under
				subsection (e)(8).</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H42CA7F6F309B45219E47D619EF2DD541"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Program
				requirements</header>
							<paragraph id="H9A6829D3B9014E1D92663D8863FDB4E1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Program
				funds</header>
								<subparagraph id="H5A0A5A6436954372AA1C599891E27B43"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent
				necessary to carry out a housing innovation program under this section, the
				participating agency may use amounts provided to the agency from the Operating
				Fund under section 9(e), amounts provided to the agency from the Capital Fund
				under section 9(d), and amounts provided to the agency for voucher assistance
				under section 8(o). Such program funds may be used for any activities that are
				authorized by section 8(o) or 9, or for other activities that are not
				inconsistent with this section, which may include, without limitation—</text>
									<clause id="HAF7AE9DF1F9F43E5A9828724EDCA5266"><enum>(i)</enum><text>providing capital
				and operating assistance, and financing for housing previously developed or
				operated pursuant to a contract between the Secretary and such agency;</text>
									</clause><clause id="HAEED6ED7A16A451A8C719780F0850061"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the acquisition,
				new construction, rehabilitation, financing, and provision of capital or
				operating assistance for low-income housing (including housing other than
				public housing) and related facilities, which may be for terms exceeding the
				term of the program under this section in order to secure other financing for
				such housing;</text>
									</clause><clause id="H06C6AAD5E4B340E2A5571AA13A5E85F2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>costs of site
				acquisition and improvement, providing utility services, demolition, planning,
				and administration of activities under this paragraph;</text>
									</clause><clause id="H556A9DAC97AE4054ABA2F79F6C543DEC"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>housing
				counseling for low-income families in connection with rental or homeownership
				assistance provided under the program;</text>
									</clause><clause id="H77CA15400B18456A98D7D3F088B6ACF8"><enum>(v)</enum><text>safety, security,
				law enforcement, and anticrime activities appropriate to protect and support
				families assisted under the program;</text>
									</clause><clause id="H0A465A41A27E413786F62622B5B0B203"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>tenant-based
				rental assistance, which may include the project-basing of such assistance;
				and</text>
									</clause><clause id="H546505871C014E01A3A4D15BF4961FCF"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>appropriate and
				reasonable financial assistance that is required to preserve low-income housing
				otherwise assisted under programs administered by the Secretary or under State
				or local low-income housing or public housing programs.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12F928632AE548DF95597EA944004A75"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Combining
				funds</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a participating
				agency may combine and use program funds for any activities authorized under
				this section, except that a participating agency may use funds provided for
				assistance under section 8(o) for activities other than those authorized under
				section 8(o) only if (i) in the calendar year prior to its participation in the
				program, the agency utilized not less than 95 percent of such funds allocated
				for that calendar year for such authorized activities or 95 percent of its
				authorized vouchers; or (ii) after approval to participate in the program, the
				agency achieves such utilization for a 12-month period. Such limitation shall
				not apply to participating agencies approved by the Secretary to combine funds
				from sections 8 and 9 of the Act prior to enactment of this section. A public
				housing agency that uses funds provided from assistance under section 8(o) for
				activities not authorized under such subsection may not terminate assistance to
				families assisted under such subsection on the grounds of inadequate funding to
				the extent such inadequacy is caused by such use of funds for purposes not
				authorized under section 8(o).</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C27B803D508452CB6EB38D8F1906CFB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of program
				funds</header><text>In carrying out the housing innovation program under this
				section, each participating agency shall continue to assist—</text>
								<subparagraph id="H280FB8C4CC1D4FD88F2F48CA763C3C8B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not less than 98
				percent of the number of eligible low-income families under the program as it
				assisted in the base year for the agency; and</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDEBBB40182AD405889A0C828D985CA58"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a comparable mix
				of families by family size, subject to adjustment to reflect changes in the
				agency’s waiting list, except that the Secretary may approve exceptions to such
				requirements for up to 3 years based on modernization or redevelopment
				activities proposed in an annual plan submitted and approved in accordance with
				paragraph (11).</text>
								</subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">Determinations with respect to the
				number of families required to be served shall be adjusted to reflect any
				allocation of additional vouchers under section 8(o), any change in annual
				voucher proration factor, or such other appropriate adjustments as the
				Secretary may establish. For purposes of subparagraph (A), the term <term>base
				year</term> means, with respect to existing MTW agencies, the first full
				calendar year prior to approval and transfer, pursuant to subsection (c)(2),
				into the housing innovation program under this section. The Secretary shall
				monitor and enforce compliance with the requirements of subparagraph (A) on an
				annual basis.</continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEDED6A11AAF14592864BF687B3D82832"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Retained
				provisions</header><text>Each agency that is approved to carry out one of the
				two priority strategies identified in subsection (d)(2) shall comply with all
				provisions of this Act except those that are necessary to carry out one of such
				two priority strategies. Notwithstanding any other provision of this section,
				families receiving assistance under this section shall retain the same rights
				of judicial review of agency action as they would otherwise have had if the
				agency were not participating in the program, and each participating agency,
				including existing MTW agencies, shall comply with the following provisions of
				this Act:</text>
								<subparagraph id="HEBAF594A84344AF6B1C8FEDDC6F5A044"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Subsections
				(a)(2)(A) and (b)(1) of section 16 (relating to targeting for new admissions in
				the public housing and voucher programs).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB99F5F3D4EF74279B85CDCFFF73B4323"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Section 2(b)
				(relating to tenant representatives on the public housing agency board of
				directors).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5592AC88D17F4D948DA8F2BAE7CD532F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Section 3(b)(2)
				(relating to definitions for the terms <term>low-income families</term> and
				<term>very low-income families</term>).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D7994769F5941E4AC30D0BA82BE78EA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Section 5(A)(e)
				(relating to the formation of and consultation with a resident advisory
				board).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB88BBD99B928433EA601A7E0FDB26326"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Sections 6(f)(1)
				and 8(o)(8)(B) (relating to compliance of units assisted with housing quality
				standards or other codes).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF222F261897748708F55ACA209CB0898"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Sections 6(c)(3),
				6(c)(4)(i), and 8(o)(6)(B) (relating to rights of public housing applicants and
				existing procedural rights for applicants under section 8(o)).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5D4BEAE72DD482CB3B8B9AB4065C689"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Section 6(k)
				(relating to grievance procedures for public housing tenants) and comparable
				procedural rights for families assisted under section 8(o).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H286C054C86464616BEE20A437107A3EE"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Section 6(l)
				(relating to public housing lease requirements), except that for units assisted
				both with program funds and low-income housing tax credits, the initial lease
				term may be less than 12 months if required to conform lease terms with such
				tax credit requirements.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA20AF40BF2984B93AC3BE5877EBCF731"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 7 (relating to designation of
				housing for elderly and disabled households), except that a participating
				agency may make such designations (at initial designation or upon renewal) for
				a term of up to 5 years if the agency includes in its annual plan under
				paragraph (11) an analysis of the impact of such designations on affected
				households and such designation is subject to the program evaluation. Any
				participating agency with a designated housing plan that was approved under the
				moving to work demonstration may continue to operate under the terms of such
				plan for a term of 5 years (with an option to renew on the same terms for an
				additional 5 years) if it includes in its annual plan an analysis of the impact
				of such designations on affected households and is subject to evaluation under
				subsection (f).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H87A54ECA67FC4A049F69F1D1FF55DBE3"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subparagraphs (C) through (E) of section
				8(o)(7) and section 8(o)(20) (relating to lease requirements and eviction
				protections for families assisted with tenant-based assistance).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20CED326CEC7433C948E08AACA5D6980"><enum>(K)</enum><text>Section
				8(o)(13)(B) (relating to a percentage limitation on project-based assistance),
				except that for purposes of this subparagraph such section shall be applied by
				substituting <quote>50 percent</quote> for <quote>20 percent</quote>, and all
				voucher funding that is used for non-tenant based assistance purposes shall
				count towards this calculation.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBCBABB9DD83940FD86D3014C9FB28481"><enum>(L)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8(o)(13)(E) (relating to resident
				choice for tenants of units with project-based vouchers), except with respect
				to—</text>
									<clause id="HD4C1875F70AA45389BC6467B51CC1641"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in
				the case of agencies participating in the moving to work demonstration, any
				housing assistance payment contract entered into within 2 years after the
				enactment of this section;</text>
									</clause><clause id="H677D5B58374E413494C2CF18732B21B7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>project-based
				vouchers that replace public housing units;</text>
									</clause><clause id="H0FED8B309F374338AA96E099934B3918"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>not more than 10
				percent of the vouchers available to the participating agency upon entering the
				housing innovation program under this section; and</text>
									</clause><clause id="H7BF5AF344FC1430D90A79640635D7F52"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any project-based
				voucher program that is subject to evaluation under subsection (f).</text>
									</clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">Notwithstanding the exceptions
				under this subparagraph, an agency may not eliminate resident choice under
				section 8(o)(13)(E) for more than 25 percent of its authorized vouchers.</continuation-text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1817C00FB5FC4C72829BEB5BD5D57B10"><enum>(M)</enum><text>Section 8(r)
				(relating to portability of voucher assistance), except that a participating
				agency may receive funding for portability obligations under section 8(dd) in
				the same manner as other public housing agencies.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H842B011D0952401E9D5AE9B2A443350D"><enum>(N)</enum><text>Sections 8(ee) and
				6(u) (relating to records, certification and confidentiality regarding domestic
				violence).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B1009773B7D4D80B4762D2B6E933C37"><enum>(O)</enum><text>Subsections (a)
				and (b) of section 12 (relating to payment of prevailing wages).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF116B2CC2C8B4A3199214F8C95917D7E"><enum>(P)</enum><text>Section 18
				(relating to demolition and disposition of public housing).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6916EF47483B488CA23FA987A039CDCE"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>Part 964 of title
				24 of the Code of Federal Regulations (relating to tenant participation and
				tenant opportunities in public housing).</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD532EAC9FA2F429E9AE8940F95D1D830"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rents and
				requirements for continued occupancy or participation</header>
								<subparagraph id="HEE230368C9224D9FBFC81F730A7645DE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Before policy
				change</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before adopting any
				policy pursuant to participation in the housing innovation program under this
				section that would make a material change to the requirements of this Act
				regarding tenant rents or contributions, or conditions of continued occupancy
				or participation, a participating agency shall complete each of the following
				actions:</text>
									<clause id="H0931738F8D72482283E7F81E55DD3442"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The agency shall
				conduct an impact analysis of the proposed policy on families the agency is
				assisting under the program under this section and on applicants on the waiting
				list, including analysis of the incidence and severity of rent burdens greater
				than 30 percent of adjusted income on households of various sizes and types and
				in various income tiers, that would result, if any, without application of the
				hardship provisions. The analysis with respect to applicants on the waiting
				list may be limited to demographic data provided by the applicable consolidated
				plan, information provided by the Secretary, and other generally available
				information. The proposed policy, including provisions for addressing hardship
				cases and transition provisions that mitigate the impact of any rent increases
				or changes in the conditions of continued occupancy or participation, and data
				from this analysis shall be made available for public inspection and copying,
				on request, and for access through the Internet, for at least 60 days in
				advance of the public meeting described in clause (ii).</text>
									</clause><clause id="HBE388F33E5A245329D8B2C2E15AFC360"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The agency shall
				hold a public meeting regarding the proposed change, including the hardship
				provisions, which may be combined with a public meeting on the draft annual
				plan under paragraph (11) or the annual report under subsection (h)(2).</text>
									</clause><clause id="HDBF8BF9AA249413D9BBDDCC67E981BE4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The board of
				directors or other similar governing body of the agency shall approve the
				change in public session.</text>
									</clause><clause id="H690B840E25B74EC19DF62CB8E93769E8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The agency shall
				obtain approval from the Secretary of the annual plan or plan amendment. The
				Secretary may approve a plan or amendment containing a material change to the
				requirements of this Act regarding tenant rents or contributions, or conditions
				of continued occupancy or participation, only if such policy is included as
				part of the national evaluation.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2B1C5B8B38C42EC824228F9A804182E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>After policy
				change</header><text>After adopting a policy described in subparagraph (A), a
				program agency shall complete each of the following actions:</text>
									<clause id="HD9ECE2744178495FB8537C739328EDF7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The agency shall
				provide adequate notice to residents, which shall include a description of the
				changes in the public housing lease or participation agreement that may be
				required and of the hardship or transition protections offered.</text>
									</clause><clause id="HB9FCD327B49248779EE3E247BCAAE010"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>In the case of
				any additional requirements for continued occupancy or participation, the
				agency shall execute a lease addendum or participation agreement specifying the
				requirements applicable to both the resident and the agency. A resident may
				bring a civil action to enforce commitments of the agency made through the
				lease addendum or participation agreement.</text>
									</clause><clause id="HEF682738AEAE47F1A5E7FB69265877AE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The agency shall
				reassess rent, subsidy level, and policies on program participation no less
				often than every two years, which shall include preparing a revised impact
				analysis, and make available for public inspection and copying, on request, and
				for access through the Internet, the results of such reassessment and impact
				analysis. The requirement under this clause may be met by sufficiently detailed
				interim reports, if any, by the national evaluating entity.</text>
									</clause><clause id="HD66A9172400A4611B531D07343540307"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The agency shall
				include in the annual report under subsection (h)(2) information sufficient to
				describe any hardship requests, including the number and types of requests
				made, granted, and denied, the use of transition rules, and adverse impacts
				resulting from changes in rent or continued occupancy policies, including
				actions taken by the agency to mitigate such impacts and impacts on families no
				longer assisted under the program.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4AB43FBA1744D589787FFC5A1786091"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Applicability to
				existing MTW agencies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An
				existing MTW agency that, before the date of the enactment of this section,
				implemented material changes to the requirements of this Act regarding tenant
				rents or contributions, or conditions of continued occupancy or participation,
				as part of the moving to work demonstration shall not be subject to
				subparagraph (A) with regard to such previously implemented changes, but shall
				comply with the requirements of subparagraph (B)(ii) and provide the evaluation
				and impact analysis required by subparagraph (B)(iii) by the end of the second
				agency fiscal year ending after such date of enactment.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC563CF9EA3B241AEA88C679055F06147"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Prohibition
				against decrease in program funds</header><text>The amount of program funds a
				participating agency receives shall not be diminished by its participation in
				the housing innovation program under this section.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H9DA6B9F916A1458DB410CC3203108393"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Rent
				burden</header><text>A participating agency may not adopt rent policies that
				result in rents that are not affordable to assisted families.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HBD57B3AA64644DE59F2F10524666FB91"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Time
				limits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A participating agency
				may implement time limits on the term of housing assistance received by
				families under the program only for families who—</text>
								<subparagraph id="H42E7096FFD2B491CA8586F5276627963"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are gainfully
				employed and have been employed for at least 3 years; and</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97AA2FCD71EB4CD89CFF439EFBEDBB06"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have earned income
				of at least 150 percent of the poverty level for a family of the comparable
				size.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5AF995D0CAA46A88AF594D5F257E7AA"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Employment
				conditions</header><text>A participating agency may condition the receipt of
				housing assistance by families under the program on the employment status of
				one or more families members only if the agency—</text>
								<subparagraph id="H02AB7911EED94FEEADD35A6BBEF740FD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>permits compliance
				with a standard of not more than 20 hours per week in qualifying work activity
				and permits compliance based on attendance in a school or other institution in
				pursuit of a diploma or graduate equivalency diploma;</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD043AEC940642AB85F896F92819A980"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establishes
				reasonable hardship exemptions; and</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC091EF4F4C5A455195F7EC9C8F233681"><enum>(C)</enum><text>suspends
				enforcement of such condition if the unemployment rate in the area served by
				the agency exceeds such level as the Secretary shall establish.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H33456B2B3EB44807AB3D1A4975E6B3EA"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Submission of
				information</header><text>As part of the annual report required under
				subsection (h)(2), each participating agency shall submit information annually
				to the Secretary regarding families assisted under the program of the agency
				and comply with any other data submissions required by the Secretary for
				purposes of evaluation of the program under this section.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H9EC92C19930841CC81F7D2AC1B9DDDBC"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Public and
				resident participation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each
				participating agency shall provide opportunities for resident and public
				participation in the annual plan under paragraph (11), as follows:</text>
								<subparagraph id="H4F04789CFE2741CE9E0C1206878C293B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Notice to
				residents</header>
									<clause id="H09412C5E8D4C4656B3317BC7FF7D6326"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Notice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each year, the agency shall provide notice
				to the low-income families it serves under the programs authorized by this
				section as to the impact of proposed policy changes and program initiatives and
				of the schedule of resident advisory board and public meetings for the annual
				plan.</text>
									</clause><clause id="HA2DCD52692DD41D689CDCA943F357A8C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Meeting</header><text>The
				agency shall hold at least one meeting with the resident advisory board
				(including representatives of recipients of assistance under section 8) to
				review the annual plan for each year.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCAEBDFEE722641BB811EB123B2E0329C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Public
				meeting</header><text>With respect to each annual plan, the agency shall hold
				at least one annual public meeting to obtain comments on the plan, which may be
				combined with a meeting to review the annual report. In the case of any agency
				that administers, in the aggregate, more than 15,000 public housing units and
				vouchers, or that operates in more than one county, the agency shall hold
				additional meetings in locations that promote attendance by residents and other
				stakeholders.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D78FADC7B1449BFA047454B804C63F2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Public
				availability</header><text>Before adoption of any annual plan, and not less
				than 30 days before the public meeting required under subparagraph (A)(ii) with
				respect to the plan, the agency shall make the proposed annual plan available
				for public inspection and copying, on request, and for access through the
				Internet. The annual plan shall be made available for public inspection not
				less than 30 days before approval by the board of directors (or other similar
				governing body) of the agency and shall remain publicly available.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D5A998323454DF7B232F0E7370640AA"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Board
				approval</header><text>Before submitting an annual plan or annual report to the
				Secretary, the plan or report, as applicable, shall be approved in a public
				meeting by the board of directors or other governing body of the agency.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1313C51AB33D4539A84D0CD2CD3937DA"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Annual
				plan</header>
								<subparagraph id="HCBD66A26476742D1BA6F00638C62AADF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>For
				each year that a participating agency participates in the housing innovation
				program under this section, the agency shall submit to the Secretary, in lieu
				of all other planning requirements, an annual plan under this paragraph.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H027D538BA0844176BE9D71D85525FA73"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>Each
				annual plan shall include the following information:</text>
									<clause id="H5F4B50F555E849339048B8AE7E5C20BA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A
				list and description of all program initiatives and generally applicable policy
				changes, including references to affected provisions of law or the implementing
				regulations affected.</text>
									</clause><clause id="HB07342ED45B846AF89BFE218B170EF19"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A
				description and comparison of changes under the housing innovation program of
				the agency from the plan for such program for the preceding year.</text>
									</clause><clause id="HD4BCB8BC80AB4F1C917262714CD41376"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A description of
				property redevelopment or portfolio repositioning strategies and proposed
				changes in policies or uses of funds required to implement such
				strategies.</text>
									</clause><clause id="H308B2D4E84F74509A959A8EA8C23FC6D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Documentation of
				public and resident participation sufficient to comply with the requirements
				under paragraphs (4) and (10), including a copy of any recommendations
				submitted in writing by the resident advisory board of the agency and members
				of the public, a summary of comments, and a description of the manner in which
				the recommendations were addressed.</text>
									</clause><clause id="H47F8392B4E9A4D7B9344C546949C740E"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Certifications by
				the agency that—</text>
										<subclause id="HDD9F05B6F4C44368AAF0E3E0E4FDC1F1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the annual plan
				will be carried out in conformity with title VI of the Civil Rights Act of
				1964, the Fair Housing Act, section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973,
				title II of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, and the rules,
				standards, and policies in the approved plan;</text>
										</subclause><subclause id="H6856CB6EE12245989A661FFCDDEF9AAA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the agency will
				affirmatively further fair housing; and</text>
										</subclause><subclause id="H09FB7033D68E496EA3C4F0E4FED94BD2"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the agency has
				complied and will continue to comply with its obligations under the national
				evaluation.</text>
										</subclause></clause><clause id="H890616335962493CBBAE62F49AE6317B"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the agency’s local asset
				management strategy for public housing properties, which shall be in lieu of
				any other asset management, project based management or accounting, or other
				system of allocating resources and costs to participating agency assets or cost
				centers that the Secretary may otherwise impose under this Act.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94A5E55642A94497A3E6D7984067221A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Changes</header><text>If
				the agency proposes to make material changes in policies or initiatives in the
				plan during the year covered by the plan, the agency shall consult with the
				resident advisory board for the agency established pursuant to section 5A(e)
				and the public regarding such changes before their adoption.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C596F3A583E472DA6A359160CF2DB2D"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Approval
				process</header>
									<clause id="HB8F2F8C3045A4B7890166FC36FDA5F88"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall review and approve or
				disapprove each annual plan submitted to the Secretary within 45 days after
				such submission. The Secretary, directly or through the public housing agency,
				shall make information relating to such approval or disapproval available to
				the chairperson of the Resident Advisory Board of the public housing
				agency.</text>
									</clause><clause id="HF7633962A1B8467DB67037F2B4C37B47"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Standards for
				disapproval</header><text>The Secretary may disapprove a plan only if—</text>
										<subclause id="HDF64A05D669D470D9AE0B360E50DEE44"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Secretary
				reasonably determines, based on information contained in the annual plan or
				annual report, that the agency is not in compliance with the requirements of
				this section;</text>
										</subclause><subclause id="HE1F54D97B5544B559E6CB4ED273267D3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the annual plan
				or most recent annual report is not consistent with other reliable information
				available to the Secretary; or</text>
										</subclause><subclause id="HF0BA57C4BA714D1D80EAFB2DA556DD68"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the annual plan
				or annual report or the agency’s activities under the program are not otherwise
				in accordance with applicable law or with the agency’s application to
				participate in the program pursuant to this section.</text>
										</subclause></clause><clause id="H2ED48CC2DC994BBC881C9751205EE485"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Failure to
				disapprove</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a submitted
				plan is not disapproved within 45 days after submission, the plan shall be
				considered to be approved for purposes of this section. The preceding sentence
				shall not preclude judicial review regarding such compliance pursuant to
				chapter 7 of title 5, United States Code, or an action regarding such
				compliance under section 1979 of the Revised Statutes of the United States (42
				U.S.C. 1983).</text>
									</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3CFB4CCEDF9F46C6B0DA83AD7B09F060"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Evaluation of
				Performance</header>
							<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H29589C34D2CF4E21BA71BF24C49C6330"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall
				conduct detailed evaluations of all public housing agencies participating in
				the program under this section—</text>
								<subparagraph id="H22501D19790940B9BC7E30F94A462990"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to determine the
				level of success of each public housing agency in achieving the goals and
				objectives of the application to participate in the program;</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H550B9063E3B4489B99ACEEC562ED20FA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to determine the level of success of
				different types of proposals in achieving the priority strategies of subsection
				(d)(2) or other innovative strategies identified pursuant to subsection (b)(1);
				and</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H85A1289175BD42FF9888DEE156F454FF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to identify
				program models that can be replicated by other agencies to achieve such
				success.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFB1F60A93A34AEB95C675A14034B1FA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Evaluation
				methodology</header><text>Evaluations under this subsection shall be conducted
				utilizing rigorous research methodology which shall incorporate, where
				appropriate and to the extent funding is available, the following:</text>
								<subparagraph id="H6FD2332E8CED4B5B997E96729313D26F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Random assignment
				of families to experimental and control groups.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC87456BC970E432CBD44000994914676"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Comparisons of
				alternative strategies for advancing common goals.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA6AC24DE6B543FFB0DEF7F92911FB6C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An examination of
				the costs, outputs, and outcomes of tested strategies.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95F332B37F4E41B98ACFD3A43C0A3C3D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A process
				evaluation that examines the challenges faced in implementing tested strategies
				and how those challenges were overcome.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03A5BAFF01704D0984B5E97833A3A48C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A qualitative
				examination of the impacts of tested strategies on affected families, including
				families on agency waiting lists.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H571D49793E4D41C19485869F8BBF5446"><enum>(F)</enum><text>An examination of
				the impact of tested strategies on the housing needs and conditions of the
				jurisdiction in which the agency works.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43DA61670B7A4752A9C1F215628DBF65"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Appropriate
				sensitivity to the costs that evaluation places on participating agencies,
				including a recognition that smaller agencies may have more difficulty than
				larger agencies in responding to data requests.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA31522295CF94F0394CE122CE1481497"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Advisory
				Council</header><text>The Secretary shall establish an Advisory Council to
				provide input on the policies and strategies to be tested in evaluations under
				this subsection, data collection protocols, and other matters related to the
				success of the evaluation, and to assist the evaluating entity and the
				Secretary in interpreting the findings and formulating recommendations to the
				Congress to be included in the final report. The Secretary may also establish a
				separate Technical Advisory Group to provide input on technical issues
				associated with the evaluation.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H4EFFB387763A408CABC0AF08EE10F64C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Reports</header>
								<subparagraph id="H64AEF54010AE40ED850F3A195CEAFE3A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall
				submit three reports to the Congress, as provided in subparagraph (B),
				evaluating the programs of all public housing agencies participating in the
				program under this section and all agencies participating in the moving to work
				demonstration. Each such report shall include findings and recommendations for
				any appropriate legislative action.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H706A7AA433AD41AFB0EE115B00E91B6E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>The
				reports under this paragraph shall include—</text>
									<clause id="HCDD50EDD0BD043ADA310EBDA63DCB7D4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an
				initial report, which shall be submitted before the expiration of the 2-year
				period beginning on the date on which additional agencies are approved for
				participation pursuant to subsection (d);</text>
									</clause><clause id="HAB2A28E5D6924423ADC3DCCAE42710EE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an interim
				report, which shall be submitted before the expiration of the 4-year period
				beginning on such date of approval; and</text>
									</clause><clause id="H55285D8428154EF8B558A2EA59ABA759"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a final report, which shall be submitted
				before the expiration of the 10-year period beginning on the date of the
				enactment of the <short-title>Section 8 Voucher Reform Act
				of 2009</short-title>.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H49D6601CAC874DE68293E29BC3DA625C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Evaluating
				entity</header><text>The Secretary may contract out the responsibilities under
				this paragraphs (1) and (2) to an independent entity that is qualified to
				perform such responsibilities.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H8EC0BF7758F8424CA567FA0766CE17FB"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Performance
				measures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary or the
				evaluating entity, as applicable, shall establish performance measures, which
				may include—</text>
								<subparagraph id="H162E30DBE9A94D40A34F62D9243FB3D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a baseline
				performance level against which program activities may be evaluated; and</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA28F3D709094D999864F878156B3728"><enum>(B)</enum><text>performance
				measures for each of the five purposes identified in paragraphs (1) through (5)
				of subsection (a).</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1CDD9F527052416DBB46737020A6AB6C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Impact of policy
				on families being assisted</header>
							<paragraph id="H96FD3AA53EA54155925A39F9875EEDFB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Discontinuance
				or modification of policy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If
				an evaluation of an agency pursuant to subsection (f)(1)(A) includes evidence
				that a policy adopted by an agency is or has been harmful to families assisted
				by the agency, the Secretary may, after the publication of either the initial
				or the interim report pursuant to subsection (f)(4)(B), require such agency to
				discontinue such policy or to take appropriate actions to modify such policy to
				ameliorate such harm.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HC75F1D9D9FB8455DAEC64D4E57FB9379"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>The
				Secretary may not take such action unless the Secretary has made a
				determination that such policy is causing or has caused measurable harm to
				families currently or previously assisted, based on a reduction in the overall
				number of families receiving housing assistance, specific types of families
				losing their housing assistance, a reduction in the number of affordable rental
				housing units operated by the agency, a reduction in the effective targeting of
				housing assistance to extremely low- or very low-income families, or a
				combination of such factors.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HBF116426244C4432A3C733A951E68FBB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Advice and
				opportunity to contest</header><text>Before taking such action, the Secretary
				shall advise the agency and give the agency a fair opportunity to contest such
				determination or action. If an agency contests such a determination or action,
				the Secretary shall provide an opportunity for interested parties to submit
				additional relevant evidence.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H31B07CD467BA49CB8FEFB1E195C0E400"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Recordkeeping,
				reports, and audits</header>
							<paragraph id="H123699A3A31B4E45977AF326EBE7AB45"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Recordkeeping</header><text>Each
				public housing agency participating in the program under this section shall
				keep such records as the Secretary may prescribe as reasonably necessary to
				disclose the amounts and the disposition of amounts under the program, to
				ensure compliance with the requirements of this section, and to measure
				performance.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H8F83318BC09441368E83724265178D36"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In lieu of all other reporting
				requirements, each such agency participating in the program shall submit to the
				Secretary an annual report in a form and at a time specified by the Secretary.
				Each annual report shall include the following information:</text>
								<subparagraph id="H2B386304BA79485682A114768EF50C60"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A description,
				including an annual consolidated financial report, of the sources and uses of
				funds of the agency under the program, which shall account separately for funds
				made available under section 8 and subsections (d) and (e) of section 9, and
				shall compare the agency’s actions under the program with its annual plan for
				the year.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1602A3FABC6F4124B3917C4093A25C83"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An annual audit
				that complies with the requirements of Circular A–133 of the Office of
				Management and Budget, including the OMB Compliance Supplement.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A424EAFD6BA42E88CDFD8D2B390D5AF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of
				each hardship exception requested and granted or denied, and of the use of any
				transition rules.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59D864E116D04F70B48F3DD9E62B3B66"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Documentation of
				public and resident participation sufficient to comply with the requirements
				under paragraph (7).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H808ADD43FF7046D4BBCF5B8EB783F744"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A comparison of
				income and the sizes and types of families assisted by the agency under the
				program compared to those assisted by the agency in the base year.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED33595778634459A920EE00D0CAA626"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Every two years,
				an evaluation of rent policies, subsidy level policies, and policies on program
				participation.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A1DE0C2D07A42099933AEE6E5349887"><enum>(G)</enum><text>A description of
				any ongoing local evaluations and the results of any local evaluations
				completed during the year.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCFD29B1989447DDA7667201A6F46F32"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Access to
				documents by secretary</header><text>The Secretary shall have access for the
				purpose of audit and examination to any books, documents, papers, and records
				that are pertinent to assistance in connection with, and the requirements of,
				this section.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HF53741EB3C1E47208125586D77C9D710"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Access to
				documents by the Comptroller General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United
				States, or any of the duly authorized representatives of the Comptroller
				General, shall have access for the purpose of audit and examination to any
				books, documents, papers, and records that are pertinent to assistance in
				connection with, and the requirements of, this section.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HE01ADA64995D4CC4950BF311E75BB410"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Reports
				regarding evaluations</header><text>The Secretary shall require each public
				housing agency participating in the program under this section to submit to the
				Secretary such information as the Secretary considers appropriate to permit the
				Secretary to evaluate (pursuant to subsection (f)) the performance and success
				of the agency in achieving the purposes of the demonstration.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDFC559568BE14302A7123E371CD156C8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Additional
				program agencies</header><text>In participating in the program under the terms
				of this subsection, the public housing agencies designated for such
				participation shall be subject to the requirements of this section, and the
				additional following requirements:</text>
							<paragraph commented="no" id="H1049C665123945569AB258767E8BF1AA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicability of
				certain existing provisions</header><text>Such agencies shall be subject to the
				provisions of—</text>
								<subparagraph commented="no" id="H11EB0B5EEA744CCB8D04FC44E871558F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>subsections (a)
				and (b) of section 3; and</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H58DBE24C29784898B58D2924500CA55A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 8(o),
				except for paragraph (11) and except as the requirements of section 8(o) are
				modified by subsection (e)(3) of this section.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H8EAD63F42AC04E5FA0F0FEE223B53E17"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No time
				limits</header><text>Such agencies may not impose time limits on the term of
				housing assistance received by families under the program.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HB20C6A92B6DC4393848C8621BA651EB3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>No employment
				conditions</header><text>Such agencies may not condition the receipt of housing
				assistance by families under the program on the employment status of one or
				more family members.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H79CD187F9DB64553BFD526A35C2F7266"><enum>(4)</enum><header>One-for-one
				replacement</header>
								<subparagraph commented="no" id="H055A34873FC64C0E86B575A825D625B6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Conditions on
				demolition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such agencies may
				not demolish or dispose of any dwelling unit of public housing operated or
				administered by such agency (including any uninhabitable unit and any unit
				previously approved for demolition) except pursuant to a plan for replacement
				of such units in accordance with, and approved by the Secretary of Housing and
				Urban Development pursuant to, subparagraph (B).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB5C625DB8EB04FB289FFEAABF82A5749"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Plan
				requirements</header><text>The Secretary may not approve a plan that provides
				for demolition or disposition of any dwelling unit of public housing referred
				to in subparagraph (A) unless—</text>
									<clause commented="no" id="H34C546D543E643F38B11D1955B198D6F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such plan provides
				for outreach to public housing agency residents in accordance with paragraph
				(5);</text>
									</clause><clause commented="no" id="H6A852E1CA91E411DBBD011F128A73DE5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not later than 60
				days before the date of the approval of such plan, such agency has convened and
				conducted a public hearing regarding the demolition or disposition proposed in
				the plan;</text>
									</clause><clause commented="no" id="HDBF4DA847AE141058B43D566BEF8D2E2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>such plan
				provides that for each such dwelling unit demolished or disposed of, such
				public housing agency will provide an additional dwelling unit through—</text>
										<subclause commented="no" id="H8D248C3B077C4681B0F25A117BAB1FA4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the acquisition or
				development of additional public housing dwelling units; or</text>
										</subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H375A2A43807342E1B20926A4BD2AF011"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the acquisition,
				development, or contracting (including through project-based assistance) of
				additional dwelling units that are subject to requirements regarding
				eligibility for initial or continued occupancy, tenant contribution toward
				rent, and long-term affordability restrictions which are comparable to public
				housing units, except that no household may be prevented from occupying a
				replacement dwelling unit provided pursuant to clause (iii) except to the
				extent specifically provided by any other provision of Federal law (including
				subtitle F of title V of the Quality Housing and Work Responsibility Act of
				1998 (42 U.S.C. 13661 et seq.; relating to safety and security in public and
				assisted housing, subtitle D of title VI of the Housing and Community
				Development Act of 1992 (42 U.S.C. 13611 et seq.; relating to preferences for
				elderly and disabled residents), and section 16(f) of this Act (42 U.S.C.
				1437n(f)); relating to ineligibility of persons convicted of methamphetamine
				offenses);</text>
										</subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H48623F5142484F518E4F8F595CD2E1C8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such plan provides for a right, and
				implementation of such right, to occupancy of additional dwelling units
				provided in accordance with clause (iii), for households who, as of the time
				that dwelling units demolished or disposed of were vacated to provide for such
				demolition or disposition, were occupying such dwelling units;</text>
									</clause><clause commented="no" id="HD616420D570B406AA0B757060E18882F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>such plan provides
				that the proposed demolition or disposition and relocation will be carried out
				in a manner that affirmatively furthers fair housing, as described in
				subsection (e) of section 808 of the Civil Rights Act of 1968; and</text>
									</clause><clause commented="no" id="H4B0D1306918640FBAC700FADAE199413"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>to the extent
				that such plan provides for the provision of replacement or additional dwelling
				units, or redevelopment, in phases over time, such plan provides that the ratio
				of dwelling units described in subclauses (I) and (II) of clause (iii) that are
				provided in any such single phase to the total number of dwelling units
				provided in such phase is not less than the ratio of the aggregate number of
				such dwelling units provided under the plan to the total number of dwelling
				units provided under the plan.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H343CC77FFE4D4FD4BC3EB51D6BADFCB4"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Monitoring</header><text>The
				Secretary shall provide for the appropriate field offices of the Department to
				monitor and supervise the enforcement of this paragraph and plans approved
				under this paragraph and to consult, regarding such monitoring and enforcement,
				with resident councils of, and resident of public housing operated or
				administered by, the agency.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H4AEFEF3918B74EAC82E58FA615AEFF68"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Comprehensive
				outreach plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No program
				funds of such agencies may be use to demolish or dispose of any public housing
				dwelling units except in accordance with a comprehensive outreach plan for such
				activities, developed by the agency in conjunction with the residents of the
				public housing agency, as follows:</text>
								<subparagraph commented="no" id="H900028E7E9CB411C904EA16E538DEE1B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The plan shall be
				developed by the agency and a resident task force, which may include members of
				the Resident Council, but may not be limited to such members, and which shall
				represent all segments of the population of residents of the agency, including
				single parent-headed households, the elderly, young employed and unemployed
				adults, teenage youth, and disabled persons.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0D148693AEC64879904479A0AF9B89E3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The votes and
				agreements regarding the plan shall involve—</text>
									<clause commented="no" id="H5D18F8ABA7694C3E8AC77BE7D2195DC3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of any
				public housing agency that administers 250 or fewer public housing dwelling
				units, not less than 10 percent of affected residents; and</text>
									</clause><clause commented="no" id="HF360B9F7E0184B868CA442AB81534D45"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of any public housing agency
				that administers more than 250 public housing dwelling units, not less than 25
				affected residents.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE80CC1FE29ED4D118704853FE2752BAE"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The plan shall provide for and describe
				outreach efforts to inform residents of the program under this subsection,
				including a door-to-door information program, monthly newsletters to each
				resident household, monthly meetings dedicated solely to every aspect of the
				proposed development, including redevelopment factors, which shall include the
				one-for-one replacement requirement under paragraph (4), resident rights to
				return, the requirements of the program under this subsection, new resident
				support and community services to be provided, opportunities for participation
				in architectural design, and employment opportunities for residents, which
				shall make available at least 30 percent of the total hours worked at all such
				employment, and shall also make available at least 25 percent of unskilled jobs
				in demolition activities and 25 percent of unskilled jobs in construction
				activities related to the redevelopment project, including job training,
				apprenticeships, union membership assistance.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC9B55102C372463CBCB59561B7671EF5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The plan shall
				provide for regularly scheduled monthly meeting updates and a system for filing
				complaints about any aspect of the redevelopment process.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD5E658903E2348479DD157D8A9278A4D"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For
				purposes of this section, the following definitions shall apply:</text>
							<paragraph id="H5BCA485D8DF84414BFDB2346A5D7684E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Existing MTW
				agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term
				<term>existing MTW agency</term> means a public housing agency that as of the
				date of the enactment of the Section 8 Voucher Reform Act of 2009 has an
				existing agreement with the Secretary pursuant to the moving to work
				demonstration, or is authorized to enter into such an agreement under section
				230 of the Transportation, Housing and Urban Development, and Related Agencies
				Appropriations Act, 2008 (Public Law 110–161; 121 Stat. 2438) or section 236 of
				the Transportation, Housing and Urban Development, and Related Agencies
				Appropriations Act, 2009 (Division I of Public Law 111–8).</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H188CDF3EB02C443CA58E37B1A410F12A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Base
				year</header><text>The term <term>base year</term> means, with respect to a
				participating agency, the agency fiscal year or calendar year, as appropriate,
				most recently completed prior to selection and approval for participation in
				the housing innovation program under this section.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H0AEF386288BE417CB6192EE399C9FDA8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Moving to work
				demonstration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term
				<term>moving to work demonstration</term> means the moving to work
				demonstration program under section 204 of the Departments of Veterans Affairs
				and Housing and Urban Development, and Independent Agencies Appropriations Act,
				1996 (42 U.S.C. 1437f note).</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H6FBB46202DF147C7B6D4A86E21FE4C2E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Participating
				agencies</header><text>The term <term>participating agencies</term> means
				public housing agencies designated and approved for participation, and
				participating, in the housing innovation program under this section.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HD49D362D5C4547BE8E1CFC517AEBB0CE"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Program
				funds</header><text>The term <term>program funds</term> means, with respect to
				a participating agency, any amounts that the agency is authorized, pursuant to
				subsection (e)(1), to use to carry out the housing innovation program under
				this section of the agency.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HDF8BA51F667944B68A7F41CADB951068"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Residents</header><text>The
				term <term>residents</term> means, with respect to a public housing agency,
				tenants of public housing of the agency and participants in the voucher or
				other housing assistance programs of the agency funded under section 8(o), or
				tenants of other units owned by the agency and assisted under this
				section.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB0A9146F5F374616AEA7B337C22A1731"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Resident
				technical assistance</header>
							<paragraph id="H6203032FC55F4902B8C0AC6D82EDC283"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization of
				appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is
				authorized to be appropriated for each of fiscal years 2010 through 2014
				$10,000,000, for providing capacity building and technical assistance to
				enhance the capabilities of low-income families assisted or eligible for
				assistance under the program under this section to participate in the process
				for establishment and revision of annual plans under this section for
				participating agencies, including review and comment on impact analyses and
				demolition or disposition proposals.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H47E72C0B28ED4FC59979402B1BE17742"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria for
				award of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary
				shall publish the criteria to be used to award funds on a competitive basis, in
				an amount appropriate to the number of households affected by the program of
				the participating agency or agencies that such participating agency assists, to
				local, regional, State, or national organizations that—</text>
								<subparagraph id="HB92BA554F6D1482AA2CD218608910028"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H95339A5B7DB247DF9D95B4F5042A2AAA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>have members who are
				predominantly low-income;</text>
									</clause><clause id="H7808B86557E94E169C21086BC2F720F7" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>have low-income individuals on
				their boards of directors; or</text>
									</clause><clause id="H50B0F64B5EE441948E1080EAFAC64F3F" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>directly work with or represent
				low-income individuals;</text>
									</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03814EC4029A43D981CD67DC558126AA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have the legal, policy, and development
				expertise to provide such assistance or will subcontract for such services;
				and</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50DEA964BE5943EB967B078D6A18CCFB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>have a
				demonstrated capacity to manage similar grants.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4506CF978C584FA2AA2A852BAEA75322"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public housing
				agencies</header>
								<subparagraph id="H879D84DA41D84C91BC12DB771A10321F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Ineligibility;
				nonliability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Public housing
				agencies shall not be eligible to receive funds under this subsection, and
				shall not be liable for the action of any grantee.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1F6E826E4A343AC8439CCDA9E0675EE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Cooperation with
				grantees</header><text>Public housing agencies participating in the program
				under this section shall cooperate with grantees receiving technical assistance
				funds under this subsection, to assist such grantees to reach families assisted
				under the program.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF95A17F4362F42F0A36DF23D580749C6"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Authorization of
				appropriations for evaluations</header><text>There is authorized to be
				appropriated $15,000,000 to the Department of Housing and Urban Development for
				the purpose of conducting the evaluations required under subsection
				(f)(1).</text>
						</subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H6E4098D7DA574C639B75AC82DB45CFB5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>GAO
			 report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 48
			 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of
			 the United States shall submit a report to the Congress on the extent to which
			 the public housing agencies participating in the housing innovation program
			 under section 37 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 are meeting the goals
			 and purposes of such program, as identified in subsection (a) of such section
			 37.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H699B311EBF234320BEB31FEEE73FC82B"><enum>24.</enum><header>Effective
			 date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Except as otherwise
			 specifically provided in this Act—</text>
			<paragraph id="HEB43644D7F444CF29C78D96CCA55A9BD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>sections 3, 4, 6,
			 and 7 of this Act and the amendments made by such sections shall take effect on
			 January 1, 2010, except that the Secretary may delay such effective date for
			 any one or more of sections 3, 4, and 7 to January 1, 2011, upon a
			 determination by the Secretary that such extension is necessary to provide
			 program participants sufficient time to make adjustments to the changes made by
			 such sections; and</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H798B5FE0C07C4C84AB37F1038904B2D7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>all other
			 provisions of this Act and the amendments made by this Act shall take effect
			 upon the issuance by the Secretary of implementing regulations, as appropriate,
			 or by notice, which shall be issued not later than the expiration of the
			 12-month period beginning upon the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body>
</bill>
