<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HAC5243A1914F432F000072843C55904F" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>109 HR 5830 IH: Wright Amendment Reform
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2006-07-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>109th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>2d Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 5830</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20060718">July 18, 2006</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="Y000033">Mr. Young of Alaska</sponsor>
			 (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="O000006">Mr. Oberstar</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M000689">Mr. Mica</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000126">Ms. Eddie Bernice Johnson of Texas</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M001158">Mr. Marchant</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="G000377">Ms. Granger</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="B000213">Mr. Barton of Texas</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="E000063">Mr. Edwards</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="G000552">Mr. Gohmert</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="H000067">Mr. Hall</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000174">Mr. Sam Johnson of Texas</cosponsor>, and
			 <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor>) introduced the following
			 bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee
			 on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To amend section 29 of the International Air
		  Transportation Competition Act of 1979 relating to air transportation to and
		  from Love Field, Texas.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HDDED1AD0E92443F0ADE3FE6972552C20" style="OLC">
		<section id="HD227BBC2DE5E4DCE95CF6A3918247AE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Wright Amendment Reform
			 Act</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="HEB944D9EF9354903B2FC54C9819EB3E7" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Modification of
			 provisions regarding flights to and from Love Field, Texas</header>
			<subsection id="H610433F0468D4585B332002E11DE5EAF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Expanded
			 service</header><text>Section 29(c) of the International Air Transportation
			 Competition Act of 1979 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/96/192">Public Law 96–192</external-xref>; 94 Stat. 35) is amended by striking
			 <quote>carrier, if (1)</quote> and all that follows and inserting the
			 following: <quote>carrier. Air carriers and, with regard to foreign air
			 transportation, foreign air carriers, may offer for sale and provide through
			 service and ticketing to or from Love Field, Texas, and any United States or
			 foreign destination through any point within Texas, New Mexico, Oklahoma,
			 Kansas, Arkansas, Louisiana, Mississippi, Missouri, and
			 Alabama.</quote>.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H1658BF4127024BE6BE29E47357A4E44E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Repeal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 29 of the International Air
			 Transportation Competition Act of 1979 (94 Stat. 35), as amended by subsection
			 (a), is repealed on the date that is 8 years after the date of enactment of
			 this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H4CA4D0715D154ED1B59F1769EF6E5740"><enum>3.</enum><header>Treatment of
			 international nonstop flights to and from Love Field, Texas</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No person shall provide, or offer to
			 provide, air transportation of passengers for compensation or hire between Love
			 Field, Texas, and any point or points outside the 50 States or the District of
			 Columbia on a nonstop basis, and no official or employee of the Federal
			 Government may take any action to make or designate Love Field as an initial
			 point of entry into the United States or a last point of departure from the
			 United States.</text>
		</section><section id="H1F701D5FAD3F47EEB2FCA717B7A63ED8"><enum>4.</enum><header>Charter flights
			 at Love Field, Texas</header>
			<subsection id="H9A9A142D29AD4C1DBACF44F0C096406C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Charter flights (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/14/212">section 212.2</external-xref> of title 14,
			 Code of Federal Regulations) at Love Field, Texas, shall be limited to—</text>
				<paragraph id="H80CE39DFE8AE43C5BE9933EBAC8A0DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>destinations within
			 the 50 States and the District of Columbia, and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H4D798AFFB75645729BDF3BEDBB7EDD91"><enum>(2)</enum><text>no more than 10
			 per month per air carrier for charter flights beyond the States of Texas, New
			 Mexico, Oklahoma, Kansas, Arkansas, Louisiana, Mississippi, Missouri, and
			 Alabama.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2F195DF88F2D46F1AD352D00B23B78F5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Carriers who
			 lease gates</header><text>Except for any flights operated by any agency of the
			 Federal Government or by any air carrier under contract with any agency of the
			 Federal Government and except in irregular operations described in the
			 agreement referred to in section 5(a), all flights operated to or from Love
			 Field by air carriers that lease terminal gate space at Love Field shall depart
			 from and arrive at one of those leased gates.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H261DA3A4EC384B7FB4CF97EEB3A80400"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Carriers who do
			 not lease gates</header><text>Charter flights from Love Field, Texas, operated
			 by air carriers that do not lease terminal space at Love Field may operate from
			 nonterminal facilities or one of the terminal gates at Love Field.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H73F30154BEEA4681BB9397E77443F080"><enum>5.</enum><header>Agreement of the
			 parties</header>
			<subsection id="H38858A2BA2E74C4E885E7FE6BEF9E37D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Any action taken by the city of Dallas, the city of Fort
			 Worth, Southwest Airlines, American Airlines, and the Dallas-Fort Worth
			 International Airport Board (referred to in this section as the
			 <quote>parties</quote>) that is reasonably necessary to implement the
			 provisions of the agreement dated July 11, 2006, and entitled <quote>CONTRACT
			 AMONG THE CITY OF DALLAS, THE CITY OF FORT WORTH, SOUTHWEST AIRLINES CO.,
			 AMERICAN AIRLINES, INC., AND DFW INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT BOARD INCORPORATING THE
			 SUBSTANCE OF THE TERMS OF THE JUNE 15, 2006 JOINT STATEMENT BETWEEN THE PARTIES
			 TO RESOLVE THE <quote>WRIGHT AMENDMENT</quote> ISSUES</quote>, and the
			 agreement, shall be deemed to comply in all respects with the parties’
			 obligations under title 49, United States Code, and any competition
			 laws.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HFC21AA31CFBF467987D32E9364D3CBC0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Love field
			 gates</header>
				<paragraph id="H3990929B7B82442A945755D7E94BE57F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The city of Dallas, Texas, shall reduce, as soon as
			 practicable, the number of gates available for passenger air service at Love
			 Field to no more than 20 gates. Thereafter, the number of gates available for
			 such service shall not exceed a maximum of 20 gates.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H5DFE6F3AFF3F41B6A27FABA5BC75F27"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Permissible
			 airport costs</header><text>Costs associated with reduction of gates under
			 paragraph (1) are permissible airport costs and shall not be considered as
			 revenue diversion.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC47181E49D01454D8323046CD2C024D4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>General
			 aviation</header><text>Nothing in the agreement referred to in subsection (a)
			 and this Act shall affect general aviation service at Love Field, including
			 flights to or from Love Field by general aviation aircraft for air taxi
			 service, private or sport flying, aerial photography, crop dusting, corporate
			 aviation, medical evacuation, flight training, police or fire fighting, and
			 similar general aviation purposes, or by aircraft operated by any agency of the
			 Federal Government or by any air carrier under contract to any agency of the
			 Federal Government.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H002C350EE8D4417EBA4963B11C800067"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text>Notwithstanding
			 any other provision of law, the Secretary of Transportation and the
			 Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration may not make findings or
			 determinations, issue orders or rules, withhold airport improvement grants or
			 approvals thereof, deny passenger facility charge applications, or take any
			 other action, either self-initiated or on behalf of third parties, that is
			 inconsistent with the provisions of the agreement referred to in subsection (a)
			 or that challenges the legality of any of its provisions.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HB3015FD063404B728FC09D54CC2E3E65"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Limitations on
			 statutory construction</header>
				<paragraph id="HCEC26D885AA748C0A33FC6BF87135C61"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H819B7FEF0B124F8999D8F3C40097E04C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to limit the
			 obligations of the parties under the programs of the Department of
			 Transportation and the Federal Aviation Administration relating to aviation
			 safety, labor, environmental, national historic preservation, civil rights,
			 small business concerns (including disadvantaged business enterprise),
			 veteran’s preference, disability access, and revenue diversion;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6BAADD797374CF59FF4B34723F100D0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to limit the
			 authority of the Department of Transportation or the Federal Aviation
			 Administration to enforce the obligations of the parties under the programs
			 described in subparagraph (A);</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64BFEBEAA498414AACA92FD4F93680A7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to limit the
			 obligations of the parties under the aviation security programs of the
			 Department of Homeland Security and the Transportation Security Administration
			 at Love Field, Texas;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54FF0965B9C24E78B0B1B17FE63EB446"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to authorize the
			 parties to offer marketing incentives that are in violation of Federal law,
			 rules, orders, agreements, and other requirements; or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA035BA9B35664ACC9C275F5BCB68E211"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to limit the
			 authority of the Federal Aviation Administration or any other Federal agency to
			 enforce requirements of law and grant assurances (including subsections (a)(1),
			 (a)(4), and (s) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/47107">section 47107</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code) that impose
			 obligations on Love Field to make its facilities available on a reasonable and
			 nondiscriminatory basis to air carriers seeking to use such facilities, or to
			 withhold grants or deny applications to applicants violating such obligations
			 with respect to Love Field.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H79F81A0280B946D39E713600613C3549"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Facilities</header><text>Paragraph
			 (1)(E)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H753F9C87B8A04345B7520152C8A41BDA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall only apply
			 with respect to facilities that remain at Love Field after implementation of
			 subsection (b); and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC93ED3E0A4594AA18BF806FEBEEE94"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall not be
			 construed to require the city of Dallas, Texas—</text>
						<clause id="H88A38B022A064F2CBBC93F9E3B1D463C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to
			 construct additional gates beyond the 20 gates referred to in subsection (b);
			 or</text>
						</clause><clause id="HB26322B2CF31450FBBF33C73E57F6B92"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to
			 modify or eliminate preferential leases with air carriers in order to allocate
			 gate capacity to new entrants or to create common use gates, unless such
			 modification or elimination is implemented on a nationwide basis.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H308F83BB144D406FAF9EB63AC0849E8"><enum>6.</enum><header>Department of
			 Transportation review</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The
			 Department of Transportation shall have exclusive authority to review actions
			 taken under this Act (including the agreement referred to in section 5(a)), and
			 actions taken to implement the agreement, with respect to all provisions of
			 title 49, United States Code, and with respect to any Federal competition laws
			 not included in such title that may otherwise apply.</text>
		</section><section id="H02DF78E5502640AB9343AE2D001F1942"><enum>7.</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The provisions of this Act shall apply only
			 to actions taken by the parties to the agreement referred to in section 5(a) of
			 this Act at Love Field, Texas, and shall have no application to any other
			 airport (other than an airport owned or operated by the city of Dallas or the
			 city of Fort Worth, Texas, or both).</text>
		</section><section id="H52B16CD555A446C8AA24E18E79EB4258"><enum>8.</enum><header>Effective
			 date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Sections 1 through 7 and
			 the amendments made by such sections shall take effect on the date that the
			 Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration notifies Congress that
			 aviation operations in the airspace serving Love Field and the Dallas-Fort
			 Worth area, Texas, occurring as a result of the agreement referred to in
			 section 5(a) and this Act can be accommodated in full compliance with Federal
			 Aviation Administration safety standards in accordance with section 40101 of
			 title 49, United States Code, and, based on current expectations, without
			 adverse effect on use of airspace in such area.</text>
		</section></legis-body>
</bill>


