<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H033BF1B5BD5B40D2B01D0004CEA792B1" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 135 IH: Twenty-First Century Water Commission Act of 2007</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-01-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 135</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070104">January 4, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000321">Mr. Linder</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001251">Mr. Butterfield</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001245">Ms. Bordallo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000159">Mr. Norwood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001139">Mr. Gary G. Miller of California</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000459">Mr. Terry</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To establish the Twenty-First Century Water Commission to study and develop recommendations for a comprehensive water strategy to address future water needs.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HFCB9B01A0553471A97EE191880583F4F" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H714FAFBEA27248E2B99FB33733612BB9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Twenty-First Century Water Commission Act of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HB0A2433C75174613B1E62C859FC00084"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H09E2C67EF1CB4C32B6B7E5DCF0F512F4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Nation’s water resources will be under increasing stress and pressure in the coming decades;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H145CC5759C3E46938B56E2613DB9F505"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a thorough assessment of technological and economic advances that can be employed to increase water supplies or otherwise meet water needs in every region of the country is important and long overdue; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC5EC652A199D4AAFAE813813931C57E4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a comprehensive strategy to increase water availability and ensure safe, adequate, reliable, and sustainable water supplies is vital to the economic and environmental future of the Nation.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HA3B1F1676B1449A0B1495B60EABBDFA3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is established a commission to be known as the <quote>Twenty-First Century Water Commission</quote> (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Commission</quote>).</text></section> 
<section id="H06439E5D742F4388926F3B9B5004EF85"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The duties of the Commission shall be to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H19F7C8ED62EB43D3A7B9FCA15E60FDA5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>use existing water assessments and conduct such additional assessments as may be necessary to project future water supply and demand;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H13B2306EB5244B258B049E77C56CE774"><enum>(2)</enum><text>study current water management programs of Federal, Interstate, State, and local agencies, and private sector entities directed at increasing water supplies and improving the availability, reliability, and quality of freshwater resources; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE48BE9205E254DFB827D928363984E17"><enum>(3)</enum><text>consult with representatives of such agencies and entities to develop recommendations consistent with laws, treaties, decrees, and interstate compacts for a comprehensive water strategy which—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H58E49F0D9F9648A5A49F08E0A37254EA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>respects the primary role of States in adjudicating, administering, and regulating water rights and water uses;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H44239A29FA104582873C47A1071E979B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identifies incentives intended to ensure an adequate and dependable supply of water to meet the needs of the United States for the next 50 years;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF776CC9515EE4B1F9B14282457F1C970"><enum>(C)</enum><text>suggests strategies that avoid increased mandates on State and local governments;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9924C55F8C2B47C6A623695BA0A91CB8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>eliminates duplication and conflict among Federal governmental programs;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7592AB6AE113452E95C179D38CC2D081"><enum>(E)</enum><text>considers all available technologies and other methods to optimize water supply reliability, availability, and quality, while safeguarding the environment;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H67328CB0C9DA4C2FADBBD7245E545681"><enum>(F)</enum><text>recommends means of capturing excess water and flood water for conservation and use in the event of a drought;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4E758C542D854A4DAEE0B49307C6AABB"><enum>(G)</enum><text>suggests financing options for comprehensive water management projects and for appropriate public works projects;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8F1D112E191E45379998D1F980EBE77B"><enum>(H)</enum><text>suggests strategies to conserve existing water supplies, including recommendations for repairing aging infrastructure; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE5E4E9F902B24049A9A9BF5AC446877"><enum>(I)</enum><text>includes other objectives related to the effective management of the water supply to ensure reliability, availability, and quality, which the Commission shall consider appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H170C5C9749C5478DB4BD84714FF01655"><enum>5.</enum><header>Membership</header> 
<subsection id="HA203EA1CE8554A2099E53B98CED08E78"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Number and Appointment</header><text>The Commission shall be composed of 9 members who shall be appointed not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act. Member shall be appointed as follows:</text> 
<paragraph id="H25F6ACDFB396429788587FCAEAA22300"><enum>(1)</enum><text>5 members appointed by the President;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H65898198A1CE419D96D76CB9BC2CDF19"><enum>(2)</enum><text>2 members appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives, in consultation with the minority leader of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H05CAAAA3C28E42099BFDBB45C1C57CFB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>2 members appointed by the majority leader of the Senate, in consultation with the minority leader of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBFF12A2950FC4206ADAD877FE6B0E500"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text>Members shall be appointed to the Commission from among individuals who—</text> 
<paragraph id="H207A70B2B2E442A58DA644F75100F243"><enum>(1)</enum><text>are of recognized standing and distinction in water policy issues; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H581C6CB97DC94854818E3C08A53FEBE3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>while serving on the Commission, do not hold any other position as an officer or employee of the United States, except as a retired officer or retired civilian employee of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD7357BCC43F541690089C8FA95EBD826"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Other Considerations</header><text>In appointing members of the Commission, every effort shall be made to ensure that the members represent a broad cross section of regional and geographical perspectives in the United States.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFC5E764F922C4444A5AF4BBCFAC31130"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Chairperson</header><text>The Chairperson of the Commission shall be designated by the President.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD3C0652F7C7A42638C111069D67EFE4F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Terms</header><text>Members of the Commission shall be appointed not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act and shall serve for the life of the Commission.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H57E71F158EFB4A8CB049413B2BA36819"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>A vacancy on the Commission shall not affect its operation, and shall be filled in the same manner as the original appointment provided under subsection (a).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAAA0D7F302EA4806BC1DC991F114891D"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Compensation and Travel Expenses</header><text>Members of the Commission shall serve without compensation, except members shall receive travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, in accordance with applicable provisions under subchapter I of chapter 57, United States Code.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H9F481DB48C4448F99E6709B428A766FB"><enum>6.</enum><header>Meetings and quorum</header> 
<subsection id="H3C9DFB4356EA4AD4ADE5B9659EDE6CD3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Commission shall hold its first meeting not later than 60 days after the date on which all members have been appointed under section 5, and shall hold additional meetings at the call of the Chairperson or a majority of its members.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H800585A0C6984D91B48325F87572DD82"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A majority of the members of the Commission shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of business.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H78399937CA864F8193E9668B00637B6E"><enum>7.</enum><header>Director and staff</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A Director shall be appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives and the majority leader of the Senate, in consultation with the minority leader and chairmen of the Resources and Transportation and Infrastructure Committees of the House of Representatives, and the minority leader and chairmen of the Energy and Natural Resources and Environment and Public Works Committees of the Senate. The Director and any staff reporting to the Director shall be paid a rate of pay not to exceed the maximum rate of basic pay for GS–15 of the General Schedule.</text></section> 
<section id="HED57E75254B24144A7DA514034A74C39"><enum>8.</enum><header>Powers and proceedings of the Commission</header> 
<subsection id="H99CF28DA10494F6D967C78206132FCA2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Hearings</header><text>The Commission shall hold no fewer than 10 hearings during the life of the Commission. Hearings may be held in conjunction with meetings of the Commission. The Commission may take such testimony and receive such evidence as the Commission considers appropriate to carry out this Act. At least 1 hearing shall be held in Washington, DC, for the purpose of taking testimony of representatives of Federal agencies, national organizations, and Members of Congress. Other hearings shall be scheduled in distinct geographical regions of the United States and should seek to ensure testimony from individuals with a diversity of experiences, including those who work on water issues at all levels of government and in the private sector.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE516DD61C3BC42EBA73300FDFF30C722"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Information and Support From Federal Agencies</header><text>Upon request of the Commission, any Federal agency shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC0770AA2A5274EDB9832E8C99123D785"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide to the Commission, within 30 days of its request, such information as the Commission considers necessary to carry out the provisions of this Act; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H761AF7502BC74F5DB65F89003FA42FFF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>detail to temporary duty with the Commission on a reimbursable basis such personnel as the Commission considers necessary to carry out the provisions of this Act, in accordance with section 5(b)(5), Appendix, title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H89B9703B52F6462391228DFA8FFFF006"><enum>9.</enum><header>Reports</header> 
<subsection id="H7DB66EFA762F43C997EA8757F1F05190"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Interim Reports</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date of the first meeting of the Commission, and every 6 months thereafter, the Commission shall transmit an interim report containing a detailed summary of its progress, including meetings and hearings conducted in the interim period, to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H49DFB7B748F6486483033BBC40906EC5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the President;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE59BF7CDB3544424B4851D59C913075"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Resources and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8786DBE47AA84F99A59F3E01002D7DF4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources and the Committee on the Environment and Public Works of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEE2FE36E32B34EADA4CB771BECBC477"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Final Report</header><text>As soon as practicable, but not later than 3 years after the date of the first meeting of the Commission, the Commission shall transmit a final report containing a detailed statement of the findings and conclusions of the Commission, and recommendations for legislation and other policies to implement such findings and conclusions, to—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA8D19DC926BD4431BB46A75B37C388DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the President;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0780D637ED7C4A80B66093ADD1A68CAD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Resources and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8E13554658674A29A461906FC2F73806"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources and the Committee on the Environment and Public Works of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H0AF9332FF14D43AA9000C0B6B3428BD1"><enum>10.</enum><header>Termination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Commission shall terminate not later than 30 days after the date on which the Commission transmits a final report under section 9(b).</text></section> 
<section id="H33F29279579649AA8228B9B4DA7D3FA3"><enum>11.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated $9,000,000 to carry out this Act.</text></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


