<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HDC34886E42294917883C00ECB2425D00" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 2634 IH: Jubilee Act for Responsible Lending
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-06-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 2634</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20070607">June 7, 2007</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Waters</sponsor> (for
			 herself, <cosponsor name-id="B000013">Mr. Bachus</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M000087">Mrs. Maloney of New York</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="G000535">Mr. Gutierrez</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="P000149">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee</cosponsor>, and
			 <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>) introduced the following
			 bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee
			 on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To provide for greater responsibility in lending and
		  expanded cancellation of debts owed to the United States and the international
		  financial institutions by low-income countries, and for other
		  purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H33C06DE0B8E84BD789C4D5BCCEEA0092" style="OLC">
		<section id="H64A77BAB5A314E29B0444B9829005769" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Jubilee Act for Responsible Lending
			 and Expanded Debt Cancellation of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H2A9827D7AF174228B7C8ED3168EE568C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text>
			<paragraph id="H20D770FBCFB0421784C5F55771AE9D05"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Many low-income
			 countries have been struggling under the burden of international debts for many
			 years.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H7327589D72B248179BED6839F51E1BD0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Since 1996, when
			 the Heavily Indebted Poor Countries Initiative (HIPC) was created, more than 30
			 nations have seen some form of debt relief totaling approximately
			 $80,000,000,000.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H989D079C0FE74CCB9B693139C94130F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Congress has
			 demonstrated its support for bilateral and multilateral debt relief through the
			 enactment of comprehensive debt relief initiatives for heavily indebted
			 low-income countries in—</text>
				<subparagraph id="HD0D901A6956B4CCBB305AEF36C6B03CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>title V of H.R.
			 3425 of the 106th Congress, as enacted into law by section 1000(a)(5) of the
			 Act entitled <quote>An Act making consolidated appropriations for the fiscal
			 year ending September 30, 2000, and for other purposes</quote>, approved
			 November 29, 1999 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/106/113">Public Law 106–113</external-xref>; 113 Stat. 1501–311) and the amendments
			 made by such title;</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEEBE32E3AE254890BA54CFC414AF8C42"><enum>(B)</enum><text>title II of H.R.
			 5526 of the 106th Congress, as enacted into law by section 101(a) of the Act
			 entitled <quote>An Act making appropriations for foreign operations, export
			 financing, and related programs for the fiscal year ending September 30, 2001,
			 and for other purposes</quote>, approved November 6, 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/106/429">Public Law 106–429</external-xref>;
			 114 Stat. 1900A–5); and</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51F67B376ED9402EB9FFF7CF6D07C017"><enum>(C)</enum><text>title V of the
			 United States Leadership Against HIV/AIDS, Tuberculosis, and Malaria Act of
			 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/25">Public Law 108–25</external-xref>; 117 Stat. 747) and the amendment made by such
			 title.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2FC9B02C67B463CB1D656314C11271C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In 2005, the
			 United States and other G–8 nations reached an agreement to provide
			 cancellation of 100 percent of the debts owed by eligible poor nations to Paris
			 Club members, the IMF, the World Bank, and the African Development Bank. The
			 Inter-American Development Bank reached an agreement in early 2007 to provide
			 similar treatment.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HE1B978EB0AF14039B415B49B2146E83C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The 2005 agreement
			 led to the creation of the Multilateral Debt Relief Initiative (MDRI). As of
			 April 2007, 22 nations have seen the majority of their debts to the IMF, World
			 Bank, and African Development Bank cancelled under the terms of the MDRI. In
			 March 2007, the Inter-American Development Bank announced it would provide full
			 debt cancellation to 5 Latin American countries on MDRI terms.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HE77B3FA198F748EB9F968FA5FBED7B3D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Resources released
			 by debt relief efforts to date are reaching the poor. Cameroon is using the
			 $29,800,000 of savings it will gain from the MDRI in 2006 for national poverty
			 reduction priorities, including infrastructure, social sector and governance
			 reforms. Uganda is using its $57,900,000 savings in 2006 on improving energy
			 infrastructure to try to ease acute electricity shortages, as well as primary
			 education, malaria control, healthcare and water infrastructure (specifically
			 targeting the poor and under-served villages). Zambia is using its savings of
			 $23,800,000 under the MDRI in 2006 to increase spending on agricultural
			 projects, such as smallholder irrigation and livestock disease control, as well
			 as to eliminate fees for healthcare in rural areas.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HB168733E8A304CE3B95377487DFBC2D4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>While debt
			 cancellation has a record of success, there remains an unfinished agenda on
			 international debt. There are a number of challenges to the effective
			 implementation of existing commitments, and broader debt cancellation is needed
			 if the global community is to reach the Millennium Development Goals.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HE431C06C51FF47CF93AF7D5901C715D1"><enum>(8)</enum><text>2007 is an
			 important year to address the unfinished agenda on international debt as the
			 global Jubilee debt campaign has declared 2007 a <quote>Sabbath year</quote>, 7
			 years after the historic Jubilee 2000 campaign. 2007 is also the halfway point
			 to the deadline set by the world’s governments to reach the Millennium
			 Development Goals.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HF2786C76F28A4266A733D2734D79A1E"><enum>(9)</enum><text>A
			 critical issue which needs to be addressed on debt is the way that
			 non-concessional lenders stand to gain financially from lending to poor
			 countries that have benefited from debt relief without having paid for past
			 debt relief or facing the prospect of paying for the future relief of
			 unsustainable and irresponsible new lending. In these cases, the gains of debt
			 relief for poor debtor countries are at risk of being eroded. This takes the
			 form of new lending to countries that have received debt cancellation from
			 countries including China, as well as the threat posed by so-called
			 <quote>vulture funds</quote>.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H3F27DA4D05DE40028C5C6F22F6D3AC80"><enum>(10)</enum><text>It is also
			 essential that all lenders and borrowers accept co-responsibility and learn
			 from past mistakes–as evidenced by the debt crisis itself–by making more
			 productive investment choices and engaging in more responsible lending and
			 borrowing in the future. In October 2006, Norway became the first creditor to
			 accept co-responsibility for past lending mistakes and cancelled the debt of 5
			 nations on the grounds that the loans reflected poor development policy.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HB7B8FF787DE24E9FA8F7A9A7CC44957"><enum>(11)</enum><text>A
			 growing number of governments and intergovernmental bodies, including the
			 United Kingdom, the European Commission, and Norway, are raising concerns about
			 the harmful impacts of economic policy conditionality. Many impoverished
			 countries that have received debt cancellation under the HIPC and MDRI
			 initiatives have done so at a high social cost, because they have had to
			 implement economic policy conditions such as privatization of public utilities
			 and other basic services, adhere to budget ceilings imposed by the IMF, and
			 comply with other harmful requirements. Some of these policies have had the
			 effect of limiting fiscal space and making it more difficult for countries to
			 meet the Millennium Development Goals. Several countries currently eligible for
			 debt cancellation under the HIPC or MDRI programs are facing extended delays in
			 receiving cancellation because they are struggling to comply with such
			 requirements from the IMF and World Bank.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H7234AF2FE9504F5D85088166F2276956"><enum>(12)</enum><text>There is also an
			 urgent need to look beyond the constraints of current debt relief initiatives
			 to address the need for expanded debt cancellation. The current initiatives
			 allow countries to qualify for relief based on economic criteria rather than
			 human needs. A January 2007 report by the United Nations Human Rights Council
			 found that eligibility for debt cancellation should be expanded to cover all
			 low-income countries.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H725677A5DB7440FCAA17E5755B79F0F0"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The government of
			 the United Kingdom has proposed that qualification for the MDRI be extended to
			 the 67 nations which qualify for assistance exclusively from the International
			 Development Association. To be eligible for cancellation, countries must meet
			 requirements pertaining to public financial management, anti-corruption
			 measures, and budget transparency.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H9F1FEF9A9CD342B99CD0571E8B83E12C"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Debt cancellation
			 is an essential component of the United States development assistance strategy
			 and a required component to facilitate achievement of the Millennium
			 Development Goals.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H3564A31B53D34FF5BE7E1352F2A39CC"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The United States
			 has been a leader in supporting debt relief efforts to date and should continue
			 to work to improve and expand initiatives in this area.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H71F2786EDB3B4CAFA63636DA00028597"><enum>3.</enum><header>Cancellation of
			 debt owed by eligible low-income countries</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title XVI of the International Financial
			 Institutions Act (22 U.S.C. 262p—262p–8) is amended by adding at the end the
			 following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC4A9CAA741664A7BAF3E8931C06472A4" style="OLC">
				<section id="HA6716F0A8BA74160B6B0933081F8AA26"><enum>1626.</enum><header>Cancellation
				of debt owed by eligible low-income countries</header>
					<subsection id="H411BEB5BF7C6437800FE5F0022AA7C00"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall commence immediate
				efforts, within the Paris Club of Official Creditors, the International
				Monetary Fund (IMF), the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development
				(World Bank), and the other international financial institutions (as defined in
				section 1701(c)(2)), to accomplish the following:</text>
						<paragraph id="HE6B77567FD1241259D8700FDE7432879"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Cancellation by
				each international financial institution of all debts owed to the institution
				by eligible low-income countries, and, to the extent possible, financing the
				debt cancellation from the ongoing operations, procedures, and accounts of the
				institution.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="HC6BBC322D9D04BED94E4B1A7626BF8FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Cancellation by
				the United States of all debts owed to it by eligible low-income
				countries.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="HD3A2D8B2D76A42A289F617F8E800DD09"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Ensuring that any
				waiting period for the enhanced debt cancellation is not excessive.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H0CDDB599ECB644F083181D791C4B507F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Requiring the
				government of each eligible low-income country to—</text>
							<subparagraph id="H28459B4A41AA40F69194CC93B870E349"><enum>(A)</enum><text>allocate the
				savings from debt cancellation towards poverty-reducing expenditures;</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75BF494CFAB841E1A774344BCD17CB00"><enum>(B)</enum><text>engage interested
				parties, including a broad cross-section of civil society groups, in the
				allocation determination process; and</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75830FD1008D4D4EA82F2FABB9A32613"><enum>(C)</enum><text>produce an annual
				report disclosing how the savings from debt cancellation were used, and make
				the report publicly available and easily accessible to all interested parties,
				including civil society groups and the media.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB41B024C66534A0CB5BAA4704339A665"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ensuring that the provision of debt
				cancellation to eligible low-income countries is not followed by a reduction in
				the provision of any other development assistance to the countries by
				international financial institutions and bilateral creditors.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="HF6C8CCEAE30748389644D4159CB4FE6E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Encouraging the
				government of each eligible low-income country to allocate at least 20 percent
				of its national budget towards poverty-alleviation programs such as the
				provision of basic health care services, education services, and clean water
				services to all individuals in the country.</text>
						</paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5D6CBBEE9C654EC4AD2F9D3022A5C7A4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of
				framework for creditor transparency</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury
				shall commence immediate efforts, within the Paris Club of Official Creditors,
				the International Monetary Fund, the World Bank, and the other international
				financial institutions (as so defined), to ensure that each of the
				institutions—</text>
						<paragraph id="H802C80E3935A49238F7F19004E7FDA48"><enum>(1)</enum><text>continues to make
				efforts to promote greater transparency regarding the activities of the
				institution, including credit, grant, guarantee, and technical assistance
				operations, following a policy of maximum disclosure; and</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H4387AF4072A94F5CAC3EC8E4B6A881E7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>supports continued
				efforts to allow informed participation and input by affected communities,
				including translation of information on proposed projects, provision of
				information (including draft documents) through information technology
				application, oral briefings, and outreach to and dialogue with community
				organizations and institutions in affected areas.</text>
						</paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F98EC7717C64F990000A0D5564C907F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Establishment of
				framework for responsible lending</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury
				shall commence immediate efforts to—</text>
						<paragraph id="HB6290A65414644E7B6784000699B8DD1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop and
				promote policies to ensure all creditors, with no distinction, will contribute
				to preserving the gains of debt relief for low-income debtor countries;</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H6D31A3CD7C574E5D9B96B3776BC5BDEF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>collaborate with
				appropriate government agencies to prevent private investors from profiting
				from buying low-income country debts at market value and attempting to recover
				their original value or more (commonly known as <quote>vulture funds</quote>),
				including by—</text>
							<subparagraph id="H3945123CB390453EA969B9A249A948CB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>designing legal
				remedies to curtail or realign the incentives for this activity;</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC925C258D9AF4E20B5DD64F49043A94D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identifying
				avenues to provide legal support to countries being sued by <quote>vulture
				funds</quote>; and</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED49EE534E9A42228B2C4C6487D25D24"><enum>(C)</enum><text>providing
				technical assistance to advise possible targeted governments on measures to
				take to prevent <quote>vulture funds</quote> from successfully taking them to
				court;</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H568F6B144B2A4569B65C5E843D73005C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide that the
				external financing needs of low-income countries are met primarily through
				grant financing rather than new lending;</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H97293D189DB742BCB7776911A4BF5935"><enum>(4)</enum><text>seek the
				international adoption of a binding legal framework that—</text>
							<subparagraph id="HDD2355D69B7C443289425981E0226111"><enum>(A)</enum><text>guarantees that no
				creditor can take or expect to take financial advantage of acquired or newly
				awarded debt relief through the terms and rates of their new lending to
				beneficiary countries;</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD068D6E28DE04AD99EEA0092469231DE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is binding on all
				creditors, whether multilateral, bilateral or private;</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD7E8C6C50AB408D9B99AEBEA4F3377"><enum>(C)</enum><text>foresees, as a
				sanction for creditors who violate it, an equitable share in the burden of the
				losses from any future debt relief needed by the sovereign debtor to whom
				lending was irresponsibly provided;</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H130E456ED6F2480391627E11ABD88828"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provides for
				decisions on irresponsible lending to be made by an entity independent from the
				creditors; and</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10EDE54342EC4E1C9B3500FBDE22C2D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>enables fair
				opportunities for the people of the affected country to be heard; and</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA33741B8BF404D40B600F12400BC700"><enum>(5)</enum><text>support the
				development of responsible financing standards where creditors and aid/loan
				recipients alike adhere to standards to assure transparency and accountability
				to citizens, human rights, and the avoidance of new odious debt, while
				encouraging the development of renewable energy and helping countries to
				transition away from dependence on oil.</text>
						</paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H862D4A77D2094724AEFD3D83BBE2CC66"><enum>(d)</enum><header>GAO audit of
				debt portfolios of countries with questionable loans</header>
						<paragraph id="H9D6240ED44234805A705FF0020407959"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall
				undertake an audit of the debt portfolios of previous governments in countries
				such as the Democratic Republic of Congo and South Africa, where there is
				significant evidence that odious, onerous, or illegal loans were made to the
				government. Each such audit shall—</text>
							<subparagraph id="H7D6C9285ACDB419BAE6BA37C15A1A975"><enum>(A)</enum><text>consider debt owed
				to the World Bank, the IMF, and the other international financial institutions
				(as so defined), export credit debts owed to governments, and debts owed to
				commercial creditors, and assess whether or not past investments produced the
				intended results;</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB804C41E74B14E2387CBB1A541A9EA70"><enum>(B)</enum><text>investigate the
				process by which the loans were contracted, how the funds were used, and
				determine whether United States or international laws were violated in the
				contraction of these loans, and whether any of the loans were odious or
				onerous; and</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD2C215E912A4821BF9CB3761D20C2B1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>be planned and
				executed in a transparent and consultative manner, engaging congressional
				bodies and civil society groups in the countries.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H84D24D52165548B188ACB98B7D86149E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 2 years after the date of the
				enactment of this section, the Comptroller General of the United States shall
				prepare and submit to the Committees on Financial Services and on Foreign
				Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committees on Banking, Housing,
				and Urban Affairs and on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report that contains
				the results of the audits undertaken under paragraph (1).</text>
						</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2B92379269234A859346C0ACD5FFA817"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Availability on
				treasury department website of remarks of united states executive directors at
				meetings of international financial institutions’ boards of
				directors</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall make available on
				the website of the Department of the Treasury the full record of the remarks of
				the United States Executive Director at meetings of the boards of directors of
				the International Monetary Fund, the World Bank, and the other international
				financial institutions (as so defined), about cancellation or reduction of
				debts owed to the institution involved, with redaction by the Secretary of the
				Treasury of material deemed too sensitive for public distribution, but showing
				the topic, amount of material redacted, and reason for the redaction.</text>
					</subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF3E07EA4F78D4ADC92283771385E1745"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report from the
				comptroller general</header><text>Within 1 year after the date of the enactment
				of this section, the Comptroller General of the United States shall prepare and
				submit to the Committees on Financial Services and on Foreign Affairs of the
				House of Representatives and the Committees on Banking, Housing, and Urban
				Affairs and on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on the availability of
				the ongoing operations, procedures, and accounts of the IMF, the World Bank,
				and the other international financial institutions (as so defined) for
				canceling the debt of eligible low-income countries.</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="HF97FC4DDF5624893AC879E3D63AD007E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Annual reports
				from the president</header><text>Not later than December 31 of each year, the
				President shall submit to the Committees on Financial Services and on Foreign
				Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committees on Foreign Relations
				and on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate a report, which shall
				be made available to the public, on the activities undertaken under this
				section, and other progress made in accomplishing the purposes of this section,
				for the prior fiscal year. The report shall include a list of the countries
				that have received debt cancellation, a list of the countries whose request for
				debt cancellation has been denied and the reasons therefor, and a list of the
				countries whose requests for debt cancellation are under consideration.</text>
					</subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H44B1AF5AFBB84A4B9F4CD5DEE4C9046"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Eligible
				low-income country defined</header><text>In this section, the term
				<term>eligible low-income country</term> means a country—</text>
						<paragraph id="HE55A18059ED546D2841F8D695FE83C7D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>that is eligible
				for financing from the International Development Association but not the World
				Bank;</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H341C38827D7A424B9B00FF3475C40999"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that has
				transparent and effective budget execution and public financial management
				systems which ensure that the savings from debt relief are spent on reducing
				poverty; and</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H0835002EA91B4147AC04872E19D1D685"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the government of
				which does not have an excessive level of military expenditures;</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H9FF5FD2AE3F34711BFAB91239CE9007D"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the government of which has not repeatedly
				provided support for acts of international terrorism, as determined by the
				Secretary of State under section 6(j)(1) of the Export Administration Act of
				1979 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/50/2405">50 U.S.C. App. 2405(j)(1)</external-xref>), or section 620A(a) of the Foreign Assistance
				Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2371">22 U.S.C. 2371(a)</external-xref>);</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H9A6281C17051401ABEF6BA8E8B57DC00"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the government of which is cooperating on
				international narcotics control matters; and</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H4334AE46133248F18BD0337CABF621B2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the government of
				which (including its military or other security forces) does not engage in a
				consistent pattern of gross violations of internationally recognized human
				rights.</text>
						</paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="H6635708ED3CF49979BFF471152AD68E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibition of
			 harmful economic and policy conditions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title XVI of the International Financial
			 Institutions Act (22 U.S.C. 262p—262p–8) is further amended by adding at the
			 end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block id="HB4D366C6C03C4D798F5487F4C7E45290" style="OLC">
				<section id="H5C666D95CE0B4DDBAA86714198C0D379"><enum>1627.</enum><header>Prohibition of
				harmful economic and policy conditions</header>
					<subsection id="H8C3801D5E5594E57B69DF75B95DC6B51"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the
				Treasury shall commence immediate efforts within the Paris Club of Official
				Creditors, the International Monetary Fund (IMF), the International Bank for
				Reconstruction and Development (World Bank), and the other international
				financial institutions (as defined in section 1701(c)(2)), to ensure that the
				provision of debt cancellation to eligible low-income countries (as defined in
				section 1626(h)) is not conditioned on any agreement by such a country to
				implement or comply with policies that deepen poverty or degrade the
				environment, including any policy that—</text>
						<paragraph id="H4A31D8AFFB8B4136A8BDB477EAC7AC39"><enum>(1)</enum><text>implements or
				extends user fees on primary education or primary health care, including
				prevention and treatment efforts for HIV/AIDS, tuberculosis, malaria, and
				infant, child, and maternal well-being;</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="HD589CE9090E440A1B9EAF2352C64B607"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides for
				increased cost recovery from low-income people to finance basic public services
				such as education, health care, or sanitation;</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="HCB734647C0924C22B9A8FD00A03206DD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>would have the
				effect of increasing the cost to consumers with incomes of less than $2 per day
				of access to clean drinking water through—</text>
							<subparagraph id="H295C371C9F0C432EA878B1D8F0F0EB4D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>decreased public
				subsidies for water supply, treatment, disposal, distribution, or
				management;</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50A38809D8E24C9495E9AEEE5381CFBA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>reduced
				intrasectoral or intersectoral subsidization of residential water consumers
				with incomes of less than $2 per day;</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09F52CA1BA7F440E9EC171FE55453BBC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>reduced government
				ability to regulate; or</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA391DF0FDF748698F7D00FF24545CD5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>mandated
				privatization of water resources;</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF65A4BFDD704C58BB00371B5B37EF50"><enum>(4)</enum><text>undermines
				workers’ ability to exercise effectively their internationally recognized
				worker rights, as defined under section 526(e) of the Foreign Operations,
				Export Financing and Related Programs Appropriations Act, 1995 (22 U.S.C.
				262p–4p); or</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H7EB58256768148E3B018C4352C71A190"><enum>(5)</enum><text>does not exempt
				increased government spending on essential healthcare or education expenditures
				from national budget caps or restraints, hiring or wage bill ceilings, or other
				limits imposed by the IMF.</text>
						</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBBFD09DD3C88434C00663809008BAA8E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual reports
				to the congress</header><text>Not later than December 31 of each year, the
				President shall submit to the Committees on Financial Services and on
				International Relations of the House of Representatives and the Committees on
				Foreign Relations and on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate a
				report, which shall be made available to the public, on the activities
				undertaken under this section, and other progress made in accomplishing the
				purposes of this section, for the prior fiscal
				year.</text>
					</subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body>
</bill>


