<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB0ACA2F275354DD0B55829AF60FB4712" public-private="public" stage-count="1"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">112th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 2021</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Clean Air Act regarding air pollution from Outer Continental Shelf activities.<pagebreak/></official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HC2C16872212B45EEA436705391D74D1A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4B61B50A4E184DD482394C978C147A45" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Jobs and Energy Permitting Act of 2011</short-title></quote>.</text> </section>
<section id="H0465210DA037405DADE37D70B2E891D1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Air quality measurement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 328(a)(1) of the Clean Air Act (42 U.S.C. 7627(a)(1)) is amended by inserting before the period at the end of the second sentence the following: <quote>, except that any air quality impact of any OCS source shall be measured or modeled, as appropriate, and determined solely with respect to the impacts in the corresponding onshore area</quote>.</text> </section>
<section id="H1C00DE4BCA0343E79E69554C92EB037B"><enum>3.</enum><header>OCS source</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 328(a)(4)(C) of the Clean Air Act (42 U.S.C. 7627(a)(4)(C)) is amended in the matter following clause (iii) by striking <quote>shall be considered direct emissions from the OCS source</quote> and inserting <quote>shall be considered direct emissions from the OCS source but shall not be subject to any emission control requirement applicable to the source under subpart 1 of part C of title I of this Act. For platform or drill ship exploration, an OCS source is established at the point in time when drilling commences at a location and ceases to exist when drilling activity ends at such location or is temporarily interrupted because the platform or drill ship relocates for weather or other reasons.</quote>.</text> </section>
<section id="H86D47B5BC5A747F09E57266D59360A7B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Permits</header> 
<subsection id="HD70659423F7A47979B29771BDDF50987"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Permits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 328 of the Clean Air Act (42 U.S.C. 7627) is amended by adding at the end thereof the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4B12A500C7594B9080CB7E552A0C2796" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H0E13F57D47AE4DFF9F5A67649CFCB863"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Permit application</header><text>In the case of a completed application for a permit under this Act for platform or drill ship exploration for an OCS source—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBBF5B784955A482CA8641E70C40FD229"><enum>(1)</enum><text>final agency action (including any reconsideration of the issuance or denial of such permit) shall be taken not later than 6 months after the date of filing such completed application;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1F25BB59A8754E3681F3F440D52F0A1D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Environmental Appeals Board of the Environmental Protection Agency shall have no authority to consider any matter regarding the consideration, issuance, or denial of such permit;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H66879D11F1E94A84B0CC46D2EF92F465"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no administrative stay of the effectiveness of such permit may extend beyond the date that is 6 months after the date of filing such completed application;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H55B7392B381A487599528C87CADAA366"><enum>(4)</enum><text>such final agency action shall be considered to be nationally applicable under section 307(b); and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCE222A7533BE491B8C1A63DA98EDB1FF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>judicial review of such final agency action shall be available only in accordance with such section 307(b) without additional administrative review or adjudication.</text> </paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection>
<subsection id="HAED3F715D0AE42B2894A40506A4B6D85"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 328(a)(4) of the Clean Air Act (42 U.S.C. 7627(a)(4)) is amended by striking <quote>For purposes of subsections (a) and (b)</quote> and inserting <quote>For purposes of subsections (a), (b), and (d)</quote>.</text> </subsection></section>
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20110622" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives June 22, 2011.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Karen L. Haas,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 
