<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCC994C57B0F14559A2DBB7B3395497D" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>109 HR 1185 IH: Federal Deposit Insurance Reform Act of 2005</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2005-03-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>109th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 1185</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20050309">March 9, 2005</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000013">Mr. Bachus</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="H000762">Ms. Hooley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000163">Mr. Oxley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000339">Mr. Frank of Massachusetts</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000210">Mr. Gillmor</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000008">Mr. Kanjorski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000555">Ms. Pryce of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000169">Mr. Leach</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000087">Mrs. Maloney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000255">Mr. Jones of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001140">Mr. Moore of Kansas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000566">Mr. Ryun of Kansas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000057">Mr. Israel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000081">Mr. Ney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000462">Mr. Tiberi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001232">Mrs. Biggert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000535">Mr. Gutierrez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000602">Mr. Davis of Alabama</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000636">Mr. Hinojosa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000210">Mr. King of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000309">Mrs. McCarthy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000553">Mr. LaTourette</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001138">Mr. Manzullo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000182">Mr. Neugebauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000262">Mr. Ford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000326">Mr. Towns</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000574">Mr. Renzi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001049">Mr. Clay</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001139">Mr. Gary G. Miller of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001156">Mr. McHenry</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B000208">Mr. Bartlett of Maryland</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To reform the Federal deposit insurance system, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H08A9C9D30DEF483992A9007E006E463D" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HADA109DD4A8C466996F1E0A0AF634764" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header> 
<subsection id="HE46C0358C6FF43659B64F0A5E66EDDE9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Deposit Insurance Reform Act of 2005</short-title></quote>. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H03AEA15DDD5849D1A4FCAE7FC4D6965E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text> 
<toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 2. Merging the BIF and SAIF</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 3. Increase in deposit insurance coverage</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 4. Setting assessments and repeal of special rules relating to minimum assessments and free deposit insurance</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 5. Replacement of fixed designated reserve ratio with reserve range</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 6. Requirements applicable to the risk-based assessment system</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 7. Refunds, dividends, and credits from Deposit Insurance Fund</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 8. Deposit Insurance Fund restoration plans</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 9. Regulations required</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 10. Studies of FDIC structure and expenses and certain activities and further possible changes to deposit insurance system</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 11. Bi-annual FDIC survey and report on increasing the deposit base by encouraging use of depository institutions by the unbanked</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 12. Technical and conforming amendments to the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> relating to the merger of the BIF and SAIF</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 13. Other technical and conforming amendments relating to the merger of the BIF and SAIF</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section> 
<section id="H0AA7C53DE5524746929E5DB1136995A0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Merging the BIF and SAIF</header> 
<subsection id="HF93FE8C3F7D64A5EA8ADC8BAAD89734"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> 
<paragraph id="H9453F297EE584D669430255CED26A445"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Merger</header><text>The Bank Insurance Fund and the Savings Association Insurance Fund shall be merged into the Deposit Insurance Fund.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC7621BC100264CFD8C00807ED36BAFAB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disposition of assets and liabilities</header><text>All assets and liabilities of the Bank Insurance Fund and the Savings Association Insurance Fund shall be transferred to the Deposit Insurance Fund.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H704E45058B924C2DBE4752CD82E89F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>No separate existence</header><text>The separate existence of the Bank Insurance Fund and the Savings Association Insurance Fund shall cease on the effective date of the merger thereof under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA0895970D2A54D7AA4FC336F33EB1FE7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Repeal of outdated merger provision</header><text>Section 2704 of the <act-name parsable-cite="DIFA96">Deposit Insurance Funds Act of 1996</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821">12 U.S.C. 1821</external-xref> note) is repealed.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H46C0B08E843D4D32B38814EC3A4A9A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section shall take effect on the first day of the first calendar quarter that begins after the end of the 90-day period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H5181AF2A352E4B8BB7DD254E981EA690"><enum>3.</enum><header>Increase in deposit insurance coverage</header> 
<subsection id="H04F8CED0165D485580816F839420CE36"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 11(a)(1) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821">12 U.S.C. 1821(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9DBFBB59C80F4D999700408898B79DAD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (B) and inserting the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H63F75AFC5F064FABB4E8F29240DEF380"> 
<subparagraph id="HE388E848E2694342B5A56B44A3EA7FB6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Net amount of insured deposit</header><text>The net amount due to any depositor at an insured depository institution shall not exceed the standard maximum deposit insurance amount as determined in accordance with subparagraphs (C), (D), (E) and (F) and paragraph (3).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA0E5DD530DAB4763BB0031E42FD905B7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraphs:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HD0C9B9CF519A49AEB997E2EC95AB5BBA"> 
<subparagraph id="HFA54D0215220425299B88656F7DBB01F"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Standard maximum deposit insurance amount defined</header><text>For purposes of this Act, the term <term>standard maximum deposit insurance amount</term> means—</text> 
<clause id="HF0F9387F722B42508C553BFB6D58ECD7"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">until the effective date of final regulations prescribed pursuant to section 9(a)(2) of the <short-title>Federal Deposit Insurance Reform Act of 2005</short-title>, $100,000; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF51BE4EDB182407383F0FD808F6BD69F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>on and after such effective date, $130,000, adjusted as provided under subparagraph (F).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5BB8F7F3610B44B2BCBE847328B7012C"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Inflation adjustment</header> 
<clause id="HEDFBE9F52A9B4D2D8FCB78645F86307F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>By April 1 of 2007, and the 1st day of each subsequent 5-year period, the Board of Directors and the National Credit Union Administration Board shall jointly prescribe the amount by which the standard maximum deposit insurance amount and the standard maximum share insurance amount (as defined in section 207(k) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FCUA">Federal Credit Union Act</act-name>) applicable to any depositor at an insured depository institution shall be increased by calculating the product of—</text> 
<subclause id="HD22F28ED4046420FB2ABEFA6692C80AF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>$130,000; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H29CBFAB9E1F345B88F52DDD015E65CFD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the ratio of the value of the Personal Consumption Expenditures Chain-Type Index (or any successor index thereto), published by the Department of Commerce, as of December 31 of the year preceding the year in which the adjustment is calculated under this clause, to the value of such index as of the date this subparagraph takes effect.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H3CF1B09E5AA14BD7BE66BB6E4E268D62"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Rounding</header><text>If the amount determined under clause (ii) for any period is not a multiple of $10,000, the amount so determined shall be rounded to the nearest $10,000.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD7E0E0679DB241218C4B3EA4B32D5C8"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Publication and report to the Congress</header><text>Not later than April 5 of any calendar year in which an adjustment is required to be calculated under clause (i) to the standard maximum deposit insurance amount and the standard maximum share insurance amount under such clause, the Board of Directors and the National Credit Union Administration Board shall—</text> 
<subclause id="H492AEF63A9A84ABC953C7F8166CBFB4E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>publish in the Federal Register the standard maximum deposit insurance amount, the standard maximum share insurance amount, and the amount of coverage under paragraph (3)(A) and section 207(k)(3) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FCUA">Federal Credit Union Act</act-name>, as so calculated; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HAF2B23BB216946798D9B39BA2E15B580"><enum>(II)</enum><text>jointly submit a report to the Congress containing the amounts described in subclause (I).</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HA8690824D66E498EAC2D39E95CD16EBF"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>6-month implementation period</header><text>Unless an Act of Congress enacted before July 1 of the calendar year in which an adjustment is required to be calculated under clause (i) provides otherwise, the increase in the standard maximum deposit insurance amount and the standard maximum share insurance amount shall take effect on January 1 of the year immediately succeeding such calendar year.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3D5CA585DEF14F2D973EE0A506261FF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coverage for certain employee benefit plan deposits</header><text>Section 11(a)(1)(D) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821">12 U.S.C. 1821(a)(1)(D)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="Federal Deposit Insurance Act" id="H42A0DA7B764240D3ACA57CA2C39CA7CB"> 
<subparagraph id="H517E3B056208440CACC2E9371FABB0AF"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Coverage for certain employee benefit plan deposits</header> 
<clause id="H4CA73CD55B1D407CBE00DAC75846705C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Pass-through insurance</header><text>The Corporation shall provide pass-through deposit insurance for the deposits of any employee benefit plan.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5307CC6BC9DD432CA18772E4AE2657B8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Prohibition on acceptance of benefit plan deposits</header><text>An insured depository institution that is not well capitalized or adequately capitalized may not accept employee benefit plan deposits.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7A89ED2D5E0E47AA9189C3007B26ECCE"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the following definitions shall apply:</text> 
<subclause id="H60898BF5574947978D46884E385094FF"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Capital standards</header><text>The terms <term>well capitalized</term> and <term>adequately capitalized</term> have the same meanings as in section 38.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H93F3057730674735B27BA069F419EBF6"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Employee benefit plan</header><text>The term <term>employee benefit plan</term> has the same meaning as in paragraph (8)(B)(ii), and includes any eligible deferred compensation plan described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/457">section 457</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3720B87BAFBD43D1929761B80047E579"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Pass-through deposit insurance</header><text>The term <term>pass-through deposit insurance</term> means, with respect to an employee benefit plan, deposit insurance coverage provided on a pro rata basis to the participants in the plan, in accordance with the interest of each participant.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H728F27851DB640CCA2A2563FFE73F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Doubling of deposit insurance for certain retirement accounts</header><text>Section 11(a)(3)(A) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821">12 U.S.C. 1821(a)(3)(A)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>$100,000</quote> and inserting <quote>2 times the standard maximum deposit insurance amount (as determined under paragraph (1))</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5B4FE1E6409C4F6BAEEB9CA4BFD93098"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Increased insurance coverage for municipal deposits</header><text>Section 11(a)(2) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821">12 U.S.C. 1821(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H20AA42B8349542FF9D6BBD690087FB99"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6941756F76474C1EBDC422F7A8093424"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by moving the margins of clauses (i) through (v) 4 ems to the right;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H33AAF715C8AA4D4C99543D0089D56109"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking, in the matter following clause (v), <quote>such depositor shall</quote> and all that follows through the period; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H099D8BE3EC874E35BC82DEC1F169EC81"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking the semicolon at the end of clause (v) and inserting a period;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6240A8362971497295E3847D5E88E1E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(2)(A) Notwithstanding</quote> and all that follows through <quote>a depositor who is—</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HB7CD9F91B5344A429CD7783902E7D2FF"> 
<paragraph id="HDA01F96146064FF789A8B0643C08366B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Municipal depositors</header> 
<subparagraph id="HA95E87839C9347A796524EFA2E176535"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any limitation in this Act or in any other provision of law relating to the amount of deposit insurance available to any 1 depositor—</text> 
<clause id="H5187DC109E9341AD825816D75DA8CD16"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a municipal depositor shall, for the purpose of determining the amount of insured deposits under this subsection, be deemed to be a depositor separate and distinct from any other officer, employee, or agent of the United States or any public unit referred to in subparagraph (E); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H99BC0C3BCBFA477395C6DC53BE38DB73"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>except as provided in subparagraph (B), the deposits of a municipal depositor shall be insured in an amount equal to the standard maximum deposit insurance amount (as determined under paragraph (1)).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H74EE3D712384457F9E9F1FC670F7EAD3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>In-state municipal depositors</header><text>In the case of the deposits of an in-State municipal depositor described in clause (ii), (iii), (iv), or (v) of subparagraph (E) at an insured depository institution, such deposits shall be insured in an amount not to exceed the lesser of—</text> 
<clause id="H00AD465F0E5A49C09909F7A0045962E2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>$2,000,000; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H51868CEA6F854EAA9602159EF6BBD7AB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the sum of the standard maximum deposit insurance amount and 80 percent of the amount of any deposits in excess of the standard maximum deposit insurance amount.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H99F2322D42F2433A8EDB1B283955A92B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Municipal deposit parity</header><text>No State may deny to insured depository institutions within its jurisdiction the authority to accept deposits insured under this paragraph, or prohibit the making of such deposits in such institutions by any in-State municipal depositor.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H974DAA298A5E4689BCB375B9277FFCAD"><enum>(D)</enum><header>In-state municipal depositor defined</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>in-State municipal depositor</term> means a municipal depositor that is located in the same State as the office or branch of the insured depository institution at which the deposits of that depositor are held.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD18665A6AB8747A3B08D9BEC5B665300"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Municipal depositor</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>municipal depositor</term> means a depositor that is—</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H218B338008AB4E9DB8727C97AC9CCA5D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(B) The</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HB3B4D0FA9CBA427700BD151839BED550"> 
<subparagraph id="H26788D17BD3C4547849E6DEA54C27D42"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Authority to limit deposits</header><text>The</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H60C3490DB8B3427FBEAD0931CBF81299"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by striking <quote>depositor referred to in subparagraph (A) of this paragraph</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>municipal depositor</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA668858A8B864335851D6EAD2E977F3F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment relating to insurance of trust funds</header><text>Paragraphs (1) and (3) of section 7(i) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(i)</external-xref>) are each amended by striking <quote>$100,000</quote> and inserting <quote>the standard maximum deposit insurance amount (as determined under section 11(a)(1))</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCB90F45BC1DC407C00F66D3D01A34EA0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Other technical and conforming amendments</header> 
<paragraph id="H26E69CB0F0734DE7960022E5DB8552F7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Section 11(m)(6) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821">12 U.S.C. 1821(m)(6)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>$100,000</quote> and inserting <quote>an amount equal to the standard maximum deposit insurance amount</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5257D04EB12D40ED9FB46790D7FE3325"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Subsection (a) of section 18 of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1828">12 U.S.C. 1828(a)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="Federal Deposit Insurance Act" id="HE9EA4E521DFE411E9D20F705273C2070"> 
<subsection id="HDC192ADCE9AF4B3D97ACFC1BED04EBCA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Insurance logo</header> 
<paragraph id="HAD88CD283FDC470195EFB323F45068D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Insured depository institutions</header> 
<subparagraph id="H9A8927B5EF394D7300EB950080A05CE5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each insured depository institution shall display at each place of business maintained by that institution a sign or signs relating to the insurance of the deposits of the institution, in accordance with regulations to be prescribed by the Corporation.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB624E6D7C97749129C180100FB144CC3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Statement to be included</header><text>Each sign required under subparagraph (A) shall include a statement that insured deposits are backed by the full faith and credit of the United States Government.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H69356B30D35743A7BFE3922178143C7D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Corporation shall prescribe regulations to carry out this subsection, including regulations governing the substance of signs required by paragraph (1) and the manner of display or use of such signs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC181E3388B4843C682B38FF1265003E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>For each day that an insured depository institution continues to violate this subsection or any regulation issued under this subsection, it shall be subject to a penalty of not more than $100, which the Corporation may recover for its use.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1471438F8A694C39824F14DBE2823C92"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Section 43(d) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1831t">12 U.S.C. 1831t(d)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>$100,000</quote> and inserting <quote>an amount equal to the standard maximum deposit insurance amount</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCE88E3D28FAF4E160041A611B0C80097"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Section 6 of the <act-name parsable-cite="IBA78">International Banking Act of 1978</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3104">12 U.S.C. 3104</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA37E8D15B3E84069B63789E50086AEF4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>$100,000</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>an amount equal to the standard maximum deposit insurance amount</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4265AAA286D94DE8A2093E56BEC506DE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HAA4C6257B6704ED08DF8516297BFB341"> 
<subsection id="HCDBFBA71EE6649FE857469DF60867763"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Standard maximum deposit insurance amount defined</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>standard maximum deposit insurance amount</term> means the amount of the maximum amount of deposit insurance as determined under section 11(a)(1) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name>.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD5B7A7AFC5364493A25FB600E2F07406"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Conforming change to credit union share insurance Fund</header> 
<paragraph id="H5CFA71BC5C614734A2F13DE99D493484"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 207(k) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FCUA">Federal Credit Union Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1787">12 U.S.C. 1787(k)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB81813CC6AF34D4FBE05B8575CFDB1AE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(k)(1)</quote> and all that follows through the end of paragraph (1) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H9CDA9FE5789E460EAC017925BBF88CE"> 
<subsection id="H2955D13435B54545A2375E41EC90D5D2"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Insured amounts payable</header> 
<paragraph id="HE74F3BE4AEE2433B886170124CDCA993"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Net insured amount</header> 
<subparagraph id="H2765A42443A44816AFDE220030BC55A9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the provisions of paragraph (2), the net amount of share insurance payable to any member at an insured credit union shall not exceed the total amount of the shares or deposits in the name of the member (after deducting offsets), less any part thereof which is in excess of the standard maximum share insurance amount, as determined in accordance with this paragraph and paragraphs (5) and (6), and consistently with actions taken by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation under section 11(a) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name>.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEB9AA3E14D024FA8B307C005331C3CC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Aggregation</header><text>Determination of the net amount of share insurance under subparagraph (A), shall be in accordance with such regulations as the Board may prescribe, and, in determining the amount payable to any member, there shall be added together all accounts in the credit union maintained by that member for that member’s own benefit, either in the member’s own name or in the names of others.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEC4AA75C34A14D9F8D872D653C2B6BCB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Authority to define the extent of coverage</header><text>The Board may define, with such classifications and exceptions as it may prescribe, the extent of the share insurance coverage provided for member accounts, including member accounts in the name of a minor, in trust, or in joint tenancy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H35C89C81F432436B89C347790095023E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> 
<clause id="H58EC387E69CB49DA93C0D9ABCD976397"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text> 
<subclause id="HEA5B0D35DABD408F8780C8C8188871C5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clauses (i) through (v), by moving the margins 4 ems to the right;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H51246FE91C7145C5B6DCD2807475DF7D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the matter following clause (v), by striking <quote>his account</quote> and all that follows through the period; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H129C2F58567948CF841DED7F15966CDA"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by striking the semicolon at the end of clause (v) and inserting a period;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H7AD5082F465A42129E78D84F80953390"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(2)(A) Notwithstanding</quote> and all that follows through <quote>a depositor or member who is—</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H73FD3F62777F4D2DBFDB8CE88E3704B2"> 
<paragraph id="H3CFD7F59A23F44478CD5F4F56E82E9BA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Municipal depositors or members</header> 
<subparagraph id="H8BB8755097194BD5B2FA5CF00431905"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any limitation in this Act or in any other provision of law relating to the amount of insurance available to any 1 depositor or member, deposits or shares of a municipal depositor or member shall be insured in an amount equal to the standard maximum share insurance amount (as determined under paragraph (5)), except as provided in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H86E4268129604975845079D0A513BA07"><enum>(B)</enum><header>In-state municipal depositors</header><text>In the case of the deposits of an in-State municipal depositor described in clause (ii), (iii), (iv), or (v) of subparagraph (E) at an insured credit union, such deposits shall be insured in an amount equal to the lesser of—</text> 
<clause id="H0B187893A66A45CABD271424FB8B90E0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>$2,000,000; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7584C51AB69449E582AAB065EDC2E0EF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the sum of the standard maximum deposit insurance amount and 80 percent of the amount of any deposits in excess of the standard maximum deposit insurance amount.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H08A3C020BC7845AC809DD498AA007936"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>No provision of this paragraph shall be construed as authorizing an insured credit union to accept the deposits of a municipal depositor in an amount greater than such credit union is authorized to accept under any other provision of Federal or State law.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6074861BA8DE4B51AD5152A005F7EF62"><enum>(D)</enum><header>In-state municipal depositor defined</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>in-State municipal depositor</term> means a municipal depositor that is located in the same State as the office or branch of the insured credit union at which the deposits of that depositor are held.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H926AA3EB083041759D414E609164E584"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Municipal depositor</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>municipal depositor</term> means a depositor that is—</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause> 
<clause id="HD7794755FE3B42FA8DC790192E9B2403"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(B) The</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HB29EA003AA884C968F20AEE585BB5042"> 
<subparagraph id="H64BAA61D26ED45C5B52463A7143200A1"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Authority to limit deposits</header><text>The</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause> 
<clause id="HC366E18A4C61450AA517BC43BD379610"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by striking <quote>depositor or member referred to in subparagraph (A)</quote> and inserting <quote>municipal depositor or member</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HACEA6DD6625C4D0682C944B78F4EB0A2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H753CB09488CE40798F044CEA9C768D24"> 
<paragraph id="H96EEAA298A714FF7918EA993D93B9C88"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Coverage for certain employee benefit plan deposits</header> 
<subparagraph id="H6C1F4A59BAFA434C91B28FFF618915F7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Pass-through insurance</header><text>The Administration shall provide pass-through share insurance for the deposits or shares of any employee benefit plan.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC7758E74AFF24A46A49CFCB89DF6535"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Prohibition on acceptance of deposits</header><text>An insured credit union that is not well capitalized or adequately capitalized may not accept employee benefit plan deposits.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7E7EA178611C4427A889F5E002DC5BE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the following definitions shall apply:</text> 
<clause id="H7982FAC451FB4ACFA8A3D472B60E957"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Capital standards</header><text>The terms <term>well capitalized</term> and <term>adequately capitalized</term> have the same meanings as in section 216(c).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDEFBA2E6825D482AB6D5AE642CC4A7AB"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Employee benefit plan</header><text>The term <term>employee benefit plan</term>—</text> 
<subclause id="HF91BB4400E364820B439A504C4596DAF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>has the meaning given to such term in section 3(3) of the <act-name parsable-cite="ERISA">Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974</act-name>;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HDE7573E8B91743A98CC3EB29714B4797"><enum>(II)</enum><text>includes any plan described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/401">section 401(d)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H855A7E374CAC402697262EB779958846"><enum>(III)</enum><text>includes any eligible deferred compensation plan described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/457">section 457</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H03FA3FED1FB64A5F8D7DDA06BF1E6DCA"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Pass-through share insurance</header><text>The term <term>pass-through share insurance</term> means, with respect to an employee benefit plan, insurance coverage provided on a pro rata basis to the participants in the plan, in accordance with the interest of each participant.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4B47499203FA47D89828EE408BED0089"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>No provision of this paragraph shall be construed as authorizing an insured credit union to accept the deposits of an employee benefit plan in an amount greater than such credit union is authorized to accept under any other provision of Federal or State law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1751F7C031C04A599FBDDAE24C700AB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Standard maximum share insurance amount defined</header><text>For purposes of this Act, the term <term>standard maximum share insurance amount</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFA9C20D7EFE44D7A8CDC80B8EE4368AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>until the effective date of final regulations prescribed pursuant to section 9(a)(2) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Reform Act of 2005, $100,000; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDE3E71A0A8224B91821D194C1B009EC4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>on and after such effective date, $130,000, adjusted as provided under section 11(a)(1)(F) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA187AF3C3E7C4E8B9B99F4079BACBA6F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Doubling of share insurance for certain retirement accounts</header><text>Section 207(k)(3) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FCUA">Federal Credit Union Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1787">12 U.S.C. 1787(k)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>$100,000</quote> and inserting <quote>2 times the standard maximum share insurance amount (as determined under paragraph (1))</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H701CD0B5F7F74148947E667FC334C31F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section and the amendments made by this section shall take effect on the date the final regulations required under section 9(a)(2) take effect.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HDF27682AAAC747D7818E241FEA9CB34"><enum>4.</enum><header>Setting assessments and repeal of special rules relating to minimum assessments and free deposit insurance</header> 
<subsection id="HA722559FF63342C68DAAC4A2E26604D1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Setting assessments</header><text>Section 7(b)(2) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HAA77D6AAFC3E46A1AA42D19A2746900"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking subparagraphs (A) and (B) and inserting the following new subparagraphs:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H90DB1707ECB0447591FEC9833004E00"> 
<subparagraph id="H1A304A14B97A48C1856891ED029FBD4B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board of Directors shall set assessments for insured depository institutions in such amounts as the Board of Directors may determine to be necessary or appropriate, subject to subparagraph (D).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9D51F0E7872D459A919E721FFC9CF49D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Factors to be considered</header><text>In setting assessments under subparagraph (A), the Board of Directors shall consider the following factors:</text> 
<clause id="H32FF9DDACBD04EF3835F593D39ED08B9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The estimated operating expenses of the Deposit Insurance Fund.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H494A9336B437443F85E18DB9C9624571"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The estimated case resolution expenses and income of the Deposit Insurance Fund.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H734B0C270F58479C9ECFD220FAD4C0FB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The projected effects of the payment of assessments on the capital and earnings of insured depository institutions.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBEA3EE938AEF4F4C9DA1066232A10205"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the risk factors and other factors taken into account pursuant to paragraph (1) under the risk-based assessment system, including the requirement under such paragraph to maintain a risk-based system.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF476CEDB97AB4656ADF4A904BD53D67F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Any other factors the Board of Directors may determine to be appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD625FDC4CD364625932D00FAA1EA06B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (C) the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H377E57FAF4EC40C2A8AE12FE7F00371B"> 
<subparagraph id="H5EF0B3869EC4473EB36591A1AAB4D7C8"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Base rate for assessments</header> 
<clause id="HDC7E9BD6A53343198F00ECF3906E7E4C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In setting assessment rates pursuant to subparagraph (A), the Board of Directors shall establish a base rate of not more than 1 basis point (exclusive of any credit or dividend) for those insured depository institutions in the lowest-risk category under the risk-based assessment system established pursuant to paragraph (1). No insured depository institution shall be barred from the lowest-risk category solely because of size.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC50AC8A1E4F2404E00BD2C1322AAC400"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Suspension</header><text>Clause (i) shall not apply during any period in which the reserve ratio of the Deposit Insurance Fund is less than the amount which is equal to 1.15 percent of the aggregate estimated insured deposits.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0259FFFF6FBE45629CC1A81D23F867A1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Assessment recordkeeping period shortened</header><text>Paragraph (5) of section 7(b) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(b)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="Federal Deposit Insurance Act" id="HB65AD07A6E55406C8216A5DE85003847"> 
<paragraph id="H6A21821CEB294825AE9F00927573E952"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Depository institution required to maintain assessment-related records</header><text>Each insured depository institution shall maintain all records that the Corporation may require for verifying the correctness of any assessment on the insured depository institution under this subsection until the later of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H106F441EAC4F48EFB2A1F4D5FA028BB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the end of the 3-year period beginning on the due date of the assessment; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF5403F032AE14390B7BC94D7AEFB00F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a dispute between the insured depository institution and the Corporation with respect to such assessment, the date of a final determination of any such dispute.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H25B56994344141C9BDA22901E276FC2E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Increase in fees for late assessment payments</header><text>Subsection (h) of section 18 of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1828">12 U.S.C. 1828(h)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="Federal Deposit Insurance Act" id="H60FF7F80950947A8B23DB63396040954"> 
<subsection id="H1F3C031BA2A942C8856EF1EA3D6E98C3"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Penalty for failure to timely pay assessments</header> 
<paragraph id="H86FC38004FFE4FA50000D778EADCEEF6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any insured depository institution which fails or refuses to pay any assessment shall be subject to a penalty in an amount not more than 1 percent of the amount of the assessment due for each day that such violation continues.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBBB56D6954B347DE90966BE9ACE3901"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception in case of dispute</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply if—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H102E61FDCB614524B5BA24779401069D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the failure to pay an assessment is due to a dispute between the insured depository institution and the Corporation over the amount of such assessment; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H735040D706EC4C828873AE1EBBD4DF95"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the insured depository institution deposits security satisfactory to the Corporation for payment upon final determination of the issue.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3E1CB09CC6C048909C4E90562725CF8F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authority to modify or remit penalty</header><text>The Corporation, in the sole discretion of the Corporation, may compromise, modify or remit any penalty which the Corporation may assess or has already assessed under paragraph (1) upon a finding that good cause prevented the timely payment of an assessment.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDFCB8CF20C4543B6BE59861F02B5593F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Assessments for lifeline accounts</header> 
<paragraph id="HF4F31A201E034A1792CBB90F99BF8D4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 232 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation Improvement Act of 1991 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1834">12 U.S.C. 1834</external-xref>) is amended by striking subsection (c).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H30006BE527A841DAB2C2A1AFDDAF2340"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clarification of rate applicable to deposits attributable to lifeline accounts</header><text>Section 7(b)(2)(H) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(b)(2)(H)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>at a rate determined in accordance with such Act</quote> and inserting <quote>at <fraction>1/2</fraction> the assessment rate otherwise applicable for such insured depository institution</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB5034130D4E64C0CB605072FA53CDED"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Section 232(a)(1) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation Improvement Act of 1991 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1834">12 U.S.C. 1834(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, and the</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5F7040F1957D4E180031BCA5D44957FD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header> 
<paragraph id="H07814C250C15468B9E4600395D6100EB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Paragraph (3) of section 7(a) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(a)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by striking the 3d sentence and inserting the following: <quote>Such reports of condition shall be the basis for the certified statements to be filed pursuant to subsection (c).</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB9C7EFEAB0C8411C84D1B8122B101B66"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Subparagraphs (B)(ii) and (C) of section 7(b)(1) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(b)(1)</external-xref>) are each amended by striking <quote>semiannual</quote> where such term appears in each such subparagraph.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6DF532B85F3D4F0D92980057940638FC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Section 7(b)(2) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H37A6377E26B6487FA45119DF60AAEED9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking subparagraphs (E), (F), and (G);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCE988F9C4AFD41719584744600C06ECC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>semiannual</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB8A56048AAC648E59304989CFCA5A096"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (H) (as amended by subsection (e)(2) of this section) as subparagraph (E).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9AD11B949DFD4C4600607B41B33BE362"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Section 7(b) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(b)</external-xref>) is amended by striking paragraph (4) and redesignating paragraphs (5) (as amended by subsection (b) of this section), (6), and (7) as paragraphs (4), (5), and (6) respectively.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5ACB4956BC334043A7F32B2FA6703EA4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Section 7(c) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8BC4CC0F6F8B4BC4A977456BF42A900"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A), by striking <quote>semiannual</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB7C353E1ACC74275A69296D6B5390003"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(A), by striking <quote>semiannual</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA4E50D78DFB4420F849CDDB601A37C84"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>semiannual period</quote> and inserting <quote>initial assessment period</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4612E5961F2E4FF3BE4623EC3F14A52B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Section 8(p) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1818">12 U.S.C. 1818(p)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>semiannual</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD58B5E4C6623448DA228FD4E004FCC93"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Section 8(q) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1818">12 U.S.C. 1818(q)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>semiannual period</quote> and inserting <quote>assessment period</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEE7253F9F225469C832C39E52F4FD2D3"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Section 13(c)(4)(G)(ii)(II) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1823">12 U.S.C. 1823(c)(4)(G)(ii)(II)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>semiannual period</quote> and inserting <quote>assessment period</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF9830FD5586A40D9B2C91C23BA191829"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Section 232(a) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation Improvement Act of 1991 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1834">12 U.S.C. 1834(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5398083578EE4E028803239E3C216151"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A) of paragraph (2), by striking <quote>the Board and</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC759E1A7F90B4C749F479B43946225C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (J) of paragraph (2), by striking <quote>the Board</quote> and inserting <quote>the Corporation</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD7E48EF5A6DD4260A9BFB3CC911682C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (A) of paragraph (3) and inserting the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H24B773835EF0424D902CC4BF8958F5B2"> 
<subparagraph id="H51512CD89C06452A9F5D174EC7C97B99"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Corporation</header><text>The term <term>Corporation</term> means the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB1F1A72F95304C92A6D643585813A0AE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C) of paragraph (3), by striking <quote>Board</quote> and inserting <quote>Corporation</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H28F7F12C532F4CD387638C110850E698"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section and the amendments made by this section shall take effect on the date that the final regulations required under section 9(a)(5) take effect.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HD683C049B47448AFB02ED1519845DF71"><enum>5.</enum><header>Replacement of fixed designated reserve ratio with reserve range</header> 
<subsection id="H39F572270CAD4D90A6BCFD91A0CAC27B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 7(b)(3) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(b)(3)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="Federal Deposit Insurance Act" id="HC65A4D076BC64E9ABB06E88C99EA00F6"> 
<paragraph id="H07CA50FA281E47D78EB3140664BDDD75"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Designated reserve ratio</header> 
<subparagraph id="H602B30396A6A4A67B1A092E9ED712E2C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment</header> 
<clause id="HFF6DC3899FD24991A2C0E64E24FD2644"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board of Directors shall designate, by regulation after notice and opportunity for comment, the reserve ratio applicable with respect to the Deposit Insurance Fund.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA10E63E6F76345A0BFE981F0F33BA6C2"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Not less than annual redetermination</header><text>A determination under clause (i) shall be made by the Board of Directors at least before the beginning of each calendar year, for such calendar year, and at such other times as the Board of Directors may determine to be appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2B2354D012E84766A5B30643DB3BA00"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Range</header><text>The reserve ratio designated by the Board of Directors for any year—</text> 
<clause id="H319CE101A9C34C23B1D94E32D7804EFE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may not exceed 1.4 percent of estimated insured deposits; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD7BEED74937A49D8A4007E1C35A665D3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may not be less than 1.15 percent of estimated insured deposits.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H441B1C980AA546D7A14849A4CA84E745"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Factors</header><text>In designating a reserve ratio for any year, the Board of Directors shall—</text> 
<clause id="H7922F575F3F2468396ADF1467FB0482E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>take into account the risk of losses to the Deposit Insurance Fund in such year and future years, including historic experience and potential and estimated losses from insured depository institutions;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H92D01A885E754166974780009C42D101"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>take into account economic conditions generally affecting insured depository institutions so as to allow the designated reserve ratio to increase during more favorable economic conditions and to decrease during less favorable economic conditions, notwithstanding the increased risks of loss that may exist during such less favorable conditions, as determined to be appropriate by the Board of Directors;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD302F62895DE485B8C8EFD00CB1B9CFC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>seek to prevent sharp swings in the assessment rates for insured depository institutions; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0531EFCCEB774A64901EA4DEA207CFB9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>take into account such other factors as the Board of Directors may determine to be appropriate, consistent with the requirements of this subparagraph.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3D38FFE5750442C6BF00B227D7DA06CA"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Publication of proposed change in ratio</header><text>In soliciting comment on any proposed change in the designated reserve ratio in accordance with subparagraph (A), the Board of Directors shall include in the published proposal a thorough analysis of the data and projections on which the proposal is based.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H17FF9C833C2E4D2F8C7500C240009614"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text>Section 3(y) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813(y)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF630A039B6664C68BC9336F5F44C3FB0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(y) The term</quote> and inserting</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HF87FF8B4C9B64FF79CAA8EFA3079A531"> 
<subsection id="H9039B54A649D4294A53582AD76993BAC" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(y)</enum><text>Definitions Relating to Deposit Insurance Fund.—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC3687EA7CB224C0CA9FBBEBDF9CC095"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deposit Insurance Fund</header><text>The term</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H85D40B465DE74295B2CE00220357D5A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (1) (as so designated by paragraph (1) of this subsection) the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HA71329A81335405CBDBEDEDC75C16D"> 
<paragraph id="H84A42015B3EF4E80BA7B2FD09E36E834"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Designated reserve ratio</header><text>The term <term>designated reserve ratio</term> means the reserve ratio designated by the Board of Directors in accordance with section 7(b)(3).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9C2FACF43D7E466A87DF0011D3BC9BDA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section and the amendments made by this section shall take effect on the date that the final regulations required under section 9(a)(1) take effect.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HD7E2C63C02014027A6B7F32BEDAABFE"><enum>6.</enum><header>Requirements applicable to the risk-based assessment system</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 7(b)(1) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(b)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraphs:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="Federal Deposit Insurance Act" id="HF0312AA2E61B4DEDB1E853FC6B863DFD"> 
<subparagraph id="HFC161AD371CD4BD79FFF448DD710AC"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Information concerning risk of loss and economic conditions</header> 
<clause id="H8DBE710C0D8045A8A47024802CD5C600"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Sources of information</header><text>For purposes of determining risk of losses at insured depository institutions and economic conditions generally affecting depository institutions, the Corporation shall collect information, as appropriate, from all sources the Board of Directors considers appropriate, such as reports of condition, inspection reports, and other information from all Federal banking agencies, any information available from State bank supervisors, State insurance and securities regulators, the Securities and Exchange Commission (including information described in section 35), the Secretary of the Treasury, the Commodity Futures Trading Commission, the Farm Credit Administration, the Federal Trade Commission, any Federal reserve bank or Federal home loan bank, and other regulators of financial institutions, and any information available from credit rating entities, and other private economic or business analysts.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H683EFA65E5094B1082C8FA5330DBAD8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Consultation with Federal banking agencies</header> 
<subclause id="H7CACC0E65B0E485EA19ECBB69CD0042"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subclause (II), in assessing the risk of loss to the Deposit Insurance Fund with respect to any insured depository institution, the Corporation shall consult with the appropriate Federal banking agency of such institution.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H021F4D9DC6034DCFA600345B679FA567"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Treatment on aggregate basis</header><text>In the case of insured depository institutions that are well capitalized (as defined in section 38) and, in the most recent examination, were found to be well managed, the consultation under subclause (I) concerning the assessment of the risk of loss posed by such institutions may be made on an aggregate basis.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HE0E7EC0FBE464489849C13616D71A44"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>No provision of this paragraph shall be construed as providing any new authority for the Corporation to require submission of information by insured depository institutions to the Corporation.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2EC472E0095F49C0A359DE00A730A26C"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Modifications to the risk-based assessment system allowed only after notice and comment</header><text>In revising or modifying the risk-based assessment system at any time after the date of the enactment of the Federal Deposit Insurance Reform Act of 2005, the Board of Directors may implement such revisions or modification in final form only after notice and opportunity for comment.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H5D03211D057B4337BC206D9853AAA670"><enum>7.</enum><header>Refunds, dividends, and credits from Deposit Insurance Fund</header> 
<subsection id="H77592EA9AD8546809E779DA817FCEC2D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (e) of section 7 of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(e)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="Federal Deposit Insurance Act" id="H83BAEEDABA134B67AAA3A53BD9A86DCB"> 
<subsection id="H131C6AE69E854CF79CACA8460086B430"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Refunds, dividends, and credits</header> 
<paragraph id="H15D826CC0E164822B37F001F94456CE6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Refunds of overpayments</header><text>In the case of any payment of an assessment by an insured depository institution in excess of the amount due to the Corporation, the Corporation may—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9EEFB555C4884FF4895803E221B5A388"><enum>(A)</enum><text>refund the amount of the excess payment to the insured depository institution; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0EFA1FBD5B8F447B8481CF9D06DBE263"><enum>(B)</enum><text>credit such excess amount toward the payment of subsequent assessments until such credit is exhausted.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H02990E93890E4F83B7F00F61E61C72B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Dividends from excess amounts in Deposit Insurance Fund</header> 
<subparagraph id="H17EF0F25579144F69C0530C3B4C29C00"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Reserve ratio in excess of 1.4 percent of estimated insured deposits</header><text>Whenever the reserve ratio of the Deposit Insurance Fund exceeds 1.4 percent of estimated insured deposits, the Corporation shall declare the amount in the Fund in excess of the amount required to maintain the reserve ratio at 1.4 percent of estimated insured deposits, as dividends to be paid to insured depository institutions.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9BF319A03B2D428BAFC2D3379400CE6D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reserve ratio equal to or in excess of 1.35 percent of estimated insured deposits and not more than 1.4 percent</header><text>Whenever the reserve ratio of the Deposit Insurance Fund equals or exceeds 1.35 percent of estimated insured deposits and is not more than 1.4 percent of such deposits, the Corporation shall declare the amount in the Fund that is equal to 50 percent of the amount in excess of the amount required to maintain the reserve ratio at 1.35 percent of the estimated insured deposits as dividends to be paid to insured depository institutions.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7C6E20CEE2DF47D5B79BA86465325812"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Basis for distribution of dividends</header> 
<clause id="H01361509CA4A4BE2AAEC8FBC07BDCD6D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Solely for the purposes of dividend distribution under this paragraph and credit distribution under paragraph (3)(B), the Corporation shall determine each insured depository institution’s relative contribution to the Deposit Insurance Fund (or any predecessor deposit insurance fund) for calculating such institution’s share of any dividend or credit declared under this paragraph or paragraph (3)(B), taking into account the factors described in clause (ii).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0DC2EDB5E4CF443B96BA351BA36C1933"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Factors for distribution</header><text>In implementing this paragraph and paragraph (3)(B) in accordance with regulations, the Corporation shall take into account the following factors:</text> 
<subclause id="H435E832FEB0244E1BC69569FB522FFF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The ratio of the assessment base of an insured depository institution (including any predecessor) on December 31, 1996, to the assessment base of all eligible insured depository institutions on that date.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H6A8D8764D44A433FAF6F385005324FD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The total amount of assessments paid on or after January 1, 1997, by an insured depository institution (including any predecessor) to the Deposit Insurance Fund (and any predecessor deposit insurance fund).</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HD069A17A7D8A43A084FBB85C72A9B399"><enum>(III)</enum><text>That portion of assessments paid by an insured depository institution (including any predecessor) that reflects higher levels of risk assumed by such institution.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H424CA0085DBA4F439C2E2424856500FA"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Such other factors as the Corporation may determine to be appropriate.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H29F9473ADB4040D0BA003975F13D0051"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Notice and opportunity for comment</header><text>The Corporation shall prescribe by regulation, after notice and opportunity for comment, the method for the calculation, declaration, and payment of dividends under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H87D5E4DEBADB4A82AC8318845EAEB727"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Credit pool</header> 
<subparagraph id="H414D8843473746DA9D04382106207D40"><enum>(A)</enum><header>One-time credit based on total assessment base at year-end 1996</header> 
<clause id="H368EE5E9642E46F28FF5C49000AF911F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Before the end of the 270-day period beginning on the date of the enactment of the Federal Deposit Insurance Reform Act of 2005, the Board of Directors shall, by regulation, provide for a credit to each eligible insured depository institution, based on the assessment base of the institution (including any predecessor institution) on December 31, 1996, as compared to the combined aggregate assessment base of all eligible insured depository institutions, taking into account such factors as the Board of Directors may determine to be appropriate.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7A45523CB30C46CF836713F04F82D034"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Credit limit</header><text>The aggregate amount of credits available under clause (i) to all eligible insured depository institutions shall equal the amount that the Corporation could collect if the Corporation imposed an assessment of 12 basis points on the combined assessment base of the Bank Insurance Fund and the Savings Association Insurance Fund as of December 31, 2001.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0B59F9F356644EB4A4C928B5A18D474F"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Eligible insured depository institution defined</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>eligible insured depository institution</term> means any insured depository institution that—</text> 
<subclause id="HAC897EF0C71E4182BB265B2DA6760007"><enum>(I)</enum><text>was in existence on December 31, 1996, and paid a deposit insurance assessment prior to that date; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3BDD3DE862D44CA08C86FFB6A26A640"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is a successor to any insured depository institution described in subclause (I).</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H4D5A49D3242840DFAC36782D7E111CCF"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Application of credits</header> 
<subclause id="H7304A95EFD5E454B8D55F9B0C3F9288"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The amount of a credit to any eligible insured depository institution under this paragraph shall be applied by the Corporation, subject to subsection (b)(3)(E), to the assessments imposed on such institution under subsection (b) that become due for assessment periods beginning after the effective date of regulations prescribed under clause (i).</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H878CE181810A4A9D9D1378379D8BCEEF"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The regulations prescribed under clause (i) shall establish the qualifications and procedures governing the application of assessment credits pursuant to subclause (I).</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H22E4AFFB3C2A457CBAC896FDF313F371"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Limitation on amount of credit for certain depository institutions</header><text>In the case of an insured depository institution that exhibits financial, operational, or compliance weaknesses ranging from moderately severe to unsatisfactory, or is not adequately capitalized (as defined in section 38) at the beginning of an assessment period, the amount of any credit allowed under this paragraph against the assessment on that depository institution for such period may not exceed the amount calculated by applying to that depository institution the average assessment rate on all insured depository institutions for such assessment period.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0802C027E4C64EDC88F8796B414DCB2D"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Predecessor defined</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>predecessor</term>, when used with respect to any insured depository institution, includes any other insured depository institution acquired by or merged with such insured depository institution.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA4F1F9090BBD4234AD212D58115F7C1B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>On-going credit pool</header> 
<clause id="HF642364EB4EC42AFB42577F953AC5C27"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In addition to the credit provided pursuant to subparagraph (A) and subject to the limitation contained in clause (v) of such subparagraph, the Corporation shall, by regulation, establish an on-going system of credits to be applied against future assessments under subsection (b)(1) on the same basis as the dividends provided under paragraph (2)(C).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H56FFC7DAF67E42339FA1EBE5A540562F"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Limitation on credits under certain circumstances</header><text>No credits may be awarded by the Corporation under this subparagraph during any period in which—</text> 
<subclause id="HBFF79B85115140E0A77E9C831C45E49D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the reserve ratio of the Deposit Insurance Fund is less than the designated reserve ratio of such Fund; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HE18F9B7089264534B4EACC5817C37D1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the reserve ratio of the Fund is less than 1.25 percent of the amount of estimated insured deposits.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HFAC9781610A34DB5A3EFF61D97A81438"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Criteria for determination</header><text>In determining the amounts of any assessment credits under this subparagraph, the Board of Directors shall take into account the factors for designating the reserve ratio under subsection (b)(3) and the factors for setting assessments under subsection (b)(2)(B).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8FE133702F6F41E2A4BEB3B7B79EFF87"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Administrative review</header> 
<subparagraph id="H57FEEEB2EF3D487C9F23133B7FAF4290"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The regulations prescribed under paragraph (2)(D) and subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (3) shall include provisions allowing an insured depository institution a reasonable opportunity to challenge administratively the amount of the credit or dividend determined under paragraph (2) or (3) for such institution.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1777BA39F12247CEBFB5F330C113DFA6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Administrative review</header><text>Any review under subparagraph (A) of any determination of the Corporation under paragraph (2) or (3) shall be final and not subject to judicial review.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3F45AD3D6DC248FEBFE95627A82D369B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition of reserve ratio</header><text>Section 3(y) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813(y)</external-xref>) (as amended by section 5(b) of this Act) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="Federal Deposit Insurance Act" id="HDEBCCD2074704273BD469976E1E471F"> 
<paragraph id="HCE97DE5CCF934A378E47052E05F25436"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reserve ratio</header><text>The term <term>reserve ratio</term>, when used with regard to the Deposit Insurance Fund other than in connection with a reference to the designated reserve ratio, means the ratio of the net worth of the Deposit Insurance Fund to the value of the aggregate estimated insured deposits.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H91E7194286654F65B4FAAA92D182C954"><enum>8.</enum><header>Deposit Insurance Fund restoration plans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 7(b)(3) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(b)(3)</external-xref>) (as amended by section 5(a) of this Act) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="Federal Deposit Insurance Act" id="HFD3BF7E3A6454337AA071EF7907E9262"> 
<subparagraph id="H0A2828B431F34DEAAC663658A4CA9990"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Dif restoration plans</header> 
<clause id="H93364A2DAFA54D32A547BEBACCD1CFCB"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Whenever—</text> 
<subclause id="H8F3E1AAB9C314DA093B6599EE98FE8F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Corporation projects that the reserve ratio of the Deposit Insurance Fund will, within 6 months of such determination, fall below the minimum amount specified in subparagraph (B)(ii) for the designated reserve ratio; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HEDD445C3A4674960868629DA74BE79FF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the reserve ratio of the Deposit Insurance Fund actually falls below the minimum amount specified in subparagraph (B)(ii) for the designated reserve ratio without any determination under subclause (I) having been made,</text></subclause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="clause">the Corporation shall establish and implement a Deposit Insurance Fund restoration plan within 90 days that meets the requirements of clause (ii) and such other conditions as the Corporation determines to be appropriate.</continuation-text></clause> 
<clause id="HBCAB9E3D88CA4D1B98D8F9977BE4FC6"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Requirements of restoration plan</header><text>A Deposit Insurance Fund restoration plan meets the requirements of this clause if the plan provides that the reserve ratio of the Fund will meet or exceed the minimum amount specified in subparagraph (B)(ii) for the designated reserve ratio before the end of the 10-year period beginning upon the implementation of the plan.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD28497FD8E91495FB434CDFDC83F66B1"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Restriction on assessment credits</header><text>As part of any restoration plan under this subparagraph, the Corporation may elect to restrict the application of assessment credits provided under subsection (e)(3) for any period that the plan is in effect.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF5A05D7CA2CE424A855E4115EE42B3D6"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Limitation on restriction</header><text>Notwithstanding clause (iii), while any restoration plan under this subparagraph is in effect, the Corporation shall apply credits provided to an insured depository institution under subsection (e)(3) against any assessment imposed on the institution for any assessment period in an amount equal to the lesser of—</text> 
<subclause id="HBE0C5F562C0D426F8B919203820489FC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the amount of the assessment; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3C68A556920948C0BBC5FA2FF1BBEBF3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the amount equal to 3 basis points of the institution’s assessment base.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HDF524C30BE8C4D43A8CC2D2E11A27641"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Transparency</header><text>Not more than 30 days after the Corporation establishes and implements a restoration plan under clause (i), the Corporation shall publish in the Federal Register a detailed analysis of the factors considered and the basis for the actions taken with regard to the plan.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H5113DEB79EA24FA2888D22B0CD773FF"><enum>9.</enum><header>Regulations required</header> 
<subsection id="H0D9ABDD8FCD6481FA5F8D29363AD495B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Board of Directors of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation shall prescribe final regulations, after notice and opportunity for comment—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2BE925DFF604431FB3521167F56D3B8C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>designating the reserve ratio for the Deposit Insurance Fund in accordance with section 7(b)(3) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (as amended by section 5 of this Act);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB612B9EF80474518A2B9A5A47C66B47D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>implementing increases in deposit insurance coverage in accordance with the amendments made by section 3 of this Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H30427371C1A84F95B975C13DE14E007B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>implementing the dividend requirement under section 7(e)(2) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (as amended by section 7 of this Act);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H69E50FE7425B49E18257DB72D92DFA74"><enum>(4)</enum><text>implementing the 1-time assessment credit to certain insured depository institutions in accordance with section 7(e)(3) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name>, as amended by section 7 of this Act, including the qualifications and procedures under which the Corporation would apply assessment credits; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H85D7B1A689EF4E04A7DA44A1BCF33500"><enum>(5)</enum><text>providing for assessments under section 7(b) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name>, as amended by this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFEF5DA28D2FE457BA28694E250F3849D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>No provision of this Act or any amendment made by this Act shall be construed as affecting the authority of the Corporation to set or collect deposit insurance assessments before the effective date of the final regulations prescribed under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H7EFBD146027A4A9FBE2DF9FABBD1CD12"><enum>10.</enum><header>Studies of FDIC structure and expenses and certain activities and further possible changes to deposit insurance system</header> 
<subsection id="H656F5338B5C24DAC9C646B8C3E7F3BEC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study by Comptroller General</header> 
<paragraph id="HABA3EFEB524E4DE389E8A5D6129591D4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study required</header><text>The Comptroller General shall conduct a study of the following issues:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEC60AEBB033A4722002141DECAEFAA04"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The efficiency and effectiveness of the administration of the prompt corrective action program under section 38 of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> by the Federal banking agencies (as defined in section 3 of such Act), including the degree of effectiveness of such agencies in identifying troubled depository institutions and taking effective action with respect to such institutions, and the degree of accuracy of the risk assessments made by the Corporation.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H12B153A906E04735AEF004FCE840060"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The appropriateness of the organizational structure of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation for the mission of the Corporation taking into account—</text> 
<clause id="H95604A9461FF4B85ABA2B7DCFFC71036"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the current size and complexity of the business of insured depository institutions (as such term is defined in section 3 of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name>);</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBBD1690AA8FF445BA552B2225F1C1C32"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the extent to which the organizational structure contributes to or reduces operational inefficiencies that increase operational costs; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H24BE33C2351943E4927442E275BF82B1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the effectiveness of internal controls.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF78152C3268A4F6FBB57AD4BB613DDB7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to the Congress</header><text>The Comptroller General shall submit a report to the Congress before the end of the 1-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act containing the findings and conclusions of the Comptroller General with respect to the study required under paragraph (1) together with such recommendations for legislative or administrative action as the Comptroller General may determine to be appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9557DB919891494980F03DC79A64EC6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Internal study by the FDIC</header> 
<paragraph id="H96F06098453C47B99C3D5E5995F298ED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study required</header><text>Concurrently with the study required to be conducted by the Comptroller General under subsection (a), the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation shall conduct an internal study of the same conditions and factors included in the study under subsection (a).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4A7C9A233740444EAA2C6E016B7BA9F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to the Congress</header><text>The Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation shall submit a report to the Congress before the end of the 1-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act containing the findings and conclusions of the Corporation with respect to the study required under paragraph (1) together with such recommendations for legislative or administrative action as the Board of Directors of the Corporation may determine to be appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD553EFF3C69945E0A54F1B00ADFA47E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Study of further possible changes to deposit insurance system</header> 
<paragraph id="HA040E8A049294A9785B800667277963C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study required</header><text>The Board of Directors of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation and the National Credit Union Administration Board shall each conduct a study of the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H06D93FADABA54A74B6AA00F7CA514219"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The feasibility of establishing a voluntary deposit insurance system for deposits in excess of the maximum amount of deposit insurance for any depositor and the potential benefits and the potential adverse consequences that may result from the establishment of any such system.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1E0DBBE27D9846C585D9D65AD00F5CB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The feasibility of privatizing all deposit insurance at insured depository institutions and insured credit unions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H91329FF8EC454D468500CFF2F211138"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Before the end of the 1-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Board of Directors of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation and the National Credit Union Administration Board shall each submit a report to the Congress on the study required under paragraph (1) containing the findings and conclusions of the reporting agency together with such recommendations for legislative or administrative changes as the agency may determine to be appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H44FB052928524922B0EAE9142E007FD3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Study regarding appropriate deposit base in designating reserve ratio</header> 
<paragraph id="HA97D800725C9461D8E72345EF1E4BD5D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study required</header><text>The Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation shall conduct a study of the feasibility of using actual domestic deposits rather than estimated insured deposits in calculating the reserve ratio of the Deposit Insurance Fund and designating a reserve ratio for such Fund.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE15C93EA53DB47D190F60031BC6B35C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation shall submit a report to the Congress before the end of the 1-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act containing the findings and conclusions of the Corporation with respect to the study required under paragraph (1) together with such recommendations for legislative or administrative action as the Board of Directors of the Corporation may determine to be appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF45F67DF08F840789CFDF506FE4C914"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Study of reserve methodology and accounting for loss</header> 
<paragraph id="H51BF85190200447DB2FDD394659B72E0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study required</header><text>The Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, in consultation with the Comptroller General, shall conduct a study of the reserve methodology and loss accounting used by the Corporation during the period beginning on January 1, 1992, and ending December 31, 2004, with respect to insured depository institutions in a troubled condition (as defined in the regulations prescribed pursuant to section 32(f) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H326140CF77E24AC5AF2E3E65F0A5F7AE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Factors to be included</header><text>In conducting the study pursuant to paragraph (1), the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD492AB164EA9407CB600452EDD9CF439"><enum>(A)</enum><text>consider the overall effectiveness and accuracy of the methodology used by the Corporation for establishing and maintaining reserves and estimating and accounting for losses at insured depository institutions, during the period described in such paragraph;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD6B9E4700AA34074A9048305261F8000"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consider the appropriateness and reliability of information and criteria used by the Corporation in determining—</text> 
<clause id="H1A360446DDF04D15ABC5626B3F20CA73"><enum>(i)</enum><text>whether an insured depository institution was in a troubled condition; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7FC552F85FA64A37A991DD71812DDC6C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the amount of any loss anticipated at such institution;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H82D9D18667A847CEBA00AB47CA9988D6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>analyze the actual historical loss experience over the period described in paragraph (1) and the causes of the exceptionally high rate of losses experienced by the Corporation in the final 3 years of that period; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H47D2015B207349FFB31377BD1F002351"><enum>(D)</enum><text>rate the efforts of the Corporation to reduce losses in such 3-year period to minimally acceptable levels and to historical levels.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3CBB4B4972AA4EFB0047F0AC71619DE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>The Board of Directors of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation shall submit a report to the Congress before the end of the 6-month period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, containing the findings and conclusions of the Corporation, in consultation with the Comptroller General, with respect to the study required under paragraph (1), together with such recommendations for legislative or administrative action as the Board of Directors may determine to be appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HF6856706A66E46B49843E97ECDEA5B71"><enum>11.</enum><header>Bi-annual FDIC survey and report on increasing the deposit base by encouraging use of depository institutions by the unbanked</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1811">12 U.S.C. 1811 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="Federal Deposit Insurance Act" id="HB83D90BF6C324C5FB800799B277D82C7"> 
<section id="H649BC34877E5410BADDD892EC7AF6C1E"><enum>49.</enum><header>Bi-annual FDIC survey and report on encouraging use of depository institutions by the unbanked</header> 
<subsection id="H9FDAA0627E424741AF2700DB592EA52E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Survey required</header> 
<paragraph id="HFF2395DCF1164E6B8E1E26FA5C2DA5C7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Corporation shall conduct a bi-annual survey on efforts by insured depository institutions to bring those individuals and families who have rarely, if ever, held a checking account, a savings account or other type of transaction or check cashing account at an insured depository institution (hereafter in this section referred to as the <quote>unbanked</quote>) into the conventional finance system.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H72B3102421DC4E6DA78C001183998FAD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Factors and questions to consider</header><text>In conducting the survey, the Corporation shall take the following factors and questions into account:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3C16CC6585954E90000252EBE73CD4C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To what extent do insured depository institutions promote financial education and financial literacy outreach?</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE0568E8BC35F4B5290C268369FF8771C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Which financial education efforts appear to be the most effective in bringing <quote>unbanked</quote> individuals and families into the conventional finance system?</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H838084AF2BF242B1A5C2D6EF43C1C79"><enum>(C)</enum><text>What efforts are insured institutions making at converting <quote>unbanked</quote> money order, wire transfer, and international remittance customers into conventional account holders?</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6B777FFA20F34C1CB09F00B04B18104F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>What cultural, language and identification issues as well as transaction costs appear to most prevent <quote>unbanked</quote> individuals from establishing conventional accounts?</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD460D139B3A24F7C9F1929E2C686BA18"><enum>(E)</enum><text>What is a fair estimate of the size and worth of the <quote>unbanked</quote> market in the United States?</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC301B2C7FB19447494C8F0B6B41014D2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>The Chairperson of the Board of Directors shall submit a bi-annual report to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate containing the Corporation’s findings and conclusions with respect to the survey conducted pursuant to subsection (a), together with such recommendations for legislative or administrative action as the Chairperson may determine to be appropriate.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H8035AD89576546F2A8B3EBE2417BD170"><enum>12.</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments to the <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> relating to the merger of the BIF and SAIF</header> 
<subsection id="H6089AEB4B7D34FF495B494C7D7FD94F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The <act-name parsable-cite="FDIA">Federal Deposit Insurance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1811">12 U.S.C. 1811 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9667A45EE8C74610997E901E9342C4AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 3 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFFE920A2DE244DCFA631D30524136717"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (B) of subsection (a)(1) and inserting the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HBCD01F5DB0004FF9B910B874DB52D59F"> 
<subparagraph id="H583410DD18E2451CB4626F06BAFC129B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes any former savings association.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3A08BB042BC84AA2B0FFA21C47D88918"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (1) of subsection (y) (as so designated by section 5(b) of this Act) and inserting the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HBE950078A375458300C6E22CA35BC705"> 
<paragraph id="H0E78972DD84843AA866533D6FA83583C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deposit Insurance Fund</header><text>The term <term>Deposit Insurance Fund</term> means the Deposit Insurance Fund established under section 11(a)(4).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H06BB6908476E4D5B9FC23811CF67AB8C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 5(b)(5) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1815">12 U.S.C. 1815(b)(5)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>the Bank Insurance Fund or the Savings Association Insurance Fund,</quote> and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund,</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3903F0DE34574A1D8F96CBCEB8C1DB68"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 5(c)(4), by striking <quote>deposit insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5DB65136388C43A9A3A283171506D1AC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 5(d) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1815">12 U.S.C. 1815(d)</external-xref>), by striking paragraphs (2) and (3) (and any funds resulting from the application of such paragraph (2) prior to its repeal shall be deposited into the general fund of the Deposit Insurance Fund);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB00E13DC602F4C92ADDB00CBD008E5D7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in section 5(d)(1) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1815">12 U.S.C. 1815(d)(1)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBB135833389E417F80FDF67484287D2F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>reserve ratios in the Bank Insurance Fund and the Savings Association Insurance Fund as required by section 7</quote> and inserting <quote>the reserve ratio of the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4320CF5521FB44D5BD9B625346545100"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (B) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HE7CED343EFB44643B6E57ED58EA0A0EE"> 
<paragraph id="H8BD7E04400D34ABD90112DB123E37FBF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fee credited to the Deposit Insurance Fund</header><text>The fee paid by the depository institution under paragraph (1) shall be credited to the Deposit Insurance Fund.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6CA890F7CC6E4646BA7DF67F568CA600"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(1) <header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Uninsured institutions</header-in-text>.—</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAF22ABF0A4E0466497D16762A1513C71"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (A) and (C) as paragraphs (1) and (3), respectively, and moving the left margins 2 ems to the left;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF1C5A2EBFD984118AF6E9F1D475227CE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in section 5(e) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1815">12 U.S.C. 1815(e)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H056A593C28124738A82F12008DD3E8FC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)(A), by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund or the Savings Association Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H551EFAAE0E1546CA9958CA05EE13F3E7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (6); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3B8875DD4E284DB6AB915CF519B7E02"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (7), (8), and (9) as paragraphs (6), (7), and (8), respectively;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFA5D866FAAF9455188B9BA769A95E03"><enum>(7)</enum><text>in section 6(5) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1816">12 U.S.C. 1816(5)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund or the Savings Association Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H08BA47DA388B4EF5A97C3E00812BC8B5"><enum>(8)</enum><text>in section 7(b) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(b)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6426F2B6CBC74DDBAF58E396BEBE77A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(C), by striking <quote>deposit insurance fund</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD097B93F3EBD42B3AFA9EEDF6DA72B47"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(D), by striking <quote>each deposit insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB4221F96477042CAAA4D1D5390345E00"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (5) (as so redesignated by section 4(e)(4) of this Act)—</text> 
<clause id="HECD60D9B7ED241E18BD10064506120A0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>any such assessment</quote> and inserting <quote>any such assessment is necessary</quote>;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H93D3052686F04AB9A06619E65DFDDE93"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (B);</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB8A94700FBB74F858631BC39D2B76DEC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text> 
<subclause id="H74D88CF4A0544F2694FD9318AF2CE944"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(A) is necessary—</quote>;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HE1913EA5AE6443B6B1A19B3E8837E31B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund members</quote> and inserting <quote>insured depository institutions</quote>; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3779DCD32BAA46DBB600A9F73D47CB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by redesignating clauses (i), (ii), and (iii) as subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C), respectively, and moving the margins 2 ems to the left; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HE7EABE9F2A2948658C48989FD2C67DB0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C) (as so redesignated)—</text> 
<subclause id="HAFA2E291D2D5445B86FB2C6B7CFDB935"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>that</quote> before <quote>the Corporation</quote>; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H95D50E3FA8594C1A82E7CEBB1957FE5D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a period;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB01039A449E4466A83B6C76FEBA1AC48"><enum>(9)</enum><text>in section 7(j)(7)(F) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1817">12 U.S.C. 1817(j)(7)(F)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund or the Savings Association Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H33324211F0814152806433C835B01809"><enum>(10)</enum><text>in section 8(t)(2)(C) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1818">12 U.S.C. 1818(t)(2)(C)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>deposit insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H278B8E030AC94A6AB655391C14A25130"><enum>(11)</enum><text>in section 11 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821">12 U.S.C. 1821</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9531F79344E948EB99DA462600A6EAEA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>deposit insurance fund</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0461F5819E1D4464B4ECBC2AD6DF359"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (4) of subsection (a) and inserting the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H827DAC3858D74274B87EBCAB3EAA5BB"> 
<paragraph id="H3911FC4425824DD6AABB8E47432BDEF6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Deposit Insurance Fund</header> 
<subparagraph id="H476B423830C14E1C92EFF96B1F670009"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established the Deposit Insurance Fund, which the Corporation shall—</text> 
<clause id="HECABC8A212F24D589CCD41B761B5752D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>maintain and administer;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H70483341E54D482A004F6CF2F51DE244"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>use to carry out its insurance purposes, in the manner provided by this subsection; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5A0AAD5017F64D0F82E01C198083D0A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>invest in accordance with section 13(a).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA96DCFB397E04106A1B58020845161EE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Uses</header><text>The Deposit Insurance Fund shall be available to the Corporation for use with respect to insured depository institutions the deposits of which are insured by the Deposit Insurance Fund.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H13EBF7B6E72B4795B971FD68A61B13DC"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limitation on use</header><text>Notwithstanding any provision of law other than section 13(c)(4)(G), the Deposit Insurance Fund shall not be used in any manner to benefit any shareholder or affiliate (other than an insured depository institution that receives assistance in accordance with the provisions of this Act) of—</text> 
<clause id="HD3A0F7B510124D20B4FE873B1F8F6708"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any insured depository institution for which the Corporation has been appointed conservator or receiver, in connection with any type of resolution by the Corporation;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H68052582C94842A2A4FCBDE2703E337D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other insured depository institution in default or in danger of default, in connection with any type of resolution by the Corporation; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8BD9C4366CE242EF9716CE2DF3730028"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any insured depository institution, in connection with the provision of assistance under this section or section 13 with respect to such institution, except that this clause shall not prohibit any assistance to any insured depository institution that is not in default, or that is not in danger of default, that is acquiring (as defined in section 13(f)(8)(B)) another insured depository institution.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H82EE62A7C90643088F6CFED1CA00AEA"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Deposits</header><text>All amounts assessed against insured depository institutions by the Corporation shall be deposited into the Deposit Insurance Fund.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB14C052EF8CB47E1AE37A05F8BC38E4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking paragraphs (5), (6), and (7) of subsection (a); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9FCBAE30875D4FE1A226BC7BE7535E3D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (8) of subsection (a) as paragraph (5);</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H978A26AFDD854097A2ADD4CA1BF9B05F"><enum>(12)</enum><text>in section 11(f)(1) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821">12 U.S.C. 1821(f)(1)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>, except that—</quote> and all that follows through the end of the paragraph and inserting a period;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0165BA1806664C5081444DE39EE84203"><enum>(13)</enum><text>in section 11(i)(3) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821">12 U.S.C. 1821(i)(3)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7F79301E53F84331ADCADC7958688873"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (B);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H62BEE72701BF42EC88156E006229D75F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (C) as subparagraph (B); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF6A25C45E3F5498E00C3DDB2FC5DB9EA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B) (as so redesignated), by striking <quote>subparagraphs (A) and (B)</quote> and inserting <quote>subparagraph (A)</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBDCFA72074744534AF62C9334612CD71"><enum>(14)</enum><text>in section 11(p)(2)(B) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821">12 U.S.C. 1821(p)(2)(B)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>institution, any</quote> and inserting <quote>institution, the</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5B8B58A12D9F4EA682E0A17574FE74E5"><enum>(15)</enum><text>in section 11A(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821a">12 U.S.C. 1821a(a)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9CF7B1FDA8754F6681001C35F77F7BA7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">liabilities</header-in-text>.—</quote> and all that follows through <quote>Except</quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">liabilities</header-in-text>.—Except</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1BC0EAB6DB6F4D1399981334C1FDB56"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (2)(B); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H85871ED45E2747C6BF675C12B000E100"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>the Bank Insurance Fund, the Savings Association Insurance Fund,</quote> and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H56CD1262BB1F47F092003495E8D8E818"><enum>(16)</enum><text>in section 11A(b) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821a">12 U.S.C. 1821a(b)</external-xref>), by striking paragraph (4);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6A4A05768B5E40E687DD617915319BCA"><enum>(17)</enum><text>in section 11A(f) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1821a">12 U.S.C. 1821a(f)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6683579532CB469FA9E7BC8EFF08A7F4"><enum>(18)</enum><text>in section 12(f)(4)(E)(iv) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1822">12 U.S.C. 1822(f)(4)(E)(iv)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>Federal deposit insurance funds</quote> and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund (or any predecessor deposit insurance fund)</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6593F6576FD74E0F87B5A264FC2430B0"><enum>(19)</enum><text>in section 13 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1823">12 U.S.C. 1823</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H16FD72474D0F4C749CFDF24C94DDDBE8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>deposit insurance fund</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H101270E804F1452FB7C45942717F8C36"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1), by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund, the Savings Association Insurance Fund,</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3B9DE91FDEFC413A80D7977B3724B9C4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(4)(E)—</text> 
<clause id="H2EF7AE973E304206811F6DD18D254627"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the subparagraph heading, by striking <quote>funds</quote> and inserting <quote>fund</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H04E800B79A45409E89B6CCF0A6E07ED3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>any insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H013FAA500218492DA7256BAECF86760"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(4)(G)(ii)—</text> 
<clause id="H304257957F05494C8D1BC33FC7CE054"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>appropriate insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9653BC4B2C3E44388F95426FF5F8B85E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the members of the insurance fund (of which such institution is a member)</quote> and inserting <quote>insured depository institutions</quote>;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBA9D88F280484C849189F332B3693405"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>each member’s</quote> and inserting <quote>each insured depository institution’s</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2BB8EEA2D5A04C00BB1396BC6E3BC369"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the member’s</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>the institution’s</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB43E63245AAC49F4A7866714AD68E9E4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by striking paragraph (11);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4D2562B28577420FB1BEDD42C067D790"><enum>(F)</enum><text>in subsection (h), by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H57D33A6F3D454D9D8618101F29E4E7B"><enum>(G)</enum><text>in subsection (k)(4)(B)(i), by striking <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund member</quote> and inserting <quote>savings association</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE211A3214F94428FAABF5600A45BF8FA"><enum>(H)</enum><text>in subsection (k)(5)(A), by striking <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund members</quote> and inserting <quote>savings associations</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEBB801FBA61546099B158F47EABE3F00"><enum>(20)</enum><text>in section 14(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1824">12 U.S.C. 1824(a)</external-xref>), in the 5th sentence—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD0E5A997D9E14271BD1CCE3C5061C377"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund or the Savings Association Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1CE946B22DC444A9B7897FC344E76240"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>each such fund</quote> and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H514F462F13A64DC5997919369858004D"><enum>(21)</enum><text>in section 14(b) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1824">12 U.S.C. 1824(b)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund or Savings Association Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8D5B9EA4A24F46FDB1DCCB527721D5DB"><enum>(22)</enum><text>in section 14(c) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1824">12 U.S.C. 1824(c)</external-xref>), by striking paragraph (3);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA7C844BE7213409F88B23B686343BFB6"><enum>(23)</enum><text>in section 14(d) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1824">12 U.S.C. 1824(d)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB1137617208444DC868CCB42CDB275E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund member</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>insured depository institution</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3727591B6FC247569B08EF6F52E0EFD3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund members</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>insured depository institutions</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H117F3435CE4D4BD2A037DBB934F44192"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund</quote> each place that term appears (other than in connection with a reference to a term amended by subparagraph (A) or (B) of this paragraph) and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7BC4D6AE1A454F7F8948CB0013078299"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by striking the subsection heading and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H54B3BDF738F04C8BAC00A029006586E1"> 
<subsection id="HBB929831E8B643EC9973CF40DF8985E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Borrowing for the Deposit Insurance Fund from insured depository institutions</header></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD9C2BEDB432946079FE9004B32FE51A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), in the paragraph heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">bif</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">the deposit insurance fund</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE436284D855E42CB97A7BEE293450000"><enum>(F)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), in the paragraph heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">bif members</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">insured depository institutions</header-in-text></quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H765DAC11C3C74E009824CD6FFB071BA"><enum>(24)</enum><text>in section 14 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1824">12 U.S.C. 1824</external-xref>), by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H75E585A7C7474FEA8EFAD43095B261B"> 
<subsection id="HE75FD646986848BE92E700CC857EEF8E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Borrowing for the Deposit Insurance Fund from Federal home loan banks</header> 
<paragraph id="H3C4755ACA4F843AB84BA5B00A9C77EC3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Corporation may borrow from the Federal home loan banks, with the concurrence of the Federal Housing Finance Board, such funds as the Corporation considers necessary for the use of the Deposit Insurance Fund.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1A5547AB2C074F70B71C21DB5495B6C6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Terms and conditions</header><text>Any loan from any Federal home loan bank under paragraph (1) to the Deposit Insurance Fund shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6D62D737B1DF47D6A7448D75F2293B98"><enum>(A)</enum><text>bear a rate of interest of not less than the current marginal cost of funds to that bank, taking into account the maturities involved;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2F8657B7962B43BDB9D16E76AA670006"><enum>(B)</enum><text>be adequately secured, as determined by the Federal Housing Finance Board;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H64305E479B7C48ABACCC5BE07D31EE29"><enum>(C)</enum><text>be a direct liability of the Deposit Insurance Fund; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3503D612F5C24256888973A39F264019"><enum>(D)</enum><text>be subject to the limitations of section 15(c).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8348F70C68D145DFAA7D0029BF58CA77"><enum>(25)</enum><text>in section 15(c)(5) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1825">12 U.S.C. 1825(c)(5)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEE96BC819F9D4B759C678301D2EBFE9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the Bank Insurance Fund or Savings Association Insurance Fund, respectively</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H47D6CAC9835E435EACB789B89DC5FB7E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>the Bank Insurance Fund or the Savings Association Insurance Fund, respectively</quote> and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCDBF76F66AC8447BA26275BE916B3097"><enum>(26)</enum><text>in section 17(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1827">12 U.S.C. 1827(a)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFD419BEA0AF24E7D002CFA32C9C7CE92"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the subsection heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">BIF, SAIF,</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">the Deposit Insurance Fund</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4007EEFE1969450D0025A282CE54DF99"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> 
<clause id="HFBA3B8561308441F8DBA6F9399AAD9C9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the Bank Insurance Fund, the Savings Association Insurance Fund,</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD97FAC616FC3444485F3C04F545564A8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>each insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2E94424D3EEE462C89EB647ED4737476"><enum>(27)</enum><text>in section 17(d) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1827">12 U.S.C. 1827(d)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>, the Bank Insurance Fund, the Savings Association Insurance Fund,</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3E3544D7A60344488C933676D4FD50ED"><enum>(28)</enum><text>in section 18(m)(3) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1828">12 U.S.C. 1828(m)(3)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H068FA8D69408420BACDFB28003BE01F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund</quote> in the 1st sentence of subparagraph (A) and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEC7ACFA2683C4F51AADBDDDE4EE152E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund member</quote> in the last sentence of subparagraph (A) and inserting <quote>savings association</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H45C6B51C080644588DCCB39CDE51232D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund or the Bank Insurance Fund</quote> in subparagraph (C) and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2EDA636939674D3CBCA1A5249F54D549"><enum>(29)</enum><text>in section 18(o) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1828">12 U.S.C. 1828(o)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>deposit insurance funds</quote> and <quote>deposit insurance fund</quote> each place those terms appear and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB889E5EEBF9D4F31A279A00500687D3F"><enum>(30)</enum><text>in section 18(p) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1828">12 U.S.C. 1828(p)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>deposit insurance funds</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC700049A53C6454DA17119DDBB7D0239"><enum>(31)</enum><text>in section 24 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1831a">12 U.S.C. 1831a</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3D471F81FF21458186C039F5C86B8B4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsections (a)(1) and (d)(1)(A), by striking <quote>appropriate deposit insurance fund</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H87EDB0F52CA74A30A059FAE41D6B83D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(2)(A), by striking <quote>risk to</quote> and all that follows through the period and inserting <quote>risk to the Deposit Insurance Fund.</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD10E4C07266E4CCEBE881CCBC214007F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsections (e)(2)(B)(ii) and (f)(6)(B), by striking <quote>the insurance fund of which such bank is a member</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE8012AEEFAB0405AAF3700786566C8E3"><enum>(32)</enum><text>in section 28 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1831e">12 U.S.C. 1831e</external-xref>), by striking <quote>affected deposit insurance fund</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDEB5307B37EE46769F296B62B45CF433"><enum>(33)</enum><text>by striking section 31 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1831h">12 U.S.C. 1831h</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDB4C5D342D734208AD06D0744649D4CD"><enum>(34)</enum><text>in section 36(i)(3) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1831m">12 U.S.C. 1831m(i)(3)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>affected deposit insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H36E87A16BC9F4190A4CEEB6335C6C900"><enum>(35)</enum><text>in section 37(a)(1)(C) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1831n">12 U.S.C. 1831n(a)(1)(C)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>insurance funds</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5D516B271F5D4B37B45B1BE9259BC9D"><enum>(36)</enum><text>in section 38 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1831o">12 U.S.C. 1831o</external-xref>), by striking <quote>the deposit insurance fund</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HED263F09E3CB4BCD000455589EFFDFC"><enum>(37)</enum><text>in section 38(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1831o">12 U.S.C. 1831o(a)</external-xref>), in the subsection heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Funds</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Fund</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HED1CCBE6783640699F9FD14016044946"><enum>(38)</enum><text>in section 38(k) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1831o">12 U.S.C. 1831o(k)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H229B5247C4134F7D974E4F3196C99E5E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>a deposit insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAB46D556FE414B8187EBE9451389086D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>A deposit insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>The Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H91860BE9D1E6475FA6465FB65935C156"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraphs (2)(A) and (3)(B), by striking <quote>the deposit insurance fund’s outlays</quote> each place that term appears and inserting <quote>the outlays of the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8397AC2EAEE449F78F00437C923F3B02"><enum>(39)</enum><text>in section 38(o) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1831o">12 U.S.C. 1831o(o)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBD44D9C68300401491134CE448C0CD9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Associations</header-in-text>.—</quote> and all that follows through <quote>Subsections (e)(2)</quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Associations</header-in-text>.—Subsections (e)(2)</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9B834E51AB3E47418738EE001186F743"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C) as paragraphs (1), (2), and (3), respectively, and moving the margins 2 ems to the left; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H45C2130E822B4EF48243BCB4EEA0EDCF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (1) (as so redesignated), by redesignating clauses (i) and (ii) as subparagraphs (A) and (B), respectively, and moving the margins 2 ems to the left.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE10662144446402CB3D27E3480599724"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section and the amendments made by this section shall take effect on the first day of the first calendar quarter that begins after the end of the 90-day period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H8BC2620DABA145DC8577AA1920581FB4"><enum>13.</enum><header>Other technical and conforming amendments relating to the merger of the BIF and SAIF</header> 
<subsection id="HFF19E04DE7C74FF5A303780067F8478F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Section 5136 of the revised statutes</header><text>The paragraph designated the <quote>Eleventh</quote> of section 5136 of the Revised Statutes of the United States (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/24">12 U.S.C. 24</external-xref>) is amended in the 5th sentence, by striking <quote>affected deposit insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H25F9071BDA43496DBD6F59B9AA3C95DF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Investments promoting public welfare; limitations on aggregate investments</header><text>The 23d undesignated paragraph of section 9 of the <act-name parsable-cite="FRA">Federal Reserve Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/338a">12 U.S.C. 338a</external-xref>) is amended in the 4th sentence, by striking <quote>affected deposit insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2460140E0E4A4060BBEBF6581804F35"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Advances to critically undercapitalized depository institutions</header><text>Section 10B(b)(3)(A)(ii) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FRA">Federal Reserve Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/347b">12 U.S.C. 347b(b)(3)(A)(ii)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>any deposit insurance fund in</quote> and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund of</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H786BB6B4E5EF45E9811139BC6CC3D473"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Amendments to the Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985</header><text>Section 255(g)(1)(A) of the Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/905">2 U.S.C. 905(g)(1)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBFCA8ED54DF44156AAB743A022001B07"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEE50D497BBB345EDB2BB005B269DA000"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, Savings Association Insurance Fund (51–4066–0–3–373);</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBCEB2DD600BD459FBC5EF300E1FDC779"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Amendments to the <act-name parsable-cite="FHLBA">Federal Home Loan Bank Act</act-name></header><text>The <act-name parsable-cite="FHLBA">Federal Home Loan Bank Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1421">12 U.S.C. 1421 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H233C6AF7006B441BA316159CA00AAFD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 11(k) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1431">12 U.S.C. 1431(k)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBD17ED5E62944CFF96718941113F6059"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the subsection heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">SAIF</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">the Deposit Insurance Fund</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAD05890BD5734CFDA68E84CCF4518F3C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D8F4D87366F426CB8AC3FA8FF325F34"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 21 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1441">12 U.S.C. 1441</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBFA6D3FDD5A84671AE45D7FB83924638"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (f)(2), by striking <quote>, except that</quote> and all that follows through the end of the paragraph and inserting a period; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H43F435E8DC534E76AE65B4D29C439F00"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (k), by striking paragraph (4);</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3AC97BCE0D6A43DF8EF97C6062B12EE9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 21A(b)(4)(B) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1441a">12 U.S.C. 1441a(b)(4)(B)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>affected deposit insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7810218EB7184256A627D628311B661C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 21A(b)(6)(B) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1441a">12 U.S.C. 1441a(b)(6)(B)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2C8FAA1F826D4693B3E7EF00DEC61922"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the subparagraph heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">SAIF-insured banks</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Charter conversions</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H516795CAFE154B33A7D6C23C19AB8B25"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund member</quote> and inserting <quote>savings association</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8FD2DAFD747F427C900532E77006900"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in section 21A(b)(10)(A)(iv)(II) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1441a">12 U.S.C. 1441a(b)(10)(A)(iv)(II)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCBCFF19FAA014290B41730728058AF99"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in section 21A(n)(6)(E)(iv) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1441">12 U.S.C. 1441(n)(6)(E)(iv)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>Federal deposit insurance funds</quote> and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H346DB27088124391A03148BA31082D16"><enum>(7)</enum><text>in section 21B(e) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1441b">12 U.S.C. 1441b(e)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA59E47305E2D4278813E7640FEB0044F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by inserting <quote>as of the date of funding</quote> after <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund members</quote> each place that term appears; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA3C5543E7332485CBB00124DE3E03BDC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking paragraphs (7) and (8); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3999D24978C447E7A37DF2B987A47900"><enum>(8)</enum><text>in section 21B(k) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1441b">12 U.S.C. 1441b(k)</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7D6DDA6AEBD542D2A5F4541FC804C892"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting before the colon <quote>, the following definitions shall apply</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H437F5E07449C4C05B9431BB3FF39F6A4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (8); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEFC49727CF1642A38EA89F16C752CBA2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (9) and (10) as paragraphs (8) and (9), respectively.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE83FB744882148C3922B16A2A7ACE5A5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Amendments to the Home Owners’ Loan Act</header><text>The <act-name parsable-cite="HOLA">Home Owners’ Loan Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1461">12 U.S.C. 1461 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0DD2FD269D694CB1A145975EEA85906E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 5 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1464">12 U.S.C. 1464</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3F04C09331D0441380892C6312BBCC56"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(5)(A), by striking <quote>that is a member of the Bank Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H81292FA58D1B4DE3B84F1C35A59969F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(6), by striking <quote>As used in this subsection—</quote> and inserting <quote>For purposes of this subsection, the following definitions shall apply:</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H131B3CF3BA5F438BBAB0A5D3DB8D174F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (o)(1), by striking <quote>that is a Bank Insurance Fund member</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6255CB7787814C2A98E6ACE1B88B8847"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subsection (o)(2)(A), by striking <quote>a Bank Insurance Fund member until such time as it changes its status to a Savings Association Insurance Fund member</quote> and inserting <quote>insured by the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H359D3FC9BD95459698618C10F5AB8BCE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in subsection (t)(5)(D)(iii)(II), by striking <quote>affected deposit insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0190AF5026B8402DA1368EDBAB86E8E4"><enum>(F)</enum><text>in subsection (t)(7)(C)(i)(I), by striking <quote>affected deposit insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAD6AB8C9046D47D2839C51DD76B913FA"><enum>(G)</enum><text>in subsection (v)(2)(A)(i), by striking <quote>the Savings Association Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>or the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8C75C1AFFA104B23A20693D6F4531E8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 10 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1467a">12 U.S.C. 1467a</external-xref>)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE96A1AB534AC4ED9996644B1AE8E74D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(6)(D), by striking <quote>this title</quote> and inserting <quote>this Act</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9164B3A4631446B59497EB4666D8A418"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(1)(B), by striking <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund or Bank Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1E05A44809584B589E1112743C97E7C1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(2), by striking <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund or the Bank Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3CC22698F8994689913880B7B2628759"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(4)(B), by striking <quote>subsection (1)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (l)</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H307EECFEA721444A8D62CD66E75EC181"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in subsection (g)(3)(A), by striking <quote>(5) of this section</quote> and inserting <quote>(5) of this subsection</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1B0BA57A1F4149CD898957F08BB59DD"><enum>(F)</enum><text>in subsection (i), by redesignating paragraph (5) as paragraph (4);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7F23F1A3963142C69109243EC5D03868"><enum>(G)</enum><text>in subsection (m)(3), by striking subparagraph (E) and by redesignating subparagraphs (F), (G), and (H) as subparagraphs (E), (F), and (G), respectively;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAE298F859321413992503597BBA15013"><enum>(H)</enum><text>in subsection (m)(7)(A), by striking <quote>during period</quote> and inserting <quote>during the period</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H857E7797F4F24F61A99ED8B94401174E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in subsection (o)(3)(D), by striking <quote>sections 5(s) and (t) of this Act</quote> and inserting <quote>subsections (s) and (t) of section 5</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H875F760959B2478E9BF5CC136912B5D1"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Amendments to the <act-name parsable-cite="NHA">National Housing Act</act-name></header><text>The <act-name parsable-cite="NHA">National Housing Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1701">12 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF85FAB43755F418000FED1C0D31422CF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 317(b)(1)(B) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1723i">12 U.S.C. 1723i(b)(1)(B)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund for banks or through the Savings Association Insurance Fund for savings associations</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0C5950648AD84133B0A024BC8DCF842C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 536(b)(1)(B)(ii) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1735f-14">12 U.S.C. 1735f–14(b)(1)(B)(ii)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund for banks and through the Savings Association Insurance Fund for savings associations</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H19311ECB9DD44E9D81D0A7D61F007C7B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Amendments to the financial institutions reform, recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989</header><text>The Financial Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1811">12 U.S.C. 1811</external-xref> note) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H86BBC1401E95476A8E5F3E80A87F67C0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 951(b)(3)(B) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1833a">12 U.S.C. 1833a(b)(3)(B)</external-xref>), by inserting <quote>and after the merger of such funds, the Deposit Insurance Fund,</quote> after <quote>the Savings Association Insurance Fund,</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H48959B8F63724CC1B7ECB5C4D4005977"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 1112(c)(1)(B) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3341">12 U.S.C. 3341(c)(1)(B)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>Bank Insurance Fund, the Savings Association Insurance Fund,</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE12EFD00786C4561AACCDD33500013CD"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Amendment to the <act-name parsable-cite="BHC65">Bank Holding Company Act of 1956</act-name></header><text>The <act-name parsable-cite="BHC65">Bank Holding Company Act of 1956</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1841">12 U.S.C. 1841 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9167B324148F4A259452D78279AFBB69"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 2(j)(2) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1841">12 U.S.C. 1841(j)(2)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>Savings Association Insurance Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC593673F1852458CB8C8983B83954C09"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 3(d)(1)(D)(iii) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1842">12 U.S.C. 1842(d)(1)(D)(iii)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>appropriate deposit insurance fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBB9D7CB8A6D2418FACDABBB717529710"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Amendments to the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act</header><text>Section 114 of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1828a">12 U.S.C. 1828a</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>any Federal deposit insurance fund</quote> in subsection (a)(1)(B), paragraphs (2)(B) and (4)(B) of subsection (b), and subsection (c)(1)(B), each place that term appears and inserting <quote>the Deposit Insurance Fund</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H59D2760B2EA545649FBC007B1787AABF"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section and the amendments made by this section shall take effect on the first day of the first calendar quarter that begins after the end of the 90-day period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


