<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDCF6396C351142FA8287F6DCF17EFF55" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>109 HR 4650 IH: National Levee Safety Program Act of 2005</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2005-12-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>109th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 4650</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20051222">December 22, 2005</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000533">Mr. Duncan</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="J000126">Ms. Eddie Bernice Johnson of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Y000033">Mr. Young of Alaska</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000006">Mr. Oberstar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001255">Mr. Boustany</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000072">Mr. Baker</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001161">Mr. Melancon</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To direct the Secretary of the Army to carry out programs and activities to enhance the safety of levees in the United States.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H9004BBED4A0F424A989D451BA330CB09" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H8D2568EDA0EC40E99C199C8119DFA22C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Levee Safety Program Act of 2005</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> 
<section id="HDD1BF53E604E4DA793B37AFE0999384"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the following definitions apply:</text> 
<paragraph id="H29BF2C726F1D4337B8945955EB7A902"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Board</header><text>The term <term>Board</term> means the National Levee Safety Review Board established under section 6(a).</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2535B6D6FD46455EBEDEBFA052B8EC26"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Committee</header><text>The term <term>Committee</term> means the Interagency Committee on Levee Safety established under section 5(a).</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H66EE2549A830401700D3A8B0C4D5400"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Levee</header> 
<subparagraph id="H22EF59637F544F278644409C4D8F00BC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>levee</term> means an embankment (including floodwalls)—</text> 
<clause id="H8A9690F8A87245008BCF1DC889A4C524"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the primary purpose of which is to provide hurricane and flood protection relating to seasonal high water and storm surges; and</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H80C56415E03B44F400F1D5C795DE2D67"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that normally is subject to water loading for only a few days or weeks during a year.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCF897F2016CE46E7B78F72C3AE669DCB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>levee</quote> includes structures along drainage canals that are subject to more frequent water loadings but that do not constitute a barrier across a watercourse. </text> </subparagraph> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEE80B2F8E0994A47A9F2C9748E592803"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <term>Federal agency</term> means a Federal agency that designs, finances, constructs, owns, operates, maintains, or regulates the construction, operation, or maintenance of a levee.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5BED67D43B514CBD848EC77912875912"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Army, acting through the Chief of Engineers.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6AFB52AF07654500B246C14DEC54FD9"><enum>(6)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3E1954CA477D413481BE985665A73097"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0618EE88D89643A792FE5E00F03D6172"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the District of Columbia;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA1ACCA9CB00E4F328099A9914ACE87C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC60E8B1BEDC74DBBA816E5FED4DCCFF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other territory or possession of the United States.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6F978731C25C4958AA49005B30C59503"><enum>(7)</enum><header>State levee safety agency</header><text>The term <term>State levee safety agency</term> means the State agency that has regulatory authority over the safety of any non-Federal levee in a State.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA4F65C1C91E64672B23FE75B89E5EDB8"><enum>(8)</enum><header>United States</header><text>The term <term>United States</term>, when used in a geographical sense, means all of the States.</text> </paragraph></section> 
<section id="H5226C04CC9554749BDBD9FDE90E3C121"><enum>3.</enum><header>Inspection of levees</header> 
<subsection id="H9299C88FC3FD4509B6EF5ECDEF5425F4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out a program under which, as soon as practicable after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall inspect levees in the United States for the purpose of protecting human life and property.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HAE64328A82C54CDBAA6EBF0400599F55"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Levees to be inspected</header> 
<paragraph id="H4325FA24BF434F8FA118FE96A91C6FD0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program under subsection (a), the Secretary shall inspect—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H388154C9468549B4A2C1FF6B61C1F8E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each levee in the United States constructed by the Secretary;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4DEDE9F8B59A42C79849F64F98630886"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each levee in the United States maintained by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1A473FA9D9B64017A41B4297CC3FBAA3"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each levee located in a State identified by the Governor of the State in a list transmitted to the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H69EB1930009341A9853C90D620005C32"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (1), in carrying out the program under subsection (a), the Secretary shall not be required to inspect—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAC301394DFBB44BF9D344505CEF9E958"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any levee that has been inspected by a State levee safety agency during the 1-year period immediately preceding the date of enactment of this Act, if the Governor of the State requests an exception; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB267943D9B494BA58CCD16FC0070E336"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any levee that the Secretary determines would not pose a significant threat to human life or property in case of failure.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H811B3E84BDC44BBDAE5DA0EB44EBEB9B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>State participation</header><text>On request of a State levee safety agency, with respect to any levee the failure of which would affect the State, the head of a Federal agency shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HDB65DC5DF2174A72B1B69B446307CEB7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide information to the State levee safety agency relating to the construction, operation, or maintenance of the levee; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCD611755CAA646E59B646F75B5F83400"><enum>(2)</enum><text>allow an official of the State levee safety agency to participate in the inspection of the levee.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF8993FD3E23742BE9385B0FCEB8600F6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Determination</header> 
<paragraph id="H84627BC04C494090AD54A39CD63FE16B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Inspection requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of determining whether the failure a levee, including the release of any water constrained by the levee, constitutes a danger to human life or property, the Secretary shall take into consideration the possibility that the levee may be in danger of failing due to disparities in floodwall height or construction materials, overtopping due to storm surges, seepage, settlement, piping or internal erosion, sediment, cracking, earth movement, earthquakes, hurricanes, the failure of bulkheads or sheet walls, flashboards, gates or conduits, or other conditions that exist or may occur in any area in the vicinity of the levee.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8A6E826745164BA28BC32D772F72A806"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Previously-inspected levees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For any levee with respect to which the Secretary made any determination regarding the safety of the levee before the date of the inspection of the levee under this section, the Secretary shall review the determination, taking into consideration information most recently available to the Secretary relating to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5B69E5B69891486CAF052CA749B52499"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the likelihood that a storm surge would exceed the designed level of protection of the levee; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6DB14360281E4F8C8FB03FAFD4F07D4D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the effect of wetlands erosion, subsidence, or any other natural process on the vulnerability of the area surrounding the levee to flooding or an extreme weather event.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7F7A86F6B2704B4098E57C5BEF209C4B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Inspection results</header> 
<paragraph id="H4DAA4159C2F24FCA86F791FD00BAAB9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice to states</header><text>As soon as practicable after the inspection of a levee, the Secretary shall notify the Governor of the State in which such levee is located of the results of the inspection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H95776420D93D4D588863535B409C2341"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Hazardous conditions</header> 
<subparagraph id="HB57EA8399F334E2BA3A7F50900D411B0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Engineering studies</header><text>In any case in which a hazardous condition is found during an inspection of a levee, the Secretary may perform, upon request of the owner of the levee, detailed engineering studies to determine the structural integrity of the levee, subject to reimbursement of such expense by the owner.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDC06F873FCFF462AA8620015FD090044"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notice and remedial measures</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> 
<clause id="HD5D94895D9614F5F90F821F6ACBC2CA8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>immediately notify the Governor of a State of a hazardous condition found during an inspection of a levee located in the State under subparagraph (A); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1C7591ECFC994CDDB0A0174775B40000"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide to the Governor, upon request, advice relating to timely remedial measures necessary to mitigate or obviate the hazardous condition.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8668E8DCDBA4420F98A880AF5BF0DE8C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Priority list</header> 
<paragraph id="H2F59A0B3E18E487D9C85C3CFAA5287F0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than August 1 of each year, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a priority list of flood damage reduction studies and projects that constitutes a ranking of studies and projects that should be carried out, taking into consideration the results of any inspection under this section. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9B7155033EF94F68A5804EF8646ADFC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In establishing the priority list under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consider—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H452E39A33BD444B4B0FA9EDD6E751984"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the potential risk to human life or the environment if a study or project to address potential flood damage is not carried out;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBA8C78C51A68465989A4927422BD09D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the benefits of protecting critical infrastructure and population centers; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD758DF807B8F4E219112CDBBF035EF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the implementation of Federal guidelines relating to levee safety.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection></section> 
<section id="H25A01BA67D2C4BF0A2B9F1FAB4F5B77"><enum>4.</enum><header>National levee inventory</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary may maintain and periodically publish an inventory of levees in the United States, including the results of any levee inspection conducted under section 3.</text> </section> 
<section id="HA2A3F31284FD4D7A00036342F2B7BF9"><enum>5.</enum><header>Interagency Committee on Levee Safety</header> 
<subsection id="HCE3EC723A0124472813716CF13D81D82"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established a committee to be known as the <quote>Interagency Committee on Levee Safety</quote>.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H676A401245F04F7B8F9E018440C33432"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Committee shall be composed of 4 members as follows:</text> 
<paragraph id="H5DEDBF234933459D9DEB6760D2F7F682"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary (or the Secretary’s designee), who shall serve as the chairperson of the Committee.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HABFEBD5A57534E9000165F4BA9437751"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary of Agriculture (or the Secretary’s designee).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3CDBBC7521FD4BC490843E2DDECE01F9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Secretary of the Interior (or the Secretary’s designee).</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC8011039160F494682D26D7355BB208D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Director of the Federal Emergency Management Agency (or the Director’s designee).</text> </paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H36826CF60CC14AE9ADCA1295C564C838"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Committee shall support the establishment and maintenance of effective Federal programs, policies, and guidelines to enhance levee safety for the protection of human life and property through coordination and information exchange among Federal agencies concerning the implementation of Federal guidelines relating to levee safety.</text> </subsection></section> 
<section id="HDB8EA3BEF3124C4100AA977DD4322FCC"><enum>6.</enum><header>National Levee Safety Review Board</header> 
<subsection id="H132F79B75CE5417FA8B2B04269C127E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall establish an advisory board, to be known as the <quote>National Levee Safety Review Board</quote>, to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1E176C49289648A78D04214B2046431D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>monitor the safety of levees in the United States;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H080A4A37477345BB83D3E6C8DB764EED"><enum>(2)</enum><text>monitor the implementation of this Act by State levee safety agencies; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H36F31D2ADEB34E0394BC990000885009"><enum>(3)</enum><text>advise the Secretary on policy relating to national levee safety.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7F2C7F1B6E4D474884A38CE5D3B3F6C6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header> 
<paragraph id="H0A02559A421F4F619E6338F21E2CF615"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Voting members</header><text>The Board shall be composed of 10 voting members as follows:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD389F25BEA2B40D08016CCF7996B63C8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary (or the Secretary’s designee), who shall serve as the chairperson of the Board.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8848034C2AD34BFD899773D1895985D0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture (or the Secretary’s designee).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H86409404C77C4411AAF5CB19BFD0A54F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Secretary of the Interior (or the Secretary’s designee).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4154C1172B694848B74540367B1D691C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency (or the Administrator’s designee).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBBE2CE3601074C68BCC11C5995316130"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Director of the Federal Emergency Management Agency (or the Director’s designee).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7227C896B4184620AB143DA744469D8C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>4 representatives of State levee safety agencies, to be appointed by the Secretary.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2CA10536142E42B3B8512EFC0069EC3E"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">1 representative of the private sector who has expertise in levee safety, to be appointed by the Secretary.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4D1A2675C02F46D19BFF3956A2D034C5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Nonvoting members</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the voting members of the Board, may invite to participate in meetings of the Board as a nonvoting member—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8C113FE0955F463AA45429479F033DDB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a representative of the National Laboratories;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBE8A6436683949B69E1C4E8049B54BA6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a representative of any Federal or State agency; or</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H285BABF93D604CEDA654E27EA8509B07"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a levee safety expert.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H71B70C1B6F2D4345A94E2C1108C591A5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text></text> 
<paragraph id="HEB44C811208640F98FB4A8BC45B8D5B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board shall support the establishment and maintenance of effective programs, policies, and guidelines to enhance levee safety for the protection of human life and property throughout the United States.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H90DAC4FD085F46E28B66A57372BA8409"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coordination and information exchange among agencies</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Board shall support coordination and information exchange among Federal agencies and State levee safety agencies that share common problems and responsibilities relating to levee safety, including planning, design, construction, operation, emergency action planning, inspections, maintenance, regulation or licensing, technical or financial assistance, research, and data management.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2A8001372C7E4B9CA1AF83F982D744E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Contracts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board may use the expertise of Federal agencies and request the Secretary to enter into contracts for necessary studies to carry out this section.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HC2F78AC2BE8149DA00285C6F2FB34CFD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Working groups</header> 
<paragraph id="H78F4A33641C24FD1B52C006CBC438EDF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Board, may establish working groups to assist the Board in carrying out this section.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDE1EDE7B87E14396008D2F6813688400"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>A working group under paragraph (1) shall be composed of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H69AA7D51D8384E8493B0CCDB07F325D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>members of the Board; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9EA09499387041EE83A5B1E5917CC28"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other individual, as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD19FC864E7DE4BDCB768A5186F204700"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Compensation of members</header><text></text> 
<paragraph id="H96AB04F2FE8345DC8EA299E67E297F43"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal employees</header><text>A member of the Board who is an officer or employee of the United States shall serve without compensation in addition to compensation received for the services of the member as an officer or employee of the United States.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4E9739D31AD94DAEA9748E673FA11E00"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other members</header><text>A member of the Board who is not an officer or employee of the United States shall serve without compensation.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6C6632072B844E4FA9D8C454A4042ED"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Travel expenses</header><text></text> 
<paragraph id="HACF2193683264F1A936419B19B805D7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Representatives of Federal agencies</header><text>To the extent amounts are made available in advance in appropriations Acts, a member of the Board who represents a Federal agency shall be reimbursed for travel expenses by the agency of the member, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, at rates authorized for an employee of an agency under subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, while away from home or regular place of business of the member in the performance of services for the Board.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H515252DCF80F4DC19CB913D2216AD41"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other individuals</header><text>To the extent amounts are made available in advance in appropriations Acts, a member of the Board who represents a State levee safety agency, a member of the Board who represents the private sector, and a member of a working group created under subsection (e) shall be reimbursed for travel expenses by the Secretary, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, at rates authorized for an employee of an agency under subchapter 1 of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, while away from home or regular place of business of the member in performance of services for the Board.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H64A3F7D14D014273A714F55E147827C8"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Applicability of federal advisory committee act</header><text>The Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.) shall not apply to the Board.</text> </subsection></section> 
<section id="HA988B686C59B49CA9CAA00A0C75415B2"><enum>7.</enum><header>National levee safety program</header> 
<subsection id="H9C103B6F52574401A766EEF69F7ED45E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Committee, the Board, and State levee safety agencies, shall establish and maintain a national levee safety program.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HDB3AEDBCEF3F4F84AB1786D594578785"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of the program under this section are—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2C5DB4BB0E0C4DD1B4D17464C9EF8166"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to ensure that new and existing levees are safe through the development of technologically and economically feasible programs and procedures for hazard reduction relating to levees;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8933C220D9FE462E83B3DA9007523A2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to encourage acceptable engineering policies and procedures to be used for levee site investigation, design, construction, operation and maintenance, and emergency preparedness;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H559CD1FDF3B340A5B501BD8745A8F282"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to encourage the establishment and implementation of effective levee safety programs in each State based on State standards;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD893409A900D4ED9A278DB8BA610083"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to develop and support public education and awareness projects to increase public acceptance and support of State levee safety programs;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H269E238B7607444298C1867B4D7EA738"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to develop technical assistance materials for Federal and State levee safety programs;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC8C0B9ACDE7549AABD2B6EA8003307C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to develop methods of providing technical assistance relating to levee safety to non-Federal entities; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3105F0E60ED947B3ABBF82B7559D3C4E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to develop technical assistance materials, seminars, and guidelines to improve the security of levees in the United States.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6411DEF85D4843F7A8BB5FE70436B32"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Strategic plan</header><text>In carrying out the program under this section, the Secretary shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC217AE5999874F979E23DEFAF6BD0008"><enum>(1)</enum><text>prepare a strategic plan to achieve the purposes of the program under this section; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA53F5AD27E99455FB0BBD6DA3016A646"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, transmit the plan to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB932A615F74A4B5C95E4825D937C0097"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Federal guidelines</header> 
<paragraph id="H87C13D7AA74644C78220366FF93437F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the program under this section, the Secretary, in consultation with the Board, shall establish Federal guidelines relating to levee safety.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5FA7BD222636441C9DCC978CCB7D85C9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Incorporation of Federal activities</header><text>The Federal guidelines under paragraph (1) shall incorporate, to the maximum extent practicable, activities and practices carried out by a Federal agency as of the date on which the guidelines are established.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDD83A4FB7DF64FF7A405009C6B531DA7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Incorporation of State and local activities</header><text>The program under this section shall incorporate, to the maximum extent practicable—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFD719EE444764D0F9E474505A6007810"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the activities and practices carried out by States, local governments, and the private sector to safely build, regulate, operate, and maintain levees; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBBC04D8330C44ABC887BCE62E46CEB93"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Federal activities that foster State efforts to develop and implement effective programs for the safety of levees.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1083DE154F4D422C9141BA9B2FEBBFC5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Assistance for State levee safety programs</header> 
<paragraph id="H32A0FA63921F43638F6128635E55A2DB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To encourage the establishment and maintenance of effective State programs intended to ensure levee safety, to protect human life and public property, and to improve State levee safety programs, the Secretary shall provide assistance, using amounts made to carry out this Act, to assist States in establishing and carrying out levee safety programs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H317D639513514B128065E593A03C5934"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>To be eligible for assistance under this subsection, a State shall have in effect a State levee safety program under which the State levee safety agency shall, in accordance with State law—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H081582857B5644ADA7C52BAF5C5DFA5C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>review and approve plans and specifications to construct, enlarge, modify, remove, and abandon levees;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H12D42A682E074FBE90253300E02FE2BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>perform periodic inspections during levee construction to ensure compliance with approved plans and specifications; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB5FBEE4A7CD1448491F92C66B43340B0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>require or perform the inspection, at least once every 5 years, of all levees that would pose a significant threat to human life and public property in case of failure to determine the continued safety of the levees and a procedure for more detailed and frequent safety inspections;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3EF5BB9CD8BE49D6B8D934280017FDAC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>require that all inspections of levees be performed under the supervision of a State-registered professional engineer with related experience in levee design and construction; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H50DA844A31BC453997443055E7957545"><enum>(E)</enum><text>issue notices, when appropriate, to require owners of levees to perform necessary maintenance or remedial work, improve security, revise operating procedures, or take other actions, including breaching levees when necessary; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H97BC9FBD21B84B728EA960882D5E48BF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>provide necessary funds—</text> 
<clause id="H9EA3982A4B164527A7AB7990E0E51175"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to ensure timely repairs or other changes to, or removal of, a levee in order to protect human life and public property; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4857FD798B2F42F8959B000044406170"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the owner of the levee does not take an action described in clause (i), to take appropriate action as expeditiously as practicable; </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H448F45E37489403096A3F2B883C985FF"><enum>(G)</enum><text>establish a system of emergency procedures to be used if a levee fails or if the failure of a levee is imminent;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4B1322143A0440499162D764EB11CCCF"><enum>(H)</enum><text>identify—</text> 
<clause id="HF3881B50C9D646C583C3E2A1B7E490ED"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each levee the failure of which could be reasonably expected to endanger human life;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H745015AE7FCF41318682566CAC5E912F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the maximum area that could be flooded if the levee failed; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0B25DA95678E48CD97AF548988A9E1E1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>necessary public facilities that would be affected by the flooding; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4376F5CA965E40FBA63F9C80750098AA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>issue regulations to carry out the program. </text></subparagraph> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0AB665DB6901413992DACF786CDF21EE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Budgeting requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for assistance under this subsection, a State shall allocate sufficient funds in its budget to carry out a State levee safety program. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBAA60ED0BB9F45A9AABD8340895BE380"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Work plans</header><text>The Secretary shall enter into an agreement with each State receiving assistance under this subsection to develop a work plan necessary for the State levee safety program to reach a level of program performance specified in the agreement.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF9F097D45AD643ED9D864865639300C0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort</header><text>Assistance may not be provided to a State under this subsection for a fiscal year unless the State enters into such agreement with the Secretary as the Secretary requires to ensure that the State will maintain the aggregate expenditures of the State from all other sources for programs to ensure levee safety for the protection of human life and property at or above a level equal to the average annual level of such expenditures for the 2 fiscal years preceding the fiscal year. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC81F5E4725F34234A23F70E54E250AB"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Approval of programs</header> 
<subparagraph id="H76E680F66EC44E3B8EE86B74AF95A100"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Submission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for assistance under this subsection, a State shall submit to the Secretary a State levee safety program and receive the Secretary’s approval of the program.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6DD3DD0A3540474D901FCAF089879D3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Approval</header> 
<clause id="HA77D326A13BE41F1BACB8523BEF2075"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Secretary determines that a program submitted by a State under subparagraph (A) substantially meets the requirements of this subsection, the Secretary shall approve the program and immediately notify the State in writing of the approval.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H891048F49AEC44B7B2A54612DFD912B"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Deemed approval</header><text>A program submitted by a State under subparagraph (A) shall be deemed to be approved by the Secretary on the 120th day following the date of the Secretary’s receipt of the program unless the Secretary before such 120th day approves or disapproves the program.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD411E15BEBEB4DF8851DBA8423D830EB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Notification of disapproval</header><text>If the Secretary determines that a program submitted by a State under subparagraph (A) does not substantially meet the requirements of this subsection, the Secretary shall disapprove the program, immediately notify the State in writing of the disapproval, and provide the reasons for the disapproval and the changes that are necessary for the program to be approved. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBCB7DA4DF9D34DA281577684CF7FA087"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Reviews of state levee safety programs</header> 
<subparagraph id="H736AAE76D89A408D884E5C8C6E8D24F0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Periodic reviews</header><text>Using the expertise of the Board, the Secretary shall periodically review State levee safety programs.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9641358697974B7FAF1D906CF8886C67"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Revocation of program approval</header><text>If the Board finds that a State levee safety program has proven inadequate to reasonably protect human life and public property and the Secretary concurs, the Secretary shall revoke approval of the State levee safety program, and withhold assistance under this subsection, until the State levee safety program again substantially meets the requirements for approval.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0D7BA8FBCC254515A96BE1A3EB332266"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than January 1, 2007, and every 2 years thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report describing—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD3A9AF312CE64D1100BAC563FDFF33D2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the status of the program under this section;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAB5AF4ED42D74A17B645A2AE07AA91A0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the progress made by Federal agencies during the 2 preceding fiscal years in implementing Federal guidelines for levee safety;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8F271C0C8D944E92BCD246599B281BD5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the progress made by State levee safety agencies participating in the program; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7AB58574608C455085A3001689BD4BE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recommendations for legislative or other action that the Secretary considers to be necessary, if any.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H2C2E9112E8A3424FACE85E1D55DF0422"><enum>8.</enum><header>Research program</header> 
<subsection id="H43FBB656A87D4D96832446A8FE1F6CF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in cooperation with the Board, shall carry out a program of technical and archival research to develop and support—</text> 
<paragraph id="H461B32C0C3DA4759920590104B17EEA3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>improved techniques, historical experience, and equipment for rapid and effective levee construction, rehabilitation, and inspection;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6B7E2B94270B462FA7541C7DB6A19651"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the development of devices for the continued monitoring of levee safety;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE30E10FB4E3C4101977F77249355C890"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the development and maintenance of information resources systems required to manage levee safety projects; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7D260BA2787A4A9D927DED5F3FE55BB2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>public policy initiatives and other improvements relating to levee safety engineering, security, and management.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF32E9E343ABD4BD98DA8EFB586ADE228"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Participation by State levee safety agencies</header><text>In carrying out the program under subsection (a), the Secretary shall—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC173275B3DB143F0ADC164719855C64"><enum>(1)</enum><text>solicit participation from State levee safety agencies; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H42C1486DE15843789B555F37A8B758CD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>periodically update State levee safety agencies, the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives, and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate on the status of the program.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H04EF51231C2447DEAC72C43CA7A51324"><enum>9.</enum><header>Levee safety training program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a program under which the Secretary shall provide, upon request of a State that has (or intends to develop) a State levee safety program, training for State levee safety agency staff and inspectors.</text> </section> 
<section id="H23955D18B7F6494F992F14B4B3605101"><enum>10.</enum><header>Effect of Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBAB905DDB7584F679BDB4B4C82366F8B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">creates any liability of the United States or its officers or employees for the recovery of damages caused by an action or failure to act; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5CF59C6339FB492BA4B8E96F4026CBDD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relieves an owner or operator of a levee of a legal duty, obligation, or liability incident to the ownership or operation of a levee. </text> </paragraph></section> 
<section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H21F56617B1C14D86914E60DD14DE4FFF" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>11.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this Act $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2007 through 2012. Such sums shall remain available until expended.</text> </section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


