<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1D52FB04518149F3AFE8EB9C075FB952" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 4255 IH: United States Olympic Committee Paralympic Program Act of 2007</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-12-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 4255</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20071204">December 4, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000116">Mr. Filner</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to authorize the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to provide assistance to the Paralympic Program of the United States Olympic Committee, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HC614AE9E7FDB48AA8729F8DB0524FF75" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H9D98FADF26C54710901C07707F43E515" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United States Olympic Committee Paralympic Program Act of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H2F71838072E7489CB976F8DD9BE0D502" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings and purpose</header> 
<subsection id="H28DC071DE12F4168949000CFB592DA7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress makes the following findings:</text> 
<paragraph id="H7D7BDA1DEB004C08BDF0369F79CE26BA" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 1998, Congress enacted the Olympic and Amateur Sports Act Amendments of 1998, which amended <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/36/2205">chapter 2205</external-xref> of title 36, United States Code, which included a statement that the purpose of the Act was <quote>to encourage and provide assistance to amateur athletic programs and competition for amateur athletes with disabilities, including, where feasible, the expansion of opportunities for meaningful participation by such amateur athletes in programs of athletic competition for able-bodied amateur athletes</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D2A30562C19446F98C76956BB69B676"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United States Olympic Committee manages and administers the Paralympic Program for physically disabled athletes.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H45AE9AB8DBD445A085C05200CBD89C90"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In 2005, the United States Olympic Committee entered into a memorandum of understanding with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to expand the Paralympic Program to provide special training and rehabilitation to physically disabled members of the Armed Forces and veterans as part of their rehabilitation and return to an active lifestyle.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7BB2C1EFE0C84187BE6F20F393C9B2DA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Paralympic Program has a significant positive effect on the quality of life of members of the Armed Forces and veterans with physical disabilities, including helping to improve the mobility, vitality, physical, psychological, and social well-being of physically disabled members of the Armed Forces and veterans who participate in the program and reducing the incidence of secondary medical conditions in those participants.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6C785E097B8244AE997DCE3A087F9AD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Because of Operation Iraqi Freedom and Operation Enduring Freedom, the number of physically disabled members of the Armed Forces and veterans has increased substantially and it is therefore necessary to expand the scope and size of the United States Olympic Committee’s Paralympic Program to provide rehabilitative services through sports to physically disabled members of the Armed Forces and veterans.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5EF58E981B264D648225ACC4B933C6D9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purposes of this Act are as follows:</text> 
<paragraph id="H80905471850C46DDAC833487317800E9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To provide support to the United States Olympic Committee for the Paralympic Program to increase the participation of physically disabled members of the Armed Forces and veterans in sports as part of their rehabilitation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE32F2ED07C3C4776B379995054EECA86"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To promote the life-long health of members of the Armed Forces and veterans with service-connected disabilities through regular participation in physical activity and sports.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3E110C1431A640D69BA6142512F3E4D4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>To provide training and support to local organizations to provide paralympic sports training to physically disabled members of the Armed Forces and veterans in their own communities.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H79F04FA338104E15A34F48E04CB71E82"><enum>3.</enum><header>Department of Veterans Affairs provision of assistance to United States Olympic Committee Paralympic Program</header> 
<subsection id="H889EB4DE10554CDC9B04468881F9D874"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Provision of assistance authorized</header><text>Subchapter II of chapter V of title 38, United States Code, is amended by inserting after section 521 the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H83859288BE694D1493A160A82771FDC" style="USC"> 
<section id="H275ABEA7910040B0B0DC4959266101AB"><enum>521A.</enum><header>Assistance for the United States Olympic Committee’s Paralympic Program</header> 
<subsection id="HABFFA4B882624F70A47100F7941682B6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization To provide assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may make a grant to the United States Olympic Committee to plan, develop, manage, and implement the Paralympic Program for veterans and members of the Armed Forces.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB38718311CE24C749CD92E38B0D78641"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Oversight by Under Secretary for Health</header><text>As a condition of receiving a grant under this section, the United States Olympic Committee shall permit the Under Secretary for Health to conduct such oversight of the use of grant funds as the Under Secretary determines is appropriate.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H353BC21D13E04C0188007651419606A8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds</header> 
<paragraph id="HD709811B3DFF46FDB9B0E7E91D00D2A" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The United States Olympic Committee, with the assistance and cooperation of the Secretary and the heads of other appropriate Federal and State departments and agencies, shall use a grant under this section to recruit, support, encourage, schedule, facilitate, supervise, and implement the activities described in paragraph (3) for veterans and members of the Armed Forces with physical disabilities, either directly or by supporting a program described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1B4E09665C544F1091BEA86B9DBD2ED" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A program described in this paragraph is a community-based paralympic sport program, including such a program that promotes basic physical activity, games, recreation, training, and competition, that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1BE4E828E6404C15A365C20300AFD85"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is approved by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEE23FF4E0E474B91AE50B2B77FD6703E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provides services and activities for veterans and members of the Armed Forces with physical disabilities and may provide such services and activities for individuals with physical disabilities who are not veterans or members of the Armed Forces.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6EAD9ECB0DB04B9E8399AE922931AFAD" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Activities described in this paragraph are—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEF2346A9F13446318C87DF34421783AC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>instruction and competition in paralympic sports;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDCFDAC34B55E4D620074BE500719D44"><enum>(B)</enum><text>training and technical assistance to program administrators, coaches, recreational therapists, instructors, Department employees, and other appropriate individuals; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF696CB0004C74994AFC000D57BB24472"><enum>(C)</enum><text>coordination, Paralympic classification of athletes, athlete assessment, sport-specific training techniques, program development, program specific medical and personal care support, sports equipment, supplies, program evaluation, and other activities related to the implementation and operation of the program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB192627A16884DDDBE4FBCFD0874306F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation on use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a program described in subsection (c)(2) provides services or activities for individuals with physical disabilities who are not veterans or members of the Armed Forces, funds provided to the program through the United States Olympic Committee under this section may not be used for such services and activities.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBE092F9FA4F04E798881003578F57820"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Outreach requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall inform all veterans with physical disabilities about the existence of the Paralympic Program and shall provide for, facilitate, and encourage participation of such veterans. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3DCB0692F4834CC2AF263B029DB2F1A0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure access to and use of appropriate Department facilities by all individuals participating in the Paralympic Program.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H26E7735B8DEF42EF93FD3D3899C5B94E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Application requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before the Secretary may make a grant to the United States Olympic Committee under this section, the United States Olympic Committee shall submit to the Secretary an application that describes the activities to be carried out with the grant, including information on specific measurable goals and objectives to be achieved using grant funds. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H05DFE6675C88481DBDB63F2D7B491733"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated for each of fiscal years 2008 through 2012 $10,000,000 to carry out this section.</text> </subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H284EB0687B0D45A4B9A3F51EF37CF942"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 521 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H116EB1806CBC486400724668C925D71" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">521A. Assistance for United States Olympic Committee’s Paralympic Program.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H61C813F6976F41DA8D05D697344F9B60"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Deadline for memorandum of understanding</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs may not award a grant under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/521A">section 521A</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), until the United States Olympic Committee has entered into a memorandum of understanding or cooperative agreement with the Secretary regarding implementation of the Paralympic Program. Such agreement shall be concluded not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


