<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB10DCCB009FF48A4A20031D8FF3FFEDA" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 2259 IH: To ensure that members of the National Guard and Reserves
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 2259</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20070509">May 9, 2007</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000800">Mr. Welch of Vermont</sponsor>
			 introduced the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed
			 Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on
			 <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name>, for a
			 period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for
			 consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the
			 committee concerned</action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To ensure that members of the National Guard and Reserves
		  are able to fully participate in the benefits delivery at discharge program
		  administered jointly by the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans
		  Affairs to provide information and assistance on available benefits and other
		  transition assistance to members of the Armed Forces who are separating from
		  the Armed Forces.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HECB9F419FF41467E00499127F9403F00" style="OLC">
		<section id="HAA52D48BE4F34D4DA37FAAB58BDDE614" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Participation by members of
			 reserve components in benefits delivery at discharge program</header>
			<subsection id="HA844CF684E134836B50034DA1EA95E20"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Plan To maximize
			 participation</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the
			 enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans
			 Affairs shall jointly submit to Congress a plan to maximize access to the
			 benefits delivery at discharge program for members of the reserve components of
			 the Armed Forces who have been called or ordered to active duty at any time
			 since September 11, 2001.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H3A80CE76C7644DD094D5D0164E2629EE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The plan submitted under subsection (a)
			 shall include a description of efforts to ensure that services under the
			 benefits delivery at discharge program are provided, to the maximum extent
			 practicable—</text>
				<paragraph id="HBD4ECC80D9BA41939EF4D9CA1E006C19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>at each military
			 installation;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HD672814CE2D241BC9973D174D08E00EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>at each armory and
			 military family support center of the National Guard;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H492C830702284683A481701C61F4BB02"><enum>(3)</enum><text>at each military
			 medical care facility at which members of the Armed Forces are separated or
			 discharged from the Armed Forces; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H912A6FABF0A7420D8B78B5EBAC2D6489"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in the case of a
			 member on the temporary disability retired list under section 1202 or 1205 of
			 title 10, United States Code, who is being retired under another provision of
			 such title or is being discharged, at a location reasonably convenient to the
			 member.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9EF27F033150494B900309C2EAB37300"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Benefits
			 delivery at discharge program defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>benefits
			 delivery at discharge program</quote> means a program administered jointly by
			 the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to provide
			 information and assistance on available benefits and other transition
			 assistance to members of the Armed Forces who are separating from the Armed
			 Forces, including assistance to obtain any disability benefits for such members
			 may be eligible.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


