<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H7274F588E8B244EE9CFC5242D0E8FB3F" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 4332 EH: Financial Consumer Hotline Act of 2007</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 4332</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Financial Institutions Examination Council Act to require the Council to establish a single telephone number that consumers with complaints or inquiries could call and be routed to the appropriate Federal banking agency or State bank supervisor, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H863C3CFAA2A24DC2AADDBAF2CE123646" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H596D4F0BEF0E4CBE9931E728392CF68" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Financial Consumer Hotline Act of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text> </section>
<section id="HC5E88A5D72064B4FAEAF67ABC9577143"><enum>2.</enum><header>Centralized intake of consumer complaints and inquiries made to Federal financial institution regulatory agencies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Federal Financial Institutions Examination Council Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3301">12 U.S.C. 3301 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 1009A the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2DC835F97D944D1F84F0468E56001889" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H8BC1E676475F48268CF0683C76535743"><enum>1009B.</enum><header>Consumer complaints and inquiries</header> 
<subsection id="H4DB90A012E9E417DBCF120B018B6CDB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Single toll-free telephone number for consumer complaints and inquiries</header> 
<paragraph id="HF07D8561C2EE4C53951DF1ACC9C34BFE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Call intake system</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal financial institution regulatory agencies, coordinating through the Council, shall establish a single, toll-free telephone number for consumer complaints and inquiries concerning institutions regulated by such agencies and a system for routing such calls to the Federal financial institution regulatory agency that primarily supervises the financial institution, or that is otherwise the appropriate agency to address the subject of the complaint or inquiry.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDACB5756364649F4BFE1BBB30096033E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Routing calls to States</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent practicable, State agencies may receive appropriate call transfers from the system established under paragraph (1) if—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD9B7FC9E120D4EF09F737C7FF88402AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the State agency’s system has the functional capacity to receive calls routed by the system; and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H19FD1619EA4547A6B305219016D9F1B9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the State agency has satisfied any conditions of participation in the system that the Council, coordinating with State agencies through the chairperson of the State Liaison Committee, may establish.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H738C400E6FFC478E00C616942CBDDCC9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report to the Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of the enactment of the Financial Consumer Hotline Act of 2007, the Federal financial institution regulatory agencies shall submit a report to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate describing the agencies’ efforts to establish—</text> 
<paragraph id="H610A3780B39E4819976687298418082E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a public interagency Web site for directing and referring Internet consumer complaints and inquiries concerning any financial institution to the Federal financial institution regulatory agency that primarily supervises the financial institution, or to the Federal financial institution regulatory agency or State agency that is otherwise the appropriate agency to address the subject of the complaint or inquiry; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA34EA3F495CA4CC69F41D9D0DC13E3AD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a system to expedite the prompt and effective rerouting of any misdirected consumer complaint or inquiry documents between or among the agencies, with prompt referral of any complaint or inquiry to the appropriate Federal financial institution regulatory agency, and to participating State agencies.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section>
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20080429" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives April 29, 2008.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 


