<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H180355C238C249498B79F102B5AAEA2B" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 698 IH: Industrial Bank Holding Company Act of 2007</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-01-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 698</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070129">January 29, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000210">Mr. Gillmor</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000339">Mr. Frank of Massachusetts</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000087">Mrs. Maloney of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000284">Mrs. Jones of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000482">Mr. Doyle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000535">Mr. Gutierrez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000794">Ms. Watson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001152">Mrs. Musgrave</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000725">Mr. George Miller of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000280">Mr. Goode</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000361">Mr. Alexander</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000030">Mr. Farr</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000712">Mr. Holden</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000449">Mr. Fortenberry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000552">Mr. LaHood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001158">Mr. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Al Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000523">Mr. Price of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000258">Mr. Peterson of Minnesota</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000453">Ms. Fallin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="U000038">Mr. Udall of Colorado</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001058">Mr. Chandler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000191">Ms. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001043">Mr. Hodes</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend the Federal Deposit Insurance Act to establish industrial bank holding company regulation, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HAD719163BBBD489C8F8D501218C0B758" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HDCD519B5AA5C41BAA4A066D1009D4B3D" section-type="section-one" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Industrial Bank Holding Company Act of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H330FF71AA84142CF90C95E606FBDEF3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Industrial bank holding company regulation</header> 
<subsection id="H7404BCA51853479A8F7E18CDFD502F6D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header> 
<paragraph id="HCDEC2D13985E4A05AE26532F275CEDD2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Industrial bank</header><text>Section 3(a) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD13F54D63173448982A96D56001C377E" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H321A5EE14C79451596B019CA2D95C449"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Industrial bank</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>industrial bank</term> means any insured State bank that is an industrial bank, industrial loan company, or other institution described in section 2(c)(2)(H) of the <act-name parsable-cite="BHC65">Bank Holding Company Act of 1956.</act-name></text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H606292653A5F41A7961BD83D62DB285D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Industrial bank holding company</header><text>Section 3(w) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813(w)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3F7C0FD0BAB64F3B93420090993621F6" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="HD076306C201143E68246F336DA253BCA"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Industrial bank holding company</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>industrial bank holding company</term> means any company that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H67D66B54574E460AA2A0254700E7257B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>controls (as determined by the Corporation), directly or indirectly, any industrial bank; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB52B82068A4148FABF006B15B3EF66E0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is not a bank holding company, a savings and loan holding company, or a company that is subject to the Bank Holding Company Act of 1956 pursuant to section 8(a) of the International Banking Act of 1978.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H393C29FB32BD45A8A7950713C2C22193"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments to other definitions</header> 
<subparagraph id="HC81E55AA8E8847DB997DA3039E935B6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Appropriate federal banking agency</header><text>Section 3(q)(3) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813(q)(3)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<clause id="H3CF6C6E13DB54B759CFF2300ED85009B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or a foreign</quote> and inserting <quote>, any foreign</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7C4F34A66524456EAAB115B021D63100"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, and any industrial bank holding company</quote> after <quote>insured branch</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1FEDE340AC8F41DE9676F37D0074789E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Depository institution holding company</header><text>Section 3(w)(1) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813(w)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<clause id="H89DAD43199A042CCBCF0DC6DB0D84B28"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or a savings</quote> and inserting <quote>, any savings</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA0EA3E2D8FD74378A126FC401012BFD3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, and any industrial bank holding company</quote> before the period at the end.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H71BA1FE2C4B14D1F9C731251A9000264"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Industrial bank holding company registration and ownership</header><text>The Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1811">12 U.S.C. 1811 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBF2FF9EF95E2401EB2C823D939F44BFF" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA084625883FB48E7B329C234C57A176"><enum>51.</enum><header>Industrial bank holding company regulation</header> 
<subsection id="HF8AC6D29B4084802985C96A17D6700BE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Registration</header> 
<paragraph id="H28C1E4A6758C43C695E014B72F5A7D6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Within 90 days after becoming an industrial bank holding company, each industrial bank holding company shall register with the Corporation on forms prescribed by the Corporation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCC3C3E0E910A43DCBF70CDE3E93BC8E6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information to be included</header><text>Each registration submitted under paragraph (1) shall include such information, under oath, with respect to the financial condition, ownership, operations, management, and intercompany relationships of the industrial bank holding company and subsidiaries of such holding company, and other factors (including information described in subsection (b)(1)(C)), as the Corporation may determine to be appropriate to carry out the purposes of this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8FCDCAD68935481195F06B455E3FBD5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Extension of time for submitting complete information</header><text>Upon application by an industrial bank holding company and subject to such requirements, factors, and evidence as the Corporation may require, the Corporation may extend the period described in paragraph (1) within which such company shall register and file the requisite information.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB4F2B2DF9F0F4966B105D01FCF5CDAE7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Application to prior holding companies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any company that becomes an industrial bank holding company by virtue of the enactment of the Industrial Bank Holding Company Act of 2007, the 90-day period referred to in paragraph (1) shall begin on the date of the enactment of such Act.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5FBB3E1952C443FA92337E1BC8CBEDEF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports and examinations</header> 
<paragraph id="H86ED4071E663473EBA2493F5AE8F185D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reports</header> 
<subparagraph id="H26B060F0084D49FD8BF48C39F180BE81"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Reports required</header><text>Each industrial bank holding company and each subsidiary of an industrial bank holding company, other than an industrial bank, shall file with the Corporation such reports as may be required by the Corporation.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA4374722245D4629B71B1599AEB1F9AD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Form and manner</header><text>Reports filed under subparagraph (A) shall be made under oath and shall be in such form and for such periods, as the Corporation may prescribe.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA93C4CDD2D2F4D278508E300D1B3AD66"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report filed under subparagraph (A) shall contain such information as the Corporation may require concerning—</text> 
<clause id="H77EEB0A9409348729209F5564980073"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the operations of the industrial bank holding company and its subsidiaries;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDA462B6B459943309289928ECD976858"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the financial condition of the industrial bank holding company and such subsidiaries, together with information on systems maintained within the holding company for monitoring and controlling financial and operating risks, and transactions with industrial bank subsidiaries of the holding company;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA4485860126B4AE699D3544E042BEE03"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">compliance by the industrial bank holding company and its subsidiaries with all applicable Federal and State law; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H15F60380CB45472CB0EFFE38AC00E2BC"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>such other information as the Corporation may require.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H40C3036CB4784934A12C642739187799"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Acceptance of existing reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this paragraph, the Corporation may accept reports that an industrial bank holding company or any subsidiary of such company has provided or has been required to provide to any other Federal or State supervisor or to any appropriate self-regulatory organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H37295C5B3DB24FAD8EE77B2544007200"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Examinations</header> 
<subparagraph id="H65936E6B334248C48CA7586588CCDDDB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each industrial bank holding company and each subsidiary of each such holding company (other than an industrial bank) shall be subject to such examinations by the Corporation as the Corporation may prescribe for purposes of this section.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCD8D2ED4AF784FAB87D1114E5C83233F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Furnishing reports to other agencies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Examination and other reports made or received under this section may be furnished by the Corporation to any other Federal agency or any appropriate State bank supervisor.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF16B1D2367CA40F4B4389C4B3900523B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Use of reports from other agencies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Corporation may use, for the purposes of this subsection, reports of examination made by any other Federal agency or any appropriate State bank supervisor with respect to any industrial bank holding company or subsidiary of any such holding company, to the extent the Corporation may determine such use to be feasible for such purposes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC94AD5222C2B4923B8B458102C9506EF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitation on control</header> 
<paragraph id="H5A2DB7DF668647BF84A89887BD5C008E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (3) or (4), no industrial bank may be controlled, directly or indirectly, by a commercial firm.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDD4080A74C934048A46BF522B810E2B0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commercial firm defined</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>commercial firm</term> means any entity at least 15 percent of the annual gross revenues of which on a consolidated basis, including all affiliates of the entity, were derived from engaging, on an on-going basis, in activities that are not financial in nature or incidental to a financial activity during at least 3 of the prior 4 calendar quarters, as determined by the Corporation in accordance with regulations which the Corporation shall prescribe.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAFEA69F578574663A10092A290226CCB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Pre<enum-in-header>-</enum-in-header>2003 exclusions</header> 
<subparagraph id="H052E3B0AAAB64B95B700F37D848ED364"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Grandfathered institutions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (1) shall not apply with respect to any industrial bank—</text> 
<clause id="H68BA4D6343054253B2D94793E07027DA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>which became an insured depository institution before October 1, 2003, or pursuant to an application for deposit insurance which was approved by the Corporation before such date; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4257B1DE2EFD4A40A6ABFBA6C7C693E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to which there is no change in control, directly or indirectly, of the bank after September 30, 2003, that requires a registration under this section or an application under section 7(j) or 18(c), section 3 of the <act-name parsable-cite="BHC65">Bank Holding Company Act of 1956</act-name>, or section 10 of the <act-name parsable-cite="HOLA">Home Owners’ Loan Act</act-name>.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8B61FCFE16FF4D0BB0E43DA8AFC989A9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Corporate reorganizations permitted</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The acquisition of direct or indirect control of the industrial bank referred to in subparagraph (A)(ii) shall not be treated as a <quote>change in control</quote> for purposes of such subparagraph if the company acquiring control is itself directly or indirectly controlled by a company that was an affiliate of such bank on the date referred to in such paragraph, and remains an affiliate at all times after such date.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCC475F5B66684BEBB4C42F2C8102646F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Pre<enum-in-header>-</enum-in-header>2007 exclusions</header> 
<subparagraph id="HE5D2C0F2EBAB43EC91068B5FCCDE244D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Grandfathered commercial firms</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to any commercial firm—</text> 
<clause id="H7C624E7D86944A6885F29D80259B63F4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">which became an industrial bank holding company by virtue of acquiring control of an industrial bank on or after October 1, 2003, and before January 29, 2007;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H465E6366411B4D7CBBEC898B425BDDF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">which does not acquire control of any other depository institution after January 28, 2007;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5A67B583164648EFB5A49CA891FAEDA0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to which there is no change in control, directly or indirectly, of any depository institution subsidiary after January 28, 2007, that requires a registration under this section or an application under section 7(j) or 18(c), section 3 of the <act-name parsable-cite="BHC65">Bank Holding Company Act of 1956</act-name>, or section 10 of the <act-name parsable-cite="HOLA">Home Owners’ Loan Act</act-name>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H94F1753228554238A2EB1BA73B11CD01"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>each industrial bank subsidiary of which remains in compliance with the limitations contained in subparagraph (B).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H23985865C25940688127F4060300B47E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Activity and branching limitations</header><text>An industrial bank subsidiary of a commercial firm described in clauses (i), (ii) and (iii) of subparagraph (A) is in compliance with the requirements of this subparagraph for purposes of subparagraph (A)(iv) so long as the industrial bank—</text> 
<clause id="HA294B32CE2934D16A05C2489AB89BD90"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">engages only in activities in which the industrial bank was engaged on January 28, 2007; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD30CA773ADA34922A95BA333D191D517"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not acquire, establish, or operate any branch, deposit production office, loan production office, automated teller machine, or remote service unit in any State other than the home State of the bank or any host State in which such bank operated branches on January 28, 2007.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3971614690A14F269623A900BADA7877"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Corporate reorganizations permitted</header><text>The acquisition of direct or indirect control of a depository institution subsidiary referred to in subparagraph (A)(iii) shall not be treated as a <quote>change in control</quote> for purposes of such subparagraph if the company acquiring control is itself directly or indirectly controlled by a company that was an affiliate of such subsidiary on the date referred to in such paragraph, and remains an affiliate at all times after such date.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3FE4FA04C9E947BD005147003F008200"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Transition provision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any divestiture of any industrial bank by an industrial bank holding company that is required by operation of this section shall be completed as quickly as is reasonably possible and not later than the end of the 2-year period beginning on the earliest of, as appropriate—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB10FE1D262B54AEA9CFF8DFE43FCD9C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the date on which control of the industrial bank is acquired by a commercial firm;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H768A4F4C04044F60AA82BABF9778B623"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the date on which the industrial bank holding company that controls such bank becomes a commercial firm; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9E766CE38C6940CCB3AD96FA7B003100"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the date on which an industrial bank subsidiary of the industrial bank holding company ceases to comply with any limitation applicable to such bank under paragraph (4)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6594897AE2874C96A59ED3A1F2EF4F12"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Administrative provisions</header> 
<paragraph id="HC74529768652439FA349EC7AADA455C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agent for service of process</header><text>The Corporation may require any industrial bank holding company, or persons connected with such holding company if it is not a corporation, to execute and file a prescribed form of irrevocable appointment of agent for service of process.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA19AE47AB32643C7910274DBD35F5C38"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Release from registration</header><text>The Corporation may at any time, upon the Corporation’s own motion or upon application, release a registered industrial bank holding company from any registration previously made by such company, if the Corporation determines that such company no longer controls any industrial bank.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE5949F03E14A428A8C705C3CF871BCF9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text>Section 8(b) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1818">12 U.S.C. 1818(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H806D320A0F5740869F87D9ADC414C9F" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H94D9CBCDD95C4049A75B60B1FD1C1E5B"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Industrial bank holding companies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This subsection and subsections (c) through (s) and subsection (u) of this section shall apply to any industrial bank holding company, and to any subsidiary (other than an industrial bank) of an industrial bank holding company in the same manner as such subsections apply to State nonmember banks.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAF3FFF65FC3545F4AF20CAC2C024192D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text>Section 10(e)(2) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1820">12 U.S.C. 1820(e)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>or section 50(b)(2)</quote> after <quote>subsection (b)(4)</quote>.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


