<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H6AD2EFA629B74DAEB67AC4E5BD61540B" public-private="public">
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>111th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 3655</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20090925">September 25, 2009</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000515">Mr. Rush</sponsor> introduced
			 the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and
			 Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To direct the Federal Trade Commission to establish rules
		  to prohibit unfair or deceptive acts or practices related to the provision of
		  funeral services.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H43CD75226684425383BCF4A15D32E9E4" style="OLC">
		<section id="HC72145D0F02D4FDE89A6C3A6D2A2A080" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Bereaved Consumer’s Bill of Rights Act
			 of 2009</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H2D93BBDB096E42D3BB1798418DC53945"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text>
			<paragraph id="H069424875B40429694602A6F80C4C251"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">there have been shocking consumer abuses in
			 the funeral industry, including scandals at Burr Oak Cemetery in Alsip,
			 Illinois, Menorah Gardens Cemetery in Palm Beach, Florida, and the Tri State
			 Crematory in Noble, Georgia;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HB384AE6DC812479EB61178C3D6D1E4E5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>funeral
			 arrangements are a major expense for most American households and
			 families;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H01114E1BB9604220ABD0B9E394551686"><enum>(3)</enum><text>some consumers
			 seek to ease the burdens on their families by arranging and paying for pre-need
			 funeral and cemetery arrangements;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H6A4D5612818F4E0DA1C4932096F36A81"><enum>(4)</enum><text>most funerals are
			 planned by grieving family members at a time when they are especially
			 vulnerable and unlikely to focus on cost comparison;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HBE97DD7FF39A415484E6A9C0D4395F6C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Federal Trade
			 Commission’s Funeral Industry Practices Trade Regulation Rule (known as the
			 Funeral Rule) dictates consumer protections in the funeral home, but does not
			 cover the practices of cemeteries, crematoria, or sellers of monuments, urns,
			 or caskets;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H511DE31DCDEB4AECB93048F48BC9CB65"><enum>(6)</enum><text>State laws are
			 inconsistent and frequently too weak to provide adequate consumer protections,
			 creating a need for minimum federal standards in this area;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HDCD597F728514A739DF74092AE627BCB"><enum>(7)</enum><text>consumers have the
			 right to receive clear and accurate information about all funeral goods and
			 services offered for sale;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H076605A4A13F46948756BF3745A9917F"><enum>(8)</enum><text>consumers need
			 effective protection from fraud and abusive practices by all providers of
			 funeral goods and services and at all stages of the funeral planning process;
			 and</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HDE5AA047FD154524A047012D097EA6F7"><enum>(9)</enum><text>a
			 new Federal law that provides adequate protections to grieving families is
			 warranted.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H2176C56D033940D9BE77A0400F5AAD8F"><enum>3.</enum><header>FTC rulemaking
			 relating to unfair or deceptive acts or practices in the provision of funeral
			 goods or services</header>
			<subsection id="HD8EF8C7A2A4A4D25BAD514D7D79E99CA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Trade
			 Commission shall prescribe rules prohibiting unfair or deceptive acts or
			 practices in the provision of funeral goods or services. Such rules shall
			 include the following:</text>
				<paragraph id="HD19DC1E048F3452290C9C37FED9C6D19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A
			 requirement that providers of funeral goods or funeral services furnish
			 accurate price information disclosing the cost to the purchaser for each of the
			 specific funeral goods or funeral services provided or offered for sale.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H087D1A2EF91D4BA79A4D24186FEF7BBA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A
			 prohibition on misrepresentations by such providers, including
			 misrepresentations of the requirements of Federal, State, or local law.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HB95A7C9F566A412F8AE24CFB287447E7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A prohibition on conditioning the provision
			 of any funeral good or funeral service upon the purchase of any other funeral
			 good or funeral service from that provider, except as required by law.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H3497B22A76F644D1907CBE23BC6F35B3"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A requirement that contracts for funeral
			 services or funeral goods be written clearly, stating the merchandise and
			 services that purchasers are buying and their prices.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H133AB732EF1B44E99FD834540BA0E02C"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of contracts for funeral
			 services or funeral goods that are pre-paid in whole or in part, required
			 disclosures in the contract regarding any penalties incurred if the consumer
			 decides to cancel or transfer the contract to another provider of funeral
			 services or funeral goods.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HFEE60E8925EE46E4AE87D4609ED85A7B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A
			 requirement that contracts for funeral services or funeral goods disclose all
			 fees and costs to be incurred in the future or at the time that the funeral
			 services or funeral goods are provided.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HD47E02D2C1144EEEAD36FAFA0EDF5B39"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A requirement that cemeteries provide to
			 consumers, in a timely manner, all written rules and regulations of the
			 cemetery, and a clear explanation in writing of the interment, inurnment, or
			 entombment right that has been purchased, and any material terms and conditions
			 of that purchase, including any repurchase option by the cemetery or resale
			 rights available to the consumer.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H27A1B2FEFF3F458D989B3D39F3FF5116"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A requirement that cemeteries—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HE867348D4FD54042B508B847AB74EFB6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>retain all records
			 in existence on the date of enactment of this Act, including maps or other
			 systems indicating the location and date of each interment, inurnment, or
			 entombment;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D9E6710195342A5842837E413799226"><enum>(B)</enum><text>accurately record
			 and retain records of all interment, inurnment, or entombment rights sold after
			 the effective date of the regulations issued under this subsection, in such
			 manner and form as the Commission may prescribe in such regulations; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5BC0B6AA2A124920A82B329E08177785"><enum>(C)</enum><text>make such records
			 available to Federal, State, and local governments, as appropriate.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H28878D75106344B7AF3F5256C6DC421C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header>
				<paragraph id="H7423A0EEAA2B422396F9F57793B81472"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Commission shall prescribe the rules under subsection
			 (a) within 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act. Such rules, and any
			 future rules or revision of rules prescribed by the Commission prohibiting
			 unfair or deceptive acts or practices in the provision of funeral goods or
			 services, shall be prescribed in accordance with section 553 of title 5, United
			 States Code.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H2D95D6D4E57B41E098E5EFD6A6A9FCFF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Relationship to
			 Funeral Rule</header><text>No rule prescribed pursuant to this Act shall be
			 less protective of consumers than the Trade Regulation Rule on Funeral Industry
			 Practices (16 C.F.R. part 453).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD345C4747FBE43398AE9E442AF25EB35"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application of
			 Rules to Tax Exempt Organizations and States</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding the definition of
			 corporation in section 4 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (15 U.S.C. 44),
			 the rules prescribed under subsection (a), and any future rules or revision of
			 rules prescribed by the Commission prohibiting unfair or deceptive acts or
			 practices in the provision of funeral goods or funeral services, shall also
			 apply to cemeteries organized or operated by—</text>
				<paragraph id="H7A71A037CCE74ECD893B2487293D76A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>organizations
			 described in section 501(c) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 that are
			 exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HD5D76B0FB20140278ED28EF28B5B19DE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">religious organizations (notwithstanding
			 any contrary provisions of law set forth in the Religious Freedom Restoration
			 Act, 42 U.S.C. 2000bb—2000bb–4); and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H121DFFFC1A8141D782A1363F0B878733"><enum>(3)</enum><text>States or any
			 political subdivision of a State.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H635D76E63BEC4F2D99E86A2F9B9A42C9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any violation of any rule prescribed under
			 this section shall be treated as a violation of a regulation prescribed under
			 section 18(a)(1)(B) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (15 U.S.C.
			 57a(a)(1)(B)) regarding unfair or deceptive acts or practices. The Federal
			 Trade Commission shall enforce this Act in the same manner, by the same means,
			 and with the same jurisdiction as though all applicable terms and provisions of
			 the Federal Trade Commission Act were incorporated into and made a part of this
			 Act. Any person who violates the regulations prescribed under this Act shall be
			 subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided
			 in that Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HFF15BE9E8AD64FF3AE87D2C0CF431304"><enum>4.</enum><header>Enforcement by
			 states</header>
			<subsection id="HE1755D2F838940428130E773B0955581"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whenever an attorney
			 general of any State has reason to believe that the interests of the residents
			 of that State have been or are being threatened or adversely affected because
			 any person has engaged or is engaging in an act or practice which violates any
			 rule of the Commission issued under section 3 of this Act, the State, as parens
			 patriae, may bring a civil action on behalf of its residents in an appropriate
			 district court of the United States to enjoin such violative act or practice,
			 to enforce compliance with such rule of the Commission, to obtain damages,
			 restitution, or other compensation on behalf of residents of such State, or to
			 obtain such further and other relief as the court may determine appropriate.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H0CFAEC04FBA343868DF9D19652094C75"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The State shall provide prior written
			 notice of any civil action under subsection (a) or (f)(2) to the Commission and
			 provide the Commission with a copy of its complaint, except that if it is not
			 feasible for the State to provide such prior notice, the State shall provide
			 such notice immediately upon instituting such action. Upon receiving a notice
			 respecting a civil action, the Commission shall have the right—</text>
				<paragraph id="HC4501D7C351144DCAB0F8FE861EA4369"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to intervene in
			 such action;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H21B8036A53604A91974C581D7F568E5F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>upon so
			 intervening, to be heard on all matters arising therein;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H36F07F588BC74C68A5EADD3E8E2AD180"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to remove the
			 action to the appropriate United States district court; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HA1EF50D73BA64C93B71AE492ED82BDD5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to file petitions
			 for appeal.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC6828D78147046D7946783EAE8F13E15"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of bringing any civil action
			 under subsection (a), nothing in this Act shall prevent an attorney general
			 from exercising the powers conferred on the attorney general by the laws of
			 such State to conduct investigations or to administer oaths or affirmations or
			 to compel the attendance of witnesses or the production of documentary and
			 other evidence.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H67D34EE2A6A24F618D78A67CDA9B9513"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Actions by
			 Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whenever a civil
			 action has been instituted by or on behalf of the Commission for violation of
			 any rule prescribed under section 3 of this Act, no State may, during the
			 pendency of such action instituted by or on behalf of the Commission, institute
			 a civil action under subsection (a) or (f)(2) of this section against any
			 defendant named in the complaint in such action for violation of any rule as
			 alleged in such complaint.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H57FB3936381C46DFA649E8B2204775EE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Venue; Service
			 of Process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any civil action
			 brought under subsection (a) of this section in a district court of the United
			 States may be brought in the district in which the defendant is found, is an
			 inhabitant, or transacts business or wherever venue is proper under section
			 1391 of title 28, United States Code. Process in such an action may be served
			 in any district in which the defendant is an inhabitant or in which the
			 defendant may be found.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HC4DE4189E800473EBDA95796354DC7D5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Actions by other
			 State officials</header>
				<paragraph id="HE2ADAFD8E3FB4ADF8CB06AA4F518E123"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>Nothing
			 contained in this section shall prohibit an authorized State official from
			 proceeding in State court on the basis of an alleged violation of any civil or
			 criminal statute of such State.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H8292E69F26BD4FDEA1FCBC8997C9E3B6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>other State
			 actions</header><text>In addition to actions brought by an attorney general of
			 a State under subsection (a) of this section, such an action may be brought by
			 officers of such State who are authorized by the State to bring actions in such
			 State on behalf of its residents.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE3D6CA1C81DC473D9ADD6887A2D04017"><enum>5.</enum><header>Effect on other
			 law</header>
			<subsection id="H1F39D29C219D48308067E7143F217360"><enum>(a)</enum><header>No
			 preemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this
			 Act or the rules prescribed under this Act shall be construed to preempt any
			 provision of any law of a State or political subdivision of that State that
			 provides protections to consumers of funeral services or funeral goods, except
			 to the extent that the provision of law is inconsistent with any provision of
			 this Act or a rule prescribed under this Act, and then only to the extent of
			 the inconsistency.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H5DF03685D5DA4ABAB394A06B79B96BDF"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act—</text>
			<paragraph id="H955E7DED455840C0B195E7A3C8DA06C4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term
			 <term>cemetery</term> means any organization, association or other business
			 that offers for sale the interment, inurnment, or entombment of human remains,
			 but does not include any cemetery that—</text>
				<subparagraph id="HED67BFAB0F4440BF96EFBB739951321A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>performs fewer
			 than 25 interments, inurnments, and entombments during any calendar year;
			 or</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0CADF5A636874E709BEB43D9739E0E95"><enum>(B)</enum><text>sells fewer than
			 25 interment, inurnment, or entombment rights during any calendar year;</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E478B56565B4BD4B7DC8A1D65B2E886"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term
			 <term>funeral goods</term> are the goods which are sold or offered for sale
			 directly to the public for use in connection with funeral services; and</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H911E8BA744E6462C967CFB37E4D05942"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term
			 <term>funeral services</term> means—</text>
				<subparagraph id="HEF5A1787298C48128A410886E094A265"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any services which
			 are sold or offered for sale to the public in order to—</text>
					<clause id="H90EBEF80080E4018924182C62AA0040E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>care
			 for and prepare deceased human bodies for burial, cremation, or other final
			 disposition; or</text>
					</clause><clause id="H72DFF0E0AF7F4ABBAA9DBA40DE006057"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>arrange,
			 supervise, or conduct the funeral ceremony or the final disposition of deceased
			 human bodies; or</text>
					</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E5DEF4C11154541A462B74C2CF70574"><enum>(B)</enum><text>services provided
			 by funeral directors, morticians, cemeterians, cremationists, and retailers of
			 caskets, urns, monuments, and markers.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body>
</bill>
