<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H61A53BDCC38D467F00B0DC9DCBF726CC" public-private="public"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">111th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 1088</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to provide for a one-year period for the training of new disabled veterans’ outreach program specialists and local veterans’ employment representatives by National Veterans’ Employment and Training Services Institute.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HE305EF76BFB2454F943D9D23218C7CA3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD9178AD8FF544A989CC633A1C1BBEE99" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Mandatory Veteran Specialist Training Act of 2009</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> 
<section id="HCF3641BFB0734C3583C478C44E4B687D"><enum>2.</enum><header>One-year period for training of new disabled veterans’ outreach program specialists and local veterans’ employment representatives by National Veterans’ Employment and Training Services Institute</header> 
<subsection id="H14F68B3210824FD8B9494133ACE8109F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>One-year period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 4102A(c)(8)(A) of title 38, United States Code is amended by striking <quote>three-year period</quote> and inserting <quote>one-year period</quote>.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H45EB65FDB33B491D955EC47570E49B3C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header> 
<paragraph id="H28F650E5C7AB4B73AA8789CC001343BA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicability to new employees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by subsection (a) shall apply with respect to a State employee assigned to perform the duties of a disabled veterans’ outreach program specialist or a local veterans’ employment representative under chapter 41 of such title who is so assigned on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF5F5F039AC90483183C8237542E8E0A6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability to previously-hired employees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of such a State employee who is so assigned on or after January 1, 2006, and before the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall require the State to require, as a condition of a grant or contract under which funds are made available to the State in order to carry out section 4103A or 4104 of title 38, United States Code, each such employee to satisfactorily complete the training described in section 4102A(c)(8)(A) of such title by not later than the date that is one year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20090519" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives May 19, 2009.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 
