<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5AC60B8A1BBF4ABAB7A1F3C9BE8C18" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 112 IH: G.I. Advanced Education in Science and Technology Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-01-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 112</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070104">January 4, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000597">Mrs. Jo Ann Davis of Virginia</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to provide for the payment of stipends to veterans who pursue doctoral degrees in science or technology.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H7264139423604F2EB894EB14AA3CCD34" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H67AB45A01C864E169E00FD7D44F99175" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>G.I. Advanced Education in Science and Technology Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HAC0911B3B3A74A25BCFDA92276C9B38D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text> 
<paragraph id="H0D4B2F0C2A0747FC8008002F34511327"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The United States is starting to lose dominance in science and technology.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2B6A3740CBC9420C84311E8F56B2767B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Increasingly the mothers and fathers of scientific and technological invention are not American, and the number of new doctorates in the sciences, and the number of doctoral students from other countries staying in the United States, are on the decline.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8CC8AC943B1040999BD9333D3CF32F6E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>This decline has serious implications for jobs, industry, and national security in the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4B14BE92F2A547DBA48F0037E6CF2000"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Shortages in the science and technology base of the United States will be addressed, in part, by creating a scientific and technology doctoral study program in the sciences of engineering, mathematics, and technology for veterans.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H2451EDE6924443D800C335C428C9FAA7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Stipends for pursuit of doctoral degrees in science and technology</header> 
<subsection id="H5498EAEC2819492E9FB837AA88AAD30"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/30">Chapter 30</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subchapter:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H13F1B1097F7D4DB1A85617B442415570"> 
<subchapter id="H486D052D602F4AB8A3D2D5CEA35B20B0"><enum>V</enum><header>Stipends for veterans pursuing doctoral degrees in science or technology</header> 
<section id="H9F87E1E64C2F46EABFB0A32BD13E735C"><enum>3041.</enum><header>Stipend for pursuit of certain doctoral degrees</header> 
<subsection id="HD8870CF9D309477798869D44D383C6DB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations for such purpose, the Secretary shall pay a monthly stipend to each eligible doctoral candidate under this subchapter for each month that the candidate is pursuing full-time a doctoral degree in the sciences of engineering, mathematics, or other technology disciplines.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBC2BFD7B88FF4EE5AF4BD8973E93B34"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible doctoral candidates defined</header><text>In this subchapter, the term <term>eligible doctoral candidate</term> means an individual who meets the following requirements:</text> 
<paragraph id="H17A55FD20DC948CCA5C58C10E1057343"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The individual meets the requirements that apply under section 3011 for entitlement to basic educational assistance under subchapter II of this title, other than requirement under subsection (c) of such section 3011 (relating to reductions in basic pay).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC2C334CFEBA040109153889E2EA97FAE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The individual is pursuing full-time a doctoral degree in the sciences of engineering, mathematics, or technology disciplines, after having completed a bachelor’s degree program in any academic discipline at an institution of higher education.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD3C8BADA658243A686454D79002488D4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Relation to basic Montgomery GI bill educational assistance</header><text>Payment of educational assistance under this subchapter is in addition to payment of educational assistance under subchapter II or III of this chapter.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HD9813D9C72BD443DBE7416C7F2986572"><enum>3042.</enum><header>Duration of payments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Payments of stipends under section 3041 of this title to an eligible doctoral candidate may be made for a period not to exceed a total of 60 months.</text></section> 
<section id="H5EAA2E5C0A0A453C9F68F6356BA81EB8"><enum>3043.</enum><header>Amount of stipend</header> 
<subsection id="HE23BADC35C1642459DCA8219007FE6D2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subsection (b), the Secretary shall pay to an eligible doctoral candidate pursuing a course at an institution of higher learning leading to a doctoral degree referred to in section 3041(a) of this title at the monthly rate of $1,200.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3C2B0BAB2D494FAE99DBE36F2936849C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Adjustment for inflation</header><text>With respect to any fiscal year beginning after fiscal year 2007, the Secretary shall provide a percentage increase (rounded to the nearest dollar) in the rate payable under subsection (a) equal to the percentage by which—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4EC6F0A8B13D4F0500267611BF443F18"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Consumer Price Index (all items, United States city average) for the 12-month period ending on the June 30 preceding the beginning of the fiscal year for which the increase is made, exceeds</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1EB66534A2AD474296BF0000AEDAB4D0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such Consumer Price Index for the 12-month period preceding the 12-month period described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H80442E8F20644B7AA6F2C8C807EE6121"><enum>3044.</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Payments of stipends under section 3041 of this title to an eligible doctoral candidate may be made only insofar as the eligible doctoral candidate—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC607F1621CDF4DBB98E353A0F8C656F0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has been accepted into an accredited doctoral program at an institution of higher learning;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBE83AF2A75FF468296605063A3B7C118"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides annual documentation to the Secretary of full-time matriculation in the doctoral program; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H94F9F3480153488C8D6EE3B5003D8DCB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>maintains good academic standing.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H5316AAFC93464AED9C31B0093B5DFC29"><enum>3045.</enum><header>Time limitation for payment of stipends</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The period during which the Secretary may make payments of stipends under section 3041 of this title to an eligible doctoral candidate under this subchapter expires at the end of the 10-year period beginning on the date on which the eligible doctoral candidate is discharged or released from active duty in the Armed Forces.</text></section></subchapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCD601A5B4ACB438894B193FD82B72C2F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header> 
<paragraph display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H31BB8AABBE8A4EEAAD00315EC3F255BD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Section 3011 of such title is amended in subsection (f)(1) and (g) by striking <quote>chapter</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>subchapter</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph indent="up1" id="H113DAF1F33534032874300AA112F153E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Section 3018A(a) of such title is amended by striking <quote>education assistance under this chapter</quote> and inserting <quote>educational assistance under this subchapter</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph indent="up1" id="H9FD6F6BDC8CB480794372F68C633D36C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Section 3018B of such title is amended by striking <quote>education assistance under this chapter</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>educational assistance under this subchapter</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph indent="up1" id="H479A4E4EBC5B44E796CDB1201DA41E00"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Section 3018C of such title is amended by striking <quote>educational assistance under this chapter</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>educational assistance under this subchapter</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph indent="up1" id="H5102C3D658EC474280ADF257C9127133"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Section 3019 of such title is amended by striking <quote>chapter</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>subchapter</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE3613C4CBE8E4730BDB939ED2EF53CE8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/30">chapter 30</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new items:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HE3FD0AECD9DD4145BF50D5A661468764"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="subchapter">Subchapter V—Stipends for veterans pursuing doctoral degrees in science or technology</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3041. Stipend for pursuit of certain doctoral degrees.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3042. Duration of payments.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3043. Amount of stipend.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3044. Requirements.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3045. Time limitation for payment of stipends.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


