<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H263984250FCE4A108634D45558BFC9F3" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 6707 IH: Taking Responsible Action for Community Safety Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2008-07-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 6707</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20080731">July 31, 2008</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="O000006">Mr. Oberstar</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001253">Ms. Bean</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001232">Mrs. Biggert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000108">Mr. Visclosky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000454">Mr. Foster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001138">Mr. Manzullo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000580">Mr. Roskam</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000666">Mr. Hobson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000015">Mr. Neal of Massachusetts</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000365">Mr. Kagen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000188">Mr. Kind</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001231">Ms. Berkley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000762">Ms. Hooley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001259">Mr. Braley of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000555">Ms. Pryce of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000180">Mr. Gilchrest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000552">Mr. LaHood</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C000868">Mr. Cramer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To require Surface Transportation Board consideration of the impacts of certain railroad transactions on local communities, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HAE589BE6D76F43FA9D7FAD584D873295" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HCE2073B3395244DDA0A3F3F53DBCC7C7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Taking Responsible Action for Community Safety Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HBDF311C586D741C48B51FBD7B61F0986"><enum>2.</enum><header>Effect of mergers on local communities and rail passenger transportation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/11324">Section 11324</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HDDFDAC4FE11A4E889EE7519CF3D8D43"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H553B141F70D54E20A7472E822FC45359"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking the last sentence and inserting <quote>The Board shall hold public hearings on the proposed transaction, including public hearings in the affected communities, unless the Board determines that public hearings are not necessary in the public interest.</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H52D7A960E8034F53A300CBBE4FB874F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5ADC8B606CCC44D7976DE9E1677C5DF9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>which involves the merger or control of at least two Class I railroads,</quote> and inserting <quote>with respect to a transaction that involves at least one Class I railroad,</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDD868F5225D44901BFB3AA1D7860E746"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of paragraph (4);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6F0720D0AC8D4BFB0000C78800AED4C2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of paragraph (5) and inserting a semicolon; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA9CCB672793E4F26B5715952C8BA067E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H6A78926CFFEB4384B3C57C92E3865CB9" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H9B3A33C65FAC4077B527E2E5DC279C3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the safety and environmental effects of the proposed transaction, including the effects on local communities, such as public safety, grade crossing safety, hazardous materials transportation safety, emergency response time, noise, and socioeconomic impacts; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5D5BFDAA05FF4D5294B17BBE60A64C15"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the effect of the proposed transaction on intercity rail passenger transportation and commuter rail passenger transportation, as defined by section 24102 of this title.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF891A3356B124F32B9AB9E79E03D5E05"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (c), (d), (e), and (f) as subsections (d), (e), (f), and (g) and inserting a new subsection (c) as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H1B16A106F7184929AAF21080367F1BAD"> 
<subsection id="HC7C8E39E961F4F98904545B48BFEBD9F"><enum>(c)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall approve and authorize a transaction under this section when it finds the transaction is consistent with the public interest. The Board shall not approve a transaction described in subsection (b) if it finds that the transaction’s adverse impacts on safety and on the affected communities, as defined under subsection (b), outweigh the transportation benefits of the transaction. The Board may impose conditions governing a transaction under this section, including conditions to mitigate the effects of the transaction on local communities.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF2926B666EF24014AA8F762F683408CE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (d), as redesignated, by striking <quote>The Board shall approve</quote> and all that follows through <quote>the transaction, including</quote> and insert <quote>The conditions the Board may impose under this section include</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAE038E0303E34C77B7FA1EFE8C99FCC6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subsection (e), as redesignated, by striking <quote>the merger or control of at least two Class I railroads, as defined by the Board</quote> and inserting <quote>a transaction described in subsection (b)</quote>.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H8E311494668549F8828273F4BC527742"><enum>3.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The amendments made in this Act shall be applied to all transactions that have not been approved by the Board as of August 1, 2008.</text></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


