<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H7218B43E52254AE695D600CE44431EDD" key="H" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 3467 IH: Second Chance for America's Veterans
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-08-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 3467</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20070804">August 4, 2007</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="Y000062">Mr. Yarmuth</sponsor>
			 introduced the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans'
			 Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To expand and extend counseling and referral programs
		  that minimize recidivism by reintegrating at-risk veterans into meaningful
		  employment.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H047BFCF2F2264867AF77DC2EF8AC14C8" style="OLC">
		<section id="HDBBDDD274A2F4054A04530B0AD6300D4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Second Chance for America's Veterans
			 Act</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H9C9B5636A36142188BDC33F4F3337648"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
			<paragraph id="HF1D7315DEFA445A5B38BC7B4EC00B4EA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>States average a
			 60 percent rate of recidivism among veterans.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HCD34AE030C864651AA75F49C595F643F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>As a demonstration
			 program in seven States, the Incarcerated Veterans Transition Program (IV–TP)
			 has cut recidivism among its veterans by 90 percent.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H53F947B95F2E4B6497E000A32BE877AA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Of the veterans
			 engaged in the national IV–TP program, 90 percent were moved into permanent
			 housing and 72 percent became gainfully employed.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H08B47805C98C4FC59839E9EFD06369BA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>IV–TP saves
			 taxpayers millions of dollars a year in incarceration costs and stimulates
			 local job growth and economic development. In Kentucky’s IV–TP, for example,
			 studies show that up to 166 individuals from the program would have re-offended
			 and returned to a correctional institution at a financial cost of $1.6 million
			 per year. The aggregate annual wages of the veterans assisted by the Kentucky
			 IV–TP program is more than $2.1 million.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H82314E04903644A2A327EC261DBE7676"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment of
			 grant program for referral and counseling services to assist at-risk veterans
			 transitioning into the workplace</header>
			<subsection id="H4249061C2280419CA100E8B8791082D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program
			 authority</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs (hereinafter in this
			 section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall establish a
			 workforce reentry program for eligible veterans consisting of job referral,
			 counseling, and other services deemed necessary by the Secretary to minimize
			 recidivism and improve job placement.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HC16D9A4BE4B547CFB04DCC148723651E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Location of
			 program</header><text>The program shall be carried out in at least twenty-four
			 locations equitably distributed within the United States. One location shall be
			 a penal institution under the jurisdiction of the Bureau of Prisons.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HB1870E4D68224DD8878EC48133E93B66"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Scope of
			 program</header>
				<paragraph id="H3037D007195D45589BBB4D3BC4226400"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To the extent
			 practicable, the program shall provide both referral and counseling services,
			 including assistance with job training and placement (including job readiness),
			 housing, health care, and other benefits to assist eligible veterans in the
			 transition from institutional living.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H797F15DB5A384BEA9EC5B6DB705F0447"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="id1C8A9036CA1D4F51BA35F9C5084E5B0C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To the extent that
			 referral or counseling services are provided at a location under the program,
			 the Secretary must ensure that referral services are administered in person
			 preceding the date of release or discharge from incarceration. Counseling
			 services must begin after an eligible veteran is discharged from incarceration.
			 The Secretary may determine an acceptable period of time to begin referral and
			 counseling services.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4FE58C2B06704546BACCC7DF53093B18" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Secretary may, as part of the
			 program, furnish to officials of penal institutions outreach information with
			 respect to referral and counseling services for presentation to veterans in the
			 custody of such officials during the 18-month period that precedes such date of
			 release or discharge.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H409004B4C83C4A84B249F581895BCFE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible
			 entities</header><text>The Secretary may distribute funds to eligible entities
			 to carry out the referral and counseling services required under the program.
			 Eligible entities may include: Relevant State agencies, non-profit
			 organizations, or State and local workforce investment boards as defined in
			 sections 111 and 117 of the Workforce Investment Act. Eligible entities must
			 have demonstrated competence in managing grants and the capability to provide
			 referrals to other service providers.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H3C24BCC32EB6473D8C4D7F61195D001E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In developing the
			 program, the Secretary shall consult with officials of the U.S. Bureau of
			 Prisons, officials of penal institutions of States and political subdivisions
			 of States, and such other officials as the Secretary determines
			 appropriate.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB5B7BB55F1194E1BBD41E534D6306520"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The
			 Secretary shall have authority to make grants for fiscal years 2008 to
			 2011.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HFE9AA59874454E7181A9D98DD0CCF4D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>Each
			 program shall provide a report to the Secretary containing all relevant program
			 data including percentage of veterans moved into permanent housing, percentage
			 of veterans gainfully employed, and rates of recidivism among participants.
			 Grantees must submit an evaluation exactly three years after grants are
			 awarded.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H4F59A81CA56D42938CB72D316C4BFBA"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In
			 this section, the term <term>eligible veteran</term> means a veteran
			 who—</text>
				<paragraph id="H16B6BAF666704678AEC206D2E3999919"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is a resident of a
			 penal institution or an institution that provides long-term care for mental
			 illness; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H74A14002FEC64A13A01D3B1D132FD7F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is at risk for
			 homelessness absent referral and counseling services provided under the program
			 (as determined under guidelines established by the Secretary).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3E33059ED23943D5B88514B63BB8FAD2"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of
			 appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $15,000,000
			 for each of fiscal years 2008 through 2011 to carry out this program.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


