<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1F1200B5CAB14CACA7B7344EA294183E" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 2703 IH: Private Security Officer Employment Authorization Act of 2007</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-06-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 2703</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070613">June 13, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000210">Mr. Andrews</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and Labor</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend the Private Security Officer Employment Authorization Act of 2004.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HC9D5F1C3DF7745868C1E5F23EEE615DD" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H9AEC4BAB3F254F28A7C3C6F7D0A47312" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Private Security Officer Employment Authorization Act of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H3DF5622AD5194AB6BECCBFE2B2B90328" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reviews of criminal records of applicants for private security officer employment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6402 of the Private Security Officer Employment Authorization Act of 2004 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/28/534">28 U.S.C. 534</external-xref> note) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1E7050A218684C30B102E898FAFD349D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(2)(B), by inserting <quote>, or through an entity designated by the Attorney General,</quote> after <quote>identification bureau</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCCEF1F09B5194711A0984BD305EB3A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H96828A60BF63460DB6747F4104968E00"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>, or to an entity designated by the Attorney General,</quote> after <quote>participating State</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3031253C0DA54408B47D3465E7B98032"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text> 
<clause id="HF13E94F8F7F3495A88EE00AB4DF95188"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>to the State identification bureau of the participating State</quote>;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H48852BBED0CE443EB7804B3C3FD13C83"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (ii) the following new clause:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H283C67864D56412B90F55678932722E9" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<clause id="HA72C1D40ACA74A3D8CF86D40EEA34225"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Accuracy and completeness</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall ensure that there is a process whereby a covered employee subject to a request for a National Crime Information Center criminal history records check under subsection (c)(1) will have the opportunity to provide to the head of the National Crime Information Center of the Federal Bureau of Investigation information concerning the accuracy or completeness of such results. The covered employee involved must provide such information within 30 days after the employee receives such results.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H32393DFAF1CB41D5B108BB1B08E4F81"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)—</text> 
<clause id="H21CA8D18E6534C3100A03C3ED57CC00"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">or authorized employer or entity</header-in-text></quote> after bureau;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HAFDD9330206D4EADBE0092A53EF53668"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the text following the heading, by striking <quote>submitted through the State identification bureau of a participating State, the Attorney General shall</quote> and inserting <quote>the Attorney General or an entity designated by the Attorney General shall</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4E49794A524B442EA100272C4EAF4204"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by inserting <quote>or, if submitted through an entity designated by the Attorney General, to the employer or entity,</quote> before <quote>requesting the information</quote>; </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4DE6B78CA0BB4B58BCD4D77372B1D4D1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D)—</text> 
<clause id="H82E125C17F7D4270B78FD6FB24C9EC1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>the information shall be used only as provided in clause (ii)</quote> and inserting <quote>or by an authorized employer or entity, the information shall be used only as provided in this Act</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA9C5DA82F40D4BC793264F10BBC8CC5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by amending clause (ii) to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H37692A8ABCB04823BFBA2966F59E906D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<clause id="H24654FE3861D4FD9AEFDB61724C6CF9B"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An authorized employer may not employ a covered employee to provide a security service described in subparagraph (B), unless, in the case of—</text> 
<subclause id="HD0187B487518446800F97DC98E5C1939"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a participating State that has no State standards for qualification to be a private security officer, the State shall notify an authorized employer as to the fact of whether the employee has any unpardoned conviction under any Federal or State law of any felony or any one or more of the following offenses, except that, for crimes other than those described in subsection (ll), records will only be provided for convictions that occurred during the previous 10 years or for which the employee completed serving a prison sentence within the previous 5 years:</text> 
<item id="HC1804D6236F94500B2C175C04EFAD616"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>Illegally using, carrying, or possessing any firearm or other dangerous weapon.</text></item> 
<item id="HF639ADF24ED84A6AB0B0E053828900FB"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>Making or possessing an instrument, the primary use of which would be to facilitate burglary, theft, or a similar crime.</text></item> 
<item id="H60DF560D901A44B7A67E0397239B7E61"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>Buying or receiving stolen property.</text></item> 
<item id="HD8F537B5D58E47A3B8EFA60399C7BFE"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>Unlawful entry of a building.</text></item> 
<item id="H9896FDB4587E425A0093DBA3D3DDEF68"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>Aiding escape from prison.</text></item> 
<item id="HFA4C884AA4414DAE8857BF8500B41C7B"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>Unlawfully possessing or distributing any illegal narcotic drug.</text></item> 
<item id="H8A229F74E36846248C5EE6373628BBC6"><enum>(gg)</enum><text>Any act involving theft, including theft by deception.</text></item> 
<item id="H2F9AD1AB22DD4CB685004456AD278F5C"><enum>(hh)</enum><text>Recklessly endangering another person.</text></item> 
<item id="H8BE260C7C4ED459488A780DE32500983"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Making any threat of terror.</text></item> 
<item id="H4466ED588FAB42719DF2941300ED7072"><enum>(jj)</enum><text>Any crime of violence against another individual, including assault or battery, or any crime of violence against the property of an individual.</text></item> 
<item id="H6F6F19DEE4C84018A74482F21B5944F0"><enum>(kk)</enum><text>Attempting or conspiring to commit any of the offenses described in subclauses (I) through (X).</text></item> 
<item id="H0AD58F4AA44D421EA33D4B9ECDBB00EF"><enum>(ll)</enum><text>Any other offense relevant to the ability of the covered employee to provide reliable security services, as specified by the Attorney General by regulation;</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H0F14130DED2343E700C6B360BF06B9FF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a participating State that has State standards for qualification to be a private security officer, the State shall use the information received pursuant to this Act in applying the State standards and shall only notify the employer of the results of the application of the State standards; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H2E0D75E802904EBA94DAFB7703DEDB00"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an authorized employer or entity request through an entity designated by the Attorney General, the Attorney General shall notify the authorized employer or entity as to the fact of whether an employee has any unpardoned conviction under any Federal or State law of any felony or any one or more of the following offenses, except that, for crimes other than those described in subsection (ll), records will only be provided for convictions that occurred during the previous 10 years or for which the covered employee completed serving a prison sentence within the previous 5 years:</text> 
<item id="H30587B5A11E7420EA5349400C56C7CB"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>Illegally using, carrying, or possessing any firearm or other dangerous weapon.</text></item> 
<item id="H099C1FD4B2A24465810003CAAF18B51D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>Making or possessing an instrument, the primary use of which would be to facilitate burglary, theft, or a similar crime.</text></item> 
<item id="H225FD5C6E73C4960801FDD968C81AA4D"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>Buying or receiving stolen property.</text></item> 
<item id="H7C6376A5D3534D60B007E1A7B3ACAF07"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>Unlawful entry of a building.</text></item> 
<item id="H4499A20A282D4A0F96222DEB3DD00656"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>Aiding escape from prison.</text></item> 
<item id="H2A25BDDD6F8140689F213C142C5D493F"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>Unlawfully possessing or distributing any illegal narcotic drug.</text></item> 
<item id="HBD5B5B4A2B314BFCAC696CF0DE18838C"><enum>(gg)</enum><text>Any act involving theft, including theft by deception.</text></item> 
<item id="H020D4DAD3A6A48488602FB6759693790"><enum>(hh)</enum><text>Recklessly endangering another person.</text></item> 
<item id="HDC67AC5697F64EBD9E8DC0465695C86"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Making any threat of terror or engaging in any act of terror.</text></item> 
<item id="H485E5D4861CD4F63AC4D00AAF6917E98"><enum>(jj)</enum><text>Any crime of violence against another individual, including assault or battery, or any crime of violence against the property of an individual.</text></item> 
<item id="H515FD1C5162B4241B9F6A56359C8819C"><enum>(kk)</enum><text>Attempting or conspiring to commit any of the offenses described in subclauses (I) through (X).</text></item> 
<item id="H7D38E052863B4ABC95AC671403D6C55F"><enum>(ll)</enum><text>Any other offense relevant to the ability of the covered employee to provide reliable security services, as specified by the Attorney General by regulation.</text></item></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H76A6B3AA49914CE6AFF7EA500771608"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (E) as subparagraph (F), and by inserting after subparagraph (D) the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1B82F29EF87C447E96088CBBD4376B69" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="HDEA8A5B91732422C934B99BCDA93BBE"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Notifications</header><text>With regard to records that are incomplete, notifications under subparagraph (D)(ii)(lll) shall also provide notice of any state(s) in which such records may be completed or verified.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBF0B332D35CA48D78E2C55CE5215EBE9"><enum>(F)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6F5565B1384F49C3B1D0A845BE684DB1" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="H62903876381F4564B6227602A1F7E88"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Records management</header> 
<clause id="H65D552A52D1140778BB26B005F2F60DD"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An authorized employer receiving any results from a criminal history records check carried out under subsection (c)(1), with respect to a covered employee, shall ensure each of the following:</text> 
<subclause id="H1BA264463DC04124B2C7735EDD087C94"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Such results are maintained confidentially.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HAB364114C5B549CE8C7E385E960593C1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Such results are not misused or disseminated to any person not involved in the employment decision with respect to the covered employee.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HB59CC656B44D4F3DBDE56DFF69D9554E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Subject to paragraph (2), such results are destroyed within one year after the latter of the following dates, with respect to such results:</text> 
<item id="HEAEC273FC3F14400AD00F29D1C0256A0"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>The first of the following dates:</text> 
<subitem id="HCED8C34F570B4F0292B9CC17FAF4684"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>The date of the decision whether to employ or continue to employ the covered employee.</text></subitem> 
<subitem id="HCE2A65DD1F64461C96B90047B7DFCDC"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>The date that is one year after the date on which the authorized employer received the results.</text></subitem></item> 
<item id="HC8B477EA87C748FEBF7300BF84E02417"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>The date that is one year after the final disposition of a claim or proceeding relating to the employment of the covered employee.</text></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HDBCC6A2006B74A1890FC41A28834AFA9"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>No destruction of results if related claim pending</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In no case shall the results from a criminal history records check carried out under subsection (c)(1) be destroyed pursuant to paragraph (1)(C) while a claim or proceeding described in clause (ii) of such paragraph is pending. </text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H09AC30BC82514AEDBEE08FF185C75753"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(2)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC766EE7EDFE248428918001D21F4BA61"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of subparagraph (B);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC394D6CB09E94999BB347FC0A460C971"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (C) as subparagraph (E); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H75C92D03279241029C1E2435C772333F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (B) the following new subparagraphs:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFF1AB3F43F5444C68C49E74FF019CE00" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="H21CB05CD2FA847E38874EDDAF3DA1241"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">standards for the scope of access and the methods and time frames for providing access and responses for these checks, including a requirement that a participating state or the FBI or designated entity is required to respond to a submission by an authorized employer, entity, or consumer reporting agency within three business days of the submission of the fingerprints supporting the request for the criminal history record check;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6BFDE7FE8E594F66BBFF4F11FEB95D1F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a process for providing access for employers and entities to FBI-maintained criminal history records when access is unavailable through the state level because the state has not opted to provide such access or does not meet the standards set forth by the Attorney General; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF545D2E4548442868C94008B4FE5D835"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (4) and (5) of subsection (d) as paragraphs (6) and (7), respectively, of such subsection; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H77AA88B7CDFC4BCEA7220096E8473C37"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (3) of subsection (d) the following new paragraphs:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD5566EC5F3D1434E92726371CCDFC707" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H4A315FFDBCFC421682180013A4AF6600"><enum>(4)</enum><header>No liability for good faith determinations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No authorized employer shall be liable for any determination made by such employer in good faith that an offense identified from a criminal history records check conducted under subsection (c) for such employer on a covered employee is within the scope of offenses described in paragraph (2)(D)(ii) for purposes of such employer making an employment decision with respect to such employee.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBE1370A845444215BA6CB08D34EE7023"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in paragraph (1) shall be construed as preventing an authorized employer from making an employment decision, with respect to a covered employee, based on any lawful reason not described in such subsection, including the reason that the results of a criminal history records check conducted under subsection (c)(1) (or any other information made available to the employer) on such employee indicate that the employment of the employee would violate any applicable State law.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph> </section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


