<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7C2CBB2CA3E146F5A735D025FBF62D50" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>111th CONGRESS</congress> <session>2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 4692</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20100225">February 25, 2010</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000563">Mr. Lipinski</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001259">Mr. Braley of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000577">Mr. Ryan of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001138">Mr. Manzullo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001174">Ms. Sutton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000092">Mr. Ehlers</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001040">Mr. Hare</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000355">Mr. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001149">Mr. Michaud</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001179">Mr. Schock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000108">Mr. Visclosky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000801">Mr. Wilson of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Linda T. Sánchez of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000365">Mr. Kagen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001045">Mr. Stupak</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000565">Mr. Loebsack</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000608">Mrs. Dahlkemper</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000288">Mr. Ellison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000289">Mr. Ellsworth</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000600">Mr. Perriello</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000172">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000595">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001170">Ms. Shea-Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000074">Mr. Taylor</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000285">Mr. Johnson of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on the <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">Budget</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To require the President to prepare a quadrennial National Manufacturing Strategy, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H128EF8E474EB45EC99482AE74377071E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4E992EBB7C87446DB9091721AAC2E70A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote>National Manufacturing Strategy Act of 2010</quote>. </text></section> 
<section id="H5ECDBD709D0C40A9AEC08F9A784AD0C2" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the United States Government should promote policies related to the Nation’s manufacturing sector that are intended to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5919A485B5E14EBD85E372B123116494" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>create sustainable economic growth and increased employment; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD2C06F2E649B4D1596BF388BF757B980" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>create high-quality jobs and decent employment;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD1B82E08953E477F9FF68948F5AEE82E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>increase per capita income;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC1DEEF69619E4F698B339923EEC3AB87" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recruit, improve, and educate the workforce;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1B17607267D441D594F114DB0989AACA" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>increase productivity, exports, and global competitiveness;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9C9240B6A0C94061BAF483799365D28D" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>increase resilience to global economic pressure and fluctuations;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H92BA458807C8430B87210ECF4F28180A" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>increase domestic manufacturing capacity;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H15D03DEFB11448818D09876293E4E6A5" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>maintain and improve national and homeland security;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC1D2F01BCB87455BB63D80BEC6A0A87F" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text>identify and preserve specific manufacturing capabilities and technologies which are considered vital to national defense and security;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCC1CF230F39B4D62B1F1421DC9323668" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><text>assure a reliable and efficient supply chain;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5E38D3D60EE544869F23DDF6C1F8BD9D" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><text>increase access to financial capital and encourage private investment in domestic manufacturing;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H45CA5BEEE33E4CA4AEB29C79904045D6" commented="no"><enum>(12)</enum><text>expand research and development activities and innovation;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE384DC19769142EBADE98F6895BD7F48" commented="no"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improve competitiveness in emerging markets, products, and industries of the manufacturing sector;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8C96B0D5582C4FE98B3C298CE3713B9C" commented="no"><enum>(14)</enum><text>support industries of the manufacturing sector that are facing critical challenges to competitiveness and sustainability; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC374C8E0C2954D87A6B0717C5E5D5188" commented="no"><enum>(15)</enum><text>improve the quality and excellence of manufacturing; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H719E9F5E74C841A5A16111B1C0C58875" commented="no"><enum>(16)</enum><text>enhance collaboration among Government, labor, industry, and academia;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCEDC182813BF4490B6B13614BAC51763" commented="no"><enum>(17)</enum><text>pursue resource and economic sustainability, including increases in energy efficiency; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H68EEA0BDFA85435697C6BE82D0EC704B" commented="no"><enum>(18)</enum><text>improve coordination among agencies in carrying out Government policies.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H91177D4461C141C88A9C7C01214C376B"><enum>3.</enum><header>National Manufacturing Strategy</header> 
<subsection id="HAEADB6F228E84CA389F1110BA4274E4A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the last day of February of the second year of each Presidential term, the President shall conduct a comprehensive analysis of the Nation’s manufacturing sector and submit to Congress a report containing a National Manufacturing Strategy. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H20F92AC02C7E401C9216BB42E4E6AFEB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Comprehensive analysis</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before developing each National Manufacturing Strategy, the President shall conduct a comprehensive analysis of the Nation’s manufacturing sector and related Government programs that will, at a minimum, consider the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HB5A74AD0A6234A3095145132EAB93B65" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The fundamental value and role, both historic and current, of manufacturing in the Nation’s economy, security, and global leadership.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H65131C77F36C4E8E91131BE64337AAE9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The current domestic and international environment for the Nation’s manufacturing sector, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4E30ACDF3E3943C2846A08418C41507D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">specific consideration of particular industries within the manufacturing sector, as determined by the President, from among industries categorized in the North American Industry Classification System as codes 31 to 33;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF1B4F581D9044506B9E80D6591206F74"><enum>(B)</enum><text>regional industrial bases; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5B37847E8E1F4D72A8E3AB9C104600C9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>consideration of firms that have relocated manufacturing operations overseas or relocated overseas operations to the United States, and the factors involved in such relocations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA2B1FA8D9CC14C7D901848338DEBC5EF" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Workforce-related elements, such as the demographics of the labor force, the availability of highly skilled workers, and specific skill sets that are likely to be required of workers in the future. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2136ADFC6872484D9204683F29FE0A06" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The need for research and development to improve innovation and productivity in manufacturing and to enable sustainable domestic production, and an analysis of the impacts of Federal grants, tax credits, and other investments in such research and development on employment in the manufacturing sector.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H235443839A3F43DCAD764ABF98EBB87D" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The importance of exports to manufacturers and the Nation’s trade balance, and the existence of barriers to exports and market access. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2DFDD278DFEB4AB99D6BC6D6DC551052"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The availability of financial capital to the manufacturing industry.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H28E5CB95A1574549B5C449C4E3E14ACC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The role of domestic manufacturing in national security, and the potential for related joint international acquisition, development, and procurement programs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4E1A9D42F414460383C2B57553F17E2A" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The impact that Government policies and actions have, directly and indirectly, on manufacturing industries, including taxation policy, regulations, procurement, and domestic sourcing requirements.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0CD4CCA7FF4C4B539BED16AFC0D82658" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The impact of Federal procurement, funding, and tax credits on the importation of foreign manufactured goods, including the amount of funds expended on, and identification of, products in defense, energy, communications, infrastructure, and other critical technologies that are imported. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H78CD3726CBD84E24B9C51A9C6B72DB95"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The identification of emerging or evolving markets, technologies, and products that the Nation’s manufacturers could compete for. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB1CC4C243E3949D094C756CCB627CFC5"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The identification of specific manufacturing industries in the United States that are facing critical challenges.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6C78B75F66AB4270923A09D67EDC3FA4" commented="no"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The identification of critical technologies required to sustain national defense and security, including energy and communications technologies. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEA25C6581CDE41618992442910811136" commented="no"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Establishment of minimum manufacturing capability baselines needed to rapidly respond in times of national emergencies, including wartime scenarios.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCE7EBA1D53C84A07A079424B6A922B56"><enum>(14)</enum><text>The problems faced in particular by small- and medium-sized manufacturers.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0A55B7E426244C838739B9954C6A33C0"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Aspects of the global supply chain and the availability of natural resources. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2F83AABC6A264B9782655798729F1961"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The interaction among various Federal Government policies that affect manufacturing, the manufacturing-related workforce, and manufacturing-dependent communities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE2B1C32CE7C44C1D95ACE46C9A6758F4"><enum>(17)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">State, local, and territorial policies and conditions that affect manufacturing, including interstate competition and public subsidies for facility siting and relocation. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1AE719069A444073B5295AC315103756"><enum>(18)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A comparison of the manufacturing policies of the United States relative to other nations’ policies and strategies.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1ACB7798591B4BE0868B7BF93ED903A4"><enum>(19)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The effects of international trade agreements and other treaties or international agreements, both that the United States is party to and others that affect the United States or markets for its products.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4719DB5D259F4D6F8E197ED70C3EC838"><enum>(20)</enum><text>The status of international intellectual property protections.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HECF7F912ACEE4E599F1F5CBC159CF837"><enum>(21)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The short- and long-term forecasts for the Nation’s manufacturing sector, and forecasts of expected national and international trends and factors likely to affect such sector in the future.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDDAD3A54EF684F7294A7D41FA1A35A89"><enum>(22)</enum><text>The role that the authority provided under the Defense Production Act of 1950 (50 U.S.C. App. 2061 et seq.) could have in the implementation of the National Manufacturing Strategy.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBD7CF11B95A34FADAA5C087D1BAF0685"><enum>(23)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An analysis of any other factors affecting manufacturing competitiveness, growth, stability, and sustainability.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0563F33352CF4023B96E28810F50F364"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Task force</header> 
<paragraph id="HA433D840E55B4CE9ADCFD1EA3F089D4D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing each National Manufacturing Strategy, the President shall convene a Manufacturing Strategy Task Force. </text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H332ED1AA50C14E68B2D2B4EBCD787BE5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Members</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Manufacturing Strategy Task Force convened with respect to a National Manufacturing Strategy shall include the following individuals:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7135980A66634F628DF9B5301C565F53"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Secretary or head (or the designee of the Secretary or head) of each of the following organizations:</text> 
<clause id="HEC6141CDCB6A4DC9A64369F89321C00D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Department of the Treasury.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE9B876BF55394659AA2CB841F90D1D03"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Department of Defense.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC4E225F6575746ABBE7DAECEA5E26E87"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The Department of Commerce.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H02753BC8B3A24409A19527FEB7401D46"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The Department of Labor.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H208C2283AD954FA3BE6A3C1EBACC8459"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The Department of Energy.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H589628EA80F543B2890A4C5F04224C4D"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>The Domestic Policy Council.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H89C95858A05046E6B70092CF0501FE0E"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>The National Economic Council.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2C0AE0428AAB4224A8D7E1500C5C09B1"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>The Council of Economic Advisors.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7A9B88190890450E8B0E3C8101039BAD"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>The National Security Council.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7FD1BFA1960F4D379301B4C188F10D73"><enum>(x)</enum><text>The Office of Management and Budget.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H215E03BDD6A94863902E58A276CA0F00"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>The Office of Science and Technology Policy.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4386CA4DC3AF4C1F9AA44E0931E024A3"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>The Small Business Administration.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA625662FB42F46819D6F897637C52A26"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>Other Federal agencies the President determines appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3127C06743FD444587CEC958B5365AB1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Governors of two States, from different political parties, appointed by the President in consultation with the National Governors Association.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0DA419DDF0D84B26B75114A6630709DC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Chairman</header><text>The President shall designate a Chairman of the Manufacturing Strategy Task Force from among Cabinet-level appointees and other advisors to the President who are officers or employees of the Federal Government.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6B7AFC619FEA43B4A6658EDDC59DAD41" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Subgroups</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Manufacturing Strategy Task Force may convene subgroups to address particular industries, policy topics, or other matters. Such subgroups may include members representing any of the following: </text> 
<subparagraph id="H4D85C0497A6948A0A48ECE30D055FBB4" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Such other Federal agencies as the Chairman determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7D4CD18B6067434A8DEABDBDEA3BCF95" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>State, local, tribal, and territorial governments.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H271E4314BF4E424CB80AA6AE225F57E9" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The private sector, including labor, industry, academia, trade associations, and other appropriate groups.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4090FC212707470594FA4E3CAF9FC975"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text>The Manufacturing Strategy Task Force shall make recommendations to the President for incorporation into the National Manufacturing Strategy regarding the following matters:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H93E957D62D3042248948D2CAD4741F7C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The results of the comprehensive analysis conducted by the President under subsection (b). </text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0041A0B19187470F9E3A4F09D08649F6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The design, effectiveness, purpose, funding levels, and other features of current Federal Government programs and policies that are intended to assist the manufacturing sector, including taxation, workforce development, research and development, technical assistance, export control requirements, procurement, and domestic sourcing policies. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFFAA3C0088D241E197D442D96E0591C6"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The interaction among, and integration of, Federal Government policies that affect manufacturing, the manufacturing-related workforce, and manufacturing-dependent communities.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3A40ECC49969437C94F1FEA2B6D08B38"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Areas of need that could be addressed by new Federal Government programs.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H46DC6912FA03487DA2AB8C65BD1C5D79"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Emerging markets, industry shifts, workforce changes, or other transformations foreseen to affect the manufacturing sector in the future. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDB4E2A7575654FC297CFA1320695DA74"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The availability of financial capital to the manufacturing sector, with particular emphasis on lower tiers of the supply chain and small businesses. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3D0FB43E4ACF4767B47A8E9A16158363"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Opportunities to increase exports and enhance international trade competitiveness.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD2FD3F764E554263AF79A1CEA5B45624"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Federal incentives to encourage industry to balance pressures for short-term profits with implementation of the National Manufacturing Strategy.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE1325C9A4FCE4EED944F93ABFF7C9E68"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Other areas designated by the President for consideration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA7739A84C3C14D9AA461000E9933774F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Public meetings required</header><text>The Manufacturing Strategy Task Force shall convene public meetings to solicit views on the manufacturing sector and proposed recommendations for the National Manufacturing Strategy. The locations of these meetings shall ensure the inclusion of multiple regions and industries of the manufacturing sector. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC1CF7596AB8248FAB915D4A75068D11E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Goals and recommendations</header> 
<paragraph id="H08F06EE0415D493EB764CFAC39E53394"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Goals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each National Manufacturing Strategy shall provide short- and long-term goals for the Nation’s manufacturing sector, including goals—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H807B60F0516441C8A409D7456B69C244"><enum>(A)</enum><text>related to improving—</text> 
<clause id="HCF76A546C90E4FFC975E262EEBEDABFB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>levels of domestic production; </text></clause> 
<clause id="HFCB3483A52D54DD29677619D77FAE9C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>productivity; </text></clause> 
<clause id="H65C54F9D5FE14D87B673658DBE3DA305"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>investment in particular industries;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HCD171266165B40089FE755F5A47A9147"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>research and development intensity;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE8D515FCBD764D99A7DB391BE95FC8EF"><enum>(v)</enum><text>innovation;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4184C06B74294E9BB2AC55638068494F"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>employment;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE4216E4BC37E410FABC8B18DFE6198F3"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>workforce skills and development; </text></clause> 
<clause id="HB3FDAB70E69746D7ADA6867A9B48ECD1"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>international competitiveness; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDB4D36255C034F69B74F9CC838833B27"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>the industrial base to ensure it is adequate for maintaining national security; and </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6479B732A49A42BA9DF870931F30DA6A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for any other relevant economic, social, and policy factors.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2F981AE2A4B241F99B5C2FEE03D88FAA" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each National Manufacturing Strategy shall include recommendations for achieving the goals provided under paragraph (1). Such recommendations may propose—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFDB364C1F8124E33BF3B746F673A10A5" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>actions to be taken by State, local, and territorial governments, the President, Congress, the private sector, universities, industry associations, and other stakeholders; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H62E19E73ABB5409D8ED7BEE7BD8DFC1F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ways to improve Government policies and interaction with the manufacturing sector. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9655F098969343CAA58F9204C8013803"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Strategy board</header><text>In developing each National Manufacturing Strategy, the President shall consider the recommendations of the President’s Manufacturing Strategy Board established under section 5.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3BAABD49FBC04C2FBCFB7022FC690998"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Studies</header><text>In developing each National Manufacturing Strategy, the President shall consider the results of the studies carried out pursuant to section 6.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HA7F213CFB64C445E8323D266773D4126"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report</header> 
<paragraph id="HEAB0246E4F9C45F6B45B342D8BF44C99"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Draft</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A draft report containing a National Manufacturing Strategy shall be published for public comment in the Federal Register and on a public website for a period of 90 days. Following the comment period, the Manufacturing Strategy Task Force shall review any comments and reflect those views in its recommendations to the President under subsection (c)(5).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA1DBA644FF594C099022C134D736148A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Submission to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each final National Manufacturing Strategy shall be submitted to Congress upon completion.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCBB21B8724B848DEB463BEC3BA58A099"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Publication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each final National Manufacturing Strategy shall be published on a public website.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCAAB493187B8481BBA74266834E02693"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Deadline for first National Manufacturing Strategy</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (a), the President shall issue the first National Manufacturing Strategy not later than February 28, 2011.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H870AA281CA164B88BD7EDEA73ADAC0A9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Government Accountability Office review of National Manufacturing Strategy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Three years following publication of a National Manufacturing Strategy under section 3, the Comptroller General shall conduct a review of the recommendations contained in such National Manufacturing Strategy, including—</text> 
<paragraph id="H451EBC05FBA04FF283A2944A7D106E93"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of whether the recommendations were implemented;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC787BAD9C89A4E6D940F5C10FC1EE911"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis of the impact of those recommendations;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H62F86EA1C68A44F2BD0C68E94AF53931"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a review of the trends and short- and long-term forecasts of manufacturing contained in previous National Manufacturing Strategies, compared to actual events and trends; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD86424B3A8F0461F8F787896FD175F96"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a review of the process involved in developing the previous National Manufacturing Strategy; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA139874B10AE4F0EBB0A746A0740FAF7"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations for improvement in developing the next National Manufacturing Strategy.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H3066E7A9B5364FBCA5EDA16620D1A695"><enum>5.</enum><header>President’s Manufacturing Strategy Board</header> 
<subsection id="H914F4C84920B45138857549D4F5FCD0F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall convene a President’s Manufacturing Strategy Board, which shall provide the President with information and recommendations regarding the needs of, and opportunities for, the Nation’s manufacturing sector. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7B04CD37F4D3490B8D9BB295C6C82834"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header> 
<paragraph id="H202219643CDF48D3994FDF4B7D8E162C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President’s Manufacturing Strategy Board shall consist of 21 individuals from the private sector, appointed by the President after consultation with industrial organizations. Such individuals shall represent a broad range of regions and industries, including individuals with experience in the areas of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9FD620F04A694911A7F0B1FFB28E4D32"><enum>(A)</enum><text>managing manufacturing companies;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2AEE0D81AFEF447C9858F7D5310A083E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>managing supply chain providers;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEA6319271F7C488389E6C377DD9085C8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>financing manufacturing operations;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H797A27FB712B4584BFD26DF442FA0F9C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>labor-management relations;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8EF6D75CD0C2425EBD4CD92EE304CB6C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>workforce development;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA4BB55C2B9F14B6895A18E3AFA8AEB9D"><enum>(F)</enum><text>conducting related research and development; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H720E3AFE797B42368332D16D3248A4D7"><enum>(G)</enum><text>other fields related to manufacturing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H20748F03991F49129600E4E2870D1641" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation regarding affiliations</header><text>The President’s Manufacturing Strategy Board shall include individuals of whom there are no fewer than—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF022E49D46FE410EA50419CC8696383D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>3 representatives of labor organizations;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H55D7277FE2104CC0853A0200AB0B653D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>3 representatives of manufacturing firms with fewer than 500 employees; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE41F3763CF934FC89CAF5449EBAB05D4" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>1 representative of an academic institution who is involved in research and development regarding manufacturing-related technology or systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3F63D0A1C88947D3A4266BB77EBEF57F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Balance in representation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making appointments to the Manufacturing Strategy Board, the President shall seek to ensure that the individuals appointed represent a balance among and within industries of the manufacturing sector. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0AFB706F890341B4931327B5CE7F480C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Co-Chairmen</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President’s Manufacturing Strategy Board shall be co-chaired by 3 members representing the President’s Council of Advisors on Science and Technology, the Manufacturing Council of the Department of Commerce, and the Defense Policy Board.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H73FBCEC5482F4EF49C44CFC58BBC3260"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Terms</header> 
<paragraph id="H4427B40B30104E5A96998D89E09BD7C6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each member shall be appointed for a term of 6 years, except as provided in paragraphs (2) and (3).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3DFB00463652424797969DD319E4BF9F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Terms of initial appointees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As designated by the President at the time of appointment, of the members first appointed—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7A8E28CBA91F4C16B8C6F9166634120F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>7 shall be appointed for a term of 2 years;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD81A6A9560674B68A4A4FF2D78641C83"><enum>(B)</enum><text>7 shall be appointed for a term of 4 years; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2DC92E445E14426C9B1C126456B9400F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>7 shall be appointed for a term of 6 years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBA3E0BC283EA447C978DA3DBA207C937"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any member appointed to fill a vacancy occurring before the expiration of the term for which the member’s predecessor was appointed shall be appointed only for the remainder of that term. A member may serve after the expiration of that member’s term until a successor has taken office.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H8D80589CF76A417891A0054063A0D17F"><enum>6.</enum><header>Studies</header> 
<subsection id="HC563520A50E9473EB41249C808E8870B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Quadrennial study</header> 
<paragraph id="H6E9B29D27ED040D597F5CE846C928B6D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In developing each National Manufacturing Strategy, the President, acting through the Office of Science and Technology Policy, shall enter into an agreement with the National Academy of Sciences to conduct a study in accordance with this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCC093A96925149938C17C915FF2DC99A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The study shall examine the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H70C04258FC344C54858D1A0F14D11159"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The current state of manufacturing in the United States.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7B42D21CC1D1424CA2ABFE6430912B5E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Federal programs and activities related to, and Government reliance on, manufacturing systems.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H30EEFE40F06B45E6BE52D3A31AADCFDF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The ways in which Federal policies affect manufacturing, and likely future trends in manufacturing if such policies remain unchanged.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H820F30DCED5441F38BC7EEA248702CDB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Various possible standards for evaluating the implementation of the National Manufacturing Strategy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD0AEC859E5074F20B6198778EB6A5C6E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The agreement shall provide that not later than the last day of February of the first year of each Presidential term, the National Academy of Sciences shall submit to Congress and the President a report containing the findings of the study.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBAD3D2765621403AB2E2EAB81FC8FC47"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Deadline for first report</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (3), the first agreement entered into under this subsection shall provide that the National Academy of Sciences shall submit to Congress and the President a report containing the findings of the study not later than 2 years after the date such agreement is entered into.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDEB43AE845F24B36ADFB744904D138B7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Deadline for subsequent agreements</header><text>After the first agreement entered into under this subsection, all subsequent agreements under this subsection shall be entered into not later than 18 months before the deadline for submission of the corresponding report under paragraph (3).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H67BED992C03145E080E8DE9B86DDC8E2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional studies</header> 
<paragraph id="HB981876037E1499C87BD048C4B12AC5A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Required studies</header><text>In order to inform future National Manufacturing Strategies, not later than 60 days after the enactment of this Act the President shall enter into an agreement with the National Academy of Sciences to develop three reports as follows:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0D2E31CE54484184BE9FF37C5A9C97E5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 14 months after entering into an agreement under this paragraph, the National Academy of Sciences shall submit to Congress and the President a report that describes the stresses on the Nation’s manufacturing sector and recommends ways in which the Federal Government can support such sector. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H36C88432140B428B89F7EB0C6D64E535"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 20 months after entering into an agreement under this paragraph, the National Academy of Sciences shall submit to Congress and the President a report that predicts the likely needs of, and challenges to, the manufacturing sector in the year 2035. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDC66CE5B614540E7BBF47324599AA3C2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 24 months after entering into an agreement under this paragraph, the National Academy of Sciences shall submit to Congress and the President a report that assesses Government manufacturing programs and research and development portfolios (including the interrelation of such programs and portfolios), how well such programs and portfolios address perceived needs of the manufacturing sector, and recommendations for a research strategy to address any gaps in such programs and portfolios. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3B4369A8841D48C1AFDEAED5729EDED7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Discretionary studies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After the required studies are complete, the President may enter into further agreements with the National Academy of Sciences to develop reports to inform future National Manufacturing Strategies.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H86E87F6221DE43A5BCF3C2E9E14E2D3F"><enum>7.</enum><header>Requirement to consider National Manufacturing Strategy in budget</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In preparing the budget for a fiscal year under section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code, the President shall include information regarding the consistency of the budget with the goals and recommendations included in National Manufacturing Strategy covering that fiscal year.</text> </section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 
