<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H5706E0CE124D4473917D46849DF1475E" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 2721 IH: To amend title 10, United States Code, to require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to develop, and the Secretary of Defense to distribute to members of the Armed Forces upon their discharge or release from active duty, information in a compact disk read-only memory format that lists and explains the health, education, and other benefits for which veterans are eligible under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-06-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 2721</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070614">June 14, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001050">Mr. Cardoza</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend title 10, United States Code, to require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to develop, and the Secretary of Defense to distribute to members of the Armed Forces upon their discharge or release from active duty, information in a compact disk read-only memory format that lists and explains the health, education, and other benefits for which veterans are eligible under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H8EA283C6FE6347D2925221AB491EB4CD" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3DACDCE53D464437B5624E30E1BA505F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Veterans health, education, and other benefits information in compact disk read-only memory format for members of the Armed Forces upon their discharge or release from active duty</header> 
<subsection id="H004FC6E19EE24353BF23DAD3BADE7CA5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Development and distribution of information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1142">Section 1142</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H88F01B4F9568401000036FD3AD3428C5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(17), by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>, including, once available, a copy of the compact disk developed by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs under subsection (d) and containing the information described in such subsection.</quote>; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1979698121864109B7B1CD84DBF5E757"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD995113077104085AB192D3FBC5B4E70" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HBA3E53A79F97429C81105C106C68495F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Compact disk of veterans health, education, and other benefits information</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4611089814584AA4BEE2801D38C24B4D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall develop and maintain, in a compact disk read-only memory format, certain information that the Secretary determines would be helpful to veterans. The information shall include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF545DA599D5A43F09F0056C1992CC7F2" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A listing and explanation of all the benefits for which veterans may be eligible under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H00940BBB3BD2496D8D19DF00BAB247A1" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A comprehensive explanation of how veterans may apply for such benefits, including procedures, requirements, and locations for submitting applications for such benefits.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H89B529B32DA04D5E8C236ECD97E568B7" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A listing of all facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs and contact information for such facilities.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC6D3B65A92F54740BAC57B9E230030D4" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The compact disk developed under this subsection shall be distributed to members of the Armed Forces pursuant to subsection (b) and, upon request, to family members of members of the Armed Forces.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7ED150DBE98B4EF291B284451906E66"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Internet website</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs, the Secretary of Defense, and the head of any other relevant Government agency shall each maintain an Internet website on which information shall be made available at all times that clearly explains the benefits administered by that Secretary or agency head to which veterans are entitled and how veterans can secure those benefits. The website shall include information about how family members of veterans may request a compact disk pursuant to subsection (d)(2).</text> </subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H20996F0A763C4D85869B946E00F3176C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The compact disk required by <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1142">section 1142(d)</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), shall be developed and ready for distribution to members of the Armed Forces not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text> </subsection></section>
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


