<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7137C77EAE6243EEBDEE6E56FADC1C1" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>111th CONGRESS</congress>
<session>1st Session</session>
<legis-num>H. R. 1546</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20090317">March 17, 2009</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001166">Mr. McNerney</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001236">Mr. Boozman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to establish the Committee on Care of Veterans with Traumatic Brain Injury.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H5F94B2428BCC4ED681383D00484B1569" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4CD413C81AB34BB2BBA9E3854117EABB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Caring for Veterans with Traumatic Brain Injury Act of 2009</short-title></quote>.</text></section>
<section id="H3315180A57AC4B10A5DA262259A835CF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Committee on Care of Veterans with Traumatic Brain Injury</header>
<subsection id="H14D066A13E6640F3B6AED6E1FD8C7E1C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of committee</header><text>Subchapter II of chapter 73 of title 38, United States Code, is amended by inserting after section 7321 the following new section:</text>
<quoted-block id="H0E626E5F07A04A3F82BEDE10FEDAC7F9" style="USC">
<section id="HFED84DBE331C42C3B3E355F08284FB71"><enum>7321A.</enum><header>Committee on Care of Veterans with Traumatic Brain Injury</header>
<subsection id="H1715DFF4062843998E6139AA25559FA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall establish in the Veterans Health Administration a committee to be known as the <quote>Committee on Care of Veterans with Traumatic Brain Injury</quote>. The Under Secretary for Health shall appoint employees of the Department with expertise in the care of veterans with traumatic brain injury to serve on the committee.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H36B01BCC0C3A42CCA92FABAC3996C262"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities of committee</header><text>The committee shall assess, and carry out a continuing assessment of, the capability of the Veterans Health Administration to meet effectively the treatment and rehabilitation needs of veterans with traumatic brain injury. In carrying out that responsibility, the committee shall—</text>
<paragraph id="HCADC6E3B923F47CC81EF2DDB173E0022"><enum>(1)</enum><text>evaluate the care provided to such veterans through the Veterans Health Administration;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1F136B8D19154C56B19C1386C245DDD8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify systemwide problems in caring for such veterans in facilities of the Veterans Health Administration;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2F51DB09AF994D6100889CAEE871AB00"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify specific facilities within the Veterans Health Administration at which program enrichment is needed to improve treatment and rehabilitation of such veterans; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF2CABFA8C14747E881AD36B62E29679D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identify model programs which the committee considers to have been successful in the treatment and rehabilitation of such veterans and which should be implemented more widely in or through facilities of the Veterans Health Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H136B3CBA31B141E5B39B17369428CD9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Advice and recommendations</header><text>The committee shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H51950E48BF5349AF82C756F1219BEA32"><enum>(1)</enum><text>advise the Under Secretary regarding the development of policies for the care and rehabilitation of veterans with traumatic brain injury; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2EF63939D8AF42BBBCBCDEB4E0632CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make recommendations to the Under Secretary—</text>
<subparagraph id="HA9F713F6BCAF471CB8003C86B3134E45"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for improving programs of care of such veterans at specific facilities and throughout the Veterans Health Administration;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H496E7885F5CA4F6E96E0A574B0D3D9C9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for establishing special programs of education and training relevant to the care of such veterans for employees of the Veterans Health Administration;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE1327116FF39422ABD67FA3B91269592"><enum>(C)</enum><text>regarding research needs and priorities relevant to the care of such veterans; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7C9A36A6772E4FE9AF47D7793D548F3E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>regarding the appropriate allocation of resources for all such activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA7EF93178987408B96FB231042638CDD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than June 1 of 2010, and each subsequent year, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives a report on the implementation of this section. Each such report shall include the following for the calendar year preceding the year in which the report is submitted:</text>
<paragraph id="H9EDAB278204D48DF86B181E1CDDF319"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A list of the members of the committee.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HED14DDD9881543B491E4EA6949007538"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The assessment of the Under Secretary for Health, after review of the initial findings of the committee, regarding the capability of the Veterans Health Administration, on a systemwide and facility-by-facility basis, to meet effectively the treatment and rehabilitation needs of veterans with traumatic brain injury.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3A5256E193424CF9904CB4C666B800FE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The plans of the committee for further assessments.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE6D1ADDB0F5F49BF98AF3BB2F57C51FE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The findings and recommendations made by the committee to the Under Secretary for Health and the views of the Under Secretary on such findings and recommendations.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H08E683F457B549D3BC1F51D5ECFA07A9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A description of the steps taken, plans made (and a timetable for the execution of such plans), and resources to be applied toward improving the capability of the Veterans Health Administration to meet effectively the treatment and rehabilitation needs of veterans with traumatic brain injury.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H2A928D8D4ABA48739278678001C663E0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 7321 the following new item:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H894E2D1238FD4538A3C3DF2C9156202" style="USC">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">7321A. Committee on Care of Veterans with Traumatic Brain Injury.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 
