<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HAC54898F0D97473FB0DA8A6EA9E74902" public-private="public">
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>111th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 1796</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20090330">March 30, 2009</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001142">Mr. Matheson</sponsor>
			 introduced the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and
			 Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To amend the Consumer Product Safety Act to require
		  residential carbon monoxide detectors to meet the applicable ANSI/UL standard
		  by treating that standard as a consumer product safety rule, to encourage
		  States to require the installation of such detectors in homes, and for other
		  purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HE3094D819D4744C6A6DAC3A6BCBFB3F3" style="OLC">
		<section id="H0CE71BA8258648A585D86DC4266B8A32" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Residential Carbon Monoxide Poisoning
			 Prevention Act</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="HA24A3934443A4DA69D6252A052C5AC0B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
			<paragraph id="H520F7F187F264DF7893F9CC87A6AD3E3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Carbon monoxide is
			 a colorless, odorless gas produced by burning any fuel. Exposure to unhealthy
			 levels of carbon monoxide can lead to carbon monoxide poisoning, a serious
			 health condition that could result in death.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HBC4605F6F71742289EFB7E5FC290C211"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Carbon monoxide poisoning from the use of
			 fuel-burning appliances, such as furnaces, water heaters, portable generators,
			 and stoves, in residential homes and other dwelling units kills at least 500
			 people each year and sends more than 20,000 to hospital emergency rooms for
			 treatment.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H1B4C4CC7549B40E1AF644CCD8B090376"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Research shows
			 that purchasing and installing carbon monoxide alarms close to the sleeping
			 areas in residential homes and other dwelling units can help avoid
			 fatalities.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HFE1FF8BE55604CD1AF0D0359EDC060F5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Congress should
			 promote the purchase and installation of carbon monoxide alarms in residential
			 homes and dwelling units nationwide in order to promote the health and public
			 safety of citizens throughout the Nation.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H5BCB82A70C2F44029DC7BCC15F4E65B0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Adoption of
			 ANSI/UL 2034 as consumer product safety rule</header>
			<subsection id="H082F467461C940E19B34493D411A6718"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 General</header><text>The Consumer Product Safety Act (15 U.S.C. 2051 et seq.)
			 is amended by adding at the end thereof the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="HC5447D51B0BA4E8A9E2C88200B37C59E" style="OLC">
					<section id="HDF419404878742FDBA3FE9F78A0BEAD9"><enum>43.</enum><header>Residential
				carbon monoxide detectors</header>
						<subsection id="H1A88DA9C94C840F99AF604B8A9BD1AAD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
				General</header>
							<paragraph id="HEDA8C8A397164C4CB5841F02890ED593"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Mandatory
				standard</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, within 90
				days after the date of enactment of the Residential Carbon Monoxide Poisoning
				Prevention Act, the Consumer Product Safety Commission shall publish in the
				Federal Register as a mandatory consumer product safety standard the American
				National Standard for Single and Multiple Station Carbon Monoxide Alarms
				(American National Standard ANSI/UL 2034–2005). The standard shall take effect
				180 days after it is published.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H48DF6F13CEBC439A9C9E567685EDD24C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compliance with
				standard</header><text>After the standard takes effect, it shall be unlawful
				for any manufacturer or distributor to import into or distribute in commerce in
				the United States any new assembled or unassembled residential carbon monoxide
				detector unless it complies with the standard.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H47649AA383E14EBF8AAE52F85339CA4A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Violation</header><text>The
				failure to comply with paragraph (2) shall be deemed to be a failure to comply
				with a consumer product safety standard under this Act and subject to all of
				the penalties and remedies available under this Act.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H2163B3CCBA8643A8B2345385D92BC702"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Other types of
				carbon monoxide detectors</header><text>Paragraph (2) does not apply to any
				carbon monoxide detector not covered by the standard as provided in section 1.4
				of the standard.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9BA7F25B07B7401A947A74C2869A503B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Labeling</header><text>Beginning
				1 year after the date of enactment of the Residential Carbon Monoxide Poisoning
				Prevention Act, a manufacturer selling or offering for sale in the United
				States a residential carbon monoxide detector manufactured more than 1 year
				after the date of enactment of that Act, shall clearly identify on any
				container of the detector and on the detector its conformance with the
				requirements of the consumer product safety standard promulgated under
				subsection (a).</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H132457366C9D4710AE4F12B5BD2190A3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Modification of
				Standard</header>
							<paragraph id="H9F065EA6868E4D5F834AD71E5A0E47C5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>ANSI
				revisions</header><text>If the American National Standard ANSI/UL 2034–2008 is
				revised through the applicable consensus standards development process after
				the date on which the product safety standard for residential carbon monoxide
				detectors is published in the Federal Register, the American National Standards
				Institute shall notify the Commission of the revision.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H91AF2B7935D746848A156A8B9EB4EAE5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commission
				action</header><text>Within 120 days after it receives notice of such a
				revision by the American National Standards Institute, the Commission shall
				issue a notice of proposed rulemaking in accordance with section 553 of title
				5, United States Code, to amend the product safety standard for residential
				carbon monoxide detectors to include any such revision that the Commission
				determines is reasonably related to the performance of such detectors, and
				notify the Institute of any revision it has determined not to be so related.
				The Commission shall promulgate an amendment to the standard for such detectors
				within 180 days after the date on which the notice of proposed rulemaking for
				the amendment is published in the Federal Register.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HE6F3522CEE3B467E837E868179C53076"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional
				safety requirements</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this
				Act, the Commission may, pursuant to sections 7 and 9 of this Act, amend the
				product safety standard for residential carbon monoxide detectors to include
				any additional provision that the Commission determines is reasonably necessary
				to ensure their safe and effective operation.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H1FFED8EB351844E19F4D1DAD3F985745"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Certain
				provisions not applicable</header><text>Sections 7 and 9 of this Act shall not
				apply to promulgation of any amendment of the product safety standard under
				paragraph (2). Judicial review of any amendment of the standard under paragraph
				(2) shall be in accordance with chapter 7 of title 5, United States
				Code.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H6E39326E7B624176AC9EC06AA52EB3AC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming
			 Amendment</header><text>The table of contents of the Consumer Product Safety
			 Act is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 42 the
			 following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4F1EA9CA478142419E098F34469197D5" style="OLC">
					<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
						<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 43. Residential carbon monoxide
				  detectors.</toc-entry>
					</toc>
					<after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section><section id="H7150251C8F0E4E359F00A4009B9D7AE2"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reducing deaths
			 and injuries from carbon monoxide poisoning</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of
			 enactment of this Act, the Consumer Product Safety Commission shall promulgate
			 consumer product safety rules, pursuant to section 7 of the Consumer Product
			 Safety Act (15 U.S.C. 2056), requiring, at a minimum, the following:</text>
			<paragraph id="H2C939573C73C4E789CBAFDAD599EC31C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Warning
			 labels</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each portable
			 generator sold to the public for purposes other than resale shall have a large,
			 prominently displayed warning label on the exterior packaging, if any, of the
			 portable generator and permanently affixed on the portable generator regarding
			 the carbon monoxide hazard posed by incorrect use of the portable generator.
			 The warning label shall include the word <quote>DANGER</quote> in prominently
			 displayed text and shall include the following information, at a minimum,
			 presented in a clear manner:</text>
				<subparagraph id="H46802D3A1E9244E0ACD0E2AAE1C02E12"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Indoor use of a
			 portable generator can kill quickly.</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCE2DED3F09545E4BC6083CFB2C6DFCE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Portable
			 generators should be used outdoors only and away from garages and open
			 windows.</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF63F8886FEFC445C9EF58CF18C2640CE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Portable
			 generators produce carbon monoxide, a poisonous gas that people cannot see or
			 smell.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4DFCA51666564E668A9E3AED23F6981F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Pictogram</header><text>Each
			 portable generator sold to the public for purposes other than resale shall have
			 a large pictogram, affixed to the portable generator, which clearly states
			 <quote>OUTDOOR USE ONLY: EMITS POISONOUS GAS</quote> and visually depicts the
			 harmful effects of breathing carbon monoxide.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H099A1CA55C33444697A5F125C5A5533E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Instruction
			 manual</header><text>The instruction manual, if any, that accompanies any
			 portable generator sold to the public for purposes other than resale shall
			 include detailed, clear, and conspicuous statements that include the following
			 elements:</text>
				<subparagraph id="H1DE63C2A5F634946BD0EE2D50D6C6A66"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A warning that
			 portable generators emit carbon monoxide, a poisonous gas that can kill
			 people.</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H786E9143DC7B4C6BBFA3B1FA8479325F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A warning that
			 people cannot smell, see, or taste carbon monoxide.</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H930D08952B204087BE65DEE52E58080A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An instruction to
			 operate portable generators only outdoors and away from windows, garages, and
			 air intakes.</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7268AA5012B64AA58EA513199880E5A0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An instruction
			 never to operate portable generators inside homes, garages, sheds, or other
			 semi-enclosed spaces, even if a person runs a fan or opens doors and
			 windows.</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE308255808E8414D8B789082DE25E649"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A warning that if
			 a person begins to feel sick, dizzy, or weak while using a portable generator,
			 that person should shut off the portable generator, get to fresh air
			 immediately, and consult a doctor.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HB7A8D10574064CF2BAE661253F9996FF"><enum>5.</enum><header>State grant
			 program for carbon monoxide alarms</header>
			<subsection id="H51B6E4559F5A4E8C9DBABBA8ACF04234"><enum>(a)</enum><header>State Approved
			 Carbon Monoxide Alarm Grant Program</header>
				<paragraph id="HDB2BCD28251E4525A45BF873C655F35C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations authorized
			 by subsection (c), the Consumer Product Safety Commission shall establish a
			 grant program to provide assistance to eligible States to carry out a carbon
			 monoxide alarm program.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H27F08D9CB6204FBDA50E88E4AA799D12"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To
			 be eligible for a grant under the program, a State shall—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H0721F3859FDE42F4ADA49892F8165A7D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>demonstrate to the
			 satisfaction of the Commission that the State has adopted a statute, or a State
			 agency has adopted a state-wide rule, regulation, or similar measure with the
			 force and effect of law, requiring the inclusion of approved carbon monoxide
			 alarms installed in accordance with NFPA 720 in all commercial residential
			 dwelling units and all new dwelling unit construction and providing penalties
			 for failure to include such alarms; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E52786539FB4673BAD9F0DBEEC69A30"><enum>(B)</enum><text>submit an
			 application to the Commission at such time, in such form, and containing such
			 additional information as the Commission may require. The application may be
			 filed on behalf of any qualified State by the fire code enforcement officials
			 for such State.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H57EDDDC9220348F6967AC610DC9A8255"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Grant amount;
			 priority</header><text>The Commission shall determine the amount of the grants
			 awarded under this section, and shall give priority to—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H1044373C309B4DF48BF22800E6CCC989"><enum>(A)</enum><text>multi-State
			 applications (including those made by a nonprofit organization representing
			 fire code enforcement officials on behalf of more than 1 State) if all
			 participating States meet the requirements of this paragraph; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD955ADF225443F48F2F524659B9107D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>States
			 demonstrating greater than average losses of life from carbon monoxide
			 poisoning in the home.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H09316AB3C2ED4553A0947DD17397F815"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Use of
			 funds</header><text>A State receiving a grant under this section may use grant
			 funds—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H79D4D9FBDF95429CB90D3E45D3678298"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to train that
			 State’s fire code enforcement officials in the proper enforcement of State laws
			 concerning approved carbon monoxide alarms and the installation of such alarms
			 in accordance with NFPA 720;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02B2896E8BDD42A08EDC9439C60D57A6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for the
			 development and dissemination of training materials, instructors, and any other
			 costs related to the training sessions authorized by this paragraph; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BD0B26072FA4D93842718745D84CE27"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to educate the
			 public about the risk associated with carbon monoxide as a poison and the
			 importance of proper carbon monoxide alarm use.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C677B4D64374512ADDF5DB148B5C37D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Limitation on
			 use of funds</header>
					<subparagraph id="HC6A5266426DF407A810C334AEF6960AC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Administrative
			 costs</header><text>No more than 10 percent of any grant funds may be used to
			 cover administrative costs not directly related to training described in
			 paragraph (4)(A).</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3510C0101EA44C308040326317AF656F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Public
			 outreach</header><text>No more than 25 percent of any grant may be used to
			 cover costs of activities described in paragraph (4)(C).</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDB151DC85D924122A4A0601EF5DDD872"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In
			 this section:</text>
				<paragraph id="H79E44375A0B34DF7B55A5EA1A68C2DA5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Approved carbon
			 monoxide alarm</header><text>The term <term>approved carbon monoxide
			 alarm</term> means a carbon monoxide alarm that complies with the standards,
			 whether voluntary or mandatory, issued, approved, or otherwise supported by the
			 Commission with respect to such alarms, whether those standards have been
			 developed unilaterally by the Commission or in conjunction with other
			 parties.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H4340F0AF6CAC47C8BAE39298917FDD55"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Carbon monoxide
			 alarm</header><text>The term <term>carbon monoxide alarm</term> means a device
			 that detects the presence of carbon monoxide and sounds an alarm if the level
			 of carbon monoxide detected by the device poses a health risk to persons within
			 the vicinity of the device.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H7EC88C375A764BE4ADC436DAFD611E03"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The
			 term <term>Commission</term> means the Consumer Product Safety
			 Commission.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HD64C751AF64A402F848B2B8C8C4D3DA4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Dwelling
			 unit</header><text>The term <term>dwelling unit</term> means a room or suite of
			 rooms used for human habitation, and includes a single family residence as well
			 as each living unit of a multiple family residence (including apartment
			 buildings) and each living unit in a mixed use building.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HBF48C6B450FF4BDE9CB46DC1D687570F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Fire code
			 enforcement officials</header><text>The term <term>fire code enforcement
			 officials</term> means officials of the Fire Safety Code Enforcement Agency of
			 a State.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H3178239D651947438D92770021D6CF44"><enum>(6)</enum><header>NFPA
			 <enum-in-header>720</enum-in-header></header><text>The term <term>NFPA
			 720</term> means the Standard for the Installation of Carbon Monoxide (CO)
			 Warning Equipment in Dwelling Units issued by the National Fire Protection
			 Association in 2008 and any amended or similar successor standard pertaining to
			 the proper installation of carbon monoxide alarms in dwelling units.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBEC448A5CA05449F86C2E3038FDC64E8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of
			 appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are
			 authorized to be appropriated to the Commission $2,000,000 for each of fiscal
			 years 2010 through 2014 to carry out this subsection, such sums to remain
			 available until expended. Any amounts appropriated pursuant to this paragraph
			 that remain unexpended and unobligated at the end of fiscal year 2014 shall be
			 retained by the Commission and credited to the appropriations account that
			 funds enforcement of the Consumer Products Safety Act.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H8CFED43FF1B34245ACD7DFA15CDCCE1F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Commission
			 report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the last day of each fiscal
			 year for which grants are made under this section, the Commission shall submit
			 to Congress a report evaluating the implementation of the grant program
			 authorized by this section.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>
