<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H43A68F61846E484D88B4FBBD10A377E9" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 1338 EH: Paycheck Fairness Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">110th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 1338</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 to provide more effective remedies to victims of discrimination in the payment of wages on the basis of sex, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="HC9156FC9CC23418F8700E1E704225E31" style="OLC"> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H971A2A1BDB1D47599FF622B002310819" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Paycheck Fairness Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> 
<section id="HAD521B222E194569979D735417CAA4BD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD8293008208542BBA59355150069D458"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Women have entered the workforce in record numbers over the past 50 years.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H645C36E7DE8E42A284AABF64872B8B88"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Despite the enactment of the Equal Pay Act in 1963, many women continue to earn significantly lower pay than men for equal work. These pay disparities exist in both the private and governmental sectors. In many instances, the pay disparities can only be due to continued intentional discrimination or the lingering effects of past discrimination.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H693F4F18ED3843A3B272FF4D93507316"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The existence of such pay disparities—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC752D287D0CC4E61B4678B190079D006"><enum>(A)</enum><text>depresses the wages of working families who rely on the wages of all members of the family to make ends meet;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3FBCB4F44DD14120A3BB6FF89E51F5FA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>undermines women's retirement security, which is often based on earnings while in the workforce;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF17BFE3E38824ADDA5704CCDFE516900"><enum>(C)</enum><text>prevents the optimum utilization of available labor resources;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD95B3A19291347D8914E67A00791ACAC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>has been spread and perpetuated, through commerce and the channels and instrumentalities of commerce, among the workers of the several States;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA9FA2D8C5F2140B18FAFE88405F4545"><enum>(E)</enum><text>burdens commerce and the free flow of goods in commerce;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6E2F401708C84452882D7B2D6BAF372"><enum>(F)</enum><text>constitutes an unfair method of competition in commerce;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6EAB1F7E6AFC4ADCA2AADA87E2E79FEF"><enum>(G)</enum><text>leads to labor disputes burdening and obstructing commerce and the free flow of goods in commerce;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD62F7E6CC842420C80F7B5E526D94800"><enum>(H)</enum><text>interferes with the orderly and fair marketing of goods in commerce; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7F883492F9704B009C5756E5F736ABB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in many instances, may deprive workers of equal protection on the basis of sex in violation of the 5th and 14th amendments.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2263C066C95142FF8FEB76C15F3BFB35"><enum>(4)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1F5E1CF603724ED0BF9836CC490822BF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Artificial barriers to the elimination of discrimination in the payment of wages on the basis of sex continue to exist decades after the enactment of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/201">29 U.S.C. 201 et seq.</external-xref>) and the <act-name parsable-cite="CRA64">Civil Rights Act of 1964</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000a">42 U.S.C. 2000a et seq.</external-xref>).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9C4F42D72EA847C5A4BC307BB97F9F6D" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">These barriers have resulted, in significant part, because the Equal Pay Act has not worked as Congress originally intended. Improvements and modifications to the law are necessary to ensure that the Act provides effective protection to those subject to pay discrimination on the basis of their sex.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6EBB57264BF3467AB58902CCD1A702EA" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Elimination of such barriers would have positive effects, including—</text> 
<clause id="HC361C351D87849C0B5B824019EC98FD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>providing a solution to problems in the economy created by unfair pay disparities;</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H03249A0D9A77493F8C308D84927B1BC6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>substantially reducing the number of working women earning unfairly low wages, thereby reducing the dependence on public assistance;</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H18CA9C1B87B34C3ABF7652ECBD53453E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>promoting stable families by enabling all family members to earn a fair rate of pay;</text> </clause> 
<clause id="HC556FC94291D4E259B5F9B10A7B4F700"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>remedying the effects of past discrimination on the basis of sex and ensuring that in the future workers are afforded equal protection on the basis of sex; and</text> </clause> 
<clause id="HC7B65C65332F467C8017BEBC40CA0446"><enum>(v)</enum><text>ensuring equal protection pursuant to Congress’ power to enforce the 5th and 14th amendments.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5B998DBA4775438DBE729FC858009B00"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Labor and the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission have important and unique responsibilities to help ensure that women receive equal pay for equal work.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1F73382829244C59AF728F85AC5BC2E0"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Labor is responsible for—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2B98FC39E3DC471993E28606A651F681"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collecting and making publicly available information about women’s pay;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H49A530DCDD6B4BAAA8AEA79E2EFD3612"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensuring that companies receiving Federal contracts comply with anti-discrimination affirmative action requirements of Executive Order 11246 (relating to equal employment opportunity);</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H323C236BAF354C51A959F4C52100561F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">disseminating information about women’s rights in the workplace;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0A3F395C16E342E2A1FB8F8F81E111A4"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">helping women who have been victims of pay discrimination obtain a remedy; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H25EC29833A78437D80505D9E9F11C6B3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>being proactive in investigating and prosecuting equal pay violations, especially systemic violations, and in enforcing all of its mandates.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF446F5AA561C4357921BDCC9C6E8498C"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Equal Employment Opportunity Commission is the primary enforcement agency for claims made under the Equal Pay Act, and issues regulations and guidance on appropriate interpretations of the law.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H43B1F388386C47D98DC1C589095D6024"><enum>(8)</enum><text>With a stronger commitment by the Department of Labor and the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission to their responsibilities, increased information about the provisions added by the Equal Pay Act of 1963, wage data, and more effective remedies, women will be better able to recognize and enforce their rights.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1D6D13ECEEF046839CFB8ED2E39276F7"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Certain employers have already made great strides in eradicating unfair pay disparities in the workplace and their achievements should be recognized.</text> </paragraph></section> 
<section id="H131B98ABE92D4EB199C9EAD9E845A5A0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Enhanced enforcement of equal pay requirements</header> 
<subsection id="H4E35ACB48084400A90AEA6378500C459"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Bona-fide factor defense and modification of same establishment requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 6(d)(1) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/206">29 U.S.C. 206(d)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H8F1A121166184E0C99221742044D5467"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>No employer having</quote> and inserting <quote>(A) No employer having</quote>;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H54DB33AA3D7842C493466CFB28C2D054"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>any other factor other than sex</quote> and inserting <quote>a bona fide factor other than sex, such as education, training, or experience</quote>; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCDBEDDBE0A8A44198C09DE23EE2BE24"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F70BF9325D24CFE804182A867A1AE79" style="traditional"> 
<subparagraph id="H6CD45EAAABD44B939E0047FB62DC377D" indent="up2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The bona fide factor defense described in subparagraph (A)(v) shall apply only if the employer demonstrates that such factor (i) is not based upon or derived from a sex-based differential in compensation; (ii) is job-related with respect to the position in question; and (iii) is consistent with business necessity. Such defense shall not apply where the employee demonstrates that an alternative employment practice exists that would serve the same business purpose without producing such differential and that the employer has refused to adopt such alternative practice.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H496CE980756A461A00E5EEF8F08B43B" indent="up2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (A), employees shall be deemed to work in the same establishment if the employees work for the same employer at workplaces located in the same county or similar political subdivision of a State. The preceding sentence shall not be construed as limiting broader applications of the term <quote>establishment</quote> consistent with rules prescribed or guidance issued by the Equal Opportunity Employment Commission.</text> </subparagraph> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9DD1846F4DC04F2A8FC8989E475DDCA3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Nonretaliation provision</header><text>Section 15 of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/215">29 U.S.C. 215(a)(3)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2759FA6C3C9B44199322A9CDB730395"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(3), by striking <quote>employee has filed</quote> and all that follows and inserting</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HF24631E6FEA149E9BB0839B3CC00B8E5" style="OLC"><text>employee—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H362A90F548764A30A79808F23D655373"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has made a charge or filed any complaint or instituted or caused to be instituted any investigation, proceeding, hearing, or action under or related to this Act, including an investigation conducted by the employer, or has testified or is planning to testify or has assisted or participated in any manner in any such investigation, proceeding, hearing or action or in an investigation conducted by the employer, or has served or is planning to serve on an industry Committee; or</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H54AC6B084C8B47A49BA87D03F1C6CFD5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has inquired about, discussed or disclosed the wages of the employee or another employee.</text> </subparagraph> <after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3B047E170CFA428689DA27D81AC2B9C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H623545588F7C4F7D90F32DF23F3263F" style="traditional"> 
<subsection id="H68F0782ECA8C445CBB694D005DBC44CE"><enum>(c)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (a)(3)(B) shall not apply to instances in which an employee who has access to the wage information of other employees as a part of such employee’s essential job functions discloses the wages of such other employees to individuals who do not otherwise have access to such information, unless such disclosure is in response to a complaint or charge or in furtherance of an investigation, proceeding, hearing, or action under section 6(d) or an investigation conducted by the employer. Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to limit the rights of an employee provided under any other provision of law.</text> </subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H655134B0D2A545ED8000A0A8CC004BA7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enhanced penalties</header><text>Section 16(b) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/216">29 U.S.C. 216(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4A95FBB80CC54348BEB9F3B81DBF86F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting after the first sentence the following: <quote>Any employer who violates section 6(d) shall additionally be liable for such compensatory damages, or, where the employee demonstrates that the employer acted with malice or reckless indifference, punitive damages as may be appropriate, except that the United States shall not be liable for punitive damages.</quote>;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBF048F267E93459D934400E1B348BC1D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the sentence beginning <quote>An action to</quote>, by striking <quote>either of the preceding sentences</quote> and inserting <quote>any of the preceding sentences of this subsection</quote>;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2A68B0EEF21842D89E5C38ECBD940038"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in the sentence beginning <quote>No employees shall</quote>, by striking <quote>No employees</quote> and inserting <quote>Except with respect to class actions brought to enforce section 6(d), no employee</quote>;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFD4BCF3A5FED480B8E7E8F19857B7D29"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after the sentence referred to in paragraph (3), the following: <quote>Notwithstanding any other provision of Federal law, any action brought to enforce section 6(d) may be maintained as a class action as provided by the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure.</quote>; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8BFE0C1CF15643619D685F006EDFAC3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in the sentence beginning <quote>The court in</quote>—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB6BC1E47695942F48F2793F00B886C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>in such action</quote> and inserting <quote>in any action brought to recover the liability prescribed in any of the preceding sentences of this subsection</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9EDDCB363AD94BA7AA9FBB3B9100D8B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting before the period the following: <quote>, including expert fees</quote>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0BD7190685864AA781D1D5FDF7069704"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Action by Secretary</header><text>Section 16(c) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/216">29 U.S.C. 216(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2B3B074ECFB247CD8C62C500358798B2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the first sentence—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2A62352EC577490A8C17DA1D950229D6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or, in the case of a violation of section 6(d), additional compensatory or punitive damages,</quote> before <quote>and the agreement</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD9527E5DB9ED47089F1386A4FD13C4F4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting before the period the following: <quote>, or such compensatory or punitive damages, as appropriate</quote>;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE6744001FB92421EA364595B610027BA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the second sentence, by inserting before the period the following: <quote>and, in the case of a violation of section 6(d), additional compensatory or punitive damages</quote>;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0DE4E24FB0534FEF95F3CF7E0028DE61"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in the third sentence, by striking <quote>the first sentence</quote> and inserting <quote>the first or second sentence</quote>; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H20672EC6801A485BA6729E883DAB6D84"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in the last sentence—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBE543719A19B4A22AA3C91DB632043B8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>commenced in the case</quote> and inserting</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H73BEA0FE3A024C5200F93D8CE9166E72"><text>commenced—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4F10AC0BE23343E196999ED47C5FBEB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case</text> </paragraph> <after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H07A67B5A709C4722855500CBBB982E98"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking the period and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H71F8A38694CC49FABCCB036D67E18B67"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H8F5290E118574F7BB425077C0916A2C9"> 
<paragraph id="H3030009F3A7E49B19CCF39FAA161F1DB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of a class action brought to enforce section 6(d), on the date on which the individual becomes a party plaintiff to the class action.</text> </paragraph> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HDA536ACA00D1465DA39079258D1E517F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Training</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Equal Employment Opportunity Commission and the Office of Federal Contract Compliance Programs, subject to the availability of funds appropriated under section 11, shall provide training to Commission employees and affected individuals and entities on matters involving discrimination in the payment of wages.</text> </section> 
<section id="H8DF01D8337E04ED88155DC207D0559E3"><enum>5.</enum><header>Negotiation skills training for girls and women</header> 
<subsection id="H5E010064403F4697ACB3CDAB22FDD00"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authorized</header> 
<paragraph id="H17E0D83455C747CBA31D9875FCC1A290"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Labor, after consultation with the Secretary of Education, is authorized to establish and carry out a grant program.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H44F9FDC415F74805BD56D94F980DE5C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>In carrying out the program, the Secretary of Labor may make grants on a competitive basis to eligible entities, to carry out negotiation skills training programs for girls and women.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3574B71FA9B64AA0ADB5FA696ED754FF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an entity shall be a public agency, such as a State, a local government in a metropolitan statistical area (as defined by the Office of Management and Budget), a State educational agency, or a local educational agency, a private nonprofit organization, or a community-based organization.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF06FD0EA36264FAB8BECBF90D0FEF9E1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an entity shall submit an application to the Secretary of Labor at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary of Labor may require.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7FBBA8ED85E8460883F0B0BC3D00F683"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity that receives a grant under this subsection shall use the funds made available through the grant to carry out an effective negotiation skills training program that empowers girls and women. The training provided through the program shall help girls and women strengthen their negotiation skills to allow the girls and women to obtain higher salaries and rates of compensation that are equal to those paid to similarly-situated male employees.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFE5CDACD032F4B049E24EA131D51D81C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Incorporating training into existing programs</header><text>The Secretary of Labor and the Secretary of Education shall issue regulations or policy guidance that provides for integrating the negotiation skills training, to the extent practicable, into programs authorized under—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD2629DCAA7E749AF9D5DDE90C15DF455"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of the Secretary of Education, the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6301">20 U.S.C. 6301 et seq.</external-xref>), the Carl D. Perkins Vocational and Technical Education Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2301">20 U.S.C. 2301 et seq.</external-xref>), the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001 et seq.</external-xref>), and other programs carried out by the Department of Education that the Secretary of Education determines to be appropriate; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC04925625A65484BB54BE058AC1B6EE3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of the Secretary of Labor, the Workforce Investment Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2801">29 U.S.C. 2801 et seq.</external-xref>), and other programs carried out by the Department of Labor that the Secretary of Labor determines to be appropriate.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H61B0D889900440FE8F9975DA416D6B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Labor and the Secretary of Education shall prepare and submit to Congress a report describing the activities conducted under this section and evaluating the effectiveness of such activities in achieving the purposes of this Act.</text> </subsection></section> 
<section id="H553E705472104B4A9EB9440B6E77488"><enum>6.</enum><header>Research, education, and outreach</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Labor shall conduct studies and provide information to employers, labor organizations, and the general public concerning the means available to eliminate pay disparities between men and women, including—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4C79373BA39F49019DD3AFAE18E1412B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conducting and promoting research to develop the means to correct expeditiously the conditions leading to the pay disparities;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H17134FCA633E48BBBCABA03B5962FAF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>publishing and otherwise making available to employers, labor organizations, professional associations, educational institutions, the media, and the general public the findings resulting from studies and other materials, relating to eliminating the pay disparities;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H662E2F87E84048678131670104A00795"><enum>(3)</enum><text>sponsoring and assisting State and community informational and educational programs;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5641247122B246E5928FA415E4C5146E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>providing information to employers, labor organizations, professional associations, and other interested persons on the means of eliminating the pay disparities;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD9EC57FF844E403F98A0654E067273B1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>recognizing and promoting the achievements of employers, labor organizations, and professional associations that have worked to eliminate the pay disparities; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4EE8E210E64D4940856E17832D07C0F3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>convening a national summit to discuss, and consider approaches for rectifying, the pay disparities.</text> </paragraph></section> 
<section id="HC6C0F246DBC2436E9CB9D7ABE2360004"><enum>7.</enum><header>Establishment of the National Award for Pay Equity in the Workplace</header> 
<subsection id="H7109DEB5AF954CA199C351A49D89F6FC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established the Secretary of Labor’s National Award for Pay Equity in the Workplace, which shall be awarded, as appropriate, to encourage proactive efforts to comply with this Act.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H7967F36C7795414F93746C7E032E42CA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Criteria for qualification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Labor shall set criteria for receipt of the award, including a requirement that an employer has made substantial effort to eliminate pay disparities between men and women, and deserves special recognition as a consequence of such effort. The secretary shall establish procedures for the application and presentation of the award.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H5940FDD9FEEB4FA4ABE0E437AE03A55E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Business</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>employer</quote> includes—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2C30FF0A8C144F60A7E15638584B6C6B"><enum>(1)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H356389010F3E40238B1376522DD8ADAD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a corporation, including a nonprofit corporation;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H316DE712D70D46A5B9A36048A20199D6" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a partnership;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H085ECA48A559450A8F759391FC9D26E7" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a professional association;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H03A442A62D3E40829435EE217D82DF04" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a labor organization; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDAC2E90FEF9649F097BFF772E9FA1E8" indent="up1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a business entity similar to an entity described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (D);</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBB981C8FCA154EA19169BA232E419C09"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an entity carrying out an education referral program, a training program, such as an apprenticeship or management training program, or a similar program; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3DF5FDAA49434CAC870572B3531EA988"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an entity carrying out a joint program, formed by a combination of any entities described in paragraph (1) or (2).</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HD1C2EA2099A74D7CBCF413196F45BE32"><enum>8.</enum><header>Collection of pay information by the equal employment opportunity Commission</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 709 of the <act-name parsable-cite="CRA64">Civil Rights Act of 1964</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000e-8">42 U.S.C. 2000e–8</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="Civil Rights Act of 1964" id="H372FD2DEE3E648338C40F58F2B621F23"> 
<subsection id="H45AF3B182CD4485100318142B24623BF"><enum>(f)</enum> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H679B461A177D4F3EB74B54A35B99B1FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Commission shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA89B5AEBAFD74BB3BBB5A14810EFF92E" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>complete a survey of the data that is currently available to the Federal Government relating to employee pay information for use in the enforcement of Federal laws prohibiting pay discrimination and, in consultation with other relevant Federal agencies, identify additional data collections that will enhance the enforcement of such laws; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFC17FFBE26D9445DA2A89602BD8783C3" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>based on the results of the survey and consultations under subparagraph (A), issue regulations to provide for the collection of pay information data from employers as described by the sex, race, and national origin of employees.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H166050E8B34C4010A89F1CFA8759912E" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In implementing paragraph (1), the Commission shall have as its primary consideration the most effective and efficient means for enhancing the enforcement of Federal laws prohibiting pay discrimination. For this purpose, the Commission shall consider factors including the imposition of burdens on employers, the frequency of required reports (including which employers should be required to prepare reports), appropriate protections for maintaining data confidentiality, and the most effective format for the data collection reports.</text> </paragraph></subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> 
<section id="H4E7859F941C34942BA114EACD8415C46"><enum>9.</enum><header>Reinstatement of pay equity programs and pay equity data collection</header> 
<subsection id="H942F1C78681C4C8CA5DBC85702C55D05"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Bureau of Labor Statistics data collection</header><text>The Commissioner of Labor Statistics shall continue to collect data on women workers in the Current Employment Statistics survey.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H546E48EE314E4E6ABB868DE7F26B9D5D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Office of Federal Contract Compliance Programs initiatives</header><text>The Director of the Office of Federal Contract Compliance Programs shall ensure that employees of the Office—</text> 
<paragraph id="H98F9D0B507E04258A8BFDCBCEBEDDF6D"><enum>(1)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE5D0B5844DBA4A46A9FC8399B50043DC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall use the full range of investigatory tools at the Office's disposal, including pay grade methodology;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA8541A247A9949629B62EC870CC7C08" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in considering evidence of possible compensation discrimination—</text> 
<clause id="HBD425BA9926C4B78B402B394D5ED385B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall not limit its consideration to a small number of types of evidence; and</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H7D20418B29E84F319F0200F7863DF8C2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall not limit its evaluation of the evidence to a small number of methods of evaluating the evidence; and</text> </clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H92A33882CF214CB99025B79F3CC493CC" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall not require a multiple regression analysis or anecdotal evidence for a compensation discrimination case;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9CD736F08CA844E897CB72BCDAC2201"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for purposes of its investigative, compliance, and enforcement activities, shall define <term>similarly situated employees</term> in a way that is consistent with and not more stringent than the definition provided in item 1 of subsection A of section 10–III of the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission Compliance Manual (2000), and shall consider only factors that the Office's investigation reveals were used in making compensation decisions; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDA82156F68F648C1AE885288D8D3EDDE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall reinstate the Equal Opportunity Survey, as required by <external-xref legal-doc="regulation" parsable-cite="cfr/41/60">section 60–2.18</external-xref> of title 41, Code of Federal Regulations, designating not less than half of all nonconstruction contractor establishments each year to prepare and file such survey, and shall review and utilize the responses to such survey to identify contractor establishments for further evaluation and for other enforcement purposes as appropriate.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBD685A9550454DF883EF000403B196D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Department of Labor distribution of wage discrimination information</header><text>The Secretary of Labor shall make readily available (in print, on the Department of Labor website, and through any other forum that the Department may use to distribute compensation discrimination information), accurate information on compensation discrimination, including statistics, explanations of employee rights, historical analyses of such discrimination, instructions for employers on compliance, and any other information that will assist the public in understanding and addressing such discrimination.</text> </subsection></section> 
<section id="H5B74421BB63446A0B5E3272EF909EA7F"><enum>10.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header> 
<subsection id="H23D76FF7078A4BE8928200B4945FD6B1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated $15,000,000 to carry out this Act.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H06EC63040C0A461796CDA5636C00BB20"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on Earmarks</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds appropriated pursuant to subsection (a) for purposes of the grant program in section 5 of this Act may be used for a Congressional earmark as defined in clause 9(d) of rule XXI of the Rules of the House of Representatives.</text> </subsection></section> 
<section id="H5A41B09C8DE6409D81C8D98EC3E6ACCE" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>11.</enum><header>Small Business Assistance</header> 
<subsection id="H679E7082422E42828800004E844D8EFB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act and the amendments made by this Act shall take effect on the date that is 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF4086226D4F0444DAB249FB0BC59D954"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical assistance materials</header><text>The Secretary of Labor and the Commissioner of the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission shall jointly develop technical assistance material to assist small businesses in complying with the requirements of this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA1D6FFB6F09E4505861EA8D482B22B4D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Small Businesses</header><text>A small business shall be exempt from the provisions of this Act to the same extent that such business is exempt from the requirements of the Fair Labor Standards Act pursuant to section 3(s)(1)(A)(i) and (ii) of such Act.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H32C38528C4854431B436A67272BC7875" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>12.</enum><header>Rule of Construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act, or in any amendments made by this Act, shall affect the obligation of employers and employees to fully comply with all applicable immigration laws, including any penalties, fines, or other sanctions.</text></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20080731" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives July 31, 2008.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation> 
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement> 
</bill> 


