<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H51545060BF4F45129B232889978979F4" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 4889 IH: The Guard and Reserves Are Fighting Too Act of
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 4889</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20071219">December 19, 2007</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000116">Mr. Filner</sponsor> introduced
			 the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’
			 Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on
			 <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a
			 period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for
			 consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the
			 committee concerned</action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to recodify as
		  part of that title <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1607">chapter 1607</external-xref> of title 10, United States
		  Code.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H5A76BE5C1CF04917AE62509119B5E500" style="OLC">
		<section id="H9725322A1BBB49048208CBC6E525B574" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as <quote><short-title>The Guard and Reserves Are Fighting Too Act of
			 2008</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H903B406E6F494DF5941ED274AF94BF2B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Recodification in
			 title <enum-in-header>38</enum-in-header>, United States Code, of certain
			 educational assistance programs for members of the Reserve components</header>
			<subsection id="HB1E8E997A57C4593007EC33AE04AF69"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Part III of title 38, United States Code, is amended by
			 inserting after chapter 32 the following new chapter:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H368F251809564F08AB002C48EC6586AC" style="USC">
					<chapter id="H29081E9149DA4E79B2FDB177AF869200"><enum>33</enum><header>EDUCATIONAL
				ASSISTANCE FOR MEMBERS OF THE RESERVE COMPONENTS SUPPORTING CONTINGENCY
				OPERATIONS AND CERTAIN OTHER OPERATIONS</header>
						<toc container-level="chapter-container" idref="H29081E9149DA4E79B2FDB177AF869200" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration">
							<toc-entry idref="HA99A8683066B43FEAC1010FF6391625C" level="section">3301. Purpose.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="H6242C494D2F843B7B9C63876BE8F00DF" level="section">3302. Educational assistance program.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="H10400571783747C9A13E4317C88013E" level="section">3303. Eligibility for educational assistance.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="H673D85D4BD9842F296B2ADB966549E5" level="section">3304. Time limit for use of entitlement.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="HBB5E59A797944D01B2CE8DDAEA29738F" level="section">3305. Termination of assistance.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="H382C9596EBA1419BA3B560D52DE3007F" level="section">3306. Administration of program.</toc-entry>
						</toc>
						<section id="HA99A8683066B43FEAC1010FF6391625C"><enum>3301.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this chapter is to provide
				educational assistance to members of the reserve components called or ordered
				to active service in response to a war or national emergency declared by the
				President or Congress, in recognition of the sacrifices that those members make
				in answering the call to duty.</text>
						</section><section id="H6242C494D2F843B7B9C63876BE8F00DF"><enum>3302.</enum><header>Educational
				assistance program</header>
							<subsection id="HD685F2672C514829A5FCA14C72935D61"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program
				Establishment</header><text>The Secretary of each military department, under
				regulations prescribed by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, shall establish
				and maintain a program as prescribed in this chapter to provide educational
				assistance to members of the Ready Reserve of the Armed Forces under the
				jurisdiction of the Secretary concerned.</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="H71B3DD10D1634191A5A3242BE659633"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorized
				Education Programs</header><text>Educational assistance may be provided under
				this chapter for pursuit of any program of education that is an approved
				program of education for purposes of chapter 30 of this title.</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="HA1046301ECF54326865FD2244A55F00"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Benefit
				Amount</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HBF6DCFDAFCF14E3FB31408524903D9CE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The
				educational assistance program established under subsection (a) shall provide
				for payment by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs of an educational assistance
				allowance to each member entitled to educational assistance under this chapter
				who is pursuing a program of education authorized under subsection (b).</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HC0CA8933E1774BB4AAD7BCE35F761CCB" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The educational assistance allowance
				provided under this chapter shall be based on the applicable percent under
				paragraph (4) to the applicable rate provided under section 3015 of this title
				for a member whose entitlement is based on completion of an obligated period of
				active duty of three years.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H293B734DB6724C71918B648BD97B5F1E" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The educational assistance allowance
				provided under this section for a person who is undertaking a program for which
				a reduced rate is specified in chapter 30 of this title, that rate shall be
				further adjusted by the applicable percent specified in paragraph (4).</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H5EE2AFDDB03547D6AFD7F6EBBBB64CB" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The adjusted educational assistance
				allowance under paragraph (2) or (3), as applicable, shall be—</text>
									<subparagraph id="H27635680253A443B81C1E5379B3378A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>40 percent in the case of a member of
				a reserve component who performed active service for 90 consecutive days but
				less than one continuous year;</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA82F2714E3254813ADAF56EF8129F00"><enum>(B)</enum><text>60 percent in the case of a member of
				a reserve component who performed active service for one continuous year but
				less than two continuous years; or</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE8A7AD721F874AE482A5A7F1195592B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>80 percent in the case of a member of
				a reserve component who performed active service for two continuous years or
				more.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBF4E7B82291941C4A14300CCBFF17DE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Maximum Months of
				Assistance</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD5B2DDC650A045958BCA42B351B003A1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Subject to section 3695
				of this title, the maximum number of months of educational assistance that may
				be provided to any member under this chapter is 36 (or the equivalent thereof
				in part-time educational assistance).</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H7C2E9556F18F4AFD9CC8B9825BFC00B0" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE597E421C15844619EDBD7C12F001518"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Notwithstanding any
				other provision of this chapter or chapter 36 of this title, any payment of an
				educational assistance allowance described in subparagraph (B) shall
				not—</text>
										<clause id="HB7860E5B2538465C940058822B68CEDA" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be charged against the entitlement of
				any individual under this chapter; or</text>
										</clause><clause id="H52DEF7A35CC34DCFAFB7D3002EF9CC55" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>be counted toward the aggregate
				period for which section 3695 of this title limits an individual's receipt of
				assistance.</text>
										</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3CFA5C90676F43959D1BBA20244E8300" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The payment of the educational
				assistance allowance referred to in subparagraph (A) is the payment of such an
				allowance to the individual for pursuit of a course or courses under this
				chapter if the Secretary of Veterans Affairs finds that the individual—</text>
										<clause id="H408D15F081CF43D5A2F362F579A8E600"><enum>(i)</enum><text>had to discontinue such course pursuit
				as a result of being ordered to serve on active duty under section 12301(a),
				12301(d), 12301(g), 12302, or 12304 of title 10; and</text>
										</clause><clause id="HAF6C156B71994F15A1EAEAE4898E41D6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>failed to receive credit or training
				time toward completion of the individual's approved educational, professional,
				or vocational objective as a result of having to discontinue, as described in
				clause (i), the individual's course pursuit.</text>
										</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E90771E20F84040BFD96F8E8556A940" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The period for which, by reason of
				this subsection, an educational assistance allowance is not charged against
				entitlement or counted toward the applicable aggregate period under section
				3695 of this title shall not exceed the portion of the period of enrollment in
				the course or courses for which the individual failed to receive credit or with
				respect to which the individual lost training time, as determined under
				subparagraph (B)(ii).</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3AB7AC79D24745DBA943C796D8580021"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Availability of
				Assistance for Licensing and Certification Tests</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0F0FB4D4C93C47AE00C3368BE835211E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Subject to paragraph
				(3), the amount of educational assistance payable under this chapter for a
				licensing or certification test described in section 3452(b) of this title is
				the lesser of $2,000 or the fee charged for the test.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H86416AB8F460424191EB79221C50F8F4" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The number of months of entitlement
				charged in the case of any individual for such licensing or certification test
				is equal to the number (including any fraction) determined by dividing the
				total amount of educational assistance paid such individual for such test by
				the full-time monthly institutional rate of educational assistance which, but
				for paragraph (1), such individual would otherwise be paid under subsection
				(c).</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAFD44CAB83024F7184E8A7E82FE1E900" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In no event shall payment of
				educational assistance under this subsection for such a test exceed the amount
				of the individual’s available entitlement under this chapter.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2DAB9337DEE544BB825263B1A3294450"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Flight
				Training</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs may approve the
				pursuit of flight training (in addition to a course of flight training that may
				be approved under section 3680A(b) of this title) by an individual entitled to
				educational assistance under this chapter if—</text>
								<paragraph id="H2D73DA49E9E245F8B57D9D570078C1CE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such training is
				generally accepted as necessary for the attainment of a recognized vocational
				objective in the field of aviation;</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HAD2E59DF3DAA424D8652B1BCB967245E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the individual
				possesses a valid private pilot certificate and meets, on the day the member
				begins a course of flight training, the medical requirements necessary for a
				commercial pilot certificate; and</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H862AD148DBA148698FF45D7BF05EA9BA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the flight school
				courses meet Federal Aviation Administration standards for such courses and are
				approved by the Federal Aviation Administration and the State approving
				agency.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H10400571783747C9A13E4317C88013E"><enum>3303.</enum><header>Eligibility for
				educational assistance</header>
							<subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC6F5CDE4788345A8B5B2BAC37900B8B3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>On
				or after September 11, 2001, a member of a reserve component is entitled to
				educational assistance under this chapter if the member—</text>
								<paragraph id="HE7DB229EB7EA463CBA3D98201800491C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>served on active
				duty in support of a contingency operation for 90 consecutive days or more;
				or</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HD322911F445A43B59ECA56B0B594DA84"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of a
				member of the Army National Guard of the United States or Air National Guard of
				the United States, performed full time National Guard duty under section 502(f)
				of title 32 for 90 consecutive days or more when authorized by the President or
				Secretary of Defense for the purpose of responding to a national emergency
				declared by the President and supported by Federal funds.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H55D5E023633D4C3CA664D2E5D4C83BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Disabled
				Members</header><text>Notwithstanding the eligibility requirements in
				subsection (a), a member who was ordered to active service as prescribed under
				subsection (a)(1) or (a)(2) but is released from duty before completing 90
				consecutive days because of an injury, illness or disease incurred or
				aggravated in the line of duty shall be entitled to educational assistance
				under this chapter at the rate prescribed in section 3302(c)(4)(A) of this
				title.</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="H09C09C570CE1473094E107BAB6C38CC6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Written
				Notification</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC8CB191C20A44393A2BCAB7B89194EC3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Each member who becomes
				entitled to educational assistance under subsection (a) shall be given a
				statement in writing prior to release from active service that summarizes the
				provisions of this chapter and stating clearly and prominently the substance of
				section 3305 of this title as such section may apply to the member.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H071DFB9D3A564156BF67A5846402753D" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>At the request of the Secretary of
				Veterans Affairs, the Secretary of the military department concerned shall
				transmit a notice of entitlement for each such member to that Secretary.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3E7CA71A37D54AB8A828B18DF0001223"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Bar From Dual
				Eligibility</header><text>A member who qualifies for educational assistance
				under this chapter may not receive credit for such service under both the
				program established by chapter 30 of this title and the program established by
				this chapter but shall make an irrevocable election (in such form and manner as
				the Secretary of Veterans Affairs may prescribe) as to the program to which
				such service is to be credited.</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="HC93397784D624461A000C7EDCA12C08"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Bar From
				Duplication of Educational Assistance Allowance</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H59ACEF98DA1F43029E04A9AA21A830A4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Except as provided in
				paragraph (2), an individual entitled to educational assistance under this
				chapter who is also eligible for educational assistance under subchapter I of
				this chapter, chapter 30, 31, 32, or 35 of this title, or under the Hostage
				Relief Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/96/449">Public Law 96–449</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/5561">5 U.S.C. 5561</external-xref> note) may not receive
				assistance under more than one such programs and shall elect (in such form and
				manner as the Secretary of Veterans Affairs may prescribe) under which program
				the member elects to receive educational assistance.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HBB6C81BA20B84189003448D15E815571" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The restriction on duplication of
				educational assistance under paragraph (1) does not apply to the entitlement of
				educational assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/16131">section 16131(i)</external-xref> of title 10.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H673D85D4BD9842F296B2ADB966549E5"><enum>3304.</enum><header>Time limit for
				use of entitlement</header>
							<subsection id="HA62F2FC2B455448789618B5089766F7F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Duration of
				Entitlement</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b), a member
				remains entitled to educational assistance under this chapter while
				serving—</text>
								<paragraph id="H1F7AE8C637EF4F8287931B0024D800CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the Selected
				Reserve of the Ready Reserve, in the case of a member called or ordered to
				active service while serving in the Selected Reserve; or</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H66581C9FA713431BA6E6D7A5A13BF700"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the Ready
				Reserve, in the case of a member ordered to active duty while serving in the
				Ready Reserve (other than the Selected Reserve).</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3348020ACFB94B7DA9C87170AAD07DF5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duration of
				Entitlement for Disabled Members</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HDD5F25DDAE7146368C2DAFBF382EA5FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the case of a person
				who is separated from the Ready Reserve because of a disability which was not
				the result of the individual's own willful misconduct incurred on or after the
				date on which such person became entitled to educational assistance under this
				chapter, such person's entitlement to educational assistance expires at the end
				of the 10-year period beginning on the date on which such person became
				entitled to such assistance.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HE014AA535275466F8373A2151920D66F" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The provisions of subsections (d) and
				(f) of section 3031 of this title shall apply to the period of entitlement
				prescribed by paragraph (1).</text>
								</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HBB5E59A797944D01B2CE8DDAEA29738F"><enum>3305.</enum><header>Termination of
				assistance</header>
							<subsection id="H2C7F64B74C364A38A82C0096574CFCEC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
				General</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b), educational
				assistance may not be provided under this chapter, or if being provided under
				this chapter, shall be terminated—</text>
								<paragraph id="H10A4510DAAF640EFB31D285F2DFD4271"><enum>(1)</enum><text>if the member is
				receiving financial assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2107">section 2107</external-xref> of title 10 as a member of
				the Senior Reserve Officers' Training Corps program; or</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H60433314309544B8A0CDCC10D84F1283"><enum>(2)</enum><text>when the member
				separates from the Ready Reserve, as provided for under section 3304(a)(1) or
				section 3304(a)(2), as applicable, of this title.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8A3E49C0A06440CC96BBE44DDE5EF40"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Under
				regulations prescribed by the Secretary of Defense, educational assistance may
				be provided under this chapter to a member of the Selected Reserve of the Ready
				Reserve who incurs a break in service in the Selected Reserve of not more than
				90 days if the member continues to serve in the Ready Reserve during and after
				such break in service.</text>
							</subsection></section><section id="H382C9596EBA1419BA3B560D52DE3007F"><enum>3306.</enum><header>Administration
				of program</header>
							<subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE75E646E5F3F44DAB8179D4843084FFE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Payments</header><text>Payments
				for educational assistance under this chapter shall be made from funds
				appropriated or otherwise made available to the Department of Veterans Affairs
				for fiscal year 2010 or any subsequent fiscal year for the payment of
				readjustment benefits.</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="H235E25E431764C058683BA822F3B98AC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program
				Management</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as
				otherwise provided in this chapter, the provisions of sections 3470, 3471,
				3474, 3476, 3482(g), 3483, and 3485 of this title and the provisions of
				subchapters I and II of chapter 36 of this title (with the exception of
				sections 3686(a) and 3687) shall be applicable to the provision of educational
				assistance under this chapter. The term <term>eligible veteran</term> and the
				term <term>person</term>, as used in those provisions, shall be deemed for the
				purpose of the application of those provisions to this chapter to refer to a
				person eligible for educational assistance under this
				chapter.</text>
							</subsection></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HA67DF2787C2B413ABBA7C4DE021D6963"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transfer of
			 amounts for benefits accrued before October 1, 2009</header>
				<paragraph id="H1372BB48C2104546A964943C00211BD2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Fiscal year
			 2010</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">By not later than
			 October 1, 2009, the Secretary of Defense shall transfer to the Secretary of
			 Veterans Affairs from the funds in the Department of Defense Education Benefits
			 Fund under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2006">section 2006</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, that are attributable
			 to armed forces education liabilities under chapter 1607 of such title that
			 accrue before such date, such funds as may be required by the Secretary of
			 Veterans Affairs to make payments with respect to such liabilities during
			 fiscal year 2010. Such amounts shall be deposited into the education account of
			 the Readjustment Benefits Account of the Department of Veterans Affairs and
			 shall be available to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to make payments of
			 educational assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, as
			 added by subsection (a).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HB61CB05BBF4E4CF7BC1516DFEA6B8100"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Agreement for
			 subsequent fiscal years</header><text>By not later than October 1, 2009, the
			 Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall enter into an
			 agreement under which the Secretary of Defense shall transfer to the Secretary
			 of Veterans Affairs all remaining funds in the Department of Defense Education
			 Benefits Fund under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2006">section 2006</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, that are
			 attributable to armed forces liabilities under chapter 1607 of such title that
			 accrue before such date. Such amounts shall be deposited into the education
			 account of the Readjustment Benefits Account of the Department of Veterans
			 Affairs and shall be available to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to make
			 payments of educational assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 38, United States
			 Code, as added by subsection (a).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H2DECF819DAF74E0B93691C552B6C507B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">By not later than October 1, 2009, the
			 Secretary of Defense shall submit to the congressional defense committees, the
			 Committee on Veterans Affairs of the Senate, and the Committee on Veterans
			 Affairs of the House of Representatives a detailed report on the agreement
			 between the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the
			 status of the transfer of funds described in paragraph (2). Such report shall
			 include the date on which the Secretary of Defense has agreed to complete such
			 transfer.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3F685611CF0A4527A3FF93436E000405"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical
			 amendments</header><text>The tables of chapters at the beginning of title 38,
			 United States Code, and at the beginning of part III of such title, are each
			 amended by inserting after the item relating to chapter 32 the following new
			 item:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id17D1BA02EFC94A96831EB17EFAA101AA" style="OLC">
					<toc>
						<multi-column-toc-entry bold="on" level="chapter"><toc-enum>33.</toc-enum><level-header level="chapter"> Educational Assistance for Members of the Reserve Components
				  Supporting Contingency Operations and Certain Other
				  Operations</level-header><target> 3301</target></multi-column-toc-entry>
					</toc>
					<after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H87D0F45A60744B1F96B21B60D1AC06DB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Technical and
			 conforming amendments</header>
				<paragraph id="H1045ED094CD743908C25864D5CD14BF2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Conforming
			 Amendments on Bar on Dual Eligibility for Benefits</header>
					<subparagraph commented="no" id="H4A19A1EECDAC4B699C4E478E3386FF41"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Section 3033 of
			 title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text>
						<clause commented="no" id="HDF1EA23C111749BB8F00A800FCF58611"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (a)(1), by striking <quote>chapter 31, 32, or 35 of this title, under chapter
			 106 or 107 of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>under chapter 31, 32, 33,
			 or 35 of this title, under chapter 107 or 1606 of title 10</quote>; and</text>
						</clause><clause commented="no" id="H75EEBF0BEC7644BAA1580038CE932C38"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (c), by striking <quote>chapter 106 of title 10</quote> and inserting
			 <quote>chapter 1606 of title 10</quote>.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5FA22CDE24A0476A9700D1CD3E541771"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Section 3221(f) of
			 such title is amended by striking <quote>chapter 106 of title 10</quote> and
			 inserting <quote>chapter 1606 of title 10</quote>.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H35B534CC38754AE28DD65680619EFCCE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Section 3681 of
			 such title is amended—</text>
						<clause commented="no" id="H9D1BF0471E43409CB1615ED2B7A3DB7C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (a),
			 by striking <quote>34, 35, or 36 of this title or 106 or 107 of title
			 10,</quote> and inserting <quote>33, 34, 35, or 36 of this title or chapter 107
			 or 1606 of title 10</quote>; and</text>
						</clause><clause commented="no" id="H3243C5C5513649B69924C35DEF624462"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (b)—</text>
							<subclause commented="no" id="H5B7789B2D8284A918DC5005EE6BB912F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in paragraph (1),
			 by inserting after <quote>32,</quote> the following: <quote>33,</quote>;
			 and</text>
							</subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H310A1F1124344FF785B746649DFA988"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in paragraph (2),
			 by striking <quote>Chapters 106 and 107</quote> and inserting <quote>Chapters
			 107 and 1606</quote>.</text>
							</subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H644680760E1D43D8A6DDD9D3D5B71AD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming
			 Amendments Relating to Department of Defense Education Benefits Fund</header>
					<subparagraph id="H7FFBB41D4CBA471C8FA81900FFD0E22C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Definition of
			 armed forces education liabilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (1) of section 2006(b) of title
			 10, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAEF70DFAAF3D46D7A59377BC9E3BCA2E" style="USC">
							<paragraph id="HD40F53A872CB421DB0D1B6F39E06E1BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>armed forces education
				liabilities</term> means liabilities of the armed forces for benefits under
				chapter 30 and of title 38 and for Department of Defense benefits under
				paragraphs (3) and (4) of section 510(e) and chapter 1606 of this title,
				including funds provided by the Secretary of Homeland Security for education
				liabilities for the Coast Guard when it is not operating as a service in the
				Department of the
				Navy.</text>
							</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA7578A4312A48C596E5994C53AB8556"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Definition of
			 normal cost</header><text>Paragraph (2) of such section is amended by striking
			 subparagraph (C) and inserting the following new subparagraph:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H20BCBBE5764043B49B22DD4CABC29103" style="OLC">
							<subparagraph id="HE3AC261CBB674BB7BA4CCEFED3ED7915"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The present value of the future Department
				of Defense benefits payable from the Fund (including funds from the Department
				in which the Coast Guard is operating) for educational assistance under chapter
				1606 of this title to persons who during such period become entitled to such
				assistance.</text>
							</subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC02D0DB88E5B42C096E18136B9F55FB4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional
			 technical and conforming Amendments</header>
					<subparagraph id="H723D0D6BE40A4A2DAED800EEB3AE71A1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Title
			 <enum-in-header>38</enum-in-header>, united states code</header>
						<clause id="HAB57399065584FA1B3D8E7AB2500729F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Section 3485 of
			 title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text>
							<subclause commented="no" id="H1E40D3E9E32542A59C5F7600D9D84006"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (a)(4)(E), by striking <quote>or 1607</quote>;</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H30749E69D8CD45D996D58800BE594C5D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (b), by striking <quote>chapter 30, 31, 32, or 34 of this title or chapter 1606
			 or 1607 of title 10,</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 30, 31, 32, 33, or 34
			 of this title or <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1606">chapter 1606</external-xref> of title 10,</quote>; and</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="HF951046E83ED4ED40071F9751060EB11"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (e)(1)—</text>
								<item id="H4A250044F90D475497C9088D15DDF2D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by
			 striking <quote>, chapter 30, 31, 32, 35, or 36 of this title, or chapter 1606
			 or 1607 of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>or chapter 30, 31, 32, 33, 35,
			 or 36 of this title or <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1606">chapter 1606</external-xref> of title 10</quote>; and</text>
								</item><item commented="no" id="H3CE1D7CE9169436EB87BE6DADB2700A"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>section 2135</quote> and inserting <quote>section 16135</quote>.</text>
								</item></subclause></clause><clause id="H616871C417ED44DA81A609955210B7D8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Section 3672(c)
			 of such title is amended—</text>
							<subclause id="H8D71E91E2D0D4C02921BA9C00294C15E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in paragraph
			 (3)(A), by striking <quote>chapters 30 and 35 of this title</quote> and
			 inserting <quote>chapters 30, 33, and 35 of this title</quote>; and</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="HD1C81BBD21864560BCC337FDDDD28CE5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in paragraph (4),
			 by striking <quote>chapter 30 or 35 of this title</quote> and inserting
			 <quote>chapter 30, 33, or 35 of this title</quote>.</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H8F3201C6A08D41D8B07D149C12602573"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Section 3674 of
			 such title is amended—</text>
							<subclause commented="no" id="H6E121E1BC7DA4DEA908885E86FC0F031"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (a)(1), by striking <quote>chapter 106</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter
			 1606</quote>; and</text>
							</subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H2397BA456CC9410890B0131F21B14576"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (c), by inserting <quote>33,</quote> after <quote>32,</quote>.</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H43C139DF493F4154A4D3D71CF1018447"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Section
			 3680A(d)(1) of such title is amended—</text>
							<subclause commented="no" id="HCDEF7C1EC5C445DCBFFB4D9230710770"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>chapter 106</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>chapter
			 1606</quote>; and</text>
							</subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H498CE554BFEC433B8B3DEC98B64E00C3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting
			 <quote>, 33</quote> after <quote>32</quote>.</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H66AB46714BB9491AADF128B101D880E4"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Section
			 3684A(a)(1) of such title is amended by striking <quote>chapter 30 or 32 of
			 this title or in chapter 106</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 30, 32, or 33
			 of this title or in chapter 1606</quote>.</text>
						</clause><clause commented="no" id="H1BEF3CB661934ED9BB8483A6EDADF218"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Section 3688(b)
			 of such title is amended by striking <quote>, chapter 30, 32, or 35 of this
			 title, or chapter 106</quote> and inserting <quote>or chapter 30, 32, 33, or 35
			 of this title, or chapter 1606</quote>.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H9F06D34EFA3340048F953FBF69C003F4"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Section 3689 of
			 such title is amended by inserting <quote>33,</quote> after <quote>32,</quote>
			 each place it appears.</text>
						</clause><clause id="HD1DBCC0B409C4C7C8DFAD5D5D724B4EB"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Section 3692 of
			 such title is amended—</text>
							<subclause id="H72D2EA5CE4594708A397DE95967CC2C3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in subsection (a),
			 by striking <quote>or 35 of this title</quote> and inserting <quote>33, or 35
			 of this title</quote>; and</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="HBA83A62E15F3480C8ED8AC5571CD9857"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (b), by striking <quote>, chapters 30, 32, and 35 of this title</quote> and
			 inserting <quote>and chapters 30, 32, 33, and 35 of this title</quote>.</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause id="HB0366C71774149DC8156B9F0CDA5053C"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Section 3695(a)
			 of such title is amended—</text>
							<subclause commented="no" id="HE855DF82CDBE4C2F96F4FFEFF7B52CDB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking
			 paragraph (4) and inserting the following new paragraph (4):</text>
								<quoted-block id="H9A8AC7ABD48A48E88D45B88B4F86DE84" style="OLC">
									<paragraph commented="no" id="HFC182F3E92CC40DEAD787D878B6916E1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Chapters 30, 32,
				33, 34, 35, and 36 of this title.</text>
									</paragraph><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
							</subclause><subclause id="HBFE223886186474DBDFBBC388A05EFE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in paragraph (5),
			 by striking <quote>1607,</quote>.</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H53CFF4E100CB4F2B8E82F6D9E6B2237F"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Section 3697(a) of
			 such title is amended by striking <quote>chapter 30, 32, 34, or 35 of this
			 title, or chapter 106</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 30, 32, 33, 34, or
			 35 of this title or chapter 1606</quote>.</text>
						</clause><clause commented="no" id="H37B0956C365A4C389FBCF508B8785937"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>Section
			 3697A(b)(1) of such title is amended by striking <quote>or 32 of this title or
			 chapter 106 or 107</quote> and inserting <quote>32, or 33 of this title or
			 chapter 107 or 1606</quote>.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19BD1998F87D4623BB8070E19D143BA2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Title
			 <enum-in-header>10</enum-in-header>, united states code</header><text>Section
			 510(h)(1) of title 10, United States Code, is amended—</text>
						<clause id="H9D51F12E607A4266BA04F921BB08C337"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in
			 subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>or chapter 33</quote> after
			 <quote>chapter 30</quote>; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="HD4CD3EF66A584DB5A8634B21434219A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in
			 subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>either such chapter</quote> each place it
			 appears and inserting <quote>any such chapter</quote>;</text>
						</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HD2AFD9046B1F42959956465EE900C946"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Effective
			 date</header><text>This section and the amendments made by this section shall
			 take effect on October 1, 2009.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


