<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H2B18A4F69E75493A8C209C2F3935D49E" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 5522 IH: Combustible Dust Explosion and Fire
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2008-03-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>2d Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 5522</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20080304">March 4, 2008</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000725">Mr. George Miller of
			 California</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001252">Mr.
			 Barrow</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and
			 Labor</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To require the Secretary of Labor to issue interim and
		  final occupational safety and health standards regarding worker exposure to
		  combustible dust, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HB3B492FABD1C4C01A417EF080027CD81" style="OLC">
		<section id="HCFF6D704E72C434B847FC386C678E808" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Combustible Dust Explosion and Fire
			 Prevention Act of 2008</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H457E472AD7FA4145AD19050000878022"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
			<paragraph id="HB14B934A0CF34309B71D8984D820544F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An emergency
			 exists concerning worker exposure to combustible dust explosions and
			 fires.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HFA09FB40652B475F8ED13882FC007C39"><enum>(2)</enum><text>At least 12
			 workers were killed and more than 60 seriously injured in a catastrophic
			 combustible dust explosion at Imperial Sugar in Savannah, Georgia, on February
			 7, 2008.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H055CE6CBC81F49B7982C4CCE499892DE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Following 3
			 catastrophic dust explosions that killed 14 workers in 2003, the Chemical
			 Safety and Hazard Investigation Board (CSB) issued a report in November 2006
			 which identified 281 combustible dust incidents between 1980 and 2005 that
			 killed 119 workers and injured 718. A quarter of the explosions occurred at
			 food industry facilities, including sugar plants.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H78FA9D92D92B4F049098289F2BE707E2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The CSB concluded
			 that <quote>combustible dust explosions are a serious hazard in American
			 industry</quote>.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HED1F885D6CE840B191D6685C8DDD61C8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Material Safety
			 Data Sheets (MSDSs) often do not adequately address the hazards of combustible
			 dusts and the hazard communication standard promulgated by the Occupational
			 Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) (29 C.F.R. 1910.1200) inadequately
			 addresses dust explosion hazards, and fails to ensure that safe work practices
			 and guidance documents are included in MSDSs.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H2037EB75D8614C73A8E926C7C0231C49"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The CSB
			 recommended that OSHA issue a standard designed to prevent combustible dust
			 fires and explosions in general industry, based on current National Fire
			 Protection Association dust explosion standards, and also that OSHA revise the
			 hazard communication standard to clarify that combustible dusts are covered and
			 that Material Safety Data Sheets contain information about the hazards and
			 physical properties of combustible dusts.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HFEFD672E123F4117B73DA5629B4160B4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>OSHA has not
			 formally acted on either of the CSB’s regulatory recommendations.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H0CDBB8B8E6854EBDACBA372F779BB0E8"><enum>(8)</enum><text>OSHA issued a
			 grain handling facilities standard in 1987 (29 C.F.R. 1910.272) that has proven
			 highly effective in reducing the risk of combustible grain dust explosions,
			 according to an OSHA evaluation.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HD9E9F5590F644CCC85D3130700291314"><enum>(9)</enum><text>No OSHA standard
			 comprehensively addresses combustible dust explosion hazards in general
			 industry.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H05ADF30BDFC644EA9FA577B3D6C2CB8"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Voluntary National
			 Fire Protection Association standards exist which, when implemented,
			 effectively reduce the likelihood and impact of combustible dust
			 explosions.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H6CD8183FC457449CA930E59B9F00632F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Issuance of
			 standard on combustible dust</header>
			<subsection id="H7435277CBE644E12815968C843E3C36"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Interim
			 standard</header>
				<paragraph id="HEC172C247DAB418491C6B0B78B3D03BE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>Not
			 later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of
			 Labor shall promulgate an interim final standard regulating combustible dusts.
			 The interim final standard shall apply to manufacturing, processing, blending,
			 conveying, repackaging, and handling of combustible particulate solids and
			 their dusts, including food (such as candy, starch, flour, sugar, feed),
			 plastics, wood, rubber, furniture, textiles, pesticides, pharmaceuticals,
			 fibers, dyes, coal, metals (such as aluminum, chromium, iron, magnesium, and
			 zinc), fossil fuels power, and any other industry in which combustible dust
			 presents a hazard, but shall not apply to processes already covered by OSHA’s
			 standard on grain facilities (29 C.F.R. 1910.272).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H16B16DD5003D421891002E01988F8562"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The
			 interim final standard required under this subsection shall provide no less
			 protection than the recommendations contained in the National Fire Protection
			 Association’s Standard for the Prevention of Fire and Dust Explosions from the
			 Manufacturing, Processing, and Handling of Combustible Particulate Solids–2006
			 (NFPA 654) and Standard for Combustible Metals–2006 (NFPA 484) and shall
			 provide for the following:</text>
					<subparagraph id="HCABA81D900954260AC5617E7008E8BC7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Requirements for
			 hazard assessment to identify evaluate and control combustible dust
			 hazards.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D0072B55AE84214A03DD9552BE948CA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Requirements for a
			 written program which includes plans for hazardous dust inspection, testing,
			 housekeeping, and control, with established frequency and methods.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C9B19AAB1BF4278A79CE6B89801027D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Requirements for
			 engineering, administrative controls and operating procedures such as means to
			 controlling fugitive dust emissions and ignition sources, the use of dust
			 collection systems and filters, minimizing horizontal surfaces where dust can
			 accumulate, and sealing of areas inaccessible to housekeeping.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0FDA57925704498D9D26E2E393D5DDB7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Requirements for
			 managing change of dust producing materials, technology, equipment, staffing,
			 and procedures.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B4CC48F632240CE80F2433C51034C6B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Requirements for
			 housekeeping to control accumulation of combustible dust.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2B1D5D415044798B7D9B6104006128"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Requirements for
			 building design, such as equipping buildings with explosion venting or
			 sprinklers.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1E98525CBED4E30980032FA51B06DC"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Requirements for
			 explosion protection, including separation and segregation of the
			 hazard.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA422D474456E40C48266002771004BF6"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Requirements for
			 employee participation in hazard assessment, development of and compliance with
			 the written program, and other elements of hazard management in this
			 standard.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB5AAD1EEE3949B2ABD8D8E59BA88330"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Requirements to
			 provide written safety and health information and training to employees,
			 including hazard communication information, labeling, and training.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D66EA88F6774C2F9C014937C0CE0041"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date
			 of interim standard</header><text>The interim final standard shall take effect
			 upon issuance. The interim final standard shall have the legal effect of an
			 occupational safety and health standard, and shall apply until a final standard
			 becomes effective under section 6 of the Occupational Safety and Health Act (29
			 U.S.C. 655).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8CAD4F33FB114463A2FBA96E6C37D7F4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Final
			 standard</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18
			 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor shall,
			 pursuant to section 6 of the Occupational Safety and Health Act (29 U.S.C.
			 655), promulgate a final standard regulating combustible dust explosions. The
			 final standard shall contain, at a minimum, the worker protection provisions in
			 subsection (a)(2).</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HD3CF711B4BBC4F0BBA48C95BCD21149D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Revision of the
			 hazard communication standard</header>
			<subsection id="HF832100B27C448A3B035D33F701FFE2E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>The
			 hazard communications standard in section 1910.1200(c) of chapter 29, Code of
			 Federal Regulations, shall be revised as follows:</text>
				<paragraph id="H85D816A6C8A64EE590081986E578D3F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The definition of
			 <quote>physical hazard</quote> (29 C.F.R. 1910.1200(c)) shall be revised to
			 include <quote>a combustible dust</quote> as an additional example of a
			 physical hazard.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H440DE23396F74279ADC9C70083F7D67B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>combustible dust</term> shall be added to the definitions in such section
			 and such term shall be defined as <quote>a combustible particulate solid or
			 finely divided metal that presents a fire or deflagration hazard when suspended
			 in air or some other oxidizing medium over a range of concentrations regardless
			 of particle size and shape</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H37C702632CBA42B98FFC4552BCA2EEF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Procedure and
			 effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The
			 modifications of the standard required by subsection (a) shall be made and
			 published in the Federal Register not later than 6 months after the date of
			 enactment of this Act by the Secretary of Labor acting through the Occupational
			 Safety and Health Administration without regard to the procedural requirements
			 applicable to regulations promulgated under section 6(b) of the Occupational
			 Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/655">29 U.S.C. 655(b)</external-xref>) or the procedural requirements
			 of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code. Such revised standard shall take
			 effect not later than 90 days after the publication in the Federal
			 Register.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H19DBECFE04CA4AB5997EC0CA91846400"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effect of
			 modifications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The
			 modifications under this section shall be in force until superseded in whole or
			 in part by regulations promulgated by the Secretary of Labor under section 6(b)
			 of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/655">29 U.S.C. 655(b)</external-xref>) and shall
			 be enforced in the same manner and to the same extent as any rule or regulation
			 promulgated under such section.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


