<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HFD8A35F3765C428394F82401C5414A23" public-private="public">
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>111th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 3993</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20091103">November 3, 2009</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000179">Mr. Engel</sponsor> introduced
			 the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and
			 Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To require accurate and reasonable disclosure of the
		  terms and conditions of prepaid telephone calling cards and
		  services.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H36B8EE851B71424A8056F1C39EF8ED34" style="OLC">
		<section id="H46DF04835D55426FBDE39C7F07E286EA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Calling Card Consumer Protection
			 Act</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section commented="no" id="HE71F45E9245B4F59BE2719CA28B49A59"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this Act, the following
			 definitions apply:</text>
			<paragraph commented="no" id="H482A7901DAB44245ACACFAA41A54A5C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Commission</term> means the
			 Federal Trade Commission.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HA37F8CD8372E4CAAB7AA53FC00603F8E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>prepaid calling card</term> has the meaning given the term <term>prepaid
			 calling card</term> by section 64.5000(a) of the Federal Communications
			 Commission’s regulations (47 C.F.R. 64.5000(a)). Such term shall also include
			 calling cards that use VoIP service or a successor protocol. Such term shall
			 also include an electronic or other mechanism that allows users to pay in
			 advance for a specified amount of calling. Such term shall not include—</text>
				<subparagraph commented="no" id="HCCFBC936BCD1401EAFFB23A6B83E70E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>calling cards or
			 other rights of use that are provided for free or at no additional cost as a
			 promotional item accompanying a product or service purchased by a
			 consumer;</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE39E170BAA434327B9B8A8913FD7E6C2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any card, device, or other right of use,
			 the purchase of which establishes a customer-carrier relationship with a
			 provider of wireless telecommunications service or wireless hybrid service, or
			 that provides access to a wireless telecommunications service or wireless
			 hybrid service account wherein the purchaser has a pre-existing relationship
			 with the wireless service provider; or</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HADBF5DAB4C1746389798432252E811FF"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">payphone service, as that term is defined
			 in section 276(d) of the Communications Act of 1934 (47 U.S.C. 276(d)).</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H1FBB950525DF420C9E208CFFD2DBC186"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>prepaid calling card
			 provider</term> has the meaning given the term <term>prepaid calling card
			 provider</term> by section 64.5000(b) of the Federal Communications
			 Commission’s regulations (47 C.F.R. 64.5000(b)). Such term shall also
			 include—</text>
				<subparagraph id="HAE8400CCBD254FA7AF9D9F4FDCCA4827"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a provider of a
			 prepaid calling card that uses VoIP service or a successor protocol; and</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H506D6C819CA34765BC432BA4A6A7FA2F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a provider of a
			 prepaid calling card that allows users to pay in advance for a specified amount
			 of minutes through an electronic or other mechanism.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H8952348560574BD599D6637DE4BA1F3E"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>prepaid calling card
			 distributor</term> means any entity or person that purchases prepaid calling
			 cards from a prepaid calling card provider or another prepaid calling card
			 distributor and sells, re-sells, issues, or distributes such cards to one or
			 more distributors of such cards or to one or more retail sellers of such
			 cards.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H7300765D39B14A9FBB1E32772BFC922A"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>wireless hybrid
			 service</term> is defined as a service that integrates both commercial mobile
			 radio service (as defined by section 20.3 of the Federal Communications
			 Commission’s regulations (47 C.F.R. 20.3)) and VoIP service.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H3DF82D8DAED94B1099623C015333950F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>VoIP service</term> has the meaning given the term <term>interconnected
			 Voice over Internet protocol service</term> by section 9.3 of the Federal
			 Communications Commission’s regulations (47 C.F.R. 9.3). Such term shall
			 include any voice calling service that utilizes a voice over Internet protocol
			 or any successor protocol in the transmission of the call.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF89490518B744B0DA088938115D91DCC"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>fees</term> includes all
			 charges, fees, taxes, or surcharges applicable to a prepaid calling card that
			 are—</text>
				<subparagraph commented="no" id="H4848464BE1A9443F92D380D73526C62F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>required by
			 Federal law or regulation or order of the Federal Communications Commission or
			 by the laws and regulations of any State or political subdivision of a State;
			 or</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB82E877BB05E4ED0BE65BA3B7A4780E3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expressly permitted to be assessed under
			 Federal law or regulation or order of the Federal Communications Commission or
			 under the laws and regulations of any State or political subdivision of a
			 State.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HD53BC4673F49402689B9D27F3A9C2E7A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>additional charge</term> means any charge assessed by a prepaid calling
			 card provider or prepaid calling card distributor for the use of a prepaid
			 calling card, other than a fee or rate.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H9D18225A0E844375B8EC45CC9993D5C1"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>international preferred destination</term> means one or more specific
			 international destinations named on a prepaid calling card or on the packaging
			 material accompanying a prepaid calling card.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H46E3796FAC5B4B4D98E9973F0DB7BF2E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Required
			 disclosures of prepaid calling cards</header>
			<subsection id="H756CEB3EE7F8452FA27EE8F6636ABC38"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Required
			 disclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any prepaid
			 calling card provider or prepaid calling card distributor shall accurately
			 disclose in a clear and conspicuous manner the following information relating
			 to the terms and conditions of the prepaid calling card:</text>
				<paragraph id="H88522776E90C4A04B10B0FF8A6172FF2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The name of the prepaid calling card
			 provider and such provider’s customer service telephone number and hours of
			 service.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HFE676BE9CEFD475C8B814D068FA65DDC"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H78CE83243CF243E78BAABE11E9AC3C61"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of domestic interstate minutes
			 available from the prepaid calling card and the number of available minutes for
			 all international preferred destinations served by the prepaid calling card at
			 the time of purchase; or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51805C105AF342A7BA2AC023B36B3962" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the dollar value of the prepaid calling
			 card, the domestic interstate rate per minute provided by such card, and the
			 applicable per minute rates for all international preferred destinations served
			 by the prepaid calling card at the time of purchase.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H025A491A34DF4C5686BB70AE9F4499C2"><enum>(3)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H06256E80A1AA43B89BABEF6633812F4A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The applicable per
			 minute rate for all individual international destinations served by the card at
			 the time of purchase; or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3EC1C72162734EB7BE834B60A6F80147" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a
			 toll-free customer service number and website (if the provider maintains a
			 website) where a consumer may obtain the information described in subparagraph
			 (A) and a statement that such information may be obtained through such
			 toll-free customer service number and website.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4542186C7EAB44CB9BEF4A1D0A18E485"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The following
			 terms and conditions pertaining to, or associated with, the use of the prepaid
			 calling card:</text>
					<subparagraph commented="no" id="H03B7A51C632F4428B8F65858F0161885"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any applicable fees associated with the use
			 of the prepaid calling card.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H492D170D4E204EC095056DCE926FB8B3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of
			 any additional charges associated with the use of the prepaid calling card and
			 the amount of such charges.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC602357FB3124D8D9FAEE44DE151D7F3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any limitation on
			 the use or period of time for which the promoted or advertised minutes or rates
			 will be available.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5479AD1D405F42019D2EED2D41C82509"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Applicable
			 policies relating to refund, recharge, and any predetermined decrease in value
			 of such card over a period of time.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H69E2BEAA81884ECBB96AC2ABA98F392A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Any expiration
			 date applicable to the prepaid calling card or the minutes available with such
			 calling card.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H73E32CFF43934ED390E270DFB5F5E048"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Location of
			 disclosure and language requirement</header>
				<paragraph id="H9F754D3C88354856977045BCD809082E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Clear and
			 conspicuous</header>
					<subparagraph id="H4645E96C155A48E1AC9BCA4CDC8FC648"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Cards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The disclosures required under subsection
			 (a) shall be printed in plain English language (except as provided in paragraph
			 (2)) in a clear and conspicuous manner and location on the prepaid calling
			 card. If the card is enclosed in packaging that obscures the disclosures on the
			 card, such disclosures also shall be printed on the outside packaging of the
			 card.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4146592E2B54CC0AD204B9CBD5C455A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Online
			 services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to the
			 requirements under subparagraph (A), in the case of a prepaid calling card that
			 consumers purchase via the Internet, the disclosures required under subsection
			 (a) shall be displayed in plain English language (except as provided in
			 paragraph (2)) in a clear and conspicuous manner and location on the Internet
			 website that the consumer must access prior to purchasing such card.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC3F687965E1645CB9911075DC81BDECE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Advertising and
			 other promotional material</header><text>Any advertising for a prepaid calling
			 card that contains any representation, expressly or by implication, regarding
			 the dollar value, the per minute rate, or the number of minutes provided by the
			 card shall include in a clear and conspicuous manner and location all the
			 disclosures described in subsection (a).</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3842BAE92CA84C8FAE9AE9CE24D5FC06"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign
			 languages</header><text>If a language other than English is prominently used on
			 a prepaid calling card, its packaging, or in point-of-sale advertising,
			 Internet advertising, or promotional material for such card, the disclosures
			 required by this section shall be disclosed in that language on such card,
			 packaging, advertisement, or promotional material.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H1DEDE64E649C41C6994F00D93E401092"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Minutes
			 announced, promoted, or advertised through voice prompts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any information provided to a consumer by
			 any voice prompt given to the consumer at the time the consumer uses the
			 prepaid calling card relating to the remaining value of the calling card or the
			 number of minutes available from the calling card shall be accurate, taking
			 into account the application of the fees and additional charges required to be
			 disclosed under subsection (a).</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HFF931F6589414A59B0A98114B075920B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Disclosures
			 required upon purchase of additional minutes</header><text>If a prepaid calling
			 card permits a consumer to add value to the card or purchase additional minutes
			 after the original purchase of the prepaid calling card, any changes to the
			 rates or additional charges required to be disclosed under subsection (a) shall
			 apply only to the additional minutes to be purchased and shall be disclosed to
			 the consumer before the completion of such purchase.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HDC66A2B80A6C4EC6BC2C12A5739BEFE7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Enforcement by
			 the Federal Trade Commission</header>
			<subsection id="H434EC60E678D4F7DB9E63877A6E49B8A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Unfair and
			 deceptive act or practice</header><text>A violation of section 3 shall be
			 treated as a violation of a rule defining an unfair or deceptive act or
			 practice prescribed under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the Federal Trade Commission
			 Act (15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)).</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HAC17A28ADB584965801C45796EE223EF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authority of the
			 commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission
			 shall enforce this Act in the same manner and by the same means as though all
			 applicable terms and provisions of the Federal Trade Commission Act were
			 incorporated into and made a part of this Act. Notwithstanding any provision of
			 the Federal Trade Commission Act or any other provision of law and solely for
			 purposes of this Act, common carriers subject to the Communications Act of 1934
			 (47 U.S.C. 151 et seq.) and any amendment thereto shall be subject to the
			 jurisdiction of the Commission.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H2099998707934D10933DC8E6ABDFEDF6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rulemaking
			 authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180
			 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall, in
			 consultation with the Federal Communications Commission and in accordance with
			 section 553 of title 5, United States Code, issue regulations to carry out this
			 Act. In promulgating such regulations, the Commission shall—</text>
				<paragraph id="H5AB66ACCBEE445019C1DFA602406A670"><enum>(1)</enum><text>take into
			 consideration the need for clear disclosures that provide for easy
			 comprehension and comparison by consumers, taking into account the size of
			 prepaid calling cards; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H06AA132F2F274796AE3C3BD707E7AE11"><enum>(2)</enum><text>give due
			 consideration to the views of the Federal Communications Commission with regard
			 to matters for which that Commission has particular expertise and authority and
			 shall take into consideration the views of States.</text>
				</paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">In
			 promulgating such regulations, the Commission shall not issue regulations that
			 otherwise affect the rates, terms, and conditions of prepaid calling
			 cards.</continuation-text></subsection><subsection id="H7141630A533842728EB0806FE442F990"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Savings
			 provision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act
			 shall be construed to limit the authority of the Commission under any other
			 provision of law. Except to the extent expressly provided in this Act, nothing
			 in this Act shall be construed to alter or affect the exemption for common
			 carriers provided by section 5(a)(2) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (15
			 U.S.C. 45(a)(2)). Nothing in this Act is intended to limit the authority of the
			 Federal Communications Commission.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HCDE215481747493B88A3D9961A680B48"><enum>5.</enum><header>State
			 enforcement</header>
			<subsection id="H813044572A7A4E46A9F5D761C92BF4C8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header>
				<paragraph id="HFDE876D1860148418B49AA47B1618C6C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Civil
			 actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In any case in which
			 the attorney general of a State, a State utility commission, or other consumer
			 protection agency has reason to believe that an interest of the residents of
			 that State has been or is threatened or adversely affected by the engagement of
			 any person in a practice that is prohibited under this Act, the State utility
			 commission or other consumer protection agency, if authorized by State law, or
			 the State, as parens patriae, may bring a civil action on behalf of the
			 residents of that State in a district court of the United States of appropriate
			 jurisdiction, or any other court of competent jurisdiction to—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HCF6A8675EED74A398FF760C91F1394E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enjoin that
			 practice;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AC786B5F9934F4FA38B61A78A9FC0B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enforce compliance
			 with this Act;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F896805587F4B7380B81A6B1BA0E076"><enum>(C)</enum><text>obtain damage,
			 restitution, or other compensation on behalf of residents of the State;
			 or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A959F65F52B406881DD30998ED08926"><enum>(D)</enum><text>obtain such other
			 relief as the court may consider to be appropriate.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H54B63A3429FD4F55BE501E7817B4ADA3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice to the
			 Commission</header>
					<subparagraph id="H894861EE4DEF44B6A64AEEF6A5A44F9E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before filing an
			 action under paragraph (1), the State shall provide to the Commission—</text>
						<clause id="H2AA89737BD7B4C1999EF53D0DFFA55CF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>written notice of
			 the action; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H563A9A8B3F7449359D5258C083FBEDC6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a
			 copy of the complaint for the action.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66BB8251AA40434792725B129E9438B2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exemption</header>
						<clause id="H99E423BF31AC4A8B8F2F43B2E6DC3F8D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subparagraph (A)
			 shall not apply with respect to the filing of an action by a State under this
			 subsection, if the attorney general or other appropriate officer determines
			 that it is not feasible to provide the notice described in that subparagraph
			 before the filing of the action.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H6781BEF2A4434D8098920A594CA56EA4"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In an action described in clause (i), the
			 State shall provide notice and a copy of the complaint to the Commission at the
			 same time as the State files the action.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD655C596C7CA462E9386E5B9CEFAF86D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Intervention by
			 Commission</header>
				<paragraph id="H6FA96C8B7FFF4D618B2CF28F0EC32523"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>On receiving notice under subsection (a)(2), the
			 Commission shall have the right to intervene in the action that is the subject
			 of the notice.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HE063321E9C8C481FBDB603566C88B9F2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effect of
			 intervention</header><text>If the Commission intervenes in an action under
			 subsection (a), it shall have the right—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H9E15F84774F54B4A80F3412E62918550"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to be heard with
			 respect to any matter that arises in that action;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1AF968BF258741F9BF2D1B7372ED1070"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to remove the
			 action to the appropriate United States District Court; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1DA988D0A4C470FA31B7FC439E2F886"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to file a petition
			 for appeal.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H48ADF56DE4BC451BB5C5A693F4262331"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of bringing any civil action
			 under subsection (a), nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent an
			 attorney general of a State, a State utility commission, or other consumer
			 protection agency authorized by State law from exercising the powers conferred
			 on the attorney general or other appropriate official by the laws of that State
			 to—</text>
				<paragraph id="H65B6C6BB904845A1AADE8C42DC1A9544"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct
			 investigations;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H7FC62066894F4B599C2A4AAD0D004B51"><enum>(2)</enum><text>administer oaths
			 or affirmations;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H6DA6D83758E943FBAED27AE723E2BD55"><enum>(3)</enum><text>compel the
			 attendance of witnesses or the production of documentary and other evidence;
			 or</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HCC49111738614D2F8FB79BC6DAB18ED8"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enforce any State law.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC55515F3D8AF435C87C6D6E344461798"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Action by the
			 Commission may preclude State action</header><text>In any case in which an
			 action is instituted by or on behalf of the Commission for violation of this
			 Act, or any regulation issued under this Act, no State may, during the pendency
			 of that action, institute an action under subsection (a) against any defendant
			 named in the complaint in that action for violation of this Act or
			 regulation.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H99010B7D94A64B25834E8C4C639BACA9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Venue; service
			 of process</header>
				<paragraph id="H76E298BDA5A4474AAC22E5509AFE4A3C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Venue</header><text>Any
			 action brought under subsection (a) may be brought in the district court of the
			 United States that meets applicable requirements relating to venue under
			 section 1391 of title 28, United States Code.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HB24A7E0FE34745F29ABB7C4BE3511ED3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Service of
			 process</header><text>In an action brought under subsection (a), process may be
			 served in any district in which the defendant—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H38076CBB71554E968DAF5183995DEF0C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is an inhabitant;
			 or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H91BE92DAC8434244B70D5FEC48C0E3D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may be
			 found.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HE40CC84A83244AABA2A1A41C6165F2E9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>No
			 prepaid calling card distributor who is a retail merchant or seller of prepaid
			 calling cards, who, with respect to such cards, is exclusively engaged in
			 point-of-sale transactions may be liable for damages in an action authorized
			 under this section unless such distributor acted with actual knowledge that the
			 act or practice giving rise to such action is unfair or deceptive and is
			 unlawful under this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HDA5A0EB4078340489A6B91C073D502F5"><enum>6.</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act shall apply to—</text>
			<paragraph id="HF94C76CCECD8495CA0FF7015CBBDE895"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any prepaid
			 calling card issued or placed into the stream of commerce beginning 90 days
			 after the date on which final regulations are promulgated pursuant to section
			 4(c); and</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H6B3EF88BFF6A471285C47CFD7619CE1F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any advertising, promotion, point-of-sale
			 material or voice prompt regarding a prepaid calling card that is disseminated
			 beginning 90 days after the date on which final regulations are promulgated
			 pursuant to section 4(c).</text>
			</paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="section">If the
			 Commission determines that it is not feasible for prepaid calling card
			 providers or distributors to comply with the requirements of this Act with
			 respect to prepaid calling cards issued or placed into the stream of commerce
			 after such 90-day period, the Commission may extend such period by not more
			 than an additional 90 days.</continuation-text></section><section commented="no" id="H0073186956E148C0A3811F77E095247D"><enum>7.</enum><header>Effect on State
			 laws</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall
			 affect the authority of any State to establish or continue in effect a
			 provision of the law of a State relating to regulation of prepaid calling
			 cards, prepaid calling card distributors, prepaid calling services, or prepaid
			 calling service providers, except to the extent that such provision of law is
			 inconsistent with the provisions of this Act or a regulation prescribed under
			 this Act, and then only to the extent of such inconsistency. A provision of the
			 law of a State is not inconsistent with this Act or a regulation prescribed
			 under this Act if such provision provides equal or greater protection to
			 consumers than what is provided under this Act or the regulations prescribed
			 under this Act.</text>
		</section><section id="H56D8DBAB601B45E18A88E6BA5927FB09"><enum>8.</enum><header>GAO
			 Study</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Beginning 2 years after
			 the date on which final regulations are promulgated pursuant to section 4(c),
			 the Comptroller General shall conduct a study of the effectiveness of this Act
			 and the disclosures required under this Act and shall submit a report of such
			 study to Congress not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this
			 Act.</text>
		</section></legis-body>
</bill>
