<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H893BE9D7D70142418D3632013B247B13" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 4053 IH: Mental Health Improvements Act
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-11-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 4053</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20071101">November 1, 2007</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001231">Ms. Berkley</sponsor> (for
			 herself, <cosponsor name-id="B000911">Ms. Corrine Brown of Florida</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="D000210">Mr. Delahunt</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="F000116">Mr. Filner</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="W000794">Ms. Watson</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="F000010">Mr. Faleomavaega</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="H001039">Mr. Hall of New York</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="H001040">Mr. Hare</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001234">Mr. Baca</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001166">Mr.
			 McNerney</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000365">Mr. Kagen</cosponsor>)
			 introduced the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’
			 Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To improve the treatment and services provided by the
		  Department of Veterans Affairs to veterans with post-traumatic stress disorder
		  and substance use disorders, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" style="OLC">
		<section id="H2EBA1874E9A246F2B96EEBC86D54488F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of
			 contents</header>
			<subsection id="HEB922C43F157454C8D004DF02606137B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short
			 title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited
			 as the <quote><short-title>Mental Health Improvements Act
			 of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H3648CFA89FF24C51B292002D6415E148"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of
			 contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
				<toc>
					<toc-entry idref="H2EBA1874E9A246F2B96EEBC86D54488F" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="title">TITLE I—Substance use disorders and mental health
				care</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="section">Sec. 101. Findings on substance use disorders and mental
				health.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="section">Sec. 102. Expansion of substance use disorder treatment
				services at Department of Veterans Affairs Medical Centers.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="section">Sec. 103. Care for veterans with mental health and substance
				use disorders by clinician teams.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="section">Sec. 104. Program for enhanced treatment of substance use
				disorders and post-traumatic stress disorder in veterans.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="section">Sec. 105. National centers of excellence on post-traumatic
				stress disorder and substance use disorders.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="section">Sec. 106. Report on residential mental health care facilities
				of the Veterans Health Administration.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="section">Sec. 107. Tribute to Justin Bailey.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="title">TITLE II—Mental health accessibility enhancements</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="section">Sec. 201. Pilot program on peer outreach and support for
				veterans and use of community mental health centers and Indian Health Service
				facilities.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="title">TITLE III—Research</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="section">Sec. 301. Research program on comorbid post-traumatic stress
				disorder and substance use disorders.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="section">Sec. 302. Extension of authorization for Special Committee on
				Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="title">TITLE IV—Assistance for families of veterans</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="section">Sec. 401. Clarification of authority of Secretary of Veterans
				Affairs to provide mental health services to families of veterans.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFD607C99FAA14C4593E88E37D5E5A1E5" level="section">Sec. 402. Pilot program on provision of readjustment and
				transition assistance to veterans and their families in cooperation with Vet
				Centers.</toc-entry>
				</toc>
			</subsection></section><title id="H96C7EF4236224A5600B4A6135DF63C7B"><enum>I</enum><header>Substance use
			 disorders and mental health care</header>
			<section id="H3733EAA150774AAAB8C91F0027A108D" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>101.</enum><header>Findings on
			 substance use disorders and mental health</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following
			 findings:</text>
				<paragraph id="H0A1FF62C00E84546AB8622A22D87DC2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>More than 1,500,000
			 members of the Armed Forces have been deployed in Operation Iraqi Freedom and
			 Operation Enduring Freedom. The 2005 Department of Defense Survey of Health
			 Related Behaviors Among Active Duty Personnel reports that 23 percent of
			 members of the Armed Forces on active duty acknowledge a significant problem
			 with alcohol use, with similar rates of acknowledged problems with alcohol use
			 among members of the National Guard.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HAD92C78D2C1D4552954043AC176EA3D7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The effects of
			 substance abuse are wide ranging, including significantly increased risk of
			 suicide, exacerbation of mental and physical health disorders, breakdown of
			 family support, and increased risk of unemployment and homelessness.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HE25EF67D972344DD8839BA4EFFF47581"><enum>(3)</enum><text>While veterans
			 suffering from mental health conditions, chronic physical illness, and
			 polytrauma may be at increased risk for development of a substance use
			 disorder, treatment for these veterans is complicated by the need to address
			 adequately the physical and mental symptoms associated with these conditions
			 through appropriate medical intervention.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H2CADE0B139E14AD380EE1C53F1A63C1C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>While the Veterans
			 Health Administration has dramatically increased health services for veterans
			 from 1996 through 2006, the number of veterans receiving specialized substance
			 abuse treatment services decreased 18 percent during that time. No comparable
			 decrease in the national rate of substance abuse has been observed during that
			 time.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H7660CFEA51F84F75934C835C680037D6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>While some
			 facilities of the Veterans Health Administration provide exemplary substance
			 use disorder treatment services, the availability of such treatment services
			 throughout the health care system of the Veterans Health Administration is
			 inconsistent.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H1BF27B4274A645099E1B30FA185656E2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>According to the
			 Government Accountability Office, the Department of Veterans Affairs
			 significantly reduced its substance use disorder treatment and rehabilitation
			 services between 1996 and 2006, and has made little progress since in restoring
			 these services to their pre-1996 levels.</text>
				</paragraph></section><section id="H8ED62ED71F964448B3578676BFB2C7A6"><enum>102.</enum><header>Expansion of
			 substance use disorder treatment services at Department of Veterans Affairs
			 Medical Centers</header>
				<subsection id="H132E0A7F909241DA8520020778DFEC8D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Provision of
			 substance use disorder treatment services</header><text>The Secretary of
			 Veterans Affairs shall ensure the provision, at each Department of Veterans
			 Affairs medical center and community based outpatient clinic, of the following
			 services and treatments with respect to substance use disorder for
			 veterans:</text>
					<paragraph id="H8225441F162A4708B5C243FE996F93BD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Short term
			 motivational counseling services.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H0488A4582F8747B78FB69B8856B7C37D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Intensive
			 outpatient care services.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H36160C66D7A64A6DA5A04EE582A91442"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Relapse prevention
			 services.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H12F01D015C514D2986B254B723894DF8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Ongoing aftercare
			 and outpatient counseling services.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HEF3C7DC64EB740219E5B320079E472A7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Opiate
			 substitution therapy services.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HE0EBEC43199C4D8D955ECE71F44377A1"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Pharmacological
			 treatments aimed at reducing craving for drugs and alcohol.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HE8C781B8B5CB45C191A11B1860A3C595"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Detoxification and
			 stabilization services.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HC9D6A4E0F0DB4E5E8C187303C86E3351"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Such other
			 services as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8A8C7337CE17410186952818F1C5DA32"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exemptions</header>
					<paragraph id="H7C797B8858884921943C5FF0D7354707"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Secretary may exempt an individual medical center or
			 community based outpatient clinic from providing all of the services otherwise
			 required by subsection (a).</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HBE039C67ABD140FEBE9522A32D9273B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual
			 report</header><text>Each year, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on
			 Veterans' Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the
			 House of Representatives a report setting forth the exemptions made under
			 paragraph (1) as of the date of the report and the reasons therefor.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB11AE94A750244A6902C5D17B026FB89"><enum>103.</enum><header>Care for
			 veterans with mental health and substance use disorders by clinician
			 teams</header>
				<subsection id="H1E4F95E9C8D04A46BADD3226344EBD43"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the event the
			 Secretary of Veterans Affairs provides a veteran inpatient or outpatient care
			 for a substance use disorder and a comorbid mental health disorder, the
			 Secretary shall ensure that treatment for such disorders is provided
			 concurrently by a team of clinicians with appropriate expertise.</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="HCC593585DDEE47A498D1B63572B40000"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Team of
			 clinicians with appropriate expertise defined</header><text>In this section,
			 the term <term>team of clinicians with appropriate expertise</term> means a
			 team consisting of the following:</text>
					<paragraph id="H9B931F44BA0842F5A4001D44A8F8BB98"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Clinicians and
			 health professionals with expertise in treatment of substance use disorders and
			 mental health disorders.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H990D4A2027FD4D59AB8E16C9D6680EC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Such other
			 professionals as the Secretary considers appropriate for the provision of
			 treatment to veterans for substance use and mental health disorders.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE77806F4B89A4FD3B71972E8D8532AD"><enum>104.</enum><header>Program for
			 enhanced treatment of substance use disorders and post-traumatic stress
			 disorder in veterans</header>
				<subsection id="H040D1B6BEA2E4DDCA3A96E2479D57FA5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall carry out a
			 program for the purpose of enhancing the care and treatment for veterans with
			 substance use disorders and post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD).</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="H1DB06EA809A44C2397704FD6F522088"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Allocation of
			 funds</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall carry out the
			 program through a competitive allocation of funds to facilities of the
			 Department of Veterans Affairs for the provision of care and treatment to
			 veterans described in subsection (a).</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="HFFA6A88E75644234BB23AD6798701EB3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>A
			 facility of the Department, including a medical center, a community based
			 outpatient clinic, or a readjustment counseling center, seeking an allocation
			 of funds under this section shall submit to the Secretary an application
			 therefor in such form and in such manner as the Secretary considers
			 appropriate.</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="H7422303AA1DF408F986737A16C57D622"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of allocated
			 funds</header><text>Each Department facility receiving an allocation of funds
			 under this section shall use such funds for the purpose described in subsection
			 (a), including the establishment or improvement of the following:</text>
					<paragraph id="H965BEB0919D44B77A3551C3D04662D00"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Programs that
			 treat veterans with post-traumatic stress disorder and a substance use disorder
			 through a systematic integration of treatment for such disorders.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H51477FFDDFA14FCBBBE3BD19C8B4E9C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Programs that
			 treat veterans with substance use disorders through the development of
			 substance use disorder intervention strategies, including strategies developed
			 in collaboration with the families of veterans.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HB37712E448E14B24AB8300D76CEE5EB0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Peer outreach
			 programs that—</text>
						<subparagraph id="HB98E9BDCF83D4957B516D2B4019736BC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>re-engage veterans
			 of Operation Iraqi Freedom and Operation Enduring Freedom who miss multiple
			 appointments for treatment of post-traumatic stress disorder or a substance use
			 disorder; and</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3BF56EB0CC7E49BFAA705FFCBFB5C900"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are
			 conducted—</text>
							<clause id="H0CB51ADD4231447EA55F9288A776E06"><enum>(i)</enum><text>through
			 readjustment counseling centers;</text>
							</clause><clause id="HFA4EF89EF60A446F9043BACA3E38264"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in
			 tandem with efforts of community-based outpatient clinics and post-traumatic
			 stress disorder and substance use disorder treatment teams based in Department
			 of Veterans Affairs medical centers; and</text>
							</clause><clause id="HF9AE33E2F4E541A7AFF489352F030200"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>with appropriate
			 regard for patient privacy.</text>
							</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC406855859A444CDA466EF1EC1DDEB46"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Collaboration
			 between urgent care clinicians at Department of Veterans Affairs medical
			 centers and substance use disorder and post-traumatic stress disorder treatment
			 professionals to ensure expedited referral of veterans who are diagnosed with
			 post-traumatic stress disorder or a substance use disorder.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H4FD552EEEC714FF99D5154EEA8BB75DB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Programs of
			 treatment or services for veterans with substance use disorders and
			 post-traumatic stress disorder that utilize innovative and flexible scheduling
			 of treatment and services by emphasizing scheduling of group meetings or
			 appointments in the evening and on weekends.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H99BCB18688294F30BFE0661364BC1BEC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Evidence-based
			 treatment of post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use disorders.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1F052AF0C1D24478A0CFAC488CAAEFC7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not
			 later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary
			 shall submit to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the Senate and the
			 Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the House of Representatives a report setting
			 forth the programs and facilities for which funds have been allocated under
			 this section as of the date of the report.</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="H7F743241BA7242D5A6413F04AF614008"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Funding</header>
					<paragraph id="H057911AF1BA74659838957A9E2D89FA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>In carrying out the program described in this section,
			 the Secretary shall allocate for each of fiscal years 2008, 2009, and 2010,
			 from funds available to the Department for medical care in such fiscal year, an
			 amount equal to not less than $50,000,000 to carry out the program.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HFCF90CFF35014E9AA674A4C81C8390B3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minimum
			 funding</header><text>In allocating amounts under paragraph (1), the Secretary
			 shall ensure that, after funds are allocated under this section for a fiscal
			 year, the total expenditure for programs of the Department relating to the
			 treatment of post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use disorders is not
			 less than $50,000,000 in excess of the baseline amount in that fiscal
			 year.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H2C5AC2EB8792416487D95331B41E9015"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Baseline</header><text>For
			 purposes of paragraph (2), the baseline amount is the amount of the total
			 expenditures on programs of the Department relating to the treatment of
			 post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use disorders for the most recent
			 fiscal year for which final expenditure amounts are known (except for amounts
			 made available to carry out this section), adjusted to reflect any subsequent
			 increase in applicable costs to deliver such programs.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HDDA9B3D0C47449468E5981F3FE522F4"><enum>105.</enum><header>National centers
			 of excellence on post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use
			 disorders</header>
				<subsection id="H4600650208EE4649B59B6DD86DC2E317"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/73">chapter 73</external-xref> of title 38, United States
			 Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE01A795DFDEE47B084AEBB5276E0C77C" style="USC">
						<section id="H6ADB7EB84AC748FCBD004B5DD8E645DF"><enum>7330A.</enum><header>National
				centers of excellence on post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use
				disorders</header>
							<subsection id="HD137F1F348B74EFF93917516ABF2C14"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of
				Centers</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H721904E9E5754A4389B114939233F888"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall
				establish not less than six national centers of excellence on post-traumatic
				stress disorder and substance use disorders.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H61DF187112D8494B8B4F4E43461099C3" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The purpose of the centers
				established under this section is to serve as Department facilities that
				provide comprehensive inpatient treatment and recovery services for veterans
				newly diagnosed with both post-traumatic stress disorder and a substance use
				disorder.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF2B290D9071F406F96E0A40230656154"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Location</header><text>Each
				center established in accordance with subsection (a) shall be located at a
				medical center of the Department that—</text>
								<paragraph id="H79E72B39F11F4B88BB00636F0922D68"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provides inpatient
				care;</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H1FCF57CC76E5474BB323006704EF316D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is geographically
				situated in an area with a high number of veterans that have been diagnosed
				with both post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use disorder; and</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H4DC5B9D1EA9748B4973E162EDEE8EDC6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>is capable of
				treating post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use disorders.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H750D82C0869C40A4971FC64F78D9B1BD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Process of
				referral and transition to step down diagnosis rehabilitation treatment
				programs</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a process to refer and aid
				the transition of veterans from the national centers of excellence on
				post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use disorders established pursuant
				to subsection (a) to programs that provide step down rehabilitation treatment
				for individuals with post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use
				disorders.</text>
							</subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</subsection><subsection id="H2458D47E4BA04CC7BB738D07C8E1C2EF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical
			 amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 73 of
			 such title is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 7330 the
			 following new item:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBC459D53F1114927A2DC32005734E03F" style="OLC">
						<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
							<toc-entry level="section">7330A. National centers of excellence on
				post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use
				disorders.</toc-entry>
						</toc>
						<after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</subsection></section><section id="H2342AAF0C5F24FF283F881E4EB0057B4"><enum>106.</enum><header>Report on
			 residential mental health care facilities of the Veterans Health
			 Administration</header>
				<subsection id="H76F5E21B14194092B9EE45BCA053898E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than six
			 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans
			 Affairs shall, acting through the Office of the Medical Inspector of the
			 Department of Veterans Affairs—</text>
					<paragraph id="H8D167A9AA95D4CECA8C781406900C0ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct a review of all residential mental
			 health care facilities, including domiciliary facilities, of the Veterans
			 Health Administration; and</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H9BD144452264411792007024ED3F967"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to the
			 Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans'
			 Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on the review.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD5D1EE60730B4C388CA942ED36EFF412"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The
			 report required by subsection (a)(2) shall include the following:</text>
					<paragraph id="H15C6CC578F53442BA2A32492883FB28D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A
			 description of the availability of care in residential mental health care
			 facilities in each Veterans Integrated Service Network (VISN).</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H3E3B9B63EBFB48C3A249020730CDA346"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An assessment of
			 the supervision and support provided in the residential mental health care
			 facilities of the Veterans Health Administration.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H5C208D9C26234E9DB8E105593FA56550"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The ratio of staff
			 members at each residential mental health care facility to patients at such
			 facility.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HF4B1E9AACA3D4ED99FAFF8A950E8F838"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An assessment of
			 the appropriateness of rules and procedures for the prescription and
			 administration of medications to patients in such residential mental health
			 care facilities.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HDFBBBC5A14F54F84909C042E96E8887F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A
			 description of the protocols at each residential mental health care facility
			 for handling missed appointments.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6317485C9DAD4485AA54C1EF25C1A1BC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any
			 recommendations the Secretary considers appropriate for improvements to such
			 residential mental health care facilities and the care provided in such
			 facilities.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6E06B9CC73F9411D896B8CC2F16DDCA6"><enum>107.</enum><header>Tribute to
			 Justin Bailey</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This title is
			 enacted in tribute to Justin Bailey, who, after returning to the United States
			 from service as a member of the Armed Forces in Operation Iraqi Freedom, died
			 in a domiciliary facility of the Department of Veterans Affairs while receiving
			 care for post-traumatic stress disorder and a substance use disorder.</text>
			</section></title><title id="H7555AC573B9A46B49DE46FDC8F3210FE"><enum>II</enum><header>Mental health
			 accessibility enhancements</header>
			<section id="H90399A0E56D247D3930072414DF74DBD"><enum>201.</enum><header>Pilot program
			 on peer outreach and support for veterans and use of community mental health
			 centers and Indian Health Service facilities</header>
				<subsection id="H49BBAC064C914168932ED58CAB1E8F4F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Pilot program
			 required</header><text>Commencing not later than 180 days after the date of the
			 enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall carry out a
			 pilot program to assess the feasability and advisability of providing to
			 veterans of Operation Iraqi Freedom and Operation Enduring Freedom, and, in
			 particular, veterans who served in such operations as a member of the National
			 Guard or Reserve, the following:</text>
					<paragraph id="H852C45BECDAE42438440E212F6A8A0F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Peer outreach
			 services.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HC5C242DA3F9548DCA65F8F35DB947DEE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Peer support
			 services.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H80F73A675C474C418301DA2D00A181DB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Readjustment
			 counseling services described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1712A">section 1712A</external-xref> of title 38, United States
			 Code.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H32B137287372424EB7CDED630095F2FC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Other Mental
			 health services.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8539932D52FA4F73899256214C881C00"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Provision of
			 certain services</header><text>In providing services described in paragraphs
			 (3) and (4) of subsection (a) under the pilot program to veterans who reside in
			 rural areas and do not have adequate access through the Department of Veterans
			 Affairs to the services described in such paragraphs, the Secretary shall,
			 acting through the Office of Rural Health, provide such services as
			 follows:</text>
					<paragraph id="H1D94926A00A34A5C893D955DD282E227"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Through community
			 health centers under contracts or other agreements for the provision of such
			 services that are entered into for purposes of the pilot program.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H3E25840B681B455B9F97BAAFFC3DD800"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Through the Indian
			 Health Service pursuant to a memorandum of understanding entered into by the
			 Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretary of Health and Human Services
			 for purposes of the pilot program.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H55AE2AFDE82A44C19DFA72A6886E0039"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The
			 pilot program shall be carried out during the three-year period beginning on
			 the date of the commencement of the pilot program.</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="HB8B5C47BC93E45A89978DEE33BAAF072"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Program
			 locations</header>
					<paragraph id="H0BA3774ACCB042B79C851818B346317C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The pilot program shall be carried out in at least two
			 Veterans Integrated Service Networks (VISN) selected by the Secretary for
			 purposes of the pilot program.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H50F2DEADAA794A72B0DF709319BCCEC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rural geographic
			 locations</header><text>At least two of the locations selected shall be in
			 rural geographic locations that lack access to comprehensive mental health
			 services through the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H899CBFCFC0A844F4B241CC4C0C36D97"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Participation in
			 program</header><text>Each community mental health center or facility of the
			 Indian Health Service participating in the pilot program under subsection (b)
			 shall—</text>
					<paragraph id="HA651FED9DBD94CC984DA67E4BBEDCE2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide the
			 services described in paragraphs (3) and (4) of subsection (a) to eligible
			 veterans, including, to the extent practicable, through the utilization of
			 telehealth services for the provision of such services;</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HFC4FF2BD7B0145B6BBEA3EB6251D3F57"><enum>(2)</enum><text>utilize best
			 practices and technologies; and</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HA14C0669CF7442D4B485B34F739A77D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>meet such other
			 requirements as the Secretary shall require.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD31AA00C596A4142A9ADA4981DC1FC00"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Compliance with
			 Department protocols</header><text>Each community mental health center or
			 facility of the Indian Health Service participating in the pilot program under
			 subsection (b) shall comply with applicable protocols of the Department before
			 incurring any liability on behalf of the Department for the provision of
			 services as part of the pilot program.</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="H6E2096A4E07748D486B69701C860493B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Provision of
			 clinical information</header><text>Each community mental health center or
			 facility of the Indian Health Service participating in the pilot program under
			 subsection (b) shall provide the Secretary with such clinical information on
			 each veteran for whom such health center or facility provides mental health
			 services under the pilot program as the Secretary shall require.</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="HE7C225DAF8854AD9990316537C295823"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Training</header>
					<paragraph id="HC34209E4DF1D497CBDA46EFA8C99ACE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Training of
			 veterans</header><text>As part of the pilot program, the Secretary shall carry
			 out a national program of training for veterans described in subsection (a) to
			 provide the services described in paragraphs (1) and (2) of such
			 subsection.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H0F03CBA2FFBD452F86F0C4B481C8F6BC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Training of
			 clinicians</header>
						<subparagraph id="H6799733450434117A6C85144B03003DC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct a training program for
			 clinicians of community mental health centers or Indian Health Service
			 facilities participating in the pilot program under subsection (b) to ensure
			 that such clinicians can provide the services described in paragraphs (3) and
			 (4) of subsection (a) in a manner that accounts for factors that are unique to
			 the experiences of veterans who served on active duty in Operation Iraqi
			 Freedom or Operation Enduring Freedom (including their combat and military
			 training experiences).</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51B66A181D9D468AACFF95FF101D00A0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Participation in
			 training</header><text>Each community mental health center or facility of the
			 Indian Health Service participating in the pilot program under subsection (b)
			 shall participate in the training program conducted pursuant to subparagraph
			 (A).</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6D1C98031FD348BDBC986D6079C854D7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Annual
			 reports</header><text>Each community mental health center or facility of the
			 Indian Health Service participating in the pilot program under subsection (b)
			 shall submit to the Secretary on an annual basis a report containing, with
			 respect to the provision of services under subsection (b) and for the last full
			 calendar year ending before the submission of such report—</text>
					<paragraph id="HB7AF5F711C1B4CE686B301D74BCA8C2C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number
			 of—</text>
						<subparagraph id="H81D956251F0F4DDCA6D422CDE76546A2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>veterans served;
			 and</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A1D69C10DF84E6989FADBDD301C0007"><enum>(B)</enum><text>courses of
			 treatment provided; and</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7A2DAF5E6B864B0AA3A6B2FD618C0001"><enum>(2)</enum><text>demographic
			 information for such services, diagnoses, and courses of treatment.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4496AD9D18BE42D7A256002F26A827AA"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In
			 this section:</text>
					<paragraph id="HF18ADBF56891485D8866F9FF339CFD5B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>community mental health center</term> has the meaning given such term in
			 <external-xref legal-doc="regulation" parsable-cite="cfr/42/410.2">section 410.2</external-xref> of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the day
			 before the date of the enactment of this Act).</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HFB3CA72DBC0B454AB74FA32100E01831"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>eligible veteran</term> means a veteran in need of mental health services
			 who—</text>
						<subparagraph id="H07AC28EC1001472DA2E14EA78FCC6F00"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is enrolled in the
			 Department of Veterans Affairs health care system; and</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D15DF86CFB44C80A89E00039E9992AD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has received a
			 referral from a health professional of the Veterans Health Administration to a
			 community mental health center or to a facility of the Indian Health Service
			 for purposes of the pilot program.</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5BB59CF57FAA487998DAE1AE3BAA7715"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>Indian Health Service</term> means the organization established by
			 section 601(a) of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act (25 U.S.C.
			 1661(a)).</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2227F04EFA8746E9B1A1D5284831B43C"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Authorization of
			 appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated such sums
			 as may be necessary to carry out the provisions of this section.</text>
				</subsection></section></title><title id="H2B84E133B0C2415A9684062BC572CE65"><enum>III</enum><header>Research</header>
			<section id="H37CF48AE04C94CD595C6DD96BDA55BDF"><enum>301.</enum><header>Research
			 program on comorbid post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use
			 disorders</header>
				<subsection id="HB151B38C5D4341F1B74FB85BAEC847C8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program
			 required</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall carry out a
			 program of research into comorbid post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) and
			 substance use disorder.</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="H2F65682F719C4FFD8D8DEC00BBFF12A3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Discharge
			 through National Center for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder</header><text>The
			 research program required by subsection (a) shall be carried out and overseen
			 by the National Center for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder. In carrying out the
			 program, the Center shall—</text>
					<paragraph id="H16A9D084231A4641A7DD7600D35C3106"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop protocols
			 and goals with respect to research under the program; and</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H94A4501ADE0F4855A3FA53F5E2AA218F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinate
			 research, data collection, and data dissemination under the program.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H02EBE49C7FA24E8386ABB6308879C5A6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Research</header><text>The
			 program of research required by subsection (a) shall address the
			 following:</text>
					<paragraph id="H16396FC39F464607BE05225FEEFA09FE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Comorbid
			 post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use disorder.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H743F41B6BA6448AE8D5B7E564467B121"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The systematic
			 integration of treatment for post-traumatic stress disorder with treatment for
			 substance use disorder.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H7F352B5191A74EE900DAAD62F43558"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The
			 development of protocols to evaluate care of veterans with comorbid
			 post-traumatic stress disorder and substance use disorder and to facilitate
			 cumulative clinical progress of such veterans over time.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H92671B193F0845EBAFF4EDBEB584B77"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Funding</header>
					<paragraph id="H8A0396A245224F1EB16C7E35BC176406"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization of
			 appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated for the
			 Department of Veterans Affairs for each of fiscal years 2008 through 2011,
			 $2,000,000 to carry out this section.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H7282E642B20744C780D5BAA1E48BD8E6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>Amounts
			 authorized to be appropriated by paragraph (1) shall be made available to the
			 National Center on Posttraumatic Stress Disorder for the purpose specified in
			 that paragraph.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H0229147632A44CA1831851F605016C73"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Supplement not
			 supplant</header><text>Any amount made available to the National Center on
			 Posttraumatic Stress Disorder for a fiscal year under paragraph (2) is in
			 addition to any other amounts made available to the National Center on
			 Posttraumatic Stress Disorder for such year under any other provision of
			 law.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H02557DC40CC94144B76897006768CEBD"><enum>302.</enum><header>Extension of
			 authorization for Special Committee on Post-Traumatic Stress
			 Disorder</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 110(e)(2) of
			 the Veterans' Health Care Act of 1984 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1712A">38 U.S.C. 1712A</external-xref> note) is amended by
			 striking <quote>through 2008</quote> and inserting <quote>through
			 2012</quote>.</text>
			</section></title><title id="H00F9E2C4409E49A3A4B070FE707795BF"><enum>IV</enum><header>Assistance for
			 families of veterans</header>
			<section id="H93AF8FF672F6438BB5A1A8B88DD824A2"><enum>401.</enum><header>Clarification
			 of authority of Secretary of Veterans Affairs to provide mental health services
			 to families of veterans</header>
				<subsection id="H0A187945B084489891DAD1702D8D731F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1701(5)(B) of
			 title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text>
					<paragraph id="H0235FE7647FA4E12B96546C027A3409F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>marriage and family
			 counseling,</quote> after <quote>professional counseling,</quote>; and</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HFE19A48A5CCE446CB6C0A5A6FC7761AC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>as may be essential to</quote> and inserting <quote>as the Secretary
			 considers appropriate for</quote>.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3F74CD2D83FA4934B5F61DC2D63002B0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Location</header><text>Paragraph
			 (5) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1701">section 1701</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, shall not be construed to
			 prevent the Secretary of Veterans Affairs from providing services described in
			 subparagraph (B) of such paragraph to individuals described in such
			 subparagraph in Readjustment Counseling Centers, Department of Veterans Affairs
			 medical centers, community-based outpatient clinics, or in such other
			 facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs as the Secretary considers
			 necessary.</text>
				</subsection></section><section id="H2F235A8BA372420D995289B885F400C4" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>402.</enum><header>Pilot program on
			 provision of readjustment and transition assistance to veterans and their
			 families in cooperation with Vet Centers</header>
				<subsection id="HCB3EA73DEE8F4A0A8F53C71BDA243503"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Pilot
			 program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of
			 Veterans Affairs shall carry out, through a non-Department of Veterans Affairs
			 entity, a pilot program to assess the feasability and advisability of providing
			 readjustment and transition assistance described in subsection (b) to veterans
			 and their families in cooperation with centers under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1712A">section 1712A</external-xref> of title 38,
			 United States Code (commonly referred to as <quote>Vet Centers</quote>).</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="HC763B8731C8F465193CF4C7600315BFB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Readjustment and
			 transition assistance</header><text>Readjustment and transition assistance
			 described in this subsection is assistance as follows:</text>
					<paragraph commented="no" id="H43CD895B013341219DF6EBB84CECB9DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Readjustment and
			 transition assistance that is preemptive, proactive, and
			 principle-centered.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HE772D4EC227243BDA873CFEB7897E300"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Assistance and
			 training for veterans and their families in coping with the challenges
			 associated with making the transition from military to civilian life.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9E7F23A3A6044E529390941D3B80FBE1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Non-Department
			 of Veterans Affairs entity</header>
					<paragraph id="H703AD73004EC415EB797EB71166100DF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out the pilot program through
			 any for-profit or non-profit organization selected by the Secretary for
			 purposes of the pilot program that has demonstrated expertise and experience in
			 the provision of assistance and training described in subsection (b).</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H0BE561B4F3074A3AB197FC00588FB8BB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contract or
			 agreement</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out the pilot program through
			 a non-Department entity described in paragraph (1) pursuant to a contract or
			 other agreement entered into by the Secretary and the entity for purposes of
			 the pilot program.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE06B1780DC26416EA6D000E81DFE00A4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duration of
			 pilot program</header><text>The pilot program shall be carried out during the
			 three-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, and may
			 be carried out for additional one-year periods thereafter.</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="HB826C8CE98F24B4893A1465CBE33ADF2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Location of
			 pilot program</header>
					<paragraph id="HA07B2CFAE2A443228D61B7C491145039"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall provide
			 assistance under the pilot program in cooperation with 10 centers described in
			 subsection (a) designated by the Secretary for purposes of the pilot
			 program.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H078E361F18B542C787009BC658003EBA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Designations</header><text>In
			 designating centers described in subsection (a) for purposes of the pilot
			 program, the Secretary shall designate centers so as to provide a balanced
			 geographical representation of such centers throughout the United States,
			 including the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, tribal
			 lands, and other territories and possessions of the United States.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6ED580E9A63A48A6BEC9652D70F177B5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Participation of
			 centers</header><text>A center described in subsection (a) that is designated
			 under subsection (e) for participation in the pilot program shall participate
			 in the pilot program by promoting awareness of the assistance and training
			 available to veterans and their families through—</text>
					<paragraph id="H02E10BB3D08B4A638E00AEC3BD00084C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the facilities and
			 other resources of such center;</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HBDC3B9A6B3E74CAFB6866C9C11A3601D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the non-Department
			 of Veterans Affairs entity selected pursuant to subsection (c); and</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H2C453E9E6FC64AF7A0DFC34B129FF0C2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>other appropriate
			 mechanisms.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H50BB61EE37BF470890C8A08409D53494"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Additional
			 support</header><text>In carrying out the pilot program, the Secretary of
			 Veterans Affairs may enter into contracts or other agreements, in addition to
			 the contract or agreement described in subsection (c), with such other
			 non-Department of Veterans Affairs entities meeting the requirements of
			 subsection (c) as the Secretary considers appropriate for purposes of the pilot
			 program.</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="HFC1F2A60052742E5A557EC94F5754EF5"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Report on pilot
			 program</header>
					<paragraph id="H5E4BB8EAAD9D46D8BBA644A6E9AE4973"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report
			 required</header><text>Not later than six months after the date of the
			 conclusion of the pilot program, the Secretary shall submit to the
			 congressional veterans affairs committees a report on the pilot program.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H9A02198BFC314C9E9BC1F79CB540D62"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each
			 report under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text>
						<subparagraph id="H800F49E21C5048F7B60844006F623094"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A description of
			 the activities under the pilot program as of the date of such report, including
			 the number of veterans and families provided assistance under the pilot program
			 and the scope and nature of the assistance so provided.</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9CA22BDAA304391A6FE278892B69F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A current
			 assessment of the effectiveness of the pilot program.</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA9D7D88D29440428D9F37433EA83CF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any recommendations
			 that the Secretary considers appropriate for the extension or expansion of the
			 pilot program.</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H27BC2B1D6F704890B6CB221DFB63453"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Congressional
			 veterans affairs committees defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term
			 <term>congressional veterans affairs committees</term> means—</text>
						<subparagraph id="H96308288605F4EA500AF38D502E1E840"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committees on
			 Veterans' Affairs and Appropriations of the Senate; and</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03B81A74B29C42698B9D691EAF270086"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committees on
			 Veterans' Affairs and Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H54D2A3BB683A4448BF2739002EE058CF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of
			 appropriations</header>
					<paragraph id="H109900D710B64929BFA2C2C1770000A3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated for the Department
			 of Veterans Affairs for each of fiscal years 2008 through 2010 $1,000,000 to
			 carry out this section.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4207AA1CFDDB458BBF27002600002B83"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>Amounts
			 authorized to be appropriated by paragraph (1) shall remain available until
			 expended.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section></title></legis-body>
</bill>


