<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB86857A282FC4441ACDFB1D2A23F5946" public-private="public"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">111th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 627</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Truth in Lending Act to establish fair and transparent practices relating to the extension of credit under an open end consumer credit plan, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="HF95445E825D64218A216F1AA28783F51" style="OLC"> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H67A6540204D843DD8F71874DE367B716" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Credit Cardholders’ Bill of Rights Act of 2009</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> 
<section id="HE52CC6D72620426D80F35C730DA5B195"><enum>2.</enum><header>Credit cards on terms consumers can repay</header> 
<subsection id="H3DD2775688C74E7E90D8AD8E1C7A2991"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Retroactive rate increases and universal default limited</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Chapter 2 of the Truth in Lending Act (15 U.S.C. 1631 et seq.) is amended by inserting after section 127A the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35077E12AA794BCE90BD918D9A00191A" style="USC"> 
<section id="H7551B8A1F74F44E7BD054CFC8149C281"><enum>127B.</enum><header>Additional requirements for credit card accounts under an open end consumer credit plan</header> 
<subsection id="H5CB669D6DBD74C2785BE7E28CF94DEEB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Retroactive rate increases and universal default limited</header> 
<paragraph id="H866B29C5D7CF4969AACDF28F6EBC236F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (b), no creditor may increase any annual percentage rate of interest applicable to the existing balance on a credit card account of the consumer under an open end consumer credit plan.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2F5A8B8F5EDA4447BC145327CFB66054"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Existing balance defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection and subsections (b) and (c), the term <term>existing balance</term> means the amount owed on a consumer credit card account as of the end of the 7th day after the creditor provides notice of an increase in the annual percentage rate in accordance with subsection (c).</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H35C8975B56FD45058236D47AEBA04549"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Treatment of existing balances following rate increase</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a creditor increases any annual percentage rate of interest applicable to the credit card account of a consumer under an open end consumer credit plan and there is an existing balance in the account to which such increase may not apply, the creditor shall allow the consumer to repay the existing balance using a method provided by the creditor which is at least as beneficial to the consumer as 1 of the following methods:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H437F56FB02E04EE68895FD4DEA76D986"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An amortization period for the existing balance of at least 5 years starting from the date on which the increased annual percentage rate went into effect.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H14CB790AA2E4427180FEC20F95F17E75"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The percentage of the existing balance that was included in the required minimum periodic payment before the rate increase cannot be more than doubled.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5A82D87B43EF42B08FD0C2B5512C72C5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation on certain fees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9D091AB2617D436F9B33AA76258B61FD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a creditor increases any annual percentage rate of interest applicable on a credit card account of the consumer under an open end consumer credit plan; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF79531949C334E47A4BF69430DB0CF0F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the creditor is prohibited by this section from applying the increased rate to an existing balance,</text> </subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">the creditor may not assess any fee or charge based solely on the existing balance.</continuation-text></paragraph></subsection></section> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HC06749BCEA254CCD8F121418175760EC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exceptions to the amendment made by subsection <enum-in-header>(a)</enum-in-header></header><text>Section 127B of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after subsection (a) (as added by subsection (a)) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEA495F0F34DD4117A86E5FF70DB67C47" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H78E0C6FCB14D49B080CE14760E78667A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exceptions</header> 
<paragraph id="H8B1EC6787F4B4CC5B78313DB220804A6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A creditor may increase any annual percentage rate of interest applicable to the existing balance on a credit card account of the consumer under an open end consumer credit plan only under the following circumstances:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5DC0DF7E330342589B7BA3E346EDEE26"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Change in index</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The increase is due solely to the operation of an index that is not under the creditor's control and is available to the general public.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H08B2E1511A344554A216FBC8E99C8DDC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Expiration of promotional rate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The increase is due solely to the expiration of a promotional rate.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA8ED3043981541C7B2AB87541B566DBB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Failure to comply with workout plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The increase is due solely to the fact the consumer failed to comply with a negotiated workout plan with the creditor.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H04A97BED248A4DA5A1FA68503FAD9C96"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Payment not received during 30-day grace period after due date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The increase is due solely to the fact that any consumer's minimum payment has not been received within 30 days after the due date for such minimum payment.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H35E6CD5350FC45C09A29C3B638319AAE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation on increases due to failure to comply with workout plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding paragraph (1)(C), the annual percentage rate in effect with respect to each category of transactions for a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan after the increase permitted under such subsection due to the failure of a consumer to comply with a workout plan may not exceed the annual percentage applicable to such category of transactions on the day before the effective date of the workout plan.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE45B57F15C4F444EABBDF344436ADC8B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Standards required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall prescribe, by regulation, standards—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H529E05511B8749FD92F6B6A81FF8872A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for entering into any workout plan applicable to any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H840D3FE62CA341CDBCED148E987E3E11"><enum>(B)</enum><text>governing any such workout plan.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H9BAA637FEC70408C91FEF7F6E15A8950"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Advance notice of rate increases and significant contract changes</header><text>Section 127B of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after subsection (b) (as added by subsection (b)) the following new subsections:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H815823962DDA40FDA95C289CCAAF7788" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H3EEE4700F2CE4171A10751157EA941BC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Advance notice of rate increases</header> 
<paragraph id="HA5B53D4A7C1044E79858C0FFB53C95EC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan, no increase in any annual percentage rate of interest (other than an increase described in subsection (b)(1)(A)) may take effect unless the creditor provides a written notice to the consumer at least 45 days before the increase takes effect which fully describes the changes in the annual percentage rate, in a complete and conspicuous manner, and the extent to which such increase would apply to an existing balance.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDBE3759AE4C14E53A4C0243DA9D07CBF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation on rate increase notices within first year</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except in the case of an increase described in subparagraph (B), (C), or (D) of subsection (b)(1), no written notice under paragraph (1) of an increase in any annual percentage rate of interest on any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan (for which notice is required under such paragraph) shall be effective before the end of the 1-year period beginning when the account is opened.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE75AE0ED7EAB4027887E30A3752CE6CB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Minimum term for promotional rates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a promotional rate, no written notice under paragraph (1) of an increase in any annual percentage rate of interest on any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan shall be effective before the end of a 6-month period beginning from the date the promotional rate takes effect.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD908BBFFCE464316B34BEE2CB333B02F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Advance notice of account closure</header> 
<paragraph id="H76B2755D13284E24AFB06A4B28ABFF63"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan, a creditor may not close such account unless the creditor provides a written notice to the consumer at least 30 days before the closure takes place, and which notifies the consumer—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H22D8FB13258547AF8B0558A4673397C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>of the reason the account is being closed;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBD6D3D3CB63E47B291F58DD587B01824"><enum>(B)</enum><text>of any recourse that the consumer may take to prevent the account from being closed;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF6C4B3442EE14894A8A1844368A22093"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> of any program under which the consumer may repay the balance on the account over a period of time; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE80E652A60014853AC98B8D512C4D24D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>that if the consumer’s account is closed, it may have an impact on the consumer’s credit score.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8D57963161E343B283E77B7D37F54756"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The requirements of paragraph (1) shall not apply in the case of a consumer request that the creditor close such account.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF1211B6BD1354CAE8D34989AA8C9531E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Advance notice of significant contract changes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan, no significant change to the contract (such as any fee) may take effect unless the creditor provides a written notice of at least 45 days before the change takes effect which fully describes the changes in the contract, in a complete and conspicuous manner.</text> </subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H0841E0260D3B4B6392EDFCDC6519B26B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for chapter 2 of the Truth in Lending Act (15 U.S.C. 1631 et seq.) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 127A the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4480A53CD6B2482390302F36D4DA5D82" style="USC"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">127B. Additional requirements for credit card accounts under an open end consumer credit plan.</toc-entry> </toc> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection></section> 
<section id="HB12D26CE6DD6443D80B4EAE43277E538"><enum>3.</enum><header>Additional provisions regarding account features, terms, and pricing</header> 
<subsection id="HCFF7A90504324585899F22B5FC42B298"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Double cycle billing prohibited</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 127B of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after subsection (d) (as added by section 2(c)) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD61812D7EC464836B9D8C1A7E6F69AC3" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H74F580ADFDA349AC8066BFE08C627934"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Double cycle billing</header> 
<paragraph id="H4BF956BE662849D690C0328ED5A60789"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No finance charge may be imposed by a creditor with respect to any balance on a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan that is based on balances for days in billing cycles preceding the most recent billing cycle as a result of the loss of any grace period.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9FE10F64E53C44A4AB381237A703FB22"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (1) shall not apply so as to prohibit a creditor from—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H168C97F3A25E4FC9B9EBEC7DA49EE0F0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">adjusting finance charges following the return of a payment for insufficient funds; or</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2ACAA6CB25B941F181772B094B840339"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">adjusting finance charges following resolution of a billing error dispute.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H66EA15D3EDD04DA19E5B226192DF7D5B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Grace period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>grace period</term> means, with respect to any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan, the time period, if any, provided by the creditor within which any credit extended under such credit plan for purchases of goods or services may be repaid by the consumer without incurring a finance charge.</text> </paragraph></subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H1D0CE241771D4499A22EBB029388C48E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitations relating to account balances attributable only to accrued interest</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 127B is amended by inserting after subsection (e) (as added by subsection (a)) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2CEDD3D021884211A186B8366FB99162" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HBB33F2DCD05247359228AD0B1DC565E5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitations relating to account balances attributable only to accrued interest</header> 
<paragraph id="HFCB322937E204146953147E8EC0BD945"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the outstanding balance on a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan at the end of a billing period represents an amount attributable only to interest accrued during the preceding billing period on an outstanding balance that was fully repaid during the preceding billing period—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3E6C1EF4712940BE91B002F6C30954D2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no fee may be imposed or collected in connection with such balance attributable only to interest before such end of the billing period; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0EE2BFADC6E34B9BB8B6C3C7B531D367"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any failure to make timely repayments of the balance attributable only to interest before such end of the billing period shall not constitute a default on the account.</text> </subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">Such balance remains a legally binding debt obligation.</continuation-text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HFE4C426CEF994719B4E1C9C31F915FA9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not be construed as affecting—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H84DAD3A629294D43A855984F84A8D565"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the consumer’s obligation to pay any accrued interest on a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan; or</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H028F9623175A4DFC93CBCC314C734B0A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the accrual of interest on the outstanding balance on any such account in accordance with the terms of the account and this title.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HD28599ADC6C6450F8F706EA6F6A04242"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Access to payoff balance information</header><text>Section 127B of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after subsection (f) (as added by subsection (b)) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3550926059CC4952B95E6D7A042B74BB" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HA0D1751C16D34F969E984E83D1F8C9FD"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Payoff balance information</header> 
<paragraph id="HD18648023D0848C4A028467D8671BAE0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each periodic statement provided by a creditor to a consumer with respect to a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan shall contain the toll-free telephone number, Internet address, and website at which the consumer may request the payoff balance on the account.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF894FA75ACB14230A5E9630A23FB834F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Small issuers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding paragraph (1), in the case of any credit card issuer which issues fewer than 50,000 credit cards in conjunction with credit card accounts under open end consumer credit plans, each periodic statement provided by such a creditor to a consumer with respect to any such credit card account shall contain the toll-free telephone number, Internet address, or website at which the consumer may request the payoff balance on the account.</text> </paragraph></subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H3230EE6981014C6DB62CCB9F05549EB8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consumer right To reject card after notice is provided of open account</header><text>Section 127B of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after subsection (g) (as added by subsection (c)) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1927B9790CD64885B2FE99F42D007B3A" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HA79FAD00183E4177BAB286C041FBD3AB"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Consumer right To reject card after notice of new account is provided to consumer reporting agency</header> 
<paragraph id="HED6DEC56C70C4A47893081A0B58BDD2A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A creditor shall remove any information furnished to a consumer reporting agency (as defined in section 603) concerning the establishment of a newly opened credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan if the consumer has not used or activated the account and the consumer contacts the creditor within 45 days of the establishment of the account to close the account.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2CE546D925534C308288EEAE748707B0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (1) shall not be construed as prohibiting a creditor from furnishing information about any application for a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan or any inquiry about any such account to a consumer reporting agency (as so defined).</text> </paragraph></subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H6B4FE5FE8D324CEEB57C3F7140C2F9FB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of terms clarified</header><text>Section 127B of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after subsection (h) (as added by subsection (d)) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H21B567AFB547429285D89EF8EDC6EC54" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HF945C061DAA142C7A0383594FF8193FA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Use of terms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The following requirements shall apply with respect to the terms of any credit card account under any open end consumer credit plan:</text> 
<paragraph id="H7C2C7983DF814B1F87988B97D5A93925"><enum>(1)</enum><header><quote>Fixed</quote> rate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>fixed</term>, when appearing in conjunction with a reference to the annual percentage rate or interest rate applicable with respect to such account, may only be used to refer to an annual percentage rate or interest rate that will not change or vary for any reason over the period clearly and conspicuously specified in the terms of the account.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H49C7761755974350A8A63B781036654F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prime rate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>prime rate</term>, when appearing in any agreement or contract for any such account, may only be used to refer to the bank prime rate published in the Federal Reserve Statistical Release on selected interest rates (daily or weekly), and commonly referred to as the H.15 release (or any successor publication).</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7F4B5E406C1D4262987244703DE3D335"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Due date</header> 
<subparagraph id="H95EB60E918A84D4092B9544CC8D5EE8B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each periodic statement for any such account shall contain a date by which the next periodic payment on the account must be made to avoid a late fee or be considered a late payment, and any payment received by 5 p.m., local time at the location specified by the creditor for the receipt of payment, on such date shall be treated as a timely payment for all purposes.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAD7EF1ED480D4B809B87E604AC597617"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Certain electronic fund transfers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any payment with respect to any such account made by a consumer online to the website of the credit card issuer or by telephone directly to the credit card issuer before 5 p.m., local time at the location specified by the creditor for the receipt of payment, on any business day shall be credited to the consumer’s account that business day.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0A271A42E297418D98E393DA0E543A7C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Presumption of timely payment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any evidence provided by a consumer in the form of a receipt from the United States Postal Service or other common carrier indicating that a payment on a credit card account was sent to the issuer not less than 7 days before the due date contained in the periodic statement under subparagraph (A) for such payment shall create a presumption that such payment was made by the due date, which may be rebutted by the creditor for fraud or dishonesty on the part of the consumer with respect to the mailing date.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H7D814090F3AD4664BD4B05E6A7D29EF6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Payment allocations</header><text>Section 127B of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after subsection (i) (as added by subsection (e)) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6CADA89855AA4251AFF6B77C656C6A82" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HD202253CD30C49F3B05CE6DD4E80C797"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Payment allocations</header> 
<paragraph id="H3328C56446D5493F96A0D008DA668B89"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If 2 or more different annual percentage rates apply to different portions of an outstanding balance on a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan, the amount of any periodic payment in excess of the required minimum payment shall be allocated first to the balance with the highest annual percentage rate and any remaining portion is allocated to any other balance in descending order, based on the applicable annual percentage rate each portion of such balance bears, from the highest such rate to the lowest.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9F5A26028B2A49FE8B02E29E074C222E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clarification relating to certain deferred interest arrangements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A creditor may allocate the entire amount paid by the consumer in excess of the required minimum periodic payment to a balance on which interest is deferred during the 2 billing cycles immediately preceding the expiration of the period during which interest is deferred.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H77794DF1D1DC4FC9996680FAB26D71F0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prohibition on restricted grace periods under certain circumstances</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If, with respect to any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan, a creditor offers a time period in which to repay credit extended without incurring finance charges to cardholders who pay the balance in full, the creditor may not deny a consumer who takes advantage of a promotional rate balance or deferred interest rate balance offer with respect to such an account any such time period for repaying credit without incurring finance charges.</text> </paragraph></subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HA00FD3431F6C447E8EFE3ED7057B26FE"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Timely provision of periodic statements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 127B of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after subsection (j) (as added by subsection (f)) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H502589406A664C73911174ED5568B1A9" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HA65508CE0E68452DA7EFA3A4A1469C91"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Timely provision of periodic statements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each periodic statement with respect to a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan shall be sent by the creditor to the consumer not less than 21 calendar days before the due date identified in such statement for the next payment on the outstanding balance on such account, and section 163(a) shall be applied with respect to any such account by substituting <quote>21</quote> for <quote>fourteen</quote>.</text> </subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H36FAD453CCDF423D9E62C8F00FD91B7A"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Due dates</header><text>Section 127B of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after subsection (k) (as added by subsection (g)) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE99114F19FB84FFBA243B3BDB3D3FA16" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H651CD50553DA438DB6D84BA94096661B"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Due dates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the date established by a creditor as the date on which a periodic payment on a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan is due is a day on which mail is either not delivered to such creditor or is not accepted by the creditor for processing on such day, the creditor may not treat the receipt by the creditor of any such periodic payment by mail as of the next business day of the creditor as late for any purpose.</text> </subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HC6D75DB9964C4F319B1F0304453F7F84"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Availability of legitimate and accredited credit counseling</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System shall suggest appropriate guidelines for creditors to follow with respect to credit card accounts under open end consumer credit plans to supply consumer cardholders with information regarding the availability of legitimate and accredited credit counseling services.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H5DB340802CC34817B055D8E46778FD22"><enum>4.</enum><header>Consumer choice with respect to over-the-limit transactions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 127B of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after subsection (l) (as added by section 3(h)) the following new subsections:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD2D0072EC8984D74B423DF87DB1B69CC" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HC271DE89AFD244938896A6366C5DEA6D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Opt-in required for over-the-limit transactions if fees are imposed</header> 
<paragraph id="H4878910643944A2EBAAFA53A54F8D15E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan under which an over-the-limit-fee may be imposed by the creditor for any extension of credit in excess of the amount of credit authorized to be extended under such account, no such fee shall be charged unless the consumer has elected to permit the creditor, with respect to such account, to complete transactions involving the extension of credit, with respect to such account, in excess of the amount of credit authorized. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8A14B4813CC540AE942BBA7F92802CD3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disclosure by creditor</header><text>No election by a consumer under paragraph (1) shall take effect unless the consumer, before making such election, received a notice from the creditor of any over-the-limit fee in the form and manner, and at the time, determined by the Board.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD411C030F2D14C4E9918C4A825B4AFC8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Form of election</header><text>A consumer may make the election referred to in paragraph (1) orally or in writing. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1974083A6F954A72B0B6F5752994C7F7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Time of election</header><text>A consumer may make the election referred to in paragraph (1) at any time and it shall be effective until the election is revoked by the consumer orally or in writing.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE3BF660CE95B47318AB30C7B536F76FC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Regulations</header> 
<subparagraph id="HF8B595ACCDED45059956BEE788A398C7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall issue regulations allowing for the completion of over-the-limit transactions that for operational reasons exceed the credit limit by a de minimis amount, even where the cardholder has not made an election under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5E6032ED0B5441ABAC6E01FB01A4091E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Subject to no fee limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The regulations prescribed under subparagraph (A) shall not allow for the imposition of any fee or any rate increase based on the permitted over-the-limit transactions with respect to the account of any cardholder who has not made the election in paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H766A40EC3C264F50BBA786DA9DDF1138"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Disclosures</header><text>The Board shall prescribe regulations governing any disclosure under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H83422A8DA8424E74B54C03834097AB70"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Over-the-limit fee restrictions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan, an over-the-limit fee may be imposed only once during a billing cycle if, on the last day of such billing cycle, the credit limit on the account is exceeded, and an over-the-limit fee, with respect to such excess credit, may be imposed only once in each of the 2 subsequent billing cycles, unless the consumer has obtained an additional extension of credit in excess of such credit limit during any such subsequent cycle or the consumer reduces the outstanding balance below the credit limit as of the end of such billing cycle.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H1315A208DED941568091341454C35BB7"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Over-the-limit fees prohibited in conjunction with certain credit holds</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (n), an over-the-limit fee may not be imposed if the credit limit was exceeded due to a hold unless the actual amount of the transaction for which the hold was placed would have resulted in the consumer exceeding the credit limit.</text> </subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> 
<section id="HA3C383F6846F4B878C17F0F3F1DD13E9"><enum>5.</enum><header>Strengthen credit card information collection</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 136(b) of the Truth in Lending Act (15 U.S.C. 1646(b)) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H493DBEE8E08D469497B4CD30662EB4E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6A773EB8DD024CB894196CD4E0F36CE6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Collection required</header-in-text>.—The Board shall</quote> and inserting</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H753A06790DD944B9BE1C24CBD9586FAE" style="OLC"><text><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Collection required</header-in-text>.—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2931C27EEF1E4E67842E70F248EA25B4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall</text> </subparagraph> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H98AFD04592BA4379AE2E8D27F5169296"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC8C96728895D4E31ABE4A4611FC9F039" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H7427400A1B604D128B9EB65EE471AB96"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Information to be included</header><text>The information under subparagraph (A) shall include, for the relevant semiannual period, the following information with respect each creditor in connection with any consumer credit card account:</text> 
<clause id="H7684857E858843DAB74F6130CC07E630"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A list of each type of transaction or event during the semiannual period for which 1 or more creditors has imposed a separate interest rate upon a consumer credit card accountholder, including purchases, cash advances, and balance transfers.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H6F12C9CB8A6244A8BEDC033EC266CB47"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>For each type of transaction or event identified under clause (i)—</text> 
<subclause id="HE1260A31D2CA400291BE9708B7F71973"><enum>(I)</enum><text>each distinct interest rate charged by the card issuer to a consumer credit card accountholder during the semiannual period; and</text> </subclause> 
<subclause id="H37D9BAA72C094F209EA1CD395CE559AD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the number of cardholders to whom each such interest rate was applied during the last calendar month of the semiannual period, and the total amount of interest charged to such accountholders at each such rate during such month.</text> </subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H5512531B16D04772AA2C71A09F1E07B1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A list of each type of fee that 1 or more of the creditors has imposed upon a consumer credit card accountholder during the semiannual period, including any fee imposed for obtaining a cash advance, making a late payment, exceeding the credit limit on an account, making a balance transfer, or exchanging United States dollars for foreign currency.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="HE82D6D65DA0E4E8D9C7F116C1A246586"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>For each type of fee identified under clause (iii), the number of ac­count­hold­ers upon whom the fee was imposed during each calendar month of the semiannual period, and the total amount of fees imposed upon cardholders during such month.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H03C3A13FF76948648AFFD02B603FBF01"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The total number of consumer credit card accountholders that incurred any finance charge or any other fee during the semiannual period.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="HD9789E969A3144298B83391106694632"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total number of consumer credit card accounts maintained by each creditor as of the end of the semiannual period.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H78746453747C4366A5B3F91371032781"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total number and value of cash advances made during the semiannual period under a consumer credit card account.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H3A1AEFB558BC40078E42E9FD86EC9108"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total number and value of purchases involving or constituting consumer credit card transactions during the semiannual period.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="HA69763EE0E8340F9BB915739B489476A"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total number and amount of repayments on outstanding balances on consumer credit card accounts in each month of the semiannual period.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H51F2F97BA3BA4864A641608FE2324F04"><enum>(x)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The percentage of all consumer credit card accountholders (with respect to any creditor) who—</text> 
<subclause id="H720170C174D944179497B10A8C84FFB0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>incurred a finance charge in each month of the semiannual period on any portion of an outstanding balance on which a finance charge had not previously been incurred; and</text> </subclause> 
<subclause id="H45C8EF5CEC174679B1C427338B7A6A84"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">incurred any such finance charge at any time during the semiannual period.</text> </subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H59A25AA39B934E0B92F7BAA72247A58B"><enum>(xi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total number and amount of balances accruing finance charges during the semiannual period.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H39F26F6722824AC3B896336498766242"><enum>(xii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total number and amount of the outstanding balances on consumer credit card accounts as of the end of such semiannual period.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="HECF7DAF8C33D4D0DAFAEE5F737C74C9F"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Total credit limits in effect on consumer credit card accounts as of the end of such semiannual period and the amount by which such credit limits exceed the credit limits in effect as of the beginning of such period.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H8364BCDF711E4F5386B9ED1A58B9E3A7"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>Any other information related to interest rates, fees, or other charges that the Board deems of interest.</text> </clause></subparagraph> <after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H786BC0C1D30F415A9FE45355A6B29990"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8B2EB699845D452E98334D5F087DA54E" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H2D549BB8255845A090E2569FDE03D9BE"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall, on an annual basis, transmit to Congress and make public a report containing estimates by the Board of the approximate, relative percentage of income derived by the credit card operations of depository institutions from—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6DB7019B0034435599AE183A3C8EDCCA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the imposition of interest rates on cardholders, including separate estimates for—</text> 
<clause id="H58A47A4B56C74BC6900E40DB4AB722B0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>interest with an annual percentage rate of less than 25 percent; and</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H227BADE88FBD4192B9DEB3E6A0557A30"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>interest with an annual percentage rate equal to or greater than 25 percent;</text> </clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF569C6E373574DD1BF1BFB745BEECE7E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the imposition of fees on cardholders;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBE01ACF278BC47B4BD72FB93FA274E2A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the imposition of fees on merchants; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC7CEB6FE84E842DB9B1B8B647F390459"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other material source of income, while specifying the nature of that income.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></section> 
<section id="H1D9A236594F14196AD0E28FB902C2AEF"><enum>6.</enum><header>Standards applicable to initial issuance of subprime or <quote>fee harvester</quote> cards</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 127B of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after subsection (o) (as added by section 4) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H33101D866D5E4DC1A4A8BCB03A808F27" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H8C2B2A982D11404D9319D9A589D46611"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Standards applicable to initial issuance of subprime or <quote>fee harvester</quote> cards</header> 
<paragraph id="H76C8EE933B9E423F9896D7C99617B7B2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan the terms of which require the payment of any fee (other than any late fee, any over-the-limit fee, or any fee for a payment returned for insufficient funds) by the consumer in the first year the account is opened in an amount in excess of 25 percent of the total amount of credit authorized under the account when the account is opened, no payment of any fee (other than any late fee, any over-the-limit fee, or any fee for a payment returned for insufficient funds) may be made from the credit made available by the card.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0C8F8D6E2D604571A44B43148608941B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>No provision of this subsection may be construed as authorizing any imposition or payment of advance fees otherwise prohibited by any provision of law.</text> </paragraph></subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB44F2B1A78A846929CB3D63FD92D4BCF"><enum>7.</enum><header>Extensions of credit to underage consumers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 127(c) of the Truth in Lending Act (15 U.S.C. 1637(c)) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5AF58EE2AB28404BA7A6036A421E09C5" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="HFF0F433B59344747BCFB7280466C321C"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Extensions of credit to underage consumers</header> 
<subparagraph id="H5E80B56189A041D390C850641F2147EE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No credit card may be knowingly issued to, or open end credit plan established on behalf of, a consumer who has not attained the age of 18, unless the consumer is emancipated under applicable State law or the parent or legal guardian of such consumer is designated as the primary account holder.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H60BB5DD7A64041149D7173F700352C94"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of determining the age of an applicant, the submission of a signed application by a consumer stating that the consumer is over 18 shall be considered sufficient proof of age.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7B7DFEF5F1FC416288B382BB8274D4E2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Provisions applicable with regard to the issuance of credit cards to full-time, traditional-aged college students</header> 
<subparagraph id="H71A4B1A80CAB42D1A6FB4A85B4EDF8D6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the following definitions shall apply:</text> 
<clause id="HE4F152732EE74213BE972BC65439DC33"><enum>(i)</enum><header>College student credit card account defined</header><text>The term <term>college student credit card account</term> means a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan established or maintained for or on behalf of any college student.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="HB977870346D84FFCB6B240D5C65650B4"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>College student</header><text>The term <term>college student</term> means an individual—</text> 
<subclause id="HAB43385A53454511AB6FA8E6E286A80B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>who is a full-time student attending an institution of higher education; and</text> </subclause> 
<subclause id="H073AE8FDB85A4BC7B69C601C16585444"><enum>(II)</enum><text>who has attained the age of 18 and has not yet attained the age of 21.</text> </subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HE0AE0FCD59394DA69FB058A5290156B3"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the same meaning as in section 101(a) of the <act-name parsable-cite="HEA65">Higher Education Act of 1965</act-name> (20 U.S.C. 1001(a)).</text> </clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H681588DA88AA46DFAB208F3F8714A468"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Maximum amount limitation as a percentage of gross income</header><text>Unless a parent, legal guardian, or spouse of a college student assumes joint liability for debts incurred by the student in connection with a college student credit card account—</text> 
<clause id="H33981BB9D07F45BCB82A4F2270D6B41F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the amount of credit which may be extended by any one creditor to the full-time college student may not exceed, during any full calendar year, the greater of—</text> 
<subclause id="HC789E9C7B75242F68735E1E03236C2CF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>20 percent of the annual gross income of the student; or</text> </subclause> 
<subclause id="H3D84655E02344C44A423505B889E00D2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>$500; and</text> </subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H2481594C5A3C43B59F75DD96C8270546"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>no creditor shall grant a student a credit card account, if the credit limit for that credit card account, combined with the credit limits of any other credit card accounts held by the student, would exceed 30 percent of the annual gross income of the student in the most recently completed calendar year.</text> </clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBE55515801B84A6697A9687E271999C9"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Parental approval required to increase credit lines for accounts for which parent is jointly liable</header><text>No increase may be made in the amount of credit authorized to be extended under a college student credit card account for which a parent, legal guardian, or spouse of the consumer has assumed joint liability for debts incurred by the consumer in connection with the account, before the consumer attains the age of 21, with respect to such consumer, unless the parent, guardian, or spouse of the consumer, as applicable, approves in writing, and assumes joint liability for, such increase.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0B62B377A5CA41508AEB45CE866B6C73"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Income verification</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, a creditor shall require adequate proof of income, income history, and credit history, subject to the rules of the Board, before any college student credit card account may be opened by or on behalf of a student.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3D2279E441B543DEBBD471EB9862520A"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Prohibition on more than 1 credit card account for any college student</header><text>No creditor may open a credit card account for, or issue any credit card to, any college student who—</text> 
<clause id="H1B51648D4ACE40D0B9C9B2984DAF4949"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has no verifiable annual gross income; and</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H3626458DA5BD4D19B4F6F7CB188F86F8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>already maintains a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan with that creditor, or any affiliate thereof.</text> </clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H325664A0F3FB41DBBBDF06E6B387E3D7"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Exemption authority</header><text>The Board may, by rule, provide for exemptions to the provisions of this paragraph, as deemed necessary or appropriate by the Board, consistent with the purposes of this paragraph.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> 
<section id="HF2FE3D77560242CAA1A3F9B546314999" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>8.</enum><header>Prohibit fees for payment on credit card accounts by telephone or electronic fund transfers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 164 of the Truth in Lending Act (15 U.S.C. 1666c) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H59B8CBC014104FCD89D6F3EEF79B1D33"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Payments received</quote> and inserting <quote>(a) <header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">In general</header-in-text>.—Payments received</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H830BC9AAE94E468782184F4F26698CA3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H497F71EB461B4A738894415C8CA53868" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H9DE39FDD2CAC41AA95183F1D4B8CD09B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Payment fees</header> 
<paragraph id="H282BA329ED8E42398FD75B449BFBE7A0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition on fee based on mode of payment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), in the case of a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan, a creditor may not impose a fee on the obligor based on the particular manner in which the obligor makes a payment on such account.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE600952E5B0D4012B77A22B614532A40"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the obligor requests to make an expedited payment on a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan by telephone on the date that a payment is due, or the day immediately preceding such date, the creditor may assess a fee for crediting the payment to the obligor’s account on or by such date.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H5E9D26A717874095AFE9BE5AC74CA9FD" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>9.</enum><header>Regulations relating to active duty military consumers and recently disabled veterans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 127B of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after subsection (p) (as added by section 6) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9333093B679F478F962013B99A98EAB0" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H185B5E0ADE334FE29DAE8376EB123A6F"><enum>(q)</enum><header>Regulations relating to active duty military consumers and recently disabled veterans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any credit card account, under an open end consumer credit plan, held by any veteran receiving compensation for a service-connected disability (as such terms are defined in section 101 of title 38, United States Code) that occurred less than 2 years before or any active duty military consumer (as defined in section 603(q)(2) of this Act) , the Board shall prescribe regulations that prohibits the creditor with respect to such account from making adverse reports to any consumer reporting agency with respect while the consumer maintains status as such a veteran or as an active duty military consumer.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H9ACFBD2B7DE745FE857CB0D3FBCB684E" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>10.</enum><header>Posting information on the Internet</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 122 of the Truth in Lending Act ( U.S.C. 1632) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H19535561EAEA437AB70492A16FE251E5" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H3AFF6BF8EE384370BC58A78C6E7973A4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Internet posting of credit card agreements</header> 
<paragraph id="H637EAE9CC7C246A0BC146316C4052A81"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Posting Agreements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">.A creditor shall establish and maintain an Internet site on which the creditor will post the written agreement between the creditor and the consumer for each open-end consumer credit plan not secured by a dwelling that has a credit card feature.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H867ACDCD4CC44B3BBA849048E9914258"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Providing copy of contracts to the board</header><text>A creditor shall provide to the Board in electronic format, the consumer credit card agreements that the creditor publishes on the creditor's Internet site.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE1922C5A8A654541AB450C02C2C08B9B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Record Repository</header><text>The Board shall establish and maintain on its publically available Internet site a central repository of the consumer credit card agreements received from the creditors pursuant to this subsection and such agreements shall be easily accessible and retrievable.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2F59D6E027984DC5A0F5874DC38514D1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Paragraphs (1) and (2) shall not apply to individually negotiated changes to contractual terms, such as individually-modified workouts or renegotiations of amounts owed by a consumer under an open end consumer credit plan.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4328D0C12F61419D9E78E0ED23C9106B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Board, in consultation with the other agencies described in section 108 and the Federal Trade Commission, may prescribe regulations to implement this subsection, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5426803E93F846F6B363025367AE3706"><enum>(A)</enum><text>specifying the format for posting the agreements on the creditor's Internet site; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBF24838670DB4478AE4197515547B926"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establishing exceptions to paragraphs (1) and (2) in cases where the administrative burden outweighs the benefit of increased transparency, such as where a credit card plan has a de minimis number of consumer account holders</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H7BC40A8B40E54AF49E825DCC3DD095CA" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>11.</enum><header>Enhanced minimum payment disclosures</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Paragraph (11) of section 127(b) of the Truth in Lending Act (15 U.S.C. 1637(b)(11)) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9E32965409604C09A6854BC60121EBC6" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H212F724A7B754B3380072B293D8DBBED"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Minimum payment disclosures</header> 
<subparagraph id="HF95AF82889884992A105137EAC9F563E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Minimum payment warning</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A written statement in the following form: <quote>Minimum Payment Warning: Making only the minimum payment will increase the interest you pay and the time it takes to repay your balance.</quote>.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC04EE7DEDB414638BE0FF96EF34C44ED"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Information on outstanding balance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less than once per calendar quarter, such billing statement shall also include repayment information that would apply to the outstanding balance of the consumer under the credit plan, including—</text> 
<clause id="HAC6FE9945F364E95A677F14D8E4E4242"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of months (rounded to the nearest month) that it would take to pay the entire amount of that balance, if the consumer pays only the required minimum monthly payments and if no further advances are made;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7BEA0F0450AA4D0DA1367B2BFAD2848E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total cost to the consumer, including interest payments, of paying that balance in full, if the consumer pays only the required minimum monthly payments and if no further advances are made;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H851159D97BF64C5B8CF5FC66C2F2CD11"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the monthly payment amount that would be required for the consumer to eliminate the outstanding balance in 12 months, 24 months, and 36 months, if no further advances are made, and the total cost to the consumer, including interest and principal payments, of paying that balance in full if the consumer pays the balance over 12, 24, or 36 months, respectively; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6632E5A52F544E46B56B628D50F37356"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a toll-free telephone number at which the consumer may receive information about accessing credit counseling and debt management services.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF2198229463145F9AD66139E656FE4E3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exception to requirements of subsection (B)</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The quarterly disclosure requirements in subsection (B) shall not apply with respect to—</text> 
<clause id="HD4813715F1394C10A2E0F7AA2E6A5422"><enum>(i)</enum><text> a calendar quarter if, in the 2 consecutive billing cycles preceding the end of such quarter, a consumer has paid the entire balance of the bill in full;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA9A4305BA28E40208FFD4F8C99254352"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> a calendar quarter if, at the end of the calendar quarter, a consumer has an outstanding credit balance of zero or has a positive credit; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB750A37C2995488BB3842C90BEF93DF2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any class of consumers for which the Board has determined will not benefit substantially from additional disclosures.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H94BABC37989F4334A6264AC4D2B8968D"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Applicable rates to be used in disclosures</header> 
<clause id="H200A6F7E80C349C7AC11EF5A1EDB79EC"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to clause (ii), in making the disclosures under subparagraph (B), the creditor shall apply the interest rate or rates in effect on the date on which the disclosure is made until the date on which the balance would be paid in full.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF412F83A4D754B26975F80CAA69FDC7B"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Special rule in case of temporary rate</header><text>If the interest rate in effect on the date on which the disclosure is made is a temporary rate that will change under a contractual provision applying an index or formula for subsequent interest rate adjustment, the creditor shall apply the interest rate in effect on the date on which the disclosure is made for as long as that interest rate will apply under that contractual provision, and then apply an interest rate based on the index or formula in effect on the applicable billing date.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC131E95B64084BE98EFBDE823169391A"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Form and prominence of disclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All of the information described in subparagraph (B) shall—</text> 
<clause id="H4409BA475B8F429DB8154F172A037C0B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be disclosed in the form and manner which the Board shall prescribe, by regulation, and in a manner that avoids duplication; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF72EEEA7F5924D0DBECA7CF1B9DCD004"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>be placed in a conspicuous and prominent location on the billing statement in conspicuous typeface.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H992F79DAFDA94625A6EB01562116B4A4"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Tabular format</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the regulations prescribed under subparagraph (D), the Board shall require that the disclosure of such information shall be in the form of a table that—</text> 
<clause id="HA181FB51D9B14FC08344DB07E4A8634E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>contains clear and concise headings for each item of such information; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H47E836872BF445848B5EAC780808AE2B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provides a clear and concise form stating each item of information required to be disclosed under each such heading.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCF6E9BC0ED364768BD3FD6D5BF9739E9"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Location and order of table</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In prescribing the form of the table under subparagraph (E), the Board shall require that—</text> 
<clause id="H28F57B0FD1E24B3BA8BAD042863A274D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>all of the information in the table, and not just a reference to the table, be placed on the billing statement, as required by this paragraph; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF30AAE10D5F640D1BA8C07212467D501"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the items required to be included in the table shall be listed in the order in which such items are described in subparagraph (B).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB9CCEAAF2B744D7492F4A12191F1D414"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Substitution of terminology</header><text>In prescribing the form of the table under subparagraph (D), the Board may employ terminology which is different than the terminology used in subparagraph (B), if such terminology is more easily understood and conveys substantially the same meaning.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFFC1928C66114ACCA13E1417B01B5269"><enum>(I)</enum><header><quote>Rounding</quote> regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of determining whether an error in the disclosures required by subparagraph (B) constitutes a legal cause of action against a creditor or any other party, the standard referred to under the heading <quote>Rounding assumed payments, current balance and interest charges to the nearest cent</quote> in the publication by the Board in the Federal Register (74 Fed. Reg. 5385) on January 29, 2009, of the final regulation revising part 226 of title 12 of the Code of Federal Regulations (Regulation Z), or a standard that affords substantially similar protections as determined by the Board, shall apply for purposes of the determination with regard to such disclosures.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HFC7C91C0090A4A21A6B20B5E88485CE0" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>12.</enum><header>Board review of consumer credit plans and regulations</header> 
<subsection id="H8E601300CC2F45F9B0F27D54CE5A2A77"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Required review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the effective date of this Act and every 2 years thereafter, except as provided in subsection (c)(2), the Board shall conduct a review, within the limits of its existing resources available for reporting purposes of the consumer credit card market including—</text> 
<paragraph id="HEB3FCB1947704A4FBF7D236F2DF9B3CF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the terms of credit card agreements and the practices of credit card issuers;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H52D378DDCB414CA6BDD460F8047E1F01"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the effectiveness of disclosure of terms, fees, and other expense of credit card plans; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H80278939A6EB4342B6BEFBF8151618CA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the adequacy of protections against unfair or deceptive acts or practices relating to credit card plans, and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC4D08F652F424E04B5CC90DB68E71342"><enum>(4)</enum><text>whether or not, and to what extent, the Credit Cardholders’ Bill of Rights Act of 2009 has resulted in—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDCC79CE25C5B4B039BF77D93840AA843"><enum>(A)</enum><text>higher annual percentage rates of interest, on average, for credit card users than the average of such rates of interest in effect before the effective date of the Act;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0144911F8B6A4C3AA30ECCBC11DA1A9F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the imposition of annual fees or other credit card fees—</text> 
<clause id="H3A2BCDD6E66C4E798D7749FF32D8D0FE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that did not exist before such effective date;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H514B53612DBF4B1C84895274CD3A868A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>at a higher average rate of applicability than existed before such effective date; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H425A680585AC478DA88C738A7D2FFE54"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>with higher average costs to the consumer than were in effect before such effective date;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA50E9A6068F240F8BC63488726E81E5F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an increase in the rate of denial of—</text> 
<clause id="H0C968B6F622342D3929837D061A03673"><enum>(i)</enum><text>new credit card accounts for consumers; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC98D328C05124C4FBC5E8EC9F9129CB8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>new extensions of credit, or additional lines of credit, for existing credit accounts established before such effective date; or</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8953E0CFD68D49388C1A2F41D82F9A07"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other adverse or negative condition or effect on consumers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0F76D7AC0137414B9F903A258B76AFE8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Solicitation of public comment</header><text>In connection with conducting the review required by subsection (a), the Board shall solicit comment from consumers, credit card issuers, and other interested parties, such as through hearings or written comments.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H249C8B1D4BB841EC8672407BB5C03C26"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regulations</header> 
<paragraph id="HCAB1DCBFB095463DA4570696804BB22C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Following the review required by subsection (a) the Board shall publish a notice in the Federal Register that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H860753D8A9F649ABB582AF6855BBA407"><enum>(A)</enum><text>summarizes the review, the comments received from the public solicitation, and other evidence gathered by the Board such as through consumer testing or other research; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDB2F2242F5B9427B9B4FF66D729F0268"><enum>(B)</enum><text>either—</text> 
<clause id="H26F3BFDA673143CA99218FAF840C3F04"><enum>(i)</enum><text>proposes new or revised regulations or interpretations to update or revise disclosures and protections for consumer credit cards as appropriate; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H199D2C89392648EA97C919F3DD33BDC4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>states the reason for the Board’s determination that new or revised regulations are not proposed.</text></clause></subparagraph> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7BBF83746FB74E1DA1857D5EC3E8A215"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Revision of review period following material revision of regulations</header><text>In the event the Board materially revises regulations on consumer credit card plans, a review need not be conducted until 2 years following the effective date of the revised regulations, which thereafter shall become the new date for the biennial review required by subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF3EBD9360B3F446694BA1151FAD94A3A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Board report to the congress</header><text>The Board shall report to the Congress no less frequently than every 2 years, except as provided in subsection (c)(2), on the status of its most recent review, its efforts to address any issues identified from the review, and any recommendations for legislation.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4B6B16C0D7A74A749E22097B6004B744"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Additional reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal banking agencies and the Federal Trade Commission shall provide annually to the Board, and the Board shall include in its annual report to Congress under section 10 of the Federal Reserve Act, information about the supervisory and enforcement activities of the agencies with respect to credit card issuers' compliance with applicable Federal consumer protection statutes and regulations including—</text> 
<paragraph id="H637687CC0BD24F7E8DAF1E3934274E39"><enum>(1)</enum><text>this Act, the amendments made by this Act, and regulations prescribed under this Act and such amendments; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H38CAD4FD8DA94B5485832EE3A8808B55"><enum>(2)</enum><text>section 5 of the Federal Trade Commission Act, and regulations prescribed under the Federal Trade Commission Act, such as part 227 of title 12 of the Code of Federal Regulations as prescribed by the Board (Regulation AA).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H57306AA541E64095839471DFE5C15010" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>13.</enum><header>Solicitations required to include warning on adverse effects of excessive credit inquiries</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 127(c)(1)(B) of the Truth in Lending Act (15 U.S.C. 1637(c)(1)(B)) is amended by adding at the end the following new clause:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBF4A70F9D5E54DB49646FDFB0CF3962B" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<clause id="H6A1B7842400A42E6860137A2C7D76236"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Excessive credit inquiries</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A warning that excessive credit inquiries, which occur in connection with credit applications and solicitations and under other circumstances, can have an adverse effect on a consumer credit score.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H86BC8884164247B4AA60DEEEAD79CB31"><enum>14.</enum><header>Readability requirement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 122 of the Truth in Lending Act (U.S.C. 1632) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H263E223A5077489DBBAEA9CCCECCC4B2" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H3B559DC1B2BD480385F8111E2C72C485"><enum>(d) </enum><header>Minimum type-size and font requirement for credit card applications and disclosures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All written information, provisions, and terms in or on any application, solicitation, contract, or agreement for any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan, and all written information included in or on any disclosure required under this chapter with respect to any such account, shall appear—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA98448D010A54DEDABCA29AAC82D5F62"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in not less than 12-point type; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA5BAE11DC7AE498CB8FB085FF71467A4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in any font other than a font which the Board has designated, in regulations under this section, as a font that inhibits readability.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2C4A42E1B13944F5AD028B79F9DE3DD5" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>15.</enum><header>Report to Congress on reductions of consumer credit card limits based on certain information as to experience or transactions of the consumer</header> 
<subsection id="H02D932C8F65A4C07BB0EB6665FB392BD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report on creditor practices required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before the end of the 6-month period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, in consultation with the Comptroller of the Currency, the Director of the Office of Thrift Supervision, the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, the National Credit Union Administration Board, and the Federal Trade Commission, shall report to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate on the extent to which, during the 3-year period ending on such date of enactment, creditors have reduced credit limits or raised interest rates applicable to credit card accounts under open end consumer credit plans based on—</text> 
<paragraph id="H894A3A1D29184B67BE7F805D0DFD0C4B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the geographical location where a credit transaction with the consumer takes place or the identity of the merchant involved in the transaction;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4E8FEDE60F3F4CB7AD1764F486C39499"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the consumer’s credit transactions, including the type of credit transaction, the type of items purchased in such transaction, the price of items purchased in such transaction, any change in the type or price of items purchased in such transactions, and other data pertaining to the consumer’s use of such credit card account; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6BBB97BB99644CB68FF44FF99118F90F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the identity of the mortgage creditor which extended or holds the mortgage loan secured by the consumer’s primary residence.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H44EA756ED30B4B6A9424DB8226F92629"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Other information</header><text>The report required under subsection (a) shall also include—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB1639DAE70BE46C48ECB14ADBA2B48EE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number and identity of creditors that have engaged in the practices described in subsection (a);</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCEDC7B2D773343A8B673F9BC9DECF1B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the extent to which the practices described in subsection (a) have an adverse impact on minority or low-income consumers;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4CB4AFBAE1EA4EFE89AFC613FCFAF0CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any other relevant information regarding such practices; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6478D83CCD994BCD876C6C9BD378C158"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recommendations to the Congress on regulatory or statutory changes that may be needed to restrict or prevent such practices.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H158EAD54088F4DB6BB9EF9941AA818F4" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>16.</enum><header>Procedure for timely settlements of decedent obligors’ estates</header> 
<subsection id="HBA94663D10574FCF9BB39862057DE054"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Chapter 2 of the Truth in Lending Act ( U.S.C. 1631 et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following new section: </text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HC2BB8E4BD1F74448A6869C152780393D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H4A8F55D8DB59484FAA27AA4DF55311BE"><enum>140A</enum><header>Procedure for timely settlements of decedent obligors’ estates</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Board, in consultation with the Federal Trade Commission and each other agency referred to in section 108(a), shall prescribe regulations to require any creditor, with respect to any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan, to establish procedures to ensure that any administrator of an estate of any deceased obligor with respect to such account can resolve outstanding credit balances in a timely manner.</text> </section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB681F191885940F28E52015D3D4A1280"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for chapter 2 of the Truth in Lending Act is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 140 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HBF4B1B6AA7D14CEB96A2DD704278BD20" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">140A. Procedure for timely settlements of decedent obligors’ estates.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H2FD81BA0FD3B451C96B60A0BEC7A3EC2" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>17.</enum><header>Interim implementation reports to the Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Chairman of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System shall submit a report each 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act on the level of implementation of the regulations required to be prescribed under this Act to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate until the Chairman can report full industry implementation.</text></section> 
<section id="H5718E2D45825446D94B569D7AAE9203B" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>18.</enum><header>Disclosure requirement for stores accepting credit card account applications</header> 
<subsection id="H00F6444F0862449D8AAFAF03C0CE6266"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 122 of the Truth in Lending Act (15 U.S.C. 1632) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HD49EE6671171443EA9ACB25375DE2B4E"> 
<subsection id="HE1B57664483A4CCCB0817ADEF986E895"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Signs required on certain premises where credit card account applications accepted</header> 
<paragraph id="H401DC1103A58407D9298192E7402DB34"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A person who sells personal property to consumers on a business premises and makes available to consumers on such premises any application to open a credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan, and where such person is the issuer of such account, shall display in the premises on a sign any information that is subject to subsection (c) and that is required to be disclosed by the person on that application.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD2AFAC9BFE5244669EA1AAB8B1814DBD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Format</header><text>Such information shall be displayed on the sign in the form and manner which the Board shall prescribe by regulations and which, to the extent practicable and appropriate, shall be consistent with the form and manner required for the disclosure of such information on the credit card application.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE11774C4ED4D4F12870085C0C746A55E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Sign placement</header><text>Such signs shall be conspicuously placed at each location on the premises where the credit card application may be submitted by the consumer.</text> </paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HAD8F46DA487F4310948A06A1E8A12D82"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 111(e) of the Truth in Lending Act (15 U.S.C. 1610(e)) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H8F94A936F85F49879B5A6CC14C0F2D87"> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 122(d) shall supersede State laws relating to store display of the information that is subject to the requirements of such section, except that any State may employ or establish State laws for the purpose of enforcing the requirements of such section.</text> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection></section> 
<section id="H21F344744E3F458B9783CBE830AC66A6" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>19.</enum><header>Effective date</header> 
<subsection id="HD85A78E4A02B436DA4F24C88C9F3D7C9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (c) for the period described in such subsection, the amendments made by this Act shall apply to all credit card accounts under open end consumer credit plans after the earlier of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H74F69293D05E4FE29526243F85A27CCE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the end of the 12-month period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act; or</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H607D51DE2AFE42C69A83B254D4E58C49"><enum>(2)</enum><text>June 30, 2010.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB749DC0D223C46B4AA60743F6F8386D7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (c) for the period described in such subsection, the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, in consultation with the Comptroller of the Currency, the Director of the Office of Thrift Supervision, the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, the National Credit Union Administration Board, and the Federal Trade Commission, shall prescribe regulations, in final form, implementing the amendments made by this Act before the earlier of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3158DE18AE254DF58D585786F4B9249D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the end of the 5-month period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act; or</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE57CF2F0E47A4A25913A210EEA501D51"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">June 1, 2010.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0E40BB318E03403F92D5807CA2782B2F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Interim effective period for advance notices of rate increases</header> 
<paragraph id="HF49D9C626A4A4A0ABF299D3B12258F0E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the period beginning 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act and ending on the effective date of all the amendments under this Act as determined pursuant to subsection (a), no increase in any annual percentage rate of interest on any credit card account under an open end consumer credit plan (as such terms are defined in the Truth in Lending Act) may take effect unless the creditor provides a written notice to the consumer at least 45 days before the increase would otherwise take effect which fully describes the changes in the annual percentage rate, in a complete and conspicuous manner, and the extent to which such increase would apply to an existing balance.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H976778BFFD7C468EB9BD1A843BC79547"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A notice shall not be required under paragraph (1) for an increase in an annual percentage rate described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) of section 127B(b)(1) (as added by section 2).</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H488BD890097C427BB545FC05A5F378D8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System shall prescribe regulations implementing the amendment referred to in paragraph (1), for purposes of this subsection, before the end of the 60-day period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20090430" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives April 30, 2009.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation> 
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement> 
</bill> 
