<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H57AF073C68814BA78B54582EA7FE16BC" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 2818 IH: To amend title 38, United States Code, to provide for the
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-06-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 2818</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20070621">June 21, 2007</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000593">Mr. Perlmutter</sponsor> (for
			 himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000116">Mr. Filner</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M001149">Mr. Michaud</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="K000113">Mr. Kennedy</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="S001158">Mr. Salazar</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="W000314">Mr. Wexler</cosponsor>, and
			 <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>) introduced the following
			 bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee
			 on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to provide for the
		  establishment of Epilepsy Centers of Excellence in the Veterans Health
		  Administration of the Department of Veterans Affairs.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HE585361E7A7C48529B5B80F63E3900A6" style="OLC">
		<section id="H9C15392A5097461195D360DCE4C624FD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Epilepsy Centers of
			 Excellence</header>
			<subsection id="H90B89CF2391C4A57B9BA873409F8B45C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement for
			 establishment of epilepsy centers of excellence</header><text>Subchapter II of
			 <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/73">chapter 73</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the
			 following new section:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0D1EE62CCC4842C585F15F006D4D52AE" style="USC">
					<section id="HA2849A4990604CF88BFCEE004407AB1C"><enum>7330A.</enum><header>Epilepsy
				centers of excellence</header>
						<subsection id="HAE8C81F8A3AB4178AD3290D2F9AE14F3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of
				Centers</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4923938A7E2A45B1A413B8AB1FC7806"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Not
				later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary,
				upon the recommendation of the Under Secretary for Health, shall designate not
				less than six Department health-care facilities as the locations for epilepsy
				centers of excellence.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H313BB1A86EE54FA18BEFA11FDEFBAB99" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Subject to the availability of
				appropriations for such purpose, the Secretary shall establish and operate
				epilepsy centers of excellence at the locations designated pursuant to
				paragraph (1).</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44687EDDE7324497943410DC00E8CC28"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Designation of
				Facilities</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H461DAB5FAD0A471784A33EE63C6736F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary may not
				designate a Department health-care facility as a location for an epilepsy
				center of excellence under subsection (a)(1) unless the peer review panel
				established under subsection (c) has determined under that subsection that the
				proposal submitted by such facility seeking designation as a location for an
				epilepsy center of excellence is among those proposals that meet the highest
				competitive standards of scientific and clinical merit.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H8F376F29F399435880393447E438A700" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In choosing from among the
				facilities meeting the requirements of paragraph (1), the Secretary shall also
				consider appropriate geographic distribution when designating the epilepsy
				centers of excellence under subsection (a)(1).</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H00A418C7A6A8470CB62EAAC280CF2842"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Peer Review
				Panel</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7D8AF29BB1014DA3A6ACB1009168CB9C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The
				Under Secretary for Health shall establish a peer review panel to assess the
				scientific and clinical merit of proposals that are submitted to the Secretary
				for the designation of epilepsy centers of excellence under this
				section.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H85DB297553574382939B52C999E81954" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HDD1FBFAD8A0E41D2A0D4B36FAB9B3EE6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The membership of the
				peer review panel shall consist of experts on epilepsy, including
				post-traumatic epilepsy.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3FFCB04A79A436D92FEB0D37749B9B0" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Members of the peer review panel
				shall serve for a period of no longer than two years, except as specified in
				subparagraph (C).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04492FD508EE4596BA6587F98E27056D" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Of the members first appointed to the
				panel, one half shall be appointed for a period of three years and one half
				shall be appointed for a period of two years, as designated by the Under
				Secretary at the time of appointment.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3DAC9F9E2DCE4FAC93C9829F6C7354" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The peer review panel shall review
				each proposal submitted to the panel by the Under Secretary for Health and
				shall submit its views on the relative scientific and clinical merit of each
				such proposal to the Under Secretary.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H75A62FA7CF404F06B095F64E7B01D981" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The peer review panel shall not be
				subject to the Federal Advisory Committee Act.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H05714EC304C34BF3822F8EA5942373FA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Priority of funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that each
				Department health-care facility that, as of January 1, 2007, was operating a
				nationally designated VA Center of Excellence for Epilepsy Monitoring and is
				designated as an epilepsy center of excellence under subsection (a)(1) shall
				receive adequate funding to enable those centers to function effectively in the
				areas of epilepsy research, education, and clinical care activities before
				providing funds to facilities designated under subsection (a)(1) that were not
				operating a nationally designated VA Center of Excellence for Epilepsy
				Monitoring as of January 1, 2007.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H27F5638873114DBE8F50E6BD181BC57B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Epilepsy Center
				of Excellence Defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The
				term <quote>epilepsy center of excellence</quote> means a Department
				health-care facility that has (or in the foreseeable future can develop) the
				necessary capacity to function as a center of excellence in research,
				education, and clinical care activities in the diagnosis and treatment of
				epilepsy and has (or may reasonably be anticipated to develop) each of the
				following:</text>
							<paragraph id="HD4C209ED6BCA478FB0CBC000B8E6394D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An affiliation
				with an accredited medical school that provides education and training in
				neurology, including an arrangement with such school under which medical
				residents receive education and training in the diagnosis and treatment of
				epilepsy (including neurosurgery).</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H6778338195DA4643B6000071B52791E2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The ability to
				attract the participation of scientists who are capable of ingenuity and
				creativity in health-care research efforts.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H9D74F25D0C79475B9334F7BE95841D48"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An advisory
				committee composed of veterans and appropriate health-care and research
				representatives of the facility and of the affiliated school or schools to
				advise the directors of such facility and such center on policy matters
				pertaining to the activities of the center during the period of the operation
				of such center.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H65BBE8C02EC341C59F97EBF82D5B1BA2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The capability to
				conduct effectively evaluations of the activities of such center.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H4AF051DBA82046949BE7710045ED41B5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The capability to
				coordinate (as part of an integrated national system) education, clinical care,
				and research activities within all facilities with such centers.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HC1D51A9662D24A5D916D2B07A816E3F2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The capability to
				develop jointly a national consortium of providers with interest in treating
				epilepsy at Department health-care facilities lacking such centers in order to
				ensure better access to state-of-the-art diagnosis, research, clinical care,
				and education for traumatic brain injury and epilepsy throughout the
				health-care system of the Department. Such consortium should include a
				designated epilepsy referral clinic in each Veterans Integrated Service
				Network.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HE3EE4F544370482CB47DCBD8097C511D"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The capability to assist in the expansion
				of the Department’s use of information systems and databases to improve the
				quality and delivery of care for veterans enrolled within the Department’s
				health care system.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HE4DB604584174239AD9D084960C1A97"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The capability to
				assist in the expansion of the Department telehealth program to develop,
				transmit, monitor, and review neurological diagnostic tests.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HC71B240F79354017AC4D7DD83EC7B5B3"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The ability to perform epilepsy research,
				education, and clinical care activities in collaboration with Department
				medical facilities that have centers for research, education, and clinical care
				activities on complex multi-trauma associated with combat injuries established
				under section 7327.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7C407BBA656B4A8A94FBC3D235496BF3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Administration</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HDE275D463CA4418CBBC1E55B24313D24"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In order to assist the
				Secretary and Under Secretary for Health in carrying out this section, a
				national coordinator for epilepsy programs shall report to the official
				responsible for neurology at the Veterans Health Administration and
				shall—</text>
								<subparagraph id="H3D43C19AC6A148DEAA43A20000447389" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>supervise the operation of the centers
				established pursuant to this section;</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E547DC25560469EB0CD44122DBFF785" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>coordinate and support the national
				consortium of providers with interest in treating epilepsy at Department
				health-care facilities lacking such centers in order to ensure better access to
				state-of-the-art diagnosis, research, clinical care, and education for
				traumatic brain injury and epilepsy throughout the health-care system of the
				Department; and</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B4C40F946AB4C63B60421A5D1C42216" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>conduct regular evaluations of the
				epilepsy centers of excellence to ensure compliance with the requirements of
				this section.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB96301E3D73E409B942BF1D13ED2BDF" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In addition to amounts authorized
				under subsection (g), there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may
				be necessary to fund such national coordinator.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6EBEE591F3A84C379949D061275CC655"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of
				Appropriations</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H45EC84E12B02489FA807D582B7DB6590"><enum>(1)</enum><text>There are authorized to
				be appropriated $6 million for each fiscal year from fiscal year 2008 through
				fiscal year 2012 for the support of the clinical care, research, and education
				activities of the epilepsy centers of excellence established and operated
				pursuant to subsection (a)(2).</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H37BF6E3C5C6946568C449182B3A9A43B" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>There are authorized to be
				appropriated such sums as may be necessary after fiscal year 2012 for the
				support of the clinical care, research, and education activities of the
				epilepsy centers of excellence established and operated pursuant to subsection
				(a)(2).</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H775114BF025643BA96A600D100F86BE5" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Secretary shall ensure that funds
				for such centers are designated for the first three years of operation as a
				special purpose program for which funds are not allocated through the Veterans
				Equitable Resource Allocation system.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H0EB411FA58B34FCEAD48BE9C022363C4" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In addition to amounts authorized to
				be appropriated under paragraph (1) for a fiscal year, the Under Secretary for
				Health shall allocate to such centers from other funds appropriated generally
				for the Department medical services account and medical and prosthetics
				research account, as appropriate, such amounts as the Under Secretary for
				Health determines
				appropriate.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HAE2F45DA2A764507AAD800E35284769D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical
			 amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 73 of
			 title 38, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating
			 to section 7330 the following new item:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H662A0845CECA4220A4C8F814EDD4DFA9" style="OLC">
					<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
						<toc-entry level="section">7330A. Epilepsy centers of
				excellence.</toc-entry>
					</toc>
					<after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


