<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBEE9BB2AF582424CA1C22F19C000708E" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 920 IH: Multiple Peril Insurance Act of 2007</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-02-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 920</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070208">February 8, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000074">Mr. Taylor</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Waters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000287">Mr. Jindal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001161">Mr. Melancon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000255">Mr. Jones of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000070">Mr. Jefferson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001244">Mr. Bonner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000087">Mrs. Maloney of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Al Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001049">Mr. Clay</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000133">Mr. Markey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000599">Mr. Lincoln Davis of Tennessee</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="A000361">Mr. Alexander</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend the National Flood Insurance Act of 1968 to provide for the national flood insurance program to make available multiperil coverage for damage resulting from windstorms or floods, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H64F3B1176C094F9BB43B53E6B066E99" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H02853931738B45E0B0A3E8A127F1B5B6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Multiple Peril Insurance Act of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H63BB3FA6BBAE49E58668ACBE36C1ACCE" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Flood and windstorm multiperil coverage</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1304 of the National Flood Insurance Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4011">42 U.S.C. 4011</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H13A3CE6300E4408AADA9169B138E00E2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (c) as subsection (d); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFFA3DABF9CB546209C5E40C3007B6CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (b) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEB0DE09402E545A69E64222848A3C5EC" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="HF809947FFC264118819D9F8E61F76667"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Multiperil coverage for damage from flood or windstorm</header> 
<paragraph id="HD9BB020AC4524F1D94B3F2CA09003140"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The national flood insurance program established pursuant to subsection (a) shall enable the purchase of optional insurance against loss resulting from physical damage to or loss of real property or personal property related thereto located in the United States arising from any flood or windstorm, subject to the limitations in this subsection and section 1306(b).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H44AAF6068DDD416FB57E3D00D0B96B9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Community participation requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Multiperil coverage pursuant to this subsection may not be provided in any area (or subdivision thereof) unless an appropriate public body shall have adopted adequate land use and control measures (with effective enforcement provisions) which the Director finds are consistent with the comprehensive criteria for land management and use relating to windstorms establish pursuant to section 1361(d)(2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC7B1563CD2264E85A2B44BB261C31599"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prohibition against duplicative coverage</header><text>Multiperil coverage pursuant to this subsection may not be provided with respect to any structure (or the personal property related thereto) for any period during which such structure is covered, at any time, by flood insurance coverage made available under this title.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H84229508EA2343E6BE4BD6A74634DC79"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Nature of coverage</header><text>Multiperil coverage pursuant to this subsection shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB7BEAF2E86AD4097B6C90133A9CEBAED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>cover losses only from physical damage resulting from flooding or windstorm; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA6BF79F160334CC58E5DEDD2879B943"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide for approval and payment of claims under such coverage upon proof that such loss must have resulted from either windstorm or flooding, but shall not require for approval and payment of a claim that the specific cause of the loss, whether windstorm or flooding, be distinguished or identified.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7486AD22F6AE42E180ED59CA0200BF48"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Actuarial rates</header><text>Multiperil coverage pursuant to this subsection shall be made available for purchase for a property only at chargeable risk premium rates that, based on consideration of the risks involved and accepted actuarial principles, and including operating costs and allowance and administrative expenses, are required in order to make such coverage available on an actuarial basis for the type and class of properties covered.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H14E6ACA7541B4380BE6F9F18BABB4F2D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Terms of coverage</header><text>The Director shall, after consultation with persons and entities referred to in section 1306(a), provide by regulation for the general terms and conditions of insurability which shall be applicable to properties eligible for multiperil coverage under this subsection, subject to the provisions of this subsection, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H30E7FC44C13A4BA5B59887CB979DBF97"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the types, classes, and locations of any such properties which shall be eligible for such coverage, which shall include residential and nonresidential properties;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5C3100E5C2B647FE9C7DC126A9DCD1C7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subject to paragraph (7), the nature and limits of loss or damage in any areas (or subdivisions thereof) which may be covered by such coverage;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3C984C2B8F104DB68E5DE1D844D08100"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the classification, limitation, and rejection of any risks which may be advisable;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H584A80EFC32B4867903C513266EB22CE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>appropriate minimum premiums;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8C314646F41942AC9300DB3100B2A231"><enum>(E)</enum><text>appropriate loss deductibles; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5EA5C1A01E494797B38385F2D38BC634"><enum>(F)</enum><text>any other terms and conditions relating to insurance coverage or exclusion that may be necessary to carry out this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2E357B90025F47B1AAD387B35C352D95"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Limitations on amount of coverage</header><text>The regulations issued pursuant to paragraph (6) shall provide that the aggregate liability under multiperil coverage made available under this subsection shall not exceed the lesser of the replacement cost for covered losses or the following amounts, as applicable:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H50452EB80CE449F68904192790B43786"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Residential structures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of residential properties—</text> 
<clause id="HE79485DF0E4D49C1957C828F09473E9E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for any single-family dwelling, $500,000; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB041C249BA8B4D27AE7373FB2AC6EC7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for any structure containing more than one dwelling unit, $500,000 for each separate dwelling unit in the structure; and </text></clause> 
<clause id="H47AD92466AE64553B709EB3BC756AA93"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>$150,000 per dwelling unit for—</text> 
<subclause id="HDE705B1E46FC41D699BA1CDFEE1BF7B7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any contents related to such unit; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H5BFEF8B673394168A7BD5B0CAE38750"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any necessary increases in living expenses incurred by the insured when losses from flooding or windstorm make the residence unfit to live in.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H09E19327412243E8899B8239ECD4E3A0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Nonresidential properties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of nonresidential properties (including church properties)—</text> 
<clause id="H9D44C6CA3FF945E8939DCE1BDC8E8419"><enum>(i)</enum><text>$1,000,000 for any single structure; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H586AEAD819A94A3A8000B55B85E335D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>$750,000 for—</text> 
<subclause id="HF0CC88AFCDD5405ABA19C9148300D79E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any contents related to such structure;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H98F1045E50B7429B969D2113E6CF3196"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of any nonresidential property that is a business property, any losses resulting from any partial or total interruption of the insured’s business caused by damage to, or loss of, such property from flooding or windstorm, except that for purposes of such coverage, losses shall be determined based on the profits the covered business would have earned, based on previous financial records, had the flood or windstorm not occurred.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> </paragraph> </subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HC03885BE2C574F79B704000030A1CEC3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition against duplicative coverage</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The National Flood Insurance Act of 1968 is amended by inserting after section 1313 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4020">42 U.S.C. 4020</external-xref>) the following new section;</text> 
<quoted-block style="traditional" id="H84DF5539D2174A86BE285462173F5BCF" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H11DA48AFEB14411CB717643E522905A8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1314.</enum><header>Prohibition against duplicative coverage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Flood insurance under this title may not be provided with respect to any structure (or the personal property related thereto) for any period during which such structure is covered, at any time, by multiperil insurance coverage made available pursuant to section 1304(c).</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H04952D08744C4F9ABEE38E2313C94E6C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Compliance with State and local law</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1316 of the National Flood Insurance Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4023">42 U.S.C. 4023</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5E05619D1F4A48128455B22ECF253405"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(a) <header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Flood protection measures</header-in-text>.—</quote> before <quote>No new</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3F27AFDA7ED64B00B309523B50C300E0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H29F0A43309D6446CB049A6B9C139CB18" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="HA1E9B643446D4A43A151709927B30047"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Windstorm protection measures</header><text>No new multiperil coverage shall be provided under section 1304(c) for any property that the Director finds has been declared by a duly constituted State or local zoning authority, or other authorized public body to be in violation of State or local laws, regulations, or ordinances, which are intended to reduce damage caused by windstorms.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H5D29B7B567684E599B21DE2EACE59BFE"><enum>5.</enum><header>Criteria for land management and use</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1361 of the National Flood Insurance Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4102">42 U.S.C. 4102</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HCAF0799AF9154813954D6246D49DF7B9" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H2A9C779706AB4DE1A5005FC076FB2BD3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Windstorms</header> 
<paragraph id="H817E2D53983C484C8D8C8282D81EAA66"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Studies and investigations</header><text>The Director shall carry out studies and investigations under this section to determine appropriate measures in windstorm-prone areas as to land management and use, windstorm zoning, and windstorm damage prevention, and may enter into contracts, agreements, and other appropriate arrangements to carry out such activities. Such studies and investigations shall include laws, regulations, and ordinance relating to the orderly development and use of areas subject to damage from windstorm risks, and zoning building codes, building permits, and subdivision and other building restrictions for such areas.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5D6CABDE82E14682B8BEFB5D8F04037"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On the basis of the studies and investigations pursuant to paragraph (1) and such other information as may be appropriate, the Direct shall establish comprehensive criteria designed to encourage, where necessary, the adoption of adequate State and local measures which, to the maximum extent feasible, will assist in reducing damage caused by windstorms.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H11B00FE4842C454C919B99575D9FC758"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Coordination with State and local governments</header><text>The Director shall work closely with and provide any necessary technical assistance to State, interstate, and local governmental agencies, to encourage the application of criteria established under paragraph (2) and the adoption and enforcement of measures referred to in such paragraph .</text> </paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H9529EBFB384349F192FCE8EFEB0700F6"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1370 of the National Flood Insurance Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4121">42 U.S.C. 4121</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7939A178C5434FDCB3766E5F193EFD32"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (14), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAA53E9D3366E4FF4A3B475B1A2827664"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (15) by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9A9F08FE606649A8A6A1D60011C481C7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA51A1796378E404F903F4619004BB810" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HA3BFB3D91336485E9357F3EB56ED50A4"><enum>(16)</enum><text>the term <term>windstorm</term> means any hurricane, tornado, cyclone, typhoon, or other wind event.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


