<?xml version="1.0"?>
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H8CE240D0F6374001A8769EFB28C1EE2" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 5579 RH: Emergency Mortgage Loan Modification Act of 2008</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2008-03-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code> 
<calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 382</calendar> 
<congress display="yes">110th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 5579</legis-num> 
<associated-doc display="yes" role="report">[Report No. 110–615]</associated-doc> 
<current-chamber display="yes">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20080311">March 11, 2008</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000243">Mr. Castle</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000008">Mr. Kanjorski</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HBA00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<action> 
<action-date>May 1, 2008</action-date> 
<action-desc>Additional sponsor: <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor></action-desc> 
</action> 
<action> 
<action-date>May 1, 2008</action-date> 
<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc> 
<action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction> 
<action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on March 11, 2008</action-instruction> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To remove an impediment to troubled debt restructuring on the part of holders of residential mortgage loans, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body changed="added" committee-id="HBA00" display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="HDF53209F09CA454200CA19E218C9EB00" reported-display-style="italic" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H29F7F5F49F9449A59D62FCD4D1781506" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Emergency Mortgage Loan Modification Act of 2008</short-title></quote>.</text> </section>
<section id="HDAA47BD9E87B4E0D8C00FC8CB990F76F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Safe harbor for qualified loan modifications or workout plans for certain residential mortgage loans</header> 
<subsection id="H6B2D91E520C3494CAEAC9E8E2E9B1F42"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Standard for loan modifications or workout plans</header><text>Absent contractual provisions to the contrary—</text> 
<paragraph id="HFB834186D22E4254BD01A1D39C183B41"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the duty to maximize, or to not adversely affect, the recovery of total proceeds from pooled residential mortgage loans is owed by a servicer of such pooled loans to the securitization vehicle for the benefit of all investors and holders of beneficial interests in the pooled loans, in the aggregate, and not to any individual party or group of parties; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8C4FF27C07F043B9B8E0E7E514D9791"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a servicer of pooled residential mortgage loans shall be deemed to be acting on behalf of the securitization vehicle in the best interest of all investors and holders of beneficial interests in the pooled loans, in the aggregate, if for a loan that is in payment default under the loan agreement or for which payment default is imminent or reasonably foreseeable, the loan servicer makes reasonable and documented efforts to implement a modification or workout plan or, if such efforts are unsuccessful or such plan would be infeasible, engages in other loss mitigation, including accepting a short payment or partial discharge of principal, or agreeing to a short sale of the property, to the extent that the servicer reasonably believes the particular modification or workout plan or other mitigation actions will maximize the net present value to be realized on the loan, including over that which would be realized through foreclosure.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H5D853F635F0946BBBD73E264832D3B1E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Safe harbor</header><text>Absent contractual provisions to the contrary, a servicer of a residential mortgage loan that acts in a manner consistent with the duty set forth in subsection (a), shall not be liable for entering into a qualified loan modification or workout plan, to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H66FD1B83294344BDBC22E7D8E7DC045"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any person, based on that person’s ownership of a residential mortgage loan or any interest in a pool of residential mortgage loans or in securities that distribute payments out of the principal, interest and other payments in loans on the pool;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9A7E7D9ED1AC402582D423DB17700D7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any person who is obligated pursuant to a derivatives instrument to make payments determined in reference to any loan or any interest referred to in paragraph (1); or</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD805625119CF4BC49FAEA5E6192BD593"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any person that insures any loan or any interest referred to in paragraph (1) under any law or regulation of the United States or any law or regulation of any State or political subdivision of any State.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA255BD32A819425C9BA1DBE710CF1209"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>No provision of this section shall be construed as limiting the ability of a servicer to enter into loan modifications or workout plans other than qualified loan modification or workout plans.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HCE481FC82F494DD593B19BE8ED9D7B99"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section, the following definitions shall apply:</text> 
<paragraph id="H370457BF6C994BDEAD9D0787A6BBFDA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Qualified loan modification or workout plan</header><text>The term <quote>qualified loan modification or workout plan</quote> means a modification or plan that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8ABD17D50D8344858210E8D816DB18EA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is scheduled to remain in place until the borrower sells or refinances the property, or for at least 5 years from the date of adoption of the plan, whichever is sooner;</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB447F0928F08491DB132FB00BDB5C888"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not provide for a repayment schedule that results in negative amortization at any time; and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H23C20DACC91C4837840100B2DCB4FDBC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>does not require the borrower to pay additional points and fees.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4B469D03F2F94F17B75E1614D01CD427"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Negative amortization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of paragraph (1), the term <quote>negative amortization</quote> does not include the capitalization of delinquent interest and arrearages.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H301F9B45AEC745EB87F4C0253AF6B1B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Residential mortgage loan defined</header><text>The term <quote>residential mortgage loan</quote> means a loan that is secured by a lien on an owner-occupied residential dwelling.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H908B06F0184F4A2BA88CF68708958946"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Securitization vehicle</header><text>The term <quote>securitization vehicle</quote> means a trust, corporation, partnership, limited liability entity, special purpose entity, or other structure that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H631E90F1812A476D00B901B4D2ADE8B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is the issuer, or is created by the issuer, of mortgage pass-through certificates, participation certificates, mortgage-backed securities, or other similar securities backed by a pool of assets that includes residential mortgage loans; and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H59BFA5B45B554FBA8DF61372004557F3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>holds such loans.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H9FC24D0FD07540708243B467239CD4F0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Effective period</header><text>This section shall apply only with respect to qualified loan modification or workout plans initiated prior to January 1, 2011.</text> </subsection></section>
</legis-body> 
<endorsement display="yes"> 
<action-date>May 1, 2008</action-date> 
<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc> </endorsement> 
</bill> 


