<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="27491">
    <intro>    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <Doc-title>EXAMINING CHALLENGES IN PUERTO RICO'S RECOVERY AND THE ROLE OF THE FINANCIAL OVERSIGHT AND MANAGEMENT BOARD</Doc-title>
    <option>               FINANCIAL OVERSIGHT AND MANAGEMENT BOARD
=======================================================================
                           OVERSIGHT HEARING
                               before the
</option>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES</committee_name>
    <option>                     U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                       Tuesday, November 7, 2017
                               __________
                           Serial No. 115-27
                               __________
       Printed for the use of the Committee on Natural Resources
        Available via the World Wide Web: http://www.govinfo.gov
                                   or
          Committee address: http://naturalresources.house.gov
                              ________ 
                 U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
 27-491 PDF                 WASHINGTON : 2018       
____________________________________________________________________
 For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing Office,
Internet:bookstore.gpo.gov. Phone:toll free (866)512-1800;DC area (202)512-1800
  Fax:(202) 512-2104 Mail:Stop IDCC,Washington,DC 20402-001              
</option>
</intro>
    <committeeComposition>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES</comitteeM_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROB BISHOP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RAUL M. GRIJALVA</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ranking Democratic Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Don Young</Pname>
        <Plocation> AK</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Grace F. Napolitano</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Chairman Emeritus</Pname>
        <Plocation>Chairman Emeritus</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Madeleine Z. Bordallo</Pname>
        <Plocation> GU</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Louie Gohmert</Pname>
        <Plocation> TX</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jim Costa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Chairman</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Gregorio Kilili Camacho Sablan</Pname>
        <Plocation> </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug Lamborn</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CNMI</Pname>
        <Plocation>CNMI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Robert J. Wittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Niki Tsongas</Pname>
        <Plocation> MA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Tom McClintock</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jared Huffman</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Stevan Pearce</Pname>
        <Plocation> NM</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Ranking Member</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Ranking Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Glenn Thompson</Pname>
        <Plocation> PA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Alan S. Lowenthal</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul A. Gosar</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Donald S. Beyer</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Raul R. Labrador</Pname>
        <Plocation> ID</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Norma J. Torres</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Scott R. Tipton</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Ruben Gallego</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug LaMalfa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Colleen Hanabusa</Pname>
        <Plocation> HI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jeff Denham</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Nanette Diaz Barragan</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul Cook</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darren Soto</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Bruce Westerman</Pname>
        <Plocation> AR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>A. Donald McEachin</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Garret Graves</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Anthony G. Brown</Pname>
        <Plocation> MD</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jody B. Hice</Pname>
        <Plocation> GA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Wm. Lacy Clay</Pname>
        <Plocation> MO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Aumua Amata Coleman Radewagen</Pname>
        <Plocation> AS</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jimmy Gomez</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darin LaHood</Pname>
        <Plocation> IL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Daniel Webster</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jack Bergman</Pname>
        <Plocation> MI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Liz Cheney</Pname>
        <Plocation> WY</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Mike Johnson</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jenniffer Gonzalez-Colon</Pname>
        <Plocation> PR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Greg Gianforte</Pname>
        <Plocation> MT</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Cody Stewart</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chief of Staff</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Lisa Pittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chief Counsel</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>David Watkins</Pname>
        <Plocation> Democratic Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
</committeeComposition>
    <Directory>
    <table-of-content>CONTENTS</table-of-content>
    <peopleSpeaker>   Hearing held on Tuesday</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>November</peopleinfo>
    <Members>Statement of Members:</Members>
    <Speaker>Hon Rob Bishop</Speaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Utah Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>Statement of Witnesses:</witnesses>
    <Witness>Hon Raul M Grijalva</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Arizona Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Natalie Jaresko</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Executive Director Financial Oversight and Management Board for Puerto Rico</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Noel Zamot</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Revitalization Coordinator Financial Oversight and Management Board for Puerto Rico</peopleinfo>
    <submittedMaterial>Additional Materials Submitted for the Record:</submittedMaterial>
    <SubmittedMaterial>List of documents submitted for the record retained in the Committee's official files Massachusetts Black and Latino Legislative Caucus</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Letter to Rep Tsongas</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>OVERSIGHT HEARING ON EXAMINING CHALLENGES IN PUERTO RICO'S RECOVERY AND THE ROLE OF THE FINANCIAL OVERSIGHT AND MANAGEMENT BOARD  Tuesday</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>US House of Representatives Committee on Natural Resources Washington DC</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>The Committee met</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>at : am in</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>room</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Hon Rob Bishop [Chairman of the Committee] presiding</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Present: Representatives Bishop</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Lamborn Wittman</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>McClintock</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Thompson Labrador</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Westerman</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Hice LaHood</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Johnson</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Gianforte; Grijalva Napolitano</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Bordallo</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Sablan Tsongas</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Gallego</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Barragan Soto</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Gomez Also present: Representatives Serrano</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Gutierrez</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Velazquez</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>and Ruiz</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Mr Ruiz; the gentleman from New York</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Mr Serrano; the</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>gentleman from Illinois</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Mr Gutierrez; and the gentlewoman</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>from New York</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>all be allowed to sit with the</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Committee and participate in the hearing And I notice at least three of you are already here</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>thank you</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Hearing no objections</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>that is so ordered</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Under Committee Rule (f)</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>any oral opening statements at</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>the hearing are limited to the Chairman</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>the Ranking Minority</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Member</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>and the Vice Chair This will allow us to hear from our</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>witnesses sooner I am asking unanimous consent that any other Member that has an opening statement</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>they will be made part of</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>the hearing record if they are submitted to the Subcommittee Clerk by : pm today Once again</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>that will be so ordered</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>First</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>I appreciate the witnesses being on the panel Let's</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>start with the opening statements first</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>and I will recognize</peopleinfo>
    <option>                     FROM THE STATE OF UTAH
    The Chairman. We are here today to look at the hurricane-
impacted territories of Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands. 
Next week, the governors from Puerto Rico and the Virgin 
Islands will be here with us also to testify.
    Before we start, I want it very clear that our thoughts and 
prayers are with those who are still suffering in the Virgin 
Islands and Puerto Rico, as well as in Florida and Texas who 
have suffered these hurricane damages. I also want to thank the 
emergency responders for all their hard work and kind efforts 
and what they have done.
    There is still a humanitarian crisis going on in Puerto 
Rico and the Virgin Islands, but today we are going to 
concentrate on Puerto Rico. The hurricanes may have gone, but 
now mudslides are threatening people. So, this is not over yet, 
and there is much work that still has to be done.
    Today, the Committee is going to examine the challenges to 
recovery in Puerto Rico and the role of the Financial Oversight 
and Management Board.
    The two hurricanes that hit may have been historic, but 
they exposed a state of affairs in Puerto Rico that existed 
well before any of the hurricanes made landfall. Decades of 
mismanagement led to a paralyzing debt burden. Last year, 
Congress stepped forward with a bipartisan PROMESA bill that 
was signed into law to try to rectify this particular problem.
    The Board has, so far, been focused on governance reform. 
But now, with this hurricane, there is also other work that the 
Board must be doing, and the Board's work has become even more 
complicated as we move forward.
    For example, we have to deal with the Puerto Rico Electric 
Power Authority, known as PREPA, which was already bankrupt, 
severely mismanaged, with a long history of inadequate 
maintenance and political cronyism.
    Recovering the power grid remains of paramount interest and 
importance to us. Energy is not only important to the people's 
lives in the emergency situation, but if Puerto Rico is to 
economically recover and become vibrant, it has to have 
reliable, abundant, and affordable energy. And that is really 
one of the key elements if we are going to do anything 
whatsoever with that.
    I appreciate the appointment of the Chief Transformation 
Officer of PREPA, and I appreciate the fact that the Board is 
now looking at contract review policies as part of the role of 
PROMESA. These are decisions that make it important, because we 
do not want another situation like Whitefish to happen again, 
which may have had some initial purpose to it, but the 
procedure was certainly suspect. And I appreciate that there 
has to be some kind of oversight for this going through there.
    What we are concerned with today is making sure that the 
Oversight and Management Board, the PROMESA board, has the 
tools they need to fulfill this responsibility and move 
forward, and also has cooperation. We have four entities down 
there on the island that are working on the recovery. There is 
the Commonwealth government, the Oversight Board, and there are 
also two Federal agencies, FEMA and the Army Corps of 
Engineers. All four of them have to work together. Otherwise, 
it is simply chaos. This cannot be an adversarial situation. 
And what we are going to do today is make sure that we have the 
tools necessary to see that go into fruition. The Board is not 
going to go away until their job happens to be finished at some 
particular time.
    So, in today's hearing we are not going to ascribe blame. I 
hope we don't try to play politics. Our goal is to fix the 
problems and help the people. The problems in Puerto Rico and 
the Virgin Islands are too serious for us to politicize and try 
to make headlines. We owe the citizens more than that.
    Last week, or yesterday, actually, Mr. Graves came back 
from Puerto Rico with Representative Gonzalez. Ten days ago, 
there were five of us that went down there: Mr. Denham, Mrs. 
Torres, Mr. Brown, myself, and Ms. Gonzalez, along with the 
Majority Leader and the Minority Whip, to see firsthand what is 
happening down there in both the Virgin Islands and in Puerto 
Rico. It is very clear from what we saw that the devastation 
and the suffering is sobering, and it is real.
    [Slide.]
    The Chairman. What was the positive aspect of this is, even 
though their homes are broken, their spirits are not. We went 
into the interior, not staying around San Juan, into this 
particular community. As you can see, there was a bridge that 
connected the one side of the valley with the other side of the 
valley where the stores and the roads and the community were. 
That bridge was washed out in the hurricane. That is all that 
is left.
    The ingenuity of those 22 families on the other side is 
brilliant, because they have jerry-rigged this contraption, 
which means it simply is a zip line with a supermarket cart 
attached to it, where they can take it from the one side, where 
the stores are, put the supplies in, and then manually bring it 
across to the other side, a very ingenious contraption.
    It is also one of those things in which we were able to, 
you notice there is a very wooden ladder going up, give me the 
next slide, if you would.
    [Slide.]
    The Chairman. And Tony here actually, Representative Brown, 
was the first one to go across the river bed, to go up that 
ladder, followed by the rest of us. I promise you OSHA did not 
actually certify that particular ladder.
    As we all walked to the other side to meet those 22 
families that are not there, give me the next one, if you 
could, and I think Mrs. Torres can verify this, going down was 
a lot slower than it was going up. Yes, that ladder.
    [Slide.]
    The Chairman. But this is what I found on the other side. 
The Governor and Representative Gonzalez are there, and I have 
to give kudos to Representative Gonzalez. No one works harder 
to try to help her constituents down there than Representative 
Gonzalez has. She is not only the first female Representative 
from Puerto Rico, she is also the youngest they have ever had. 
And that energy is shown every time she has gone with every 
single group that has gone down there, to show them exactly 
what is taking place in that time.
    But what I want to point out is the teenager that is 
standing with us right there. I had the opportunity of meeting 
that kid on the other side. He is one of the 22 families that 
are cut off from the rest of the village, using the zip line 
and the wooden ladder, just trying to get from side to side.
    But that kid was amazing. He was a fascinating kid, he was 
interested in what was going on, he was intellectual, he was 
fluent, and he wanted to become involved in the future. I was 
so excited talking to him, because that kid, that kid, is the 
future of Puerto Rico. That kid is why I know that Puerto Rico 
is not just going to recover, they are going to succeed. And 
the spirit that he had is the kind of spirit we saw in all of 
the citizens with whom we were talking that realize they were 
not after some kind of blame, they are simply after a way of 
making their lives better.
    What I want our Committee to do, which has general 
jurisdiction over there, is to make sure that we have the tools 
for the Board, and we have the tools for the government to make 
sure that the dreams that that kid has will be realized. That 
is Puerto Rico to me.
</option>
    <option>   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman, Committee on 
                           Natural Resources
    Good morning. This meeting is a continuation of oversight of 
hurricane-impacted territories of Puerto Rico and the U.S. Virgin 
Islands. In addition to today's hearing, next week we will hear from 
the governors of Puerto Rico and the U.S. Virgin Islands.
    Let me begin with thoughts and prayers for these communities, and 
offer thanks to emergency responders and everyone involved for their 
bravery during hardship. In both territories, the detestation is 
overwhelming.
    Today, the Committee will examine recovery challenges in Puerto 
Rico and the role of the Financial Oversight and Management Board.
    Hurricane Maria, although historic in its severity, exposed the 
tragic state of affairs that existed on the island well before its 
landfall. Decades of mismanagement led to a paralyzing debt burden. The 
government and its municipalities, already constrained by the fiscal 
crisis, are now severely overwhelmed despite Federal support.
    Last year, Congress took a step forward to help Puerto Rico 
restructure and reform with the creation of a Federal Oversight Board 
under a law known as PROMESA that was signed into law on a bipartisan 
basis in July 2016. Since their appointment, the Board has focused on 
governance reform, the formulation of fiscal plans and budgets for the 
territory and the facilitation of debt restructuring. With the recent 
devastation, however, the Board's work has become even more difficult 
and complicated.
    For instance, the Puerto Rico Electric Power Authority, known as 
PREPA, was already bankrupt and severely mismanaged with a long history 
of inadequate maintenance and political cronyism. Restoring the power 
grid is paramount to immediate emergency needs. Long-term energy 
transformation is equally important. Transparent accountability at 
PREPA, now and moving forward, is essential for both to succeed. The 
Board will play a critical role ensuring all parts of this puzzle 
align.
    The Board's actions in this regard include the appointment of a 
Chief Transformation Officer of PREPA, Mr. Noel Zamot, and the 
implementation of a contract review policy in accordance with PROMESA. 
Both steps will add needed transparency, accountability and structure 
to the island's recovery.
    While there is no question the Board provides a critical nexus for 
Congress and the Administration to carry out a coordinated recovery 
effort, there are concerns whether the tools the Board possesses can 
meet the challenge and ensure long-term success. Transparent 
accountability at all levels is essential to a sustained recovery with 
the full support of Congress. With this imperative in my Committee, and 
strong cooperation between the Commonwealth, the Oversight Board and 
Federal partners--including FEMA and USACE--we can achieve a viable 
path forward for Puerto Rico.
    [Slideshow.]
    Ten days ago, a congressional delegation led by the House Majority 
and Minority Leader, visited both territories and Florida. In Puerto 
Rico, residents are still suffering. The infrastructure is demolished 
in many areas. Communities remain isolated.
    During our visit to the central mountainous region of Puerto Rico, 
we met with residents in the remote town of Utuado. A bridge connecting 
the main north-south road was entirely wiped out. The residents had 
built a pulley system overhanging the divide. Attaching a shopping cart 
to the line, the jerry-rigged contraption was their lifeline to food, 
water and supplies. We all walked across the river and up the stairs. 
We spoke with residents. The conversations were fascinating. While 
homes are broken and lives have been lost, spirits are not.
    In this context, the point today isn't to ascribe blame or browbeat 
or play politics. The goal isn't to shame for shame sake. The goal is 
to fix problems and help people. The problems in Puerto Rico are too 
serious for us to politicize or seek headlines. We owe these citizens 
more than that.
    I thank our witnesses for appearing today and look forward to 
today's testimony.
                                 ______
    The Chairman. With that, I apologize for going over, but I 
didn't care, I wanted you to see that kid.
    [Laughter.]
    The Chairman. I will yield to the Ranking Member.
</option>
    <option>               CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF ARIZONA
    Mr. Grijalva. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Yourself, and the 
Members that have gone to Puerto Rico, have been on the ground, 
and have firsthand experience and observations about the 
urgency and the need for this Congress to respond in a 
proactive and transparent way, and in a way that deals with the 
emergency and the urgency as it is now. As we go forward, how 
do we build sustainability, resilience for the long-term, both 
in the economy and the growth of the rebirth of the 
infrastructure on the island of Puerto Rico.
    If a man is drowning in the ocean, you don't stop to tell 
him he should take swimming lessons. If a woman is having a 
heart attack, you don't take time to preach to her about the 
value of a low-fat, gluten-free diet. Instead, you act 
immediately to save lives. Our American brothers and sisters 
living on the island of Puerto Rico are drowning in the ocean. 
Their water, sewer, transportation, electricity, health, and 
banking systems are in the midst of what we would consider 
grave danger, if not close to a fatal heart attack.
    Puerto Rico, quite frankly, does not need a lecture. They 
don't need advice. What Puerto Rico needs, at this juncture in 
time and in history, is help, our help.
    A month-and-a-half after Hurricane Maria hit the island 
with winds of 150 miles per hour, we still find two-thirds of 
the Puerto Rico households without electricity, and 20 percent 
are without potable, safe drinking water. The island continues 
to see landslides, the record flooding that occurred, hundreds 
of blocked roads, thousands of fallen trees, and damaged homes 
and buildings. Tens of thousands of people have left Puerto 
Rico, and thousands of businesses remain closed.
    Puerto Rico's government expects an estimated cash loss of 
$1.7 billion as a result of reduced collections, with an 
additional $1.18 billion loss in power and water income. Those 
two agencies are currently running on cash reserves.
    The American people in Puerto Rico are counting on us to 
help rebuild the island, starting with the basics. The disaster 
supplemental spending package we passed is a start, but we need 
to do much more, and we need to do it immediately.
    The decimated electrical grid and water and sewer systems 
must be restored, and no more sweetheart deals to fly-by-night 
companies. That needs to stop, and it needs to stop 
immediately, as well.
    FEMA was slow to arrive and slow to engage. Even the 
President's most recent amendment to the disaster declaration 
issued on November 2 requires a 10 percent cost match for 
certain assistance, while piling on extra requirements. These 
attempts to get more blood out of a stone also need to stop.
    Once the lights are back on, and the families have access 
to clean drinking water and medical care, then Congress can 
turn its attention to the future of the island and its economy. 
We should not be asked to look away from this Administration's 
embarrassing recovery effort, and respond to Puerto Rican 
families not with the help they need, but with the help that 
would please investors.
    To use this natural disaster as an excuse to give even more 
advantages to investors who bear much of the responsibility for 
the shameful fiscal crisis that Puerto Rico finds itself in is 
wrong. To use this natural disaster as an excuse to say that 
those living on the island no longer deserve flood prevention 
regulations or strong protections for clean air and clean 
water, or that they no longer deserve the chance to participate 
in transparent, public planning processes would be wrong.
    Title V of PROMESA already gives investors the dual gift of 
deregulation and privatization for no-bid infrastructure 
projects. If the Majority would like to use the hurricane 
devastation to ram these projects through even faster, then 
that would be a mistake. How is it in the interest of the 
people of Puerto Rico to get rid of the ability for the public 
to comment on these projects, or to remove the Energy 
Commission's authority to make sure that the project will work 
with long-term grid plans? The Oversight Board has enough power 
and doesn't really need more.
    Our response to human suffering has to be about food, 
shelter, and water first, not deregulation or politics. It is 
time to assess the damage, get a real relief package together 
as fast as possible, and start rebuilding in a sustainable way.
    I hope that all my colleagues will join me in getting 
resources to the people who need them most, and resist the urge 
to haggle over the price tag or insist on weakening 
environmental standards and public processes in exchange for 
aid needed to save lives and rebuild communities.
</option>
    <option>   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Raul M. Grijalva, Ranking Member, 
                     Committee on Natural Resources
    Mr. Chairman, if you see a man drowning in the ocean, you don't 
stop to tell him he should take swimming lessons. If a woman is having 
a heart attack, you don't take time to preach to her about the value of 
a low-fat diet. Instead, you act immediately to save lives.
    Our American brothers and sisters living on the island of Puerto 
Rico are drowning in the ocean. Their water, sewer, transportation, 
electricity, and banking systems are in the midst of what could be a 
fatal heart attack.
    Puerto Rico does not need a lecture. They don't need advice. Puerto 
Rico needs our help!
    A month and a half after Hurricane Maria hit the island with winds 
of 150 miles per hour, more than two-thirds of Puerto Rico households 
are still without electricity and 20 percent are without drinking 
water. The island has seen landslides, record flooding, hundreds of 
blocked roads, thousands of fallen trees, and damaged homes and 
buildings. Tens of thousands of people have left Puerto Rico and 
thousands of businesses remain closed.
    Puerto Rico's government expects an estimated cash loss of $1.7 
billion as a result of reduced collections, with an additional 
estimated $1.18 billion loss in power and water income. Those two 
agencies are currently running on cash reserves.
    The American people in Puerto Rico are counting on us to help 
rebuild the island, starting with the basics. The disaster supplemental 
spending package we passed is a start, but we need to do much more and 
we need to do it now.
    The decimated electrical grid and water and sewer systems must be 
restored; no more sweetheart deals to fly by-night companies.
    FEMA was slow to arrive and slow to engage. Even the President's 
most recent amendment to the disaster declaration issued on November 2 
requires a 10 percent cost match for certain assistance while piling on 
extra requirements. These attempts to get more blood from this stone 
need to stop.
    Once the lights are back on and families have access to clean 
drinking water and medical care, then Congress can turn its attention 
to the future of the island and its economy. But now, we are being 
asked to look away from this Administration's embarrassing recovery 
effort and respond to Puerto Rico families, not with the help they 
need, but with the help that pleases investors.
    To use this natural disaster as an excuse to give even more 
advantages to the investors who bear much of the responsibility for the 
fiscal crisis would be shameful. To use this natural disaster as an 
excuse to say that those living on the island no longer deserve flood 
prevention regulations or strong protections for clean air and water, 
or that they no longer deserve the chance to participate in 
transparent, public planning processes would be wrong.
    Title V of PROMESA already gives investors the dual gift of 
deregulation and privatization for no-bid infrastructure projects. The 
Majority would like to use the hurricane devastation to ram those 
projects through faster.
    How is it in the interest of the people of Puerto Rico to get rid 
of the ability for the public to comment on these projects, or to 
remove the Energy Commission's authority to make sure the project will 
work with long-term grid plans? As if the Oversight Board didn't 
already have enough power.
    Our response to human suffering has to be about food, shelter and 
water first, not deregulation or politics. It's time to assess the 
damage, get a real relief package together as fast as possible and 
start rebuilding in a sustainable way. I hope my Republican colleagues 
will join me in getting resources to the people who need them most, and 
resist the urge to haggle over the price tag or insist on weakening 
environmental standards in exchange for aid needed to save lives and 
rebuild communities.
                                 ______
    Mr. Grijalva. With that, Mr. Chairman, I yield back.
    The Chairman. Thank you. I appreciate that. We will now 
recognize our witnesses who are here.
    I would first like to recognize, starting from my left: Ms. 
Natalie Jaresko, who is the Executive Director of the PROMESA 
Board; Mr. Noel Zamot, the Revitalization Coordinator of the 
Financial Oversight and Management Board for Puerto Rico; and 
also Mayor Perez Otero, who is here. I appreciate you getting 
here at the last moment. I realize it was a rush job to get 
here. Thank you for joining us.
    I speak German, I don't speak Spanish, so when you are 
recognized, you are going to tell us the name of your community 
and where it is, because otherwise no one will ever find it if 
I try to do that. So, thank you for being here.
    I also want to say I am a little bit chagrined. We were 
originally going to have a couple more panelists here. Last 
night, two of the witnesses decided not to be here. One was the 
PROMESA Director. He was here specifically to talk about 
Whitefish.
    [Laughter.]
    The Chairman. I am sorry, PREPA, the PREPA Director. He was 
going to be here to answer the questions about the Whitefish 
contract. I understand there are circumstances that require 
their efforts back on the island, but I am sad that it is going 
to be there.
    A couple of weeks ago we requested some documents. Those 
documents arrived very late last Friday. We have only looked 
through them very, very briefly. Already there are some other 
circumstances within those documents that add more questions, 
which means at some point I would like those to be answered, 
and someone needs to look at that perhaps next week.
    When the Governor is here with others, we can have somebody 
from PREPA go through that. So, I am very disappointed they are 
not here to answer our questions today, but that is the way it 
is, because, obviously, we will take them at their word that 
their work there on the island is significant, it is important, 
and it needs to be done here.
    Mr. Brown, you were not here originally when I showed the 
slides. I did show the slides of you going down the 
mountainside, going through the river, and up that ladder. I 
just want you to know that you still have your athleticism and 
dexterity, because you put mountain goats in Utah to shame with 
the way you went down and climbed back up again. And it is your 
fault, because you were the first one to go over, and you kind 
of shamed the rest of us into following you.
    [Laughter.]
    The Chairman. Do you want to respond?
    Mr. Brown. Mr. Chairman, as a point of personal privilege, 
I do want to, in all seriousness, thank you for ensuring that I 
was able to accompany you, Leader McCarthy, and Whip Hoyer on 
what I thought was an important and enlightening delegation to 
Puerto Rico, the U.S. Virgin Islands, and the Keys, and I hope 
later today to be able to share some of my observations. Thank 
you, Mr. Chairman.
    The Chairman. No, thank you. Thank you very much. And 
thanks to all the Members who actually have been down there. I 
mentioned to Representative Graves that you just came back from 
there yesterday.
    Eventually you will shave, right? Never mind, never mind.
    [Laughter.]
    Mr. Graves. You know, Mr. Chairman, I have been seeking to 
be more like you for some period of time now. And I was going 
to color my hair white, but I decided that my wife would not be 
happy about that. So, I decided to grow a beard and put little 
white speckles in there.
    The Chairman. If you are going to be like me, it is going 
to be more than just speckles.
    [Laughter.]
    The Chairman. All right. Now, to get on to significant 
stuff, let me turn to Ms. Jaresko from the Board for your 
testimony.
    I would like to coach all the witnesses that our Committee 
Rules give you 5 minutes for oral testimony. Your written 
testimony is already part of the record. Anything you want to 
add to it will be part of it. If you have not been here before, 
these are manual microphones, so you have to turn them on to 
speak. And please watch the clock in front of you.
    When the green light is on, that means everything is cool. 
When it hits yellow, that means, like in traffic in the United 
States, you have to speed up as fast as you can. When it goes 
to red, that is when I want you to stop. And don't make me have 
to cut you off. I do it with our Members with glee, but I don't 
want to do it with you guys.
    So, Ms. Jaresko, if you would, you are recognized for 5 
minutes.
</option>
    <option>   OVERSIGHT AND MANAGEMENT BOARD FOR PUERTO RICO, SAN JUAN, 
                          PUERTO RICO
    Ms. Jaresko. Thank you, Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member 
Grijalva, members of the Committee, and Mayor Perez. I am 
Natalie Jaresko, Executive Director of the Puerto Rico 
Financial Oversight and Management Board. Thank you for this 
opportunity to update the Committee on the work of the Board 
and the situation in Puerto Rico in light of the tragic damage 
done to the island and its people by Hurricane Maria and, to a 
lesser extent, Hurricane Irma.
    I have submitted written testimony for the record, and I 
look forward to the Committee's questions. I want to use my 
oral statement to make just a few points.
    First, I want to thank this Committee, Congress, the 
Administration, and the American people for the generous just-
passed emergency aid package. Likewise, we are deeply grateful 
for the extraordinary efforts of FEMA, the U.S. military, the 
Army Corps of Engineers, and all those involved in this 
historic relief effort.
    I also wish to acknowledge the tireless efforts of Governor 
Rossello, his administration, local mayors, and all those in 
Puerto Rico who are saving lives and supporting the recovery 
efforts.
    Having served as Minister of Finance of Ukraine in times of 
war and fiscal crisis, I understand the complicated and often 
difficult measures that are required in times like these. I 
lived through the painful process of determining how to use 
limited funds to ensure that government could effectively 
govern, despite the realities. And I know the importance of the 
need to restore confidence and build a recovery that inspires 
individuals and businesses to play their vital and valuable 
ongoing role in rebuilding Puerto Rico.
    As you well know, the Board was established by Congress to 
support the fiscal and economic turnaround of Puerto Rico, as 
well as to restructure the sizable debt obligations that the 
Commonwealth and a number of governmental entities have 
incurred over the years. The Board is fully authorized to deal 
with the fiscal and debt issues that Puerto Rico faced before 
Hurricane Maria.
    After the hurricane, it is even more critical that the 
Board be able to operate quickly and decisively. The Board, 
therefore, asks that Congress underscore the importance of this 
Board in this post-hurricane environment by clarifying that we 
have this critical role to play in any Federal funding that the 
Congress appropriates, which will, in large measure, define 
Puerto Rico's future, given the devastation to the economy and 
in any long-term liquidity mechanism.
    Clarification in these regards will provide us with more 
agility and certainty, avoid time-consuming and costly 
litigation, and reduce the risks to the overall fiscal and 
economic recovery of Puerto Rico.
    I would like to conclude by outlining four ways we have 
been pursuing our mission since the hurricane.
    First, disciplined liquidity assistance processes. In my 
written testimony, I have tried to summarize the hurricane-
caused liquidity needs as we best see them. In short, because 
of the damage to the ability to collect revenues, the 
disruption of the underlying economic activity, and storm 
recovery spending, the Commonwealth and its instrumentalities 
are facing billions of dollars in cash shortfalls, just to 
provide the basic functions of government.
    It is essential that the process of providing liquidity 
assistance does not become detached from the fiscal plan 
process that is the essence of our charge under PROMESA. The 
longer-term solution that Congress is contemplating in the next 
emergency supplemental should, in our view, have formalized 
mechanisms to tie liquidity relief to the fiscal plans.
    Second, revision of those fiscal plans. We are well aware 
that, just as you have stated, Mr. Chairman, we will have to 
revise the certified fiscal plans in light of the hurricane's 
devastation. This process will take several weeks. The Board 
will hold three listening sessions to which all stakeholders 
are invited to provide input to those fiscal plans, as part of 
the revision process. And we have also agreed with the Federal 
mediators to hold two additional sessions with creditor 
stakeholders.
    Our aim is to move deliberately to prepare and approve 
revised plans, and the deadline for the Commonwealth, PREPA, 
and PRASA to submit these draft fiscal plans to the Board is 
December 22, 2017, with review and revision ongoing through the 
certification date of February 2, 2018. Deadlines for other 
entities will follow closely on the heels of that.
    Third, a chief transformation officer for PREPA. As the 
Committee is aware, the Board has recently named Noel Zamot as 
Chief Transformation Officer of PREPA, with all the powers of a 
CEO, and reporting to the Board. We believe this is absolutely 
essential, both to restoring service as soon as possible, and 
to creating a sustainable, efficient, resilient, and fiscally 
accountable power system for the island.
    While the Board is confident that PROMESA, coupled with 
fundamental aspects of bankruptcy law, gives us the power and 
responsibility to do as we have done, some parties are 
vigorously contesting our authority and proceedings before the 
Title III judge. To avoid uncertainty and lengthy delays in 
litigation, congressional reaffirmation of our exercise of our 
authority is welcome.
    Fourth, contract review. We have also implemented a 
contract review policy as a tool to ensure transparency 
throughout the government for the benefit of the people of 
Puerto Rico and all stakeholders. The policy applies to all 
contracts in which the Commonwealth or any covered 
instrumentality is a counter-party, including those with the 
Federal Government, state governments, and private parties. The 
policy provides that all contracts of $10 million or more must 
be submitted to the Board for its approval before execution.
    In addition, the Board retains the authority to adopt other 
methods, such as random sampling of contracts below that $10 
million threshold, to assure that they promote market 
competition and are not inconsistent with the approved fiscal 
plan.
    Again, Mr. Chairman, Ranking Member, and members of the 
Committee, we deeply appreciate your concern for the American 
citizens who live in Puerto Rico. And on behalf of the Board, I 
pledge to continue to work with you to do all we can to meet 
the new challenges and to achieve PROMESA's goals. I look 
forward to your questions.
</option>
    <option> Prepared Statement of Natalie Jaresko, Executive Director, Financial 
             Oversight and Management Board for Puerto Rico
    Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva and members of the 
Committee, I am Natalie Jaresko, Executive Director of the Puerto Rico 
Financial Oversight and Management Board (the ``Board''). Thank you for 
this opportunity to update the Committee on the work of the Board and 
the situation in Puerto Rico in light of the tragic damage done to the 
Island and its people by Hurricane Maria and to a lesser extent Irma. 
Puerto Rico and its residents were engaging in often heroic efforts to 
help those who suffered greatly from Irma when Maria unleashed its fury 
on us. My testimony will concentrate on the Maria-caused challenges.
    First, I want to thank this Committee, Congress, the Administration 
and the American people for the generous, recently-enacted emergency 
aid to the Island along with support for our fellow citizens in Texas, 
Florida, California and USVI. Likewise, we are deeply grateful for the 
efforts of FEMA, the U.S. military, the Army Corps of Engineers and all 
those involved in this historic relief effort. I also wish to 
acknowledge the efforts of Governor Rossello, local mayors, and all 
those in Puerto Rico who are saving lives and supporting the recovery 
efforts. Maria was the worst storm to hit Puerto Rico in the past 100 
years. The entire island was devastated.
    As you know, the Board was established by Congress to support the 
fiscal and economic turnaround of Puerto Rico, as well as restructure 
the sizable debt obligations that the Commonwealth and a number of 
additional governmental entities in Puerto Rico have incurred over the 
years. The terrible impact of Hurricane Maria makes these challenges 
both more difficult and more urgent. The Board and I have been working 
every day to make sure that we are providing the kind of support, 
leadership and oversight necessary to help the Island.
    The day after Hurricane Maria hit, the Board provided Governor 
Rossello with the authority to reallocate up to $1 billion of the 
Commonwealth's budget to give the government flexibility to respond to 
the most pressing needs presented by the first weeks of the crisis. 
Shortly thereafter, we focused on the need for emergency liquidity 
assistance to deal with the fact that the hurricane caused revenues to 
drop and expenditures to increase. We worked closely with the Governor 
and his staff to estimate the dimensions of the cash-flow shortfall 
caused by the hurricane's damage and disruption. We jointly presented 
the results of that work to the Administration and Congress. Again, we 
thank the Administration and Congress for including liquidity relief 
via the Community Disaster Loan Program with the other essential 
assistance provided in the emergency supplemental legislation. We know 
that longer term liquidity to keep the government functioning and to 
provide key basic services to the residents of the Island is a subject 
that we will need to continue to work to address with the Governor, 
Congress and the Administration.
    I served as Minister of Finance of Ukraine after the Revolution of 
Dignity and during the war in the east. I understand the complicated 
and often difficult measures that are required in times of crisis. I 
lived through the painful process of determining how to use limited 
funds in the Treasury to ensure the government could effectively govern 
despite the realities. I know the importance of the need to restore 
confidence and build a recovery that inspires individuals and 
businesses to play their valuable ongoing role in rebuilding Puerto 
Rico. The work of recovery and rebuilding will be long and taxing. In 
many ways it has barely begun. For these reasons, we will continue to 
do everything in our power to help the Governor and local authorities 
in the ongoing efforts.
    The hard truth is that the Island now needs help--emergency and 
restoration funds and assistance on an unprecedented scale. Before the 
hurricanes, the Board was determined that Puerto Rico and its 
instrumentalities could achieve balanced budgets, work its way through 
its debt problems, and develop a sustainable economy without Federal 
aid. That is simply no longer possible. Without unprecedented levels of 
help from the United States government, the recovery we were planning 
for will fail.
    More immediately, there are areas of pressing need--problem areas 
turned into full-blown emergencies by the hurricanes. These include 
energy, water, housing, and health care. While conditions have 
improved--for example, distribution of fuel has normalized and grocery 
store shelves have been restocked--the Island continues to lack 
electricity, which will not only frustrate economic recovery but 
impacts daily life, particularly for people who need access to 
refrigeration for their medicines. Thousands remain in shelters, 
including seniors, people with disabilities and the bedridden. Tens of 
thousands of houses do not have roofs, and the installation of 
temporary tarps will not be completed for months.
    In PROMESA, Congress charged us with guiding and overseeing the 
restoration of the Island to fiscal health via long-term fiscal 
planning and annual balanced budgeting, restoring its ability to access 
private capital via both debt restructuring and economic development, 
and, as part of that, helping the Island transition to a sustainable 
economic model that provides opportunities for our citizens.
    We are all too well aware, and as you, Mr. Chairman, and this 
Committee well knows, that Hurricanes Irma and Maria have made our job 
much more challenging. The hurricane-caused damage has added greatly--
and will add greatly--to the financial distress of the Commonwealth and 
its instrumentalities. In our view, while our job has become more 
difficult, it has also become ever more important.
    Every dollar of relief funds must be used to address the hurricane-
caused needs of those on the Island and to meet the extraordinary 
challenges of rebuilding a more resilient Puerto Rico with a 
revitalized economy. It would be tragic if the hurricane-recovery 
efforts were not integrated into the broader and lasting plan for 
economic recovery upon which the Board and the Government were focused 
prior to the hurricane.
    Central to avoiding such outcomes will be rethinking and adapting 
the Fiscal Plans created before the hurricanes in a way that is 
cognizant of the on-the-ground realities of a hurricane-devastated 
island but that does not lose sight of our charge to restore Puerto 
Rico to long-term financial health. I will describe in some detail in 
this testimony how we are approaching the dual challenges.
    Hurricane Maria and the infusion of Federal rebuilding funds it 
will involve likewise raise questions about how to apply PROMESA to the 
challenges ahead which were not part of the original thinking when 
PROMESA became law.
                           our work pre-maria
    The period after the passage of PROMESA and before Hurricanes Irma 
and Maria stretched a little more than a year. In that time, much had 
been done to fulfill our charge to work with the government of Puerto 
Rico to ensure Puerto Rico achieves fiscal balance, to provide a path 
for its return to the capital markets, and to restore economic growth 
and opportunity for the people of the Island.
    Consistent with its charge under PROMESA, the Board conducted an 
independent and comprehensive analysis of Puerto Rico's fiscal 
situation. Before the hurricanes, Puerto Rico had over $74 billion in 
debt, over $53 billion of unfunded pension liabilities, an economy that 
had contracted nearly 15 percent over the last decade, and a nearly 50 
percent poverty rate. In addition, Puerto Rico's structural budget 
deficits were projected to average 50 percent of recurring revenues. 
Severe liquidity challenges and persistent budget deficits have 
contributed to a perilous lack of investment in infrastructure.
    The certified Fiscal Plan for Puerto Rico and those for its covered 
instrumentalities charted a path for a turnaround without new Federal 
funding. The fiscal and structural reform measures--from transforming 
the energy sector and modernizing labor laws to reducing government 
spending by approximately 30 percent over 3 years--were ambitious and 
required unprecedented levels of effort by the government of Puerto 
Rico.
    The government of Puerto Rico was acutely aware of the difficult 
choices necessary to achieve fiscal balance and restore economic growth 
when it developed 10-year Fiscal Plans for Puerto Rico and its 
instrumentalities, as was the Board when it assessed, amended and 
certified them. The government of Puerto Rico had begun the hard work 
of implementing the changes required by the Fiscal Plans via the 
adoption and certification of the first fiscal year budget compliant 
with the Fiscal Plan, which included reducing subsidies, increasing tax 
compliance, taking on direct payment of pensions in the budget, and 
beginning a 3-year process of rightsizing the government. More medium-
term work had begun on deeper pension reform, as well as healthcare 
reform that would reduce forecast costs some 30 percent within 10 
years.
                       puerto rico's new reality
    Puerto Rico is faced with a unique set of circumstances--the 
largest public entity restructuring in the history of the United States 
combined with the greatest hurricane devastation to strike in 100 
years.
Liquidity
    Let me shed some light on Puerto Rico's liquidity situation. The 
devastation has destroyed critical infrastructure, making revenue 
collection extremely difficult. Moreover, Hurricane Maria has caused 
severe damages to the private sector. Many businesses were forced to 
shut down due to structural damage, while those able to continue 
operating will likely incur substantial losses due to the additional 
expenses they must make in order to stay open, such as purchasing and 
running generators for electricity. Puerto Rico's tax revenue 
collection will be severely impacted.
    At the same time, operating expenses during this period, such as 
paying for essential services, will remain generally the same, while 
disaster-related expenses will increase relative to the baseline, which 
had not contemplated a historic hurricane. In addition, there is a 
timing mismatch between when disaster-related expenses are incurred and 
when, if at all, FEMA reimburses the government for those expenses.
    Therefore, without support from the Federal Government, Puerto Rico 
would run out of cash by the end of this quarter. That means no money 
to make payroll for teachers, police, and first responders, or pay 
pensions and other liabilities. This puts the Commonwealth, with 
limited cash on hand, in a liquidity crisis.
    In the first weeks after the hurricane, the Board and the 
government jointly produced an estimate of the size of this liquidity 
crisis based on the best available data. The extent of the short-term 
impact of the hurricane on the capacity of the Commonwealth and its 
instrumentalities is illustrated by the work we did with the government 
in estimating its cash requirement through the end of this year to be 
approximately $5 billion. The government subsequently revised the 
estimate to $3.6 billion to account for the facts that the government 
has been able to receive FEMA advances to pay for expenditures and FEMA 
has been directly paying other Federal agencies, such as the U.S. Army 
Corps of Engineers. The original $5 billion estimate did not anticipate 
either of these developments.
    The liquidity analysis relied on many factors, some of which are 
difficult to forecast. For example, we know that Puerto Rico is 
experiencing a massive population exodus, but the exact amount of that 
exodus is unknowable. We used a figure of 5 percent, or 170,000 people 
through the end of the calendar year. The number is certainly alarming, 
but not far from reality. In fact, Florida Governor Rick Scott has said 
that since October 3, more than 90,000 Puerto Ricans have arrived in 
Florida through Miami, Orlando, and Port Everglades.
    Most of the revised liquidity shortfall estimate of $3.6 billion 
results from updates to disaster relief funding assumptions. In 
particular, the funding requirement has been reduced by approximately 
$1.5 billion to account for the fact that most disaster relief spending 
is presently being funded directly and wholly by FEMA, rather than 
being processed through Puerto Rico's Treasury Single Account with a 
reimbursement lag and a partial cost share. The estimate for recovery 
expenditures was based on the public portion of total reconstruction 
costs from Hurricane Katrina, scaled to the population and construction 
costs of Puerto Rico, and taking into account a timing lag of 
reimbursements which is typical in recovery situations. The forecast 
will continue to be updated to reflect official damage assessments and 
updated relief funding projections as that data becomes available.
    We have also worked with the government to provide a more medium-
term perspective. Our initial estimates of the Island's liquidity over 
the next seven quarters, including the present quarter, for which 
Congress has already provided liquidity assistance, are in the range of 
$13 to $21 billion, but they are currently being revised. This is the 
amount of money we, along with the government, project is necessary to 
ensure provision of the basic functions of government, keep on the job 
policemen, firemen, teachers, healthcare workers and all public service 
employees who are helping in the hurricane recovery efforts, and 
advance the funds required for recovery before FEMA reimburses.
    As Congress considers its support for Puerto Rico, it will be vital 
that any loans or grants provided to meet these needs be measured 
against the Fiscal Plans and integrated with them. The mechanisms of 
PROMESA and the full participation of the Board will be required. We 
have proposed legislative language to this end with regard to 
liquidity. It would require the Board to certify all requests for 
liquidity advances. This will assure that only hurricane-caused 
liquidity advances will be sought.
Fiscal Plan Revision
    We are well aware that--just as you have stated, Mr. Chairman--we 
will have to revise the certified Fiscal Plans in light of the 
hurricanes' devastation. Working closely with the government of Puerto 
Rico, it is essential to use the process of revising Fiscal Plans to 
return to the PROMESA goals of fiscal responsibility, access to private 
capital markets, and sustainable economic independence. The baseline of 
the existing certified Fiscal Plans and their associated budgets 
provides critical information against which to measure the changes 
caused by the hurricane. But the existing Fiscal Plans do not provide a 
map for the post-hurricane future and do not provide timely oversight. 
In this light, the process of thinking through the nature and scope of 
the changes to Puerto Rico's economy post-hurricane has already begun.
    Responding to the humanitarian crisis on the Island must be the 
government's first priority, and the Fiscal Plans must be revised to 
reflect that priority--just as they must be revised to reflect the 
economic-realities of hurricane devastation. Fiscal and structural 
reforms need to be reviewed in light of the new baseline that results 
from this disaster. A critical additional element in the Fiscal Plan 
process will be understanding the amount of Federal funding for 
rebuilding which we understand will be made available later this year 
once more detailed damage assessments can be provided. These Federal 
funds will be essential to understanding the economic assumptions, 
projections and capital expenditure plans that will drive much of the 
revised Fiscal Plan. Revisions to the Fiscal Plan are necessary due to 
four primary reasons:
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; First, the Commonwealth's ability to collect revenues has 
            been significantly compromised as a result of the serious 
            negative effect of infrastructure damage and population 
            outflows on underlying economic activity.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Second, recovery-related expenses are substantial, not all 
            will be reimbursed by Federal aid, especially if local 
            share requirements are not waived, and are not currently 
            accounted for in the existing fiscal plans.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Third, many of the cost-saving measures built into the 
            budgets--the reduction in certain subsidies incorporated 
            into the certified budget, for example--must be looked at 
            with a fresh perspective given the demands of the recovery 
            process.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Fourth, the ``Federal line'' will be significantly larger 
            than the existing Fiscal Plans. It is important to note 
            that the revised plans will reflect any and all capital 
            expenditures funded by FEMA or other Federal recovery 
            assistance. It will also involve any revisions to Medicaid 
            funding.
    The Board has outlined nine principles for the Government to guide 
the work on revised Fiscal Plans:
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Principle 1: The fiscal plan must reflect the current 
            demographic trends, economic challenges, hurricane damage 
            assessments, Federal funding commitments, and a government, 
            both the central government and local governments, sized to 
            this post-hurricane reality.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Principle 2: The revised fiscal plan must cover 5 fiscal 
            years, the first fiscal year being FY 18 and concluding 
            with FY 22.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Principle 3: To properly establish an accurate assessment 
            of the fiscal outlook, the base-case scenario within the 
            fiscal plan must assume no additional Federal support 
            beyond that which is already established by law. 
            Nevertheless, fiscal plans should be adjusted as additional 
            Federal funding is committed.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Principle 4: The revised fiscal plan must provide 
            sufficient resources to ensure appropriate immediate 
            emergency response and recovery effort in anticipation of 
            Federal funds, including provision of public safety, health 
            care and education, in order to avoid increased 
            outmigration--particularly by working families and working 
            age populations. The fiscal plan must include metrics 
            focused on the improvement of living standards, e.g. 
            education, health care, job creation.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Principle 5: Pension reform, corporate tax reform, and 
            other structural reforms necessary to improve the business 
            climate must remain priorities in the fiscal plan.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Principle 6: Based on available and dedicated resources, 
            the capital expenditure plan must provide the basis for a 
            long-term economic recovery plan for Puerto Rico, focusing 
            on increased and expedited support for rebuilding critical 
            infrastructure such as energy, water, transportation and 
            housing.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Principle 7: The fiscal plan must include the resources to 
            complete the FY 15 Commonwealth consolidated audited 
            financial statements by no later than December 31, 2017, 
            and FY 16 and FY 17 Commonwealth consolidated audited 
            financial statements by no later than June 30, 2018. 
            Thereafter, Commonwealth consolidated audited financial 
            statements should be issued no later than within 6 months 
            of the fiscal year-end.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Principle 8: Structural balance should be achieved as soon 
            as possible, in any event by no later than FY 22, after 
            taking into account the period of time required for the 
            stabilization of Puerto Rico's humanitarian crisis.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Principle 9: The fiscal plan must be accompanied by a 
            long-term debt sustainability analysis (DSA) and detailed 
            economic projections, reflecting a 30-year period.
    Finally, the Commonwealth's Fiscal Plan revision process is based 
on three key components:
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Revising macroeconomic driver effects on revenue and 
            expenses,
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Adapting fiscal and structural reform schedules based on 
            the recovery timeline and feasibility, and
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Integrating recovery funds and reimbursement timing with a 
            capital plan.
    This process will require us to make the best possible analytical 
projections on the basis of all data available. However, given the 
level of uncertainty, it is important to note that unlike the original 
fiscal plan which covered 10 years, the revised fiscal plan will cover 
5 years, as required by PROMESA, with the first fiscal year being FY 18 
and concluding with FY 22.
    In an effort to incorporate input from all stakeholders, the Board 
will hold three listening sessions to which all stakeholders are 
invited to provide input to the Fiscal Plans as part of the revision 
process. They each will be a full day in duration; two of them in 
Puerto Rico, and one in New York City. In addition, we have agreed with 
the court-appointed mediators to hold two additional sessions with 
creditor stakeholders. The government will participate in these 
sessions as well.
    Our aim is to move deliberately to prepare and approve revised 
Fiscal Plans. The reason is simple: a revised fiscal plan is key for 
the government to move forward in requesting Federal funds, outlining 
structural and fiscal reforms, implementing capital expenditure plans, 
and enabling proper oversight on a timely basis, as required by 
PROMESA. The deadline for the Commonwealth, PREPA, and PRASA to submit 
draft Fiscal Plans to the Board is December 22, 2017 with review and 
revision ongoing through the goal certification date of February 2, 
2018. The deadline for the University of Puerto Rico, HTA, GDB, and 
COSSEC to submit draft Fiscal Plans to the Board is February 9, 2018 
with review and revision ongoing through the goal certification date of 
March 16, 2018.
    In keeping with PROMESA's purposes, it will take great discipline, 
transparency and accountability to make the best use of Federal and 
Commonwealth rebuilding funds. To the full extent possible, the 
rebuilding of hurricane-damaged Puerto Rico should serve PROMESA's goal 
of a financially sustainable Puerto Rico enabled by a resilient and 
vibrant economy that makes sense for the Commonwealth.
Contracts Review Policy
    We have also taken other steps to fulfill our mandate under 
PROMESA. As we embark on the immense task of rebuilding Puerto Rico in 
the wake of Hurricanes Irma and Maria, we expect the government to 
enter into numerous large contracts. We have implemented a Contract 
Review Policy (``Policy'') as a tool to ensure transparency throughout 
the entire government for the benefit of the people of Puerto Rico and 
all stakeholders. The Policy is implemented pursuant to Section 
204(b)(2) of PROMESA to assure that contracts promote market 
competition and are not inconsistent with the approved fiscal plan. It 
also follows sections 204(b)(3) and 204(b)(5).
    In establishing the Policy, the Board is mindful of Section 
204(d)(2) of PROMESA and does not intend to impede the government's 
implementation of any Federal programs, particularly those related to 
disaster response and recovery. To the contrary, the Board established 
the Policy in large part to support the government's implementation of 
Federal programs, including, for example, to ensure that contracts are 
consistent with the requirements of Federal programs, particularly 
those related to funding and reimbursement for disaster aid spending. 
Non-compliance with Federal requirements could cause substantial fiscal 
costs to be borne by the Commonwealth, having a severely adverse fiscal 
effect on compliance with fiscal plans.
    The Policy applies to all contracts in which the Commonwealth or 
any covered instrumentality is a counterparty, including those with the 
Federal Government, state governments, private parties, and nonprofit 
organizations. The Policy provides that effective November 6, 2017, all 
contracts or series or related contracts, inclusive of any amendments 
or modifications, with an aggregate expected value of $10 million or 
more must be submitted to the Board for its approval before execution. 
In addition, the Board retains the authority to adopt other methods, 
such as random sampling of contracts below the $10 million threshold, 
to assure that they promote market competition and are not inconsistent 
with the approved fiscal plan.
    The Oversight Board is prepared to review contracts in a timely 
manner. As such, we have identified an internal working group to take 
the lead on the contract review process. We look forward to working 
hand-in-hand with the government of Puerto Rico to ensure the upmost 
transparent, fair, and competitive contracting processes.
Appointment of Chief Transformation Officer for PREPA
    PREPA is a case in point of an entity within the government that 
needs to be transformed. Past mismanagement has led to an outmoded, 
unstable, patch-work grid and an inefficient and unduly expensive power 
sector. Rebuilding efforts should be integrated into the planning that 
avoids reprising past mistakes. We should plan and build for a better 
power sector and one that can move rapidly toward attraction of private 
capital to ensure the most effective transformation of the power 
sector.
    As a critical step toward this, the Board has appointed Noel Zamot, 
the Board's current Revitalization Coordinator, as the Chief 
Transformation Officer of PREPA in accordance with its authority under 
Title III of PROMESA. The Title III court set a hearing for November 
13, 2017 to consider our motion. In bankruptcy proceedings, it is 
common practice for a debtor in possession to name a Chief 
Transformation Officer, sometimes also referred to as a chief 
restructuring officer, to help turn around organizations and manage 
them while in bankruptcy. This is no different, but certainly more 
urgent.
    Upon confirmation by the court, Noel's task will be to lead the 
transformation of PREPA and the rebuilding of the electricity sector 
following the devastation of Hurricane Maria. His immediate priority 
will be to fast-track reconstruction efforts on the Island in close 
coordination with the government of Puerto Rico, the Board, and the 
Federal Government. In addition, Noel will be fully committed to 
bringing the resources necessary to restore electricity to the people 
of Puerto Rico as quickly as possible, and to re-activate the economy 
and bring normalcy to the Island.
    The appointment of Noel is an essential step in achieving the goal 
of providing Puerto Rico residents and businesses reliable, resilient 
and reasonably priced electricity supply, which will also require 
attracting the private capital we need to revitalize the power sector. 
Our vision for the future of Puerto Rico's energy sector is simple: a 
more modern, efficient and resilient power sector to revitalize the 
economy and deliver a better future for the people of Puerto Rico.
Role of the Oversight Board
    PROMESA and its tools were not written for responding to or 
recovery from a catastrophic hurricane. The reality in which we 
operated prior to the devastation is much different than Puerto Rico's 
current reality. The tools to rebuild a more resilient and economically 
viable Puerto Rico now include significant Federal funds, and we see 
the Board having an active role in ensuring those monies are used in 
the best interest of the Island. For us, ensuring fiscal controls to 
deliver confidence in the government is key. The role we can play is 
clear, but we remain cognizant that in several occasions in which we 
have exercised our authority, there has been substantial opposition, 
often resulting in litigation.
                               questions
    I will now turn directly to the questions the Committee has posed 
to us:
1. What is the Board doing now to fulfill its oversight function, 
        specifically with respect to revision of Fiscal Plans?
    As indicated above, careful, principled and transparent revision of 
the Fiscal Plans is essential. We are actively engaged, along with the 
government, in the analytical work that underlies that process. The 
extent of Federal aid in the year-end disaster relief package Congress 
is planning is obviously a key variable. The ``Federal line'' will 
constitute a very significant change from the existing Fiscal Plans. As 
you know, the earlier plans were balanced without any Federal 
assistance. The revised plans will reflect any and all capital 
expenditures funded by FEMA or other Federal recovery assistance. It 
will also involve any revisions adopted to Medicaid funding. As soon as 
we know that and have had an opportunity to study its impact, we will 
have all we need to work with the government in finalizing revised 
Fiscal Plans. We aim to complete Board certification in the first week 
of February 2018 for the Commonwealth, PREPA, and PRASA.
    We are also reviewing and renewing all of the liquidity estimates 
we submitted to Treasury and Congress with the government over the last 
few weeks. The passage of a few months should give us a better idea of 
the extent of revenue losses, hurricane-caused net increase in 
expenditures, and delayed cost reductions. We will continue to monitor 
liquidity weekly, which is now being published publicly by the 
government.
    With respect to budgeting, we are updating our reporting blueprint 
to incorporate information on disbursements and use of Federal funds 
received by the government and its instrumentalities, as well as 
reallocation of budget items for emergency measures as we laid out in 
our letter to the Governor the day after Hurricane Maria hit. We also 
will receive a budget compliance report next week that will show how 
actual expenses and revenues compare to budgeted expenses and revenues 
for the first fiscal quarter, ending September 30, 2017.
    Moreover, pursuant to Section 103(d) of PROMESA, the Board is 
initiating formal requests to Federal department and agency heads to 
detail personnel of their respective department and agencies to the 
Board to assist it in carrying out its duties under the Act. We are 
certain that we will receive cooperation from our Federal counterparts 
in detailing subject matter experts to support the Board and the 
government of Puerto Rico.
2. What can the Board do to oversee the proper expenditure of Federal 
        Hurricane recovery funds?
    Through the process of working with the Governor to create and 
certify Fiscal Plans under Section 201 of PROMESA, we can make sure 
that hurricane recovery funds are properly accounted for and directed 
in a revised Fiscal Plan. We have similar authority with respect to 
making sure that the more detailed annual operating budgets developed 
by the Governor or covered instrumentalities conform with the certified 
Fiscal Plans.
    Once certified Fiscal Plans and budgets are in place, we have 
authority to ensure compliance with those Fiscal Plans and budgets. 
Section 203 requires the Governor to submit a report at the end of each 
fiscal quarter on actual receipts, expenditures and cash-flow. We are 
instructed to alert the Governor to any inconsistencies with the 
certified Fiscal Plan and budgets. If the Governor or a covered 
instrumentality fails to make corrections, the Board is empowered to 
make appropriate reductions in non-debt expenditures to ensure the 
quarterly budget aligns with the certified budget. Further clarity with 
regard to these authorities may prevent challenges that have previously 
resulted in litigation.
    With respect to the actual contracting process by the Commonwealth 
or covered instrumentalities, as just described, we can review 
contracts under our policy created under Section 204 to ensure they are 
consistent with the fiscal plan, promote market competition, and as 
applicable are consistent with Federal regulations pertaining to 
reimbursement and funding. Section 204(d) does state that the Board 
shall not impede the government's actions to implement Federal 
authorized or federally delegate programs, but our policy does not 
impede the implementation of Federal disaster relief programs--to the 
contrary, it should provide stakeholders with greater confidence in the 
process itself.
    With respect to debt, pursuant to Section 207 the Board must 
approve any new debt issuance or debt exchange or modification. Under 
the legislation you just passed to assist Puerto Rico with its 
liquidity challenges, the funds will be distributed via the Community 
Disaster Loan Program. Because these are loans, the Board must and will 
review each loan to ensure it is advisable that the borrower take out 
that specific loan with those specific terms.
3. What additional tools does the Board need to ensure that Federal 
        funds are properly expended and that they are expended as part 
        of a plan that makes sense for Puerto Rico's future?
    Mr. Chairman and members of the Committee, I understand the 
importance of this question and the imperative for this Committee to 
examine it. My general answer--and my answers to any particular 
questions posed to me today--will of course reflect the current 
limitations of the Board's ability to meet the great challenges that 
the hurricanes' devastation has caused Puerto Rico and the new 
challenges it presents to Congress and the PROMESA structure as well.
    I want to emphasize, though, that while the question is expressed 
in terms of ``need,'' the Board is not seeking additional 
responsibilities nor the tools to go with them. The Board is a creature 
of Congress, appointed on a voluntary, bipartisan basis, serving the 
American citizens of Puerto Rico. We have been exercising our authority 
under PROMESA.
    If Congress determines that additional Board responsibilities will 
enhance confidence and enable greater support for Puerto Rico after 
these devastating hurricanes, I believe the Board would be willing to 
accept additional responsibilities. Similarly, if Congress determines 
that clarification and reaffirmation of our existing authority in light 
of the new demands placed on all of us by the necessity of hurricane 
recovery will be useful to avoid litigation and the uncertainty, time, 
and cost it entails, we would of course welcome that. Like the people 
and government of Puerto Rico, Congress and the Administration, we know 
that the hurricanes have produced new realities we must deal with as 
wisely and faithfully as we can.
    I can give one example of where congressional clarification and 
ratification of our authority may well be critical--the appointment of 
the PREPA Chief Transformation Officer. We believe our authority--and 
responsibility--under PROMESA and basic bankruptcy tenets is clear. 
However, our authority is being vigorously opposed by some parties in 
the Title III proceeding. Even after an initial ruling, litigation and 
associated uncertainty may linger during appeals. Congressional 
clarification would resolve what otherwise is potentially very damaging 
litigation.
                               conclusion
    Again, Mr. Chairman and members of the Committee, we deeply 
appreciate your concern for the American citizens who live in Puerto 
Rico, and, on behalf of the Board, I pledge to continue to work with 
you to do all we can to meet the new challenges and to achieve 
PROMESA's goals. I look forward to your questions.
                                 ______
  Questions Submitted for the Record to Ms. Jaresko and Mr. Zamot are 
                  combined and can be found on page 24
                                 ______
    The Chairman. Thank you.
    Mr. Zamot, 5 minutes. Welcome.
</option>
    <option>   OVERSIGHT AND MANAGEMENT BOARD FOR PUERTO RICO, SAN JUAN, 
                          PUERTO RICO
    Mr. Zamot. Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and 
members of the Committee, I am Noel Zamot. It is an honor for 
me to appear before this Committee. I currently serve as the 
Revitalization Coordinator for the Puerto Rico Financial 
Oversight and Management Board.
    I have also been named by the Oversight Board to serve as 
the Chief Transformation Officer for the Puerto Rico Electric 
Power Authority, or PREPA. A motion seeking confirmation of 
that appointment is before the court overseeing the 
restructuring of PREPA's debt under Title III of PROMESA. My 
written testimony briefly describes my current role and my 
conception of the PREPA CTO role. I will use my limited time in 
this oral statement to outline some of the key aspects of the 
CTO role and my plans for it.
    As mentioned, my appointment as CTO is pending approval by 
the Title III court. I do not want in any way to appear to be 
presumptuous about the outcome, but I also understand the 
Committee's need for information about my plans for this role. 
I believe the court will understand that my testimony is 
provisional. That is, it represents my plans if I am confirmed.
    The role of CTO is essential, both to deal with the short-
term crisis and the long-term transformation of PREPA. We need 
dramatic action to create a fast-moving, de-politicized entity 
driven by a vision of an efficient, durable, sustainable, and 
affordable power sector for the island.
    I have three principal objectives for my role of Chief 
Transformation Officer: first, bring all available resources to 
bear to restore power to Puerto Rico as quickly as possible; 
second, develop and implement the transformation plan for 
PREPA, ensuring that the near-term recovery activity is 
consistent with the long-term vision; and third, ensure the 
utility exits PROMESA's Title III via the implementation of a 
plan of adjustment.
    The overall objective is a utility that provides stable, 
reliable, and cost-effective power to Puerto Rico, and becomes 
an engine of sustained economic growth.
    The first objective requires us to leverage all available 
resources for Puerto Rico. Much has already been done, but 
there is much more to do. Based on my interactions to date, I 
am encouraged that the Army Corps of Engineers, the Department 
of Energy, and FEMA can provide us even greater and better 
coordinated resources. Similarly, we can do much more to 
involve industry groups such as APPA and the Edison Electric 
Institute.
    During this first phase, organizational structure will be 
of critical importance. I will employ an approach that I have 
used with success when I had to lead organizational 
transformation in the middle of chaotic and uncertain 
environments. I have followed this approach in the military, 
where, as a colonel, I led organizations in peace time and 
during emergencies, and in the private sector, where I had to 
transform an organization in the middle of difficult economic 
and market conditions.
    I believe in establishing a straightforward, clear chain of 
authority, with well-defined roles and responsibilities that 
track with the overall objective and with strategic priorities. 
I will retain key leaders on my staff to enable speed and 
effectiveness in our decision making.
    I would like to highlight two key roles.
    The Chief Operations Officer will be responsible for day-
to-day operations of the utility. This will initially be a 
senior leader from within PREPA, but will be augmented by an 
industry executive identified in conjunction with input that we 
are receiving from the Edison Electric Institute.
    The Storm Boss will liaise directly with FEMA, the 
government of Puerto Rico, local mayors, the Corps of 
Engineers, as well as other stakeholders. This person will be 
responsible for identifying, onboarding, and integrating all 
help, as required, as well as acting as a primary stakeholder 
to ensure that short-term recovery actions are consistent with 
a long-range plan. I expect to coordinate with a Storm Boss 
frequently, likely several times per day.
    I have also identified key executives to serve on a Board 
of Advisors. These are CEOs from public and private utilities 
who have generously volunteered to bring their considerable 
expertise to help with this task. I will also rely on an 
internal group of world-class actors from multi-national 
utilities, the energy sector, academia, and more.
    The second objective is to transform PREPA under the fiscal 
plan, which is developed by the Oversight Board, in conjunction 
with the government of Puerto Rico and PREPA. This plan 
reflects a transformation of PREPA in broad agreement with 
Puerto Rico's energy strategy and the Governor's energy 
priorities.
    The end state is to provide stable, reliable, and cost-
effective power via a grid that incorporates best practices and 
that acts as a catalyst for sustained economic growth. Puerto 
Rico's energy strategy calls for 50 percent renewables by 2040, 
with a balance of natural and LP gas mix, regional grids with 
generation close to demand, physical hardening and control 
systems to provide resiliency, and widespread distributed 
generation, all wrapped by an empowered and accountable energy 
regulator.
    PROMESA is clear in its guidance to attract private capital 
to achieve this end state. We need to do just that, not only 
for generation, but to attract innovative capital solutions 
from the private sector for transmission and distribution, as 
well.
    We will update the existing PREPA fiscal plan, based on 
post-Maria reality. PREPA's asset base has been decimated, and 
we will have to rebuild the infrastructure with virtually no 
revenues and minimal liquidity. Fortunately, Congress and the 
Administration created a Community Disaster Loan Program in 
their recently passed supplemental appropriations bill and made 
PREPA an eligible borrower.
    Our FEMA and DOE colleagues have worked with us closely to 
identify the proper Federal programs to rebuild the asset base, 
and generously offered their considerable expertise. We will 
work closely with the Governor, PREPA officials, professional 
and industry groups, as well as thought leaders from the 
private sector to amend the plan.
    We are integrating outside stakeholders into our process, 
with recurring milestone meetings every 10 days to 2 weeks. We 
will have an additional draft of the revised plan by mid-
December, and a more polished version by mid-January. The 
January product should include sufficient detail to be crafting 
actionable engineering requirements to begin execution during 
the second quarter of 2018.
    Finally, the binding actionable implementation of the 
amended transformative fiscal plan is via the plan of 
adjustment. This is the legally enforceable outcome of the 
Title III court proceeding. This plan assures the 
transformation of a utility far beyond the termination of my 
tenure, which will occur upon approval of this plan of 
adjustment.
    The court process associated with plan construction 
approval also assures the input of creditors and the 
recognition of their legal rights, as provided for in PROMESA. 
I look forward to answering your questions.
</option>
    <option>Prepared Statement of Noel Zamot, Revitalization Coordinator, Financial 
             Oversight and Management Board for Puerto Rico
    Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva and members of the 
Committee, I am Noel Zamot, Revitalization Coordinator for the Puerto 
Rico Financial Oversight and Management Board (the ``Board''). I have 
also been named by the Oversight Board to serve as the Chief 
Transformation Officer (``CTO'') for the Puerto Rico Electric Power 
Authority (``PREPA''). A motion seeking confirmation of that 
appointment by the Court overseeing the restructuring of PREPA's debt 
under Title III of the Puerto Rico Oversight, Management and Stability 
Act (``PROMESA'') is pending.
    It is an honor for me to appear before the Committee. I will first 
briefly describe my current role, next outline my conception of the 
PREPA CTO role, and then stand ready to answer the Committee's 
questions to the best of my ability.
                       revitalization coordinator
    As the Committee well knows, the Revitalization Coordinator, like 
the Board itself, owes its existence to Congress. Section 502 of 
PROMESA established the position of Revitalization Coordinator, under 
the Board. My role is part of Title V of PROMESA--Puerto Rico 
Infrastructure Revitalization. My job, in a nutshell, is to accelerate 
the Island's economic recovery by bringing private capital to address 
infrastructure challenges, in order to create jobs and set the 
conditions for growth.
    This has become all the more important in the aftermath of 
Hurricanes Irma and Maria. I am just back from the Island, where I have 
been coordinating with the government of Puerto Rico, the U.S. Army 
Corps of Engineers, military personnel generally, FEMA personnel and 
others to address the immediate aspects of the Island's infrastructure 
devastation in as coordinated and efficient a manner as possible. I 
myself have a military background, having retired from the U.S. Air 
Force in the rank of colonel. I have also been trained in and have led 
emergency responses to crises.
    I can assure you that the troops on the ground in Puerto Rico are 
acting heroically. I can also assure you it is a daunting effort in 
which they are engaged.
    Our Executive Director, Natalie Jaresko, has delivered the Board 
testimony in chief. For this portion of my testimony, I want to very 
briefly discuss the great promise of private investment in Puerto Rico 
as catalyzed by PROMESA, and, as the Committee has asked us to do, 
briefly address some of the challenges presented by our limited role.
    The good news is that even though Puerto Rico's ability to borrow 
is compromised, it does have access to private capital--through 
projects identified by the Board under PROMESA's Critical Project 
provisions. The central mechanism of Title V is identification of 
``Critical Projects.'' Once identified, these projects benefit from 
provisions designed to expedite their realization. We have identified 
to date $3.3 billion in private capital that seeks to invest in Puerto 
Rico infrastructure projects.
    One example is a waste-to-energy project sought by a New York-based 
firm called Energy Answers. This project would involve an $800 
million--fully private--investment to create a plant to convert waste 
into electricity. It has a dual objective and many advantages. It would 
not only generate electricity that would be contributed to the grid, 
but also alleviate some of the pressure on a full and leaking landfill.
    In recommending this project and approving it for the expedited 
permitting provided for Critical Projects, we apply the statutory 
PROMESA criteria. These include the ``impact it will have on an 
emergency''; the availability of immediate private capital; the cost of 
the project, if any, to Puerto Rico; and its jobs impact. With respect 
to energy projects, the criteria also include whether the project will 
reduce reliance on oil for energy generation, improve energy 
infrastructure and overall energy efficiency, expedite conversion of 
fuel sources to natural gas and renewables, contribute to transitioning 
to private generation capacity, and support the Energy Commission of 
Puerto Rico in achievement of its goal of reducing energy costs.
    Private capital is an essential ingredient of restoration of the 
Island's infrastructure, and the Critical Projects process has shown it 
can be a valuable tool to help privately financed projects succeed.
    The Committee has also asked what else is required for successful 
rebuilding of Puerto Rico's infrastructure and what limitations I see 
in Title V as a tool for aiding the rebuilding. That is an important 
topic, and I look forward to discussing it in response to your 
questions today.
    As a general matter, I would emphasize that as useful as I think 
Title V is, it is quite narrow. Beyond identifying and expediting 
discrete Critical Projects, Title V offers few tools to the 
Revitalization Coordinator to realize broader economic development in 
Puerto Rico. The Revitalization Coordinator also does not have the 
formal power to reform the management, operations, or contracting of 
instrumentalities, such as PREPA--a void that has become much more 
consequential after Hurricanes Irma and Maria.
                   prepa chief transformation officer
    I would now like to share my thoughts on PREPA and the decision by 
the Board to appoint a Chief Transformation Officer. My appointment as 
CTO, as I have indicated, is pending approval by the Title III court. I 
do not want in any way to appear to be presumptuous about the outcome, 
but I also understand the Committee's need for information on my 
understanding of and plans for the CTO role. I believe the Court will 
understand that my testimony is provisional--that is, what I plan to do 
assuming I am confirmed.
    The decision to name a CTO was the Board's, not mine. Suffice it to 
say that from my perspective of months on the ground in Puerto Rico, 
and regardless of who fills the role, it is absolutely essential. Both 
to deal with the short-term crisis and the long-term transformation of 
PREPA, we need dramatic action that creates a fast-moving, 
depoliticized entity driven by a compelling vision of an efficient, 
durable, sustainable and affordable power sector for the island.
    I have three principal objectives for my role as Chief 
Transformation Officer. First, bring all available resources to bear to 
restore power to Puerto Rico as quickly as possible. Second, develop 
and implement the transformation plan for PREPA, ensuring that the 
near-term recovery activity is consistent with the long-term vision. 
And, third, ensure the utility exits PROMESA's Title III via the 
implementation of a plan of adjustment as a system that can provide 
stable, reliable, and cost-effective power to Puerto Rico's inhabitants 
and institutions.
Restoring Power--and Early Organizational Steps
    The first objective requires us to leverage all available resources 
for Puerto Rico. Much has already been done, but there is much more to 
do. Based on my interactions with them to date, I am greatly encouraged 
that the Army Corps of Engineers, the Department of Energy and FEMA can 
provide us even greater, and better coordinated, resources. Similarly, 
we can do much more to involve industry groups such as the American 
Public Power Association to a greater degree.
    During this first phase, the organizational structure will be of 
critical importance. I will employ an approach that I have used with 
success in previous times when we had to transform organizations in the 
middle of chaotic and uncertain environments. I have found success by 
establishing a straightforward, clear chain of authority, with well-
defined roles and responsibilities that track with the overall 
objective and with strategic priorities. Especially during this initial 
phase, we must prioritize speed--with discipline, transparency and 
integrity--over endless analysis. The people of Puerto Rico deserve no 
less. We will keep our objectives--recovery and transformation--front 
and center throughout every action we take.
    I plan to have five key direct reports on my staff. They will 
enable me both to act fast and effectively in the first phase and to 
integrate our actions with our long-term transformation plan and to 
ensure that I have advisors with the right expertise helping me achieve 
our goals. These are a: Chief Operations Officer (``COO''), Storm Boss, 
VP for Transition, Chief Financial Officer (``CFO''), and General 
Counsel (``GC'').
    The Chief Operations Officer will be responsible for day-to-day 
operations of the utility. This will initially be a senior leader from 
PREPA, but will be augmented by an industry executive, identified in 
conjunction with input we are receiving from the Edison Electric 
Institute.
    The Storm Boss will liaise directly and freely with FEMA, the 
government of Puerto Rico, the Army Corps of Engineers, as well as 
other members of the team. This person will be responsible for 
identifying, onboarding, and integrating all help as required, as well 
as acting as the primary stakeholder to ensure that short-term recovery 
actions under Stafford Act Category B are consistent with the long-term 
plan for the island. I expect to coordinate with the Storm Boss 
frequently--likely several times per day.
    The VP for Transition will lead the mechanics of developing the 
transformation plan, as embodied in the revised Fiscal Plan for PREPA, 
ensuring that we remain on the timeline and that all stakeholders are 
represented and contribute appropriately. This person will further 
insure that the various working groups are integrated with the outside 
and internal stakeholders, and that the evolving vision is shared with 
the COO and Storm Boss to ensure continuity of effort and consistency 
between near-term recovery and the transformation vision.
    The CFO will have traditional financial responsibilities. The CFO 
will develop an improved, open and transparent procurement process, 
fully compliant with all Federal requirements, such as FEMA's. In my 
experience, much of the challenge with problematic contracts has less 
to do with the substance of the contract--which can be reviewed and 
amended--than with the RFP process and selection criteria. Without 
sound controls and protocols for those two, you could end up with a 
perfectly executed contract that was awarded inappropriately.
    Finally, we will have a General Counsel. As a three-time military 
commander and industry executive, my experience is that the roles and 
responsibilities of management and GC are and must be clear. Leadership 
establishes vision and executes strategy; the GC ensures that those 
objectives are accomplished in an ethical and legal manner.
    I have been engaging in informal conversations with potential 
candidates for all these positions so that they can be hired and join 
the team as soon as I am confirmed to the role by the Court.
    Outside of the organization, I have already identified key 
executives to serve on a Board of Advisors. These are Chief Executive 
Officers from public and private utilities, who have generously 
volunteered to bring their considerable expertise to help with the 
task. I will also rely on professional, engineering, and sector 
insights from seasoned experts in the field. This is my ``deep bench,'' 
and it includes former executives from multi-national utilities, energy 
experts, economists and more. These will include experts from McKinsey 
&amp;amp; Company and Ernst &amp;amp; Young, who currently serve as outside consultants 
to the Board, as well as economists from MIT's Sloan School, my alma 
mater. My intent is to reach out to them on a regular, scheduled basis. 
I have already asked this team to identify key process and 
organizational efforts in the first critical days of transition.
The Fiscal Plan and Its Transformative Character
    The Board, in conjunction with the government of Puerto Rico and 
PREPA, has developed a Fiscal Plan that reflects a transformation of 
PREPA that is in broad agreement with Puerto Rico's energy strategy and 
the Governor's energy priorities. Our goal or ``end state'' is to 
provide stable, reliable, and cost-effective power via a grid that 
incorporates best practices, in order to act as a catalyst for 
sustainable economic growth. Puerto Rico's energy strategy calls for: 
50 percent renewables by 2040, with the balance a natural/LP gas mix; 
regional grids with generation close to demand; physical hardening and 
control schemes to provide resiliency; and widespread distributed 
generation, all wrapped by an empowered, accountable energy regulator.
    PROMESA is clear in its guidance to attract private capital to 
achieve this end state. We intend to do just that, not only for 
generation, but to attract innovative capital solutions from the 
private sector for transmission and distribution as well.
    To be sure, we must update the existing PREPA Fiscal Plan based on 
the post-Maria reality. Not only has the asset base been decimated, but 
now we have to rebuild the infrastructure with virtually no revenues 
and minimal liquidity. Fortunately, Congress and the Administration 
created a Community Disaster Loan Program in the recently passed 
supplemental appropriations bill and made PREPA an eligible borrower. 
Moreover, our FEMA and DOE colleagues have worked closely with us to 
identify the proper Federal programs to rebuild the asset base and to 
give us the benefit of their expertise. We will work closely with the 
Governor and existing PREPA officials with expert knowledge of the 
Fiscal Plan and its transformative role, and the process for amending 
the Plan will also include professional and industry groups and thought 
leaders.
    We will begin integrating outside stakeholders into our process by 
mid-November, with recurring milestone meetings every 10 days to 2 
weeks. We will have an initial draft of the revised Plan by mid-
December, and a more polished version by mid-January. The January 
product should include sufficient detail to begin crafting actionable 
engineering and policy requirements to begin execution during the 
second quarter of 2018.
Plan of Adjustment
    The binding, actionable implementation of the resulting, amended 
transformative Fiscal Plan is via the Plan of Adjustment, the legally 
enforceable outcome of the Title III court proceeding. This Plan 
ensures the transformation of the utility far beyond the termination of 
my tenure, which will occur upon approval of the Plan. The court 
process associated with Plan construction and approval also assures the 
input of creditors and the recognition of their legal rights, as 
provided for in PROMESA.
    I look forward to answering your questions.
                                 ______
   Questions Submitted for the Record to Natalie Jaresko, Executive 
    Director, and Noel Zamot, Revitalization Coordinator, Financial 
             Oversight and Management Board for Puerto Rico
                  Oral Questions Posed at the Hearing
    Question 1. What is the latest damage assessment for Puerto Rico, 
and in particular, for the energy sector?
    Answer. The FOMB has not completed a damage assessment for Puerto 
Rico and does not plan to. The only damage assessments that the FOMB is 
aware of at this time are informal Federal Government agency estimates 
of $5-$12 billion and the one released on November 13, 2017 by the 
government of Puerto Rico, state of New York, Open Society Foundations, 
Ford Foundation, and Rockefeller Foundation. That damage assessment 
estimated a total of $94.4 billion in damage, of which the power grid 
was responsible for $17.8 billion.
    Question 2. What are the salaries for all executive staff and 
deputies?
    Answer. The FOMB has attached a table that shows the position, 
compensation, and starting date for all executive staff and deputies.
    [The information follows:]
    Question 3. When was the last time the trash incinerator was 
tested for lead, arsenic, and other contaminants?
    Answer. Since the waste-to-energy facility has not yet been built, 
no emissions testing has been completed. However, the FOMB understands 
that a similar facility of the same design has been operating 
consistent with local and Federal regulations for several years in 
Massachusetts.
    Question 4. Why would Puerto Rico use the most expensive form of 
energy, renewables, to comprise a portion of restoring its power?
    Answer. The FOMB's energy plan for Puerto Rico envisions long term 
a mix of renewables and natural gas. The FOMB's understanding is that 
most of the work to restore power is being done on the transmission and 
distribution portions of the grid, not the generation, so Puerto Rico 
is not materially changing the existing energy mix as it restores 
power.
    Question 5. What are the interim and long-term costs to Puerto Rico 
from the FOMB?
    Answer. At the time PROMESA was passed, the Congressional Budget 
Office projected that the FOMB would cost $370 million over 10 years. 
Actual audited expenditures of the FOMB for Fiscal Year 2017 were 
approximately $30 million. The FOMB's budget for Fiscal Year 2018 is 
approximately $60 million.
    Question 6. How will Noel Zamot as the CTO for PREPA be different 
from existing PREPA management?
    Answer. In light of the Title III court's ruling regarding the 
FOMB's appointment of Noel Zamot as the Chief Transformation Officer 
(``CTO'') for PREPA, the FOMB respectfully submits that this question 
is now moot.
    Question 7. What can the Federal Government do to restore 
prosperity in Puerto Rico?
    Answer. The FOMB has attached a separate letter describing actions 
that the Federal Government can take, particularly with respect to tax 
reform, recovery and rebuilding assistance, and economic development 
that would catalyze economic growth in Puerto Rico.
    [The information follows:]
                                              November 22, 2017
Dear Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and Members of the 
Committee:
In the course of the Oversight Hearing, ``Examining Challenges in 
Puerto Rico's Recovery and the Role of the Financial Oversight and 
Management Board,'' on November 7, 2017, our Executive Director, 
Natalie Jaresko, received numerous inquiries about various proposals to 
aid Puerto Rico in light of the devastation caused by Hurricanes Maria 
and Irma. In the same vein, many Oversight Board members and staff in 
their interactions with Congress and the Administration have been asked 
for their recommendations on what the Federal Government can and should 
do to help.
We greatly appreciate the depth and breadth of concern expressed by 
Congress and the Administration for the plight of the people of Puerto 
Rico. We know that these questions are part of an ongoing and difficult 
effort to put together a comprehensive plan to deal with the Island's 
current distress as well as its long-term wellbeing.
Likewise, we acknowledge that, in light of the hurricanes, such 
inquiries are deeply connected to our mission under PROMESA. As you 
know, before the hurricanes we were dedicated to achieving fiscal and 
economic health for Puerto Rico and its instrumentalities without 
additional federal aid. After the hurricanes, of course, continued 
generous and well directed federal aid is essential.
Accordingly, without in any way presuming to be experts in all the 
areas affected or to be the final word on any of them, we want to be as 
responsive as we can. This letter focuses on a few areas where we see 
particular need.
Hurricanes Maria and Irma have fundamentally altered Puerto Rico's 
fiscal and economic reality, worsening the Island's already deeply 
troubled fiscal situation and destroying much of its infrastructure. 
Tax reform legislation, if approved in its current form, would further 
devastate the Island's economy. Achieving fiscal balance, providing a 
path for the Island's return to capital markets, and restoring economic 
growth and opportunity for the people of Puerto Rico, as required by 
PROMESA, remains a critical priority. Achieving PROMESA's goals will 
require significant investments in recovery efforts and in rebuilding 
and transforming the Island's infrastructure, as well as tax reform 
legislation that does not adversely impact businesses operating on the 
Island. It will also require a new economic model bolstered by expanded 
economic tools and increased labor force participation.
World-class pharmaceutical manufacturing plants and other multinational 
corporations manufacturing and otherwise doing business in Puerto Rico 
are a cornerstone of Puerto Rico's economy and a key source of income. 
In fact, manufacturing exports account for roughly 30 percent of Puerto 
Rico's general revenues. If not remedied, current federal tax reform 
provisions that consider businesses operating in Puerto Rico as doing 
work in a foreign jurisdiction could destroy the Island's manufacturing 
base, causing critical tax revenues to evaporate. Puerto Rico's economy 
was already in decline before the hurricanes. Tax changes that make 
Puerto Rico's economy even less competitive with foreign jurisdictions 
would be crushing and would frustrate efforts to restore growth. We 
urge you to modify the current tax reform legislation to encourage 
companies to remain in Puerto Rico and to increase their presence in 
Puerto Rico instead of moving to truly foreign jurisdictions.
Puerto Rico's infrastructure, particularly its energy sector, water and 
sewer systems, and roads need to be rebuilt and transformed in the 
aftermath of Hurricanes Irma and Maria. Schools, hospitals and housing 
have also suffered extensive damages and need substantial support for 
repairs and replacement. Prior to the hurricanes, the Oversight Board 
had certified fiscal plans that included well over $10 billion in 
capital needs incorporating approximately $7 billion for energy 
generation and for transmission and distribution of electricity, as 
well as $2 billion for water systems. Extensive hurricane damages have 
substantially increased the Island's infrastructure needs and 
accelerated the timeline under which reconstruction efforts must occur. 
Initial damage assessments estimate tens of billions in damages. It is 
imperative that the federal government expeditiously complete its 
assessments of the impacts of the hurricanes on Puerto Rico's 
infrastructure and that Congress commit needed resources to support 
rebuilding a stronger, more resilient Puerto Rico. Reconstruction funds 
must be subject to effective oversight, spent judiciously and used to 
support transformation efforts reflected in revised and improved Fiscal 
Plans under PROMESA. Without rebuilding and transforming its 
infrastructure, Puerto Rico will not be able to address its dire fiscal 
and economic challenges, or restore growth and opportunity.
We are hopeful that Hurricanes Irma and Maria can be a catalyst for 
change. Puerto Rico's fiscal, economic and demographic crisis preceded 
the hurricanes. The challenges of limited economic tools, sub-state 
funding levels for various critical programs, different eligibility 
rules for Puerto Ricans living on the Island than U.S. citizens living 
in the mainland, as well as multiple self-inflicted wounds already made 
achieving the goals of PROMESA very difficult. The hurricanes have made 
the job of restoring economic growth infinitely more so. However, in 
crisis there is opportunity.
Puerto Rico needs a new economic model--a specific, attainable, 
transformational economic plan. It needs to increase its labor force 
participation. It needs to improve service delivery and fiscal 
accountability. The Financial Oversight and Management Board will work 
with the Government of Puerto Rico to accomplish these important goals. 
However, to be successful in restoring opportunity for the people of 
Puerto Rico, it is critical that tax reform legislation not further 
cripple its economy and that Puerto Rico have the necessary resources 
to recover from Hurricanes Irma and Maria and rebuild and transform its 
infrastructure.
            Sincerely,
                                           Jose B. Carrion,
                                                             Chair.
                                 ______
     Written Questions Submitted for the Record to Natalie Jaresko
                  Questions Submitted by Rep. Grijalva
    Question 1. You indicate in your statement that the Oversight Board 
has proposed legislative language to ensure that congressional support 
to help Puerto Rico address its liquidity problems is consistent with 
the Fiscal Plans. Said language would require the Board to certify all 
requests for liquidity advances. Have you shared this language with the 
Committee? Is such a degree of micromanagement of the Puerto Rican 
government really necessary? Aren't Puerto Rico's current liquidity 
problems the result of the hurricane?
    Answer. Yes, the current liquidity problems are indeed a result of 
the hurricane, which is the reason the FOMB believes it should certify 
all liquidity advances. The FOMB, through the pre-hurricane fiscal 
plans, can verify that the liquidity problems are in fact caused by the 
hurricane. To the extent that liquidity support from the Federal 
Government comes in the form of loans, such as Community Disaster 
Loans, the FOMB has the responsibility to approve any such loans under 
PROMESA. Yes, this language has been shared with the Committee.
    Question 2. You point out that several areas of the island can be 
classified as ``immediate or pressing needs.'' These include energy, 
water, housing and health care. Besides installing the Title V 
Revitalization Coordinator as the Chief Transformation Officer for 
PREPA, what else is the Oversight Board doing to address these pressing 
needs?
    Answer. The FOMB acknowledges that the government of Puerto Rico 
and the relevant Federal agencies are the proper entities for 
addressing Puerto Rico's pressing needs. What the FOMB has done is 
provide the Governor with the authority to reallocate up to $1 billion 
of the budget to give the government of Puerto Rico flexibility to 
respond to the disaster, worked with the government of Puerto Rico to 
determine its short-term liquidity needs, and advocated in Washington 
that Puerto Rico be given emergency liquidity assistance and 
unprecedented Federal disaster assistance.
    Question 3. What is the basis for the Board claiming that any money 
from the Federal Government for disaster relief will fall under board's 
purview? Aren't these funds to be used for specific purposes, such as 
rebuilding damaged schools and hospitals and covered by various 
agencies audit and other authorities to ensure they are used as 
intended? Why is there a need for the Board to intervene is how 
disaster funds are spent?
    Answer. The FOMB and government of Puerto Rico are in the process 
of developing revised fiscal plans, which include all capital 
expenditures. After Hurricane Maria, the bulk of these capital 
expenditures will be funded with Federal disaster funds. In addition, 
the eventual fiscal plans for the Commonwealth and certain of its 
instrumentalities that the FOMB certifies will contain reforms and 
measures that should be consistent with how the disaster funds are 
intended to be spent. The FOMB also believes that it can provide 
effective oversight of the significant amount of Federal disaster funds 
that will be spent in Puerto Rico, which in turn will create increased 
confidence for all stakeholders.
    Question 4. Congress recently approved a $4.9 billion loan in the 
disaster relief package to ease the government of Puerto Rico's 
liquidity crisis. You mentioned in your statement that additional 
liquidity assistance will be necessary. Can you elaborate on what it 
will mean if Puerto Rico runs out of cash due to the devastation caused 
by the storm?
    Answer. If Puerto Rico does not get liquidity assistance before it 
runs out of cash, the government of Puerto Rico will not have 
sufficient money to fund governance, and will have to choose among 
making payroll for teachers, police, and first responders, paying 
pensions, and honoring other liabilities.
    Question 5. We have reports, both from humanitarian organizations 
such as Oxfam who are on the ground, as well as through media coverage, 
that supplies such as tarps, food, and water, are being shipped to 
Puerto Rico are not reaching the highland and rural areas. Challenges 
in road clearances, lack of telephone coverage or electricity 
exacerbate these backlogs. Can you describe how the FOMB can help to 
ensure that those difficult-to-reach areas are able to receive critical 
supplies?
    Answer. The FOMB does not have a direct role in carrying out the 
disaster response efforts--that is the responsibility of the government 
of Puerto Rico along with relevant Federal agencies. The FOMB is doing 
what it can to support the government of Puerto Rico in Washington to 
obtain the Federal assistance that it needs so that it the recovery 
effort in difficult to reach areas is as effective as possible.
    Question 6. One of the purposes of this hearing is to determine 
whether and how to expand the jurisdiction of the Fiscal Oversight and 
Management Board to shepherd the recovery efforts in Puerto Rico. We 
know that local first responders, civil society organizations, and 
citizens are working day-in and day-out to address acute needs. They 
have the firsthand knowledge and relationships to know and adapt to 
what communities most need. If the FOMB does acquire greater fiscal 
control over recovery funds, what mechanisms will be in place to ensure 
that these groups on the ground have a meaningful role in determining 
how best to use the funds? Will there be any accountability to assure 
that the money is targeting the most vulnerable individuals? What 
mechanisms will be put into place to allow for civil society groups to 
serve as watchdogs of funds?
    Answer. Like it does with the development of fiscal plans, the FOMB 
will solicit and welcome all input from all stakeholders, especially 
local Puerto Ricans who are most effected by the FOMB's decisions. The 
FOMB will seek out best practices from entities that have performed a 
similar function for past natural disasters, like Hurricanes Katrina 
and Sandy, and model its approach off those.
    Question 7. As you are well aware, Puerto Rico is in a dire 
financial state, with $74 billion in debt. It literally cannot cost-
share on the many desperately needed Federal programs that are 
essential for it to rebuild. Some of these cost-sharing requirements 
have been waived, but what other agencies require cost-shares and what 
can be done to waive these requirements? What would happen if Puerto 
Rico's local cost sharing requirements are not waived? What will happen 
if Puerto Rico's local cost sharing requirements are not waived?
    Answer. The FOMB is concerned about the government of Puerto Rico's 
liquidity situation and supports the waiver of local cash sharing 
requirements. Failure to waive local cost sharing requirements will 
lead the government of Puerto Rico to require additional liquidity 
assistance from the Federal Government, or reduce the amount of its 
efforts to rebuild until such liquidity is made available.
    Question 8. Nearly 60 percent of Puerto Rican children live below 
the poverty line. Overall poverty is at nearly 50 percent. Families are 
extremely vulnerable. How can we ensure that funding, including 
reconstruction funds are supporting the need of these vulnerable 
Americans?
    Answer. The most vulnerable among the Puerto Rican population must 
receive all the support they need in this dire situation. The FOMB 
urges Congress to appropriate the necessary funds to the relevant 
agencies that can provide the most effective assistance to those below 
the poverty line.
                   Questions Submitted by Rep. Pearce
    Question 1. What is the FOMB doing to ensure that disaster funds 
are not used to fix pre-disaster problems?
    Answer. Currently, the FOMB does not have a role in determining on 
what projects the disaster funds are used and so the FOMB cannot ensure 
that disaster funds are not used to fix pre-disaster problems.
    Question 2. Do you believe the FOMB's new Contract Review Policy 
will slow down disaster recovery?
    Answer. No. The FOMB has committed to review and respond to all 
contracts within 7 business days and is committed to working with the 
government of Puerto Rico to make the review as fast as possible 
without compromising the integrity of the process.
                                 *****
        Written Questions Submitted for the Record to Noel Zamot
                  Questions Submitted by Rep. Grijalva
Title V
    Question 1. Mr. Zamot, I want to ask you about the dual approach of 
Title V of PROMESA--privatization and deregulation. Under Puerto Rico's 
Act 76, which was the model for Title V, a former governor tried to 
rush through 2,200 megawatts of renewable energy projects starting in 
2010. But because the process was rushed--as it would be under Title 
V--someone missed that the grid could not handle it. The project 
negotiations had to start from scratch. That was the most relevant 
deregulation precedent for the approach taken in Title V. And it failed 
because deregulation removed the protections that are in place to make 
sure these kinds of projects actually work, and that they don't do more 
harm than good. You are proposing to double down on that process by 
expanding Title V authority before we have seen any proof it can work. 
What protections have you put in place to make sure this precedent is 
not repeated?
    Answer. Title V specifies an evaluation process for projects, which 
includes analyzing the project for job creation, economic impact, and 
environmental safeguards. Only projects that meet these criteria can be 
considered as candidates as Critical Projects. The FOMB closely follows 
this process.
    Question 2. Like PREPA, PRASA has suffered for a long time from an 
old distribution system, lack of funds, and poor management. Title V of 
PROMESA proposes to address the water infrastructure problem by 
privatizing it. But that approach was tried twice in Puerto Rico. It 
failed both times, according to an in depth study from the University 
of Iowa. The relief promised by the companies who took over never came 
to pass. The contracts had to be terminated. Same question; what 
protections have you put in place to make sure this precedent is not 
repeated? Why will this time be different?
    Answer. Privatization of water infrastructure is one of many 
options that may be considered under Title V. This Critical Projects 
process includes evaluations to ensure job creation and economic growth 
without compromising environmental protection.
    Question 3. While much attention has been focused on getting the 
lights back on, there is equal urgency around the water distribution 
system. PRASA has a dilapidated infrastructure that requires major 
work. Puerto Rico had the higest rates of Safe Drinking Water Act 
violations of any state in the Nation. Businesses and economic recovery 
depend on clean water. It is likely that there are waterborne outbreaks 
happening under the radar because we cannot detect them--we cannot even 
assess the damage to the infrastructure. What are the FOMB's plans for 
revitalizing PRASA and getting people clean, reliable drinking water?
    Answer. The PRASA transformation plan currently in development will 
address a number of initiatives to provide clean, reliable water to the 
people of Puerto Rico. Among these are improved metering, 
organizational and governance changes, and capital investments.
    Question 4. You hold up the proposed Arecibo trash incinerator as a 
model project for the island. You testified that Arecibo is a privately 
financed project. But it appears to depend on a loan or loan guarantee 
from the USDA. In fact, the project's sponsors, Energy Answers, went 
through an entire Environmental Impact Statement to get the loan. The 
USDA is now saying they no longer want to issue the loan. Energy 
Answers appears to be searching for funding in case they cannot get the 
USDA to change their mind. How do you reconcile the project's need for 
Federal financing with your testimony that says it is a fully privately 
funded project?
    Answer. Projects submitted through Title V are considered a 
privately funded project if the majority of their capital structure 
comes from private capital rather than from the government of Puerto 
Rico. Many of the projects under the Title V process rely in part on a 
variety of Federal funds, including grants and loans, that make the 
overall capital structure more attractive to investors and less risky 
for the population they will ultimately serve.
    Question 5. The proposed incinerator is in a flood plain. It needs 
at least two permits or waivers as a result. The site flooded after the 
recent hurricanes. Designation of this project as a critical project 
could allow it to bypass flood prevention regulations. Since those 
safeguards would not be there, how would you ensure the project would 
prevent waste ash and trash from migrating off-site into neighborhoods 
in the event of a flood if there is no permitting process to do that?
    Answer. The Energy Answers project had already received EPA and 
local permits that addressed these issues in detail. Designation as a 
Critical Project does not exempt projects from applicable Federal or 
local regulations. To the contrary, Critical Projects must meet these 
regulations.
    Question 6. The island is already struggling with a massive coal 
ash disposal problem. There's just no where to put it. It accumulates 
in mounds across the island, creating health hazards for families 
living downwind or downstream. According to the Environmental Impact 
Statement, the proposed incinerator in Arecibo would generate 420 tons 
of toxic ash per day. The plan is to put it in landfills, most of which 
are already either full, out of compliance, or not equipped to handle 
hazardous waste. How would you make sure Puerto Rico families are not 
exposed to that ash?
    Answer. The Energy Answers project had already received EPA and 
local permits that addressed these issues in detail. Designation as a 
Critical Project does not exempt projects from applicable Federal or 
local regulations. To the contrary, Critical Projects must meet these 
regulations.
    Question 7. As you know, the mayors of areas surrounding the 
proposed incinerator oppose it. If they refuse to send their trash 
because they would lose tipping fees and instead would have to pay to 
have the trash burned, and as a result there is not enough trash to 
operate the plant, how will Energy Answers pay back the loan from 
USDA's Rural Utility Service?
    Answer. Puerto Rico is suffering from a severe shortage of landfill 
capacity and the government of Puerto Rico, upon receipt of permits and 
assuming Energy Answers demonstrates compliance with Federal and local 
regulation, the FOMB considers the Energy Answers project a possible 
tool to address the imminent business and environmental crises due to 
the overuse of non-compliant landfills elsewhere on the Island.
PREPA
    Question 8. Mr. Zamot, you have said that a strong regulator is 
needed to oversee the PREPA or whatever its successor might be. The 
Puerto Rico Energy Commission has more expertise in electric utility 
regulation than you and the rest of the Oversight Board. How do you 
think the Commission and the Oversight Board can work together to 
ensure the rebuilding of a more sustainable grid?
    Answer. The Energy Commission and the FOMB share the government of 
Puerto Rico's vision of a sustainable, resilient grid. The FOMB is 
already working closely with the Energy Commission to incorporate them 
into the PREPA transformation process. As an example, we are 
coordinating on the conceptual design of regional grids that will 
provide greater resiliency for future hurricanes. The FOMB welcomes a 
truly independent and professional energy regulator to assure all stake 
holders of a fair rate policy and provide potential private sector 
investors with confidence in the marketplace.
    Question 9. As you know, Governor Rossello has weakened the Energy 
Commission by installing his own appointees into positions, among other 
actions. Will you fight to make the Energy Commission more independent 
of the Governor and the Oversight Board? If so, how?
    Answer. We support an independent, empowered, accountable Energy 
Commission. Such an energy regulator is essential to Puerto Rico's 
energy future and is essential for proper use of Federal and private 
funds to rebuild the grid.
    Question 10. What authorities do you or the Oversight Board believe 
the Board has to take over the Energy Commission if the Board so 
desired?
    Answer. None. The FOMB cannot and has no desire or intent to take 
over the Energy Commission. The FOMB supports a strong, independent 
energy regulator.
    Question 11. Mr. Zamot, do you think there needs to be a clear 
vision of what the new grid will look like before we determine what the 
management structure will look like, as has been suggested by experts 
at the Institute for Energy Economics and Financial Analysis?
    Answer. Regardless of the vision for the new grid, the future of 
Puerto Rico's energy utility must incorporate organizational best 
practices into its management structure. Among these are transparent, 
documented procurement processes, organizational efficiency via clear 
management structure, a quality management and process improvement 
system, and a depoliticized workforce.
    Question 12. When asked about implementing renewable energy on the 
island during the hearing, you referenced a few times the island's 
self-imposed renewable energy standards. As you know, those were made 
before the hurricane. At the time, there was a limitation on renewables 
that were implementable because of funds/credit and because the grid 
was too old to handle it. Both limitations are expected to change 
dramatically now. If the island is ever going to be more self-
sufficient with its energy supply and wean from imported fuel like 
natural gas, now is the time to aim much higher than the modest pre-
hurricane goals and move toward more forward-looking energy plans for 
island economies like those of Hawaii who has a 100 percent renewable 
portfolio standard. As the potential CTO of PREPA, do you see any 
reasons that Hawaii can do it but Puerto Rico cannot? As CTO of PREPA, 
will you fight for that 100 percent renewable energy for Puerto Rico?
    Answer. In light of the Title III court's ruling regarding the 
FOMB's appointment of Noel Zamot as the CTO for PREPA, the FOMB 
respectfully submits that this question is now moot.
    Question 13. Electric sales in Puerto Rico are expected to decline 
more than 23 percent over the next decade. The private utility business 
model does not function effectively in an environment of declining 
load. Why do you believe the private utility business model is 
appropriate in this scenario?
    Answer. Puerto Rico's electric sales are declining in part because 
of high electricity prices, which leads to widespread grid defection. A 
cost-effective, reliable, and stable electric utility would also have a 
significant positive impact on Puerto Rico's economic growth, driving 
up demand.
                  Question Submitted by Rep. Hanabusa
    Question 1. After the devastation of hurricanes Irma and Maria in 
September of this year, Puerto Rico Electric Power Authority (PREPA) 
reported losing approximately 80 percent of its electrical 
infrastructure. This left millions of Puerto Ricans without power, and 
left hospitals unable to care for patients or store lifesaving 
medicine. Currently, urban centers in Puerto Rico are being powered 
primarily through generators, which can only serve as a temporary 
solution to the crisis. There are also still many Puerto Ricans 
sweltering without power in areas outside of urban centers.
    Mr. Zamot, as Chief Transformation Officer your duties include 
leading the development of a power restoration plan, and overseeing the 
application process for Federal funds. You mentioned in your testimony 
that you are currently coordinating with the Army Corps of Engineers, 
the Department of Energy, and Federal Emergency Management Agency for 
financial support and resources. However, their support has not been 
sufficient to address the ultimate goal of repairing and updating 
Puerto Rico's energy infrastructure for the long term.
    You also mentioned in your testimony that exiting the $9 billion in 
debt that belongs to PREPA is not the solution to enable PREPA to 
restore electricity as soon as possible. We discussed during the 
hearing that restoring electricity is the top priority, as it will 
facilitate other disaster recovery efforts. With that goal in mind, 
what are the necessary steps to restoring electricity in Puerto Rico? 
How much money will it take to achieve this?
    Answer. In light of the Title III court's ruling regarding the 
FOMB's appointment of Noel Zamot as the CTO for PREPA, the FOMB 
respectfully submits that this first question is now moot. The FOMB has 
not completed a damage assessment for Puerto Rico and does not plan to. 
The only damage assessments that the FOMB is aware of at this time are 
informal Federal Government agency estimates of $5-$12 billion and the 
one released on November 13, 2017 by the government of Puerto Rico, 
state of New York, Open Society Foundations, Ford Foundation, and 
Rockefeller Foundation. That damage assessment estimated a total of 
$94.4 billion in damage, of which the power grid was responsible for 
$17.8 billion.
                   Questions Submitted by Rep. Pearce
    Question 1. Do you have an accurate damage assessment for the 
island's energy infrastructure? If so, please provide.
    Answer. The FOMB has not completed a damage assessment for Puerto 
Rico and does not plan to. The only damage assessments that the FOMB is 
aware of at this time are informal Federal Government agency estimates 
of $5-$12 billion and the one released on November 13, 2017 by the 
government of Puerto Rico, state of New York, Open Society Foundations, 
Ford Foundation, and Rockefeller Foundation. That damage assessment 
estimated a total of $94.4 billion in damage, of which the power grid 
was responsible for $17.8 billion.
    Question 2. What actions do you plan on taking to ensure that PREPA 
will not run into the same problems it faced before the storm and the 
FOMB's creation?
    Answer. In light of the Title III court's ruling regarding the 
FOMB's appointment of Noel Zamot as the CTO for PREPA, the FOMB 
respectfully submits that this question is now moot.
                                 ______
    The Chairman. Thank you. And finally, Mayor Perez, we 
welcome you here. You are recognized for 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>                     GUAYNABO, PUERTO RICO
    Mr. Perez. Thank you, Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member 
Grijalva, and all members of the Committee, for having convened 
this hearing, and allowing us to share our experiences with the 
aftermath of Hurricanes Irma and Maria. I especially recognize 
our Resident Commissioner, who faced the hurricane right there, 
and now is our advocate for recovery.
    I come to you as Mayor of Guaynabo since August 18. As you 
see, I received a very special welcome to my office.
    My municipality is diverse. We do have upper-income 
neighborhoods, art centers, industries, shopping, a military 
post, but also working-class neighborhoods, public housing 
projects, economically distressed communities, and hard-to-
reach rural areas.
    In Guaynabo, like in all Puerto Rico, there was damage to 
every aspect of infrastructure and the economy in the immediate 
aftermath, besides the collapse of power and communications. 
And today we still have from 75 to 80 percent of our families 
without electricity.
    Our municipality also suffered these major damages: three 
bridges washed out, and another four compromised, resulting in 
over 15 to 20 families having no vehicle access to their homes; 
several partial roads collapsed; most of our rural areas 
lacking water service, due to pumps being offline; and 3,000 
families lost their homes or had them severely damaged.
    It was a challenge to respond, but we stepped forward. From 
the joint efforts of Puerto Rico and Federal Government 
agencies, over 30,000 families have received food and water 
supplies, but this has not always been reliable. The city has 
received 10,000 gallons of diesel fuel, but we use 3,000 every 
day. And we are being assisted with final debris disposal by 
the Corps of Engineers.
    So, work is being done, and we are grateful for the 
response from the Administration and Congress. But more is 
needed.
    For instance, municipalities are the first responders, and 
continue responding, being closest to the people. But with most 
of our businesses closed due to no power, water, or fuel, how 
do we pay our workers and expenses? We have lost a lot of 
revenue.
    Recently, Congress passed legislation that provides up to 
$4.9 billion for support to Puerto Rico, precisely due to the 
need to keep basic public services functioning in the face of 
loss of a tax base. The government of Puerto Rico had been 
granted almost an equivalent of 20 percent of its budget to 
relieve its liquidity needs. The municipality needs, in a 
future legislation, the same benefits to continue providing 
essential services that our people need.
    Another need is a disaster housing support benefit that can 
extend for at least 1 or 2 years. Currently available housing 
vouchers are too few and too low, compared with the number of 
families who lost their homes and are living with family or 
with a neighbor.
    Another is easing FEMA caps on housing rehabilitation, so 
families may rebuild with greater resiliency. Similarly, an 
expansion and flexibilization of CDBG and Section 108 funds, so 
that municipalities can better direct them to the community 
needs. In a situation like this, it is important that funds for 
the relief are guarded and used effectively, when the 
temptation is to think ``it is an emergency'' justifies waste, 
or worse. But this cannot end in more bureaucracy.
    I believe God put me in this trying time at the head of a 
city of 100,000 people, to do them justice and make a 
difference. You, too, are called upon to do justice and make a 
difference for the 3.4 million U.S. citizens in Puerto Rico. It 
is not a time just to put on patches, but to make permanent 
fixes looking toward the future. We cannot move the island away 
from the Caribbean, so Congress and the Administration must 
move to help our people.
    Members of this Committee, Federal help has aided Puerto 
Rico to survive and start a recovery. But more is needed, and I 
encourage you to listen to our Governor and our Resident 
Commissioner, our voice in this city, as she brings forward 
what are our further needs. Thank you.
</option>
</Directory>
</Hearing>
