<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="25870">
    <intro>    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <info>                         [H.A.S.C. No. 115-48]</info>
    <info>                                HEARING</info>
    <info>                                   ON</info>
    <info>                   NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT</info>
    <info>                          FOR FISCAL YEAR 2018</info>
    <info>                                  AND</info>
    <info>              OVERSIGHT OF PREVIOUSLY AUTHORIZED PROGRAMS</info>
    <info>                               BEFORE THE</info>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES</committee_name>
    <option>                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
</option>
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON SEAPOWER AND PROJECTION FORCES HEARING</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                                   ON
                     DEPARTMENT OF THE NAVY FISCAL
                      YEAR 2018 BUDGET REQUEST FOR
                     SEAPOWER AND PROJECTION FORCES
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                              MAY 24, 2017
                                   ______
                     U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE 
25-870                    WASHINGTON : 2018                 
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON SEAPOWER AND PROJECTION FORCES</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                 ROBERT J. WITTMAN, Virginia, Chairman
K. MICHAEL CONAWAY, Texas            JOE COURTNEY, Connecticut
VICKY HARTZLER, Missouri             SUSAN A. DAVIS, California
BRADLEY BYRNE, Alabama, Vice Chair   JAMES R. LANGEVIN, Rhode Island
SCOTT DesJARLAIS, Tennessee          MADELEINE Z. BORDALLO, Guam
MIKE GALLAGHER, Wisconsin            JOHN GARAMENDI, California
DUNCAN HUNTER, California            DONALD NORCROSS, New Jersey
PAUL COOK, California                SETH MOULTON, Massachusetts
JIM BRIDENSTINE, Oklahoma            COLLEEN HANABUSA, Hawaii
STEPHEN KNIGHT, California           A. DONALD McEACHIN, Virginia
RALPH LEE ABRAHAM, Louisiana
                Dave Sienicki, Professional Staff Member
              Phil MacNaughton, Professional Staff Member
                          Jodi Brignola, Clerk 
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <Directory>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <Speakers>STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>Hon Joe Courtney</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative from Connecticut Ranking Member</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon Robert J Wittman</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative from Virginia Chairman</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <Witness>Allison Stiller</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Performing the Duties of Assistant Secretary of Defense for Research Development</peopleinfo>
    <option>APPENDIX</option>
    <Speakers>Prepared Statements:</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>Allison Stiller</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>joint with LtGen Robert S Walsh and VADM William K Lescher Wittman Hon Robert J</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker>Documents Submitted for the Record: Force Structure Assessment Executive Summary February</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Accelerated Fleet Plan ``The Future Navy'' Admiral Richardson May</peopleinfo>
</Directory>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>Subcommittee on Seapower and Projection Forces,</subcomittee_name>
    <Chairman>
        <Cname>                           Washington</Cname>
        <Clocation> 2017.</Clocation>
    </Chairman>
    <people>
        <Pname>The subcommittee met</Pname>
        <Plocation> in </Plocation>
    </people>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>room 2212</Cname>
        <Clocation> Hon. Robert J. </Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <people>
        <Pname>Wittman (chairman of the subcommittee) presiding.</Pname>
        <Plocation>Wittman (chairman of the subcommittee) presiding.</Plocation>
    </people>
    <option>     FROM VIRGINIA, CHAIRMAN, SUBCOMMITTEE ON SEAPOWER AND 
                       PROJECTION FORCES
    Mr. Wittman. I will call to order the Subcommittee on 
Seapower and Projection Forces of the Committee on Armed 
Services. And today, we meet to discuss the Department of 
Navy's fiscal year 2018 budget request.
    Appearing before us today to discuss the important topic 
are three esteemed Navy witnesses. First, we have Ms. Allison 
Stiller, performing the duties of Assistant Secretary of 
Defense, Research Development and Acquisition.
    We also have Vice Admiral William K. Lescher, Deputy Chief 
of Naval Operations for Integration of Resources and 
Capabilities; and Lieutenant General Robert S. Walsh, Deputy 
Commandant of Combat Development and Integration.
    And I want to thank all of you for your service, and just 
as important, thank you for appearing before this subcommittee 
on the fiscal year 2018 budget request.
    Last week, the Chief of Naval Operations [CNO], Admiral 
Richardson, laid out a bold vision for the Navy. He indicated, 
``Both China and Russia are able to compete on a global scale, 
in all domains, and at competitive speed.'' In response to this 
increased global pressure, he stated, ``The future fleet must 
be timely--we need this more powerful fleet in the 2020s, not 
the 2040s.'' Without any reservation, I believe that the CNO is 
correct. Unfortunately, the fiscal year 2018 budget request 
does not support the vision of the CNO, nor of this 
subcommittee.
    While I do not object with the budget's emphasis on current 
readiness, I believe that there is a high degree of naivete in 
the area of ship construction. We must start now, not in 2019. 
Some believe that ship construction is like a spigot that can 
be turned off and on. I believe that there are those in defense 
budgeting that advocate for such an approach.
    In ship construction, though, we know one thing for 
certain: Ship construction is a long game and requires steady 
funding to achieve steady progress. Unfortunately, I do not see 
steady progress towards fulfilling the goal of attaining a 355-
ship Navy. The budget request of only 8 ships does little to 
build towards a 355-ship Navy. We have hot production lines 
ready to add more work, but the call to duty has not been 
sounded. It is time to get serious and match our peer 
competitors with aggressive ship construction initiatives.
    As to the specific concerns with the Navy request, building 
1 aircraft carrier every 5 years will never allow us to reach 
12 aircraft carriers; building 2 attack submarines a year will 
result in a submarine reduction in force by 20 percent in 10 
years; and building only 1 LCS [littoral combat ship] will 
result in massive layoffs at both Marinette and Mobile in the 
States of Wisconsin and Alabama. These are not acceptable 
outcomes.
    As the Marine Corps, I am pleased that this committee has 
supported--as to the Marine Corps, excuse me, I am pleased that 
this committee supported the authorization of two more San 
Antonio-class amphibious ships in the last 2 years. However, I 
hold some concerns in respect to conducting amphibious 
operations in a contested environment. As our adversaries 
become more capable, our Marine Corps may need a bold new 
vision to accomplish future missions.
    And I know, in speaking with General Walsh, that they are 
well on track to do that and looking at all the opportunities 
that are out there, using every platform at their avail, but it 
is our duty to make sure that we find ways to make sure we 
enable and allow for those visions to be accomplished.
    This vision may require a change to our legacy forces. 
Expansion of aviation projection, longer range connectors, and 
a lighter amphibious capability are all desired attributes of a 
more capable expeditionary force structure. Unfortunately, I 
see little of this in the budget request to change our current 
trajectory.
    I am reminded of the words of John F. Kennedy himself, a 
proud Navy officer, when he said that history has taught us 
that control of the seas means security. Control of the seas 
can mean peace. Control of the seas can mean victory. The 
United States must control the seas if it is to protect your 
security. Ladies and gentlemen, it is time that our Nation wake 
up and seize control of the seas.
    I would now like to turn to our ranking member, Joe 
Courtney, for any remarks that he may have.
</option>
    <option>Appendix on page 37.]
</option>
    <option>   CONNECTICUT, RANKING MEMBER, SUBCOMMITTEE ON SEAPOWER AND 
                       PROJECTION FORCES
    Mr. Courtney. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    And again, I want to thank the three distinguished 
witnesses that are here today to discuss the fiscal year 2018 
budget request for the Department of the Navy and the Marine 
Corps.
    Before we get into the substance of the hearing, I think it 
is important to remember the context in which we are 
considering the budget request submitted yesterday. In December 
of last year, the Navy, under President Obama and Secretary 
Mabus, released an updated Force Structure Assessment [FSA] 
that laid out a requirement for increasing the fleet from 308 
ships to 355. Among other factors, the FSA noted that increased 
operations, lengthened deployments, and changing conditions 
around the globe necessitated this boost.
    Then, in the early days of the Trump administration, the 
Navy submitted an Accelerated Fleet Plan that, in the words of 
Acting Navy Secretary Sean Stackley, stated: It offers a first 
step towards a framework to develop the strategic guidance and 
identify the investments needed to reinvigorate our naval 
forces. That plan identified 29 additional ships that the Navy 
found could be accelerated in support of the larger fleet 
identified in the FSA.
    And just last week, the Chief of Naval Operations, John 
Richardson, released a white paper noting the urgent need to 
boost the fleet as quickly as possible. As he concludes in the 
paper, time is of the essence. I agree and, like many of my 
colleagues on this panel, I have eagerly awaited more details 
on how the Trump administration would move forward on the 
highly bipartisan push for a larger and more capable Navy 
fleet.
    Unfortunately, the shipbuilding budget released yesterday 
reflects none of these inputs. Instead, it requests funding for 
only 8 ships and submarines, the same level as planned by the 
former Obama administration plan prior to the December FSA, 
lower than the 11 ships that we just voted on in the 2017 
Omnibus Appropriations Act that we passed out of Congress just 
this last month on a bipartisan basis, and lower than the 12 
ships that the Navy identified in its Accelerated Fleet Plan 
for 2018.
    In other words, the Trump administration has proposed a 
300-ship budget for a 355-ship plan. This proposal really begs 
the question, what is the administration waiting for? The table 
was set for this administration to take the work that had been 
done for years during the prior administration to hit the 
ground running towards a larger fleet.
    While I understand the Defense Department is planning a 
wider review of its defense strategy that will guide future 
investments, I can think of no element of the Department that 
has as solid a foundation to start from than shipbuilding. A 
year lost in shipbuilding can never be regained, and, 
unfortunately, that is what this budget proposes.
    Shipbuilding, as the chairman stated, is a long game that 
relies on certainty in the Navy's plans and intentions. Nothing 
in this budget, however, provides any clarity on where this 
administration intends to go with the buildup of the fleet. 
There is no 30-year shipbuilding plan that was submitted 
yesterday. And there was no FYDP, there was no Future Years 
Defense Plan, that defense officials so far have just simply 
named as a placeholder.
    Congress, industry, and the American people are left 
guessing as to the way ahead. For some shipyards, this could be 
a make-or-break issue for them, and we need to tread carefully 
to ensure that we have a well-rounded industrial base in the 
future.
    We have a lot of hard work ahead in the next few weeks to 
craft our 2018 defense authorization bill and an extremely 
truncated timeline. I hope that we will use the modest 
shipbuilding request submitted to us yesterday as a floor and 
not as a ceiling as we look for ways to further support the 
Navy's fleet expansion and the industrial base that we will 
need to support it.
    That is not to say that there are not elements in this 
budget that I strongly support. One area of welcome progress is 
in our undersea forces. In addition to fully funding two attack 
submarines in 2018, as planned in the 2014 multiyear contract, 
the budget supports a long-sought priority of mine, which is 
the restoration of a second attack sub in 2021, making sure 
that the two-a-year build rate will be all the way through the 
next block contract, Block V contract. That means we can expect 
at least 10 submarines in that next block, while we look for 
additional opportunities to increase that rate where the 
capacity exists to meet the increased fleet requirements of the 
FSA.
    In addition to supporting continued development and early 
production on the Columbia-class SSBN [ballistic missile 
submarine], the budget reflects the Navy's use of key 
authorities that we provided through the National Sea-Based 
Deterrence Fund. I note that nearly $100 million is allocated 
in this budget for continuous production of missile tubes and 
advanced construction activities in the first Columbia-class 
boomer, the SSBN-826.
    As we well know, which is we are the committee that drafted 
and created the National Sea-Based Deterrence Fund, the 
authorities in the NSBDF have been projected to save hundreds 
of millions of dollars if fully utilized. And I look forward to 
hearing more from the Navy about how they intend to use those 
authorities in 2018 and beyond.
    I also strongly support the increased focus on restoring 
readiness and operational availability of our fleet through 
expanding funding for the ship depot maintenance. This is a 
topic that Chairman Wittman and I recently publicly discussed 
in a forum together and one that is absolutely critical to 
ensuring that we can fully utilize the fleet we have today as 
we build towards the future.
    It appears that the budget intends to leverage capacity in 
the private yards to support maintenance priorities as well as 
focus investment in our shipyard capacity and infrastructure. 
The backlog in ship availabilities is immense, and we clearly 
need to do more to address this problem in 2018 and beyond.
    Finally, so much of what we do in the 2018 budget will 
depend on how we address the Sword of Damocles that is hanging 
over the entire process: the Budget Control Act caps, and the 
threat of sequestration. Much has been said about lifting the 
defense sequester at the expense of non-defense spending, such 
as STEM [science, technology, engineering, and mathematics] 
education and job training funding outside of the Pentagon. I 
can think of no worse approach for the overall security and 
well-being of our Nation.
    We cannot expect to embark on the buildup of our ships, 
aircraft, or other advanced technologies if we are at the same 
time gutting education, workforce development, skills training, 
and other efforts at closing the job-skill mismatch that is 
rampant in defense manufacturing all across the country. The 
only way we are going to extract ourselves from our current 
budget quagmire is through a balanced approach that ensures 
that we meet all the needs of our Nation.
    I yield back.
    Mr. Wittman. Thank you, Mr. Courtney. Thanks for those 
opening statement words. And it is good to know that I think we 
are both on the same page about what the course is ahead.
    So with that, Ms. Stiller, I will go to you for the opening 
statement that I know that you will present for both the Navy 
and Marine Corps.
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
</Hearing>
