<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="29780">
    <intro>    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <info>                             AN OVERVIEW OF</info>
    <info>                    THE NATIONAL SCIENCE FOUNDATION</info>
    <info>                  BUDGET PROPOSAL FOR FISCAL YEAR 2019</info>
    <info>=======================================================================</info>
    <info>                                HEARING</info>
    <info>                               BEFORE THE</info>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON SCIENCE, SPACE, AND TECHNOLOGY</committee_name>
    <option>                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             SECOND SESSION
                               __________
                             MARCH 15, 2018
                               __________
                           Serial No. 115-53
                               __________
 Printed for the use of the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology
[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT] 
       Available via the World Wide Web: http://science.house.gov
                                __________
                    U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE                    
29-780PDF                  WASHINGTON : 2018                     
----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing Office, 
http://bookstore.gpo.gov. For more information, contact the GPO Customer Contact Center, 
U.S. Government Publishing Office. Phone 202-512-1800, or 866-512-1800 (toll-free). 
E-mail, gpo@custhelp.com.              
</option>
</intro>
    <committeeComposition>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON SCIENCE, SPACE, AND TECHNOLOGY</comitteeM_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>HON. LAMAR S. SMITH</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chair</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>FRANK D. LUCAS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oklahoma</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>EDDIE BERNICE JOHNSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DANA ROHRABACHER</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ZOE LOFGREN</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MO BROOKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DANIEL LIPINSKI</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RANDY HULTGREN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SUZANNE BONAMICI</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oregon</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BILL POSEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>AMI BERA</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>THOMAS MASSIE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Kentucky</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ELIZABETH H. ESTY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Connecticut</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM BRIDENSTINE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oklahoma</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARC A. VEASEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RANDY K. WEBER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DONALD S. BEYER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEPHEN KNIGHT</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JACKY ROSEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nevada</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRIAN BABIN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JERRY McNERNEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BARBARA COMSTOCK</Pname>
        <Plocation> Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ED PERLMUTTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Colorado</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BARRY LOUDERMILK</Pname>
        <Plocation> Georgia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PAUL TONKO</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RALPH LEE ABRAHAM</Pname>
        <Plocation> Louisiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BILL FOSTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DANIEL WEBSTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARK TAKANO</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM BANKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Indiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>COLLEEN HANABUSA</Pname>
        <Plocation> Hawaii</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ANDY BIGGS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CHARLIE CRIST</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROGER W. MARSHALL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Kansas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>NEAL P. DUNN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CLAY HIGGINS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Louisiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RALPH NORMAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> South Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
</committeeComposition>
    <Directory>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <peopleSpeaker> March </peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Witness List Hearing Charter Opening Statements</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker>  Representative Lamar S Smith</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Chairman Committee on Science Space</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker>  Representative Eddie Bernice Johnson</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Ranking Member Committee on Science Space</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>Witnesses:</witnesses>
    <Witness>Dr France Cordova</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Director National Science Foundation Oral Statement Written Statement</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Dr Maria T Zuber</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Chair National Science Board Oral Statement Written Statement Discussion</peopleinfo>
    <option>Appendix I: Answers to Post-Hearing Questions</option>
    <option>Dr. France Cordova, Director, National Science Foundation........    70
Dr. Maria T. Zuber, Chair, National Science Board................   127
            Appendix II: Additional Material for the Record
Prepared statement submitted by Representative Daniel Lipinski, 
  Committee on Science, Space, and Technology, U.S. House of 
  Representatives................................................   130
                             AN OVERVIEW OF
                    THE NATIONAL SCIENCE FOUNDATION
                  BUDGET PROPOSAL FOR FISCAL YEAR 2019
                              ----------                              
                        THURSDAY, MARCH 15, 2018
                  House of Representatives,
               Committee on Science, Space, and Technology,
                                                   Washington, D.C.
    The Committee met, pursuant to call, at 10:06 a.m., in Room 
2318 of the Rayburn House Office Building, Hon. Lamar Smith 
[Chairman of the Committee] presiding.
[GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman Smith. Everybody got quiet very suddenly, but 
before that, this was a very happy crowd.
    The Committee on Science, Space, and Technology will come 
to order. Without objection, the Chair is authorized to declare 
recesses of the Committee at any time.
    Good morning, and welcome to today's hearing entitled ``An 
Overview of the National Science Foundation Budget Proposal for 
Fiscal Year 2019.'' And I'll recognize myself for an opening 
statement.
    Today, we welcome Dr. France Cordova, the Director of the 
National Science Foundation, and Dr. Maria Zuber, Chair of the 
National Science Board, to testify about the Administration's 
budget request and funding priorities for the National Science 
Foundation in fiscal year 2019.
    Before its creation in 1950, the NSF's mission has been to 
promote fundamental scientific discovery. The NSF is the only 
federal agency that supports basic research across all 
scientific fields, including research in areas like national 
security, energy, quantum technology, biotechnology, STEM 
education and cybersecurity. Through competitive grants, the 
NSF funds more than 360,000 scientists, engineers, and students 
across the country. This helps make the United States a world 
leader in knowledge and innovation.
    The Committee finished the last Congress by completing work 
on the American Innovation and Competitiveness Act, authorizing 
some of the NSF's activities, including work on STEM education 
and high-performance computing. The law made permanent 
transparency and accountability policies that require the NSF 
to describe the research projects it funds in nontechnical 
terms. The law also improved the NSF grantmaking process, 
affirming that research funded through the merit review 
selection process must be in the national interest.
    I want to recognize Dr. Cordova for the steps the NSF has 
taken to improve accountability over the last three years and 
acknowledge Dr. Zuber's work on behalf of the National Science 
Board as well.
    I have to say that sometimes in the past I have been 
critical of the NSF for funding too many projects that seem 
marginal or frivolous. When the NSF spent $700,000 on a Climate 
Change Musical or $1.5 million to study pasture management in 
Mongolia, it reduced investments in projects that could yield 
groundbreaking new knowledge and discoveries.
    I believe there has certainly been improvement, but 
challenges remain. I am concerned that there are too many 
projects being funded in the social, behavioral, and economic 
sciences that are not worthy of taxpayers' dollars. For 
example, in the past year the NSF has spent $310,000 to study 
Congressional ``Dear Colleague'' letters, $450,000 to study why 
there is no single English word for ``light blue,'' $330,000 to 
study cell phone use by Tanzanian women, $138,000 to study 
monkey responses to ``inequity and violated expectation,'' 
$217,000 to document a language spoken in two villages of 
northern Pakistan, and $75,000 to ``produce a description of 
Maku,'' an extinct Amazon language.
    Social-behavioral science can help solve some complex 
problems that touch several areas of science. For instance, 
protecting computers and computer networks from hackers 
requires research in both computer and behavioral science. But 
when only one out of five requests for grants is being funded, 
there must be priorities. We cannot afford to misspend another 
dollar on low-priority or frivolous activities. Simply put, the 
NSF should fund useful research over the useless.
    China now has the world's fastest supercomputer and has 
just passed the United States for the first time to lead the 
world in the number and total performance of supercomputers. 
China is also making rapid progress in artificial intelligence, 
quantum computing, human genome editing, and other crucial 
areas of science and technology. Unfortunately, as China leaps 
forward, the United States is slowing down investment in key 
areas of basic research like physics and computing. This will 
not change unless taxpayers' money is better invested.
    I also am concerned about whether or not the NSF is 
developing its STEM workforce programs to meet the needs of our 
economy. The United States continues to lag significantly 
behind China and the European Union in science and engineering 
bachelor's degrees, with China producing more than twice the 
number of STEM undergraduates. In the physical and biological 
sciences, China produces four times more undergraduates in 
those fields than the United States.
    The NSF plays a critical role in helping educate and train 
the next generation of STEM workers. We need to invest in young 
people who will go into fields where there is a national need 
and good-paying jobs.
    Now that there is a two-year budget agreement in place, we 
have an opportunity to reauthorize the science agencies under 
our Committee's jurisdiction, including the NSF, to rebalance 
priorities and ensure that our nation's science agencies are on 
a trajectory to keep America at the forefront of scientific 
knowledge and discovery.
    This Committee has demonstrated that there is broad support 
for basic and fundamental research and STEM education. Twenty 
of the twenty-two bills the Science, Space, and Technology 
Committee has brought to the House Floor this Congress have 
been bipartisan pieces of legislation. We are committed to 
maintaining America's leadership in science, thereby ensuring 
future economic prosperity.
</option>
    <option>[GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman Smith. That concludes my opening statement, and 
the Ranking Member, the gentlewoman from Texas, Ms. Johnson, is 
recognized for her opening statement.
    Ms. Johnson. Thank you very much, Chairman Smith, and good 
morning. I appreciate you holding this hearing, and I want to 
welcome Dr. Cordova and Dr. Zuber. I'm pleased that we have 
both of you here this morning to help us understand the fiscal 
2019 budget request for the National Science Foundation and the 
potential impact of this request on NSF's ability to help 
support U.S. leadership in science.
    Funding for the National Science Foundation peaked in 2010 
at $7.7 billion. In the years since then, the budget has 
stagnated at or below $7.5 billion. This is the case despite 
the Obama Administration requesting increases each year. In 
stark contrast, last year, the Trump Administration proposed to 
cut NSF by 11 percent, and this year, until Congress passed the 
budget agreement, the proposed cut was closer to 30 percent. 
This Administration has demonstrated time and again how little 
they value science.
    Given these trends, most of us are relieved when the NSF 
budget remains flat rather than cut. However, flat is a decline 
in real dollars, and it represents a terribly low standard for 
which to judge our nation's standing in science and technology. 
We will hear in Dr. Zuber's testimony how other countries are 
doubling down on their investments in R&amp;amp;D while we're cutting.
    Having said that, I applaud Dr. Cordova and your team at 
NSF for being as bold and forward-looking as you could be, 
given the constraints imposed upon you by the budget of the 
White House. I will highlight just a few items of interest or 
concern that I hope we can discuss further in the hearing.
    Advancing science to solve our national and global 
challenges increasingly depends on teams of scientists from 
various disciplines coming together in what is now commonly 
known as convergent research. However, for generations, 
universities and the National Science Foundation itself have 
been organized around disciplines. While advances in these core 
disciplines do and must continue, this organizational structure 
has created stovepipes and inhibited convergent research.
    In fiscal year 2019 budget request, NSF takes a big leap to 
transcend those traditional boundaries through dedicated 
funding for its 10 Big Ideas. In that respect, this is an 
exciting budget proposal. However, having been forced into a 
zero-sum choice, the agency had to make cuts elsewhere, namely 
to the core research programs and to education and training 
programs at all levels. These tradeoffs merit further 
discussion before we can be comfortable that the benefits 
outweigh the potential harm.
    This budget also represents the first time that the agency 
is singling out one of its research directorates for a 
disproportionate cut while every other directorate is nearly 
flat. The Social, Behavioral, and Economic Sciences 
Directorate, or the SBE, would be cut by 11 percent. I do not 
doubt this steep cut was dictated from the White House. 
However, this ongoing devaluing of the role of SBE in meeting 
our national challenges could have damaging consequences. I 
look forward to hearing from Dr. Cordova and Dr. Zuber on what 
steps NSF will take to mitigate this harm.
    I'm pleased to see the Antarctic Infrastructure 
Modernization for Science, or AIMS, project in the request, 
along with a proposal for a midscale research infrastructure 
program. I look forward to hearing more about both of these 
proposals.
    Finally, as I alluded to earlier, while there are a few 
bright spots in education and broadening participation funding, 
I am concerned about the overall cuts to education in this 
budget. Education and training programs across research 
account--would be cut by nearly 25 percent. Proven programs 
such as Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program, research experiences 
for undergraduates, and the graduate research fellowships would 
all receive steep cuts. NSF has a dual mission of research and 
education. We cannot afford to back away from our commitment to 
either one.
    I thank you, Dr. Cordova and Dr. Zuber, for being here this 
morning to help us examine these issues and concerns in more 
detail.
    I thank you, Mr. Chairman, for holding this important 
hearing, and I yield back.
</option>
    <option>[GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman Smith. Thank you, Ms. Johnson.
    Our first witness today is Dr. France Cordova, Director of 
the National Science Foundation. Dr. Cordova was sworn in as 
Director of the NSF in March 2014. She previously served as 
President of Purdue University from 2007 to 2012. From 1993 to 
1996, Dr. Cordova served as the Chief Scientist at NASA, and 
she is the recipient of NASA's highest honor, the Distinguished 
Service Medal.
    Dr. Cordova has a Bachelor of Arts from Stanford University 
and a Ph.D. in physics from the California Institute of 
Technology.
    Joining Director Cordova today to assist in answering 
technical questions is Dr. Joan Ferrini-Mundy, Acting Chief 
Operating Officer of the National Science Foundation. 
Previously, she led the NSF Education and Human Resources 
Directorate and co-chaired the White House National Science and 
Technology Council's Federal Coordination and STEM Education 
Task Force. Prior to the NSF, she was a Distinguished Professor 
of Mathematics Education at Michigan State University. Dr. 
Derrini-Mundi holds a Ph.D. in mathematics education from the 
University of New Hampshire.
    Our second witness today is Dr. Maria Zuber, Chair of the 
National Science Board. In 2013, Dr. Zuber was appointed Vice 
President for Research at the Massachusetts Institute of 
Technology where she oversees more than a dozen research 
laboratories and centers. Dr. Zuber was awarded the NASA 
Distinguished Public Service Medal in 2004, and in 2008, she 
was named to the U.S. News' list of ``America's Best Leaders.''
    She received a Bachelor of Arts in astronomy from the 
University of Pennsylvania, as well as a Master of Science and 
Ph.D. both in geophysics from Brown University.
    We welcome you all and look forward to your testimony. And 
Dr. Cordova, if you'll begin.
</option>
    <option>             DIRECTOR, NATIONAL SCIENCE FOUNDATION
    Dr. Cordova. Thank you, Chairman Smith, Ranking Member 
Johnson, and Members of the Committee. I'm pleased to be here 
today to discuss the President's fiscal year 2019 budget 
request for the National Science Foundation.
    The request is $7.47 billion, level with the fiscal year 
2017 appropriation. This level of funding reflects the 
Administration's commitment to NSF's role in strengthening the 
Nation's economy, national security, and global leadership in 
sciences and engineering.
    NSF funds basic research that advances and sustains 
American preeminence in the innovation economy. NSF accounts 
for approximately 27 percent of the total federal budget for 
basic research conducted at U.S. colleges and universities. For 
computer science, that number is 83 percent. For biology, 69 
percent, for engineering, 46 percent. These investments produce 
invaluable benefits to our nation and the world.
    Economists have noted that over 50 percent of America's 
economic growth over the past 50 years is attributable to 
technological innovation. Much of it is the fruit of the 
uniquely American research and innovation ecosystem among 
academia, industry, and government where ideas, artifacts, and 
people flow among these sectors. In information technology, 
this is embodied in this tire-tracks diagram. This 
extraordinary ecosystem has given rise to multibillion-dollar 
industries, and it all begins, as the diagram shows, with 
investment in fundamental long-term research often made with 
federal dollars and often made many years, even decades before 
it evolved into billion-dollar businesses.
    MRI technology, gene editing, barcode technology, Google, 
3-D printing, these are all areas NSF invested in early that 
have transformed our lives. Today, NSF is at the forefront of 
research in big data, quantum computing, artificial 
intelligence, cybersecurity, and robotics areas that will power 
the future economy.
    Our fiscal year 2019 request also incorporates new and 
innovative ways of doing business that will position NSF at the 
leading edge of discovery. First, NSF will invest in our 10 Big 
Ideas. The Big Ideas represent unique opportunities to position 
our nation at the frontiers, indeed to define the frontiers of 
global science and engineering leadership. An investment of $30 
million is requested for each of the six research-focused Big 
Ideas. Four other Big Ideas such as midscale facilities and the 
INCLUDES initiative focused on new approaches to increase 
opportunities for discovery and expand the STEM community.
    Our success also requires innovative approaches to 
leveraging resources over all fields of science. In fiscal year 
2019, NSF will initiate two convergence accelerators, new 
centers that will converge around important national challenges 
requiring interdisciplinary expertise. The accelerators will 
streamline operations and collaborations, focusing on results 
and outcomes that can be achieved quickly.
    An investment of $60 million will support two convergence 
accelerators for two of the Big Ideas: Harnessing the Data 
Revolution for 21st-Century Science and Engineering and the 
Future of Work at the Human-Technology Frontier. These Big 
Ideas were chosen because of the readiness for convergent and 
translational research.
    We expect to catalyze an additional $40 million in 
investment by external partners, including the private sector, 
other federal agencies, and international funders.
    Equally important to our sustained global leadership in 
science and engineering are investments in STEM education. At 
NSF our education activities are integrated with research. In 
fiscal year 2019, NSF will continue to invest in CyberCorps, 
Computer Science for All, the Advanced Technological Education 
program, and other initiatives that support teachers, students, 
and researchers from K-2 to lifelong learning environments. We 
will not have the discoveries of tomorrow without a skilled 
workforce prepared for tomorrow.
    Mr. Chairman, I had the honor of attending the 2017 Nobel 
Prize awards ceremony in Stockholm, Sweden. I was there to 
celebrate scientists in the fields of physics, economics, 
biology, and chemistry. All eight U.S. Nobelists were at some 
point in their careers supported by NSF. Three of them were 
honored for the LIGO discovery of gravitational waves, a 
discovery only made possible by 40 years of NSF support. In 
fact, NSF-funded researchers account for 231 Nobel Prizes, 
dating back to 1955. This is but one powerful example of why 
Congress' support for NSF and fundamental basic research is so 
vital.
    Another is in the tire-tracks diagram, which exhibits some 
of NSF's contributions to the growth of new robust businesses. 
This Committee has played an important role in these successes. 
Through the AICA, it continues to make our agency stronger in 
its processes to deliver the best to the American people. Thank 
you for your continued support of NSF.
</option>
    <option>[GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman Smith. Thank you, Dr. Cordova. Do you happen to 
have a hard copy of the PowerPoint that was just up on the 
screen? And if so, I'd like to make copies for members maybe 
even before the questions.
    Dr. Cordova. Yes.
    Chairman Smith. Okay. If we could----
    Dr. Cordova. If you have someone I can hand it to----
    Chairman Smith. Okay.----
    Dr. Cordova. --I would be happy to do that.
    Chairman Smith. That would be great.
    Dr. Cordova. Thank you.
    Chairman Smith. And, Dr. Zuber?
</option>
    <option>                 CHAIR, NATIONAL SCIENCE BOARD
    Dr. Zuber. Chairman Smith, Ranking Member Johnson, and 
Members of the Committee, I appreciate the opportunity to speak 
with you about the President's fiscal year 2019 budget request 
for the National Science Foundation. ``An investment in 
knowledge always pays the best interest,'' declared Benjamin 
Franklin, our nation's founding innovator. Since World War II, 
the United States has led the world in research, transforming 
our lives, driving economic growth, and underpinning national 
security. Sustained bipartisan commitment to investing in 
fundamental research helped establish and maintain U.S. 
leadership in science and technology.
    But the global science and technology landscape is rapidly 
changing. Other nations are upping their game. For the first 
time in over a half-century, our S&amp;amp;T leadership is being 
challenged. According to the Board's 2018 Science and 
Engineering Indicators Report, China's spending on R&amp;amp;D has 
grown by an average of 18 percent since the year 2000, while 
ours has grown by only four percent. Since 2000, China has 
tripled the number of STEM bachelor's degree awardees, and 
between 2013 and 2016, just three years, venture capital in 
China climbed from 5 to 27 percent of the global share, the 
fastest increase of any economy.
    Although these trends are not new, in some cutting-edge 
areas of research, the trajectory is more pronounced. Within 
the last year, China erased the U.S. advantage in 
supercomputing, claiming more than 200 of the fastest 500 
supercomputers to our 143. Over the next five years, China 
plans to invest 100 times more in artificial intelligence than 
the United States did in 2016. At the same time, total federal 
R&amp;amp;D funding has been declining from $127 billion in 2011 to 
$120 billion in 2015. Federal R&amp;amp;D spending as a share of GDP is 
now the lowest it has been since 1953. These choices have 
concrete consequences. If current trends continue, China will 
surpass the United States in total R&amp;amp;D expenditures sometime 
this year.
    Despite these ominous trends, the Board is encouraged by 
Congress' agreement on a budgetary framework and the President 
working within those caps to prioritize NSF's mission of 
discovery in research and the national interest. With the 
requested level of funding in fiscal year 2019, NSF will 
support basic research across all fields of science and 
engineering that create knowledge, while allowing investment in 
priority areas.
    The Board recognizes the fiscal challenge with--that 
Congress wrestles. In such difficult times, there can be a 
tendency to play it safe, but as America's innovation agency, 
NSF is not going to play it safe. First, the agency is 
embracing our nation's entrepreneurial spirit in trying 
something new. As the Director has just described, NSF proposes 
to break out of academic silos by investing in new elements to 
promote cutting-edge interdisciplinary research at the 
frontiers of science and technology: the Big Ideas and 
convergence accelerators. Much transformative research happens 
at the intersection of scientific fields. The Board believes 
this proactive approach is essential if NSF is to succeed in 
its mission to advance the frontiers of science.
    Next, our nation's ability to discover, invent, and 
innovate relies on our ability to leverage America's greatest 
competitive advantage: our people. To ensure that Americans are 
equipped to thrive in a globally competitive knowledge economy, 
NSF will work with Congress, the Administration, business 
leaders, educators, and others to create to create a STEM-
capable workforce. Our workforce of the future must leverage 
the hard work, creativity, and ingenuity of women and men of 
all ages, education levels, and backgrounds. NSF will continue 
to build this workforce through initiatives such as INCLUDES, 
ATE, and CyberCorps.
    Finally, NSF is committed to innovating and improving our 
internal processes. The Board takes its responsibility to 
taxpayers seriously. We are now taking a fresh look at the 
merit review report, working with NSF to advance formal risk-
thinking and strategic planning and priority-setting, and 
strengthening our oversight of major research facilities.
    And I would be remiss if I did not thank you, Chairman 
Smith, for your leadership and holding us to the highest 
standards of accountability and transparency.
    Investing in discovery research now will give us the keys 
to meeting unpredictable national security, economic, and 
health challenges of tomorrow. As President Trump warned, 
losing our innovation and technological edge would have far-
reaching negative implications for American prosperity and 
power. We need a renewed and committed strategy to hold onto 
this key national asset.
    But in challenge there is also opportunity. If we 
capitalize on the strong foundations of our innovation 
ecosystem and the talents of our people, we can pursue grand 
visions, enable revolutionary ideas, and reap the unexpected 
advances that emerge from dreaming boldly and fearlessly to 
pursue fundamental science.
    Thank you and I look forward to your questions.
</option>
</Directory>
</Hearing>
