<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="33479">
    <intro>    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <info>COMPLEXITIES AND CHALLENGES OF SOCIAL SECURITY COVERAGE AND PAYROLL TAX </info>
    <info>               COMPLIANCE FOR STATE AND LOCAL GOVERNMENTS</info>
    <info>=======================================================================</info>
    <info>                                HEARING</info>
    <info>                               BEFORE THE</info>
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON SOCIAL SECURITY</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                                  AND
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON OVERSIGHT</subcomittee_name>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON WAYS AND MEANS</committee_name>
    <option>                     U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                             JUNE 29, 2017
                               __________
                          Serial No. 115-SS04
                               __________
         Printed for the use of the Committee on Ways and Means
[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]   
                    U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE                    
33-479                      WASHINGTON : 2019                     
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <committeeComposition>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON WAYS AND MEANS</comitteeM_name>
    <Chairman>
        <Cname>                      KEVIN BRADY</Cname>
        <Clocation> Chairman</Clocation>
    </Chairman>
    <people>
        <Pname>SAM JOHNSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RICHARD E. NEAL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Massachusetts</Plocation>
    </people>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>DEVIN NUNES</Cname>
        <Clocation> California</Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>SANDER M. LEVIN</Cname>
        <Clocation> Michigan</Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <people>
        <Pname>PATRICK J. TIBERI</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOHN LEWIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Georgia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DAVID G. REICHERT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Washington</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>LLOYD DOGGETT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PETER J. ROSKAM</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE THOMPSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>VERN BUCHANAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOHN B. LARSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Connecticut</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ADRIAN SMITH</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nebraska</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>EARL BLUMENAUER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oregon</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>LYNN JENKINS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Kansas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RON KIND</Pname>
        <Plocation> Wisconsin</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ERIK PAULSEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Minnesota</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BILL PASCRELL</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Jersey</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>KENNY MARCHANT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOSEPH CROWLEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DIANE BLACK</Pname>
        <Plocation> Tennessee</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DANNY DAVIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TOM REED</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>LINDA SANCHEZ</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE KELLY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRIAN HIGGINS</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM RENACCI</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TERRI SEWELL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PAT MEEHAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SUZAN DELBENE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Washington</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>KRISTI NOEM</Pname>
        <Plocation> South Dakota</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JUDY CHU</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>GEORGE HOLDING</Pname>
        <Plocation> North Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JASON SMITH</Pname>
        <Plocation> Missouri</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TOM RICE</Pname>
        <Plocation> South Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DAVID SCHWEIKERT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JACKIE WALORSKI</Pname>
        <Plocation> Indiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CARLOS CURBELO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE BISHOP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Michigan</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>David Stewart</Pname>
        <Plocation> Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Brandon Casey</Pname>
        <Plocation> Minority Chief Counsel</Plocation>
    </people>
</committeeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON SOCIAL SECURITY</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                      SAM JOHNSON, Texas, Chairman
TOM RICE, South Carolina             JOHN B. LARSON, Connecticut
DAVID SCHWEIKERT, Arizona            BILL PASCRELL, JR., New Jersey
VERN BUCHANAN, Florida               JOSEPH CROWLEY, New York
MIKE KELLY, Pennsylvania             LINDA SANCHEZ, California
JIM RENACCI, Ohio
JASON SMITH, Missouri
                                 ______
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON OVERSIGHT</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                    VERN BUCHANAN, Florida, Chairman
DAVID SCHWEIKERT, Arizona            JOHN LEWIS, Georgia
JACKIE WALORSKI, Indiana             JOSEPH CROWLEY, New York
CARLOS CURBELO, Florida              SUZAN DELBENE, Washington
MIKE BISHOP, Michigan                EARL BLUMENAUER, Oregon
PAT MEEHAN, Pennsylvania
GEORGE HOLDING, North Carolina
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <Directory>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <peopleSpeaker> __________  Advisory of June </peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>announcing the hearing</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <Witness>Marianna LaCanfora</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Acting Deputy Commissioner Office of Retirement and Disability Policy Social Security Administration</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Sunita Lough</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Commissioner Tax Exempt and Government Entities Division</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Maryann Motza</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>PhD Legislative Committee Chair and Past President National Conference of State Social Security Administrators QUESTIONS FOR THE RECORD</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Questions from The Honorable Sam Johnson and Vern Buchanan</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>to Marianna LaCanfora Questions from The Honorable Jim Renacci to Marianna LaCanfora</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Questions from The Honorable Sam Johnson and Vern Buchanan</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>to Sunita B Lough Questions from The Honorable Tom Rice to Sunita B Lough</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Questions from The Honorable Sam Johnson and Vern Buchanan</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>to Maryann Motza Questions from The Honorable Tom Rice to Maryann Motza Questions from The Honorable Jim Renacci to Maryann Motza PUBLIC SUBMISSIONS FOR THE RECORD Rincon Band of Luiseno Indians</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>COMPLEXITIES AND CHALLENGES OF SOCIAL SECURITY COVERAGE AND PAYROLL TAX COMPLIANCE FOR STATE AND LOCAL GOVERNMENTS  THURSDAY</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>JUNE  US House of Representatives Committee on Ways and Means</peopleinfo>
</Directory>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>Subcommittee on Social Security, joint with the</subcomittee_name>
    <option>Subcommittee on Oversight,</option>
    <option>                                                    Washington, DC.
    The subcommittees met, pursuant to call, at 10:00 a.m., in 
Room 1100, Longworth House Office Building, Hon. Sam Johnson 
[chairman of the Subcommittee on Social Security] presiding.
    [The advisory announcing the hearing follows:]
[GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman JOHNSON. Good morning, and welcome to today's 
hearing on the complexities and challenges of ensuring Social 
Security coverage and payroll tax compliance for State and 
local government employees.
    Before we begin, I would like to take a moment to say a few 
words about my friend and former Social Security Subcommittee 
Chairman Jim Bunning. You remember him?
    Mr. LARSON. Absolutely.
    Chairman JOHNSON. Sadly, Jim passed away just a few weeks 
ago. Chairman Bunning was a member of the Ways and Means 
Committee for four Congresses, and he chaired this 
Subcommittee. While many will remember Chairman Bunning as a 
baseball Hall of Famer--who pitched two no-hitters, by the 
way--I will always remember him as the guy who showed me the 
ropes on serving as Chairman on Social Security.
    Among many other bills, he introduced the Rehabilitation 
and Return to Work Opportunity Act of 1996, that ultimately 
became the basis of the Ticket to Work Act of 1999.
    More than 20 years later, this Subcommittee continues to 
look for ways to help those beneficiaries who can return to 
work. And I look forward to having another hearing on that 
topic later this year.
    Jim Bunning was a patriot, a strong supporter of Social 
Security, and a friend. We are thankful for his service and 
keep his wife, Mary, and all his family in our prayers.
    Turning back to today's hearing, usually when we talk about 
State and local workers and Social Security, we talk about how 
many of them aren't covered by Social Security. But today we 
are going to focus on the close to three-quarters of State and 
local workers who are covered and figuring out why their Social 
Security coverage and payroll tax compliance is so complicated.
    When Social Secuity was created, State and local government 
employees were excluded due to constitutional concerns. Over 
time the law was changed to allow State and local governments 
to extend Social Security coverage to their employees. Today, 
all States have at least some employees who are covered by 
Social Security and pay Social Security taxes on their 
earnings. But who is covered can vary by State and even 
locality.
    With all this complexity, it is up to Social Security, the 
IRS, and the States to work together to get it right. But as we 
will hear, that doesn't always happen.
    Back in 2010, the Government Accountability Office found 
that both Social Security and the IRS have trouble identifying 
problems with Social Security coverage for State and local 
government employees and, instead, must rely on public 
employers to ensure compliance. Not much has changed, has it?
    Social Security still does not have the ability to verify 
that State and local governments are properly reporting wages 
for covered workers, and the IRS still doesn't know whether the 
employer has reported and paid the correct amount of payroll 
tax without doing an audit. Even though payroll taxes are the 
biggest tax most people pay, efforts to improve compliance 
generally focus on other taxes.
    These problems, like the one in Missouri that we will hear 
about today, can go undetected for years and have real 
consequences for Americans' retirement security and for Social 
Security's Trust Funds. If someone thinks they are covered, but 
aren't, according to Social Security they may not qualify for 
the Social Security benefits that they have been counting on. 
And if an individual receives benefits without having paid the 
correct amount of Social Security tax, the Social Security 
Trust Funds and taxpayers are left to make up the difference.
    Let me be clear. The answer here isn't mandatory coverage, 
but Social Security and the IRS need to get their act together. 
At the end of the day, we need to be sure that State and local 
employees pay the right amount of taxes and receive the Social 
Security benefits they are counting on, and that the Social 
Security Trust Funds get the taxes that they are owed. The 
American people deserve nothing less.
    I thank our witnesses for being here today, and I look 
forward to hearing their testimony.
    I now recognize Mr. Larson for his opening statement.
    Mr. LARSON. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    And thank you Chairman Buchanan and my distinguished 
colleague, Mr. Lewis.
    I would like to welcome back Chairman Johnson. As often as 
I get to say this, I will, but to be seated at this dais 
between two iconic American heroes in Sam Johnson and John 
Lewis is in and of itself, I think for every member of this 
committee and the body in general, an honor to serve with 
perhaps two of the greatest Americans in the history of our 
Nation.
    With that, Mr. Chairman, I am also going to renew my 
pledge--or request, I would say, is better put--to have a 
hearing down in Plano, Texas. Inasmuch as--and I know you have 
had hearings there before--but inasmuch as this is your last 
term, I only think it fitting that we have a hearing down in 
Plano, Texas, preferably during the winter up here, but I am 
not saying--whenever you call for that.
    Chairman JOHNSON. Thank you.
    Mr. LARSON. Listen, also, a sad note on Jim Bunning. I 
would also like to note, not of the stature of Jim Bunning, but 
equally important to me and many people in the State of 
Connecticut, Lillian Marlow passed last evening as well. Not 
known to many at this dais.
    She was, like so many people who work on this staff, just 
an extraordinary person who kept government running with her 
hard work and wit and dedication. And I just wanted to 
recognize her here today.
    Social Security is important to all Americans. And as I 
like to say when we are out talking about it, where could you 
find in the private sector guaranteed retirement income that 
cannot be outlived, protection in the event of a career-ending 
disability, life insurance for families of a worker who dies, a 
full cost-of-living adjustment to combat the effects of 
inflation? Social Security is also portable and goes with you 
everywhere. There simply is nothing on the private sector 
market that can even remotely come close to touching Social 
Security.
    Today, 94 percent of workers in the United States are 
covered by Social Security. They and their employers contribute 
to the trust fund and earn their benefits with every paycheck, 
with half of the contributions coming from the employee and 
half coming from the employer, the employer side being tax 
deductible. But it is the responsibility of the employer to 
ensure that they are in compliance with payroll taxes.
    The only large group of workers that are outside Social 
Security are some State and local government workers who have 
their own pension plan in place of Social Security. About 
three-quarters of the State and local workers participate in 
Social Security, but about a quarter don't. In my own State of 
Connecticut, teachers have a separate retirement plan and are 
not participating in Social Security, but they have an 
alternative plan that they pay for, regardless.
    The fundamental principle is one way or another, every 
American should have basic retirement coverage at work. Our job 
today is to make sure that that is the case.
    For the 90,000 units of State and local government in the 
United States, it can be complicated sometimes to determine 
which employees are participating in Social Security and who 
pays into the State plan, as Mr. Johnson has already outlined. 
But when mistakes are made, workers' financial security is at 
stake.
    That is why this hearing today is so vitally important. I 
thank our witnesses for being here.
    It is also why we have introduced the Social Security 2100 
Act, because we believe so strongly that Social Security needs 
to be expanded and needs to be made solvent into the next 
century, and so that it is there for every single American and 
providing the kind of benefits with the greatest efficiency.
    And with that, Mr. Chairman, I will yield back my time. 
And, again, it is great to see you.
    Chairman JOHNSON. Thank you. I appreciate that. Thank you 
very much.
    Would you like to make an opening statement?
    Chairman BUCHANAN. Yes. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    And I also would like to comment on Jim Bunning. As a young 
kid growing up in Detroit, he was a hero to a lot of us. He was 
an incredible pitcher. And I know he served here in Congress. 
So I share your thoughts with him.
    Good morning. I want to thank the panel for coming today 
and I look forward to the hearing. I also want to thank 
Chairman Johnson for his important oversight work.
    Today we are looking to better understand the challenge 
that State and local governments face when applying Social 
Security coverage to their workers. While many states and local 
government workers rely on their own retirement plans, others 
rely on Social Security through voluntary arrangements between 
the State and the Social Security Administration.
    Giving states flexibility on coverage decisions is 
important. However, it often leads to complication, individual 
coverage situations for State and local employees. This creates 
a unique challenge for State and local employees as well as the 
Social Security Administration, and the IRS, who oversees these 
programs.
    Nearly 70 percent of the $3.3 trillion collected by the IRS 
comes from employment-related taxes, like those for Social 
Security and Medicare. These contributions must be accurate.
    However, the complexity of the coverage issue for State and 
local governments requires a combined effort in terms of the 
Social Security Administration, the IRS, and the Social 
Security administrators to provide State and local employers 
with appropriate guidance and oversight.
    I look forward to the hearing, and also look forward to our 
witnesses, so we can assist them to ensure that we better work 
together. Also, I would like to just add, I want to make sure 
that the information we get today, that we can clearly work 
with you.
    I yield back.
    Chairman JOHNSON. Thank you, sir.
    I now recognize Mr. Lewis for any opening statement you 
wish to make.
    Mr. LEWIS. Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman.
    Chairman Johnson, Chairman Buchanan, Ranking Member Larson, 
and fellow members, good morning. And good morning to our 
witnesses. Thank you for being here.
    Chairman Johnson, thank you for remembering Jim Bunning. We 
came in the same class.
    Chairman JOHNSON. Did you?
    Mr. LEWIS. In the same class. Wonderful, wonderful man. He 
played well, baseball well, but he played well as a Member of 
the House and the Senate. And our prayers go out to his family.
    Every working American should have basic retirement 
coverage. This can be provided through Social Security or 
through a State's retirement system for public sector 
employees. These benefits help ensure that Americans maintain a 
basic standard of living during their retirement.
    Ninety-four percent of American workers receive their basic 
retirement coverage through Social Security. However, about six 
million State and local government employees do not. These 
workers participate in their State's retirement system and 
generally include teachers, firefighters, and police officers. 
In my home State of Georgia, more than 180,000 State and local 
employees are not covered by Social Security.
    State and local governments often have their own retirement 
system. However, these governments have the option to enter 
into voluntary agreements with the Social Security 
Administration to have their employees covered by Social 
Security. If a local government decides to provide coverage 
through Social Security, its employees must pay Federal payroll 
taxes just like every other American worker.
    Today's hearing will look at how Federal and State agencies 
work together to provide Social Security coverage to State and 
local government employees and ensure compliance with payroll 
tax requirements. We will learn from the witnesses more about 
how the Internal Revenue Service, the Social Security 
Administration, and State Administrators work together to 
ensure governments comply with payroll tax requirements.
    I look forward to receiving recommendations from all of our 
witnesses on how to improve compliance. And, again, I want to 
thank you for being here this morning.
    I yield back, Mr. Chairman.
    Chairman JOHNSON. Thank you.
    As is customary, any Member is welcome to submit a 
statement for the hearing record.
    Before we move on to our testimony today, I want to remind 
our witnesses to please limit your oral statements to 5 
minutes. However, without objection, all of the written 
testimony will be made a part of the hearing record.
    We have three witnesses today. Seated at the table are 
Marianna LaCanfora, Acting Deputy Commissioner, Office of 
Retirement and Disability Policy, Social Security 
Administration.
    Sunita Lough, Commissioner, Tax Exempt and Government 
Entities Divison, Internal Revenue Service.
    Maryann Motza, Legislative Committee chair and past 
president, National Conference of State Social Security 
Administrators.
    Please proceed, Ms. LaCanfora.
</option>
    <option>  OFFICE OF RETIREMENT AND DISABILITY POLICY, SOCIAL SECURITY 
                         ADMINISTRATION
    Ms. LACANFORA. Chairman Johnson, Chairman Buchanan, Ranking 
Member Larson, Ranking Member Lewis, and members of the 
subcommittees, thank you for inviting me to discuss Social 
Security coverage for State and local employees. I am Marianna 
LaCanfora, Social Security's Acting Deputy Commissioner for 
Retirement and Disability Policy.
    About 94 percent of employees in the United States are 
covered by Social Security. That is, they pay Federal Insurance 
Contributions Act, or FICA, taxes on their earnings up to a 
certain limit. Those earnings can qualify them and their 
families for benefits under our retirement, disability, and 
survivors insurance programs.
    There are approximately 23 million State and local 
employees, and about one-fourth of them are not covered by 
Social Security. My written testimony provides the long history 
of coverage-related laws for this group. But in short, when 
Social Security was enacted in 1935, no State or local 
employees were covered.
    Over time, Congress amended the Social Security Act to 
allow States to decide whether to cover employees who fall 
under a State retirement system, and to require coverage for 
those who do not. The method used by the States to establish 
coverage is called a 218 Agreement, after the authorizing 
section of the act. These Agreements specify which positions 
are covered.
    Every State, Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, and 60 
interstate instrumentalities have a 218 Agreement with us. Over 
the years, each Agreement has been modified numerous times as 
political subdivisions, positions, and retirement systems have 
been created and as groups of employees have petitioned their 
States to obtain Social Security coverage.
    Under current law, there is tremendous variability in which 
positions are covered between and even within the same State. 
For example, if two teachers are working in the same position 
in the same school district, one might be covered while the 
other is not.
    Each State and local employer is responsible for applying 
the terms of their State's 218 Agreement, accurately reporting 
earnings to SSA, and appropriately withholding FICA taxes for 
covered employees.
    Each State has a designated State Social Security 
Administrator. This State official is critical in ensuring that 
the State get its employees' coverage status right. The 
Administrator performs many functions, such as being the point 
of contact with the SSA and the IRS, interpreting the 218 
Agreement, and educating State employers and employees. They 
also hold referendums and notify us of the creation or 
dissolution of State entities.
    The IRS also plays a critical role in this process by 
performing compliance checks to ensure that States have 
appropriately withheld and remitted FICA taxes for covered 
employees.
    Given the complexity involving State and local employee 
coverage, it is no surprise that employers sometimes make 
mistakes. SSA is committed to working closely with our State 
partners and the IRS to provide the tools and training that 
States need to get these decisions right from the start and to 
address issues when they arise.
    I would like to highlight some of the actions SSA has taken 
to improve this process since GAO's last review.
    We worked with the IRS to develop a tool that States can 
use to ensure compliance with Federal tax requirements. We 
designated an employee in each of our regional offices to serve 
as an expert and point of contact. We scanned nearly all of our 
agreements and modifications, including tens of thousands of 
pages, into a central database to allow for ease of access and 
search.
    We modernized the system our employees use to resolve 
differences between the earnings reports sent to SSA and the 
IRS. We updated and clarified our policy guidance based on our 
experience and feedback from State Administrators. We developed 
comprehensive training materials and resources for the 
Administrators and provided training sessions to State and 
local employees.
    We established standing meetings with representatives from 
the IRS and the National Conference of State Social Security 
Administrators to share information and best practices and 
identify challenges and solutions to issues that arise.
    In addition, we recently started a project to compile and 
maintain lists of covered positions based on the 218 
Agreements, which will be a valuable tool and quick reference 
for the Administrators to identify coverage issues. We are also 
reviewing our regulations to identify areas that we might 
streamline or clarify.
    We remain open to ideas regarding how to further enhance 
our valuable relationship with the States and the IRS as we 
work together on these issues.
    Thank you for the opportunity to describe the history and 
complexity of Social Security coverage for State and local 
employees. I would be happy to answer any questions.
</option>
    <option>[GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman JOHNSON. Thank you, ma'am.
    Ms. Lough, welcome. Please, proceed.
</option>
    <option>                  GOVERNMENT ENTITIES DIVISION
    Ms. LOUGH. Chairman Johnson, Chairman Buchanan, Ranking 
Member Larson, Ranking Member Lewis, and members of the 
subcommittees, thank you for the opportunity to testify on 
issues surrounding the proper withholding and payment of Social 
Security and Medicare taxes in regard to State and local 
government employees.
    Mandatory Social Security and Medicare coverage for State 
and local employees is a relatively recent development. Under 
the original Social Security Act of 1935, State and local 
government employees were excluded from Social Security 
coverage. Beginning in 1951, States were allowed to enter into 
voluntary agreements with the Federal Government to provide 
Social Security coverage to public employees. These 
arrangements are called Section 218 agreements because they are 
authorized by the Section 218 of the Social Security Act.
    In 1991, Congress made Social Security coverage mandatory 
for State and local government employees who were not already 
covered by a Section 218 agreement. But this mandate does not 
apply to employees participating in a qualifying public 
retirement system sponsored by their government employer. So 
today Social Security coverage of Government employees varies 
greatly among State and local employers.
    In general, employers are required to withhold Social 
Security and Medicare taxes from employees' wages and also pay 
the employer's share of these taxes. Employers are responsible 
for furnishing Form W-2 Wage and Tax Statement annually to each 
employee when income, Social Security, or Medicare tax was 
withheld. Employers above a certain size report quarterly to 
the IRS on total wages, wages subject to Social Security and 
Medicare taxes, and Federal income taxes using the Form 941, 
Employer's Quarterly Federal Tax Return. Smaller employers file 
annually using Form 994, Employer's Annual Federal Tax Return.
    For State and local employers, determining proper 
withholding of FICA taxes for employees is especially 
challenging because some or all employees may or may not be 
covered by Social Security. For example, a school district may 
provide a qualifying retirement system only for a particular 
group of employees who meet certain criteria, not just 
teachers, making that group of employees exempt from Social 
Security coverage.
    The IRS has the responsibility for ensuring that all 
employers, both public and private, properly withhold and pay 
Social Security and Medicare taxes for their employees. The IRS 
and the SSA routinely match Social Security and Medicare wages 
on Form 941 with amounts reported on Form W-3, the Transmittal 
of Wage and Tax Statements, and follow up where there are 
discrepancies.
    In addition, the IRS reviews employment tax return 
information to classify returns for potential discrepancies 
that would indicate compliance action should be taken, 
including an audit. The IRS, through our Federal, State, and 
local function, has provided extensive outreach services and 
training to units of State and local governments. As indicated 
above, we conduct audits to evaluate employment tax and 
information reporting compliance at the State and local level.
    The IRS also works with the SSA and State Social Security 
administrators on an ongoing basis on significant issues 
related to Social Security and Medicare coverage of public 
employees. This includes coordinating, when necessary, with the 
SSA or State Administrators when there is an audit of a public 
employer.
    We look forward to continuing collaboration with State and 
local government employers, the SSA, and the State Social 
Security Administrator, to ensure that Social Security earnings 
are accurately reported for public employers.
    This concludes my statement. I would be happy to answer 
your questions.
</option>
    <option>[GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman JOHNSON. Thank you, ma'am.
    Ms. Motza, is that correct pronunciation?
    Ms. MOTZA. It is Motza, but that is close enough.
    Chairman JOHNSON. Thank you. You are recognized. Please, 
proceed.
</option>
    <option>    AND PAST PRESIDENT, NATIONAL CONFERENCE OF STATE SOCIAL 
                    SECURITY ADMINISTRATORS
    Ms. MOTZA. Thank you.
    Chairman Johnson, Chairman Buchanan, Ranking Member Larson, 
Ranking Member Lewis, and members of both subcommittees, thank 
you for inviting the National Conference of State Social 
Security Administrators, or NCSSSA, to testify about the 
States' perspectives on Social Security coverage and payroll 
tax compliance by State and local government.
    To supplement our written testimony, I want to provide 
Members of Congress with a couple of examples of the types of 
issues and concerns the State Social Security administrators 
deal with.
    A small town calls the State Administrator in utter panic. 
The IRS' service center in Cincinnati is about to seize all of 
the town's police and fire vehicles for failure to pay FICA on 
their police officers and firefighters. The service center 
assumes Social Security payments were owed based on its review 
of 941 filings.
    The State Administrator's record show that a town has a 
Section 218 agreement that covers civilian employees under 
Social Security, but excluded police officers and firefighters. 
The State Administrator intervenes and provides the accurate 
coverage and tax obligation information to the IRS, and they 
reverse their erroneous assessment. The town can continue 
protecting and serving the public.
    Another example is that in the early 1950s a State provides 
public pension plan coverage for their employees, but not for 
employees of its cities and towns. State legislature authorizes 
voluntary Social Security coverage for employees of cities and 
towns. The city of last resort enters into a Section 218 
agreement in 1954. In 1961, the State legislature establishes a 
separate public pension plan for employees of cities and towns.
    The next year, the city asked the State Administrator to 
file the necessary paperwork with the Social Security 
Administration to withdraw from the Section 218 agreement so 
they can join the new public pension plan. SSA approves the 
withdrawal from Social Security in 1965. If the city had waited 
to request permission to withdraw until the mid-1980s, the 
State Administrator would not have even contacted SSA and 
instead would have advised the city that withdrawal from Social 
Security was no longer an option.
    These two examples show how the State Administrator is the 
critical bridge or liaison and facilitator between the Federal 
Government, both SSA and IRS, and States, public employers, 
employees, and pension systems. Rather than being a one-way 
street and just sending information from the Federal Government 
down to the State and local governments, the Social Security 
State Administrator is the key conduit of information both 
ways.
    The proper performance of that facilitator role, however, 
has been problematic since 1987, in part because of how the 
Treasury Department and IRS interpreted an IRC Section 6103. 
The State Administrators are no longer aware of noncompliant 
public employers. The lack of communication between the IRS and 
State Administrators results in erroneous Social Security and 
Medicare coverage and benefits, as well as incorrect FICA tax 
assessments by the IRS.
    Since 2012, the IRS has identified approximately 10 major 
risk areas nationwide among State and local governments. The 
IRS cannot, however, tell State Administrators what specific 
issues exist in their individual States. Thus, the State 
Administrator cannot assist the public employers to voluntarily 
comply like they did prior to 1987.
    The valued partnership with SSA also needs to be renewed 
and reinvigorated. Prior to 1987, the States and SSA worked 
closely together to ensure proper coverage and collection of 
contributions. Since 1987, the efficiency and effectiveness of 
that partnership has been erratic and has even at times 
resulted in inconsistent advice from different regional offices 
and the headquarters policy office.
    A further complicating factor is that the Government 
Accounting Standards Board, GASB, disclosure standards and 
other auditing oversight organizational guidance standards do 
not test for Social Security or Medicare. As a result, when 
public employers receive a so-called clean audit, they have no 
idea that a potentially significant noncompliance area isn't 
even being examined. A FICA standard will account for 71 
percent of State and local government employees' earnings 
nationwide that are currently not even reported on financial 
statements.
    In conclusion, the irony of the State Administrator job is 
that when our role is performed properly and completely, it 
gives the impression that either nothing is being done or the 
job is minimal. To me, the job of State Social Security 
administrator is like a duck on a pond, everything looks smooth 
and unlabored on the surface, but underneath you are padding 
like crazy. NCSSSA would appreciate congressional, SSA, 
Treasury Department, and IRS help with the paddling.
    I am happy to answer questions. Thank you.
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
</Hearing>
