<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="29679">
    <intro>    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <Doc-title>LEGISLATIVE HEARING ON: H.R. 105; H.R. 299; H.R. 1328; H.R. 1329; H.R. 1390; H.R. 1564; AND A DRAFT BILL ENTITLED ``QUICKER VETERANS BENEFITS  DELIVERY ACT OF 2017. ' '</Doc-title>
    <option>1390; H.R. 1564; AND A DRAFT BILL ENTITLED ``QUICKER VETERANS BENEFITS 
                        DELIVERY ACT OF 2017.''
=======================================================================
                                HEARING
                               before the
</option>
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON DISABILITY ASSISTANCE AND MEMORIAL AFFAIRS</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                                 of the
</option>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON VETERANS' AFFAIRS</committee_name>
    <option>                     U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                        WEDNESDAY, APRIL 5, 2017
                               __________
                           Serial No. 115-11
                               __________
       Printed for the use of the Committee on Veterans' Affairs
         Available via the World Wide Web: http://www.fdsys.gov
                                   ______
                         U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE 
29-679                         WASHINGTON : 2018 
-----------------------------------------------------------------------
  For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing 
  Office Internet: bookstore.gpo.gov Phone: toll free (866) 512-1800; 
         DC area (202) 512-1800 Fax: (202) 512-2104 Mail: Stop IDCC, 
                          Washington, DC 20402-0001
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <committeeComposition>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON VETERANS' AFFAIRS</comitteeM_name>
    <Chairman>
        <Cname>                   DAVID P. ROE</Cname>
        <Clocation> Chairman</Clocation>
    </Chairman>
    <people>
        <Pname>GUS M. BILIRAKIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Vice-</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TIM WALZ</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ranking </Plocation>
    </people>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>Chairman</Cname>
        <Clocation>Chairman</Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>Member</Cname>
        <Clocation>Member</Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE COFFMAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Colorado</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARK TAKANO</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRAD R. WENSTRUP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JULIA BROWNLEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>AMATA COLEMAN RADEWAGEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> American</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ANN M. KUSTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Hampshire</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Samoa</Pname>
        <Plocation>Samoa</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BETO O'ROURKE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE BOST</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>KATHLEEN RICE</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRUCE POLIQUIN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Maine</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>J. LUIS CORREA</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>NEAL DUNN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>KILILI SABLAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Northern Mariana </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JODEY ARRINGTON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Islands</Pname>
        <Plocation>Islands</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOHN RUTHERFORD</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ELIZABETH ESTY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Connecticut</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CLAY HIGGINS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Louisiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SCOTT PETERS</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JACK BERGMAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Michigan</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM BANKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Indiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JENNIFFER GONZALEZ-COLON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Puerto </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Rico</Pname>
        <Plocation>Rico</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jon Towers</Pname>
        <Plocation> Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Ray Kelley</Pname>
        <Plocation> Democratic Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
</committeeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON DISABILITY ASSISTANCE AND MEMORIAL AFFAIRS</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                     MIKE BOST, Illinois, Chairman
MIKE COFFMAN, Colorado               ELIZABETH ESTY, Connecticut, 
AMATA RADEWAGEN, America Samoa           Ranking Member
JACK BERGMAN, Michigan               JULIA BROWNLEY, California
JIM BANKS, Indiana                   KILILI SABLAN, Northern Mariana 
                                         Islands
Pursuant to clause 2(e)(4) of Rule XI of the Rules of the House, public 
hearing records of the Committee on Veterans' Affairs are also 
published in electronic form. The printed hearing record remains the 
official version. Because electronic submissions are used to prepare 
both printed and electronic versions of the hearing record, the process 
of converting between various electronic formats may introduce 
unintentional errors or omissions. Such occurrences are inherent in the 
current publication process and should diminish as the process is 
further refined.
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <Directory>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <peopleSpeaker>  Wednesday</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>April</peopleinfo>
    <Speakers>OPENING STATEMENTS</Speakers>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <Witness>Honorable Mike Bost</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Chairman Honorable Elizabeth Esty Ranking Member The Honorable Jim Banks US House of Representatives The Honorable Julia Brownley</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Ms Beth Murphy</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Director Compensation Service Veterans Benefits Administration</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mr Zachary Hearn</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Deputy Director Veterans Affairs and Rehabilitation Division The American Legion Prepared Statement</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mr Rick Weidman</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Executive Director of Policy and Government Affairs for the Vietnam Veterans of America</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mr Patrick Murray</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Associate Director National Legislative Service Veterans of Foreign Wars Prepared Statement</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mr LeRoy Acosta</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Assistant National Legislative Director Disabled American Veterans Prepared Statement</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mr John B Wells</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Executive Director MilitaryVeterans Advocacy Inc STATEMENT FOR THE RECORD Paralyzed Veterans of America (PVA) MilitaryVeterans Advocacy</peopleinfo>
    <Doc-title>LEGISLATIVE HEARING ON: H.R. 105; H.R. 299; H.R. 1328; H.R. 1329; H.R. 1390; H.R. 1564; AND A DRAFT BILL ENTITLED ``QUICKER VETERANS BENEFITS  DELIVERY ACT OF 2017. ' '</Doc-title>
    <option>1390; H.R. 1564; AND A DRAFT BILL ENTITLED ``QUICKER VETERANS BENEFITS 
                        DELIVERY ACT OF 2017.''
                              ----------                              
                        Wednesday, April 5, 2017
             U.S. House of Representatives,
                    Committee on Veterans' Affairs,
</option>
</Directory>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>Subcommittee on Disability Assistance</subcomittee_name>
    <Chairman>
        <Cname>                                      and Memorial Affairs</Cname>
        <Clocation>                                      and Memorial Affairs</Clocation>
    </Chairman>
    <people>
        <Pname>Washington</Pname>
        <Plocation> D.C.</Plocation>
    </people>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>The Subcommittee met</Cname>
        <Clocation> in </Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <people>
        <Pname>Room 334</Pname>
        <Plocation> Hon. Mike Bost </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Present: Representatives Bost</Pname>
        <Plocation> </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Banks</Pname>
        <Plocation> and Sablan.</Plocation>
    </people>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <Statement>
    <opening>OPENING STATEMENT OF HONORABLE MIKE BOST, CHAIRMAN</opening>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Bost">Good morning, everyone.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Bost">The hearing will come to order. Before we begin, I would 
like to ask unanimous consent that Chairman Roe be allowed to 
sit at the dais and make a statement and ask questions. He is 
not here right now, but he will arrive soon.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Bost">Hearing no objections, so ordered.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you all for joining us today to discuss legislation 
before the Subcommittee. The seven bills we will talk about 
today address issues that are very important to veterans and 
their families. These bills would include and involve issues, 
things that ensure Veterans Benefits keeps pace with inflation; 
require VA to accept private medical evidence; extend benefits 
to the Blue Water Navy veterans; protect vulnerable veterans 
from fraud; give families more choice to decide where to lay 
their loved ones to rest; and clarify that VA may use mandatory 
funds to pay the cost of traveling to contract disability 
examinations.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Bost">We have a full agenda today, so to ensure that we get 
through it all, I am going to ask everyone to keep themselves 
to five minutes. I heard another Chairman say the other day 
that we will refer to that as the bull-riding rule. So, we will 
let you go and the buzzer rings at the five-minute mark, you 
have eight seconds and then we are going to throw you off.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Bost">So, at any rate, I would like to start today with the two 
bills that I am proud to have introduced, H.R. 1328, The 
American Heroes COLA Act of 2017 and H.R. 1329, The Veterans' 
Compensation Cost-of-Living Adjustment Act of 2017.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Bost">I also want to thank Ranking Member Esty for being an 
original co-sponsor on both of these bills.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Bost">H.R. 1329 would give a cost-of-living adjustment to 
veterans. This increase would be the same as Social Security 
recipients get, and would help veterans keep up with inflation; 
of course, H.R. 1329 has my full support, as it should.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Bost">I have also introduced H.R. 1328 to ensure that veterans 
will receive a COLA every time Social Security recipients get 
one. Veterans have earned these benefits and should have the 
peace of mind of knowing that they will receive a COLA every 
year without having to wait for Congress to act.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Bost">I know many of my colleagues here today have worked hard on 
these proposals and I look forward to having a constructive 
conversation.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>OPENING STATEMENT OF HONORABLE ELIZABETH ESTY, RANKING MEMBER</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="HONORABLE ELIZABETH ESTY">    I also want to thank our witnesses for testifying on these 
important bills. I am going to turn it over to my colleague, 
Ranking Member Esty, for her opening statements.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Esty</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Ms. Esty">Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman, for holding
today's hearing on behalf of our Nation's veterans.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Ms. Esty">Today we are examining seven bills that are of vital 
importance to our veterans and their families. I support them 
all and am proud to have worked with the Chairman to introduce, 
as he has just noted, H.R. 1328 and H.R. 1329, The American 
Heroes COLA Act of 2017 and The Veterans' Compensation COLA 
Adjustment Act. These are bills that ensure that we are keeping 
faith with our veterans and keeping economic pace with the 
reality of what things cost in America today, so I urge my 
colleagues to listen attentively to our witnesses and to 
support these important bills, which will make sure that our 
veterans with service-connected disabilities and surviving 
spouses of veterans, receive dependency and indemnity 
compensation that is appropriate. It is simply the right thing 
to do.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Ms. Esty">We are also considering H.R. 1725, the Quicker Veterans 
Benefits Delivery Act and it is the important part of today's 
agenda. This bill, which is introduced by Full Committee 
Ranking Member Walz, speeds up the benefits delivery process by 
allowing local physicians to conduct disability medical 
examinations for veterans.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Ms. Esty">I am sure everyone on this panel and everyone in this room 
has heard extensively about this issue from the veterans we are 
honored to represent; specifically, the bill provides that when 
a claimant submits private medical evidence that is competent, 
credible, probative, and, otherwise, adequate for rating 
purposes, the secretary will not request a VA medical 
examination.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Ms. Esty">Also on today's agenda is H.R. 105, the Protect Veterans 
from Financial Fraud Act introduced by our colleague on the 
Subcommittee, Julia Brownley. It protects veterans from the 
misuse of their money by a fiduciary by expanding the 
secretary's authority to pay recompense to a beneficiary that 
has been a victim of fraud.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Ms. Esty">H.R. 299, the Blue Water Veterans--Navy Vietnam Veterans 
Act is brought forward by Representative Valadao, who I see has 
already joined us and is on the first panel. This bill enjoys 
broad bipartisan support from this Congress and I will say I am 
strongly supportive. I have many veterans in my district who 
have spoken to me repeatedly about this issue.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Ms. Esty">It expands the compensation and health care benefits to 
veterans who served off the coast of Vietnam during the Vietnam 
War and who have manifested the statutorily defined diseases 
resulted--related to exposure to herbicides used in Vietnam, 
such as Agent Orange.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Ms. Esty">As all of us know, currently, only veterans who have served 
on land are eligible for the presumptive connection to 
herbicide exposure.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Ms. Esty">    As this group avails and moves forward toward the 
Subcommittee markup, I want to thank all the Members for their 
thoughtful legislation and I want to thank all of our witnesses 
for joining us today, as well as for your work with us on these 
bills. I look forward to hearing your testimony. Thank you, and 
I yield back.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Bost">I want to thank the Ranking Member. I look
forward to working with her on these issues as we move forward.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Bost">And I want to let you know that I am honored to be joined 
with--this morning, by several of my colleagues who are going 
to testify about the bills on our agenda that they have 
sponsored. I appreciate all of you taking the time out of your 
morning to be here with us, for sponsoring legislation to help 
the veterans.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Bost">With us this morning, we have Representative Jim Banks from 
Indiana, Representative Jack Bergman from Michigan, and 
Representative David Valadao from Florida. We believe that we 
will have Representative--from California. Sorry. It is all 
right; Bob Dole did that. Representative Julie Brown--Julia 
Brownley will be joining us later, also.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Bost">I also understand that Ranking Member Walz wanted to be 
here today, but had a scheduled conflict. I am asking unanimous 
consent that his written statement on his bill, which was 
noticed for this hearing as a draft bill, H.R. 1725, the 
Quicker Veterans Benefits Delivery Act of 2017, would be 
admitted in the record.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Bost">    Hearing no objection, so ordered.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>OPENING STATEMENT OF HONORABLE JIM BANKS</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="HONORABLE JIM BANKS"> Mr. Banks, first off, you are recognized for five
minutes to discuss your bill.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Banks</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Banks">Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Banks">In addition to ensuring that our veterans receive the 
benefits that they have earned, this Subcommittee is also 
tasked with ensuring that our Nation's heroes are treated with 
reverence after they pass. Currently, the VA only covers the 
cost of transporting a veteran's remains to a national 
cemetery, but does not pay burial transportation costs to a 
state or tribal veterans cemetery.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Banks">H.R. 1390 would correct this problem and allow the VA to 
pay the transportation costs, regardless of whether the veteran 
is buried in a national, state, or tribal veterans cemetery. By 
doing so, this bill would provide more options for families who 
are deciding where to lay their loved one to rest. A family may 
prefer to bury a veteran in a state or tribal veterans cemetery 
because it is closer to home, which would allow the family and 
friends to visit the grave and pay their respects. The bill 
would remove the financial penalty if a family chooses to inter 
their relative in a state or tribal veterans cemetery, instead 
of a national cemetery.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Banks">It is incumbent that our Nation never forget the sacrifices 
that our veterans and their families make each and every day. 
One way we can honor their service is to ease the burden of a 
grieving family deciding where to lay their loved one to rest, 
by offering them more choices.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Banks">    I ask my colleagues to join me in supporting H.R. 1390, and 
I yield back.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you, Mr. Banks.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>OPENING STATEMENT OF HONORABLE JULIA BROWNLEY</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="HONORABLE JULIA BROWNLEY">    I would like to recognize Ms. Brownley for five minutes on 
her bill. Welcome.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Brownley</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Ms. Brownley">Thank you for considering my legislation, the
Protect Veterans from Financial Fraud Act, which will ensure 
that our veterans receive the benefits they have earned and 
deserved.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Ms. Brownley">As many of you may recall, my bill passed the Subcommittee 
in the 114th Congress, but was not brought to the floor for a 
vote. I am hoping that we can get a home run this year and 
appreciate that the Subcommittee is holding a hearing on the 
bill.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Ms. Brownley">As you know, the VA's Fiduciary Program was established to 
protect veterans and other beneficiaries who, due to injury, 
disease, or old age, are no longer able to manage their 
financial affairs. Many veterans who participate in the 
Fiduciary Program depend on their VA benefits, truly, to make 
ends meet. In fact, in 2016, the Fiduciary Program served more 
than 230,000 veterans' survivors and dependents.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Ms. Brownley">My bill would protect veterans and the Fiduciary Program 
from financial fraud by ensuring that every veteran in the 
program can recover their benefits in cases when the appointed 
fiduciary misuses or steals a veteran's benefits.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Ms. Brownley">Under current law, if a VA-appointed fiduciary misuses or 
steals a veteran's benefits, the VA has the power to remove the 
fiduciary and we know this is a serious concern. In 2016, the 
VA conducted nearly 1,500 misuse investigations, of which 764 
fiduciaries were removed based upon a finding of misuse of 
benefits.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Ms. Brownley">However, in many cases, VA can't reissue the benefits to 
the veterans, who, through no fault of their own, may have been 
swindled by a VA-appointed fiduciary. This is because the VA 
can only reissue the lost benefits to the veteran if their 
fiduciary manages VA benefits for at least nine other veterans. 
This arbitrary ten-or-more rule means that veterans cannot be 
made whole, even if the veteran has been taken advantage of by 
unscrupulous individuals, often those closest to them, who were 
entrusted with management of a veteran's finances.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Ms. Brownley">My bill will ensure that all veterans who have VA- 
appointed fiduciaries are treated equally by eliminating the 
ten-or-more rule, and my bill will ensure that all veterans who 
have their benefits stolen, can recoup the lost benefits.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Ms. Brownley">I am pleased to see from the testimony that the VSOs here 
today are supportive of this change and I am glad to hear that 
the VA also believes that Congress needs to fix the statutory 
problem and allow the agency to make all veterans whole.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Ms. Brownley">The VA and our VSOs agree that the existing law is 
arbitrary because it forces VA to treat two beneficiaries 
differently and does not provide the same financial protections 
to all veterans. My bill will correct this in justice. Every 
veteran participating in the VA Fiduciary Program should be 
fully protected from fraud and abuse.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Ms. Brownley">    I urge my colleagues to support this simple common sense 
fix and am happy to answer any questions.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you, Ms. Brownley.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>OPENING STATEMENT OF HONORABLE JACK BERGMAN</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="HONORABLE JACK BERGMAN">    Representative Bergman, you are recognized for five 
minutes.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bergman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Bergman">Thank you, Mr. Chairman.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Bergman">My bill is very simple. It will clarify that the VA has the 
authority to use mandatory funds to pay for the cost of 
veterans travel to contract disability examinations.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Bergman">As you know, a veteran who files a claim for disability 
benefits may be required to undergo a VA medical examination; 
however, VA does not have enough examiners to schedule these 
evaluations in a timely manner. It can be especially 
challenging for VA to arrange for disability exams if the 
veteran needs to see a specialist, such as a cardiologist. 
Furthermore, veterans who live in rural areas often have to 
travel long distances to get to VA facilities to see an 
examiner.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Bergman">To address this issue, Congress gave the Department the 
authority to contract with non-VA physicians to perform 
disability examinations. This policy also allows VA physicians 
to devote more time to care for our wounded heroes, rather than 
spending time conducting disability exams.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Bergman">Additionally, using contract examiners has the added 
benefit of helping VA to schedule disability evaluations closer 
to the veteran's home. For more than 20 years, VA has been 
paying for beneficiary travel, regardless of whether veterans 
who needed disability evaluations used VA facilities or 
contractor facilities.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Bergman">This bill would simply codify VA's longstanding practice of 
using mandatory funds to pay beneficiary travel for contract 
exams. H.R. 1564 does not add to the deficit, because this 
money is already included in the baseline.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Bergman">This legislation will help veterans receive the benefits to 
which they are entitled by allowing VA to pay beneficiary 
travel to contract disability examinations.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Bergman">    I ask my colleagues to join me in supporting H.R. 1564 and 
I yield back.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you, Mr. Bergman.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Bost">Our colleague, Mr. Valadao, from California is at the 
witness table. First off, thank you for being here and to 
discuss H.R. 299, the Blue Water Navy Vietnam Veterans Act of 
2017.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>OPENING STATEMENT OF HONORABLE DAVID G. VALADAO</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="HONORABLE DAVID G. VALADAO">    Mr. Valadao, you are recognized for five minutes.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Valadao</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Valadao">Thank you, Chairman.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Valadao">Chairman Bost, Ranking Member Esty, Members of the 
Subcommittee, thank you for allowing me here today to offer 
testimony on my legislation, H.R. 299, the Blue Water Navy 
Vietnam Veterans Act.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Valadao">Since coming to Congress, I have been a proud supporter of 
our Nation's veterans and I am excited to sponsor this critical 
legislation today. The Members of this distinguished 
Subcommittee have a comprehensive understanding of the harmful 
effects of the herbicide Agent Orange and the lasting impact it 
has had on U.S. servicemembers who sacrificed so much for our 
country during the Vietnam War.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Valadao">Our government must now ensure that those who were exposed 
to Agent Orange during wartime are provided for when they 
return home. In the aftermath of the Vietnam War, the United 
States Government linked the chemical dioxin in Agent Orange to 
many harmful and serious medical conditions, affecting those 
who served in or around Vietnam.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Valadao">While the Federal government has provided for those who 
served on Vietnam's soil during the war, those who served in 
territorial seas of the Republic of Vietnam lack the 
compensation and treatment they deserve.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Valadao">In 2002, the Department of Veterans Affairs reinterpreted 
the language of Agent Orange Act of 1991 to apply only to 
veterans who actually set foot in the Republic of Vietnam or 
who served in the inland, round waterways. As a result, the 
veterans who served off the coast in blue water must now 
provide service-connection and exposure to Agent Orange, which 
can often prove a long and burdensome process.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Valadao">The VA continues to deny claims for blue water Navy 
veterans, despite studies that show higher rates of cancer and 
non-Hodgkin's lymphoma among shipboard veterans. While it may 
be difficult to definitely prove that blue water Navy veterans 
were exposed to Agent Orange, their higher rates of diseases 
associated with exposure to the herbicide are cause for alarm. 
This, combined with studies to show a plausible pathway for the 
herbicide to have entered the South China Sea are evidence 
enough that these brave servicemembers were exposed to the 
herbicide.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Valadao">Even more alarming, studies also show the distillation 
process to convert saltwater to drinking water enriched the 
chemical dioxin in Agent Orange's potency and contaminated the 
shipboard water system.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Valadao">My legislation, H.R. 299, the Blue Water Navy Vietnam 
Veterans Act, would restore the presumptive--the presumption of 
service-connection for blue water Navy veterans that existed 
prior to 2002 VA decision. Lifting the burden of proving 
service-connection from the individual veteran is vitally 
important, as it places blue water Navy veterans on the same 
playing field as those who served on land.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Valadao">These brave men and women of our Nation's Armed Forces have 
sacrificed their health and often times, their lives, in 
service to our great country. Providing for them when they 
return home is the least we can do to show our unwavering 
commitment to our veterans and appreciation for their service.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Valadao">Along with myself and my colleague, Ranking Member Tim 
Walz, this legislation has the support of over 250 Members of 
Congress and counting, including 16 Members of the Veterans' 
Affairs Committee. It is important for Congress to ensure our 
blue water Navy Vietnam veterans receive the support and care 
they need.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Valadao">    I thank the Subcommittee on Disability Assistance and 
Memorial Affairs, and the Veterans' Affairs Committee as a 
whole, for their consideration of this critical legislation, 
and I hope that we can work together to provide for our 
Nation's heroes. Thank you.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you, Mr. Valadao.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Bost">And we will forego any rounds of questions for Mr. Valadao 
and any questions that anyone may have for our colleague, may 
submit them to the record.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Bost">I now want to invite the second panel to the table. We are 
joined today by Ms. Beth Murphy, the director of compensation 
services at the Veterans Benefits Administration; she's 
accompanied by Ms. Patricia Watts, the director of legislative 
and regulatory services for the National Cemetery 
Administration and Mr. Ralph Erickson, the chief consultant for 
post-deployment health services at VHA.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF BETH MURPHY</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="BETH MURPHY">    Thank you for being here, and Ms. Murphy, you are 
recognized for five minutes.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Ms. Murphy">Good morning Chairman Bost, Ranking Member Esty
and Members of the Committee. We appreciate the opportunity to 
be here this morning to present views on several bills that 
would affect VA programs and services.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Ms. Murphy">The first bill I will address is H.R. 105, Protect Veterans 
from Financial Fraud Act of 2007. This bill would remove 
restrictions on VA's authority to reissue benefits in cases of 
fiduciary misuse. Also, it would codify current policy that 
mental competence determinations are appealable to a Board of 
Veterans' Appeals and U.S. Court of Appeals for Veterans 
Claims.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Ms. Murphy">VA supports this bill to ensure equal treatment of all 
fiduciary misuse victims and allow VA to promptly reissue 
benefits, thereby minimizing financial hardship to 
beneficiaries.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Ms. Murphy">H.R. 299 Blue Water Navy Vietnam Veterans Act of 2017 would 
extend the presumption of Agent Orange exposure to all veterans 
who served on ships in the territorial seas of the Republic of 
Vietnam.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Ms. Murphy">VA has concerns with H.R. 299 and cannot support the bill 
at this time. The bill does not clearly define the terms 
``territorial seas.'' VA is also concerned with the September 
25th, 1985, effective date of the bill, which would potentially 
result in many cases with retroactive awards of more than 30 
years.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Ms. Murphy">Re-adjudicating old claims and establishing large 
retroactive awards would be complex and labor-intensive and 
divert resources from other disability claims.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Ms. Murphy">Lastly, there is continued scientific uncertainty 
surrounding this issue. At VA's request, Institute of Medicine 
reviewed all scientific evidence and could not state with 
certainty that blue water Navy personnel were or were not 
exposed to Agent Orange. VA continues to review and monitor 
available scientific evidence on this issue.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Ms. Murphy">H.R. 1328, American Heroes COLA Act of 2017 would 
permanently authorize VA to implement cost-of-living increases 
to rates of disability compensation and dependency and 
indemnity compensation or DIC. VA supports this bill and this 
is consistent with the longstanding practice of Congress to 
enact regular cost-of-living increases and would eliminate the 
need for additional legislation to implement such future annual 
increases.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Ms. Murphy">H.R. 1329, Veterans Compensation Cost-of-Living Adjustment 
Act 2017 would require VA to increase rates of disability 
commencing in DIC by the same percentage as any increase to 
Social Security benefits, effective December 1st, 2017. VA 
strongly supports this bill to ensure the value of benefits 
keeps pace with the increase in consumer prices.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Ms. Murphy">H.R. 1390, Transportation of Deceased Veterans to Veterans 
Cemeteries, would increase burial location options, for which 
VA may make transportation costs for eligible veterans remains.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Ms. Murphy">VA supports H.R. 1390, because in addition to national 
cemeteries, VA would also pay transportation to veterans 
cemeteries owned by state or tribal organizations.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Ms. Murphy">Next, H.R. 1564, VA Beneficiary Travel Act of 2017, would 
direct the use of funding from the mandatory compensation and 
pension appropriations to pay for travel and incidental 
expenses associated with contract disability examinations.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Ms. Murphy">VA strongly supports the bill that would codify, clearly 
authorizing VA to fund a nationwide contract exam pilot program 
from a single source.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Ms. Murphy">Finally, H.R. 1725, Quicker Veterans Benefits Delivery Act 
of 2017 would prohibit VA from requesting a C &amp;amp; P examination 
when a claimant submits medical evidence adequate for rating 
purposes and would require VA to report on the progress of VA's 
Acceptable Clinical Evidence or ACE initiative, and submit data 
for each VA Regional Office, unused by claimants of private 
medical evidence in support of C &amp;amp; P claims.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Ms. Murphy">The VA does not support this bill, but appreciates the 
intent to more expeditiously provide benefits to veterans; 
however, VA currently has a policy of adjudicating claims 
without a C &amp;amp; P exam if a claimant submits evidence adequate 
for rating purposes, even from private providers. This practice 
is grounded in existing statute and VA regulation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Ms. Murphy">VA is especially concerned with the reporting requirements 
of the bill. VA tracks the number of ACE exams, but does not 
track when evidence is supplemented with a telephone interview 
or when private medical evidence is or isn't sufficient for 
rating purposes, as this is not a formal determination.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Ms. Murphy">If a C &amp;amp; P exam is requested after receiving and reviewing 
private medical evidence, VA has determined in its claims 
adjudication process that the evidence is insufficient for 
rating purposes.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>[The prepared statement of Beth Murphy appears in the</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="Beth Murphy appears in th">    This concludes my remarks. I would be happy to answer any 
questions you may have. Thank you.
Appendix]
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you, Ms. Murphy, and thank you for
testifying before us today.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Bost">    I am going to go ahead and go to questions and I will have 
the first five minutes. Ms. Murphy, can you elaborate, please, 
on the importance that Congress pass House Resolution 1329; 
that is the Veterans Compensation Cost-of-Living Adjustment, 
and why you think that may be necessary and you are in support 
of it.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Ms. Murphy">Mr. Chairman, thank you. This--this is--makes
good business sense. It is great for veterans. It makes sure 
that we keep pace with the economy and make sure that their 
benefits maintain viability with consumer pricing.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Ms. Murphy">    Also, I would tell you behind the scenes, there is some 
work that has to be done to make those adjustments in our 
systems every year and when we're waiting up to the minute 
sometimes for that thumbs-up, it gets a little challenging. So 
this would just make sure that that cost-of-living adjustment 
was in place and ensure veterans with confidence that we want 
to make sure that their benefits remain viable.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Well, the next question is similar, but going to
the next bill, what do you think of when House Resolution--H.R. 
1328--forgive me for the House Resolution--that is my Illinois 
side that keeps coming back on that, instead H.R. 1328--would 
provide veterans some peace of mind and to having that COLA so 
that they know that it is going to occur. What is your 
reaction, and then the reaction that you think we would get 
from veterans.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Ms. Murphy"> I think it is a win-win. We would certainly
support it. It is something that we anticipate every year and 
plan for that, but just making--knowing that it will be in 
place and that that it is not something we have to wonder and 
guess about, provides confidence for us, provides confidence 
for veterans and it honors their service, to make sure that 
they understand that their benefits are important to them and 
they are important to us, as well, and we want to make sure 
that they keep pace with economic pricing.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Bost">My next question is for Dr. Erickson. Dr.
Erickson, in the past, VA has stated that one of the reasons it 
has been so hard to determine whether an Agent Orange 
presumption should apply to blue water Navy veterans is lack of 
measures taken at the time of potential exposure.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Bost">    What efforts has the Department put in place now, to maybe 
adjust that?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Erickson</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Erickson">Thank you, Mr. Chairman.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Erickson">Just by way of introduction, I am a veteran as well; I 
served for 32 years of active duty as an Army doctor. My last 
assignment was as the commander of the Walter Reed Army 
Institute of Research. I have been with VA for now, three 
years.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Erickson">We recognize that short of inventing a time machine to go 
back and get those measurements that we don't have in this 
case, we are being prospective, and so we are actually 
partnering with the Department of Defense to create something 
called the Individual Longitudinal Exposure Record, the 
Individual Longitudinal Exposure Record, or the ILER, for 
short. This is a fairly large task that we are undertaking that 
will allow the Department of Defense to actually collect 
realtime exposure measurements on servicemembers during their 
time of service.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Erickson">    And this would be information that would be available, 
then, to health care providers while that servicemember is 
still on duty and afterwards, to providers who are within the 
VA system. We think this will take us a long way forward and 
will correct a major gap right now that we have to deal with. 
Mr. *Bost.* So, what you just said is you do have the research 
available to go back and actually identify those blue water 
Navy veterans and truly see. And the studies have been done?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Erickson</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Erickson"> No, sir. We do not have the ability--the DoD
does not have the exposure information. VA does not have the 
exposure information for blue water Navy, but from today into 
the future, for future servicemembers, we are actually trying 
to correct this; realizing that, you know, we didn't do this on 
a corporate level within DoD or VA for past cohorts of 
servicemembers, but from here on out, we are working with the 
Department of Defense to make sure that happens.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Okay. Ms. Murphy, one more question for you. Can
you please expand on why the VA extended the presumption of 
exposure of the Agent Orange to brown water Navy veterans, but 
not blue water Navy veterans.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Ms. Murphy"> So, I will ask Dr. Erickson to supplement any
science on this--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. Bost">Okay.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Mr. Bost">Ms. Murphy [continued]. --but, essentially, those that had 
boots on the ground in Vietnam and those in inland waterways 
share commonality in the types of exposure, extent of exposure 
that they would have been experiencing, which is 
differentiation from the amount of types of exposure that they 
would have had out in the blue water.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. Bost">    Dr. Erickson, can you supplement with the science behind 
that?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Erickson</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. Erickson"> Certainly. I think it was based upon the fact
that we knew that spraying had occurred along the coasts, in 
fact, included spraying by riveting vessels that would be going 
in and out of the rivers and the openings for those rivers. And 
so there was a fairly strong basis that, in fact, the Agent 
Orange had been sprayed at those locations.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="21" speaker="Mr. Bost"> My time has expired. I would like to turn the
questioning now over to the Ranking Member, Ms. Esty.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Esty</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="22" speaker="Ms. Esty">Thank you, Mr. Chairman.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="23" speaker="Ms. Esty">    If I could follow up, Dr. Erickson or Ms. Murphy, would it 
be helpful for us to be more specific on territorial seas? 
Certainly, there was some discussion, and I am hearing from 
veterans who I represent, and the mechanisms, maybe, Dr. 
Erickson, for you about the concentration, the desalination, 
and do we really know how much exposure there was? Because that 
is what I am hearing. I have to tell you, frankly, that is what 
I am hearing a lot about and I am not sure that there has been 
sufficient attention paid to what that exposure might have 
been.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="24" speaker="Ms. Murphy"> So, Congresswoman, yes, there is some
uncertainty in what the definition of ``territorial seas'' is; 
it is one of several factors that I mentioned that causes 
concern with the bill.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Esty</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="25" speaker="Ms. Esty">Would more specificity help? Because we are
facing situations in which we have veterans now, and as you 
point out, 30 years on, well, it is hard to prove 
retroactively, but let's be very clear; we sent them into 
harm's way and they are now experiencing exactly the same 
symptoms and problems that their colleagues, men and women in 
arms, were facing on land.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="26" speaker="Ms. Esty">    And you can understand our frustration and theirs in 
saying, like, we don't know enough yet; it is 30 years. You can 
understand, there might be a little bit of cynicism about, 
maybe, we will decide at a point when it is no longer possible 
to help anybody.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="27" speaker="Ms. Murphy">I can absolutely understand the frustration. I
have committed my whole career to serving veterans and finding 
ways to pay benefits and to do that, we have relied on the fact 
that there needs to be a rational basis for additional benefits 
and litigation that we--or regulations that we add in to pay 
benefits. And we have been searching for that and with blue 
water Navy veterans and broader-types of veterans to find 
benefits when there is no rational basis or no science behind 
it that we can put our finger on.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="28" speaker="Ms. Murphy">    So, it is something that we continue to look at. We have 
not had full opportunity to discuss this with the secretary. He 
is new and he is a physician and understands these issues and 
has a different perspective possibly, so this will continue--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Esty</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="29" speaker="Ms. Esty"> Okay. Great. I have some other questions.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="30" speaker="Ms. Murphy"> Yes.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Esty</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="31" speaker="Ms. Esty"> So, Dr. Erickson, can you speak to a little bit
to the desalination issue.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Erickson</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="32" speaker="Mr. Erickson">Certainly. Ranking Member Esty, you have
asked, perhaps, the central question, and we mentioned in our 
written testimony that there is uncertainty and there is 
tremendous uncertainty.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="33" speaker="Mr. Erickson">We very much respect our Australian partners who have gone 
to war with us so many times. We respect the scientist who, in 
fact, did a key study, which a number of us have read and have 
discussed, in which a laboratory setting involved adding 
different amounts of various contaminants to include dioxins to 
a mixture of water. They would then see if, in fact, during the 
distillation process, if, in fact, it was removed or if it 
would be co-distilled; it would stay with the water. Not only 
was it co-distilled, in fact, it was concentrated.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="34" speaker="Mr. Erickson">That in itself, provides the conceptual framework for how, 
in fact, onboard the Australian ships, there could be Agent 
Orange, and the contaminate of dioxin. And was mentioned by the 
authors in the article, they had regularly brought in estuarine 
water, that is water near the shore, so as to have less of a 
salt content to deal with. And for them, it made sense that 
that laboratory simulation would represent what occurred aboard 
the Australian vessels.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="35" speaker="Mr. Erickson">    As it would relate to the U.S. Navy, I understand from our 
DoD partners that as a practice, by their standard operating 
procedures, they would have drawn in water for their 
distillation from 12 miles out. And so it makes it a little bit 
harder for this conceptual framework to apply to the U.S. Navy, 
but as I mentioned at the beginning--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Esty</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="36" speaker="Ms. Esty"> The NVA processing, if you knew for a fact that
there were going to be COLA adjustments every year, would that 
allow us to get more benefits in the hands of--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="37" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Thank you. And Mr. Bergman, you are recognized
for five minutes.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bergman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="38" speaker="Mr. Bergman">Thank you, Mr. Chairman.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="39" speaker="Mr. Bergman">Listening to your questions and the responses, we would all 
likely agree that life is complex and as we try to combine 
science with what we know to be historical facts or times and 
place, it is a challenge. And so I thank everyone for their 
engagement in combining all the different factors to come up 
with a different solution.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="40" speaker="Mr. Bergman">    Dr. Erickson, is the VA working with DoD to conduct a 
comprehensive review to determine exactly which ships operated 
in inland waterways of Vietnam?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Erickson</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="41" speaker="Mr. Erickson">Congressman, General, I very much appreciate
this question, and Ms. Murphy could answer this as well. We 
have a ships list which, in fact, has been collected over, I 
believe, several decades now. Now, the ships list has over 300 
ships listed. This has been an ongoing partnership with the 
Department of Defense, with the Department of the Navy to look 
at their records to where their ships transited; when did they 
come into port, when did they anchor, where were they. And the 
goal, there, being to actually lower the threshold for 
veterans.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="42" speaker="Mr. Erickson">If, in fact, Navy veterans would be able to demonstrate 
that they were on a given ship that came into shore, that in 
itself would bolster their claims.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="43" speaker="Mr. Erickson">    And please forgive me if I am stepping on your BBA side, 
here.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="44" speaker="Ms. Murphy">Not at all.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="45" speaker="Ms. Murphy">I would say that everybody is passionate about this and 
this is the business that we should be in; is hearing from 
advocates, doing research, talking to the experts, talking to 
our DoD partners, talking to our congressional partners, and 
really getting as much evidence information and evidence on 
this topic and other similar topics that are of interest and 
passionate to veterans, because we want to find ways to pay 
them benefits, but historically, we have to say no to some 
folks when there is not a rational basis or the evidence is not 
there.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="46" speaker="Ms. Murphy">    So, we continue to look. We want it to continue to be an 
issue for discussion so that we can get as much information and 
evidence on this as possible.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bergman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="47" speaker="Mr. Bergman"> Okay. But, in placing ships at a certain place
at a certain time, is that--you can--is there a chart that 
shows which ships were in those inland waterways--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="48" speaker="Ms. Murphy"> Yes, we maintain a ships list--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bergman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="49" speaker="Mr. Bergman"> So, you have an exact list, so then we know,
exactly, given our rosters, who was aboard those ships and at 
what time. So, as the veterans come in and have a certain set 
of conditions, you can immediately go out to a list and say you 
were aboard the USS Okinawa LPH3 during the 19--so, therefore, 
if we all of a sudden have a certain number of people at a 
certain point in time who have a certain set of symptoms or 
conditions, it should make--you know, it is not an exhaustive 
list; it is a finite list, right?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="50" speaker="Ms. Murphy">Congressman, yes, we have a ships list. There
are several hundred ships, different categories of ships. We 
have gathered evidence and research in supporting putting those 
ships on the list.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="51" speaker="Ms. Murphy">And we review it quarterly. We get information from DoD and 
recently I think we added 10 or 15 ships to that list.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="52" speaker="Ms. Murphy">    So--and by certain date ranges is applicable and if a 
veteran comes in and we can identify--you know, we can connect 
the dots and say, this ship is on the list, we can place that 
veteran on that ship during that timeframe that is applicable, 
then we extend that presumption to them, yes.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bergman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="53" speaker="Mr. Bergman">Okay. And I am glad that you used the term
``connect the dots'' because that is a lot of what we do in so 
many different ways here is to connect the dots. And if we do 
it with data, which it seems like we have, then we are going to 
get the best results.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="54" speaker="Mr. Bergman">    Mr. Chairman, I yield back.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="55" speaker="Ms. Murphy"> Thank you.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="56" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you, ma'am.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="57" speaker="Mr. Bost">    Let me put on the microphone. Mr. Sablan, you are 
recognized for five minutes.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Sablan</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="58" speaker="Mr. Sablan">Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman, and Ranking
Member Esty for holding today's hearing and good morning, 
everyone.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="59" speaker="Mr. Sablan">I just have a few questions and maybe this one would go to 
Ms. Watts first, if you don't mind. Ms. Watts, under H.R. 1390, 
regarding the transportation of certain deceased veterans--and 
I really don't know the answer, which is why--would 1390 
include the territories under definition of states, because it 
says states or tribal cemeteries.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="60" speaker="Mr. Sablan">    In my jurisdiction, we have one VA cemetery, but it is--it 
belongs to the commonwealth of the territory that I am from.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Watts</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="61" speaker="Ms. Watts">Thank you, Congressman.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="62" speaker="Ms. Watts">    I believe that there are territories that do have state--
what we consider state veteran cemeteries.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Sablan</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="63" speaker="Mr. Sablan"> So, under state, territories are included.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Watts</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="64" speaker="Ms. Watts"> They fall in the definition of the state.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Sablan</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="65" speaker="Mr. Sablan"> And Northern Mariana would be included under
H.R. 1390?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Watts</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="66" speaker="Ms. Watts">Potentially, yes. And we would--there are
certain state veterans--state and tribal cemeteries that we 
provide grants--the VA provides grants to allow them to 
maintain those cemeteries.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="67" speaker="Ms. Watts">    Now, that doesn't mean--I'm sorry.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Sablan</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="68" speaker="Mr. Sablan"> Not for the Northern Mariana. Yeah, you don't
even provide--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Watts</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="69" speaker="Ms. Watts">Not every state or territory has such a granted
cemetery; that is correct.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="70" speaker="Ms. Watts">    Mr. Sablan [continued]. So, would it be asking too much to 
maybe sit down with us and consider including the territories 
or in particular, if all the territories, except the Northern 
Mariana are included, would it be--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Watts</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="71" speaker="Ms. Watts"> We would be more than happy to have any
discussion that you would like to have.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Sablan</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="72" speaker="Mr. Sablan">Well, thank you. I appreciate that.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="73" speaker="Mr. Sablan">Ms. Murphy or Dr. Erickson, would you please--would H.R. 
1564, the VA Beneficiary Travel Act, would the transportation 
costs be authorized if the veteran were required to travel by 
sea or by air? I mean you can't drive around in, for example, 
for disability exams.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="74" speaker="Mr. Sablan">    You know, if a patient from--I come from a place where 
there are 14 islands; three are inhabited primarily, so there 
is always a requirement for two of those islands, at least, to 
travel either by sea or by air to come and see a doctor.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="75" speaker="Ms. Murphy">So, Congressman, as far as the beneficiary
travel, we have been working with contract vendors to establish 
locations around the country and around the world for 
examinations. The contract--where the contract vendors are 
located, we are paying for beneficiary travel to go to those 
contract vendors, but if that is not a location that is 
accessible to a veteran or it is not some place that we would 
send them, then we would be relying on VHA to provide that 
examination and then we would have to turn to VHA to look to 
its beneficiary travel rules for that.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="76" speaker="Ms. Murphy">    I will say, also, that we do have our disability benefit 
questionnaires that we do accept from private providers. So, if 
someone were to take a DBQ to their private local provider and 
it were to be filled out by a licensed clinician, we would 
certainly accept that, as well.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Sablan</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="77" speaker="Mr. Sablan"> All right. I am actually putting together a
story, sort of--cases, different situations that I would like 
to work with the Veterans Administration to get some answers if 
possible. But thank you for that answer.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="78" speaker="Ms. Murphy"> We would be happy to work with you and talk
with you more about that.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Sablan</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="79" speaker="Mr. Sablan">I appreciate that thank you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="80" speaker="Mr. Sablan">I have just one more question, again, Ms. Murphy or Dr. 
Erickson. In a jurisdiction--and this is on H.R. 1725--in a 
jurisdiction where there are no VA health centers or VA 
clinics, wouldn't it be reasonable to allow medical or private 
practitioners' opinions to be sufficient for rating purposes 
and not require veteran to travel by sea or by air for an 
examination to see a VA doctor; otherwise, you have to send him 
to Honolulu and, of course, sometimes they have to--there are 
many instances that I am aware of, where they put up their own 
money to go a center, for example, or try and see a doctor in 
Guam, if they can.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="81" speaker="Mr. Sablan">    And I don't have the time, but--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Murphy</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="82" speaker="Ms. Murphy"> Congressman, that is absolutely an opportunity
they have. We accept private medical evidence and if it is 
sufficiently comprehensive and answers all the questions that 
we need for rating purposes, we use that.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Sablan</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="83" speaker="Mr. Sablan">I understand. Okay. Thank you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="84" speaker="Mr. Sablan">    Thank you, Mr. Chairman, I yield back.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="85" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="86" speaker="Mr. Bost">There is no one else on the dais seeking to ask questions. 
We want to thank this panel for being here today, Ms. Murphy 
and everybody involved. Thank you so much.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="87" speaker="Mr. Bost">And we want to invite up the third panel.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="88" speaker="Mr. Bost">I want to thank you as a panel for being with us. Mr. 
Zachary Hearn is with us, the Department of--I'm sorry--the 
Deputy Director for Claims of Veterans Affairs and 
Rehabilitation Division of The American Legion; Mr. Rick 
Weidman, the Executive Director of Policy and Government 
Affairs for the Vietnam Veterans of America; Mr. Patrick 
Murray, the Associate Director of National Legislative Services 
for Veterans of Foreign Wars; and Mr. Leroy Acosta, the 
Assistant National Legislative Director of the Disabled 
American Veterans; and also, Mr. John B. Wells, the Executive 
Director of Military Veterans Advocacy, Inc.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="89" speaker="Mr. Bost">First off, I want to thank you all for being here and for 
working--for the work you and your organizations do every day 
to improve the lives of our veterans. We want to thank you for 
that.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF ZACHARY HEARN</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="ZACHARY HEARN">    Mr. Hearn, we will begin with you and you are recognized 
for five minutes.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Hearn</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Hearn">Good morning. The simple fact is, serving in our
Nation's Armed Forces is inherently dangerous. Medical 
conditions may manifest due to service and we, as a society, 
have an obligation to compensate for medical conditions related 
to service.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Hearn">Many of these veterans depend upon these benefits and for 
this reason, it is imperative that we ensure these deserving 
veterans and their family members receive the highest level of 
consideration.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Hearn">Good morning, Chairman Bost, Ranking Member Esty, and 
Members of the Subcommittee. On behalf of National Commander 
Charles E. Schmidt, and the Nation's largest veteran's service 
organization, we welcome the opportunity to testify regarding 
pending legislation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Hearn">The American Legion supports the passage of H.R. 105, 
designed to protect veterans from the unscrupulous acts of 
fiduciaries. Veterans requiring fiduciaries are some of the 
most vulnerable veterans. Half of these veterans are over 80 
years old. All of them are unable to manage their financial 
affairs.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Hearn">Veterans who have been impacted by poor-acting fiduciaries 
do not have the ability to recoup their lost funds from VA 
unless the fiduciary represents 10 or greater beneficiaries. 
This bill would now permit VA to provide the lost funds to the 
veteran, regardless of the amount of beneficiaries represent by 
a fiduciary.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Hearn">H.R. 299 corrects a wrong that has played the blue water 
Navy veteran community and affords the veterans the benefits--
the benefit of doubt to herbicide exposure.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Hearn">Over 800,000 blue water Navy personnel served in Vietnam's 
territorial waters between 1962 and 1975. VA has repeatedly 
stated that there is no conclusive evidence that supports 
presumptive herbicide exposure.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Hearn">The Institute of Medicine's Committee on Veterans and Agent 
Orange stated that there were no environmental studies 
conducted during the Vietnam War, and due to that fact, it 
cannot determine the occurrence of herbicide exposure.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Hearn">In short, VA cannot prove blue water Navy veterans were 
exposed to Agent Orange and it appears they never will. Blue 
water Navy veterans, for years, have pointed to the 2002 
Australian study that found that distilling of sea water not 
only failed to eliminate the toxic chemicals, but it enhanced 
it is impact. For a blue water Navy veteran to gain service-
connection due to herbicide exposure, proof has to be provided 
that exposure occurred.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Hearn">VA is essentially directing veterans to provide proof of 
exposure to a chemical that few knew of its impact half a 
century after the incident. As you can imagine, this is a near-
impossible task. The American Legion has long believed that 
these veterans of the blue water Navy deserve to be treated as 
presumptively exposed and supports this bill.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Hearn">H.R. 1328 provides an automatic annual cost-of-living 
adjustment for veteran's disability benefits. While this bill 
would prove efficient in the administration of COLA, it would 
also come as a significant cost to the veteran, as it uses the 
chain CPI as its foundation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Hearn">The current CCPI COLA formula suggests a 30-year-old 
veteran with no children and one hundred percent disabled, 
would likely lose about $100,000 in disability compensation by 
the time that the veteran reaches 75 years of age. This is the 
equivalent of years of benefits lost, due to this bill.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Hearn">The American Legion opposes this bill and any legislative 
efforts to automatically index COLA to the COLA-authorized for 
Social Security recipients, nonservice-connected disability 
recipients, and death benefits.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Hearn">H.R. 1329 increases the rate of compensation as of December 
1, 2017, for veterans with service-connected disabilities and 
surviving spouse benefits. When inflation impacts the cost-of-
living, it is natural to adjust benefits according to the 
increases. The American Legion supports this bill.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Hearn">H.R. 1390 authorizes VA to pay costs associated with 
transporting deceased veterans to state- or tribal-owned 
veterans cemeteries. VA currently pays transportation costs 
only for national cemeteries. This bill will expand options for 
veterans' families and The American Legion supports this bill.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. Hearn">H.R. 1564 specifies the funding source for travel related 
to examinations by medical professionals, not employed by VA 
for compensation and pension examinations. This bill properly 
designates where VA draws funds for veterans to receive 
payments for travel to C &amp;amp; P exams and does not impose 
additional funding requirements. We support this bill.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Mr. Hearn">H.R. 1725 improves the treatment of medical evidence 
provided by non-VA medical professionals supporting disability 
compensation claims. It is unfortunate that a bill has to be 
passed to force VA to do what it already has the authority to 
do.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. Hearn">The American Legion regularly reviews VA adjudications and 
frequently, VA schedules exams, despite having the necessary 
evidence available to decide a claim. This second exam comes at 
a cost to VA and delays an adjudication.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. Hearn">Additionally, this process is often frustrated by raters' 
near-whole dependence upon its evaluation builder tool, it 
doesn't allow for the weighing of evidence. This bill allows 
for a streamlining of adjudications through rating based upon 
Acceptable Clinical Evidence and The American Legion supports 
the bill.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>[The prepared statement of Zachary Hearn appears in the</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="Zachary Hearn appears in th">    Again, on behalf of National Commander Charles E. Schmidt 
and the 2.2 million members of The American Legion, we 
appreciate the opportunity to speak this morning on today's 
bills. I will be happy to respond to any questions provided by 
the Committee. Thank you.
Appendix]
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you, Mr. Hearn.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF RICK WEIDMAN</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="RICK WEIDMAN">    Mr. Weidman, you are recognized for five minutes.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Weidman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Weidman">Thank you, Chairman Bost. I look forward to
getting to know you particularly in this new role.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Weidman">And Ranking Member Esty, I hear such great things about you 
from Linda Schwartz and our folks in Connecticut. They think 
you can walk the entire length of the reflecting pool in front 
of the Lincoln Memorial without getting wet, so I look forward 
to getting to know you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Weidman">I will comment just on two bills today. And we favor most 
of, actually, all of the bills that are on the docket for 
various reasons. First, I will touch on the Protect Veterans 
from Financial Fraud Act.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Weidman">The fiduciaries at VA have been a scandal for as long as I 
can remember and VA already has the statutory authority to 
investigate and to bring charges against those that are 
stealing from veterans that are not able to defend themselves, 
but they have not done it. And while we favor this particular 
act, what is really necessary is oversight hearings that demand 
that they follow the statute and the regulations pursuant to 
the statute to safeguard those individuals, most vulnerable of 
our veterans.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Weidman">So, I just want to say that as a start, and that you are 
going to accomplish, I believe, much more in passing the 
legislation--we have no problem with that--but I encourage you, 
Mr. Chairman and Madam Ranking Member that you pursue some 
oversight hearings on this.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Weidman">The Blue Water Navy Vietnam Veterans Act, Institute of 
Medicine, in every review they have done since--without 
evidence, the VA said no more blue water Navy. And to show you 
how absurd their definition is, they draw an imaginary line 
across Denang Harbor and if, in fact, you are here in the 
water, you are not exposed, and if you are here in the water, 
two feet away, you are exposed. It is preposterous; it is not 
scientific evidence. It is simply wanting to say no.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Weidman">Vietnam veterans generally believe that the policy of the 
VA, when it comes to any kind of toxic exposure, but 
particularly Agent Orange, is delay, deny, and wait for us to 
die. And, frankly, there is very little to controvert that.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Weidman">Almost everything in the environmental hazards and public 
health section of VA, may be really nice people who are good to 
their family, but by God, they are not proper arbiters of 
science and they just simply aren't.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Weidman">The Institute of Medicine study that was done, they were--
in the charge, was to find out whether or not it was plausible 
and they did find out that it was plausible. They did replicate 
the experiment of the concentration of the dioxin and found out 
it was correct.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Weidman">That is the first time that IOM, as part of one of their 
reviews that I know of, where they have actually gone and done 
original scientific experiment in order to see for, themselves, 
what is the deal. The--when the report came out, they said, 
yes, it is, in fact, plausible and, in fact, we believe it 
happened.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Weidman">As you may know, and everybody should understand, Agent 
Orange, Agent Pink, and the other defoliants were mixed with a 
mixture of kerosene and JP4. And what does that do when it hits 
water? It floats near the surface. It floats near the surface 
way the heck out to sea where it would then be picked up.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Weidman">Although Agent Orange is not water-soluble, in fact, it is 
water dispensable, and that is what happened, because it was 
wrapped in the envelope of those petroleum products that did, 
in fact, keep it near the surface.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Weidman">Coming back to the IOM study, they were charged with 
finding out whether there was a mechanism whereby people could 
be exposed. And they showed that that was the case, under 
pressure from VA. Then turned around and said, well, we can't 
really make any recommendation on this because we have no idea 
how much folks were exposed.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Weidman">And we said, so what? You have no idea how much I was 
exposed in Icor, northern part of the Republic of Vietnam, 
otherwise known as South Vietnam versus my colleague, who 
served in For Cor with the Ninth Infantry Division down in the 
southern part of Vietnam. And VA decided with the assistance, 
shall we say, of the Congress in 1991 to say, this is absurd, 
we are never going to figure out who was exposed and not. Let's 
look at the effects of this thing.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Weidman">And the VA, since the blue water Navy, they have tens of 
thousands of Navy vets who used VA services; it is very easy to 
find out who has a Southeast--or Vietnam service medal and who 
does not. And if those who do not who served on a similar 
vessel in the Atlantic or the Mediterranean, compare their 
health to those who have a Vietnam service ribbon. This is not 
a hard thing to do. It is not an expensive thing to do, but 
they haven't even requested that it be done.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. Weidman">And we are with the National Academy of Medicine in 
recommending that they be restored. We know, as valuable and as 
important and as righteous as bill is, because of offsets, it 
probably won't be able to bring it to the floor.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Mr. Weidman">But all of you on this Committee, on a bipartisan way, 
should pressure the secretary to say, this is absurd; include 
these veterans back in. They--Congress in 1991 intended for 
them to be in.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>[The prepared statement of Rick Weidman appears in the</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="Rick Weidman appears in th">    So, I am over time. I thank you for your indulgence of the 
extra one minute and four seconds sir.
Appendix]
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF PATRICK MURRAY</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="PATRICK MURRAY"> Thank you, Mr. Weidman. And with that we will
recognize Mr. Murray.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Murray</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Murray">Chairman Bost, Ranking Member Esty and the
Members of the Subcommittee, on behalf of the men and women of 
the Veterans of Foreign Wars of the United States and our 
auxiliary, thank you for the opportunity to provide our remarks 
on legislation pending before the Committee.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Murray">The VFW supports Blue Water Navy Vietnam Veterans Act, 
which would require the Department of Veteran Affairs to 
include territorial seas as part of the Republic of Vietnam, 
extending presumptive service-connection and health care for 
Agent Orange related illness to Blue Water Navy Veterans. 
Currently VA relies on what the Court of Appeals for Veterans 
Claims has called arbitrary and capricious interpretation of 
inland waterways which unjustly denies veterans who served 
aboard ships in the coastal waters of Vietnam the benefits they 
deserve. The VFW believes that Blue Water Navy Veterans were 
potentially exposed to significant level of toxins and should 
be granted the same presumption of service-connection as their 
counterparts who served in the inland waterways of Vietnam.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Murray">The VFW strongly supports the American Heros COLA Act and 
the Veterans Compensation Cost of Living Adjustment Act, which 
will increase VA compensation for veterans and survivors and 
adjust other benefits by providing a cost of living adjustment. 
The VFW is pleased to support any bill increasing COLA for our 
veterans. However, we would prefer to make COLA increases 
permanent and automatic. Disabled veterans, along with their 
surviving spouses and children, depend on their disability 
compensation plus dependency and indemnity compensation to 
bridge the gap of lost earnings caused by the veteran's 
disabilities. Each year veterans wait anxiously to find out if 
they will receive a cost of living adjustment. There is no 
automatic trigger that increases these forms of compensation 
for veterans and their dependents. Annually veterans wait for a 
separate act of Congress to provide the same adjustments that 
is automatically granted to Social Security beneficiaries.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Murray">The VFW supports the Protect Veterans From Financial Fraud 
Act, which provides the ability of veterans assigned 
fiduciaries to be compensated for having their money mishandled 
or misused. We see this bill as a common sense method to 
protect some of our most vulnerable veterans. If a veterans 
assigned a fiduciary for whatever reason, they need help and 
financial protection. And individuals who mistreat or prey upon 
their clients should be held accountable and compensation must 
be made to those affected. To go further, the VFW supports 
adding legislation that installs criminal penalties for those 
found to be intentionally preying upon veterans for any other 
financial gain. We would like to see this expanded to any 
attorneys or claims specialists that charge a fee to process 
initial claims. Abusing the health and financial welfare of 
veterans in need should be punishable by law.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Murray">The VFW strongly supports the Quicker Veterans Benefits 
Delivery Act in order to help diminish the workload within VA. 
The VFW recognizes that the VA should still be the primary 
driver in taking care of patient's examinations. But we also 
realize that using third party medical evidence that the VA--I 
am sorry--to help is necessary to reduce the workload. Until 
the backlogged files begin to diminish within the VA, they 
should continue to utilize private physician's evidence to help 
shrink the number of claims and appeals. Veterans should not 
have to see another VA doctor in order to review and confirm 
private outside doctors' findings. This only adds to more 
confusion and clogs up the system. The VA needs to allow 
acceptable clinical evidence from competent credible physicians 
and not force veterans to seek a second opinion from a VA 
physician.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Murray">While the VFW supports this bill, we do not feel it covers 
one of the most important medical issues facing veterans today, 
which is mental health. If the VA allows third-party physicians 
to examine veterans for almost all physical conditions, they 
should also utilize the appropriate medical professionals to 
examine mental health. Mental health examinations are 
increasing every day. And the VA insisting on patients seeing 
only VA doctors for initial examinations is increasing the 
burden on their own system. Initial mental health examinations 
should be added to the type of evidence accepted by VA 
examiners.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>[The prepared statement of Patrick Murray appears in the</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="Patrick Murray appears in th">    Mr. Chairman, this concludes my testimony and I'm prepared 
to take any questions you may have.
Appendix]
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF LEROY ACOSTA</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="LEROY ACOSTA"> Thank you, Mr. Murray. With that, we will go to
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Acosta</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Acosta">Thank you, Chairman Bost, Ranking Member Esty
and Members of the Subcommittee. Thank you for inviting DAV to 
testify at this legislative hearing of the Subcommittee on 
Disability Assistance and Memorial Affairs. As you know, DAV, a 
non-profit veteran's service organization comprised of 1.3 
million wartime services able veterans is dedicated to a single 
purpose, empowering veterans to lead high quality lives with 
respect and dignity. I am pleased to be here to present DAV's 
views on the bills under consideration by the Subcommittee.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Acosta">H.R. 105, Protect Veterans From Financial Fraud Act of 2017 
would require the VA to repay veterans those benefits that were 
misused by fiduciaries and establishes an appeals process for 
determinations of veterans mental capacity. DAV does not have a 
resolution specific to this issue. However, we would not oppose 
passage of this legislation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Acosta">H.R. 299, the Blue Water Navy Vietnam Veterans Act of 2017 
would expand the definition of the Republic of Vietnam to 
include its territorial seas for the purposes of the 
presumption of service-connection for diseases associated with 
herbicide exposure. The benefits under this bill would be 
retroactive to September 25th, 1985. DAV supports H.R. 299 
based on DAV Resolution Number 18, which calls for the addition 
of the territorial waters of Vietnam to be included in the 
presumption of exposure to service-connection for herbicide 
related disabilities.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Acosta">Mr. Chairman, DAV Resolution Number 13 calls on Congress to 
support legislation to provide a realistic increase in 
disability compensation. DAV supports the provision in H.R. 
1328 and H.R. 1329, which would increase veterans' disability 
compensation, survivor benefits and clothing allowances by the 
same percentage as Social Security benefit increases. However, 
DAV is concerned about the automatic adjustment provision in 
H.R. 1328. This may adversely affect congressional oversight 
meant to protect against the erosion of these critical 
benefits, particularly in years where there are no COLA 
increases, such as in 2015, or minimal increases, such as in 
2017.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Acosta">H.R. 1390 would permit the VA to cover the costs associated 
with the transportation of deceased veterans not only to 
national cemeteries, but also to other recognized veteran 
cemeteries. DAV does not have a resolution specific to H.R. 
1390. However, we would not oppose its passage. This 
legislation would benefit veteran survivors by helping to 
offset the cost of transporting the veteran to their final 
resting place.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Acosta">H.R. 1564, VA Beneficiary Travel Act of 2017, would amend 
Section 504 of the Veterans Benefits Improvement Act of 1996 to 
specify the funding source for travel related to examinations 
by physicians not employed by the VA regarding medical 
disabilities of applicants for VA benefits. DAV does not have a 
resolution. However, we would not oppose passage of this 
legislation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Acosta">The Quicker Veterans Benefits Delivery Act of 2017 would 
amend Title 38 U.S.C. to improve the treatment of medical 
evidence provided by non-VA medical professionals in support of 
veterans' claims for disability compensation. Mr. Chairman, DAV 
is pleased to provide our support of this bill, consistent with 
DAV Resolution Number 230, which seeks the enactment of 
legislation that would require VA to consider private medical 
evidence supplied by licensed private health care providers in 
private practices. This bill would give due deference to 
private medical evidence that is competent, credible, probative 
and otherwise adequate for rating purposes.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>[The prepared statement of LeRoy Acosta appears in the</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="LeRoy Acosta appears in th">    Mr. Chairman, this concludes my testimony. And I'd be 
pleased to address any questions related to the bills discussed 
today.
Appendix]
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF JOHN B. WELLS</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="JOHN B. WELLS"> Thank you, Mr. Acosta. Then we want to move on to
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wells</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Wells">Thank you, Mr. Chairman, Ranking Member Esty. My
name is Commander John Wells, USN retired. And I appreciate the 
opportunity to testify. We are going to talk mostly about Blue 
Water Navy Vietnam Veterans Act. I talk a little fast, 
especially since I'm going to try to go over some of the 
questions and red herrings given by the VA in their testimony 
to provide some real answers.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Wells">First of all, I know that they are interested in the 
definition of territorial seas. That is set by treaty, 1958 
Convention on Territorial Seas in the Contiguous Zone, which 
has been ratified by the United States Senate. And ratified 
treaties become part of domestic law. We also recognized the 
territorial seas and Vietnamese sovereignty over them in the 
1954 Geneva accords and the 1973 Paris peace treaties. And 
court decisions of the Fifth Circuit and the Supreme Court of 
the United States specify that we will follow the definition of 
territorial seas.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Wells">To make it easy, in Attachment One to my testimony we have 
shown you where the territorial seas is. It's the dashed line 
in there. So we would ask that that be made part of the 
legislative history of this so the VA won't define territorial 
seas as some lake in the middle of Hanoi.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Wells">The 1985 date was picked because of the effective namer. 
You won't be adjudicating cases back to 1985. But if there are 
new diseases which come about, we would get the same benefit of 
namer as our army and brown water brothers would. In effect, 
these rights were stripped away from us by the VA in 2002. So 
you won't be looking at anymore claims until--2002 would be the 
earliest date. And many of those claims have expired, and 
unfortunately many of the veterans have expired as well.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Wells">As far as the time to adjudicate these claims and so on a 
so forth, Mr. Chairman, Ranking Member Esty, Members of the 
Subcommittee, we are the backlog. We have kept those going. 
Okay. And if you pass this bill and give the presumption there 
is going to be a whole lot of the cases in the appellate 
backlog and in the individual claims backlog that can be 
immediately adjudicated and corrected. So and that is the truth 
of the matter.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Wells">The VA talked about cost. They threw out a 900 and some 
million dollar figure I think for the first year. No, that is 
not the case. And Attachment Five to our testimony gives the 
CBO estimate of 1.104 billion. And I have seen them give up 
costs of 20 billion. I have seen them given costs of 4.4 
billion is what they told the Senate in the last Congress. 
Let's look at what the CBO says, 1.104 billion. I have met with 
the CBO. If anything, and they will agree with this, it is 
probably a little high at this time because of the ships added 
to the ships' list.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Wells">And by the way, the DoD and the VA are not working together 
on that. That is input coming from organizations such as the 
Blue Water Navy Vietnam Veterans Association and some other 
organizations that do it. There is one guy in Cleveland, Jim 
Sampel, who does it part time. So, General, in answer to your 
question, no, they are not doing what they should, is going out 
and saying, hey, Navy, where were the positions of these ships 
vis-a-vis Vietnam. We did have a bill that passed the House 
twice. It would have done that two congresses ago. We haven't 
brought it back up again. We would sure like to see it brought 
up again because that would help us identify some more ships 
that had gone in the river.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Wells">Ms. Murray talked, I am sorry I am talking fast, Ms. Murray 
talked about, Murphy, excuse me, talked about rationality and 
there has to be a rational basis. We agree with that, we 
certainly do. But what she didn't mention was the Court of 
Appeals of veterans' claims in a case called Gray v. McDonald 
came out and said that the exclusion of the bays and the 
harbors are just simply irrational and, as somebody mentioned, 
arbitrary and capricious.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Wells">Now, they say there is no evidence that the Agent Orange 
got there. Mr. Chairman, I have shown you and probably half the 
people sitting up there Exhibit Two to our testimony, which 
shows where the bottom sediment samples were taken in Naktong 
Harbor, and Exhibit Three, which shows the toxicity levels 20 
years after the war. So they can't say it is not there. They 
don't mention the water barges, which were taking water from Da 
Nong Harbor's Monkey Mountain, this area up here that looks 
like it is low land, it is actually jungle. Was sprayed 
throughout the war. There is a reservoir there. That water was 
taken on and your staff has all this information. And they took 
it around to the ships.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Wells">And by the way, let's talk about another fallacy. They say 
that the Australian study was invalid because U.S. Navy ships 
did not make potable water within 12 miles of shore. That is 
not true. There was a manual in the medicine depart--
publication which suggested it. But I know for a fact, and I 
was a chief engineer on a number of these ships, water was my 
business, that they did make water, even potable water, in some 
of the harbors and certainly close to shore. They had to, to 
keep the water tanks going. More importantly they always made 
feed water for the boilers. And guess what, it is the same 
distillation system down to the final discharge valve. And we 
have told the VA this before, they know it. Okay. So that even 
if they were only making water for the boilers, it would still 
have been contaminated water. Okay.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Wells">And I am sorry, I am starting to pull a Rick Weidman here 
and go over time. But just a couple other quickies. As far as 
studies go, the Australian Cancer Incident Studies shows a much 
higher rate of cancer incidents among those that were in the 
Navy as against those that went to shore. And the CDC's Non-
Hodgkin's Lymphoma Study says the same thing.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Wells">And by the way, the Institute of Medicine, the VA will 
always misquote this. In the sentence that they say is they 
can't say definitely that there was no Agent Orange exposure. 
The very next sentence says ``There is no more or less evidence 
to show exposure of Blue Water Navy than there was the brown 
water or the people ashore.'' This was never about science. It 
was about a bad general counsel's opinion. And when we called 
him on it, they circled the wagons and they still do.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>[The prepared statement of John B. Wells appears in the</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="John B. Wells appears in th">    I do have a meeting coming up with Secretary Shulkin on 
April 21st and we have oral argument on a court suit coming up 
on May 5th. So we are pursuing all matters. I understand I am 
over time. Shows I can talk longer than Rick. But the problem 
is there is so much to cover. But, you know, Mr. Chairman, we 
have plenty of money to send those guys to war. We should be 
able to pay for them when they get back. I put some ideas in my 
written testimony. The Senate has shot us down on a couple. But 
frankly, we don't care how you pay for it, but you need to pay 
for it. These guys are dying and their families are being left 
destitute because of medical bills. We owe them better than 
that. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
Appendix]
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you, Mr. Wells.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Bost">I'm going to go to questioning now and I will yield myself 
five minutes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Bost">    First question is for the panel as a whole. Okay. And 
before we get to a lot bigger subject, but this is just real 
quick. This question is for all witnesses, as I said. How would 
veterans and their families benefit assuming they received a 
COLA next year? Mr. Hearn, we will start with you.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Hearn</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Hearn"> They would certainly benefit by adjusting for
the cost of inflation. I guess I am kind of confused as to 
where you are going with the question. I mean if the cost of 
living goes up, it is only natural that Congress responds 
accordingly and provides that compensation increase.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Okay. Maybe I should expand on--I think in your
testimony, the concern you had was that you feel that Congress 
needs to make an every year?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Hearn</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Hearn"> Correct. As far as the--the concern that we have
is dealing with the chain CPI. And if you project that going 
out over decades, the amount of money that is lost, and the one 
sample that we used was it would be roughly about $100,000 over 
a 30 or 40 year span. I pulled up the average income for one of 
your residents in your district. Okay. That's roughly $30,000 I 
think, somewhere in that area. That would be three years' worth 
of salary for your average constituent. So that is a sizeable 
amount of income. I mean obviously it would vary between the 
Ranking Member and yours, but--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Bost">Of course.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Bost">    Mr. Hearn [continued]. But nonetheless it would still be a 
costly endeavor over decades.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Let me ask this. And you know that I am going to
do everything I can for the veterans. It is just--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Hearn</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Hearn">Yes. Oh, I know.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Hearn">    Mr. Bost [continued]. --trying to do the thing that is 
right. My concern that I have when you say, okay, don't do 
this, is then you are just depending on Congress to make a 
decision, rather than setting something in place that actually 
guarantees and gives some sense of that there is going to be 
that COLA. And it is the same thing with Social Security. I was 
a little concerned in your testimony when you said that you--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Hearn</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Hearn"> Well, I mean, and the American Legion's position
is pretty simple. It is that the veterans didn't provide a 
diluted service to their country. And that this would provide a 
diluted benefit if you are talking about that over decades. And 
I understand what you are--where you are going with this. But I 
also know that $100,000 is a sizable amount of income. And I 
agree, we are relying upon Congress and sometimes Congress 
doesn't get along very well. But over time that we also don't 
want our veterans to be harmed just in the need of efficiency. 
If 30 or 40 years we look back at this testimony today and said 
we harmed our veterans, I don't think any of us in this room 
would feel good.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Bost"> And then I want to go down the panel with the
same question. But the only thing I would say is, is one thing 
that we are known for, and that is the big fear, is that if we 
do nothing, nothing will be done.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Hearn</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Hearn"> Right.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Weidman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Weidman"> VVA favors the automatic. We do, however,
think that really should take a hard look at the basic level, 
particularly at the 80--70, 80, 90 percent level and as well as 
100 percent. It is--if in fact somebody is 100 percent in a 
metropolitan area like Washington, what you are doing is 
guaranteeing people will be below the poverty line for the rest 
of their life. And that is just not right.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Right.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Murray</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Mr. Murray"> The VFW simply supports the automatic increase
in COLA. We think it is easier on the recipients, it is easier 
on Congress, so we don't need to be sitting here every year 
doing this.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Acosta</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. Acosta"> Many service-connected disabled veterans rely
on their disability compensation for their livelihood and to 
take care of bills, apart from their civilian counterparts. It 
is important that we get a realistic increase in those benefits 
so they can realize life in the country that they served.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Mr. Wells?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wells</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="21" speaker="Mr. Wells"> Automatic is good. That way we don't have to
fool with it. You don't have to fool with it. And it gives you 
all more time to kind of concentrate on some other things. So 
we support it.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="22" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Yeah. Okay. I'm running short on time. I know now
it is going to run over. And then I don't want to be thrown off 
like the Chairman said. But let me tell you that this is an 
important question to ask. And all of us I think are fighting 
for the same goal, but we have got to ask it. Last Congress CBO 
estimated that the legislation for the Blue Water Navy would be 
a $1.1 billion offset in mandatory funds. To avoid adding to 
the deficit and then we fall under the existing rules that we 
have here. Though many of us, probably all of us on this panel 
would want to make sure that would happen. The question that I 
have is, and I know that, Mr. Wells, you said you didn't care 
where it come from. We have to care where it comes from. And 
even though I love my veterans more than anybody else I fight 
for and will continue to do that, we have to have that answer. 
So, what, any, suggestions do you any Member of the panel have? 
Mr. Weidman?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Weidman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="23" speaker="Mr. Weidman"> We went to war on a credit card. The war in
Iraq and Afghanistan is the first time in American history 
where we have had a tax cut, in fact two, during wartime. So we 
didn't make the commitment to pay for the darn wars. Instead we 
took it out of OCO, which is nothing but an unsecured credit 
account. If you can go to war without having to find an offset, 
then, by God, you ought to be able to pay for those torn up in 
that war without an offset.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="24" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Okay. Maybe the follow up question to the rest of
you as well, and I know I am out of time, but I am going to be 
like the two on the panel. The question is, is there something 
we can work on in the bill that would actually be something 
that we could argue that would bring the cost in paperwork 
down? You understand what I am saying? So that the estimated 
cost, if we don't agree with the estimated cost, maybe we think 
that, okay, well, the assumptions are a little bit high or 
something like that, so that we can come back and deal with the 
argument on what the costs are. And like I said, I want to, if 
they do it, I want to be paying for them.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wells</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="25" speaker="Mr. Wells">Mr. Chairman, there are several things. First
off, you know, I do have the meeting with Secretary Shulkin. It 
is possible that he would just restore the benefits, in which 
case it become under appropriations and the cost of the bill 
would go to zero. Secondly, we do have our pending oral 
argument in the Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit. If we 
win that case, then the bays and the harbors would be covered. 
We would estimate that about 90 percent of the ships would be 
covered. And our estimate of the ten-year cost would then fall 
down to about between 100 and 150 million over ten years, but 
assuming we cover everybody that went in the harbors.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="26" speaker="Mr. Wells">    But here is the kicker. And, yes, you have to understand it 
is hard for me to go back and talk to my veterans and say, you 
know, and explain the Paygo Act to them.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="27" speaker="Mr. Bost"> I understand that.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wells</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="28" speaker="Mr. Wells">Because they're the ones that are dying. I
understand Paygo. Okay. I think it's done a great job in a lot 
of ways. But now this is something that we really have to look 
at because there is not a lot of mandatory spending left in the 
VA budget. There was some in the home loan. We suggested that 
and it got sucked up into the Choice Act. There are going to be 
some automatic offsets, which I'm not sure CBO has applied.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="29" speaker="Mr. Wells">First of all, people that are now eligible for non--for a 
veterans pension, okay, if they served in time of war and make 
I think it's less than about $14,000 a year, they get a 
veterans pension. That would be offset by the benefits. And so 
there would be a dollar for dollar recovery there. Secondly, 
anybody who has retired and is getting a retirement pension if 
their disability is 40 percent or less, there would be the VA 
waiver, which would be a dollar for dollar offset. We don't 
know what those numbers are because VA won't give us the 
figures. But there's other things that we need to look at.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="30" speaker="Mr. Wells">    A number of people went ashore. Now, they have problems 
proving that, and VA will want, you know, 20,000 affidavits and 
a video to show they were ashore. But probably about any one 
time, about ten percent of the fleet went ashore. They had to 
go see the doctor, the dentist, the lawyer, the chaplain, call 
home. They got transferred on and off. They made a mail run 
into the harbor. You got boat crews. You got helicopter crews, 
you know, go pick up some supplies, whatever. There's a number 
of those people. And there's no way to determine those numbers.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="31" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Right.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wells</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="32" speaker="Mr. Wells">But, you know, our estimate is about, based on
facts, is about ten percent, okay, that those are going to be 
offset.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="33" speaker="Mr. Wells">    Now, the other thing is if some of these folks are picked 
up under the VA system there was a CBO report that came out in 
December of 2015. I realize this is--I may have the year wrong, 
it may have been 2014, but I realize this is discretionary 
spending, not mandatory, but says it is about 21 percent 
cheaper to send somebody through the VA system than it is to do 
Medicare reimbursement, which makes some sense. I mean if 
you've got Tricare for life as your secondary, it is probably 
even more than 21 percent. Those are old numbers, it was before 
Choice. But, you know, it is still a factor. Okay. All that 
being said--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="34" speaker="Mr. Bost">Mr. Wells--</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="35" speaker="Mr. Bost">    Mr. Wells [continued]. Right. Can I make the bill self-pay 
for itself? No.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="36" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Let me go ahead and use--switch over to Ms. Esty
because I almost went five minutes over on my time; I said I 
wouldn't do that. But just I think it is vitally important. So, 
Ms. Esty, it is your turn.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Esty</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="37" speaker="Ms. Esty">Thank you, Mr. Chairman. We will pick up with
this. And Mr. Weidman, I definitely cannot walk on water, 
guaranteed. But Linda Schwartz is awesome and we are happy to 
have her back in Connecticut and are going to be using her as a 
resource for this Committee. And her passion and commitment 
around Agent Orange is in part what inspires me and helps me 
work every day on this.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="38" speaker="Ms. Esty">    So we are going to pick back up, Mr. Wells, with figuring 
out how we are going to pay for this because one of the things 
I think is important to note, and all of you have referenced 
this, is this cost of the system of trying to determine who is 
in and who is out. And that is part of the reason for 
presumptive. And I am not sure that the CBO scoring is really 
looking at that. And again, you are all right, everyone is 
happy to be there when we send our troops to war. And we need a 
solemn commitment to take care of them when they come home. 
That is part of the reason we need to be all over them right 
now I think on burn pits to not repeat with the current 
veterans what has happened with this delay, delay, deny for 
Vietnam vets. So if you pick back up--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wells</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="39" speaker="Mr. Wells">Yeah, thank you, Ranking Member Esty. You know,
one of the things is the Blue Water Navy is the tip of the 
spear. There is plenty of other Agent Orange exposures which we 
can go through at length. There is burn pits, there is Fort 
McClellan, there is all kinds of toxic exposures. In our 
written testimony we present--we recommended a brand new 
funding source we think to cover all toxic exposure research, 
kind of a follow on to what was passed last year, and toxic 
exposure benefits for burn pits, Fort McClellan and so on so 
forth. It is probably going to be north of $20 billion a year.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="40" speaker="Mr. Wells">    We recommended a $10 fee for everybody that turned--puts in 
a tax return. Okay. And you could make it voluntary and you are 
probably not going to get that much, but it would still be 
some. If you make it mandatory, we are talking about everybody 
who files a tax return, and there is 250 million filed every 
year, okay, in this country, to pay what we called a freedom 
fee. Okay. And that will generate not only money to pay for the 
Blue Water Navy, but the other Agent Orange exposures, Guam, 
Panama, wherever, Fort McClellan, burn pits and so on and so 
forth. The fact is there is just not enough mandatory spending 
left around to--left there to go around. I think we need a new 
funding source. That seemed to be a fair way to do it.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Esty</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="41" speaker="Ms. Esty"> Thank you. Anyone else who didn't get a chance to
do that? All right. Mr. Weidman, you do not speak as quickly as 
Commander Wells. Anything else you would like to add to your 
testimony?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Weidman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="42" speaker="Mr. Weidman">The VA never should have taken the Blue Water
Navy's sailors out of the group that was eligible for 
presumption in the first place. All of the evidence since is 
that they belong and it should be restored and that poor 
decision should be reversed. What wasn't said by our friends 
from VA was that the first thing they said was our 
desalinization units didn't work the same way. We used a 
different theory. And then it was pointed out that not only did 
we do it the same way, but the desalinization units on the 
Australian ships and the American ships were both came from WD 
Burrows and Sons and were installed by the American company on 
the Australian and the American ships. So now they have moved 
to you can't tell how much anybody got.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="43" speaker="Mr. Weidman">    Well, you know, we finally in that--when I mentioned the 
IOM report and the Chair trying to convince association of the 
United States Navy and the Fleet Reserve and the Legion 
representative and me that somehow this meant that nobody 
should be granted presumption. So we said, so, why, because you 
can't measure how much dioxin? She said yes. And so we asked 
the question what dose of dioxin is safe? And she, with all due 
respect to the lady and who is no doubt a good scientist, her 
eyes got as big as not saucers, big as great big dinner plates. 
And she said well, there is no safe does of dioxin. Admitting 
that once you have got biological plausibility and you could 
replicate this experiment about how far out at sea, it then 
reveals that the whole process inside VA veterans' benefits and 
inside the environmental hazards and public health section 
frankly is not science, it is sophistry. We should have public 
servants there who we can rely on to be neutral arbiters of 
science. And we would suggest that they are not.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Esty</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="44" speaker="Ms. Esty"> Thank you very much. And you are correct, it is
zero level of safe exposure to dioxin. We all know that. That 
is the basis of EPA regulations all across America on this 
issue. And it is doubly true for those that were sent in harm's 
way to defend freedom. And if you would, please make sure that 
we get entered into the record the full relevant reports which 
you have referenced from the National Academy of Sciences and 
Institute of Medicine, which I'd like to make sure that those 
full records are included with the relevant discussions about 
the comparative difference between the certainty that there 
exists and the certainty that there exists for blue water 
versus brown water and territorial. Thank you very much.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="45" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="46" speaker="Mr. Bost">    And Mr. Bergman?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bergman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="47" speaker="Mr. Bergman"> Thanks, Mr. Chairman. Thank all of you for
your testimony this morning. It makes a difference. Mr. Hearn, 
please explain why you believe it is important to codify a 
veteran's right to appeal VA's decision to appoint a fiduciary?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Hearn</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="48" speaker="Mr. Hearn"> The American--I mean if VA assigns a fiduciary,
there have been times where the physician will ask the veteran 
do you manage your financial affairs at home or does your wife 
pay the bills? In my own house, my wife pays a good portion of 
the bills. And using their logic, I suppose I should have a 
fiduciary. Please don't. But that is the reason. I mean, people 
make mistakes, that is human. So I think that some of the 
reason why, that is one of the bigger reasons why we should be 
appealing, why those issues should be appealed.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bergman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="49" speaker="Mr. Bergman"> Okay. So you are trying to provide a little
extra assistance for that veteran?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Hearn</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="50" speaker="Mr. Hearn"> Well, I mean if the veteran does not deserve--if
the veteran feels that he or she does not deserve a fiduciary 
and has been misunderstood during an examination, I don't think 
you would want to have those rights taken away from you. Other 
times there are issues dealing with Second Amendment issues 
that pop up because if you have been assigned a fiduciary 
sometimes they say we need to pull your weapons from you. And 
that is certainly something that the American Legion is 
against, just because it is the two don't necessarily 
correlate.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bergman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="51" speaker="Mr. Bergman"> Okay. Thank you. Mr. Hearn, based on your
experience working with veterans' claims, does the VA routinely 
accept competent medical evidence from qualified private 
physicians when evaluating claims?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Hearn</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="52" speaker="Mr. Hearn"> I wouldn't say routinely. The biggest problem
that we have noticed has dealt with this evaluation tool 
builder. Imagine being a GS-11 or 12 out of some regional 
office making adjudications and the evaluation builder says 
this. But it does not have any measure or any way to weigh 
evidence. It doesn't allow for lay testimony to be included. It 
doesn't include continuity of symptoms. This is a failure. This 
is a big failure on VA's part. And it is a failure that even 
the regional offices are noticing while we are doing these 
regional office reviews. And it really raises questions about 
the quality of adjudications when you have got a tool that the 
employees are feeling compelled to use, even though they 
recognize at times that it doesn't consider all of the evidence 
that is of record.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bergman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="53" speaker="Mr. Bergman"> Okay. Any other Members of the panel care to
comment on that question?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Weidman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="54" speaker="Mr. Weidman"> The reason why they, even if there is adequate
clinical evidence in the file, that they request an exam is 
CYA, sir. Simple as that.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bergman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="55" speaker="Mr. Bergman"> Okay. Anybody else? No. Thank you. Mr.
Chairman, I yield back.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="56" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="57" speaker="Mr. Bost">    Mr. Sablan
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Sablan</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="58" speaker="Mr. Sablan">Yeah. Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman. And
thank you gentlemen for joining us today. When I--in the 
beginning of this term in Congress I asked if I could receive a 
waiver to be in this Committee because I noticed an increasing 
number of casework from the northern--from my district for our 
veterans. And I will be very--truth be told I didn't know there 
were so many veteran service organizations.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="59" speaker="Mr. Sablan">I am aware of the presence of Veterans of Foreign Wars out 
there because there are times when we have a burial for veteran 
and it is a member of the VFW who plays the Taps. Sometimes the 
Army Reserves are given orders to perform--to give the gun 
salute. But nowadays I think they need an order to it. Even if 
they voluntarily want to do it they can't without orders.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="60" speaker="Mr. Sablan">And, but I am just getting such an education. I didn't know 
about this dioxins. You know, I know about Agent Orange, but I 
didn't know about this color of rainbow basically, a lot of 
just different things. The Vietnam War I was a young pers--
young. But I don't know if you guys were--you guys went to war. 
I don't know why we went to war. I became an American in 1986. 
We became a part of the United States in 1978. And so last 
November, Veterans Day I took the liberty of presenting a 
tribute to Vietnam veterans. And I didn't know it meant so 
much. So many of them came up to me and said thank you. This 
gentleman who I know came up to me in tears and said thank you 
because all I did was say welcome home from a very I think 
unpopular war was what it was called.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="61" speaker="Mr. Sablan">But thank you for what you do. I don't know if we have DAVs 
or, you know, but I will continue to work with this Committee. 
This Committee have been very helpful to me. And with, of 
course, the Veterans Administration. And in Northern Mariana we 
have a doctor that when I got in there was no medical services. 
So I think that the contract was negotiated, but it was 
somebody filed it somewhere. And I think the file got lost 
somewhere. So they found it and we got a physician on contract. 
And she can only take so many, so I think they got another one. 
But we are so far removed that we were forgotten. So we do have 
a VHA staff now.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="62" speaker="Mr. Sablan">The individual suffering from PTSD see a--get a counseling 
through a television screen. It is just incredibly unfair to 
someone who has put on a uniform and gone to Afghanistan and 
come back and can't see a doctor because they won't give him a 
counselor, psychologist or psychiatrist. They instead tell them 
that you have to come and sit down in front this table and 
there is a TV screen there and someone at the other end will 
talk to you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="63" speaker="Mr. Sablan">We did a test of the resource provided to our--the mili--or 
the VA's major contractors. We found out that some people on 
the list didn't know they were contractors. Some of the people 
on the list no longer--they moved away. But we got a new list 
and we checked and some of them are now okay. The emergency 
crisis line works, but it gets referred to Hawaii, and the time 
zone is, you know, different.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="64" speaker="Mr. Sablan">    But I am here because I do want to try as much as I can to 
help those veterans who have served our country. They put on a 
uniform. These people were whole when they left home. When they 
came back many of them were broken. Some of their wounds we 
can't see. But thank you everyone. I am truly getting an 
education from all of you. And Mr. Chairman and the Ranking, 
thank you for holding today's hearing. I appreciate it. I yield 
back.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="65" speaker="Mr. Bost">Thank you. And I do want to go ahead and go
around one more time if anybody that might want to. But I want 
to limit it to three minutes because I think we are into this 
enough. I know there is other hearings going on, but this is 
vitally important. And for those that didn't answer, I want to 
have the chance to respond. I understand neither one of us were 
around when the rule for the offset was written. Okay. But it 
is something that we have to do when we move forward with our 
colleagues. So anyone that didn't have the opportunity to have 
an input for possible offsets, if you have suggestions right 
now, if you come up with them later. But I would open it to 
anyone that would want to respond for possible offsets. That is 
kind of the response I have been getting too.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="66" speaker="Mr. Bost">    So let me say this and that was the main question. One 
thing I do want to ask, Mr. Wells, you talked about the $10 
fee. Okay.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wells</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="67" speaker="Mr. Wells"> Yes, sir.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="68" speaker="Mr. Bost"> The $10 fee is basically a tax increase because
basically it is everybody who fills out a form will then pay a 
$10 fee. So it is a tax increase. But I am not--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wells</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="69" speaker="Mr. Wells">Certainly.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="70" speaker="Mr. Wells">    Mr. Bost [continued]. --arguing against it. I am just 
wanting input. Have you raised any of these ideas with other 
Committees that are present here in Congress, Ways and Means 
staff or any other congressional staff? Because as they move 
forward with the different ideas for--we are talking about tax 
reform.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wells</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="71" speaker="Mr. Wells"> I was--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="72" speaker="Mr. Bost">That would mean--</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="73" speaker="Mr. Bost">    Mr. Wells [continued]. I did raise the issue with Ways and 
Means and we tried to get an appointment with the staff down 
there. I finally got a call from somebody there, it was a 
gentleman. And, I'm sorry, I don't remember his name off the 
top of my head. Who basically said, eh, mark it up, we will 
look at it. So that was the response.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="74" speaker="Mr. Bost"> All right. Well, any response you do get back I
would like to know about.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wells</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="75" speaker="Mr. Wells"> I am going to, when I am coming back here in
May, I am going to try to get back to Ways and Means and to 
Appropriations and see, you know, and try to run all the traps 
on that.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="76" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Okay.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wells</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="77" speaker="Mr. Wells"> And Mr. Chairman, you know, it may not be the
best idea in the world. Maybe something that is--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="78" speaker="Mr. Bost">It is an idea.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="79" speaker="Mr. Bost">    Mr. Wells [continued]. But it is a place to start. And one 
of the things that we proposed in our written testimony is it 
be dedicated. We will take a presidential finding of necessity 
and two-thirds concurrence of both House and Congress to use it 
for anything else. Unless we have an alien invasion I don't 
think we will get two-thirds of the Congress to agree on too 
much.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="80" speaker="Mr. Bost"> That is true.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wells</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="81" speaker="Mr. Wells"> So, but I do appreciate it. If I can just beg
your indulgence for ten more seconds. Congresswoman Stefanik 
did introduce a bill or a resolution rather to show the sense 
at Congress that the original Agent Orange Act would have 
encompassed the bays, harbors, and territorial seas. Senator 
Grassley who was on that bill originally when he was in the 
House put out a press release saying basically that is what we 
thought it was. So when the VA says they are confused, they 
shouldn't be. Thank you.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="82" speaker="Mr. Bost"> All right. Thank you. Did you--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Weidman</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="83" speaker="Mr. Weidman">The tax cut that--and several after that first
tax cut in the early aughts, if you will, upset many of us 
because it had never happened before in wartime. And to send 
the American people to the mall while our military went to war 
was setting up almost what happened to us as Vietnam vets, is 
it wasn't the whole Nation pulling together to go to the war. 
In fact, the seeds of all of our fiscal problems of our Federal 
government were laid in 1966 with the Federal Unified 
Consolidated Budget Act where they took the trust out of the 
trust, Highway Trust, FUTA, et cetera, and then started 
appropriating it out in order to paper balance the budget. So 
the guns and budget decision was that particular piece of 
legislation which has affected everything since because of the 
deficit and because of the scrambling. That is why people call 
it smoke and mirrors.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="84" speaker="Mr. Weidman">    What--and I couldn't get anybody to introduce it, that you 
could keep the tax cut if you had a veteran who served on 
active duty in your immediate family. Otherwise you couldn't 
have the tax cut. And that would distribute at least somewhat 
the pain because it is the same, I am convinced, the same 
thousand, two thousand families that have fought every doggone 
war we have ever had. And that is certainly those in the combat 
MOSs.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="85" speaker="Mr. Bost"> Yeah. I would like to turn it over to Ms. Esty.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Esty</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="86" speaker="Ms. Esty"> Thank you very much. And I just want to say thank
you to all of you for your service. Urge you to continue to 
work with us. I think we all have good intent here, but to 
figure out how to do this and the challenge meaning time, we 
really are going to need to work together. So finding where we 
can get those offsets, finding where we can get savings, 
finding where we can more rapid in determination. And I want to 
thank the VA for staying. I know in our last hearing folks were 
not able to stay. It is really important that we all be at the 
table together, that everyone listen to what everyone else is 
saying. And I want to thank you for staying because we really 
do need all of us to be partners in this endeavor to do right 
by those who have served this country. So again, I want to 
thank you all very much. I have kept mine under three minutes. 
The only--
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="87" speaker="Mr. Bost"> That is great. Mr. Sablan?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Sablan</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="88" speaker="Mr. Sablan"> I am done.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bost</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="89" speaker="Mr. Bost">Okay. That being said, we want to go ahead and
release the third and final panel. And I want to thank everyone 
for joining us here today and sharing your views with the 
Subcommittee. Your testimony provides us with important insight 
into the possibilities as we move forward through this 
legislation process.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="90" speaker="Mr. Bost">I ask unanimous consent that written statements provided by 
the Paralyzed Veterans of America and the Fleet Reserve 
Association be placed into the hearing record. Without 
objection, so ordered. Finally, I ask unanimous consent for all 
Members have five legislative days to revise and extend their 
remarks and include extraneous material on any or all of the 
bills under consideration this afternoon. And without 
objection, so ordered. This hearing is now adjourned.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="91" speaker="Mr. Bost">[Whereupon, at 12:16 p.m., the Subcommittee was adjourned.]</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="92" speaker="Mr. Bost">----------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="93" speaker="Mr. Bost">Prepared Statement of Beth Murphy</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="94" speaker="Mr. Bost">Good morning, Chairman Bost, Ranking Member Etsy, and Members of 
the Committee. Thank you for inviting us here today to present our 
views on several bills that would affect VA programs and services. 
Joining me today are Dr. Ralph L. Erickson, Chief Consultant for Post 
Deployment Health Services and Ms. Patricia Watts, Director, 
Legislative and Regulatory Service, National Cemetery Administration.
H.R. 105 - ``Protect Veterans from Financial Fraud Act of 2017"</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="95" speaker="Mr. Bost">Section 2 of H.R. 105 would amend 38 U.S.C. Sec.  6107(b) by 
removing restrictions on VA's authority to reissue benefits in cases of 
fiduciary misuse. Currently, VA is authorized to reissue benefits under 
this subsection only in cases of negligent supervision by VA, or where 
the fiduciary is not an individual, or the fiduciary is an individual 
who serves 10 or more beneficiaries for any month during a period when 
misuse occurs.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="96" speaker="Mr. Bost">Section 3 of H.R. 105 would amend 38 U.S.C. Sec.  5501A to add a 
new subsection stating that mental competence determinations may be 
appealed to the Board of Veterans' Appeals (BVA) and the U.S. Court of 
Appeals for Veterans Claims (CAVC).</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="97" speaker="Mr. Bost">VA supports this bill. Section 2 of the bill would ensure the equal 
treatment of all fiduciary misuse victims. VA would no longer be 
required to make distinctions in these cases based on the nature and 
scope of the fiduciary's business, or on the fiduciary's status. This 
bill would allow VA to promptly reissue benefits that have been 
misused, thereby minimizing financial hardship to beneficiaries caused 
by the misuse, delays in obtaining restitution, or VA determinations 
regarding negligence.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="98" speaker="Mr. Bost">We note that by broadening the cases in which the Secretary shall 
pay an amount equal to misused benefits to ``any case not covered by 
subsection (a)'' and eliminating the requirements currently found in 
section 6107(b)(2) that currently attach to non-negligence cases, this 
bill effectively allows the Secretary to reissue benefits in all cases 
of misuse. While VA supports the bill as written, it is questionable 
whether there is any utility in maintaining the distinction between 
negligence cases covered by subsection (a) and all other cases if this 
bill were to become law. Further, current subsection (b)(3), which this 
bill would move to subsection (b)(2), directs VA to pay to a 
beneficiary or a successor fiduciary any recouped benefits ``[i]n any 
other case in which the Secretary obtains recoupment from a fiduciary 
who has misused benefits.'' Insofar as subsections (a) and (b)(1) of 
section 6107 would apply to all cases in which a fiduciary misused 
benefits, there would not appear to be any ``other'' instances of 
misuse to which renumbered subsection (b)(2) would apply.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="99" speaker="Mr. Bost">The cost of this bill is associated with section 2. VA estimates 
these costs would be $2 million in FY 2018, $10 million over 5 years, 
and $20 million over 10 years. There would be no costs associated with 
section 3 of the bill because determinations of mental competence are 
already appealable to BVA and the CAVC under existing law.
H.R. 299 - ``Blue Water Navy Vietnam Veterans Act of 2017"</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="100" speaker="Mr. Bost">H.R. 299 would extend the presumption of Agent Orange exposure to 
all Veterans who served on ships in the ``territorial seas'' of the 
Republic of Vietnam. It would do so by amending subsections (a)(1) and 
(f) of 38 U.S.C. Sec.  1116, and subsection (e)(4) of 38 U.S.C. Sec.  
1710, by inserting the phrase ``including the territorial seas of such 
Republic'' after ``served in the Republic of Vietnam'' each place it 
appears.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="101" speaker="Mr. Bost">VA has a number of concerns with H.R. 299 and cannot support the 
bill at this time. The bill does not clearly define what constitutes 
``the territorial seas'' of the Republic of Vietnam. While 
international treaties prescribe general standards governing nations' 
territorial seas, it is unclear whether this bill is intended to follow 
those treaty definitions and, if so, whether it is intended to follow 
the treaty definitions extant during the Vietnam War or those extant 
today. Without a clear definition, VA could not determine which 
Veterans are eligible to receive benefits under the expanded 
presumption based on their military service. VA is also concerned with 
the September 25, 1985, effective date of the bill, which would 
potentially result in retroactive awards of more than 30 years in many 
cases. In enacting provisions extending benefits to other groups of 
Veterans, Congress generally has not extended those benefits 
retroactively, much less for such a significant time period. VA is 
concerned about the apparent inequity of this disparate treatment of 
different groups of Veterans. Further, re-adjudicating old claims and 
establishing awards covering large retroactive periods would be complex 
and labor-intensive tasks that would divert resources from other claim 
adjudications. As will be discussed in greater detail, VA estimates 
that the retroactive benefits payments in FY 2018, alone, would total 
no less than $967 million.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="102" speaker="Mr. Bost">Additionally, there is continued scientific uncertainty surrounding 
the issue of Blue Water Navy Veterans' exposure to Agent Orange. At 
VA's request, the Institute of Medicine (now National Academy of 
Medicine) reviewed all available scientific evidence concluding that 
they were ``unable to state with certainty that Blue Water Navy 
personnel were or were not exposed to Agent Orange and its associated 
TCDD'' (ref: Blue Water Navy Vietnam Veterans and Agent Orange 
Exposure, 2011). For this reason VA continues to review and monitor the 
peer-reviewed scientific / medical literature and is collaborating with 
Veterans Service Organizations (including VFW and the Blue Water Navy 
Vietnam Veterans Association) to gather more information. A new study 
of Vietnam Veterans which includes the collection of data on Blue Water 
Navy Veterans is currently ongoing with early results expected to be 
available by December 2017. Secretary Shulkin is committed to examining 
all available evidence on this issue and gathering input from 
stakeholders in order to make well-informed, scientific evidence-based 
decisions for our Nation's Veterans.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="103" speaker="Mr. Bost">VA's cost estimate for the bill is broken down into four 
categories: benefits, general operating expenses, information 
technology (IT), and health care expenditures. VA estimates the total 
benefits cost of this bill would be $1.4 billion during FY 2018, $3.0 
billion over 5 years, and $5.5 billion over 10 years.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="104" speaker="Mr. Bost">In addition to benefits costs, VA estimates the General Operating 
Expenses (GOE) costs for the first year would be $90.7 million and 
include salary, benefits, rent, training, supplies, other service, and 
equipment. Five-year costs are estimated to be $213.5 million and 10-
year costs are estimated to be $339.0 million. VA further estimates 
that the IT cost for the first year would be $2.9 million, $4.5 million 
over 5 years, and $5.9 million over 10 years. This cost would include 
the IT equipment for full-time equivalent employees, installation, 
maintenance, and IT support.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="105" speaker="Mr. Bost">Regarding health care expenditures, VA estimates the costs of the 
bill would be $36.5 million in FY 2018, $268.0 million over 5 years, 
and $618.2 million over 10 years.
H.R. 1328 - American Heroes COLA Act of 2017</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="106" speaker="Mr. Bost">H.R. 1328 would permanently authorize the Secretary to implement 
cost-of-living increases to the rates of disability compensation for 
service-disabled Veterans and the rates of Dependency and Indemnity 
Compensation (DIC) for Survivors of Veterans. This bill would direct 
the Secretary to increase the rates of those benefits whenever a cost-
of-living increase is made to benefits administered under title II of 
the Social Security Act. These rates would be increased by a percentage 
identical to increases to Social Security benefits.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="107" speaker="Mr. Bost">The Department of Veterans Affairs (VA) supports this bill because 
it would be consistent with Congress' long-standing practice of 
enacting regular cost-of-living increases for compensation and DIC 
benefits in order to maintain the value of these important benefits. 
Additionally, the bill would eliminate the need for additional 
legislation to implement such increases in the future. It would also be 
consistent with current law that requires any cost-of-living increases 
to disability compensation and DIC to be made at a uniform percentage 
that does not exceed the percentage increase to Social Security 
benefits.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="108" speaker="Mr. Bost">VA estimates the cost of this bill would be $1.3 billion in fiscal 
year (FY) 2018, $24.8 billion over 5 years, and $103.6 billion over 10 
years. However, the cost of these increases is included in VA's 
baseline budget because VA assumes that Congress will enact a cost-of-
living adjustment each year. Therefore, enactment of H.R. 1329 would 
not result in additional costs, beyond what is included in VA's 
baseline budget.
H.R. 1329 - Veterans' Compensation Cost-of-Living Adjustment Act of</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="109" speaker="Mr. Bost">2017</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="110" speaker="Mr. Bost">H.R. 1329 would require the Secretary to increase the rates of 
disability compensation and DIC by the same percentage as any increase 
to Social Security benefits effective on December 1, 2017. The bill 
would also require VA to publish these increased rates in the Federal 
Register.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="111" speaker="Mr. Bost">VA strongly supports this bill because it would express, in a 
tangible way, this Nation's gratitude for the sacrifices made by our 
service-disabled Veterans and their surviving spouses and children. The 
bill would also ensure that the value of these benefits keeps pace with 
increases in consumer prices.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="112" speaker="Mr. Bost">VA estimates the cost of this bill to be $1.3 billion in FY 2018, 
$8.1 billion over 5 years, and $17.5 billion over 10 years. However, 
the cost of these increases is included in VA's baseline budget because 
VA assumes that Congress will enact a cost-of-living adjustment each 
year. Therefore, enactment of H.R. 1329 would not result in additional 
costs, beyond what is included in VA's baseline budget.
H.R. 1390 - Transportation of Deceased Veterans to Veterans' Cemeteries</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="113" speaker="Mr. Bost">H.R. 1390 would amend 38 U.S.C. Sec.  2308 to allow payment of the 
monetary allowance currently payable for transportation of eligible 
Veterans' remains for burial in a national cemetery to be paid for 
transportation to a ``covered veterans' cemetery.'' The bill would 
define a ``covered veterans' cemetery'' as a Veterans' cemetery owned 
by a State or Tribal organization in which a deceased Veteran is 
eligible to be buried. The bill would increase the options of burial 
locations for eligible Veterans.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="114" speaker="Mr. Bost">VA supports the intent of H.R. 1390; however, VA is concerned with 
the administrative burden associated with this bill. VA currently 
reimburses actual transportation costs based on receipts submitted by 
claimants. This bill would require VA to pay no more than the cost of 
transportation to the national cemetery nearest the Veteran's last 
place of residence in which burial space is available. Calculating 
these payments would require VA to check availability at national 
cemeteries, determine the equivalent transportation cost to a national 
cemetery, and then compare that cost to the claimant's receipts for 
transportation to the State or Tribal cemetery. VA would welcome the 
opportunity to work with the Subcommittee to address this issue.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="115" speaker="Mr. Bost">VA estimates the benefits cost of the bill would be $1.2 million in 
the first year, $6.7 million over 5 years, and $15.2 million over 10 
years. Discretionary costs for this bill would be insignificant.
H.R. 1564 ``VA Beneficiary Travel Act of 2017"</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="116" speaker="Mr. Bost">H.R. 1564 would amend subsection (d) of section 504 of the 
Veterans' Benefits Improvement Act of 1996 (Public Law 104-275, as 
amended by Public Law 114-315; 38 United States Code (U.S.C.) Sec.  
5101 note), to direct the use of funding from the mandatory 
compensation and pension (C&amp;amp;P) appropriation to pay for travel and 
incidental expenses associated with contract disability examinations 
already funded by the same appropriation in FY 2017 and subsequent 
years. The bill would codify subsection (d) as 38 U.S.C. Sec.  5109C 
(``Pilot program for use of contract physicians for disability 
examinations'').</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="117" speaker="Mr. Bost">The Veterans Benefits Administration (VBA) pays for certain 
contract C&amp;amp;P examinations with funding from the mandatory C&amp;amp;P 
appropriation. Congress granted VBA this authority under section 504, 
which enabled VBA to conduct a ``pilot program'' to have contractors 
complete C&amp;amp;P examinations for Veterans applying for benefits 
administered by VBA. The pilot was initially limited to no more than 10 
VA regional offices, and the source of funding for such contracts was 
the C&amp;amp;P appropriation. In FY 2017, VBA's authority for the pilot was 
expanded to all 56 regional offices.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="118" speaker="Mr. Bost">VA strongly supports legislation to codify VA's current practice 
and clearly authorize VA to fund Veteran participation in the pilot 
program from a single source, rather than in part from the C&amp;amp;P 
appropriation and in part from funds available for the pre-existing 
beneficiary travel program under 38 U.S.C. Sec.  111.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="119" speaker="Mr. Bost">This proposal would not require any additional funding or 
administrative changes within VA. VBA planned to use the C&amp;amp;P account to 
fund beneficiary travel to and from pilot program examinations, as well 
as other incidental expenses of the pilot program, in FY 2017 and 
subsequent years. In addition, this proposal would not change the 
funding source for any other VA beneficiary travel.
H.R. 1725 - ``Quicker Veterans Benefits Delivery Act of 2017"</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="120" speaker="Mr. Bost">This bill would revise statutes pertaining to adjudication of 
disability benefit claims.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="121" speaker="Mr. Bost">Section 2 of this bill would prohibit VA from requesting a medical 
examination when the claimant submits medical evidence or an opinion 
from a non-VA provider that is competent, credible, probative, and 
adequate for rating purposes. Sections 3 and 4 would require VA to 
report to Congress on the progress of VA's Acceptable Clinical Evidence 
(ACE) initiative and, for each VA regional office, data on the use by 
claimants of private medical evidence in support of compensation and 
pension claims.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="122" speaker="Mr. Bost">VA does not support this bill. VA appreciates the intent of the 
bill, which seeks to provide benefits to Veterans more expeditiously. 
However, as written, the bill is, in some respects, unnecessary and 
unclear and would be problematic to implement.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="123" speaker="Mr. Bost">Section 2 of the bill is unnecessary given current legal standards. 
This section would prohibit VA from requesting a medical examination 
when evidence that is submitted is adequate for rating purposes. 
Section 5103A(d)(2) of title 38, U.S.C., notes that an examination or 
opinion is only required when the record does not contain sufficient 
medical evidence to make a decision. Furthermore, section 5125 of title 
38, U.S.C., explicitly notes that private medical examinations may be 
sufficient, without conducting additional VA examinations, for 
adjudicating claims. VA regulations are consistent with these statutory 
requirements. Therefore, this section is unnecessary and duplicative. 
At present, VA may adjudicate a claim without an examination if the 
claimant provides evidence that is adequate for rating purposes. There 
would be no costs associated with section 2.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="124" speaker="Mr. Bost">VA does not support section 3 or 4. VA maintains data concerning 
the number of examinations in which ACE is used, but VA does not track 
when the evidence is supplemented with a telephone interview, data that 
VA would be required to report under the bill. In addition, VA does not 
track when private medical evidence is sufficient or insufficient for 
rating purposes, as this is not a formal determination. This 
determination depends on the receipt and evaluation of each piece of 
evidence and may change at any time in the process. When a VA 
examination is requested after the submission and review of private 
medical evidence, VA has made a determination that the evidence is 
insufficient for rating purposes, as it is VA policy to evaluate a 
condition without an examination when the evidence of record is 
adequate to decide the claim. GOE costs associated with sections 3 and 
4 would be insignificant.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="125" speaker="Mr. Bost">This concludes my remarks. I would be happy to answer any questions 
that you may have. Thank you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="126" speaker="Mr. Bost">&amp;lt;F-dash&amp;gt;</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="127" speaker="Mr. Bost">Prepared Statement of Zachary Hearn</paragraph>
    <option>Subcommittee on Disability Assistance and Memorial Affairs, on behalf</option>
</Statement>
</Hearing>
