<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="33616">
    <intro>    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <info>                      DETERMINING ELIGIBILITY FOR</info>
    <info>                 DISABILITY BENEFITS: CHALLENGES FACING</info>
    <info>                   THE SOCIAL SECURITY ADMINISTRATION</info>
    <info>=======================================================================</info>
    <info>                                 HEARING</info>
    <info>                               BEFORE THE</info>
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON SOCIAL SECURITY</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                                 OF THE
</option>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON WAYS AND MEANS</committee_name>
    <option>                     U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                           SEPTEMBER 6, 2017
                               __________
                          Serial No. 115-SS06
                               __________
         Printed for the use of the Committee on Ways and Means
[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
                    U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE                    
33-616                      WASHINGTON : 2019                     
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <committeeComposition>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON WAYS AND MEANS</comitteeM_name>
    <Chairman>
        <Cname>                      KEVIN BRADY</Cname>
        <Clocation> Chairman</Clocation>
    </Chairman>
    <people>
        <Pname>SAM JOHNSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RICHARD E. NEAL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Massachusetts</Plocation>
    </people>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>DEVIN NUNES</Cname>
        <Clocation> California</Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>SANDER M. LEVIN</Cname>
        <Clocation> Michigan</Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <people>
        <Pname>PATRICK J. TIBERI</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOHN LEWIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Georgia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DAVID G. REICHERT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Washington</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>LLOYD DOGGETT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PETER J. ROSKAM</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE THOMPSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>VERN BUCHANAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOHN B. LARSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Connecticut</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ADRIAN SMITH</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nebraska</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>EARL BLUMENAUER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oregon</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>LYNN JENKINS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Kansas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RON KIND</Pname>
        <Plocation> Wisconsin</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ERIK PAULSEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Minnesota</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BILL PASCRELL</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Jersey</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>KENNY MARCHANT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOSEPH CROWLEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DIANE BLACK</Pname>
        <Plocation> Tennessee</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DANNY DAVIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TOM REED</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>LINDA SANCHEZ</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE KELLY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRIAN HIGGINS</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM RENACCI</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TERRI SEWELL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PAT MEEHAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SUZAN DELBENE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Washington</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>KRISTI NOEM</Pname>
        <Plocation> South Dakota</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JUDY CHU</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>GEORGE HOLDING</Pname>
        <Plocation> North Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JASON SMITH</Pname>
        <Plocation> Missouri</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TOM RICE</Pname>
        <Plocation> South Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DAVID SCHWEIKERT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JACKIE WALORSKI</Pname>
        <Plocation> Indiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CARLOS CURBELO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE BISHOP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Michigan</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>David Stewart</Pname>
        <Plocation> Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Brandon Casey</Pname>
        <Plocation> Minority Chief Counsel</Plocation>
    </people>
</committeeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON SOCIAL SECURITY</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                      SAM JOHNSON, Texas, Chairman
TOM RICE, South Carolina             JOHN B. LARSON, Connecticut
DAVID SCHWEIKERT, Arizona            BILL PASCRELL, JR., New Jersey
VERN BUCHANAN, Florida               JOSEPH CROWLEY, New York
MIKE KELLY, Pennsylvania             LINDA SANCHEZ, California
JIM RENACCI, Ohio
JASON SMITH, Missouri
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <Directory>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <peopleSpeaker> __________  Advisory of September </peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>announcing the hearing</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <Witness>Bea Disman</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Acting Chief of Staff Social Security Administration</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Kathryn Larin</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Director of Education Workforce and Income Security Issues</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Elizabeth McLaren</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Bureau Chief Iowa Disability Determination Services on behalf of National Council of Disability Determination Directors Marilyn Zahm</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Lisa Ekman</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Director of Government Affairs National Organization of Social Security Claimants' Representatives on behalf of the Social Security Task Force Consortium for Citizens with Disabilities QUESTIONS FOR THE RECORD</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Questions submitted by The Honorable Sam Johnson</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Chairman</peopleinfo>
</Directory>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>Subcommittee on Social Security, Committee on Ways and Means,</subcomittee_name>
    <Chairman>
        <Cname>  to Kathryn Larin</Cname>
        <Clocation> and Income </Clocation>
    </Chairman>
    <people>
        <Pname>Security Issues</Pname>
        <Plocation> Government Accountability Office..............</Plocation>
    </people>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>Questions submitted by Amy Shuart</Cname>
        <Clocation> Subcommittee </Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <people>
        <Pname>on Social Security</Pname>
        <Plocation> to Elizabeth </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>McLaren</Pname>
        <Plocation> National Council of Disability </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Determination Directors........................................</Pname>
        <Plocation>Determination Directors........................................</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Questions submitted by The Honorable Sam Johnson</Pname>
        <Plocation> </Plocation>
    </people>
    <option>Subcommittee on Social Security, Committee on Ways and Means,</option>
    <option>  to Bea Disman, Acting Chief of Staff, Social Security 
  Administration.................................................   103
Questions submitted by The Honorable Sam Johnson, Chairman, 
</option>
    <option>Subcommittee on Social Security, Committee on Ways and Means,</option>
    <option>  to Marilyn Zahm, President, Association of Administrative Law 
  Judges.........................................................   118
</option>
    <submittedMaterial>SUBMISSIONS FOR THE RECORD</submittedMaterial>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Peter J Martinelli</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>US Administrative Law Judge Office of Hearings and Appeals Social Security Administration (SSA) National Association of Disability Examiners (NADE)</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Philip B Litteral</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>President National Association of Disability Representatives (NADR)</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Anthony M Reardon</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>National President National Treasury Employees Union (NTEU) DETERMINING ELIGIBILITY FOR DISABILITY BENEFITS: CHALLENGES FACING THE SOCIAL SECURITY ADMINISTRATION  WEDNESDAY SEPTEMBER</peopleinfo>
    <submittedMaterial>Subcommittee on Social Security,</submittedMaterial>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Washington</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>DC The Subcommittee met pursuant to call at : am</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Room</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Rayburn House Office Building Hon Sam Johnson [Chairman of the Subcommittee] presiding [The advisory announcing the hearing follows:] ADVISORY FROM THE COMMITTEE ON WAYS AND MEANS</peopleinfo>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON SOCIAL SECURITY</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                                                CONTACT: (202) 225-1721
FOR IMMEDIATE RELEASE
Wednesday, September 6, 2017
SS-06
                 Chairman Johnson Announces Hearing on
            Determining Eligibility for Disability Benefits:
                 Challenges Facing the Social Security
                             Administration
    House Ways and Means Social Security Subcommittee Chairman Sam 
Johnson (R-TX), announced today that the Subcommittee will hold a 
hearing entitled ``Determining Eligibility for Disability Benefits: 
Challenges Facing the Social Security Administration.'' The hearing 
will focus on the Social Security Administration's plan to reduce the 
hearing backlog and claimant wait times, other efforts to modernize and 
improve the disability determination process, and tools available to 
expedite decisions for those with certain severe conditions. The 
hearing will take place on Wednesday, September 6, 2017 in room 2020 of 
the Rayburn House Office Building, beginning at 10:00 a.m.
    In view of the limited time to hear witnesses, oral testimony at 
this hearing will be from invited witnesses only. However, any 
individual or organization may submit a written statement for 
consideration by the Committee and for inclusion in the printed record 
of the hearing.
DETAILS FOR SUBMISSION OF WRITTEN COMMENTS:
    Please Note: Any person(s) and/or organization(s) wishing to submit 
written comments for the hearing record must follow the appropriate 
link on the hearing page of the Committee website and complete the 
informational forms. From the Committee homepage, http://
waysandmeans.house.gov, select ``Hearings.'' Select the hearing for 
which you would like to make a submission, and click on the link 
entitled, ``Click here to provide a submission for the record.'' Once 
you have followed the online instructions, submit all requested 
information. ATTACH your submission as a Word document, in compliance 
with the formatting requirements listed below, by the close of business 
on Wednesday, September 20, 2017. For questions, or if you encounter 
technical problems, please call (202) 225-3625.
FORMATTING REQUIREMENTS:
    The Committee relies on electronic submissions for printing the 
official hearing record. As always, submissions will be included in the 
record according to the discretion of the Committee. The Committee will 
not alter the content of your submission, but we reserve the right to 
format it according to our guidelines. Any submission provided to the 
Committee by a witness, any materials submitted for the printed record, 
and any written comments in response to a request for written comments 
must conform to the guidelines listed below. Any submission not in 
compliance with these guidelines will not be printed, but will be 
maintained in the Committee files for review and use by the Committee.
    All submissions and supplementary materials must be submitted in a 
single document via email, provided in Word format and must not exceed 
a total of 10 pages. Witnesses and submitters are advised that the 
Committee relies on electronic submissions for printing the official 
hearing record.
    All submissions must include a list of all clients, persons and/or 
organizations on whose behalf the witness appears. The name, company, 
address, telephone, and fax numbers of each witness must be included in 
the body of the email. Please exclude any personal identifiable 
information in the attached submission.
    Failure to follow the formatting requirements may result in the 
exclusion of a submission. All submissions for the record are final.
    The Committee seeks to make its facilities accessible to persons 
with disabilities. If you are in need of special accommodations, please 
call 202-225-1721 or 202-226-3411 TDD/TTY in advance of the event (four 
business days notice is requested). Questions with regard to special 
accommodation needs in general (including availability of Committee 
materials in alternative formats) may be directed to the Committee as 
noted above.
    Note: All Committee advisories and news releases are available at
    http://www.waysandmeans.house.gov/
    Chairman JOHNSON. Good morning to all of you, and welcome 
to today's hearing on the challenges Social Security faces when 
deciding if a person should receive disability benefits. Since 
I have been Chairman, we have held 18 hearings, including 
today, on the disability insurance program, on one topic or 
another. Now, that is a lot of hearings, but the disability 
insurance program is too important for Social Security not to 
get it right.
    Americans pay taxes on their hard-earned wages for the 
promise of future Social Security benefits when the worker 
retires, is unable to work due to a disability, or dies. These 
benefits are an important part of a family's financial 
security, and Americans rightfully expect that when they apply 
for benefits, if they are eligible, that they will receive them 
quickly. But for those applying for disability benefits, that 
isn't the case.
    Today, over 1 million people are waiting for a hearing with 
Social Security administrative law judges, and on the average 
these folks will wait around 600 days to get that hearing. That 
is nearly 2 years. And that is after waiting almost 4 months, 
on the average, for an initial decision, and more than 3 months 
for a second look, known as reconsideration.
    While not all of them will qualify for benefits, all of 
these people deserve an answer in a timely fashion. And for 
those who don't qualify for benefits, these long wait times 
make getting back to work even harder.
    With backlogs at record highs, it is more important than 
ever for Social Security to ensure that the Compassionate 
Allowances program is working as intended. The Compassionate 
Allowances program was created in 2008 as a way to help those 
with the most severe impairments jump to the front of the line. 
But as we will hear today, this program doesn't always work the 
way it should.
    It is clear Social Security has serious problems when it 
comes to making sure people get the disability decisions as 
quickly as possible. But Social Security problems and the 
disability insurance program are more than just long wait 
times. Since 2003, Social Security's disability programs have 
been on the GAO's high risk list, in large part because of 
outdated criteria to determine eligibility for disability 
benefits. While some progress has been made, there is more work 
to be done to modernize Social Security's disability program.
    As we know, more money isn't always the answer. This year, 
the Social Security Administration received $90 million in 
dedicated funding to address a disability backlog. Yet, wait 
times continue to grow. Social Security used some of this 
funding in much-needed information technology improvements that 
should pay dividends in the long run. The Social Security 
Administration must find ways to be more efficient and 
modernize the disability insurance program. And today, we are 
going to hear about how Social Security plans to do just that. 
This won't be easy work and there is plenty to do.
    Social Security needs more than just a plan to fix this; it 
needs real leadership, and that is a large part of management's 
problem. Since 2013, Social Security has had an Acting 
Commissioner. In February, Ranking Member Larson and I, along 
with our colleagues from the Human Resources Subcommittee, sent 
a letter to President Trump, asking that he nominate a 
Commissioner without delay.
    Social Security needs a Senate-confirmed Commissioner who 
can lead the agency and focus on providing the service 
Americans expect and deserve. Social Security provides 
important benefits that many Americans rely on. With the right 
leadership and a good plan, Social Security can get back on the 
right track, but until then, this Subcommittee will keep asking 
tough questions about how to get this done. The American people 
deserve nothing less.
    And I am sure that my compatriot next to me agrees with 
that. With that, I will recognize Mr. Larson.
    Mr. LARSON. Well, I thank our distinguished Chairman, and I 
certainly concur with that. And, most importantly, concur in 
saying your continued leadership to your country in every 
capacity is greatly respected. And I would say that we are in 
agreement on a number of the problems that Social Security is 
set with. As you know, Mr. Chairman, millions of Americans rely 
on Social Security for basic income when they retire, or if 
they are severely disabled or can no longer work. Social 
Security is also there to help widows and children who have 
lost a parent. There is no private plan on the market, simply 
put, that can compare to Social Security. That is just a fact.
    And we are living that fact currently. And the people at 
Social Security deserve a lot of credit. In the midst of 
Harvey, and what is going on and the devastation and the people 
of Texas in the greater Houston area, and with Irma bearing 
down upon Florida now, I think it is heartening to know that 
Social Security hasn't missed a payment. And that on the 
ground, Social Security has people working with the Red Cross 
and other volunteer agencies. And even in the case where people 
do not have electronic transfers, that they are there to help 
and make sure that America gets what is America's number one 
program, the Social Security program.
    Natural disasters remind us of how important it is to fight 
back against calls to cut Social Security, and instead, come 
together in a bipartisan way to make commonsense adjustments to 
strengthen Americans insurance plan and protect the benefits 
Americans have earned and rely on. Both the Chairman and I have 
offered comprehensive plans to address the long-term shortfall 
in the Social Security system so Americans can continue to 
count on these benefits, whether they become disabled or 
retired or they should die prematurely, leaving their young 
children behind.
    By offering--while differing in our approaches, I hope we 
will be able to have a hearing. I keep on plugging for a 
hearing in Plano, Texas, with our distinguished Chairman, but 
anywhere in the country where we will have an opportunity to 
let the Congress work its will. Let the vitality of ideas come 
forward. We both share the same goals, we just have a different 
path of getting there.
    But today's hearing is focused on a problem of record-high 
delays in processing disability applications. This is just 
simply unacceptable, and deplorable, at its very core, of what 
everyday average citizens in this country have to endure. As 
the Chairman pointed out, more than 600 days? It is 
unconscionable.
    Since 2010, the number of beneficiaries, though, has grown 
by 13 percent as baby boomers reach retirement age, and 
especially as we saw after the Great Recession, a number of 
people who lost jobs and are scrambling for their positions. 
Social Security operating budget in this same period of time 
has fallen by more than 10 percent, after accounting for 
inflation. This has made it difficult, if not impossible, for 
Social Security to serve our constituents promptly when they 
need help the most. And that is where I think that money does 
matter, and that money in these budgets, so that we can get the 
front-line people who can handle these.
    We have had many discussions about technology and there has 
been technological advances, but not on the grand scale that we 
need to address this, and nothing on a scale that will assist 
us in a way that that caseworker can--who can deal with an 
individual personally, like what these people are currently 
enduring and suffering through in Houston.
    There are delays throughout the Social Security 
Administration. Today's hearing is focused on the lengthy 
waits, and the Chairman went over this, the administrative law 
judge who can decide on disability benefits appeal. These 
hearings are important. And for the first time, an applicant 
can get to meet face to face with an examiner, in many 
instances, these hearings are the first time the Social 
Security administrator has an applicant's complete medical 
evidence in hand, and the applicant can seek help from an 
attorney or a professional, which is important, given how 
complex the law is in this area.
    But so far this year, the wait, as the Chairman 
underscored, is 600 days. I have several constituents in my 
district, and I am so glad that Ms. Ekman is here today, and we 
are going to get to hear from her. But when you find that 
people are committing suicide; when you find that, in many 
cases, they lose their homes; when you look at what happens to 
them mentally, and I am talking about people that have served 
in our armed services who have post-traumatic stress, who then 
find that their greatest post traumatic stress becomes dealing 
with the Social Security system that is there to help them.
    And so, it is unconscionable that this goes on, and we have 
to solve this problem on behalf of the citizens we are sworn to 
serve, by correcting and making sure that America's primary 
insurance program for its citizens is there to provide them 
relief on a timely basis. I say ``insurance program'' because 
that is what it is. Citizens have contributed to this program. 
They deserve the best, as the Chairman underscored in his 
remarks, from this Committee. I am looking forward to the 
testimony today. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    Chairman JOHNSON. Thank you. As is customary, any Member is 
welcome to submit a statement for the hearing record. And 
before we move on to our testimony today, I want to remind our 
witnesses to please limit your oral statements to 5 minutes. 
However, without objection, all of the written testimony will 
be made part of the hearing record. We have 5 witnesses today, 
and seated at the table are: Bea Disman, Acting Chief of Staff, 
Social Security Administration; Kathryn Larin, Director of 
Education, Workforce, and Income Security Issues, Government 
Accountability Office; Elizabeth McLaren, Bureau Chief, Iowa 
Disability Determination Services, on behalf of the National 
Council of Disability Determination Directors; Marilyn Zahm, 
President, Association of Administrative Law Judges; and Lisa 
Ekman, Director of Government Affairs, National Organization of 
Social Security Claimants' Representatives, on behalf of the 
Social Security Task Force Consortium for Citizens with 
Disabilities.
    Ms. Disman, welcome. Thank you for being here, and please 
proceed.
</option>
    <option>                         ADMINISTRATION
    Ms. DISMAN. Thank you, Chairman. Chairman Johnson and 
Ranking Member Larson, and Members of the Subcommittee, I am 
Bea Disman, Acting Chief of Staff for the Social Security 
Administration. Before I begin, on behalf of the Social 
Security----
    Mr. LARSON. Is your mic on, ma'am?
    Ms. DISMAN. Yes. Before I begin, on behalf of the Social 
Security Administration, our thoughts are with those affected 
by the devastation in Texas and parts of Louisiana by Hurricane 
Harvey. We know Chairman Brady's district in Houston is 
especially affected by the storm, and that districts across 
Texas, like Chairman Johnson's, are providing disaster relief 
services.
    Even though some of our field offices were closed, as Mr. 
Larson said, we were on-site with FEMA over the weekend at 
three sites in Texas, and two in Louisiana, where Social 
Security and Supplemental Security Income beneficiaries could 
request immediate payment in person if they did not receive 
their regular payment. We will continue to be on-site in three 
locations in Texas this whole week. And all but two of our 
field offices in Texas have opened again.
    Thank you for inviting me to discuss how we are taking a 
systematic approach to modernize our disability policies and 
processes. We appreciate the Subcommittee for its ongoing 
oversight of the disability programs and your recommendations. 
With over 50 years of experience at Social Security, I can 
assure you that we are committed to serving the public 
effectively and compassionately, and to preserving the 
integrity of the Social Security programs. We are mission-
focused, mission-driven, in developing disability policy and 
processes.
    The Social Security Act defines disability as the inability 
to engage in any substantial gainful activity due to a 
medically determinable physical or mental impairment that is 
expected to last at least 1 year or result in death. While this 
definition provides the statutory foundation of our Social 
Security disability insurance, and SSI income processes, our 
management of the program is also informed by both technology 
and policy advances.
    Changes in healthcare delivery require us to rethink our 
use of medical source information and its supportability and 
consistency. With that in mind, the policy updates and 
revisions we have recently made establish the foundation for an 
integrated systematic approach to disability decisionmaking. 
For example, we have revised most of our listings of impairment 
criteria. After we finish the updates in fiscal year 2018, we 
will then update the listings on a flow basis using a 3- to 5-
year update cycle. We have the expertise in place to meet this 
objective. We are developing an occupational information system 
that will be the primary source of occupational information 
used in disability adjudication.
    We are committed to providing accurate, high-quality policy 
research in support of this initiative. And we have been 
working with the Bureau of Labor Statistics, which has been 
collecting data for us since 2015. We plan to implement this 
occupational information system in 2020, with the introduction 
of a vocational income tool that adjudicators will use to 
decide claims.
    In January 2016, we developed our plan to improve hearing 
workloads and service delivery. We updated this plan in August 
of 2017 to meet our changing needs. We greatly appreciate the 
$90 million anomaly funding that Congress has provided. The 
plan will permit us to enhance our business efficiencies, such 
as expanding our prehearing conferences. It will also allow us 
to increase our adjudicator capacity by hiring additional ALJs, 
decision writers, and other support staff. The plan also 
supports technological investments in our hearings process, 
such as using natural language processing to improve the 
quality of our decisions.
    The quality of our decisions has always been a paramount 
concern to us. To this end, we are establishing the Office of 
Analytics, Review, and Oversight, which will improve 
coordination on the oversight of the disability adjudication 
process. This new office centralizes all agency offices that 
analyze data in our disability programs and conduct quality 
reviews of our DDS and hearings process.
    We appreciate GAO's work in assessing our Compassionate 
Allowances, or CAL program. CAL delivers faster services by 
making policy compliant benefit decisions quickly to eligible 
individuals with the most serious disabilities. We are working 
to incorporate their recommendation to strengthen the CAL 
program. For example, we have updated our CAL website to be 
more transparent, and to include useful information for 
advocates to submit CAL conditions.
    CAL will be the focus of our November National Disability 
Forum. We are looking forward to holding our outreach meetings 
again, with an eye to improving how we communicate about our 
CAL policies and updates. We are enhancing our internal 
processes as well as developing and updating CAL conditions, 
including the development of enhancements that would give us 
more flexibility to the program.
    Thank you for your interest in discussing disability with 
us. SSA disability programs serve the most vulnerable segments 
of our society. Moving forward, we are and will continue to be 
mission-driven, mission-focused, as we serve the millions of 
individuals who need our help. We look forward to continuing to 
work with you and the Subcommittee.
</option>
    <option>    [GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman JOHNSON. Thank you, ma'am. Ms. Larin, you are 
recognized.
</option>
    <option>  AND INCOME SECURITY ISSUES, GOVERNMENT ACCOUNTABILITY OFFICE
    Ms. LARIN. Chairman Johnson, Ranking Member Larson, and 
Members of the Committee, I am pleased to be here today to 
discuss GAO's report on the Social Security Administration's 
Compassionate Allowance initiative. This initiative, known as 
CAL, expedites the processing of disability claims for those 
with certain conditions, a process that could otherwise take 
months. While CAL has been effective in fast-tracking 
eligibility determinations for some applicants, questions have 
been raised about how the initiative has been implemented. 
Specifically, my remarks today will focus on three issues: how 
SSA identifies conditions for inclusion on the CAL list; how 
claims are designated for expedited processing under CAL; and 
how SSA ensures the accuracy and consistency of CAL decisions.
    First, on identifying conditions for inclusion on the CAL 
list. We found that SSA lacks a formal and systematic approach 
for identifying CAL conditions. Since the CAL initiative began 
in 2008, the number of conditions included has grown from 50 to 
228. Some conditions were added to the original list following 
a series of public hearings. But since 2011, SSA has relied 
primarily on advocates for certain diseases and disorders to 
bring conditions to its attention.
    However, SSA has not provided guidance on its web page on 
how to make suggestions. It has not consistently communicated 
with those who suggested additions about the status of their 
recommendations. And has not conducted outreach efforts to help 
ensure that all advocates are aware of the initiative.
    Relatedly, SSA does not have clear or consistent criteria 
that it uses to determine whether to designate a condition as 
CAL. As a result, SSA may be overlooking conditions that may be 
appropriate for inclusion.
    Turning now to how claims are designated as CAL. We found 
that SSA's procedures do not ensure that all claims are 
accurately identified for CAL processing. SSA relies primarily 
on selection software that uses a word search of the impairment 
description to determine whether the claim refers to a CAL 
condition. But when the text provided by claimants is 
ambiguous, incomplete, or inaccurate, the software won't catch 
the condition as a CAL condition.
    For example, we found that the software accurately flagged 
stage 4 lung cancer as advanced staged lung cancer, a CAL 
condition, but it did not flag a claim where the claimant 
described their condition as lung cancer terminal. Disability 
examiners have the opportunity to ensure that claims are 
correctly designated as CAL, even when the software makes 
errors, by manually changing a flag. But we found that staff 
vary in when or whether they add or remove CAL status from 
disability claims.
    SSA does not have clear guidance on when to change CAL 
designations. And we found that some examiners didn't 
understand the importance of making such changes. For example, 
we found that in 2016, over half of all disability offices did 
not manually add more than a single CAL designation to a claim.
    Finally, on the accuracy and consistency of CAL decisions. 
We found that SSA uses detailed condition descriptions known as 
impairment summaries as a key tool to ensure accurate claims 
decisions. However, these summaries are not regularly updated. 
We found that a third of CAL impairment summaries are more than 
5 years old. Even though medical experts we consulted suggested 
that given advances in medical research, summaries should be 
updated every 1 to 3 years.
    In addition, while SSA collects data on things like denial 
rates for specific conditions and claims processing times, they 
don't leverage this data to inform improvements in the accuracy 
and consistency of CAL claims decisions.
    In conclusion, CAL is viewed positively by SSA and many 
stakeholders, and appears to be effectively expediting the 
processing of disability claims with this designation. However, 
weaknesses in CAL have led to unintended consequences. Absent 
improvements in how they identify CAL conditions, designate CAL 
claims, and ensure the accuracy and consistency of CAL 
decisions, SSA is missing an opportunity to make needed 
improvements to this important initiative.
    This concludes my prepared statement. I am happy to answer 
any questions you may have.
</option>
    <option>    [GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman JOHNSON. Thank you very much. Ms. McLaren, 
welcome. Thank you for being here. You may proceed.
</option>
    <option> IOWA DISABILITY DETERMINATION SERVICES, ON BEHALF OF NATIONAL 
         COUNCIL OF DISABILITY DETERMINATION DIRECTORS
    Ms. MCLAREN. Chairman Johnson, Ranking Member Larson, and 
Members of the Subcommittee, thank you for this opportunity to 
testify on behalf of members of the National Council of 
Disability Determination Directors, or NCDDD, and the State 
administrators of the Disability Determination Services, or 
DDS, across the Nation.
    Currently, we direct the work of over 16,000 employees, 
processing nearly 4.7 million disability cases a year. Today, I 
am here to provide you with the on-the-ground perspectives of 
the DDS community regarding the disability process. NCDDD 
recommends consistent policy application across the Nation. 
Therefore, we support the reinstatement of the reconsideration 
step, or the first appeal of the initial DDS denial to all 
States.
    Introduced in 1999 in 10 States, the prototype pilot 
removes the reconsideration appeal level in State DDS's. In 
these 10 States, the first level of appeal is a hearing with an 
administrative law judge at the Office of Disability 
Adjudication and Review. The President's 2018 budget request 
includes a proposal to reinstate reconsideration in those 10 
States. We believe the reinstatement would help alleviate the 
ODAR backlog.
    Initially, this change would give those State citizens the 
same opportunity to get benefits sooner at less cost. NCDDD has 
previously supported this recommendation during testimony to 
this Committee in 2012. Then and today, we make this 
recommendation with the caveat that sufficient funding and 
additional resources must be included for DDS operations, 
chiefly related to staffing, funding, and infrastructure.
    NCDDD is in favor of continuing refinement of the 
Compassionate Allowance, or CAL initiative, and the associated 
fast-track processes. In fiscal year 2016, the DDS has 
processed over 16,000 CAL-only cases, and nearly 62,000 CAL- 
and QDD-designated cases. While these numbers represent a small 
percentage of the millions of initial claims the DDS's will 
process in a year, NCDDD believes in the CAL process, and we 
believe it should continue to be supported, but with some 
improvement.
    DDS's find that CAL is useful in identifying impairments 
and prioritizing cases that have a high potential for favorable 
determination. However, SSA's software has room for 
improvement, as it sometimes misidentifies cases as CAL, and at 
other times, fails to identify a CAL condition. We suggest 
refinements to the software to correct this issue.
    We also propose that SSA continuously update both the 
condition list and the impairment summaries for CAL. NCDDD is 
concerned about eliminating the use of the disability examiner 
authority for QDD in CAL cases at the end of fiscal year 2018, 
as required by the bipartisan Budget Act of 2015. This 
authority currently allows a disability examiner to make fully 
favorable determinations in certain QDD or CAL cases without 
the approval of a medical consultant.
    The DDS's give this authority to well-trained, seasoned 
adjudicators who can work independently without medical 
consultation. We believe the loss of this disability examiner 
authority will have detrimental impact on DDS operations and 
our service to those applicants who are most in need.
    NCDDD supports and recommends the development of a new 
occupational information system to replace the outdated 
Dictionary of Occupational Titles, or DOT, and its companion 
volumes. In a large percentage of cases, disability 
determinations require assessment of an applicant's ability to 
perform their tasked work.
    The 1991 edition of the DOT is a tool provided to the DDS's 
by SSA. This aged resource is a foundational piece of the 
disability determination process. We understand that SSA has 
been working with the Bureau of Labor Statistics on a solution, 
but the completion date is still years away. The lengthy 
timeline for this change is discouraging to the DDS community, 
as we now have to work through complex issues with outdated 
information and antiquated systems that are not aligned with 
the framework of determining disability. We advocate for haste 
in the development of a new tool.
    In conclusion, NCDDD advocates that we retain and/or 
implement tools and policies that enable the DDS's to continue 
to provide compassionate service to the public with timely, 
cost effective, high-quality disability determinations.
    On behalf of the NCDDD, thank you again for an opportunity 
to testify. I would like to thank our SSA partners for their 
collaboration, and commend the DDS staff across the Nation for 
their exemplary work for the American public. I would be glad 
to answer any questions you have.
</option>
    <option>   [GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman JOHNSON. Thank you. Ms. Zahm, welcome. Thanks for 
being here. You may proceed.
</option>
    <option>            ASSOCIATION OF ADMINISTRATIVE LAW JUDGES
    Judge ZAHM. Thank you. Chairman Johnson, Ranking Member 
Larson and Members of the Subcommittee, thank you for this 
opportunity to address you who have the stewardship of this 
program in your hands. I am Marilyn Zahm, a United States 
Administrative Law Judge for 23 years and elected President of 
the Association of Administrative Law Judges.
    The AALJ represents 1400 Federal administrative law judges 
located in 166 hearing offices across the country. I am 
speaking today on behalf of my judicial colleagues.
    SSA judges have been doing triage work in hearing rooms 
across the country without adequate time, resources, or staff. 
We urge Congress to draft legislation to revitalize the 
adjudicatory system. Each of you has heard stories from your 
constituents, just as we judges hear stories in our courtrooms, 
of the hardship that waiting 2 years for a hearing and decision 
takes on those who appear before us.
    However, there are some practical solutions to the problems 
that we face in the adjudicatory system. I will focus on four 
issues and our solutions: adopt an AALJ's recommended efficient 
adjudication procedures; protect and preserve the independent 
judiciary; provide judges with adequate support staff; and 
provide judges sufficient time to perform their work. I will 
briefly discuss each of these.
    Since 2011, the agency has imposed an estimated 1,000 
changes to its policies and procedures manual, most of which 
are unnecessary, and simply add to the time it takes to hear 
and decide cases. We have proposed a number of solutions to 
make the adjudicatory process more efficient and more 
effective. Streamlined fully favorable templates, which, if 
implemented, could save half a million work hours per year. An 
expedited dismissal process that has the potential to conserve 
400,000 hours annually. Rules of procedure for those who appear 
before us: properly drafted regulations; elimination of the 10 
regional offices for ODAR; and redeployment of their 400 staff 
to the hearings operation.
    The American people are entitled to an impartial 
decisionmaker. The agency, however, continues to push an 
initiative that would disable all statutory protections to 
ensure that Federal agencies cannot improperly influence their 
adjudicators. It seeks to use in-house attorneys over whom it 
exercises control, instead of independent judges to hear and 
decide cases.
    This is not a new initiative. The agency proposed this last 
year, but under pressure from Congress, backed away from the 
proposal. Nevertheless, the agency has again announced this 
plan. There should be a chart appearing on your TV screens, 
which highlights the differences between ALJs and the agencies 
attorney examiners. As you can see, ALJs have decisional 
independence; in-house attorneys do not. They are controlled by 
the agency. If you control the people who make the decisions, 
you can control their decisions.
    The agency's probationary period proposal for newly hired 
ALJs with its argument for a judicial performance plan is also 
a well-worn attempt to eliminate statutory protections for the 
American people. This idea should be unequivocally rejected. We 
Americans deserve an independent judiciary.
    Judges are hamstrung without adequate support staff. Hiring 
freezes and attrition have eroded our clerical and attorney 
writing staffs. In many hearing offices, agency management has 
stripped judges of their assigned clerical support. In order to 
be efficient, judges need to work with the same staff. Each 
judge needs to have one clerical staff member and two attorneys 
assigned to us to work directly with us.
    Each disability case involves a person who is likely to 
desperately need income. Each claim paid has an approximate 
value of $300,000. Judges need to carefully and thoroughly 
evaluate each case, and we need sufficient time to do this job. 
The agency's quota, demanding judges dispose of 500 to 700 
cases annually, was created by dividing the number of pending 
cases by the number of judges several years ago. This means 
that judges have an average of 2.5 hours to fully adjudicate a 
case. That means reviewing the entire file of hundreds of 
medical documents, sometimes thousands; holding a hearing at 
which the claimant and expert witnesses are questioned; 
drafting instructions for a decision and editing that decision; 
2\1/2\ hours.
    Judges who take the time to follow the rules, regulations, 
and policies----
    Chairman JOHNSON. Can you finish pretty quickly because 
your time is up.
    Judge ZAHM. Oh, I am sorry. Thank you for your attention.
</option>
    <option>[GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman JOHNSON. Thank you. Thank you. You know, it is 
hard to quiz a judge. Ms. Ekman, you are recognized.
</option>
    <option>      NATIONAL ORGANIZATION OF SOCIAL SECURITY CLAIMANTS' 
 REPRESENTATIVES, ON BEHALF OF THE SOCIAL SECURITY TASK FORCE 
           CONSORTIUM FOR CITIZENS WITH DISABILITIES
    Ms. EKMAN. Good morning, Chairman Johnson, Ranking Member 
Larson, Members of the Subcommittee. Thank you for the 
opportunity to testify at this hearing. My name is Lisa Ekman, 
and I am the Director of Government Affairs for the National 
Organization of Social Security Claimants' Representatives, or 
NOSSCR.
    I am testifying today on behalf of the co-chairs of the 
Social Security task force of the Consortium for Citizens with 
Disabilities, or CCD. The Social Security disability programs 
provide the modest but vital benefits to millions of people 
with disabilities so severe they are unable to perform 
substantial work, many of whom would live in abject poverty or 
be homeless without them.
    Unfortunately, it took an average of 628 days for people 
who received an eligibility determination from an ALJ during 
the month of July to get access to these vital benefits. That 
wait time, which is far too long, is due, in large part, to 
chronic underfunding of the Social Security Administration's 
administrative budget since 2010. Prior to 2010, Congress 
invested resources in SSA, and SSA had been bringing the wait 
time down. SSA has shown what it can do when it is given 
adequate resources.
    Having to wait that long for a hearing can have devastating 
consequences for an individual and his or her family. Some 
people lose their homes, some declare bankruptcy and some even 
die. Here is one such story. Ms. S was a resident of McKinney, 
Texas, Mr. Chairman. She led a comfortable life, a middle-class 
life while working as a property manager and inspector. 
However, she developed a number of conditions, including 
chronic pain syndrome, fibromyalgia, cervical spondylosis, 
thoracic and lumbar spine pain, migraine headaches, 
intracranial hypotension, and fibromuscular dysplasia. This was 
followed by ever-increasing depression and anxiety, especially 
after she could no longer work.
    She tried every treatment doctors offered to reduce her 
pain and allow her to continue working, but by 2009, she just 
could not work anymore. She waited a long time for her hearing, 
which was finally scheduled in January of 2016, but she faced a 
terrible choice: miss an appointment for a test that might 
identify treatment to alleviate her pain that took months to 
schedule or postpone her hearing.
    The hearing was postponed and rescheduled for April 2016, 
but unfortunately, Ms. S committed suicide several weeks before 
her hearing. She was 45 years old. She received a posthumous 
fully favorable decision, and her 15-year-old son now receives 
survivor's benefits.
    My written testimony contains many other stories from--
collected from claimants' representatives from all over the 
United States which highlight the hardship and debt pain 
inflicted on individuals with disabilities when they are forced 
to wait months, or even years, for a hearing on their claim. 
And these heartbreaking stories are, unfortunately, becoming 
more commonplace.
    During fiscal year 2016, 8700 people died waiting for a 
hearing for an ALJ. That is nearly one every hour. The hearing 
backlog must be addressed. The Social Security task force 
respectfully recommends the following actions for Congress and 
SSA to consider:
    Congress should provide SSA with adequate funding to 
administer the Social Security Old Age Survivors and Disability 
programs. Only sustained, adequate funding, will allow SSA to 
reduce the time it takes to get a disability determination from 
an ALJ without negatively impacting customer service in its 
other core functions.
    The task force appreciates the backlog reduction efforts 
that SSA is making within the inadequate budget it receives. 
And the CARES Plan obtained some promising initiatives, but 
more should be done to assist the nearly 1.1 million people 
facing this daunting wait.
    SSA should work to ensure that a hearing is only held when 
necessary. And so first, SSA should do a better job of 
collecting full medical evidence at the initial application and 
reconsideration levels to ensure the decision is made on as 
complete and evidentiary record as possible.
    Second, SSA should resume a robust program of reviewing 
claims for on-the-record decisions, cases where recent evidence 
clearly shows eligibility without requiring a hearing. I 
understand that this is part of the CARES Plan, but the 
attorneys who would conduct these reviews are not doing them 
because they have been pulled into addressing another horrible 
backlog, and that is, the writing of decisions after a hearing 
is held. This is yet another example of the consequences of 
inadequate funding and trying to shift things around to make it 
work within the budget that they have.
    Third, Congress can assist to get the decision right the 
first time by facilitating reviews of more DDS denials, to 
ensure that these decisions are correct and prevent the need 
for an appeal. SSA should be permitted to use its dedicated 
program integrity funds to conduct these reviews, and they 
should increase the number of reviews.
    Finally, SSA should consider revising some recently or 
finalized regulations the task force believes will harm 
applicants who are otherwise eligible for benefits and leads to 
increased appeals, including the Federal court.
    One controversial rule regards the evaluation of medical 
evidence. The relationship between a person and their treating 
provider is unique, and opinions of treating providers deserve 
more weight than the opinion of someone who examines an 
individual once or reviews the claims file. The elimination of 
the treating physician rule is likely to lead to more appeals, 
more remands, and more delays as a result.
    Thank you again for the opportunity to testify today, and I 
am happy to answer any questions you might have.
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
</Hearing>
