<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="27466">
    <intro>    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <Doc-title>INVESTING IN SMALL BUSINESSES: THE SBIC PROGRAM</Doc-title>
    <option>=======================================================================
                                HEARING
                               BEFORE THE
</option>
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON AGRICULTURE, ENERGY, AND TRADE</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                                 OF THE
</option>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON SMALL BUSINESS</committee_name>
    <option>                             UNITED STATES
                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                            NOVEMBER 7, 2017
                               __________
[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]                               
            Small Business Committee Document Number 115-046
              Available via the GPO Website: www.fdsys.gov
                               __________
                    U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE                    
27-466 PDF                  WASHINGTON : 2018                     
----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing Office, 
http://bookstore.gpo.gov. For more information, contact the GPO Customer Contact Center, 
U.S. Government Publishing Office. Phone 202-512-1800, or 866-512-1800 (toll-free). 
E-mail, gpo@custhelp.com.                   
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <committeeComposition>
    <comitteeM_name>HOUSE COMMITTEE ON SMALL BUSINESS</comitteeM_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEVE CHABOT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEVE KING</Pname>
        <Plocation> Iowa</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BLAINE LUETKEMEYER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Missouri</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DAVE BRAT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>AUMUA AMATA COLEMAN RADEWAGEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> American Samoa</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEVE KNIGHT</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TRENT KELLY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Mississippi</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROD BLUM</Pname>
        <Plocation> Iowa</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JAMES COMER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Kentucky</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JENNIFFER GONZALEZ-COLON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Puerto Rico</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DON BACON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nebraska</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRIAN FITZPATRICK</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROGER MARSHALL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Kansas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RALPH NORMAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> South Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>NYDIA VELAZQUEZ</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ranking Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DWIGHT EVANS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEPHANIE MURPHY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>AL LAWSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>YVETTE CLARK</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JUDY CHU</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ALMA ADAMS</Pname>
        <Plocation> North Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ADRIANO ESPAILLAT</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRAD SCHNEIDER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>VACANT</Pname>
        <Plocation>VACANT</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Kevin Fitzpatrick</Pname>
        <Plocation> Majority Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jan Oliver</Pname>
        <Plocation> Majority Deputy Staff Director and Chief Counsel</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Adam Minehardt</Pname>
        <Plocation> Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
</committeeComposition>
    <Directory>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <Speakers>OPENING STATEMENTS</Speakers>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <Witness>Mr Brett Palmer</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>President Small Business Investor Alliance Washington</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mr Michael Painter</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Managing Partner Plexus Capital Raleigh</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mr Mark L Walsh</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Managing Director Ruxton Ventures Chevy Chase</peopleinfo>
    <option>APPENDIX</option>
    <Speakers>Prepared Statements:</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>Mr Brett Palmer</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>President Small Business Investor Alliance Washington</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker>Mr Thies Kolln</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Partner Aavin Private Equity Cedar Rapids</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker>Mr Michael Painter</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Managing Partner Plexus Capital Raleigh</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker>Mr Mark L Walsh</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Managing Director Ruxton Ventures Chevy Chase</peopleinfo>
    <submittedMaterial>Additional Material for the Record:</submittedMaterial>
    <Doc-title>INVESTING IN SMALL BUSINESSES: THE SBIC PROGRAM</Doc-title>
    <overview>Subcommittee on Agriculture, Energy, and Trade,</overview>
    <paragraph paraId="0" speaker="">Bacon, Schneider, and Lawson.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Good morning. Thank you all for being here
with us today. I call this hearing to order.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Despite a downward trending unemployment rate and 
increasing signs of business optimism, small firms continue to 
face a rigid lending environment. Capital for the nation's 
small businesses, entrepreneurs, and startups is the difference 
between a Main Street company in my home State of Iowa turning 
on their lights or closing up operations for good. It could be 
the difference between making payroll and letting a great 
employee go. And I have been there and had to do that, so truer 
words cannot be spoken.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Chairman BLUM">While large companies finance their projects through debt 
and equity markets, small companies regularly utilize 
traditional bank lending to finance their endeavors. As a way 
to inject more equity into the small business ecosystem to 
address the gap in long-term financing, the SBA created the 
Small Business Investment Company program, also known as the 
SBIC program, in 1958.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Chairman BLUM">SBICs are for-profit entities that manage investment funds, 
but are licensed and regulated by the SBA. Through this unique 
structure, investors apply to receive an SBIC license which 
provides the ability to leverage private dollars with federal 
dollars for investments in high-growth small businesses.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Chairman BLUM">This program is what we are here to talk about today.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Chairman BLUM">This Committee has actively been studying the SBIC program 
for years. We examined two SBIC bills in the spring, one 
looking at the individual leverage limit and a second that 
looked at the threshold level in which a financial institution 
can invest in the SBIC. This program continues to be a topic of 
interest for this Committee.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Today, we will hear from SBIC participants that can share 
with us how this program is operating on the ground and how it 
impacts communities around the nation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Chairman BLUM">I am looking forward to hearing more about the role SBA 
plays in this program as well. From the issuance of leverage to 
the licensing process, it is important to know how SBA 
interacts with the SBICs.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Like many of SBA's financial programs, where the federal 
government has a role, robust and thorough Congressional 
oversight is required to ensure taxpayer money is safeguarded 
and protected. This Committee strives to create an environment 
where small businesses can flourish, and this program fits into 
that formula.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Chairman BLUM">I appreciate all of the witnesses being here today. I look 
forward to your testimony.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Chairman BLUM">    And I now yield to Ranking Member Schneider for his opening 
remarks.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. SCHNEIDER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">Thank you, Chairman Blum. Thank you for
calling this hearing. And I want to thank the witnesses for 
joining us today.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">Access to capital is essential for every business, but 
especially for smaller ones. Without it, most firms cannot make 
improvements, expand, or hire qualified works that they need to 
succeed.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">In 1958, Congress recognized the gap in the financial 
markets for long-term funding for growth-oriented small 
businesses and created the Small Business Investment Company 
Program. SBICs are privately owned and managed investment 
funds, licensed by the SBA, that use their own capital plus SBA 
guaranteed funds to make investments in small businesses.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">The SBIC program helps fill the gap in the capital markets 
for businesses that have outgrown the SBA's flagship 7(a) loan 
guarantee program but remain too small or high risk for the 
private equity industry.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">The key to the program's success is leveraging federal 
funds to expand the amount of private capital invested in 
promising small firms.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">SBA provides funding to qualified SBICs with expertise in 
certain sectors of the economy. SBICs then use their own funds 
and leverage from SBA to invest in these small businesses. 
Their actions have facilitated over 3 million jobs total and 
nearly $6 billion per year of investment in domestic small 
employers. To date, small business investment companies have 
assisted thousands of high-growth businesses, providing over 
$100 billion in capital.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">In this Congress, the House passed two pieces of 
legislation from this Committee that expand the SBIC program. 
The Small Business Investment Opportunity Act of 2017 increases 
the cap for the SBIC that manages just one company from $150 
million to $175 million. And the Investing in Main Street Act 
of 2017 increases the percentage of capital and surplus banks 
and federal and savings associations can invest in an SBIC. 
Both measures seek to increase the flow of much-needed capital 
to small businesses.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">Despite these efforts, more work needs to be done, in 
particular to diversify the program. Greater access for women 
and minority-owned funds would, in turn, increase the dollars 
flowing to women and minority-owned small businesses. 
Similarly, additional efforts to invest in rural small 
businesses could spur economic growth in these areas.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">During today's hearing, I look forward to hearing from our 
witnesses on how we facilitate investment in our nation's 
entrepreneurs and small businesses. And I thank them in advance 
for their testimony.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="21" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">    Thank you, and I yield back.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="22" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Thank you, Mr. Schneider.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="23" speaker="Chairman BLUM">I would like to explain the timing. You may all be aware of 
how the lights work, but if not, I would like to take a second 
to explain that.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="24" speaker="Chairman BLUM">You will have 5 minutes to deliver your testimony. The 
light will start out as green. When you have 1 minute 
remaining, the light will turn yellow. Finally, at the end of 5 
minutes, it will turn red. And I ask that you try to adhere to 
that time limit.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="25" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Also, if Committee members have an opening statement 
prepared, I ask that they be submitted for the record.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="26" speaker="Chairman BLUM">And now I would like to introduce our distinguished 
panelists there.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="27" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Our first witness is Brett Palmer. Mr. Palmer is the 
President of the Small Businesses Investor Alliance, also known 
as SBIA, an association that has a focus on the SBIC programs.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="28" speaker="Chairman BLUM">We need a few more acronyms here, don't we?</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="29" speaker="Chairman BLUM">With over 9 years at SBIA, Mr. Palmer is well-versed in the 
intricacies of the program. His previous experience includes 
time on Capitol Hill and at the U.S. Department of Commerce.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="30" speaker="Chairman BLUM">I appreciate you being here with us today.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="31" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Our next witness is Thies Kolln. Mr. Kolln is a Partner at 
AAVIN Private Equity in my home district of Cedar Rapids, Iowa.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="32" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Go Hawks.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="33" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Mr. Kolln has spent approximately 15 years at AAVIN, which 
focuses on late-stage and expansion-stage financing. Prior to 
AAVIN, Mr. Kolln spent time working for the Boston Consulting 
Group in Chicago and on the startup management team at Orbitz. 
He has also practiced corporate law at Kirkland &amp;amp; Ellis in 
Chicago.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="34" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Thank you for joining us today. It is always great to hear 
the perspective of a fellow Iowan.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="35" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Our next witness is Michael Painter. Mr. Painter is 
Cofounder and the Managing Partner at Plexus Capital in 
Raleigh, North Carolina, where they focus on middle market 
business. Prior to cofounding Plexus Capital, he worked for RBC 
Bank and investment firms in both New York and North Carolina.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="36" speaker="Chairman BLUM">It is a pleasure to have you with us today, Mr. Painter.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="37" speaker="Chairman BLUM">    And I yield now to Ranking Member Schneider to introduce 
the remaining witness.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. SCHNEIDER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="38" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">Thank you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="39" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">It is my honor to introduce Mr. Mark Walsh, the Managing 
Director of Ruxton Ventures here in Washington, a Washington-
based private equity firm that invests in technology, media, 
and education companies.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="40" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">Prior to this position, Mr. Walsh served as SBA Associate 
Administrator for the Office of Investment and Innovation. In 
this role, he oversaw all SBIC, SBIR, Accelerator, Incubator, 
and other growth activities at SBA and was appointed to key 
committees at the Securities and Exchange Commission and 
Department of the Treasury.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="41" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">Before his government service, he had a 30-year career in 
technology, media, venture capital, and angel investing. Mr. 
Walsh is a graduate of Union College and received his MBA from 
Harvard.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="42" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">    Welcome, Mr. Walsh.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="43" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Thank you, Mr. Schneider.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="44" speaker="Chairman BLUM">I appreciate all of our witnesses being here today.</paragraph>
</Directory>
    <Statement>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF BRETT PALMER</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="BRETT PALMER">    Mr. Palmer, you are recognized for 5 minutes. You may 
begin.
   STATEMENTS OF MR. BRETT PALMER, PRESIDENT, SMALL BUSINESS 
 INVESTOR ALLIANCE, WASHINGTON, DC; MR. THIES KOLLN, PARTNER, 
 AAVIN PRIVATE EQUITY, CEDAR RAPIDS, IA; MR. MICHAEL PAINTER, 
MANAGING PARTNER, PLEXUS CAPITAL, RALEIGH, NC; AND MR. MARK L. 
   WALSH, MANAGING DIRECTOR, RUXTON VENTURES, CHEVY CHASE, MD
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. PALMER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. PALMER">Thank you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. PALMER">My name is Brett Palmer. I am president of the Small 
Business Investor Alliance. I would like to thank the chairman, 
Ranking Member Schneider, and Congressman Lawson for being here 
today, and the rest of the members of the Subcommittee and the 
staff. Thank you for giving us the opportunity to share what we 
know about the SBIC program and small business investing and to 
answer your questions about it.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. PALMER">The SBIA is a trade association of small business investors 
that includes the SBIC industry. The goal of the SBIA is to 
promote a healthy ecosystem system for small business 
investing, one that benefits both small businesses and their 
investors and thereby promoting economic growth and job 
creation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. PALMER">Small business investment companies have been around since 
1958, and what was true in the 1950s will always be true: Small 
businesses need external, patient capital to grow and thrive 
and it is really hard to access that type of capital.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. PALMER">Debenture and non-levered SBICs have increased the amount 
of small business investment capital, with almost $6 billion 
invested in fiscal year 2016, the last year of which we have 
full data. All SBIC investments must be used for domestic small 
businesses with at least 25 percent going to even smaller 
enterprises.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. PALMER">SBICs invest across a broad range of industries and across 
a broad range of geographies. And actually I think Congressman 
Lawson's district runs from the northern part of Florida, and 
Mr. Kolln here actually, I think, is looking at an investment 
that would connect that corridor from Tallahassee to 
Jacksonville.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. PALMER">I will let you talk about that.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. PALMER">It is common to see investments in manufacturing in low and 
moderate income areas via SBICs. And this industry and 
geographic spread is important, because SBICs are often the 
first institutional capital into small businesses, which 
benefit from their capital but also from their professional 
help in scaling up their business, professionalizing 
themselves, and building up boards.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. PALMER">The program is having the best and lowest loss rate in its 
59-year history, which is important, because taxpayer 
protection is the highest priority for the SBIC industry. There 
is currently unprecedented private sector interest in getting 
capital into small businesses via SBIC funds, and the private 
sector is the leading critical component to making the program 
work effectively. It is a market-driven program.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. PALMER">A recent Library of Congress study found that SBIC-backed 
businesses created 3 million new jobs over the course of their 
study and 6.5 million jobs. That is a period that included the 
Great Recession and the tech bubble busting.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. PALMER">The study was performed with researchers from Duke's and 
Pepperdine's business school and they found that debenture-
backed SBICs created, on average, about 125 new jobs and non-
levered, more equity-oriented SBIC investors created over 530 
new jobs per small business receiving investment, which is 
pretty big numbers. Those are not uniform across every small 
business but the average.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. PALMER">Between these two types of investments, over 7 percent of 
net new jobs in the United States came from SBIC-backed 
businesses. That is an extraordinary number for a little known 
program, but that is what the program is supposed to do.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. PALMER">These quiet successes were achieved while the debenture 
program was one of the only major SBA programs that was able to 
maintain a zero subsidy rate, which matters. Again, this covers 
the period of the Great Recession and the tech bubble bursting 
for the debenture program. And with the help of Congress and 
the SBA, there has been significant operation reforms made over 
the past 8 years or so and have been producing the positive 
results that you have sought.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. PALMER">With this program having a great track record, there are 
always areas for improvement that could be made both by the 
private sector, on our side, as well from the government, 
because there are many more communities that would benefit from 
having access to this type of capital. With private capital 
investment at record highs, we would like to see that spread 
across more of the country, to more communities, to more 
businesses, across more sectors, because there has been good 
stuff that has occurred, but more certainly can and should be 
done.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. PALMER">And with that, I would like to take a moment to thank the 
Committee for passing those two bills that were mentioned 
before. They are simple, commonsense bills that will help get 
more capital out there to these worthy small businesses.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. PALMER">    And with that, thank you for your time.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Thank you, Mr. Palmer.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF THIES KOLLN</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="THIES KOLLN">    Mr. Kolln, you are recognized for 5 minutes.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. KOLLN</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">Thank you. Thank you, Chairman Blum, Ranking
Member Schneider, and Member Lawson, for the opportunity to 
testify here today and for holding this hearing.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">Access to capital is a tremendously important issue for 
small businesses across the country, and the SBIC program 
effectively helps to resolve that issue. I am eager to provide 
you with my perspective as an SBIC fund manager and also a past 
member of the SBIA board.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">My name is Thies Kolln, and I am a partner of AAVIN Private 
Equity, a private equity firm based in the heart of the 
Midwest. Our central office is in Cedar Rapids, Iowa. We have, 
at the time, two regional offices, in Madison, Wisconsin, and 
in Kansas City, and cover our Midwest footprint through those. 
I joined AAVIN in 2002, so I have been there for 15 years now, 
and it was a return to my home city of Cedar Rapids.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">At AAVIN we stay true to our roots by focusing on helping 
small regionally based businesses grow. We specialize in late-
stage and expansion-stage financings, and we partner with 
strong management teams that seek long-term business growth. 
Our focus is on smaller investment opportunities, and they are 
concentrated mostly in the upper Midwest States, such as Iowa 
and surrounding States, although we do invest nationally.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">And as Brett mentioned, we have one company now that we 
invested in about a year ago THAT is based in Jacksonville and 
recently acquired another company to help it expand into 
Tallahassee. So we are covering the northern Florida market 
with that. It is a company that does precast concrete for road 
expansions and culverts and wastewater management mainly.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">We have extensive private equity experience. There are 
seven members of our investment team. We have made investments 
in over 300 companies throughout our careers. Through our 
firm's history, just in Iowa, we have helped deploy $34 million 
in capital that helped create or sustain over 6,000 jobs. Those 
numbers may not mean a lot in a place like Manhattan, but they 
do for Iowa. These investments produce great growth for small 
businesses, as well as returns for our investment partners, 
which includes repayment in full to SBA and the American 
taxpayer.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">I have got some more detail in my written testimony, but I 
will outline a little bit about the SBIC program. It has a 
rigorous licensing process for prospective funds, which ensures 
taxpayer protection and safeguards the program's reputation. 
One requirement for licensing is that management teams have 
extensive prior investment experience and good investment track 
records.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">We meet that demand. Our firm's experience dates back to 
the start of the SBIC program in 1959, and we have basically 
over 40 years of continuous SBIC management experience in our 
firm.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">Repeat licensing like this is a good thing as it 
demonstrates to prospective small business partners our 
previous fund successes, our commitment to serving this 
undercapitalized market, and demonstrates to the taxpayer that 
we are good stewards of tax dollars. We have a history of on-
time payments to SBA and overall compliance, with clean 
examinations without findings.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">We strongly support the SBIC program because it provides 
the opportunities to supplement our capital with up to two 
times more capital to deploy to small businesses to support 
their growth.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">Given the increase in concentration of capital among large 
funds and institutions, it is difficult to find capital with a 
dedicated strategy of investing in small businesses and in 
small funds. And it is questionable whether many of the small 
funds like AAVIN could even continue to fund small businesses 
if it were not for the SBIC program.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">We are often the first providers of institutional capital 
into small businesses. We help professionalize small businesses 
and make sure they have fundamentally solid operations and 
partner with strong management teams to do so.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">I will give a little bit of a history or a little bit of 
some stories about some of our investments. We have made over 
26 investments in Iowa. Our most recent was just completed last 
month in Happy Joe's Pizza &amp;amp; Ice Cream.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">    I am sure you are familiar with that, Mr. Blum.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Chairman BLUM"> Absolutely.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. KOLLN</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. KOLLN"> It is a family-run pizza parlor chain that was
founded in 1972. It has 54 locations across Iowa and other 
Midwestern States. We have already hired additional people to 
help it on a growth strategy and are right now looking at 
additional locations to grow out the operations.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Chairman BLUM"> [Inaudible]
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. KOLLN</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">He is still involved in it, yes. He is part of
the management team now. Well, Joe is retired. His son Larry is 
still involved.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">So that is just an example of our investing in Iowa. And 
without the SBIC program we would not have had our successful 
history of deploying growth capital to American small business. 
The SBIC program has effectively helped us leverage our private 
capital that we are able to raise and invest in small 
businesses.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="21" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">    Thank you for holding this hearing. And I encourage the 
Committee and this Congress to continue to fully support the 
program so it may expand, support more domestic small 
businesses, and create even more American jobs. I look forward 
to answering any questions you may have.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="22" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Thank you, Mr. Kolln. Let the record reflect
that Happy Joe's Pizza has some pretty darn good taco pizza. 
Love it.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF MICHAEL PAINTER</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="MICHAEL PAINTER">    Mr. Painter, you are now recognized for 5 minutes.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. PAINTER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">Thank you, Chairman Blum, Ranking Member
Schneider, and Mr. Lawson for having us here today.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">So I have been involved in the SBIC program for over 20 
years. My partners and I used to work at a small regional bank 
in North Carolina called Centura Bank, and we had a fund that 
served to provide the growth capital that went beyond what the 
traditional bank could provide. And in 2004 we have been out on 
our own and formed our first independent SBIC, and we have now 
invested in 87 companies that employ collectively thousands of 
people.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">So we have made a big impact, and we are one example of 
many SBIC managers across the country who are making similar 
impacts.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">My message today is really about three things. One, this is 
the most impactful and best example of a public-private 
partnership that I know of. Second, it is a program that 
supports a perpetually underserved area of the market. And 
third, it is impacting real lives. It is easy to talk about our 
program and our business in numbers and returns. It is 
ultimately about real people, real companies, real communities, 
and impacting lives and families.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">As far as a program, public-private partnership that makes 
sense, I think the key here that I know you all understand, but 
I hope more people on the Committee and in Congress understand, 
is that all of the dollars that we raise from the private 
markets are at risk first, ahead of any Federal guarantees. 
That is a critical part of the program and why it has been so 
successful.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">So in our case, we have 56 banks, 130 individuals, 18 
family offices, and 9 institutions that have invested $475 
million with us. That all is there protecting Federal 
guarantees. So our dollars would be lost first, before the 
Federal guarantees would be hit. So that is a big 
differentiator in the public-private partnership world.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">I also think you have a staff that has been there for a 
long time that is driven by the purpose of the program. They 
are motivated by the purpose and the impact of the program, 
which is measurable and meaningful. And we have 50 years-plus 
of success in this program. So I don't know of any other 
public-private partnership that has had that level of success.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">We also support a perpetually underserved area of the 
market. There are over 100,000 small businesses in the United 
States that have $10-$100 million in sales. Roughly half of 
those are owned by somebody over the age of 40.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">So you have this big portion of the market, roughly $2 
trillion of value, that has to transition to the next 
generation of owner-operators. Public companies have ready 
access to the public markets to effect those transitions each 
and every day. The private markets don't have that luxury, 
particularly at the small end of the market.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">I have been in this market for 20-plus years. It is 
perpetually underserved. You have fund managers that come into 
our market, they have success, and they go up market, because 
it is easier to do 10 deals and grow by doing 10 bigger deals 
than it is to do 10 deals, then 20 deals. It takes a lot of 
fixed cost. We look at 100 opportunities to invest in 1.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">So to really provide capital to small businesses, you have 
to be committed to building a real business and putting 
infrastructure in place, and that is not possible without the 
SBA program.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">And back to the real driver of this. We do impact real 
lives. And I think telling stories about those lives is a good 
way to visualize it for me. We have got a company, design shop, 
in Orlando, Florida. This is Doug and Sherri Hughes, husband 
and wife, started this company in 2000, and they serve the 
trade show market. So they help companies prepare the materials 
they need for trade shows and they now employ 50 people.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">So husband and wife, 2000, start a business that now 
employs 50 people, impacting their families, not just those 50 
people, and their community.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">Another example is Huseby in Charlotte, started by Scott 
Huseby. He is a third-generation court reporter, comes from a 
long line of court reporters. Saw a need to professionalize 
this industry. He now employees 50 people at Huseby, and, more 
importantly, he engages with over 1,800 court reporters across 
the country to provide a steadier flow of business to people 
all over the country.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">So I look forward to taking questions about the program. I 
care a lot about the program and about the purpose. It is an 
impactful program. And I think the more stories that get out 
there about the people behind it, the more support there will 
be for it.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">    Thank you for having us.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Thank you, Mr. Painter.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF MARK L. WALSH</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="MARK L. WALSH">    I now recognize Mr. Walsh, a former venture capitalist, for 
5 minutes.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. WALSH</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. WALSH">Thank you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. WALSH">Good morning. My name is Mark Walsh. And from late 2015 
until January 19 of this year, I ran the Office of Investment 
and Innovation, OII, or as we call it, Oy, at the SBA here in 
Washington, D.C. My area oversaw, as was said, all SBIC, SBIR, 
and Incubator, Accelerator programs. It was my first job in 
government.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. WALSH">Before that, for 35 years or more, I had a career in 
technology, the internet, and media with senior or C-Suite 
positions at a wide variety of companies, including America 
Online, GE, HBO, VerticalNet, and more.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. WALSH">For the last 17 years, I have been an active angel investor 
and venture investor for a wide variety of startups and have 
served on the board of directors for many of those companies 
and other high-growth venture-backed entities. I have also 
served as chairman of the Bipartisan Policy Center here in 
Washington, D.C., the best think tank in town, in my personal 
opinion.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. WALSH">The SBIC program is one of the most innovative, financially 
successful, and well-structured government programs in 
existence, period, close quote. But I left the program almost 
10 months ago, and some recollections and remembrances are 
dimmed by time. Also, my opinions are my own and are not meant 
to reflect anyone else's or any other agenda.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. WALSH">As was said, the SBIC program takes low-interest debt and 
provides it to professionally managed domestic venture capital 
and private equity funds. These funds need an SBIC license to 
get the investment.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. WALSH">The license application and approval process is super 
rigorous and helps avoid mismanaged or ill-targeted funds from 
receiving taxpayer dollars.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. WALSH">Further, a licensee reports all significant investment 
activities to the OII on a regular quarterly basis, and there 
are annual on-site inspections by OII trained teammates.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. WALSH">In short, OII is as vigilant an investor as any in the 
private market, if not more so. However, as we all know, 
investment entails risk, so OII also has a trained team of 
workout experts who help funds that ran array of financial 
health and, in some cases, assumed ownership and control of 
failed funds and disposed of the assets at admirable salvage 
valuations. But make no mistake: The amount of unrecoverable 
investment was minuscule and was the envy of the private 
sector.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. WALSH">The SBIC program is a fabulous example of a public-private 
partnership, as was mentioned by my colleagues. My colleagues 
in the organization and teammates were as motivated, talented, 
and professional as any I have worked with in my private sector 
career. Some of them are here today. And I enjoyed my all-too-
short stint immensely.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. WALSH">But I was asked here to address some ways to improve the 
SBIC program. Nothing is perfect, and there are a few areas I 
would like to address if I were still in charge.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. WALSH">Number one, outreach. We made extraordinary progress during 
my time in discovering new funds and new types of funds and in 
meeting and engaging more diverse fund managers--gender, 
demographic, geographic, and market-focused diversity--more 
than prior efforts. This happened because my teammates and I 
made it a priority, and I would encourage the Committee to make 
sure the program pursues that with vigor.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. WALSH">Second, promote and award certain types of funds. Impact 
funds, which are aimed at social, environmental, educational, 
or institutional improvement, as opposed to pure profit, are 
important. The program should be more able to encourage impact 
funds with lower interest rates, more attractive payback 
options, or even faster application processing.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. WALSH">And speaking of that, number three, streamlining the 
license process. I am sure you guys would agree that. The 
amount of paperwork expected of a license applicant and license 
holder is heavy. OII and the program should continue their 
efforts to use available technologies to streamline these 
processes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. WALSH">Fourth, equity ownership. OII should have the ability to 
receive a small amount of equity in the companies its capital 
invest in. SBICs have held debt stakes in many iconic 
companies. For instance, an SBIC in 1977 held over 4 percent 
ownership in a small technology company called Apple. Imagine 
if we had that 4 percent ownership stake today. OII should 
continue efforts to create ownership upside for American 
taxpayers through this program with equity ownership.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. WALSH">Fifth, more private sector partnerships. During my stint, 
teammates and I created a wonderful board diversity initiative 
called ONBoard, the Open Network for Board Diversity, with a 
partner, LinkedIn, the professional social network. There are 
many innovative private sector companies who would be partners 
in new opportunities that OII should be freer to pursue.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Mr. WALSH">And, lastly, networking opportunities between funds and 
companies. OII is a natural clearinghouse for a wide variety of 
data it collects about its funds and the companies that it 
invests in, as you heard from my colleagues to my left. It 
should have, in my opinion, more open access to the data for 
industry observers, companies, funds, and analysts.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. WALSH">To conclude, there are improvements and opportunities that 
I could detail beyond that, but these are some that I saw that 
had great potential when I was at the agency.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. WALSH">And lastly, let me also mention the SBIA, or Small Business 
Investor Alliance. They are the industry association focused on 
the SBIC marketplace, as you heard Brett Palmer, their CEO, 
testify a moment ago. Their staff, management, members, and 
board were very helpful to me as I learned the program, and 
they were great partners for our initiatives. I can't thank 
them enough for their productive role in the ongoing success of 
the SBIC program.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="21" speaker="Mr. WALSH">    Thank you for inviting me today. And now I and my 
colleagues are ready to help with any questions and comments 
you may have.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="22" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Thank you, Mr. Walsh.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="23" speaker="Chairman BLUM">    Due to Ranking Member Schneider's tight time schedule, I 
will reserve my time until the end. And I will now recognize 
Mr. Schneider for 5 minutes of questions.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. SCHNEIDER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="24" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">Thank you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="25" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">And, again, I want to thank all of the witnesses for being 
here and sharing your experience and your perspectives on a 
program that clearly is making a difference in communities 
across the country, in particular in the heartland, and we need 
to continue to do that.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="26" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">    I just want to take the opportunity to touch on one issue. 
I think one added value of the SBIC program is the leverage it 
provides, the ability to work with public-private partnership. 
But I know from experience, I know from your submitted 
testimony, that there are many other added-value aspects to 
this. For example, the involvement of the SBIC lenders with the 
portfolio companies. I would like to open it up and have you 
touch on some of those additional benefits that are provided to 
your portfolio companies.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. PALMER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="27" speaker="Mr. PALMER">Let me start.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="28" speaker="Mr. PALMER">It is important, because this isn't just money. You are 
getting actual expertise. And I hear it all time from our 
members. We actually have recently partnered with Ohio State, 
their business school. There is something called the National 
Center for the Middle Market that GE Capital funded to train 
their portfolio companies. Well, GE Capital got broken up and 
went six ways to Sunday around the world. It got complicated. 
But they still had this training platform there.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="29" speaker="Mr. PALMER">    We have now partnered with Ohio State, and actually today 
one of these trainings sessions is going on, where portfolio 
companies of SBICs are able to attend, and it is a platform for 
training them how to scale up their business, how to attract 
talent, how to retain talent, how to really grow their business 
and scale up in a professional, organized way. And that is 
something that we are doing and in a really concise, organized, 
dedicated feature just for SBIC-backed businesses. And that is 
going well. That is one example of one of the things that we 
are doing.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. PAINTER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="30" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">I think that is a really important example.
The small businesses we invest in, they don't need to invent 
new strategy. I mean, they know how to run their business, they 
know how to manufacture their product or deliver their service.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="31" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">What they haven't done before is scale that business. So 
they need tools to learn how to do that. It is basic stuff, 
basic blocking and tackling. We actually have four of our 
operating company professionals at the Ohio State event this 
week, and we have two of our internal people there so that we 
can help learn ourselves better how to train our other 
companies.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="32" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">And that is one thing we are focused on, is we have right 
now one full-time operating partner, so somebody who has run a 
small business that is now working with four of our companies 
to help them with their growth and putting in the frameworks 
that are needed to help grow a business. And we are committed 
to growing that platform.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="33" speaker="Mr. PAINTER">    That is a key point, that it is not money. The money is 
important. That is the driver of us coming in. But we also have 
to provide more value than just dollars to make an impact.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. SCHNEIDER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="34" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER"> Mr. Kolln.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. KOLLN</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="35" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">And we are, as a small fund, and even by SBIC
standards a small fund, we are almost always the first 
institutional capital, the first, other than family money, that 
has been in the businesses that we invest in. Sometimes they 
have never even had a bank loan before.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="36" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">    So it really is the first kind of outside capital, outside 
advisors, outside board members that they take on in these 
businesses, and it is a big step toward professionalizing them. 
And one of the key things we do is help them add the management 
talent and complete the management team that is there to help 
run and grow the business.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. SCHNEIDER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="37" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER"> Mr. Walsh, as you go, as you give your
answer, also touch on how to try to expand the outreach to more 
minorities and women-owned businesses.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. WALSH</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="38" speaker="Mr. WALSH">Fair enough. If I just might say, if you read
the press, it seems like all this money is going to, like, hip 
companies in Silicon Valley and for the next Snapchat or 
whatever. But, in fact, the gentlemen to my left and the men 
and women who work with them are on the front line of 
entrepreneurship. These are first-time investors in the lunch 
bucket companies that make this Nation great. These are 
companies that aren't that sexy in many cases, but they are the 
people and the places that employ people sustainably. So that 
is my answer to the first part.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="39" speaker="Mr. WALSH">To the second part of your question, it really ended up 
being just going out there and shaking the tin cup. I mean, my 
colleagues and I, during my stint, literally went to every 
conference, every gathering, ads in newsletters, met folks like 
the men to my left and other men and women, and just tried to 
reach out to gender and racially diverse fund management. And 
more importantly, tried to exhort and encourage those funds to 
find companies that were owned and operated by diverse 
management teams.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="40" speaker="Mr. WALSH">    And a final point. This ONBoard initiative that I mentioned 
was a way to get diverse directors into those private 
companies, because a lot of times these companies had a board 
of directors that all the last name, because they are a family-
owned company. So when they were trying to expand the expertise 
of their board of directors, we would tell them to search our 
area on LinkedIn for the resumes of domain expertise people 
with diverse backgrounds and gender diverse and racially 
diverse elements to bring those people on the boards of 
directors.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. SCHNEIDER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="41" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER"> I think that is important. Oftentimes, these
companies have their board meetings when they shave. And so it 
is important to expand that.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. PALMER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="42" speaker="Mr. PALMER">Actually, one thing I would like to add to
that, Mr. Schneider, if it is all right, is we have tried very 
hard to do that, and there is more to be done. Over the course 
of 9 years, our chair of the board, four of our nine chairs of 
the board, are women. In the private equity industry that is 
unheard of. That is not 50 percent, but it is progress. There 
is some more to be done.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="43" speaker="Mr. PALMER">And Mark, who did a fantastic job when he was running the 
program, did push that, and more can be done. I think one of 
the barriers, too, as far as the fund manager side is new funds 
coming in, it is a risk to go through this regulatory process 
that really is the size of a telephone book with hundreds of 
thousands of dollars of expense. You want to make sure you can 
get through it.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="44" speaker="Mr. PALMER">    And so it is reputational risk, it is personal financial 
risk. Having some clarity as far as what that is and getting 
that streamlined would really benefit getting a broader range 
of gender, race, and geography from where we don't have it now.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. SCHNEIDER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="45" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">Great. Thank you. And my time has long
expired, but thank you for your answers.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="46" speaker="Mr. SCHNEIDER">    I yield back.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="47" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Thank you, Mr. Schneider.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="48" speaker="Chairman BLUM">I will now recognize myself for 5 minutes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="49" speaker="Chairman BLUM">    Mr. Walsh, I did the mental math. I think 4 percent of 
Apple today would be about $40 billion that we would have.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. WALSH</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="50" speaker="Mr. WALSH"> I think a tad less, but it is a heck of a lot of
money, Mr. Chairman.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="51" speaker="Chairman BLUM">I will take a tad of 40 billion.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="52" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Mr. Palmer, I think you mentioned in your testimony that we 
are experiencing our best loss rates ever. What are those loss 
rates? I was on a billion-dollar bank board for 15 years and I 
was Chairman of the Director's Credit Committee. So if our loan 
loss ratio ever got really low, sometimes we would ask: Are we 
taking enough risk or taking enough chances in loaning money?</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="53" speaker="Chairman BLUM">    Could you address both?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. PALMER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="54" speaker="Mr. PALMER">That is an excellent question.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="55" speaker="Mr. PALMER">The losses are the lowest, and the program has run at zero 
subsidy for a long time, and that is good, ever since Congress 
reformed that back in the 1990s. It is a mark of industry pride 
that has been able to maintain that zero subsidy, we want to 
take that case.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="56" speaker="Mr. PALMER">The measure that shows up as far as the losses is annual 
charge. The SBA charges a fee on the leverage as a calculation 
to offset what they think the loss history has been. It is now 
down to 22 basis points on top of the leverage.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="57" speaker="Mr. PALMER">Frankly, there is a little bit of industry concern that 
that maybe is too low, one, from a loss side; but, two, also 
making sure--look, everyone likes low fees, but we want to make 
sure we are maintaining that zero subsidy rate.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="58" speaker="Mr. PALMER">And so that 22 basis points which is calculated is low, and 
that is fine, but that is assuming that things are going to 
keep going the way they are now, which is great guns. So maybe 
we want to take a look at relooking at that fee and maybe 
setting a floor on that fee so that there is always enough of a 
cushion in the future to maintain a zero subsidy rate.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="59" speaker="Mr. PALMER">    But the investments themselves, because of the private 
capital being the first loss position, you have to lose all 
your own money first before the taxpayer money is exposed, 
which is different from 7(a) and 504. It really does align 
things in a good way as far as making good decisions and makes 
it hard to lose money. It is not that it is not possible. You 
can do it. People have risen to that challenge.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="60" speaker="Chairman BLUM"> Including the federal government.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. PALMER</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="61" speaker="Mr. PALMER">Including the Federal Government.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="62" speaker="Mr. PALMER">Quite, frankly, this is a case study in the Federal 
Government working. And that doesn't get much attention too 
often. But this really--it really is.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="63" speaker="Mr. PALMER">And so the loss rates are very low. They could do more 
risk, frankly. One of the things that they did was cleaning up 
the licensing program to minimize risk in 2008--2009, 2010, 
really, which was really helpful in filling this massive 
capital void that existed back then.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="64" speaker="Mr. PALMER">But at the same time, we ought to be taking a look smaller 
funds. It is harder to get a big fund in a smaller State, Rocky 
Mountain West and others, and the smaller funds are riskier. So 
maybe the program does need to look at allowing some smaller 
funds to more rural areas, smaller cities, to facilitate their 
market where a $200 million fund might be too big.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="65" speaker="Mr. PALMER">    But having funds in Boise or in Portland or in Colorado, 
there are no SBIC funds in Colorado. I mean, that is a pretty 
big State. There are investments there. But we need to get more 
smaller funds out to some of these smaller cities and smaller 
towns across the country.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="66" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Thank you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="67" speaker="Chairman BLUM">    Mr. Kolln, a lot of Members on this Committee represent 
rural areas. I am one of them. You are from my district. Can 
you talk to me a little bit about the challenges, if there are 
unique challenges, I assume so, in rural district, rural 
lending, rural startups versus urban areas?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. KOLLN</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="68" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">The biggest challenges in rural areas are just
that you don't have the concentration of companies. You don't 
have as many companies. You don't have as many managers to hire 
to start companies and to help grow companies. So it is really 
the challenges are finding businesses, finding enough 
businesses to make a fund work.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="69" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">And that is why, as Mr. Palmer mentioned, we run a smaller 
fund. And I think you have to be willing to run smaller funds. 
And the SBIC program is a great way to do that to be able to 
invest in these smaller areas.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="70" speaker="Mr. KOLLN">    But the challenges are finding the businesses and finding 
talent and to help the companies grow.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman BLUM</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="71" speaker="Chairman BLUM">Thank you. My time is about expired. I have
more questions, so I will do it in a second round of 
questioning.</paragraph>
    <option>Subcommittee on Health and Technology, my colleague from</option>
</Statement>
</Hearing>
