<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="26389">
    <intro>    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <Doc-title>H.R. 424, ``GRAY WOLF STATE MANAGEMENT ACT OF 2017''; H.R. 717, ``LISTING REFORM ACT''; H.R. 1274, ``STATE, TRIBAL, AND LOCAL SPECIES TRANSPARENCY AND RECOVERY ACT''; H.R. 2603, ``SAVING AMERICA'S ENDANGERED SPECIES ACT'' OR ``SAVES ACT''; AND H.R. 3131, ``ENDANGERED SPECIES LITIGATION REASONABLENESS ACT''</Doc-title>
    <option>``LISTING REFORM ACT''; H.R. 1274, ``STATE, TRIBAL, AND LOCAL SPECIES 
    TRANSPARENCY AND RECOVERY ACT''; H.R. 2603, ``SAVING AMERICA'S 
ENDANGERED SPECIES ACT'' OR ``SAVES ACT''; AND H.R. 3131, ``ENDANGERED 
                SPECIES LITIGATION REASONABLENESS ACT''
=======================================================================
                          LEGISLATIVE HEARING
                               before the
</option>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES</committee_name>
    <option>                     U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                        Wednesday, July 19, 2017
                               __________
                           Serial No. 115-18
                               __________
       Printed for the use of the Committee on Natural Resources
         Available via the World Wide Web: http://www.fdsys.gov
                                   or
          Committee address: http://naturalresources.house.gov
                                 ______
                         U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE 
26-389  PDF                     WASHINGTON : 2017 
-----------------------------------------------------------------------
  For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing 
  Office Internet: bookstore.gpo.gov Phone: toll free (866) 512-1800; 
         DC area (202) 512-1800 Fax: (202) 512-2104 Mail: Stop IDCC, 
                          Washington, DC 20402-0001
</option>
</intro>
    <committeeComposition>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES</comitteeM_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROB BISHOP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RAUL M. GRIJALVA</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ranking Democratic Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Don Young</Pname>
        <Plocation> AK</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Grace F. Napolitano</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Chairman Emeritus</Pname>
        <Plocation>Chairman Emeritus</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Madeleine Z. Bordallo</Pname>
        <Plocation> GU</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Louie Gohmert</Pname>
        <Plocation> TX</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jim Costa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Chairman</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Gregorio Kilili Camacho Sablan</Pname>
        <Plocation> </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug Lamborn</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CNMI</Pname>
        <Plocation>CNMI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Robert J. Wittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Niki Tsongas</Pname>
        <Plocation> MA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Tom McClintock</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jared Huffman</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Stevan Pearce</Pname>
        <Plocation> NM</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Ranking Member</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Ranking Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Glenn Thompson</Pname>
        <Plocation> PA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Alan S. Lowenthal</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul A. Gosar</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Donald S. Beyer</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Raul R. Labrador</Pname>
        <Plocation> ID</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Norma J. Torres</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Scott R. Tipton</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Ruben Gallego</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug LaMalfa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Colleen Hanabusa</Pname>
        <Plocation> HI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jeff Denham</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Nanette Diaz Barragan</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul Cook</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darren Soto</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Bruce Westerman</Pname>
        <Plocation> AR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>A. Donald McEachin</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Garret Graves</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Anthony G. Brown</Pname>
        <Plocation> MD</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jody B. Hice</Pname>
        <Plocation> GA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Wm. Lacy Clay</Pname>
        <Plocation> MO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Aumua Amata Coleman Radewagen</Pname>
        <Plocation> AS</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jimmy Gomez</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darin LaHood</Pname>
        <Plocation> IL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Daniel Webster</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jack Bergman</Pname>
        <Plocation> MI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Liz Cheney</Pname>
        <Plocation> WY</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Mike Johnson</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jenniffer Gonzalez-Colon</Pname>
        <Plocation> PR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Greg Gianforte</Pname>
        <Plocation> MT</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Todd Ungerecht</Pname>
        <Plocation> Acting Chief of Staff</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Lisa Pittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chief Counsel</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>David Watkins</Pname>
        <Plocation> Democratic Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
</committeeComposition>
    <Directory>
    <table-of-content>CONTENTS</table-of-content>
    <peopleSpeaker>   Hearing held on Wednesday</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>July</peopleinfo>
    <Members>Statement of Members:</Members>
    <Speaker>Hon Rob Bishop</Speaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Utah Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <Speaker>Hon Louie Gohmert</Speaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Texas Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <Speaker>Hon Raul M Grijalva</Speaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Arizona Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>Statement of Witnesses:</witnesses>
    <Witness>Hon Jared Huffman</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of California Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Jeff Corwin</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Biologist Host of ABC's Ocean Treks with Jeff Corwin</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon Louie Gohmert</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Texas Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon Glenn Hegar</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Comptroller of Public Accounts State of Texas</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Kent Holsinger</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Manager Holsinger Law</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon Bill Huizenga</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Michigan Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon Dan Newhouse</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Washington Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon Pete Olson</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Texas Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon Collin C Peterson</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Minnesota Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Greg Sheehan</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Deputy Director US Fish and Wildlife Service</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>David Willms</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Policy Advisor to Wyoming Governor Matt Mead Cheyenne</peopleinfo>
    <submittedMaterial>Additional Materials Submitted for the Record:</submittedMaterial>
    <SubmittedMaterial>List of documents submitted for the record retained in the Committee's official files Submissions for the Record by Representative Gohmert Letters of support for HR Submissions for the Record by Representative Grijalva Humane Society Legislative Fund</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>letter in opposition of HR Union of Concerned Scientists July</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>LEGISLATIVE HEARING ON HR</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>TO DIRECT THE SECRETARY OF THE</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>INTERIOR TO REISSUE FINAL RULES RELATING TO LISTING OF THE GRAY WOLF IN THE WESTERN GREAT LAKES AND WYOMING UNDER THE ENDANGERED SPECIES ACT OF</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>``GRAY WOLF STATE MANAGEMENT ACT OF ''; HR  TO AMEND THE</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>ENDANGERED SPECIES ACT OF  TO REQUIRE REVIEW OF THE ECONOMIC COST OF ADDING A SPECIES TO THE LIST OF ENDANGERED SPECIES OR THREATENED SPECIES</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>``LISTING REFORM ACT''; HR  TO AMEND THE ENDANGERED SPECIES ACT OF  TO REQUIRE MAKING AVAILABLE TO STATES</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>AFFECTED BY DETERMINATIONS THAT SPECIES ARE ENDANGERED SPECIES OR THREATENED SPECIES ALL DATA THAT IS THE BASIS OF SUCH DETERMINATIONS</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>``STATE TRIBAL</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>NONNATIVE SPECIES IN THE UNITED STATES SHALL NOT BE TREATED AS ENDANGERED SPECIES OR THREATENED SPECIES FOR PURPOSES OF THAT ACT</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>'' OR ``SAVES ACT''; AND HR  TO AMEND THE ENDANGERED SPECIES ACT OF TO CONFORM CITIZEN SUITS UNDER THAT ACT WITH OTHER EXISTING LAW</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>The Committee met</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>at : am in</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>room</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Hon Rob Bishop [Chairman of the Committee] presiding</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Present: Representatives Bishop</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Lamborn Wittman</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Gosar</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>LaMalfa Radewagen</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Gianforte; Grijalva</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Huffman Lowenthal</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Hanabusa</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Soto Clay</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Also present: Representative Polis The  Chairman The Committee on Natural Resources will come to order The Committee today is meeting to hear the testimony on several bills: HR</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Tribal and Local Species</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Transparency and Recovery Act</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>offered by Mr Newhouseyou</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>have to get smaller titles than this; HR</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>the Gray Wolf</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>State Management Act of</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>by Collin Peterson; HR</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Listing Reform Act</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Saving</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>America's Endangered Species Act</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Endangered Species Litigation Reasonableness Act by</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Representative Huizenga Under Committee Rule (f)</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>any opening oral statements are</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>going to be limited to the Chair</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Vice</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Chair</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>I ask unanimous</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>consent that other Members' statements be made part of the record if they are submitted to the Subcommittee Clerk by : pm Hearing no objections</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>we will do that And I will</peopleinfo>
    <option>                     FROM THE STATE OF UTAH
    The  Chairman. Thanks to our witnesses for being here. The 
Endangered Species Act was passed 40 years ago to try to 
recover and restore imperiled species. And, despite the best of 
intentions, all too often this Act has changed, the mission has 
changed, and has been misused to try to control land, to block 
a host of economic activities, like jobs, energy and 
infrastructure, and forest management. It also has proliferated 
costly litigation, which is actually taking taxpayers' 
resources away from actual conservation.
    In the past four Congresses, we have held over 50 hearings, 
with dozens of witnesses that have talked about the litigation 
costs, lack of transparent scientific data, consultation 
processes, both public and private, that is endless, failure to 
include states and stakeholders in the process, and also 
goalposts which simply keep moving, which promotes more 
petitions and more listings.
    That is why simply 2 percent of all the species that have 
ever been listed have ever been recovered. In short, ESA does 
not work. We have to find a way to reform it so it actually 
solves problems, not just continues on the process.
    Hopefully, working with our colleagues in the Senate and 
the Administration, we can lay a foundation for ESA reform that 
will do us well. That is why we are here today to talk about 
five bills, two of which were bipartisan, that will start the 
reform process, or at least lay a foundation for it.
    So, first, H.R. 1274, introduced by Mr. Newhouse, fosters 
greater Federal and state cooperation and data transparency.
    The second one we will talk about, H.R. 424 by Mr. 
Peterson--we welcome you here--is a bipartisan measure to 
ensure state management of gray wolves in the Western Great 
Lakes. This should be a model for success of the Endangered 
Species Act, but it has been hijacked by litigation to lose 
that concept. We need to restore it.
    H.R. 717, the Listing Reform Act by Representative Olson 
would allow consideration of economic factors in listing 
decisions.
    The fourth one, H.R. 2603, the SAVES Act by our colleague, 
Mr. Gohmert, will remove duplicative permitting requirements 
for non-native endangered species.
    And finally, H.R. 3131 by Representative Huizenga will cap 
the ESA-related attorney's fees, allowing them to prevailing 
parties only, and it will be similar to what we already do for 
Social Security and veterans' cases.
    We at this time want to say that we are looking forward to 
finding reforms as we move forward. I want our colleagues on 
that side of the dais to know we are reaching across the aisle 
to ask for your help and support, as long as the term 
``bedrock'' is not used as an adjective, but is only a noun for 
Fred Flintstone's hometown. Anything else for that word is 
total spin.
    So, I want to thank our witnesses for being here today, and 
thank the sponsors for joining us here today. I look forward to 
your testimony and the hearing.
</option>
    <option>   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman, Committee on 
                           Natural Resources
    More than 40 years ago, the Endangered Species Act was enacted to 
protect and encourage recovery of imperiled species. Though passed with 
the best of intentions, the ESA has veered away from this mission. All 
too often, the Act has been misused to control land, block a host of 
economic activities important for jobs, our energy and resources 
infrastructure and forest management. It has proliferated costly 
litigation that drains taxpayer resources away from actual conservation 
efforts.
    Over just the past four Congresses, this Committee has held more 
than 50 hearings examining the ESA. Dozens of witnesses have testified 
about litigation costs, the failure to use transparent scientific data, 
endless consultation processes, negative economic impacts, failure to 
include states and stakeholders in the process, unachievable goalposts 
to de-list healthy species and promoting more petitions and listings 
over recovery. The results speak volumes: less than 2 percent of more 
than 1,500 listed species have ever recovered.
    It is my hope that, in coordination with our colleagues in the 
Senate and this Administration, we can lay the foundation for ESA 
reform that creates better outcomes for both species and communities. 
The five bills before us today--two of which are bipartisan, and two 
that previously passed the House in some form--would begin to lay this 
foundation.
    First, H.R. 1274, introduced by Representative Newhouse, fosters 
greater Federal and state cooperation and data transparency in species 
designations.
    Second, H.R. 424, introduced by Agriculture Committee Ranking 
Member Collin Peterson, is a bipartisan measure to de-list and ensure 
state management of gray wolves in the Western Great Lakes, maintain 
Wyoming management without further litigation, and provides a model for 
how recovered species should be managed under the ESA--by states that 
have proven capable of doing so.
    Third, H.R. 717, the Listing Reform Act, sponsored by 
Representative Pete Olson, would allow for the consideration of 
economic factors in listing decisions. Countless witnesses have 
testified in prior hearings about the impacts ESA can have on economic 
activity and private property rights. The bill also provides agencies 
more flexibility in processing listing petitions to mitigate excessive 
litigation, allowing the agency to focus resources on actual species 
conservation.
    Fourth, H.R. 2603, the ``SAVES Act,'' sponsored by our colleague 
Representative Gohmert, which removes duplicative permitting 
requirements for non-native endangered species.
    And finally, H.R. 3131, sponsored by Representative Huizenga, would 
cap ESA-related attorney's fees, allowing them only to prevailing 
parties, and bringing them into conformance with fee caps allowed for 
other types of citizen lawsuits against the government, such as Social 
Security and veterans. In recent years, ESA litigation has become a 
lucrative industry, draining resources away from conservation and 
placing taxpayer funds squarely in the pockets of environmental 
attorneys and special interest groups, often at rates of $500 or more 
per hour.
    We can improve outcomes for both species and taxpayers if we build 
consensus to address existing failures and pursue targeted, common-
sense reforms. I extend my hand to Ranking Member Grijalva and my 
colleagues from both sides of the aisle as we move forward today, and 
in the coming months, in this long overdue reform effort.
    I want to thank our witnesses and bill sponsors for being here 
today, and I look forward to hearing their testimony about these 
important measures.
                                 ______
    The  Chairman. With that, I will turn to Mr. Grijalva for 
any opening statement that he may have.
</option>
    <option>               CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF ARIZONA
    Mr.  Grijalva. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. The Endangered 
Species Act works, bedrock or not.
    [Laughter.]
    Mr.  Grijalva. Despite years of Republican efforts to pass 
bills weakening the Act and cut funding from agencies that 
protect and recover imperiled American wildlife, 99 percent of 
listed species have continued to survive, and 90 percent are on 
schedule to meet their recovery goals.
    And, despite an ongoing misinformation campaign by 
Republicans and their industry allies designed to turn the 
public against ESA, 90 percent of American voters support 
keeping the law intact. These facts are not up for debate, no 
matter how strongly opponents of the law believe that polluters 
and land developers should not have to watch out for wildlife.
    Deep down, my Republican colleagues know this. Instead of a 
full frontal assault, the advocates for extinction talk about 
the need to reform or modernize the Act. These transparent 
attacks on one of the most successful and popular conservation 
statutes in the history of the world are old, tired, and 
frankly, not fooling anybody.
    The Majority has served up a weird menu of bills before us 
today, some of which have been warmed over from the last time 
we went through this pointless exercise in 2014. Three years 
later, it looks even less appealing, and represents only a 
small sample of the 200-plus legislative proposals to weaken 
ESA that have been floated since Republicans took control of 
the House in 2011.
    I cannot say this strongly or frequently enough: ESA does 
not need congressional meddling to work better; what it needs 
is congressional support.
    The Fish and Wildlife Service and the National Marine 
Fisheries Service have provided us with more than 40 years of 
evidence that the law gives states, localities, landowners, and 
private interests an incredible amount of flexibility to 
proceed with development projects in ways that conserve fish, 
wildlife, plants, and the landscapes they need to survive. 
These agencies simply need us to provide adequate funding for 
them to do their jobs, and then get out of the way.
    Claims that complying with ESA kills jobs or impedes 
economic growth are simply not grounded in reality. The U.S. 
economy has more than tripled since the law was passed--from $5 
trillion in 1973 to $16 trillion now.
    Yes, we should put the brakes on projects that would wipe 
unique forms of life off the face of the Earth. We have a moral 
duty to preserve for future generations the ability to discover 
how species can benefit them. Will the cure from cancer come 
from nature? What about the road map to a new revolution in 
agriculture or energy? We will never know if we choose to 
squander biodiversity instead of protecting it.
    For Members of this 115th Congress to declare that we 
should get to decide which species live or die for all time is, 
quite frankly, arrogant and shameful. The flaws with these 
bills before us are self-evident: basing conservation decisions 
on politics instead of science; limiting access to the courts; 
making it easier for bad guys to poach and traffic elephants, 
lions, and rhinos, just so the mega-rich can shoot them without 
having to actually travel to Africa.
    These bills are an embarrassment and a waste of time. 
Regardless of what their sponsors say, the goal of each of 
these bills is to weaken ESA, and not to make it work better. 
Enacting these bills into law would drive the extinction of 
fish, wildlife, and plants in America and around the globe, and 
they must be defeated.
    With that, I yield back, Mr. Chairman. Thank you.
</option>
    <option>   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Raul M. Grijalva, Ranking Member, 
                     Committee on Natural Resources
    The Endangered Species Act works.
    Despite years of Republican efforts to pass bills weakening the Act 
and cut funding for agencies that protect and recover imperiled 
American wildlife, 99 percent of listed species have continued to 
survive, and 90 percent are on schedule to meet their recovery goals.
    And, despite an ongoing misinformation campaign by Republicans 
designed to turn the public against the ESA, 90 percent of American 
voters support keeping the law intact. These facts are not up for 
debate, no matter how strongly opponents of the law believe that 
polluters and land developers shouldn't have to watch out for wildlife.
    Deep down, Republicans know this. So, instead of a full frontal 
assault, the advocates for extinction talk about the need to ``reform'' 
or ``modernize'' the Act. These transparent attacks on one of the most 
successful and popular conservation statutes in the history of the 
world are old, tired, and not fooling anyone.
    The Majority has served up a weird menu of bills before us today, 
some of which have been warmed over from the last time we went through 
this pointless exercise in 2014. Three years later, it looks even less 
appealing, and represents only a small sample of the 200-plus 
legislative proposals to weaken the ESA that have been floated since 
Republicans took control of the House in 2011.
    I cannot say this strongly, loudly, or frequently enough: the ESA 
does not need congressional meddling to work better. What it needs is 
congressional support.
    The Fish and Wildlife Service and the National Marine Fisheries 
Service have provided us with more than 40 years of evidence that the 
law gives states, localities, landowners, and private interests an 
incredible amount of flexibility to proceed with development projects 
in ways that conserve fish, wildlife, plants and the landscapes they 
need to survive. These agencies simply need us to provide adequate 
funding for them to do their jobs, and then get out of the way.
    Claims that complying with the ESA kills jobs or impedes economic 
growth are simply not grounded in reality. The U.S. economy has more 
than tripled since the law was passed: from $5 trillion in 1973 to $16 
trillion today.
    Yes, we should put the brakes on projects that would wipe unique 
forms of life off the face of the Earth. We have a moral duty to 
preserve for future generations the ability to discover how species can 
benefit them. Will the cure for cancer come from nature? What about the 
road map to a new revolution in agriculture or energy? We will never 
know if we choose to squander biodiversity instead of protecting it.
    For Members of this 115th Congress to declare that we should get to 
decide which species live or die--for all time--is arrogant and 
shameful. The flaws with the bills before us today are self-evident: 
basing conservation decisions on politics instead of science; limiting 
access to the courts; making it easier for bad guys to poach and 
traffic elephants, lions, and rhinos just so the mega-rich can shoot 
them without having to actually travel to Africa.
    These bills are an embarrassment and a waste of time. Regardless of 
what their sponsors say, the goal of each of these bills is to weaken 
the ESA, not to make it ``work better.''
    Enacting these bills into law would drive the extinction of fish, 
wildlife, and plants in America and around the globe, and they must be 
defeated.
                                 ______
    The  Chairman. Thank you. And I wish to hell you would quit 
trying to hide your true feelings behind rhetoric. Just say 
what you actually believe.
    [Laughter.]
    The  Chairman. I will now turn to Mr. Gohmert for 5 minutes 
for an opening statement, if he wishes to do so.
</option>
    <option>                CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF TEXAS
    Mr.  Gohmert. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Good morning and 
welcome to this vitally important hearing.
    The Endangered Species Act of 1973, or ESA, was passed with 
the best of intentions. As stewards of the Earth, it is our 
responsibility to care for and shepherd the animals under our 
dominion.
    Although it was intended to protect those species in most 
dire need, the Endangered Species Act is failing in its 
mission. In fact, the ESA often has the exact opposite effect, 
hindering instead of helping these species. States, counties, 
farmers, loggers and citizens from east Texas to the Great 
Lakes are all making it clear that the ESA is no longer 
working.
    The slate of bills we have before us today are but a small, 
necessary step in the right direction. Whether it be onerous 
permitting processes, lack of state and local stakeholder 
input, blatant disregard for relevant scientific data, or 
taxpayer dollars propping up environmental interest groups, the 
system in place is broken. These bills offer solutions.
    H.R. 424, introduced by our friend, Collin Peterson, would 
direct the Secretary of the Interior to reissue vital final 
rules from 2011 to 2012 that removed the gray wolf from the 
endangered species list in Wyoming and the Great Lakes area. 
Although litigious environmental groups have repeatedly blocked 
the return of management of gray wolves to their respective 
states, population increases have long warranted their de-
listing.
    It is difficult for anyone to say that they love and care 
about nature and ignore the damage that gray wolves have made 
when they are over-populated. It is mean, it is vicious, it is 
vile.
    While the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service de-listed wolves 
in Wyoming in accordance with a March 2017 court order, the 
decision is still subject to judicial review without this 
critical legislation. The litigiousness of environmental groups 
complicating the gray wolf situation is but a symptom of a 
larger problem: the ease with which plaintiffs can be rewarded 
by suing the Federal Government under the Endangered Species 
Act.
    My colleague, Bill Huizenga, has introduced H.R. 3131. This 
bill would standardize attorney's fees awarded in suits by 
private parties against the Federal Government, making them 
conform to the Equal Access to Justice Act. Currently, the ESA 
does not require a party suing the Federal Government to 
prevail in order to recover attorney's fees, and there is no 
cap on hourly attorney's fees. This legislation will reform 
this process by requiring plaintiffs suing the government under 
the ESA to prevail in order to collect attorney's fees, and by 
capping those fees at $125 per hour.
    Building on the importance of saving the American 
taxpayer's hard-earned money, my friend and colleague from 
Texas, Representative Pete Olson, introduced H.R. 717. This 
bill will amend the Endangered Species Act to require the 
Secretary of the Interior or Commerce to review the economic 
cost of adding a species to the endangered species list.
    Under this proposed legislation, if the Secretary 
determines that adding a species to the endangered species list 
would result in significant, cumulative economic effects, the 
species would be precluded from being placed on the list. 
Further, this bill also takes steps to streamline the 
petitioning process, thereby cutting down on excessive 
litigation.
    Finally, both my bill, H.R. 2603, the SAVES Act, which de-
lists non-native species, returning certain regulatory 
authority back to the states, and Mr. Peterson's gray wolf 
bill, are solutions for the symptoms of a larger problem, and 
that is the lack of state and local input.
    Thankfully, Representative Dan Newhouse's H.R. 1274, the 
State, Tribal, and Local Species Transparency Act, goes a long 
way in addressing this exact problem. By increasing data 
transparency and including data submitted by localities, the 
listing process will more closely adhere to the realities on 
the ground.
    I thank the Chairman for holding this important hearing, 
and the witnesses for their testimony. I yield back, Mr. 
Chairman.
</option>
    <option>Prepared Statement of the Hon. Louie Gohmert, Vice Chairman, Committee 
                          on Natural Resources
    Good morning and welcome to this vitally important hearing. The 
Endangered Species Act of 1973--or ESA--was passed with the best of 
intentions. As stewards of the Earth, it is our responsibility to care 
for and shepherd the animals under our dominion.
    Although it was intended to protect those species in most dire 
need, the Endangered Species Act is failing at its mission. In fact, 
the ESA often has the exact opposite effect, hindering instead of 
helping these species. States, counties, farmers, loggers and citizens 
from east Texas to the Great Lakes are all making it clear that the ESA 
is no longer working.
    The slate of bills we have before us are but a small, necessary 
step in the right direction. Whether it be onerous permitting 
processes; lack of state and local stakeholder input; blatant disregard 
for relevant scientific data; or taxpayer dollars propping up 
environmental interest groups, the system in place is broken.
    These bills offer solutions. H.R. 424, introduced by my friend, 
Rep. Collin Peterson, would direct the Secretary of the Interior to 
reissue vital final rules from 2011 and 2012 that removed the gray wolf 
from the endangered species list in Wyoming and the Great Lakes area.
    Although litigious environmental groups have repeatedly blocked the 
return of management of gray wolves to their respective states, 
population increases have long warranted their de-listing.
    While the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service de-listed wolves in 
Wyoming in accordance with a March 2017 court order, the decision is 
still subject to judicial review without this critical legislation. The 
litigiousness of environmental groups complicating the gray wolf 
situation is but a symptom of a larger problem: the ease with which 
plaintiffs can be rewarded by suing the Federal Government under the 
Endangered Species Act.
    My colleague, Rep. Huizenga, has introduced H.R. 3131. This bill 
would standardize attorney's fees awarded in suits by private parties 
against the Federal Government, making them conform to the Equal Access 
to Justice Act. Currently, the ESA does not require a party suing the 
Federal Government to prevail in order to recover attorney's fees, and 
there is no cap on hourly attorney's fees. This legislation will reform 
this process by requiring plaintiffs suing the government under the ESA 
to prevail in order to collect attorney's fees, and by capping those 
fees at $125 per hour.
    Building on the importance of saving the American taxpayer's hard-
earned money, my friend and colleague from Texas, Rep. Olson, 
introduced H.R. 717. This bill will amend the Endangered Species Act to 
require the Secretary of the Interior or Commerce to review the 
economic cost of adding a species to the endangered species list.
    Under this proposed legislation, if the Secretary determines that 
adding a species to the endangered species list would result in 
significant, cumulative economic effects, the species would be 
precluded from being placed on the list. Further, this bill also takes 
steps to streamline the petitioning process thereby cutting down on 
excessive litigation.
    Finally, both my bill, H.R. 2603, The SAVES Act, which de-lists 
non-native species, reducing regulations and thereby empowering states, 
and Mr. Peterson's Gray Wolf bill, are solutions for the symptoms of a 
larger problem: lack of state and local input.
    Thankfully, Rep. Dan Newhouse's H.R. 1274, the State, Tribal, and 
Local Species Transparency Act, goes a long way in addressing this 
exact problem. By increasing data transparency and including data 
submitted by localities, the listing process will more closely adhere 
to the realities on the ground.
    I thank the Chairman for holding this important hearing, and the 
witnesses for their testimony today.
                                 ______
    The  Chairman. Thank you. I now recognize Mr. Huffman as 
giving the Democrat statement as the Vice Ranking Member. You 
have 5 minutes. Go for it.
</option>
    <option>             CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA
    Mr.  Huffman. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. The slate of bills 
before us today is a painful reminder of how far we have moved 
away from the bipartisan agreement that Democrats and 
Republicans used to share over a core set of values, the values 
of conservation and respect for science, in particular.
    Both sides of the aisle used to agree that protecting 
America's natural heritage for the enjoyment of this generation 
and for future generations was a worthy goal, and that relying 
on sound science to guide conservation policy was the gold 
standard for natural resources management.
    Of course, our fish, wildlife, plants, and the landscapes 
that they need are a huge part of that heritage. When it was 
enacted in 1973, the ESA had incredibly strong bipartisan 
support. It passed the Senate unanimously and was voted 390 to 
12 out of the House of Representatives. I highlight that this 
happened during the height of the Watergate investigation--not 
exactly a high watermark of bipartisan cooperation with the 
executive branch. But the ESA, nevertheless, had that 
incredible bipartisan foundation.
    It has long been one of our most successful and broadly 
supported conservation laws, preventing the extinction of 99 
percent of the species that have received its protection over 
its 44-year run.
    Now remember, the ESA only kicks in when species are in 
real trouble, in danger of extinction, or when it is 
foreseeable that they will be in such danger.
    If an ER doctor was able to save 99 percent of the critical 
patients that came through the door of that ER, and put 90 
percent of them on a clear path to recovery, as the ESA has 
done with imperiled species, that doctor would receive 
universal praise.
    So, I think it is worth asking why the ESA receives so much 
criticism in this Committee. I suspect the answer is pretty 
simple: the law requires Federal agencies to use the best-
available science to make decisions to prevent extinction, 
regardless of who produced that science. That can be bad news 
for mining companies, the oil and gas industry, big developers, 
and others.
    For example, one of the bills before us today, H.R. 1274, 
statutorily deems anything submitted by states, tribes, or 
localities as the best available science, regardless of the 
quality of that information.
    Another bill, H.R. 717, would let economics over-ride 
science when Federal agencies are reviewing fish and wildlife 
that are in serious decline.
    Another bill, H.R. 2603, removes ESA protections from 
species that are not native to the United States, and that 
would essentially provide blank checks to private game ranchers 
in Texas to hunt the endangered African antelope, and wildlife 
traffickers to profit from the domestic sale of ivory, thereby 
exacerbating the ongoing African elephant poaching crisis. It 
is a bad idea.
    What these bills ignore is that protecting fish and 
wildlife is not just a good idea in principle; it is good for 
the economy and it is good for people. The salmon fishermen in 
my district and elsewhere on the West Coast, for example, 
depend on strong and functioning ESA protections for salmon 
runs, allowing them to continue catching healthy stocks. It is 
about protecting jobs and a way of life.
    The bottom line is that the ESA has worked, and it has 
remained untouched for more than 40 years because decisions 
under the law have to be made based on data and evidence. That 
is a pretty reasonable standard that we all should be able to 
uphold.
    The ESA is not causing drought, flood, or pestilence, as 
some have argued before this Committee. All it is doing is 
requiring us to consider the impact on fish, wildlife, plants, 
and habitat, and requiring us to avoid causing extinction.
    So, yes, we no longer just cut down as many trees, or catch 
as many fish, as possible without thinking about the future. It 
is the lesson of the Lorax, it is the tragedy of the commons. 
And, as I said before, it is not just for fish and wildlife, it 
is for future generations of people, as well.
    And, with that, Mr. Speaker, I yield back without once 
using the word ``bedrock.''
    The  Chairman. You just did it. You lost again.
    [Laughter.]
</option>
    <option>  Prepared Statement of the Hon. Jared Huffman, Vice Ranking Member, 
                     Committee on Natural Resources
    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    The slate of bills before us today is a painful reminder of how far 
we have moved away from the bipartisan agreement Democrats and 
Republicans used to share over a core set of values, and the values of 
conservation and respect for science, in particular.
    Both sides of the aisle used to agree that protecting America's 
natural heritage for the enjoyment of this generation and future ones 
was a worthy goal, and that relying on sound science to guide 
conservation policy was the gold standard for natural resources 
management.
    Of course, our fish, wildlife, plants, and the landscapes they need 
are a huge part of that heritage. When enacted in 1973, the ESA Act had 
strong bipartisan support. It passed the Senate unanimously, and was 
voted 390 for and 12 against in the House. I highlight that this was 
during height of the Watergate investigation--not exactly a high 
watermark of bipartisan cooperation with the executive branch.
    The Endangered Species Act has long been one of our most successful 
and broadly supported conservation laws, preventing the extinction of 
99 percent of the species that have received its protection over the 
past 44 years.
    Remember, the ESA only kicks in when a species is in danger of 
extinction, or when it's foreseeable that it will be in such danger. If 
an emergency room doctor saved 99 percent of the critical patients that 
came through the door, and put 90 percent of them on a clear and timely 
road to recovery as the ESA has done with imperiled species, that 
doctor would receive universal praise.
    So, why does the ESA receive so much criticism in this Committee? I 
suspect the answer is simple: the law requires Federal agencies to use 
the best available science to make decisions to prevent extinction, 
regardless of who produced that science, and that can be bad news for 
mining companies, oil and gas industry, big developers, and others.
    For example, one of the bills before us today (H.R. 1274) deems 
anything submitted by states, tribes, or localities to be the ``best'' 
available science, regardless of the quality of the information. 
Another bill, H.R. 717, would let economics over-ride science when 
Federal agencies are reviewing fish and wildlife that are on the 
decline. Yet another one, H.R. 2603 removes ESA protections from 
species that are not native to the United States. This bill would 
essentially provide blank checks to private game ranchers in Texas to 
hunt the endangered African antelope, and wildlife traffickers to 
profit from domestic sales of ivory, thereby exacerbating the ongoing 
African elephant poaching crisis.
    What these bills ignore is that protecting fish and wildlife is not 
just a good idea in principle, but good for the economy and for people 
as well. The salmon fishermen in my district and elsewhere on the West 
Coast, for example, depend on a strong and functioning ESA to protect 
salmon runs, allowing them to continue catching healthy stocks.
    The bottom line is that the ESA has worked, and has remained 
untouched for more than 40 years, because decisions under the law must 
be made based on data and evidence. That's a pretty reasonable standard 
to uphold.
    The ESA is not causing drought, or flood, or pestilence as some 
have argued before this Committee. All it's doing is requiring us to 
consider our impact on fish, wildlife, plants, and habitat--and 
requiring us to avoid causing extinction. So yes, we no longer just cut 
down as many trees, or catch as many fish, as possible without thinking 
about the future. But that's a good thing, as I said, not just for fish 
and wildlife but for future generations of people as well.
    It would be a welcome change if we were really talking about 
modernizing the ESA so that it works better for both people and 
wildlife. But these bills won't get us there.
                                 ______
    The  Chairman. All right. We thank you for the witnesses 
who are actually here, the panel.
    This is the drill. You all have been through this. You have 
5 minutes Your written statements are already in the record. 
Microphones have to be turned on. The clock is ahead of you. I 
will cut you off at the 5-minute level without trying to be 
rude.
    I will tell you now that, once you are done, we would 
invite you to stay with us and participate in the rest of the 
hearing. If you want to insult us by leaving, that is your 
right. You can claim you are busy, whatever you want to do, but 
know that you are more than welcome to stay for the entire 
hearing, as we go forward.
    So, we will do in this order, first of all, Mr. Newhouse, 
then we will go to Mr. Peterson, to Mr. Olson, to Mr. Gohmert 
up here, to Mr. Huizenga. You will be the clean-up hitter for 
us.
    So, actually, technically, you are the clean-up hitter. You 
are batting five.
    Mr. Newhouse, are you ready to lead us off? You are 
recognized for 5 minutes. Good to have you back on the 
Committee, by the way.
</option>
    <option>             CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF WASHINGTON
    Mr.  Newhouse. Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman. Ranking 
Member Grijalva, members of the Committee, it is great to be 
back with all of you, as well. And I want to thank you for the 
opportunity to address this Committee in support of my 
legislation, H.R. 1274. It is the State, Tribal, and Local 
Species Transparency and Recovery Act. And yes, we need a 
couple more words in there.
    This legislation is simple and it is logical. By including 
state and local entities in Federal determinations and decision 
making, we can improve policy making and reduce the impacts on 
states, municipalities, tribes, and local stakeholders, all 
while ensuring endangered species listing decisions include the 
best pertinent data involved in such matters.
    Federal agencies like the Fish and Wildlife Service are 
currently not required to share underlying data used in listing 
decisions made under the ESA with the states or the local 
entities that would be impacted by such listing decisions. 
These agencies too often overlook local conservation plans that 
are developed to ensure the protection of native species and 
habitats. These local efforts should not be disregarded, for 
oftentimes, the counties or the local municipalities are among 
the best sources of information. Local stakeholders deserve to 
know whether their hard work is taken into consideration long 
before the end result of a Federal listing decision is made 
public.
    My bill will amend the ESA to simply require that Federal 
agencies disclose all data used to promulgate a potential or 
final listing determination to the states and local 
jurisdictions affected by Federal regulatory actions.
    The legislation also gives local stakeholders the 
opportunity to verify, dispute, or complement the information 
the Federal agencies use in the ESA listings.
    There have been too many examples of states' data and 
species recovery plans having been effectively ignored by 
Federal agencies, even after earnest and costly efforts were 
made to develop comprehensive and effective plans at the local 
level. By providing states, tribes, and localities the data 
used to promulgate these proposed listings, an opportunity 
arises for local stakeholders to get involved and have their 
voices heard.
    Two cases in my own district in Central Washington come to 
mind regarding transparency of Federal decision making 
involving specific species.
    Earlier this year, the National Park Service, as well as 
Fish and Wildlife, released a draft plan to reintroduce the 
grizzly bear in the North Cascades ecosystem. Both agencies 
claimed the bears will be joining an existing grizzly 
population, however, the last confirmed sighting of a grizzly 
bear in that area was in 1996. The people living in these 
communities deserve to know what data the Federal agencies are 
basing their decisions on. I have expressed my deep concerns 
regarding the lack of sound science and data to support this 
decision, and will continue to do so.
    The case of the gray wolf also comes to mind. The 
Department of the Interior and the Fish and Wildlife Service 
published a proposed rule that would remove the gray wolf's 
listing over 4 years ago, and even found the best-available 
scientific and commercial information indicates that the 
currently listed entity is not a valid species under the Act.
    Yet, the wolf remains listed. The gray wolf is found in 
nearly 50 countries around the world and has grown 
substantially across its range. I can attest to that. I will 
continue to be a firm advocate of de-listing the gray wolf, and 
returning its management to the states.
    On a final note, Mr. Chairman, I often share with my 
constituents that, as a farmer, I consider myself a 
conservationist and a true steward of the gifts God has given 
us. Farmers are on the forefront of protecting our Nation's 
rich, natural heritage. I believe it is important that we 
preserve our forests, our natural resources, and wildlife for 
our children, as well as our grandchildren, to enjoy. This 
legislation will only strengthen that effort.
    By modernizing the Endangered Species Act, we can ensure 
its effectiveness in protecting imperiled species successfully. 
I look forward to working with you and with the Committee to 
move this legislation forward. And, again, thank you for the 
opportunity.
</option>
    <option>   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Dan Newhouse, a Representative in 
           Congress from the State of Washington on H.R. 1274
    Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and members of the 
Committee, thank you for the opportunity to address the Committee on 
Natural Resources in support of my legislation, H.R. 1274, the ``State, 
Tribal, and Local Species Transparency and Recovery Act.'' This 
legislation is simple, and logical--by including state and local 
entities in Federal determinations and decision making, we can improve 
policy making and reduce the impacts on states, municipalities, tribes, 
and local stakeholders, all while ensuring endangered species listing 
decisions include the best, pertinent data involved in such matters.
    Federal agencies like the U.S. Fish &amp;amp; Wildlife Service (FWS) are 
currently not required to share the underlying data used in listing 
decisions made under the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (ESA) with the 
states or local entities that would be impacted by such listing 
decisions. These agencies too often overlook local conservation plans 
developed to ensure the protection of native species and habitats. 
These local efforts should not be disregarded, for oftentimes, the 
counties or local municipalities are among the best sources of such 
information. Local stakeholders deserve to know whether their hard work 
is taken into consideration long before the end result of a Federal 
listing decision is made final and public.
    The State, Tribal, and Local Species Transparency and Recovery Act 
will amend the ESA to simply require that Federal agencies disclose all 
data used to promulgate a potential or final listing determination to 
the states and local jurisdictions affected by Federal regulatory 
actions. The legislation also gives local stakeholders the opportunity 
to verify, dispute, or complement the information Federal agencies use 
in an ESA listing. There have been too many examples of states' data 
and species recovery plans having been effectively ignored by Federal 
agencies, even after earnest and costly efforts were made to develop 
comprehensive and effective plans at local levels. By providing states, 
tribes, and localities the data used to promulgate these proposed 
listings, an opportunity arises for local stakeholders to get involved, 
and have their voices heard.
    Two cases in my own district in Central Washington come to mind 
regarding transparency of Federal decision making involving specific 
species. Earlier this year, the National Park Service and FWS released 
a draft plan to reintroduce grizzlies in the North Cascades Ecosystem 
(NCE). NPS and FWS claim the bears will be joining an existing grizzly 
population, however the last confirmed sighting of a grizzly bear in 
the NCE was in 1996. The people living in these communities deserve to 
know what data these Federal agencies are basing their decisions on. I 
have expressed my deep concerns regarding the lack of sound science and 
data to support this plan and will continue to voice them.
    The case of the gray wolf also comes to mind. The Department of the 
Interior and FWS published a proposed rule that would remove the gray 
wolf's listing over 4 years ago--and even found the ``best available 
scientific and commercial information indicates that the currently 
listed entity is not a valid species under the Act.'' Yet, the wolf 
remains listed. The gray wolf is found in nearly 50 countries around 
the world and has grown substantially across its range. I will continue 
to be a firm advocate of de-listing the gray wolf and returning its 
management to the states.
    On a final note, Mr. Chairman, I often share with my constituents 
that, as a farmer, I consider myself a conservationist and steward of 
the gifts God has given us. Farmers are on the forefront of protecting 
our Nation's rich, natural heritage. I believe it is important that we 
preserve our forests, natural resources, and wildlife for our children 
and grandchildren to enjoy. This legislation will only strengthen that 
effort. By modernizing the Endangered Species Act, we can ensure its 
effectiveness in protecting imperiled species successfully. I look 
forward to working with the Committee to move this legislation forward, 
and again thank you for the opportunity.
                                 ______
    Mr.  Newhouse. And, at the risk of the demise of my bill, I 
must excuse myself and go to another Committee hearing. Thank 
you, Mr. Chairman.
    The  Chairman. Thank you. Well, at least you gave us a nice 
segue into the next speaker, talking about farmers. We 
recognize the Ranking Member on the Ag. Committee.
    Mr. Peterson, it is nice to have you on this side of the 
building, on this side of the Floor for a change. You are 
recognized for 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>              CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF MINNESOTA
    Mr.  Peterson. Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman, Ranking 
Member Grijalva, and other members of the Committee, for the 
invitation to speak in support of my bill, the Gray Wolf State 
Management Act of 2017.
    In 2011, the Fish and Wildlife Service determined that the 
gray wolves in Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Michigan no longer 
required Federal protection, based on two main factors. First, 
the gray wolf population numbers in each state remained well 
above established recovery goals set by the 1992 recovery plan 
for the eastern timber wolf. And second, the wolf management 
plans established by each state provided for long-term 
conservation of a viable wolf population in the region. While 
under state management from 2011 to 2014, gray wolf populations 
remained well above recovery goals.
    At the end of 2014, a single judge sitting in Washington, 
DC, that I would say had no clue about what is going on in our 
part of the world, created a mess by somehow deciding that the 
wolf had not established themselves, or re-established in their 
entire range.
    Somebody convinced this judge that the range of the wolf 
was all the way down into Iowa, which I don't think is true. 
So, that means that Minneapolis and Lake Minnetonka should have 
wolves. Maybe we should release some in downtown Minneapolis or 
out in Lake Minnetonka, and if they ate some of those fancy 
little dogs, maybe we would finally get this thing fixed.
    [Laughter.]
    Mr.  Peterson. So, yes, this was all done despite 
scientific evidence that has been conducted by the U.S. Fish 
and Wildlife Service that the wolf population recovered and 
thrived, and they actually support the de-listing.
    This judge's decision suddenly put our farmers and ranchers 
in Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Michigan in a very difficult 
situation. Currently, it is illegal for a farmer to shoot a 
gray wolf that is actively attacking its cattle or pets. And 
when the attacks occur, my constituents are forced to choose 
between following the law or protecting their livestock and 
their livelihoods.
    Wyoming went through a similar situation when a judge 
single-handedly relisted wolves in 2014. In March of 2017, the 
D.C. Circuit Court of Appeals reversed that court decision, and 
the wolves are once again under Wyoming state management. But 
this bill returns the management of the gray wolves in 
Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Michigan from the Federal Government 
back to the states, and does not allow for further judicial 
review.
    The bill also includes Wyoming, to protect the state from 
further judicial over-reach, if that might happen.
    The courts have created a big enough mess already. And I 
think it is important for you to note that my bill does not 
prevent the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service from relisting 
wolves in the future.
    I would like to submit for the record letters of support 
from several organizations, and technical documents from the 
U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and the Minnesota Department of 
Natural Resources, which in this case, they did a wonderful job 
of managing the wolf population. And that is something for me 
to say, because I have not necessarily gotten along with the 
Minnesota DNR. This is one case where they did a great job.
    [The information follows:]
Rep. Peterson Submission--Letters of Support for H.R. 424
                    American Farm Bureau Federation
                                                      July 18, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
Re: Gray Wolf State Management Act (H.R. 424)
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    On behalf of the American Farm Bureau Federation, we would like to 
thank you for scheduling a hearing to consider the Gray Wolf State 
Management Act (H.R. 424). This commonsense, bipartisan legislation 
would reinstate the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service's (FWS) order to 
remove the gray wolf in the Western Great Lakes and Wyoming from the 
federal Endangered Species List. It would also provide legal clarity 
for the gray wolf's status on the Endangered Species list.
    Farm Bureau has been an active participant in the wolf issue for 
decades. That participation encompasses legal efforts in the federal 
district court in Minnesota seeking damages on behalf of Minnesota 
ranchers resulting from wolf predation; a lawsuit challenging the 
introduction of wolves into Montana, Wyoming and Idaho; comments on 
proposed federal regulations; comments delivered in public and 
congressional hearings; and regular interaction with the FWS on the 
impact of gray wolf populations on the membership.
    The purpose of the ESA is to recover species that are threatened 
with extinction: the Act clearly lays out the appropriate path to take 
after a species has recovered. In the case of the gray wolf, affected 
states have taken a positive, constructive approach in assuring 
continued recovery of the wolf, a step which supports the species' de-
listing.
    Farm Bureau supports Federal efforts to de-list the gray wolf. Such 
an effort is clearly justified in light of the goals of the Endangered 
Species Act; the best available scientific and commercial data that is 
available; the goals outlined in various recovery plans; and the 
aggressive leadership in affected states. Viewed in this context, the 
current status of the wolf clearly justifies its removal from the list 
of threatened and endangered species.
    We commend you for your leadership on this important issue, and 
look forward to continuing to work with you and the House Natural 
Resources Committee in securing enactment of this critically important 
legislation.
            Sincerely,
                                                Dale Moore,
                                 Executive Director, Public Policy.
                                 ______
                   Michigan Cattlemen's Association
                                                      July 19, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    This Michigan Cattlemen's Association wishes to thank you for 
holding a hearing to discuss H.R. 424, the Gray Wolf State Management 
Act of 2017. We fully support H.R. 424.
    The wolf population in Michigan has exceeded 600 wolves since 2011. 
Cattle farmers and ranchers in Michigan continue to be severely 
impacted by wolf attacks on their herds. There have been over 230 
verified wolf attacks on livestock and dogs in Michigan since 2010. Due 
to a Federal court decision in December 2014, wolves in the western 
Great Lakes area (including Michigan, Minnesota, and Wisconsin) were 
relisted under the Endangered Species Act (ESA).
    With ESA protection in place, lethal action against wolves is 
illegal, even if they are in the process of attacking livestock. Cattle 
producers are left completely helpless as wolves prey on their herds. 
H.R. 424 would return management of wolves to the states where the 
species can be managed properly.
    We appreciate the committee's consideration and we strongly urge 
passage of H.R. 424.
            Sincerely,
                                           Carl VanderKolk,
                                                         President.
                                 ______
                               Michigan Farm Bureau
                                                      July 17, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    Thank you for holding a hearing on H.R. 424, the Gray Wolf State 
Management Act in the House Natural Resources Committee. We support 
this legislation and appreciate your leadership in continuing the 
discussion on this critical issue.
    Michigan Farm Bureau represents nearly 45,000 farming families 
throughout the state, many of which are livestock producers. In 
particular, farmers in the Upper Peninsula have been very concerned 
about the growing threat of predation by the Western gray wolf.
    Farm Bureau supports legislation that would direct the Secretary of 
the Interior to reissue the final rule that was published on December 
28, 2011 (76 Fed. Reg. 81666 et seq) delisting the Western Great Lakes 
District Population Segment (DPS) of gray wolf, without regard to any 
other provision or statute or regulation that applies to the issuance 
of such rule and not subject to judicial review. This legislation would 
achieve this objective.
    Farm Bureau supports Rep. Collin Peterson's (MN-07) legislation and 
believes it strikes the right balance on how to address the growing 
gray wolf population in Northern Michigan and surrounding states.
            Sincerely,
                                                 John Kran,
                                      National Legislative Counsel.
                                 ______
                 Michigan United Conservation Clubs
                                                      July 19, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
    Dear Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva and Members of the 
House Committee on Natural Resources:
    I am writing to you on behalf of the 80,000 members and supporters 
of the Michigan United Conservation Clubs to convey our thanks and 
support for your consideration of H.R. 424 which concerns the 
restoration of state management for gray wolves in the western Great 
Lakes region. Our members are hunters, anglers, trappers, and 
conservationists of every background in Michigan.
    For over 15 years, wolves have met, and consistently and 
substantially exceeded population recovery goals established by the 
United States Fish and Wildlife Service. Additionally, a diverse group 
of stakeholders and state fish and wildlife agency professionals have 
collaborated on the development of a management plan to ensure the 
long-term conservation of wolves in Michigan. Yet despite their 
recovery and the preparedness of the state to assume management control 
for wolves, their legal status has not aligned with the biological 
reality of their recovery.
    We respectfully request that you join us in supporting the 
conservation success of a fully recovered, healthy, and independently 
viable wolf population in Michigan by restoring state management of 
this species.
            Sincerely,
                                          Daniel Eichinger,
                                                Executive Director.
                                 ______
            Minnesota State Cattlemen's Association
                                                      July 17, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
Re: H.R. 424--Gray Wolf State Management Act of 2017
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    The Minnesota State Cattlemen's Association thanks the House 
Committee on Natural Resources for showing support and granting a 
hearing for H.R. 424--Gray Wolf State Management Act of 2017.
    While under state control, the State of Minnesota, through the 
Minnesota Department of Natural Resources and Department of 
Agriculture, developed and implemented a comprehensive and time proven 
wolf management plan. That plan, accepted by the U.S. Department of 
Interior, was the basis for delisting and the means of ensuring 
Minnesota's wolves would never again become threatened or endangered.
    Minnesota's gray wolf, by all measures established, was effectively 
maintained in Minnesota and should once again have population control 
returned to the state. The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and the State 
of Minnesota do not dispute that wolves have recovered and maintained 
their population here. However, efforts to de-list wolves in this area 
continue to be challenged on procedural and technical, rather than wolf 
conservation, grounds. The success of the ESA in recovering this 
population and the management efforts of the Minnesota Department of 
Natural Resources have been overshadowed by litigation and the 
unnecessarily onerous process to delist the gray wolf. If the State of 
Minnesota satisfactorily follows their approved population management 
plan, then future delisting of the gray wolf should not be subject to 
judicial review. With this type of action, we firmly believe it would 
remedy what is necessary to overcome the long history of legal and 
technical challenges to managing a clearly recovered species in the 
state of Minnesota.
    Once delisted, the State of Minnesota will continue to protect 
wolves and monitor their population, while giving livestock and 
domestic pet owners and wildlife more protection from wolf depredation 
as well as diseases carried by wolves. According to the original 
recovery plan, wolves have recovered in Minnesota and no longer warrant 
listing under the Endangered Species Act of 1973. The original USFWS 
recovery plan called for 1,251 to 1,400 gray wolves in Minnesota to 
meet delisting criteria. The state plan establishes a minimum 
population of 1,600 wolves to ensure the long-term survival of the wolf 
in Minnesota. The state's wolf population, which was estimated at fewer 
than 750 animals in the 1950s, has grown an estimated 2,300 animals 
according to the 2015-16 mid-winter wolf population survey. This 
obviously far exceeds state and federal recovery goals and has led to 
increased conflicts between wolves and humans, pets, and livestock. 
This would also show that, while under state control, state agencies 
have been able to successfully manage wolf populations.
    Minnesota's cattle and beef industry is a diverse and robust sector 
of the state's agricultural economy. Cattle and beef production is the 
second largest livestock sector in Minnesota, accounting for 27% of 
Minnesota's livestock cash receipts and 13% of the state's total 
agricultural cash receipts. Nationally, Minnesota ranks tenth in cattle 
production and is home to roughly 2.4 million head of cattle and 
calves. This sector of animal agriculture has a ``multiplier effect'' 
of $2.05 for every dollar of output. Specifically, Minnesota's beef and 
cattle production creates economic activities in many other economic 
sectors including agronomy, manufacturing, transportation, trade, 
services, finance, insurance, real estate, and construction. Minnesota 
beef production's total economic impacts at the farm level (not 
including meat processing) equals 4.2 billion dollars and employs 
nearly 27,000 Minnesotans. Ensuring Minnesota's beef farmers and 
ranchers are able to protect their cattle and herds when needed is 
vital to supporting this important sector of Minnesota's economy.
    Thank you for your time and consideration of H.R. 424--Gray Wolf 
State Management Act of 2017.
            Sincerely,
                                              Krist Wollum,
                                                         President.
                                 ______
                 Minnesota Deer Hunters Association
                                                      July 15, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    We are writing to thank you for scheduling a hearing on H.R. 424 
that would restore management of the gray wolf to several states 
including Minnesota. We urge your support of this important 
legislation.
    On December 19, 2014, a U.S. District Court Judge overturned the 
Fish and Wildlife Service's (FWS) November 2011 decision to delist the 
gray wolf in the Western Great Lakes region, including Minnesota, 
Wisconsin and Michigan. The result of this decision was to relist the 
gray wolf on the Endangered Species List in Minnesota and revoke State 
of Minnesota management. For several years, Minnesota had effectively 
managed wolves in Minnesota through a conservative plan that provides 
for hunting and livestock depredation control while maintaining a 
healthy wolf population. Now, as a result of the court ruling, a person 
may only take a wolf in the defense of human life and not to protect 
property such as livestock and personal pets.
    The gray wolf has recovered in Minnesota by all reasonable 
measures, particularly those provided in the Endangered Species Act. 
The federal recovery plan for the gray wolf identified a recovered 
population number of 1,251-1,400 wolves. The Minnesota Department of 
Natural Resources (MNDNR) winter wolf population survey in 2015-16 
estimated the population to be approximately 2,300. MNDNR concluded 
there has been no biologically or statistically significant change in 
the size of the statewide mid-winter wolf population over the past 4 
years of surveys.
    An appeal of the District Court ruling has been heard, but the 
appeal process is lengthy and leaves no effective wolf management in 
Minnesota. A legislative fix is a more suitable solution to the 
problem. We ask you to support H.R. 424 that would require the FWS to 
reissue the rule that delisted the gray wolf in Minnesota and other 
states. H.R. 424 would not modify the Endangered Species Act, nor would 
it prevent the FWS from deciding to relist the gray wolf in the future 
if it determines that the wolf population is in need of federal 
protection.
    Again, we seek your support in restoring management of the gray 
wolf to the State of Minnesota. Thank you.
            Sincerely,
                                          Craig L. Engwall,
                                                Executive Director.
                                 ______
                              Minnesota Farm Bureau
                                                      July 17, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    Thank you for holding a hearing on H.R. 424, the Gray Wolf State 
Management Act in the House Natural Resources Committee. Minnesota Farm 
Bureau supports this legislation and appreciate your leadership in 
continuing the discussion on this critical issue.
    On December 19, 2014, U.S. District Judge Beryl Howell immediately 
reinstated Endangered Species Act (ESA) protections for gray wolves in 
Minnesota, Michigan, and Wisconsin. This decision now leaves farmers, 
ranchers, and pet owners helpless in protecting their animals against 
wolf attacks. Farm Bureau members continuously share devastating 
stories about the inability to protect their livestock from these 
vicious attacks with no option other than to watch their animals die.
    In order to meet delisting criteria set by USFWS, the gray wolf 
population needed to be between 1,251 and 1,400. Once turned over to 
state management, Minnesota set a minimum population of 1,600 wolves. 
The state's current wolf population is now more than 2,400, which 
clearly far exceeds state and federal recovery goals. The State of 
Minnesota has done and will continue to do a superior job of monitoring 
the population to allow for a healthy population while also giving pet 
and livestock owners options to protect their animals, but management 
needs to be back under control of the state rather than the ESA. H.R. 
424 would help to strike this balance.
    Once again, thank you for holding a hearing on H.R. 424. If you 
have any questions on the impacts of wolves to agriculture in 
Minnesota, I would be happy to answer them.
            Sincerely,
                                                Kevin Paap,
                                                         President.
                                 ______
                            Minnesota Farmers Union
                                                      July 17, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    On behalf of the membership of the Minnesota Farmers Union (MFU) we 
wish to thank you from taking time to hear H.R. 424 authored by Rep. 
Collin Peterson. MFU is a strong supporter of this legislation that 
requires the Department of the Interior to reissue the final rule 
published on December 28, 2011, that removed the gray wolf in the 
Western Great Lakes Distinct Population Segment from the List of 
Endangered and Threatened Wildlife and that removed the designation of 
critical habitat for that wolf in Minnesota and Michigan.
    De-listing the gray wolf has been a top issue for our livestock 
farmers in the northern part of the state, as we have seen continued 
conflict between wolves and livestock farmers. MFU strongly believes 
that gray wolf numbers have adequately recovered in Minnesota. MFU also 
strongly believes that the Minnesota Department of Natural Resources 
(MNDNR) is ready and able to administer the gray wolf population 
through its current management plans. Minnesota has consistently topped 
the federal delisting goal of 1,250-1,400 with numbers exceeding 2,000 
wolves in recent years surveys.
    Again, MFU appreciates Rep. Peterson carrying this important 
legislation forward, and appreciates the committees time in hearing 
this legislation, and MFU urges its passage.
            Regards,
                                              Gary Wertish,
                                                         President.
                                 ______
                             National Farmers Union
                                                      July 18, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    On behalf of National Farmers Union's roughly 200,000 family 
farmers, ranchers, and rural residents, I would like to thank you for 
scheduling a hearing to consider the Gray Wolf State Management Act of 
2017 introduced by Congressman Collin Peterson (D-MN).
    Listing Gray Wolves under ESA forces farmers and ranchers into an 
untenable position. Farmers and ranchers should be able to defend 
against predatory animals, such as the Gray Wolf, on their land. The 
Gray Wolf State Management Act of 2017 prevents farmers and ranchers 
from having to choose between their livelihood and federal punishment. 
Our support for this bill comes directly from our member approved 
policy. Our members believe they should have the right to defend 
themselves and their livestock from predatory animals, even if the 
animal is listed under ESA. Our members hold that these animals should 
be dealt with in the most effective, safe, economical and humane means.
    Should you or your staff require any additional assistance on this 
matter, NFU stands ready to assist.
            Sincerely,
                                             Roger Johnson,
                                                         President.
                                 ______
  Public Lands Council &amp;amp; National Cattlemen's Beef 
                                        Association
                                                      July 18, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
Re: Livestock Industry Support for H.R. 424, the Gray Wolf State 
        Management Act of 2017
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    The Public Lands Council (PLC) and the National Cattlemen's Beef 
Association (NCBA) support H.R. 424, the Gray Wolf State Management Act 
of 2017.
    PLC is the only national organization dedicated solely to 
representing the roughly 22,000 ranchers operating on federal lands. 
NCBA is the nation's oldest and largest national trade association for 
cattlemen and women, representing more than 170,000 cattle producers 
through direct membership and their state affiliates. PLC and NCBA are 
producer directed and in partnership with our state affiliates work to 
preserve the heritage and strength of the industry by providing a 
stable business environment for our members.
    The livestock industry has numerous concerns with the gray wolf 
being listed as an endangered species. Unlike most species listed under 
the ESA, wolves pose a serious threat to wildlife, humans, private 
property--namely, livestock--even in cases where wolf populations are 
sparse. The result is economic hardship and the possibility of a need 
to list other species. Secondly, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service has 
already determined the wolf is no longer warranted for listing under 
the ESA.
    H.R. 424, introduced by Representative Collin Peterson calls for 
the Secretary of the Interior to reinstate two U.S. Fish and Wildlife 
Service decisions that delisted the gray wolf from the endangered 
species list in the Great Lakes Region and Wyoming, allowing the states 
to continue to manage the wolf populations, as they have successfully 
done for several years. Relisting the species undermined the good work 
that has taken place on the ground, and unnecessarily takes away the 
states right to manage wildlife populations within their borders. It 
also takes away the ability for livestock producers to protect their 
herds, putting their livelihood and economic stability in jeopardy. 
H.R. 424, is a bipartisan, common sense approach to management of 
species, which promotes cooperation between the USFWS, state wildlife 
agencies, and local stakeholders.
    PLC and NCBA have been continually involved in ESA related 
activities. Our associations have submitted comments in partnership 
with our state affiliate organizations on the Gray and Mexican Wolves, 
Sage Grouse, Lesser Prairie Chicken, and the Black Footed Ferret to 
name a few. For the last two years, we have been fully engaged with the 
Western Governors Association and the ESA Initiative led by Governor 
Matt Mead of Wyoming. It is crucial for the livestock industry to be 
engaged to the fullest extent possible, in order to ensure that the 
nation's livestock producers, who provide food and fiber for the nation 
and world, are protected from harmful and unwarranted listings under 
the ESA.
    PLC and NCBA applaud the efforts of Representative Peterson and 
appreciate the opportunity to provide our input on behalf of our 
members--the nation's food and fiber producers. We encourage members of 
the Committee to support this positive and proactive piece of 
legislation.
            Sincerely,
        Dave Eliason, President,      Craig Uden, President,
        Public Lands Council          Nat'l. Cattlemen's Beef Assoc.
                                 ______
                      Rocky Mountain Elk Foundation
                                                      July 13, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
Re: July 19, 2017 Hearing on H.R. 424
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    The Rocky Mountain Elk Foundation (RMEF) would like to thank you 
for scheduling the July 19 hearing on H.R. 424, the Gray Wolf State 
Management Act of 2017.
    This bill would require the U.S. Department of Interior to reissue 
its 2011 final rule removing the gray wolf in the Western Great Lakes 
states from federal protection and the 2012 final rule removing the 
gray wolf in Wyoming from federal protection. Gray wolves have exceeded 
recovery goals in these states and no longer require federal 
protection.
    RMEF expects a decision in the next few months from the Washington, 
D.C. Circuit Court regarding the appeal to the Interior Department's 
2011 final rule. We are an intervenor in this case and are concerned 
the court may issue an unfavorable ruling, preventing the U.S. Fish and 
Wildlife Service from removing gray wolves in the Western Great Lakes 
states from the list of threatened and endangered species until they 
are deemed recovered throughout their entire historic range. This 
legislation would prevent further judicial review of the 2011 final 
rule. Passage of H.R. 424 in advance of the court's decision would make 
it a moot point. State management of wolves would be restored 
immediately and further litigation would be avoided. It is imperative 
Congress act without delay to pass this important legislation.
    Gray wolves have had a significant impact on elk, deer, other 
wildlife and livestock. We remain confident wildlife agencies in these 
states, through public hunting and trapping, will be able to strike a 
balance for gray wolf and ungulate population management.
    Thank you for the opportunity to comment on this important 
legislation.
            Sincerely,
                                               David Allen,
                                                   President &amp;amp; CEO.
                                 ______
              United States Cattlemen's Association
                                                      July 19, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    On behalf of the United States Cattlemen's Association (USCA), 
thank you for holding the upcoming legislative hearing on Congressman 
Peterson's ``Gray Wolf State Management Act of 2017,'' H.R. 424, taking 
place Wednesday, July 19th at 10:00 a.m.
    USCA supports this practical and bipartisan legislation that 
removes the gray wolf from the List of Endangered and Threatened 
Wildlife and returns management of the gray wolf population in the 
Western Great Lakes District and Wyoming to state control. The current 
listing of the gray wolf leaves farmers and ranchers in those states 
without a legal avenue to protect their livestock from problem wolves. 
The states are best positioned to balance the long-term conservation of 
a viable gray wolf population with the interests of farmers and 
ranchers in protecting their livelihood. This bill prevents judicial 
activism from undermining the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service's (FWS) 
science-based determination that the impacted states demonstrated 
suitable management plans of the gray wolf population.
    Thank you again for holding the upcoming hearing and we look 
forward to helping this bill become law.
            Sincerely,
                                              Kenny Graner,
                                                         President.
                                 ______
               Upper Peninsula Trappers Association
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    Thank you so much for holding a hearing on H.R. 424 and for 
expressing support for this bill. Here in the Upper Peninsula of 
Michigan we are over-run with wolves and our Department ofNatural 
Resources can't do anything about it.
    We had a couple of real rough winters that severely cut back our 
deer population and now the wolves are getting the survivors. Enough 
deer are gone in some areas that the wolves have turned to eating moose 
calves--and get them as soon as they are dropped. Our moose were 
getting close to allowing a limited hunt until our wolves exploded. Now 
they are struggling to survive!
    Our Wolf Advisory Committee was told that when our wolves reached 
200 animals that they could and would be delisted. Now they are just 
shy of 700 and we still can't get them delisted, so they can be managed 
by the State of Michigan! We can't even imagine how people who have 
never even seen a wolf can have more say in wolf management than our 
very capable DNR here in Michigan.
            Thanks again,
                                             Bob Steinmetz,
                                                      NTA Director.
                                 ______
                  Wisconsin Cattlemen's Association
                                                      July 17, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
Re: H.R. 424--Gray Wolf State Management Act of 2017
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    The Wisconsin Cattlemen's Association thanks the House Committee on 
Natural Resources for showing support and granting a hearing for H.R. 
424--Gray Wolf State Management Act of 2017.
    In the United States, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service holds 
complete control over the wolf management system. Once the gray wolf is 
delisted by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Wisconsin's Department 
of Natural Resources' plan will be reinstated. As a part of the wolf 
management plan, the Department of Natural Resources supervised a 
hunting and trapping season for the gray wolf. Under this system, all 
of the concerned parties for agriculture, environmental communities and 
government agencies have come together to formulate this plan. 
According to this plan, the state of Wisconsin has the capacity to home 
350 wolves. The most recent count in the winter of 2016 shows our state 
hosts over 1,000 gray wolves and counting.
    It is imperative we establish a management program to control the 
escalating wolf population in our state. Depredations of livestock in 
Wisconsin have escalated at a very rapid rate as our wolf population 
has grown. If this continues at its alarming fashion, we will witness 
Wisconsin's vibrant livestock industry, of which totals 88.3 billion 
dollars annually, perish before our eyes.
    Agriculture has always been the leading industry in the state of 
Wisconsin. Being home to more than 10,000 beef operations and over 
9,000 dairy farms with a total of animals exceeding 1.5 million head, 
it remains our goal to continue to provide a sustainable industry for 
future generations. It is imperative that the gray wolf population is 
under control to both protect our family farms and an industry that is 
so influential to the success of Wisconsin.
    Thank you for your time and consideration of H.R. 424--Gray Wolf 
State Management Act of 2017.
            Sincerely,
                                                Terry Quam,
                                        Legislative Representative.
                                 ______
                   Wisconsin Farm Bureau Federation
                                                      July 18, 2017
Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman,
Hon. Raul Grijalva, Ranking Member,
House Committee on Natural Resources,
Washington, DC 20515.
    Dear Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva:
    On behalf of the Wisconsin Farm Bureau Federation, I am writing to 
offer our thanks and support of H.R. 424, the Gray Wolf Delisting Bill. 
We appreciate the committee's support of this legislation by scheduling 
a hearing.
    This legislation would reinstate the U.S. Fish and Wildlife 
Service's (FWS) order to remove the gray wolf in Wisconsin from the 
federal Endangered Species List. It also provides legal clarity for the 
gray wolf's status on the Endangered Species list.
    Although wolf numbers in our state have long recovered past the 
point of needing federal protection, lawsuits from animal rights groups 
have kept this issue in a back-and-forth legal limbo. The latest legal 
ruling means that Wisconsin farmers do not have the authority to 
protect their livestock from wolves, even as they are being attacked.
    Wisconsin's most recent population estimation of almost 900 gray 
wolves far exceeds the state Department of Natural Resources' targeted 
management goal of 350. The number of wolves in our state also exceeds 
the USFWS criteria to federally delist wolves here. Wisconsin's 
management plan has successfully followed a science-based approach 
designed to maintain the prescribed wolf population of 350 since 2012.
    The experts at the USFWS have determined Wisconsin's wolf 
population recovered to a level that no longer requires it to be listed 
as endangered. Management of the wolf population should therefore be 
restored to the Wisconsin DNR. Farmers should have the ability to 
protect their livestock from wolves during hunting or trapping seasons, 
or during the act of attacking livestock.
    Thank you, again for your support of H.R. 424 and providing time 
for it to receive a hearing in the House Committee on Natural 
Resources.
            Sincerely,
                                            James A. Holte,
                                                         President.
                                 ______
    This is a major problem. It has been a problem for quite a 
while for my constituents, and it requires an immediate 
solution. The states, not the Federal Government, are best 
equipped to manage the gray wolf populations by balancing 
safety, economic, and species management issues. So, I urge my 
colleagues to vote this bill out of Committee, and I appreciate 
your time.
    And I also would submit that the goal for the gray wolf 
that was originally established was 1,500 in Minnesota, and it 
is 2,423 as of last year. It was 100 in Wisconsin, it is 
currently 689. And it was 100 in Michigan, and it is currently 
678. So, there is no justification for what they did, and these 
wolves have eaten a lot of sheep and cattle, and caused a lot 
of havoc. We need this fixed.
    So, I thank you, Mr. Chairman, for the opportunity to be 
here, and hope that we can move this bill forward. I yield 
back.
</option>
    <option>Prepared Statement of the Hon. Collin C. Peterson, a Representative in 
            Congress from the State of Minnesota on H.R. 424
    Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and distinguished members 
of the Committee, thank you for the invitation to speak in support of 
my bill, the Gray Wolf State Management Act of 2017.
    In 2011, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service determined that gray 
wolves in Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Michigan no longer required Federal 
protections based on two main factors. First, gray wolf population 
numbers in each state remained well above established recovery goals 
set by the 1992 Recovery Plan for the Eastern Timber Wolf. Second, the 
wolf management plans established by each state provided for the long-
term conservation of a viable wolf population in the region. While 
under state management from 2011 to 2014, gray wolf populations 
remained well above recovery goals.
    At the end of 2014, a single judge sitting in a Washington, DC 
courtroom created a big mess by somehow coming to the conclusion that 
gray wolves in Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Michigan need Federal 
protection. This was done despite the scientific evidence conducted by 
the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service that gray wolf populations recovered 
and thrived.
    This judge's decision suddenly put farmers and ranchers throughout 
Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Michigan in a very difficult situation. 
Currently, it is illegal for a farmer to shoot a gray wolf that is 
actively attacking cattle or pets. When attacks occur, my constituents 
are forced to choose between following the law or protecting their 
livestock and livelihoods.
    Wyoming went through a similar situation when a judge single-
handedly relisted wolves in 2014. In March 2017, the D.C. Circuit Court 
of Appeals reversed that court decision and wolves are once again under 
Wyoming state management.
    My bill returns management of gray wolves in Minnesota, Wisconsin, 
and Michigan from the Federal Government back to the states and doesn't 
allow for further judicial review. The bill also includes Wyoming to 
protect the state from further judicial over-reach. The courts have 
created a big enough mess already. But it is important for you to note 
that my bill does not prevent the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service from 
relisting gray wolves in the future.
    I would like to submit for the record supportive letters from 
several organizations and technical documents from the U.S. Fish and 
Wildlife Service and the Minnesota Department of Natural Resources.
    This is a major problem that requires an immediate solution. The 
states--not the Federal Government--are best equipped to manage their 
gray wolf populations by balancing safety, economic, and species 
management issues. I urge my colleagues to vote this bill out of 
Committee and I appreciate the Committee's time.
                                 ______
    The  Chairman. I thank you for that. Those things you want 
added to the record, if you make sure the Clerk gets them, 
without objection they will be added.
    You have obviously stated why we still need to regulate 
those wolves. You went past your goal, you have to stick at the 
goal. You go the 1,500, the 100, and you got it there. Sarcasm, 
sorry.
    Mr. Olson, you are up.
</option>
    <option>                    FROM THE STATE OF TEXAS
    Mr.  Olson. Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and 
members of the Committee, thank you for having me here today 
and for exploring these important issues.
    Texans value their open spaces. We value the land and the 
animals, large and small, on it. Texas is defined by that 
heritage, and it is a legacy I intend to leave to my children. 
And I daresay that an expert on your second panel, the Texas 
Comptroller of Public Accounts, my former Senator from Texas 
District 18, and my dear friend, Glenn Hegar, agrees and may be 
coaxed into giving a thumbs up.
    We need to protect our endangered species, but we need to 
do it in a smart way. Arbitrary deadlines do not help. Neither 
do large, sweeping listings that threaten the communities and 
landowners who have been on that land since before the time 
that states like mine were created.
    That is why I want to thank you for taking a look at my 
bill, H.R. 717, the Listing Reform Act. My bill is designed to 
be part of the solution through a suite of changes you all are 
considering.
    First, my bill seeks to end arbitrary deadlines and make 
sure that the government acts as quickly as possible. As this 
Committee said in its 2014 report on ESA, and I quote, 
``Witnesses have testified that time frames provided currently 
under ESA are not feasible, and that groups are litigating not 
over whether species ought to be listed, but that the Federal 
Government can't comply with rigid 90-day or 12-month time 
frames set by ESA.''
    My bill also makes sure that de-listing petitions do not 
get punted to the end of the line. We have seen that with 
species like the grizzly bear, that de-listing petitions can 
drag on for years after a species is recovered and could be 
protected locally.
    My goal with this bill is to allow the Federal Government 
to triage listing decisions. Let's work on the petitions in a 
way that makes sense for the species, not just on arbitrary 
deadlines that leave us open to lawsuits.
    My bill also adds a new class of listing determinations. 
Under current law, the government may say that listing a 
species might be warranted, but has to be precluded for the 
time being. My bill expands on that, and says the listing of a 
species that might be threatened can be precluded if listing 
would lead to certain serious damages. But if new information 
comes in, or if the species is slipping toward endangered 
status, all bets are off. In the interim, states and locals can 
continue to manage their resources and protect species without 
the Federal hammer coming down.
    I do not want to see species go extinct, but I want to 
achieve a balance that gives our wildlife the protection they 
deserve in a way that protects local communities too. We can do 
both. We can update the law without endangering our legacy for 
the next generation. I think that H.R. 717 is a step in that 
direction.
    Thank you, Mr. Chairman, I yield back the balance of my 
time.
</option>
    <option>Prepared Statement of the Hon. Pete Olson, a Representative in Congress 
                  from the State of Texas on H.R. 717
    Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and members of the 
Committee, thank you for having me today and for exploring this 
important issue.
    Texans value their open spaces. We value the land and the animals 
large and small we have on it. Texas is defined by that heritage, and 
it is a legacy I intend to leave to my children.
    We need to protect our endangered species, but we need to do it in 
a smart way. Arbitrary deadlines do not help. Neither do sweeping 
listings that threaten the communities and landowners who have been on 
that land since before the time states like mine were created.
    That is why I thank you for taking a look at H.R. 717, the Listing 
Reform Act. My bill is designed to be part of a suite of changes you 
all can consider.
    First, it seeks to end arbitrary deadlines and make sure that the 
government acts as quickly as is possible. As this Committee said in 
its 2014 report on the ESA, ``Witnesses have testified that time frames 
provided currently under ESA are not feasible, and that groups are 
litigating not over whether a species ought to be listed, but that the 
Federal Government can't comply with rigid 90-day or 12-month time 
frames set by ESA.'' \1\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \1\ Endangered Species Act Congressional Working Group ``Report, 
Findings and Recommendations'' (2014).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    It also makes sure that de-listing petitions don't get punted to 
the end of the line. As we have seen with species like the grizzly,\2\ 
these de-listing petitions can drag on for years after a species is 
recovered and could be protected locally.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \2\ Natural Resources Committee, ``Bishop: Grizzly Delisting 
Process Emblematic of Need for ESA Reform'' (2017).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    My goal with this bill is a chance for the Federal Government to 
triage listing decisions. Let's work through the petitions in a way 
that makes sense for the species, not just on arbitrary deadlines that 
leave us open to lawsuits.
    The bill also adds a new class of listing determinations. Under 
current law, the government can say that listing a species might be 
warranted but has to be ``precluded'' for the time being. My bill 
expands on that and says that the listing of a species that might be 
threatened can be ``precluded'' if listing would lead to certain 
serious damages. But if new information comes in or if the species is 
slipping toward endangered status, all bets are off. In the interim, 
states and locals can continue to manage their resources and protect 
species without the Federal hammer coming down.
    I do not want to see species go extinct. But, what I am trying to 
achieve is a balance that gives our wildlife the protection they 
deserve in a way that protects local communities too. We can do both. 
We can update the law without endangering our legacy for the next 
generation. I think H.R. 717 is a step in that direction.
    I thank you, Mr. Chairman, and yield back the balance of my time.
                                 ______
    The  Chairman. Thank you. And we will invite you when we 
are done with this panel to join us up here, where a spot is 
available.
    Mr. Gohmert, you are recognized for 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>                CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF TEXAS
    Mr.  Gohmert. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, and thank you for 
allowing me to speak on H.R. 2603, the SAVES Act.
    First, I would like to thank the Committee for considering 
this legislation, and for the staff for all their hard work, 
and especially my dear friend, Representative Brian Babin, who 
has worked hand in hand with me on this vital bill.
    This important legislation will remove duplicative and 
unnecessary regulation, reduce government waste, but, most 
important, it will enhance conservation.
    At the time it was originally enacted, the Endangered 
Species Act's inclusion of non-native species was well-
intentioned, as incipient international regulatory bodies, such 
as the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species, 
which sought to encourage international protections, lacked 
political capital.
    However, like many other aspects of the ESA, the inclusion 
of non-native species is outdated, overly burdensome, and, in 
fact, works against the very intent of the ESA. Instead of 
promoting conservation of these international species, this 
redundant regulation hampers significant non-governmental 
resources in our country genuinely seeking to enhance 
conservation of non-native endangered species through captive 
breeding programs.
    By restricting interstate movement, listing non-native 
species under the ESA renders properly conducted captive 
breeding a near impossibility. According to the American 
Federation of Aviculture and their more than 5,000 members, if 
a collection manager in Missouri would like to bring a new 
bloodline into their macaw collection from a collection in 
Pennsylvania, current regulations are so onerous as to bring 
that plan to a full stop.
    As the Zoological Association of America notes, 
conservationists often rely on the ability to move individual 
animals among collections to best maintain a robust captive 
population and to provide the best opportunities for successful 
breeding of endangered species. The onerous and prohibitive 
regulation of captive bred, non-native species under the ESA is 
counter-productive to conservation efforts.
    Such issues are nothing new for the ESA. Time and time 
again in the modern world, we see the well-intentioned 
legislation pit the Federal Government against the very private 
citizens who have a vested interest in preserving endangered 
species.
    Dr. Janice Boyd of The Parrot Fund states so clearly, ``the 
ESA simply does not deliver conservation benefits to non-native 
species.''
    To give a personal example of what got my attention is when 
a Texan notified me, a conservationist, that he had a number of 
species, as a conservationist, allowed--they had to have 
Federal permit, Federal authorization, but they were notified 
that a breed of antelope they had from Africa was extinct in 
Africa. And, therefore, they were going to take over their land 
and move to have it listed as endangered in the United States.
    So, the American conservationists all over the country that 
had bred thousands and thousands of this now-extinct breed sent 
hundreds of couples over to Africa to reinstate them. But 
because of the threat of the Federal Government to take over 
control of these conservationists' land, they had to get rid of 
all of those they had. Thus, once again, jeopardizing the very 
species that we were supposed to be protecting under this bill.
    The unfortunate reality of the ESA is that it continuously 
burdens commerce and various industries. As the National 
Association of Aquaculture alerted me just a couple of weeks 
ago, the National Marine Fisheries Service posted a notice 
seeking public comment on a proposed listing of a non-native 
giant clam. Several giant clam species are in the marine 
aquarium trade, and U.S.-owned farms in the Pacific are 
successfully producing these animals. These clams should not be 
listed, and if they are, the farms producing them will decline 
as interstate movement and commerce will be catastrophically 
impacted. How is this promoting conservation of the species?
    Removing unnecessary, outdated, and redundant regulatory 
authority over interstate movement of non-native, endangered 
species--and this is very important--that are alive--it is not 
going to help the trade of dead carcasses--but by removing them 
from the listing authority of ESA will enhance conservation, 
and that is why we are doing it. I yield back.
</option>
    <option>   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Louie Gohmert, a Representative in 
             Congress from the State of Texas on H.R. 2603
    Good morning, and thank you for allowing me to speak on H.R. 2603, 
the SAVES Act. First, I'd like to thank the Committee for considering 
this legislation, staff, for all their hard work, and, especially, my 
dear friend Rep. Brian Babin who has worked hand in hand with me on 
this vital bill.
    This important legislation will remove duplicative and unnecessary 
regulation, reduce government waste, and enhance conservation.
    At the time it was originally enacted, the Endangered Species Act's 
(ESA) inclusion of non-native species was well-intentioned, as 
incipient international regulatory bodies, such as the Convention on 
International Trade in Endangered Species (CITES) which sought to 
encourage international protections, lacked political capital. However, 
like many other aspects of the ESA, the inclusion of non-native species 
is outdated, overly burdensome, and, in fact, works against the very 
intent of the ESA. Instead of promoting conservation of these 
international species, this redundant regulation hampers significant 
non-governmental resources in our country genuinely seeking to enhance 
conservation of non-native endangered species through captive breeding 
programs.
    By restricting interstate movement, listing non-native species 
under the ESA renders properly conducted captive breeding a near 
impossibility. According to the American Federation of Aviculture and 
their more than 5,000 members, if a collection manager in Missouri 
would like to bring a new bloodline into their macaw collection from a 
collection in Pennsylvania, current regulations are so onerous as to 
bring that plan to a full stop.
    As the Zoological Association of America notes, conservationists 
often ``rely on the ability to move individual animals among 
collections to best maintain a robust captive population and to provide 
the best opportunities for successful breeding of endangered species. 
The onerous and prohibitive regulation of captive bred, non-native 
species under the ESA is counter-productive to conservation efforts.''
    Such issues are nothing new with the ESA. Time and time again in 
the modern world, we see the well-intentioned legislation pit the 
Federal Government against the very private citizens who have a vested 
interest in preserving endangered species. As the U.S. Association of 
Reptile Keepers asks: ``How is making it illegal to share education 
about ESA-listed and non-native spotted pond turtles by banning sale of 
domestically hatched turtles across state lines helpful to conservation 
of the species?'' As Dr. Janice Boyd of The Parrot Fund states so 
clearly: ``The ESA simply does not deliver conservation benefits to 
non-native species.''
    The unfortunate reality of the ESA is that it continuously burdens 
commerce in various industries. As the National Association of 
Aquaculture alerted me, just a couple weeks ago, the National Marine 
Fisheries Service posted a notice seeking public comment on a proposed 
listing for non-native giant clams. Several giant clam species are in 
the marine aquarium trade and U.S.-owned farms in the Pacific are 
successfully producing these animals. The clams should not be listed, 
and if they are, the farms producing them will surely decline as 
interstate movement and commerce will be catastrophically impacted. How 
is that promoting conservation of the species?!
    Removing unnecessary, outdated, and redundant regulatory authority 
over interstate movement of non-native endangered species by removing 
them from the listing authority of the ESA will enhance conservation 
and reduce the burden these duplicative regulations have on the 
industry. Please join me in supporting this common-sense solution to 
conservation of endangered species.
                                 ______
    The  Chairman. Thank you.
    Mr. Huizenga, you are recognized for 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>              CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF MICHIGAN
    Mr.  Huizenga. Well, thank you, Mr. Chairman, Ranking 
Member Grijalva, and members of the Committee, for holding this 
hearing. I actually had the privilege of being part of a 
working group a couple of years ago that looked at the ESA, and 
I can attest it does need reform.
    My statement today is in support of common-sense 
legislation that makes the Endangered Species Act consistent 
with current law in other areas of government litigation.
    H.R. 3131, the Endangered Species Litigation Reasonableness 
Act, reforms the ESA litigation process while enhancing 
wildlife preservation, improving government efficiency, and 
protecting taxpayer dollars.
    For too long, litigating attorneys representing non-
governmental entities have taken advantage of the Endangered 
Species Act, raking in millions of dollars in taxpayer-funded 
money. In many cases, attorney billing rates have climbed as 
high as $400, $500, or even $750 an hour, with hardworking 
American taxpayers left footing the bill. In times of tight, 
fiscal budgets and escalating national debt, taxpayer dollars 
should be prioritized for the protection and recovery of 
species, not warrantless litigation.
    Let's show taxpayers we respect their hard work by 
respecting their taxes. Records from the Dept. of Justice 
confirm the exploitation and abuse of the Endangered Species 
Act by special interest groups, including at least two 
attorneys who have accrued upwards of $2 million in legal fees 
through ESA litigation. These exorbitant payouts, funded by the 
American taxpayer, only impede efforts to achieve the common 
goal of protecting species and habitats.
    Now, how is this addressed in other areas of government 
litigation? Well, currently, the Equal Access to Justice Act, 
as was brought up by Mr. Gohmert earlier, limits the hourly 
rate for awards of fees to prevailing attorneys to $125 an hour 
in most circumstances. Unfortunately, no such fee cap currently 
exists in ESA citizen suits.
    Quite simply, this bill seeks to correct the current 
Endangered Species Act anomaly that incentivizes attorneys to 
spend time in court needlessly arguing, while earning inflated 
rates at taxpayers' expense. This bill would ensure that all 
Americans who sue the Federal Government are entitled to the 
same reasonable limits when it comes to being awarded taxpayer-
funded attorney's fees.
    Veterans, small businesses, and Federal benefit recipients 
go through this right now. And, frankly, Mr. Chairman, if it is 
good enough for our citizens, it ought to be good enough for 
our flora and our fauna. It is past time to apply this sensible 
cap to ESA suits, as well.
    And, in fact, there was a discussion about this limiting 
access to the courts. There is no limit to access with this 
particular issue. This is a matter of stewardship, of the 
resources of hardworking taxpayers, in my mind. Rather than 
these hardworking taxpayer dollars lining the pockets of trial 
attorneys or special interest groups that have made a business 
by suing the Federal Government, these scarce resources would 
be directed toward making the law more efficient and effective 
for both species and people.
    This would save millions of dollars, while not restricting 
access to the court system at all. If it truly is about 
protecting our flora and our fauna, then this reasonable 
reimbursement rate should be just fine. If it is about making 
money, well, I think you see the opposition.
    Mr. Chairman, I strongly believe that this straightforward 
legislation is a much-needed common-sense update to the ESA, 
and makes the law work better for all parties. I would like to 
thank the Committee for scheduling this hearing on H.R. 3131. 
It is my hope that this Committee will soon continue to take 
further action on this important legislation.
    With that, I yield back.
</option>
    <option>   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Bill Huizenga, a Representative in 
            Congress from the State of Michigan on H.R. 3131
    Thank you Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and members of 
the Committee for holding this hearing on much needed reforms to the 
Endangered Species Act.
    My statement today is in support of common-sense legislation that 
makes the Endangered Species Act consistent with current law. H.R. 
3131, the Endangered Species Litigation Reasonableness Act, reforms the 
ESA litigation process while enhancing wildlife preservation, improving 
government efficiency, and protecting taxpayer dollars.
    For too long, litigating attorneys representing non-governmental 
entities, have taken advantage of the Endangered Species Act, raking in 
millions of dollars in taxpayer-funded money. In many cases, attorney 
billing rates have climbed as high as $400, $500, or even $750 per 
hour, with hardworking American taxpayers left footing the bill. In 
times of tight fiscal budgets and escalating national debt, taxpayer 
dollars should be prioritized for the protection and recovery of 
species, not warrantless litigation.
    Records from the Department of Justice confirm the exploitation and 
abuse of the Endangered Species Act by special interest groups--
including at least two attorneys who have accrued upwards of $2 million 
in legal fees through ESA litigation. These exorbitant payouts--funded 
by the American Taxpayer--only impede efforts to achieve the common 
goal of protecting species and habitats.
    Currently, the Equal Access to Justice Act limits the hourly rate 
for awards of fees to prevailing attorneys to $125 per hour in most 
circumstances. Unfortunately, no such fee cap currently exists for ESA 
citizen suits. Quite simply, this bill seeks to correct the current 
Endangered Species Act anomaly that incentivizes attorneys to spend 
time in court arguing for inflated rates at the taxpayers' expense.
    The bill would ensure that all Americans who sue the Federal 
Government, such as veterans, small businesses, and Federal benefit 
recipients, are entitled to the same, reasonable limits when it comes 
to being awarded taxpayer-funded attorney's fees.
    Rather than taxpayer dollars lining the pockets of trial attorneys 
or special interest groups that have made a business by suing the 
Federal Government under ESA, these scarce resources should be directed 
toward making the law more efficient and effective for both species and 
for people.
    I strongly believe that this straightforward legislation is a much 
needed common-sense update to the ESA that makes the law work better 
for all parties.
    I would like to thank the Committee for scheduling this hearing on 
H.R. 3131. It is my hope that the Committee will soon continue to take 
further action on this important legislation.
                                 ______
    The  Chairman. Thank you. I appreciate that. Once again, I 
will make the same offer to you, Mr. Huizenga. If you would 
like to stay here, I will ask unanimous consent that both Mr. 
Olson and Mr. Huizenga can join us on the dais.
    Without objection, so ordered. Find a seat where there is 
no one sitting, and you are part of us.
    I will now bring the second witness panel up here. I will 
ask the Clerk to change the cards around so you can see where 
you are supposed to be. We will introduce you in a second.
    [Pause.]
    The  Chairman. All right. As you are getting settled in 
there, I would like to introduce this panel to you. I would ask 
the gentleman from Texas, Mr. Gohmert, if he would be happy or 
willing to introduce the Comptroller from the state of Texas to 
the Committee.
    Mr.  Gohmert. Honored to do so. It is my pleasure to 
welcome to the hearing my friend, fellow Texan, and, just as 
importantly, a fellow Texas Aggie, the 36th Texas Comptroller 
of Public Accounts, Glenn Hegar.
    Mr. Hegar worked diligently in Texas to increase government 
efficiency, while reducing government waste: knowledge that 
will prove vital to today's hearing.
    Prior to becoming Texas Comptroller, Mr. Hegar served in 
the Texas House of Representatives and the Texas Senate. So, 
welcome, and thank you for joining us today.
    The  Chairman. Thank you.
    Mr.  Gohmert. Thank you, Mr. Chair.
    The  Chairman. I appreciate you being here. Let me 
introduce Mr. Greg Sheehan, who is the Deputy Director of the 
U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service.
    Mr. Sheehan, before you came back to this place, you were 
the Director of the Utah Division of Wildlife, Natural 
Resources. I am happy to have you back here, where you can 
testify that, even though it is 100 degrees in Utah, which is 
hotter than right here, we don't have the damn humidity, and 
there is such a thing as dry heat. It does make a difference.
    Mr.  Sheehan. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    The  Chairman. I appreciate that. Mr. Jeff Corwin, I 
recognize and welcome you here. You are a biologist and host of 
ABC's Ocean Trek. Thank you for joining us.
    I am going to turn to the gentlelady from Wyoming, if she 
would like to introduce Mr. Willms, who is also on our panel.
    Ms.  Cheney. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, for the opportunity 
to introduce our Wyoming witness today.
    David Willms joined Wyoming Governor Matt Mead's staff in 
2015 to advise on endangered species and other natural resource 
matters. Before joining the Governor's office, David worked on 
endangered species issues as a field biologist, and then as an 
attorney in both the public and private sector.
    As a Senior Assistant Attorney General for the state of 
Wyoming, David represented the State Engineer's Office and the 
Game and Fish Department on issues involving myriad species 
from day-to-day wildlife management to complex matters 
involving Endangered Species Act implementation.
    In private practice, David engaged in a broad-based natural 
resource practice, where he worked on issues related to the 
lesser prairie chicken, greater sage-grouse, black-tailed 
prairie dogs, and a host of other species.
    As a field biologist, David has studied black-tailed 
prairie dogs and associated species in the Thunder Basin Region 
of northeast Wyoming, and his study area included both public 
and private land holdings.
    And David has really been at the forefront of Governor 
Mead's efforts to provide a bipartisan approach to reforming 
the Endangered Species Act, and we are very pleased to have you 
here today and to have the Committee have the opportunity to 
hear about the great things we are doing in Wyoming.
    Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I yield back.
    The  Chairman. Thank you. And I will ask Mr. Tipton if you 
would be kind enough to introduce our final witness, Mr. 
Holsinger from Colorado.
    Mr.  Tipton. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, and a pleasure to be 
able to introduce a fellow Coloradoan. I appreciate the 
opportunity to introduce Mr. Kent Holsinger, Founder and 
Managing Partner of Holsinger Law, LLC. It is a highly regarded 
law firm that specializes in land, wildlife, and water law.
    Since 2003, Kent has built an exceptional client base, 
including leading water, corporate, non-profit, and trade 
associations in Colorado and the West. Prior to that, he did 
serve for 4 years in the Colorado Department of Natural 
Resources.
    Mr. Holsinger, thanks for taking the time to join us here 
today.
    The  Chairman. Thank you, I appreciate that.
    I am going to remind the witnesses that your written 
testimony is already part of the record. You are going to be 
given 5 minutes of oral testimony right now.
    As I said to the other panel, you have to turn the mics on. 
When the timer hits 5 minutes, I will cut you off. Not trying 
to be rude, but we have a lot of you to go through.
    With that, I will turn, first of all, to Comptroller Hegar 
for your 5 minutes for your testimony.
</option>
    <option>                    ACCOUNTS, STATE OF TEXAS
    Mr.  Hegar. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, Members. It is an 
honor and a privilege to be here. I appreciate the opportunity 
to share our experience in working on ESA issues, and comment 
on the bills before you.
    I greatly appreciate the leadership of your colleagues in 
authoring these bills. As Comptroller, I serve as the chief 
steward of the state's finances, and administer a number of 
programs focused on the Texas economy. One of these programs 
works with stakeholders on practical, effective, science-based 
solutions to ESA challenges.
    The ESA is a powerful law that can be inflexible and 
costly, with far-reaching effects on local economies. It can 
threaten agriculture production, oil and gas exploration, real 
estate development, and many other important economic 
activities.
    States must be involved in an open, transparent process for 
reviewing and conserving species that also includes all 
stakeholders, both public and private. Engaging stakeholders is 
essential. This is especially true in states such as Texas, 
where more than 95 percent of all property is privately owned.
    In 2007, as a State Senator, I played an instrumental role 
in creating a stakeholder-driven process to conserve listed 
species in the Edwards Aquifer, which is the primary water 
source for more than 2 million people in south central Texas. 
Use of this aquifer was a source of contention among economic 
and environmental interests for more than 50 years.
    The program resolved the water dispute, while protecting 
the listed species in the aquifer. The Texas Legislature gave 
my current office initial ESA authority in 2009, and when I 
became Comptroller in 2015, I expanded our role, which now 
includes facilitating stakeholder and science-based 
collaborative programs, administering $15 million to fund 
species research, and also holding the permit for the Texas 
conservation plan for the dunes sagebrush lizard, which is 
found in the Permian Basin. Fish and Wildlife cited this plan 
as part of its 2012 decision not to list the species.
    Our work is done through open, transparent updates with 
stakeholders, work groups, compromising of landowners, 
industry, and environmental representatives, Fish and Wildlife, 
as well as the science community. We have identified three key 
areas for enhancing species conservation.
    First, state involvement in leadership provides more 
effective outcomes. States have the relationships and the 
infrastructure to work with landowners, communities, and 
industries, and access to research data, monitoring 
initiatives, and other resources that can lead to better 
listing decisions. In Texas, many agencies have expertise on 
conservation issues and support research related to endangered 
species.
    To ensure the Service can make the best informed decision, 
the ESA should require them to request and use all state agency 
information and participation, while implementing the law.
    A second key area for enhancing species conservation is 
science-based decision. Often relatively little is known about 
the species, providing for a poor basis for decisions that can 
have major economic consequences. The best way to ensure 
economically sound decisions are made is to ensure that science 
is good and current. Better decisions will have fewer impacts 
on state and local economies.
    Our office mainly focuses on the game-changing species, 
those species that if listed endangered could involve 
significant economic impacts. A few examples of the diversity 
of regions and stakeholders involved, we funded $3.6 million in 
research on 12 water mussel species. Listing of these species 
could affect the availability of municipal, industrial, and 
agricultural water use.
    Because of the large number of economic sectors that could 
potentially be affected across the state if the monarch 
butterfly is listed, we funded over more than $1 million in 
research to better understand the butterfly in Texas.
    Also, we supported in the Permian Basin and the Eagle Ford 
shale, two important areas of the state and also the Nation, we 
have funded over $2 million in research to identify the 
additional habitat areas for the species out there.
    A third key area for enhancing species conservation is that 
economic consideration must be part of the decision. There is a 
link between environmental protection and economic success. 
Communities and businesses often rely on the same resources for 
economic growth, such as clean water, that the species needs to 
remain viable. As written, the ESA has very little space for 
economic consideration, and this omission is remarkable, in 
light of the potential impacts on our natural resources.
    As the Services review species for listing, they must be 
able to take into account economic factors, especially when 
analyzing the scope, scale, and potential threats of these 
species. Engaging stakeholders is one of the best ways to 
gather this important economic data to make better informed 
decisions.
    The bills before you will increase the ability of the ESA 
to be more flexible, and make sure these three key areas are 
obtained. I thank you for the opportunity to be here.
</option>
    <option>Prepared Statement of the Hon. Glenn Hegar, Texas Comptroller of Public 
  Accounts on H.R. 717, H.R. 2603, H.R. 1274, H.R. 424, and H.R. 3131
                              introduction
    Thank you for this opportunity to share our views on these bills 
that offer improvements to the Endangered Species Act (ESA). I applaud 
the sponsors for their work toward solutions that can lead to a more 
science-driven process for species conservation and reduction in the 
regulatory burdens and costs for both landowners and businesses. I 
particularly appreciate the leadership of Representatives Gohmert and 
Olson in authoring two of these bills, which would be helpful not only 
to Texans, but for communities across the country.
    In my role as Texas Comptroller of Public Accounts, I serve as the 
chief steward of the state's finances, acting as tax collector, chief 
accountant, chief revenue estimator, and treasurer for all of state 
government, in addition to administering a number of other programs 
focused on the Texas economy. One of these programs focuses on working 
with community leaders, businesses, landowners, and other stakeholders 
to encourage, develop and implement practical, effective, science-based 
solutions to ESA challenges in Texas.
    The ESA is a powerful law that can be inflexible and costly, with 
far-reaching effects on local economies. It can threaten agricultural 
production, oil and gas exploration, real estate development, and many 
other important economic activities. It can involve burdensome and 
expensive requirements that may not have a significant nor a lasting 
beneficial impact on species conservation.
    I believe states need, and must be involved in, an open, 
transparent process for reviewing and conserving species that includes 
all stakeholders, both public and private. Engaging stakeholders is 
essential to getting acceptance and buy in with respect to the ESA. 
This is especially true in states such as Texas, where more than 95 
percent of all property is privately owned. Through collaborative work 
with other state agencies, universities, local communities, 
environmental organizations, and industry stakeholders, we have 
developed unique expertise in how state involvement in ESA issues can 
facilitate species conservation while maintaining local economic health 
and diversity.
    With my time today, I'd like to share examples of our experience 
that highlight the value of state involvement in the ESA decision-
making process, through the gathering of additional scientific data as 
well as information on economic impacts. The bills under review today 
expand the states' ability to become involved in ESA decisions, 
allowing for the use of more complete science in species reviews, and 
providing an opportunity to balance the requirements of species 
management with the unique economic needs of affected communities.v
                               background
    As a sixth-generation Texan from a farming family, I've spent much 
of my time in public service focused on natural resource and private 
property concerns. My direct experience with endangered species issues 
began before my current role as Comptroller. In 2007, as a State 
Senator, I created a stakeholder-driven process to develop a plan to 
conserve listed species in the Edwards Aquifer and maintained an active 
role to assist the stakeholders as they worked through an array of 
extremely difficult issues. This aquifer is the primary water source 
for more than 2 million people in south-central Texas, serving 
domestic, agricultural, industrial, and recreational needs. Use of this 
aquifer was a source of contention among these various interests for 
more than 50 years.
    This stakeholder-driven process led to the successful creation of a 
Habitat Conservation Plan (HCP) that resolved the water dispute while 
providing protection for listed species in the aquifer. This program 
received a 2013 U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (FWS) Partners in 
Conservation Award for its success in using collaboration and 
partnership to address endangered species and water-resource issues.
    In 2009, the Texas Legislature gave the Comptroller's office its 
initial responsibilities in this area and when I became Comptroller in 
2015, I expanded our agency's existing endangered species work. Our 
office currently works on ESA-related issues in three areas:
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Assisting state and local agencies and stakeholders. The 
            Comptroller's office works with state agencies, local 
            communities, private landowners, and businesses to 
            facilitate science-based, collaborative solutions to ESA 
            challenges. As part of this role, I serve as the presiding 
            officer of our state's Interagency Task Force on Economic 
            Growth and Endangered Species. The task force, created by 
            the Texas Legislature in 2009, helps state agencies, local 
            governments, communities, and other stakeholders work 
            within ESA restrictions as efficiently and cost-effectively 
            as possible.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Gathering new scientific data. Our agency administers $15 
            million in appropriations to fund research on little-known 
            species under consideration for ESA listing. We contract 
            with public state universities for scientific research on 
            species being considered for protection under the ESA, thus 
            filling gaps in our understanding of the species, while 
            also ensuring that Federal regulators have the most 
            complete and reliable information possible before making 
            decisions that can have a profound effect on private 
            property rights and local economies. This research is 
            reviewed through open, transparent discussions and updates 
            with stakeholder workgroups comprising of landowners, 
            industry and environmental representatives, FWS, and the 
            scientific community.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Managing conservation plans. The Comptroller's office 
            holds the permit for the Texas Conservation Plan (TCP) for 
            the dunes sagebrush lizard, whose habitat includes portions 
            of the Permian Basin, one of the Nation's most important 
            oil and gas production areas. This 30-year program offers 
            energy producers and landowners regulatory certainty in 
            exchange for implementing specific conservation measures 
            for the lizard. Since the TCP's implementation, fewer than 
            300 of 200,000 acres of its Texas habitat have been 
            disturbed by program participants. FWS cited the TCP 
            favorably in its 2012 decision not to list the species.
    Working with stakeholders, state and Federal agencies and 
researchers, the Comptroller's office has achieved numerous successes 
that demonstrate the value of state input and meaningful participation 
in ESA programs. To date, our efforts include:
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Contributing scientific data that led to an FWS decision 
            not to list the Sprague's pipit, a migratory bird that 
            winters in large portions of south and west Texas with 
            agricultural and oil and gas operations.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Establishing a nationally recognized monarch butterfly 
            research program to gather data on the species and its 
            habitat across its migratory pathway in Texas. If the 
            monarch butterfly is listed under the ESA, communities and 
            numerous economic sectors across the country could be 
            significantly affected.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Developing a comprehensive research initiative to study 
            the status of and threats to freshwater mussels in our 
            state, and to identify conservation approaches to minimize 
            the impact of a potential listing. If a listing of these 
            species requires specific flows in our watersheds, our 
            ability to develop and manage the state's water resources 
            could be affected dramatically, threatening the 
            availability of municipal, industrial, and agricultural 
            water supplies during droughts.
    Our efforts are intended to ensure FWS has the most complete 
information possible to make more informed decisions, while 
strengthening the role of stakeholders and the state in those 
decisions.
    Through this work, we've identified three key areas for enhancing 
species conservation. These include: (1) a meaningful role for state 
involvement in aspects of ESA implementation to provide for more 
effective outcomes, (2) state-sponsored data gathering to ensure better 
science-based decision making, and (3) the need for a consideration of 
economic impacts in listing and conservation decisions. Through all of 
these areas, management, transparency, and fairness are absolutely 
critical.
 state involvement and leadership provides more effective esa outcomes
    Meaningful incorporation of state input to ESA programs, including 
close coordination and the use of state expertise, can greatly improve 
species outcomes. States have unique relationships and infrastructure 
in place to work with landowners, communities and industries 
effectively. Through their universities, they also have access to a 
wealth of research data, monitoring initiatives and other resources 
that can lead to better listing decisions.
    In Texas, we work with a number of agencies that have expertise on 
conservation issues and support research and initiatives on species of 
concern. The Texas Parks and Wildlife Department, for instance, is 
charged with protecting our state's fish and wildlife resources. The 
Texas Commission on Environmental Quality oversees the management of 
state water quality. The Texas Department of Transportation funds 
research on species of interest that may be affected by road projects. 
The Texas State Soil and Water Conservation Board provides technical 
assistance to landowners and administers water quality and pollution 
prevention programs. The Texas General Land Office manages large swaths 
of state land and our coastal resources. The Texas Department of 
Agriculture works closely with agricultural producers and is the 
state's lead agency in regulating pesticide use.
    All of these areas of expertise are critical when addressing 
species of concern.
    To ensure FWS and the National Marine Fisheries Service (Services) 
make the best-informed decisions, the ESA should require them to 
request and use state agency information and participation while 
implementing the law. When working with states, the Services should not 
only work closely with state agencies responsible for fish, plant and 
wildlife resources, but also with other state agencies that have 
information relevant to species status and threats, or that may be 
affected by ESA actions. This coordination could occur directly with 
individual agencies or through the governor's office in each state.
    State-led initiatives offer us a tremendous opportunity to enhance 
species conservation, but they won't succeed without proper management 
and oversight. Even if everything works properly, those who want the 
process to fail will attempt to derail any success. This is why proper 
management is an absolute must, especially in ensuring the best 
available science is used.
                        science-based decisions
    At present, the bulk of time and resources devoted to ESA 
activities is directed toward the listing process itself. Improvements 
to the listing process, driven by new data from the states, will 
increase our ability to prioritize species for review and lead to more 
informed decisions. It also could save time and resources needed for 
the development of appropriate conservation plans.
    Currently, petitioners have to meet a very low bar in terms of 
species information needed to start the listing process. The Services 
must make their initial listing decision, called a 90-day finding, 
based on data submitted by the petitioner as well as readily available 
information. This lack of access to all relevant data can force the 
Services to spend scarce time and funds on species that ultimately may 
not require listing. And in a state such as Texas, again largely 
privately owned, a positive 90-day finding can limit landowners' 
ability to develop and use their property even if the species isn't 
ultimately listed.
    Because of the large number of species under review for listing, an 
in-depth study of every species simply is not possible. Currently, 
decisions on species must be made on the ``best scientific and 
commercial data available.'' But often, relatively little is known 
about the population, range, habitat and needs of these species, 
providing a poor basis for decisions that can have major economic 
consequences. In many instances, the available data is decades old. For 
instance, the last study on the Chihuahua catfish, a species slated for 
a listing decision in 2020, was conducted in the late 1990s. Do we want 
to make a decision on its status based on limited data from decades 
ago?
    The best way to ensure economically sound decisions are made is to 
ensure the science is good and current. Better decisions will have 
fewer impacts on state and local economies, plus ensure a more positive 
result for the species in question.
    As I noted earlier, the Texas Legislature appropriated $15 million 
in the last 5 years to our office to support the study of species under 
review for listing in our state, gather new data and fill gaps in our 
understanding of these species. Our office has focused this funding 
mainly on ``game-changing'' species, those species that, if listed as 
endangered, could involve significant economic impacts to specific 
areas or important economic sectors. I'd like to provide the following 
examples of this work, as well as the diverse set of regions and 
stakeholders included in our programs. This work is being conducted 
openly and transparently, and research conducted with state funding is 
subject to rigorous peer review.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Twelve different freshwater mussel species found in Texas 
            river basins are under review for listing. We have 
            allocated more than $3.6 million to support research on 
            their distribution and genetics, and on appropriate 
            conservation tools. River authorities, agriculture groups, 
            environmental organizations and energy producers are all 
            involved in our stakeholder process to fine-tune the 
            science and identify conservation opportunities.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Because of the importance of Texas landscapes to the 
            monarch butterfly along its migratory pathway, and the 
            large number of economic sectors that may be affected if 
            this species is listed, we funded more than $1 million in 
            research to increase understanding of the butterfly in 
            Texas. Stakeholders involved in this working group include 
            communities, scientists, agricultural interests, 
            environmental groups, landowners and industry 
            representatives.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; The spot-tailed earless lizard is found in the Permian 
            Basin and the Eagle Ford shale, two important oil and gas 
            producing areas in Texas. Our office has funded nearly $2 
            million in research to identify additional habitat areas, 
            learn more about threats to the species, and discuss 
            potential conservation efforts that may be needed, in 
            partnership with farmers, landowners, environmentalists, 
            and the oil and gas industry.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; The Louisiana pine snake historically was found in 
            longleaf pine forests in important timber-producing areas 
            of east Texas. This snake, currently proposed for listing 
            as threatened, has not been seen in Texas since 2012. We 
            supported research to determine if any additional snakes 
            could be found in the state. We are working closely with 
            the state wildlife agency as well as the forestry industry 
            to develop ways to manage habitat in the snake's historical 
            range while still continuing timber activities.
    Our job here is not to be scientists. Rather our job is to 
understand the ESA and the science required for it, as well as the 
species themselves, and to communicate effectively with researchers so 
we can make sure their work is useful to FWS in its decisions. Even so, 
the staff members managing our endangered species work do have 
scientific and legal backgrounds related to species conservation. Dr. 
Robert Gulley, director of our Economic Growth and Endangered Species 
Management Division, has a doctorate in anatomy with over a decade of 
work in biomedical research as well as more than a quarter-century of 
experience as an environmental attorney, including serving 7 years 
working on ESA cases as senior trial attorney at the U.S. Department of 
Justice. In addition, his staff members have scientific and 
conservation backgrounds.
        economic considerations must be a part of the discussion
    I believe that you cannot make fully informed decisions regarding 
species without considering the economies of the regions where they 
live. There is a link between environmental protection and economic 
success. For example, communities and businesses often rely on the same 
resources for economic growth, such as clean water, that the species 
needs to remain viable. As the ESA is written, however, there is very 
little space for economic considerations. This omission is remarkable 
in light of the potential impacts on our Nation's resources.
    In many voluntary conservation programs, stakeholders include 
economic considerations to create successful programs. In the case of 
the Edwards Aquifer program, for instance, a key portion of the program 
involved compensating farmers in the western range of the aquifer for 
restricting water use in times of drought, thus making more water 
available for the species. For the dunes sagebrush lizard, industry 
participation resulted in a plan that minimized oil and gas drilling 
and infrastructure in the lizard's habitat, while allowing for some 
continued activity for an industry that is vital to our state economy 
and state tax revenues.
    To create similar successful outcomes under the ESA, as the 
Services review species for listing, they must be able to take into 
account economic factors, especially when analyzing the scope and scale 
of potential threats to a species. To adequately consider these 
threats, the Services should incorporate economic data on the future 
development of industries that may be affecting the species, and take 
into account any potential changes to industrial technology that may 
decrease the impact on the species. Services staff often do not have 
significant expertise in these economic areas. Engaging stakeholders is 
one of the best ways to gather this important economic data to make 
more informed decisions.
    The consideration of economic impact in critical habitat 
designations is an example of how the ESA can effectively take into 
account economic impacts. An area can be excluded from critical habitat 
designation if it is deemed the benefits of exclusion outweighs the 
benefits of designating the area. Economic impacts is a part of the 
basis for this decision. This consideration of economic impacts should 
be included in listing decisions, especially in cases of threatened 
designations where the ESA already provides the ability to craft 
flexible approaches to provide a benefit to the species.
                   bills will encourage conservation
    The bills before you today incorporate many of these concepts I've 
discussed--state coordination, transparency, usage of more complete 
data, an open process, reduced regulatory burdens, and consideration of 
economic impacts. I believe they are very important bills and an 
important step toward more effective species conservation.
    The Listing Reform Act by Representative Olson (H.R. 717) provides 
time for science-based decisions and acknowledges the importance of 
economic considerations. Giving the Services flexibility in reviewing 
petitioned species rather than requiring adherence to a strict and 
arbitrary deadline allows them to make better use of limited resources 
and work first on species truly in need. This flexibility also gives 
the Services additional time to receive more complete data from the 
states and other parties to give them a more complete view of the 
status of the species. And allowing for consideration of significant, 
cumulative economic effects that could result from a threatened listing 
decision or designation of critical habitat provides opportunities to 
further engage with industry and other stakeholders in developing 
effective conservation programs for species in important economic 
areas.
    Representative Gohmert's SAVES Act (H.R. 2603), de-listing non-
native species, takes into account stakeholder input and economic 
considerations to provide additional opportunities for species 
conservation, reduces the Federal regulatory burden on those working to 
conserve species, and allow for continued economic activities in our 
local communities.
    Representative Newhouse's bill, the State, Tribal and Local Species 
Transparency and Recovery Act (H.R. 1274), directing the Services to 
incorporate state, local and tribal data in its decisions is key to 
opening up the process and ensuring more complete data. The Gray Wolf 
State Management Act of 2017 by Representative Peterson (H.R. 424) is 
another bill emphasizing the importance of state involvement in 
managing species within their borders.
    Finally, while Texas handles a large amount of litigation, our 
office isn't heavily involved in this process. Even so, we support 
efforts such as the Endangered Species Litigation Reasonableness Act 
(H.R. 3131) by Representative Huizenga to bring more equity into the 
litigation process. The proposed changes should minimize litigation by 
ensuring attorney's fees are only awarded to those parties who prevail 
in the litigation.
                               in closing
    These bills and my comments today address several significant 
changes that can be made to improve the ESA's effectiveness, but it 
should only be part of a larger effort to modernize a statute that has 
received too little congressional reform over the years. Many groups 
across the country, including the Western Governors' Association, have 
developed proposals to encourage proactive, voluntary science-based 
species conservation and ESA implementation. In general, these 
recommendations align with our thoughts on how to improve the ESA. I 
encourage you to review their recommendations and incorporate them in 
future legislation as you continue your work on this very important 
issue.
    My office will remain engaged in working with stakeholders and 
continue funding research on species to develop collaborative, 
transparent solutions. We are available as a resource to you and your 
staff as you continue your work. I look forward to working with you as 
you move forward in making the ESA a more workable and effective tool 
for species conservation, while still allowing economic opportunity for 
our communities and citizens.
                                 ______
   Questions Submitted for the Record to Glenn Hegar, Comptroller of 
                    Public Accounts, State of Texas
                   Questions Submitted by Rep. Bishop
    Question 1. As Texas has demonstrated, states are well positioned 
to effectively keep species stable and off the endangered and 
threatened list. However, the Federal Government has often kept states 
away from the table in species designation process.
    1a. How does the Texas program identify which species to preserve?
    Answer. The Economic Growth and Endangered Species Management 
Division (EGESM) of my office is responsible for our species research 
program. The focus of this program to date has been on those species 
currently under review for potential listing by the U.S. Fish and 
Wildlife Service (the Service). Division subject matter experts review 
scientific literature, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service information 
including that on the Environmental Conservation Online System (ECOS), 
existing listing petitions and other listing documents, and similar 
documentation to understand the data available on each species, the 
extent of data gaps, threats to the species, and potential 
effectiveness of conservation measures to ameliorate those threats. 
EGESM also considers the economic impact of a possible listing. In 
establishing our priorities for funding species research, EGESM 
consults with the Texas Parks and Wildlife Department, other state 
agencies, the Service, independent university experts, both in and 
outside of Texas, and stakeholders.
    In identifying species, EGESM staff assess the potential impacts of 
a listing. The factors considered in this review include, but are not 
limited to, the overlap of species habitat with areas of economic 
activity, identification of industry sectors affected by a potential 
listing, consultation with industry and related stakeholder working 
groups, the scope of natural resources potentially affected by a 
listing, and the ability of conservation measures to reasonably 
ameliorate the threats.
    Through this analysis, the program is able to identify those 
species that if listed, could have a significant economic effect on 
Texas citizens, business and communities. These ``game-changer'' 
species with a large potential economic effect are priorities to 
develop additional research and science based conservation programs to 
preserve the species.
    1b. Do you believe that programs like that of Texas in other states 
would help keep species healthy and off the list?
    Answer. I do believe that programs like in Texas can be successful 
in keeping species healthy and off the Federal list of endangered 
species. The Texas Conservation Plan (TCP) is an exemplary model of 
such a successful program. There, the listing of the species was 
avoided through an agreement by the oil and gas industry operating in 
the energy-rich Permian Basin, in coordination with the Comptroller's 
office (CPA), to implement voluntary conservation measures under a 
Candidate Conservation Agreement with Assurances (CCAA). CPA holds the 
permit for the CCAA and oversees the implementation of the TCP. A 
similar CCAA was established in New Mexico with the oil and gas 
industry in that state. The TCP played a large role in the Service's 
decision not to list the dunes sagebrush lizard.
    CPA is currently developing similar programs to either avoid 
listing or minimize the economic impacts of any species listings with 
respect to four Central Texas mussel species and the spot-tailed 
earless lizard, found in the Permian Basin, Eagle Ford shale and 
agricultural areas in the state. These programs center on funding 
strong science to fill extensive gaps in the scientific knowledge 
regarding these species. CPA is engaging diverse stakeholder 
communities in open, transparent, collaborative processes to evaluate 
the scientific data and to see if buy-in is possible for any voluntary 
conservation programs that may be needed to avoid listing or minimize 
the impact of any listing that is appropriate.
    As described in my testimony, as a State Senator, I was very 
involved in the creation and oversight of a program that utilized this 
open, transparent approach to resolve a 50-year old contentious dispute 
over the use of the Edwards Aquifer while protecting the listed species 
that depend on the water from that aquifer.
    I am confident that similar programs, in conjunction with research 
funding and the reforms considered by your Committee, can be successful 
in balancing the needs of the species with the need for a vibrant 
economy in Texas and elsewhere. Also, in appropriate instances, 
avoiding the need to list species as Texas and New Mexico were able to 
do with respect to the dunes sagebrush lizard.
    Question 2. Mr. Olson's Listing Reform Act allows for threatened 
species designations to be precluded due to economic factors, and 
allows for reconsideration of precluded threatened species listings 
only if the Secretary determines there is a danger of species 
extinction, or if the Service receives a new petition that includes 
alternative actions that can be taken to avoid the economic impacts of 
listing.
    2a. Should economic factors be considered in threatened species 
designations, and if so, why?
    Answer. First, I believe that as a general rule, listing decisions 
should be based solely on the science. However, economic factors should 
be considered and, in limited circumstances, where the economic 
consequences of listing outweigh the benefits of listing, reflected in 
the listing decision. Mr. Olson's bill sets out a reasonable approach 
to economic considerations in the listing process. It recognizes that, 
unlike an ``endangered'' determination which requires a finding that 
the species is in actual danger of extinction, a determination that a 
species is threatened requires a finding only that the species may 
become endangered in the future. Under such circumstances, a reasonable 
inquiry into the economic impacts of listing is appropriate. If the 
economic benefits of listing outweigh the benefits of listing, Mr. 
Olson's bill does not over-ride the determination that listing is 
warranted. Instead, it simply precludes listing until such time that 
the species is endangered or a petition is filed mitigating the 
economic impacts.
    Beyond the reasonableness of the approach, I support Mr. Olson's 
bill because, although the status of threatened species is less 
imperiled than that of an endangered designation, the economic 
consequences of both determinations may be the same. Under current 
Service regulations, absent promulgation of a 4(d) rule, threatened 
species are subject to the same requirements as endangered species with 
respect to Sections 7 and 9 of the Act.
    2b. From your perspective, would the ability to preclude threatened 
species listings due to economic factors facilitate higher-quality 
listing decisions that benefit both species and our Nation?
    Answer. The ability to preclude threatened species listing due to 
economic factors can allow for a more reasonable balance between 
species protection and economic growth. Precluding species can also 
provide additional flexibility in developing conservation programs for 
species of concern through a non-regulatory and voluntary environment. 
Candidly, I am somewhat concerned, however, that because the scientific 
boundaries between threatened and endangered are obscure, the Service 
may decide to avoid the requisite economic considerations by finding a 
species to be endangered.
                   Questions Submitted by Rep. Pearce
    Question 1. How does the science produced by your universities and 
other state agencies compare to the science that the Fish and Wildlife 
Service would otherwise be forced to rely on?
    Answer. The Service often relies only on existing research--some 
current, some not. In many instances, the research was not designed to 
answer the specific questions of the listing process. The funding 
administered by CPA provides science that is more current and complete 
than what the Service might otherwise have available to use in make 
listing decisions.
    Our research is focused on filling the gaps in understanding of 
species and provide data specifically designed to inform the Species 
Status Assessment and listing process. CPA, in designing and funding 
the science, consults with the Texas Parks and Wildlife Department, 
other state agencies, independent university experts, the Service, and 
stakeholders. Independent technical advisory panels are used during the 
course of the research to ensure that sound approaches and methods are 
being employed. Independent peer review of the science is commonly used 
to ensure the validity of the research.
    Question 2. You mentioned in your testimony that you are 
administering $3.6 million to support research ``12 different 
freshwater mussel species.'' You also claim the research is on their 
``distribution and genetics, and on appropriate conservation tools.''
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Is one of those species the Texas Hornshell mussel 
            (Popenaias popeii)?
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; Can you forward any science you have on this species to my 
            office?
    Answer. The Texas hornshell is one of the species funded by CPA. 
Scientific information from my office has been forwarded to the office 
of Representative Pearce. This information includes a final report on 
research by Texas A&amp;amp;M University on the Texas hornshell and other 
mussels in west and central Texas, and a final report on research by 
Texas State University on the Texas hornshell and other aquatic species 
in the Delaware River in Texas.
                                 ______
    The  Chairman. Thank you. I appreciate that. We will now 
turn to Mr. Sheehan for your 5 minutes. Welcome to the 
Committee, welcome back to Washington, welcome to the 
bureaucracy.
    [Laughter.]
    The  Chairman. You have 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>                        WILDLIFE SERVICE
    Mr.  Sheehan. Thank you. Good morning, Chairman Bishop, 
Ranking Member Grijalva, and members of the Committee. My name 
is Greg Sheehan, and I am the Acting Director of the U.S. Fish 
and Wildlife Service. I appreciate the opportunity to testify 
before you today on five bills to amend the Endangered Species 
Act.
    As I said, I am a new appointee of the Fish and Wildlife 
Service, but I have been engaged in the ESA issues for many 
years. I have spent the past 25 years with the state of Utah in 
natural resource and wildlife management, with most of the last 
5 years of my career as the Director for the Utah Division of 
Wildlife Resources.
    I partnered with the Fish and Wildlife Service through my 
participation on the Joint Federal-State Task Force on 
Endangered Species Act Policy. Additionally, I served as 
Chairman of the Threatened and Endangered Species Policy 
Committee for the Association of Fish and Wildlife Agencies.
    As the Director of our state wildlife agency, I was 
involved in actions with many species, including desert 
tortoise, California condor, sage-grouse, gray wolves, and Utah 
prairie dogs, among others.
    The ESA is one of our Nation's most important wildlife 
conservation laws. Its purpose is to conserve threatened and 
endangered species and their ecosystems. The law directs the 
Service to use the best-available science, scientific and 
commercial information, to determine whether a species needs to 
be listed to identify and address the threats to the species, 
and to facilitate the recovery of the species.
    I find it helpful to think of the ESA as a hospital, where 
critically ill patients are admitted in anticipation of 
recovery. In this hospital, there has been success in keeping 
the ESA patients from dying, but not so much on getting them 
discharged in healthy condition. Therefore, we need to step up 
our efforts to quickly diagnose the problems, define recovery 
actions, and get those patients back out into society.
    In the case of these ESA patients, that means getting them 
back under state management authority. While there are those 
who believe otherwise, the ESA, the hospital was never intended 
to keep all patients indefinitely. Just as is the case with any 
hospital, there are limited resources to manage the patients, 
and we need to focus those resources on those that are in the 
greatest need, not those who are recovered and simply waiting 
to be released.
    Success of the ESA will ultimately be defined by the number 
of patients leaving the hospital, not the number going in.
    While the ESA has had success since its passage 43 years 
ago, there have been challenges, as well. My goal, as Acting 
Director of the Service, is for the organization to be a better 
neighbor and partner to the public and states.
    It is essential that we forge collaborative partnerships 
with landowners, states, tribes, territories, local 
governments, and industry. The resources brought to the table 
by these partners is fundamental for achieving the conservation 
objectives of the ESA. It is time that we recognize those 
efforts and rebuild the collaborative spirit of conservation 
that has restored most all fish and wildlife species in America 
during the past 120 years.
    Additionally, we must ensure balanced conservation 
stewardship, while engaging our committed industry partners, 
including power, water, energy, timber, farmers, and others, to 
ensure that ESA regulatory requirements do not overtake our 
ability to be strong and grow as a nation.
    There are three tools in our toolbox to achieve these 
goals.
    First is our ability to seek out and retain top-notch 
people on the ground who have the inter-personal skills and 
ability to work with landowners, industry representatives, 
local governments, tribes, and state agencies. There are many 
on the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service team that have those 
skill sets, and who can succeed at this heavy lift.
    Second, we need effective agency policy. This policy is 
fundamental in creating a defensible rule book that all can 
use, as we aspire to achieve the goals of species and ecosystem 
conservation, as well as societal growth and its associated 
demands on natural resources.
    The third tool available is the set of legislative 
authorities created by Congress. The laws you craft identify 
the sideboards that we must operate within to successfully 
implement the ESA and, hence, work toward the conservation of 
fish, wildlife, and plant species in America.
    The bills before the Committee today seek to improve the 
implementation of the ESA and, in general, the Administration 
supports them. My written testimony contains comments on each 
of the bills. We would appreciate the opportunity to meet with 
the Committee and bill sponsors to discuss technical 
modifications as the bills work through the legislative 
process.
    We are committed to making ESA work for the American people 
to accomplish its purpose of species conservation. I am happy 
to answer any questions you have, and thank the Committee for 
this opportunity to testify today.
</option>
    <option> Prepared Statement of Gregory Sheehan, Acting Director, U.S. Fish and 
 Wildlife Service on H.R. 424, H.R. 717, H.R. 1274, H.R. 2603 and H.R. 
                                  3131
                              introduction
    Good morning Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and members 
of the Committee. I am Greg Sheehan, Acting Director for the U.S. Fish 
and Wildlife Service (Service). I appreciate the opportunity to testify 
before you today on five bills to amend the Endangered Species Act of 
1973 (ESA). I have spent most of the last 5 years of my career as the 
Director for the Utah Division of Wildlife Resources, where I was very 
involved in the implementation of the ESA from the state perspective. I 
dealt with individual species issues in Utah and was involved in 
broader policy discussions through the Western Governors' Association 
and my participation on the Joint Federal/State Task Force on 
Endangered Species Act Policy. I was also Chair of the Threatened and 
Endangered Species Policy Committee for the Association of Fish and 
Wildlife Agencies (AFWA). I am hopeful that those experiences will give 
me a solid framework from which to serve in my new role as Acting 
Director of the Service.
    Each of the bills--H.R. 424, H.R. 717, H.R. 1274, H.R. 2603, and 
H.R. 3131--is focused on improving implementation of the ESA to reduce 
or eliminate certain burdens on the public and to help achieve the 
ESA's statutory purpose to conserve threatened and endangered species 
and their ecosystems. In general, the Administration supports these 
bills and the Service welcomes the opportunity to work with the 
Committee to address some recommended technical modifications.
    The Administration is committed to making the ESA work for the 
American people. While the ESA has had some success since its passage 
over 40 years ago, challenges still remain. Implementation of the law 
regularly generates controversy among private landowners, regulated 
industries, and environmental advocates alike. In particular, in 
Western states, the law and certain species have become lightning rods 
for intense disagreement. My goal as the Acting Director of the Service 
is for the organization to be a better neighbor and partner to the 
public and the states. The Federal role under the ESA in preventing 
extinctions and facilitating recovery is critical; but states and the 
people on the ground who have long been stewards of the land are in the 
best position to be the primary caretakers of species over the long 
term.
    I look forward to discussing these issues and working with the 
Committee to address them in these and other legislative efforts.
                               background
    The ESA is one of our Nation's most important wildlife conservation 
laws. It is implemented jointly by the Service and the National Marine 
Fisheries Service (NMFS, together, ``the Services''). The law's stated 
purpose is to provide a program and means for the conservation of 
threatened and endangered species and the ecosystems upon which they 
depend. When a species is designated as threatened or endangered--or 
``listed'' under the ESA--it is in urgent need of help. The law directs 
the Services to use the best available scientific and commercial 
information to determine whether a species needs to be listed, to 
identify and address the threats to the species, and to facilitate the 
recovery of the species.
    Successes under the ESA almost always involve partnerships between 
the Service and others--states, tribes, territories, local governments, 
private landowners, and other Federal agencies. Partnership efforts 
guided by the Service have led to several recent decisions to de-list 
species due to recovery. These include the Yellowstone population of 
grizzly bear, Louisiana black bear, Oregon chub, Delmarva fox squirrel, 
Virginia northern flying squirrel, Modoc sucker, island night lizard, 
and brown pelican. Conservation partnerships have also prevented the 
need to list a number of species that were once in trouble, including 
the New England cottontail, dunes sagebrush lizard, and arctic grayling 
in Montana.
    Despite these successes, there are also challenges and frustrations 
with implementing the Endangered Species Act. I find it helpful to 
think of the ESA as a hospital, where critically ill patients are 
admitted in hopes of recovery. We have done a pretty good job of 
keeping those patients from dying, but not so well on getting them 
discharged in healthy condition. Therefore, we need to step up our 
efforts to quickly diagnose the problems, define recovery actions, and 
get those patients back out into society. The ESA hospital was never 
intended to keep all patients indefinitely. I want the Service and our 
partners to be more successful in recovering listed species so that the 
ESA is not needed for their protection.
    Making the Service more successful in achieving species recovery is 
a multi-faceted endeavor:
  1.  A collaborative partnership with states, tribes, territories, 
            local governments, and landowners is essential for 
            achieving the conservation objectives of the ESA. The 
            Service has made some important investments in this area, 
            including through our development of policy and tools for 
            voluntary conservation agreements, the establishment and 
            support of a Joint Federal/State Task Force on Endangered 
            Species Act Policy and our support and active participation 
            in the Species Conservation and the Endangered Species Act 
            Initiative of the Western Governor's Association. We will 
            build on those efforts to ensure we have a strong 
            foundation of trust and partnership as we continue to seek 
            to improve implementation of the ESA.
  2.  Our ability to succeed in conservation efforts is also dependent 
            on our people on the ground, who need to have the skills 
            and ability to work with landowners and agencies on 
            solutions that serve the needs of both the species and the 
            landowners. Our Partners for Fish and Wildlife program and 
            Joint Ventures programs have been great models for that 
            approach, and I would like to see those kinds of 
            relationships with landowners and local communities 
            reflected more broadly throughout the Service, including in 
            our endangered species recovery work. The Service has made 
            progress in recent years, but there is still more work to 
            do.
  3.  Being more successful in species recovery also requires effective 
            and creative agency policy. I fully support the recent 
            direction from Congress through the appropriations process 
            to focus more intently upon the mandatory duties associated 
            with recovery of listed species--timely development of 
            recovery plans, reviews every 5 years of the status of 
            listed species, and timely rulemaking to down-list or de-
            list species that are recovering. There are many competing 
            demands for our limited time and energy, and we must have 
            clear agency policy that establishes our priorities and 
            encourages conservation partnerships.
  4.  Our legislative authorities are clearly the backbone for 
            successful implementation of the ESA and recovery of listed 
            species. The bills under consideration by this Committee 
            are all focused on helping improve implementation of the 
            Act, and we look forward to working with the Committee on 
            these measures as they move through the legislative 
            process.
    To that end, we offer the following comments on the individual 
bills under consideration today:
H.R. 424--Gray Wolf State Management Act
    H.R. 424, the Gray Wolf State Management Act, would require the 
Service to reissue the 2011 Western Great Lakes population de-listing 
rule and the 2012 Wyoming population de-listing rule. It would also 
insulate both rules against judicial review. Each of these de-listing 
rules was based on the best available science, was consistent with the 
requirements of the ESA, and reflected extensive work with the relevant 
states and a deliberative and lengthy public comment process. The 
legislation would not legislatively de-list these wolf populations, 
rather it would reinstate science-based rules that went through the 
public rulemaking process.
    Earlier this year, the Federal Government prevailed in litigation 
challenging the 2012 Wyoming de-listing rule, and has accordingly de-
listed that population and transitioned management to the state. This 
legislation would not, in the Service's view, affect our recent rule 
that reaffirmed the de-listing of the Wyoming population.
    The Service determined that the Western Great Lakes gray wolf 
population has exceeded recovery goals and is biologically recovered. 
Our de-listing rule was challenged and vacated, and that decision is 
currently under appeal.
H.R. 717--Listing Reform Act
    H.R. 717, the Listing Reform Act, would allow the Service to 
prioritize petitions other than by the order received, except that 
listing petitions would not be prioritized over de-listing petitions. 
The legislation would also remove the 90-day and 12-month finding 
deadlines for petitions. Finally, it would add an option for warranted 
but precluded findings for petitions to list species as threatened if 
the listing or critical habitat designation would result in significant 
cumulative economic impacts.
    The provision allowing the Service to prioritize petitions based on 
need would give the Service more flexibility to implement the ESA. We 
believe that removing the deadlines for reviewing petitions would give 
the Service even more flexibility and reduce the potential for future 
litigation.
    The Service would, however, like to work with the Committee 
regarding the bill's proposed warranted but precluded determination on 
petitions for threatened listings to better understand how economic 
impacts should be appropriately considered.
H.R. 1274--State, Tribal, and Local Species Transparency and Recovery 
        Act
    H.R. 1274, the State, Tribal, and Local Species Transparency and 
Recovery Act, would require all data used to make a listing 
determination to be made available to affected states prior to making a 
listing determination. It would also modify the term ``best scientific 
and commercial data available'' to include all data submitted by 
states, tribes, and local governments.
    The Service has worked to address concerns regarding transparency 
of the data used to make listing determinations, but recognizes that 
complications remain. The Service would recommend modifying this 
legislation to require the Service to consider all data submitted by 
states, tribes, and local governments, rather than automatically 
deeming that data to be the ``best scientific and commercial data 
available'' as currently required in the bill. Defining that term to 
automatically include data submitted by states, tribes, and counties, 
without regard to its quality, would be a significant departure from 
scientific integrity standards.
H.R. 2603--Saving America's Endangered Species (SAVES) Act
    H.R. 2603, the Saving America's Endangered Species (SAVES) Act, is 
bipartisan legislation that would prevent non-native species that are 
found in the United States from being treated as federally threatened 
or endangered. We understand the primary intent of this legislation is 
to reduce duplication in the regulation of non-native species in the 
United States. The Service notes that the ESA and the Convention on 
International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora 
(CITES) serve different purposes and species, and would welcome the 
opportunity to discuss this further. We also understand that a 
secondary goal of the legislation is to reduce regulation of the 
interstate movement of non-native species in the United States. The 
Service currently authorizes activities with non-native captive-bred 
wildlife that benefit the conservation of listed species. Based on our 
initial analysis, we note that bill as introduced could create 
enforcement challenges related to wildlife trafficking. We welcome the 
opportunity to work with the sponsor and Committee to examine these 
efforts.
H.R. 3131--Endangered Species Litigation Reasonableness Act
    H.R. 3131, the Endangered Species Litigation Reasonableness Act, 
would subject awards to prevailing parties in ESA citizen suits to 
judicial code standards. This legislation would in effect limit 
attorney's fees for successful citizen plaintiffs in ESA cases against 
the Federal Government. The time and cost of litigation is one of the 
significant challenges we face in implementing the ESA. As currently 
drafted, it is unclear whether the legislation would require that all 
prevailing fee awards be paid through annual appropriations, rather 
than having the option to pay through the Judgment Fund as is current 
law. The Service would welcome the opportunity to work with the 
Committee to clarify this aspect of the legislation.
                               conclusion
    The Service supports the goals of these bills and welcomes the 
opportunity to work with the Committee to address some technical 
modifications. The Service is committed to making the ESA work for the 
American people to accomplish its purpose of conserving threatened and 
endangered species and protecting the ecosystems upon which they 
depend. While the ESA has had some success since its passage over 40 
years ago, there are greater opportunities ahead. I look forward to 
discussing these issues and working with you to address them in these 
and other legislative efforts.
                                 ______
 Questions Submitted for the Record to Greg Sheehan, Acting Director, 
                     U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service
                   Questions Submitted by Rep. Bishop
    Question 1. Well-funded environmental groups that engage in 
litigation against the Department have the resources, including 
taxpayer-funded grant money, to litigate unnecessary matters as a means 
to increase their attorney's fees awards and to boost fundraising 
efforts. Would there be more resources, particularly in terms of staff 
time and focus, for species conservation efforts if there was a 
decrease in the amount of unnecessary litigation against the 
Department?
    Answer. When the Service dedicates its time and budget to defending 
prior court decisions, it redirects resources away from our 
conservation mission, which detracts from the Service's ability to 
prioritize and align our work with the most important conservation 
priorities as we see them.
    Question 2. The Listing Reform Act allows for threatened species 
designations to be precluded due to economic factors, and allows for 
reconsideration of precluded threatened species listings only if the 
Secretary determines that there is a danger of species extinction, or 
if the Service receives a new petition that includes alternative 
actions that can be taken to avoid the economic impacts of listing. 
From your perspective, would the ability to preclude threatened species 
listings due to economic factors facilitate more comprehensive listing 
decisions that benefit both species and our Nation?
    Answer. The ESA currently directs the Service to make listing 
decisions based solely upon the best available scientific and 
commercial information regarding the status of the species and the 
threats that it faces, after considering protective efforts. An 
economic analysis done during the listing determination process would 
provide a comprehensive assessment of the economic impacts resulting 
from a potential listing. Should Congress decide to amend the ESA to 
include economic considerations as part of listing criteria, it would 
create a more comprehensive review that the Service would then assess 
and evaluate petitions accordingly. At this time, without further 
clarification and definition, it would be difficult for the Service to 
implement the bill as it is currently written.
    Question 3. State-generated data and management expertise are 
utilized by states in species management efforts before listing and 
after de-listing. Such state-generated information is a valuable 
resource for the Federal Government, and use of it could alleviate some 
pressure upon agency resources and allow for more thorough and improved 
species decision-making processes. Yet, these resources have not been 
consistently utilized in the past. Furthermore, the data that the 
Federal Government does use in species decisions is not shared with the 
states, nor is it transparent. The State, Tribal, and Local Species 
Transparency Act would require greater transparency and consideration 
of state-generated data. How can the consideration of state, tribal, 
and local data assist the Federal Government in its decision making?
    Answer. The Service agrees that state-generated information is a 
valuable resource. Often, the states are among the best sources of such 
information, particularly with respect to game and other actively 
managed species. In many cases, state partners are the only entities 
with information on certain species. State partners are often 
monitoring a wider spectrum of species than the Service and often are 
our first source of information about a species.
    The Service recently modified our petition regulations to ensure 
that states are formally notified of petitions in a timely manner and 
their data available to the Service to place petitions in proper 
context as the Service develops our 90-day finding. If we proceed to a 
status review (which could lead to a listing proposal), the Service 
actively solicits all available information, including state, tribal, 
and local data formally through Federal Register notices, as well as 
informally through regular interactions with states, tribes, and other 
contacts. If a listing proposal is made, public comment and additional 
data are solicited at that time as well. Additionally, grants through 
the Cooperative Endangered Species Conservation Fund are provided to 
states, and the resulting information from those grants assists in our 
decision making. Such information is often essential in determining if 
a species warrants listing or has recovered to the point of de-listing 
or down-listing.
    Question 4. The program in Texas, and similar efforts in other 
states, have generated high-quality data and successfully kept species 
off of the list. Such information is valuable for Federal decision 
making and could demonstrate how best to manage species in specific 
areas.
    4a. How will the Federal Government support state efforts to 
contribute such data at the Federal level?
    Answer. As noted above, we formally and informally solicit 
information from state partners during our assessment process. As the 
management authority for most non-federally listed species, the states 
are often the primary source of information on these species. We 
recognize that better scientific information leads to better decision 
making under the ESA and appreciate the significant contributions made 
by states to improve the quality of data on the species that are under 
consideration for ESA decisions. Our work to make all petitions 
publicly available upon receipt, to develop multi-year listing work 
plans, and to strategically prioritize our petition work so that 
species for which additional information could affect the petition 
finding are put later in the queue, are all designed to support state 
efforts to contribute data to inform our work at the Federal level.
    4b. How will the Department support state efforts to preserve 
species and keep them off of the list?
    Answer. The Department and the Service believe in the strength, 
effectiveness, and value of collaborative conservation efforts prior to 
a species considered for listing under the ESA. This collaborative 
conservation with partners may provide species with a better chance of 
thriving than regulatory actions and protections. Bringing local 
government, landowners, and others back to the conservation table can 
be difficult after a listing action. With that in mind, keeping the 
species from being listed through collaborative conservation efforts is 
a model that works. The Service will continue to be proactive in these 
types of efforts.
    For example, collaboration between the Service and the Southeastern 
Association of Fish and Wildlife Agencies on an at-risk species 
initiative (SEARS) resulted in petitioners withdrawing 45 species when 
presented with the data compiled by the partnership. This initiative 
has helped spur similar efforts across the country, including one led 
by the Western Association of Fish and Wildlife Agencies and Regions 2 
and 6 of the Service for 12 states across the West.
                  Questions Submitted by Rep. Bordallo
    Question 1. On July 18, 2017, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 
(Service) released its final biological opinion (0lEPIF00-2015-F-0025 &amp;amp; 
0lEPIF00-2016-F-0185) regarding potential adverse impacts on the 11 
ESA-listed species from the proposed relocation of U.S. Marine Corps 
(USMC) personnel from Okinawa, Japan to Guam. Will the Service recommit 
to providing all additional technical assistance/guidance needed for 
the U.S. Department of the Navy (DON) to fully implement the 
conservation measures specified in the final biological opinion?
    Answer. The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (Service) issued the 
July 18, 2017, final biological opinion regarding the proposed 
relocation of U.S. Marine Corps personnel from Japan to Guam after 
consultation with the Department of the Navy. The Service is committed 
to working with the Navy to provide the technical assistance and input 
necessary to ensure successful implementation of the biological opinion 
and conservation of Guam's imperiled species.
    Question 2. Given the importance of the USMC relocation (proposed 
action) for national security, what steps is the Service taking or 
planning to make additional agency personnel/resources available to DON 
to support conservation measure implementation?
    Answer. The Service participates in regular meetings with 
Department of Defense (DOD) officials to discuss priorities and needs 
and to ensure our agencies are aligned and deploying resources 
accordingly. The Service recognizes the collaboration and technical 
assistance needs of the DOD in the Pacific and strives to meet those 
needs within allocated funding and staffing levels.
    Question 3. Is the Service confident that current regional agency 
resources/personnel are sufficient to meet the Service's obligations to 
support the DON's implementation of the conservation measures 
identified in the final biological opinion?
    Answer. Yes. The Service is confident that given current allocated 
funding and staffing levels, we will be able to support the Department 
of the Navy's implementation of the conservation measures identified 
within the final biological opinion.
    Question 4. To the maximum extent practicable, will the Service 
commit to meet all the deadlines and time frames specified by the final 
biological opinion, including providing agency responses to DON in a 
timely manner?
    Answer. The Service is committed to working with DON to meet time 
frames identified within the biological opinion, given current 
allocated funding and staffing levels. Coordination throughout the 
consultation process has resulted in improved communication and 
technical assistance between our agencies, and we expect that will 
continue.
    Question 5. What is the Service doing to address concerns about 
inadequate public access to the Guam National Wildlife Refuge, 
particularly the Ritidian Unit?
    Answer. The Ritidian Unit of the Guam National Wildlife Refuge is 
currently open to the public from 7:30 a.m. to 4:00 p.m., 7 days a 
week, and currently receives about 90,000 visitors a year, hosting 200-
300 visitors on the weekends. The Refuge is subject to closure on all 
major Federal holidays or during bad weather, high-surf advisories or 
other hazardous conditions in the interests of public safety. The 
Service would welcome the opportunity to work with you and your office 
to address any concerns regarding public visitation access to the 
Ritidian Unit.
    Question 6. Is the Service considering, planning, or willing to 
examine formal mechanisms for local consultation/input regarding access 
at the Refuge, including right-of-ways to privately owned land adjacent 
to the Ritidian Unit?
    Answer. The Ritidian Unit of the Guam National Wildlife Refuge lies 
within the designated Surface Danger Zone for the Marine Corps Live 
Fire Training Range. The Refuge road and unimproved right-of-way is 
currently used by adjacent landowners. In the future, access to this 
site will be controlled by the Navy, consistent with public safety 
concerns and the direction provided by Congress in the National Defense 
Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2015. We continue to support an 
alternate access route that would run outside of the Refuge and Surface 
Danger Zone. The U.S. Government will continue to work with neighboring 
landowners on access issues, while taking into account public safety 
concerns.
                   Questions Submitted by Rep. Pearce
    Question 1. You mention in your testimony the necessity for Fish 
and Wildlife Service staff on the ground to work with local landowners. 
We have a situation in my district regarding the New Mexico Meadow 
Jumping Mouse and a rancher. To date, the Fish and Wildlife has been 
unwilling to work toward a solution that works for everyone.
    Would you commit to working with our office to attempt to find 
common ground?
    Answer. Yes. The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (Service) would be 
happy to meet with your office and the U.S. Forest Service (USFS) to 
work toward a solution that addresses your concerns and those of your 
constituent while being consistent with the law. Service and USFS 
representatives have met with livestock grazing permittees to discuss 
best management practices for grazing activities that would conserve 
the New Mexico meadow jumping mouse and are committed to promoting 
collaboration with the ranching community. If our past efforts have not 
resulted in conservation actions that are suitable to the rancher and 
the needs of the species, then we must re-evaluate those efforts. We 
are committed to doing so.
                                 ______
    The  Chairman. Thank you.
    We will now turn to Mr. Corwin for your 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>                        WITH JEFF CORWIN
    Mr.  Corwin. Thank you very much. Good morning, Chairman 
Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and members of the House 
Natural Resources Committee. My name is Jeff Corwin, and I come 
to you today as a wildlife biologist, a television presenter, 
an avid outdoorsman, and a father. And I am here to discuss 
with you today the importance of the Endangered Species Act.
    I have been fortunate over my career to have many profound 
and thrilling encounters with some of our world's most 
incredible creatures. I truly feel blessed to have my life 
passion flourish into a rewarding career. And I believe this 
opportunity could only have materialized in our great country.
    A few years ago, I had the heart-pounding opportunity to 
dive with giant, tractor-sized Steller sea lions off the coast 
of Alaska to document the impact of the warming Prince William 
Sound. If you ever want to feel truly insignificant, go 
eyeball-to-eyeball with a pugnacious, 5,000-pound Steller sea 
lion at 80 feet.
    Alongside the heroes of the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, 
I helped rescue a desperately ill California condor, a bird 
that was on death's door from lead poisoning. Her blood test 
revealed that she had enough toxins in her to kill 12 adult 
men. Incredibly, she not only survived through herculean 
rehabilitation efforts, but she was released back into the 
wild.
    Why all this effort for a single bird? Well, at one time 
there were only less than 20 of these birds. Today, more than 
400 survive out in the wild. And that is because every condor 
matters, and that is because of the Endangered Species Act.
    In 2008, while white-knuckled, gripping the seat of a low-
flying helicopter, I swooped across a vast, expanse of ice with 
a team from the U.S. Geological Survey on a quest to capture a 
mighty polar bear. Soon, we spotted a robust sow with two 
galloping cubs in tow, as they moved across the expansive ice. 
The wind was whipping at 40 miles an hour, and the temperature 
was a face-numbing ^70 degrees Fahrenheit.
    Despite the bitter cold, my heart was warmed from this 
remarkable encounter, and I savored every second of this humble 
moment, working with these scientists, as they collected 
incredibly important data for genetics and health assessment 
and, of course, attached an incredibly complex transmitter to 
track this creature. Unfortunately, the results from that test 
revealed that the cubs had ingested heavy metal toxins through 
the milk from their mother: a powerful example of, no matter 
how remote, wildlife remains vulnerable to the negligence of 
human kind.
    I have been fortunate to experience the magnificent wonders 
of nature, and I can say unequivocally that there is no other 
place on Earth that boasts the diversity of landscape and 
creatures than what we have here in our country. We are truly 
blessed with an extraordinary natural heritage, and we are 
lucky to walk out each day and experience the natural splendor 
that is uniquely ours.
    I have seen firsthand the amazing efforts of the talented 
men and women who are on the front lines of our agencies of 
conservation, fighting to save endangered species. Recovering 
endangered species from the brink of extinction and restoring 
their habitat is one of our Nation's greatest success stories.
    Think of the symbol of our country: the bald eagle. In the 
1970s, only 400 pair remained. Today, more than 20,000 pair 
survive. Every child in America today in the Lower 48 can 
witness a wild bald eagle. Grizzly bears and gray wolves have 
returned to the Western Plains. Black-footed ferrets, once 
declared extinct, now thrive in the shortgrass prairie. All of 
this because of the Endangered Species Act.
    But today, I come to you as my most important reason to 
testify, and that is my most important resource, and that is my 
two daughters, Maya and Marina. The ultimate goal as a father 
is to ensure that they have a healthy, robust ecosystem where 
they can thrive and prosper. And I believe the Endangered 
Species Act is critical in securing the natural legacy that we 
all depend upon. Thank you.
</option>
    <option>  Prepared Statement of Jeff Corwin, Wildlife Biologist, Author, and 
 Television Host on H.R. 424, H.R. 717, H.R. 1274, H.R. 2603, and H.R. 
                                  3131
    Good afternoon Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and 
members of the House Natural Resources Committee. My name is Jeff 
Corwin and I am a wildlife biologist, explorer, television host, and 
lifelong naturalist. I have hosted numerous wildlife TV series, 
including the ABC TV series ``Ocean Treks with Jeff Corwin.'' I also 
authored the books ``100 Heartbeats: The Race to Save Earth's Most 
Endangered Species'' and ``Living on the Edge: Amazing Relationships in 
the Natural World.'' Thank you for inviting me to appear before the 
Committee today to deliver testimony on five bills related to Federal 
wildlife conservation.
    I've been fortunate over my career to have some amazing, intimate 
encounters with some of our world's most threatened and endangered 
species. I swam with Steller sea lions off the coast of Alaska. I 
rescued a poisoned California condor and returned it to the wild. I 
stood in Big Cypress National Preserve just 20 yards from a Florida 
panther, tracking his movements on a radio transmitter, but still 
unable to see this elusive big cat.
    In 2008, from the passenger seat of a low-flying helicopter, I 
swooped across a vast expanse of Arctic ice, searching for the mighty 
polar bear. Soon we spotted a family of gleaming white bears galloping 
at close to 20 miles an hour to escape what I'm sure momma bear thought 
to be a giant flying threat to her and her cubs. I stepped out onto the 
frozen tundra, into ^20 degree winds, the membranes of my eyes stinging 
and my breath instantly forming icicles on my face mask. The adventurer 
in me loved every second of this, even the pain and discomfort.
    We tagged the bear and used the data to learn more about how this 
magnificent creature was adapting to a swiftly shrinking ice sheet. The 
scientists I was traveling with had committed decades of their careers 
to their research, searching for ways to help these bears cope with an 
uncertain future. I've been fortunate to experience the magnificent 
wonders of nature, and I can say unequivocally that no other country in 
the world boasts the diversity of landscape and wildlife that we have 
here in America. We are truly blessed with an extraordinary natural 
heritage. And, I've seen firsthand the amazing work of the women and 
men who work for the Nation's wildlife conservation agencies. They 
should enjoy our full confidence that the science they rely on to do 
what's best for wildlife is respected and supported by us all.
    Bringing back endangered species from the brink of extinction and 
restoring their habitat is one of our Nation's greatest conservation 
success stories. Bald eagles now fly across the skies of nearly every 
state. Grizzly bears and gray wolves have returned to the Western 
Plains. Black-footed ferrets, once declared extinct, now thrive in the 
American prairie.
    But I fear that if we are not strong and resolute in our commitment 
to protecting endangered species and their habitat, we will quickly 
lose all the momentum we've gained and leave a legacy of mass 
extinction. I have spent time with hundreds of species, but I also have 
experienced seeing what extinction is like firsthand. I've encountered 
creatures that are no longer on this planet; they are gone forever. We 
cannot just rely on past accomplishments--not when we've come so far 
and still have so much further to go.
                       the sixth mass extinction
    These stories are not anomalies, but rather firsthand evidence of a 
disturbing phenomenon taking place on our planet. Scientists have 
concluded that we are well into the sixth mass extinction that planet 
Earth has experienced and that this one is largely caused by humans.\1\ 
The most recent update to the International Union for Conservation of 
Nature's (IUCN's) Red List of threatened species found that the global 
extinction crisis is much greater than we previously thought.\2\ Out of 
over 700 new species of birds that were added to the list in 2016, 11 
percent of them are threatened with extinction. Giraffes are now 
threatened with extinction, with populations in southern and eastern 
Africa declining by as much as 40 percent in the past three decades. An 
article published recently in the Proceedings of the National Academy 
of Sciences described the problem of declining wildlife populations as 
a ``biological annihilation.'' \3\ The crisis cannot be overstated.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \1\ Ceballos, G., Ehrlich, P., Barnosky, A., Garcia, A., Pringle, 
R., Palmer, T., Accelerated modern human-induced species losses: 
Entering the sixth mass extinction, June 19, 2015, http://
advances.sciencemag.org/content/1/5/e1400253.
    \2\ IUCN, New bird species and giraffe under threat--IUCN Red List, 
Dec. 8, 2016, http://www.iucnredlist.org/news/new-bird-species-and-
giraffe-under-threat-iucn-red-list.
    \3\ Ceballos, G., Ehrlich, P., Dirzo, R., Biological annihilation 
via the ongoing sixth mass extinction signaled by vertebrate population 
losses and declines, May 23, 2017, http://m.pnas.org/content/early/
2017/07/05/1704949114.full.pdf.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The loss of biological diversity is one of the most urgent global 
environmental problems we face today. Species all over the globe 
continue to face habitat loss, climate change, wildlife trafficking, 
pollution, and other existential threats. If we fail to take the 
necessary action to address human-caused threats to biodiversity, all 
species--including us--will face severe consequences in the coming 
decades and centuries. Sadly, we are on track to lose many beloved 
species forever. As the father of two daughters who love nature as much 
as I do, I am not ready to accept a future without vibrant, robust 
natural resources.
            the role of government in wildlife conservation
    The Federal Government plays an important role in conserving 
wildlife. In 2009, I testified before the House Appropriations 
</option>
</Directory>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>Subcommittee on Interior, Environment and Related Agencies to advocate</subcomittee_name>
    <option>for substantial, dedicated funding to help safeguard America's wildlife 
and natural resources from the impacts of global warming. Here we are 8 
years later. Despite some administrative progress in recent years, it 
pains me to say that the government has not done enough to protect and 
conserve our imperiled species during that time. Congress has failed to 
adequately fund the Federal agencies charged with implementing 
important wildlife conservation programs, while simultaneously aiming 
to weaken our existing conservation laws. Wildlife conservation used to 
be a priority in this country and the rest of the world looked to the 
United States as a leader in this field. Now, wildlife conservation--
especially conservation work to benefit our most vulnerable species--is 
discouraged at the highest levels of government. Instead of being a 
pioneering leader in battling the global extinction crisis, we've not 
only taken the back seat--we've hijacked the process and seem intent on 
burning it to the ground. The five bills before the Committee today 
reflect a dismal and complacent view that I believe our political 
leaders have adopted toward wildlife conservation. It's as if they've 
forgotten how rare it used to be to see wild turkeys across the 
landscape or how special it was to spot a single bald eagle flying 
along the coastline. It's only because of our focused conservation 
efforts over the past several decades that dozens of species that were 
once on the brink of extinction are now flourishing.
                       the endangered species act
    The Endangered Species Act (ESA) is a great example of a celebrated 
American law that the rest of the world looks to as a model for 
conserving wildlife. The ESA is our Nation's most effective law for 
protecting wildlife in danger of extinction. It has prevented more than 
99 percent of listed species from going extinct, including the American 
bald eagle, the brown pelican, and the Florida manatee. We have a 
responsibility to be good stewards of our environment and protect our 
natural heritage for our children and grandchildren. The ESA transforms 
this principle into practice by protecting endangered species and their 
habitat so that future generations can experience animals in the wild, 
including seeing an orca swim off the coast of Washington State, 
spotting a bald eagle soaring in Maine, or hearing the cry of a wolf in 
Yellowstone National Park.
    When my daughter Maya was 3 years old, I had the pleasure of taking 
her to participate in the historic release of 14 black-footed ferrets 
into their grassland habitat. This is an animal that nearly went 
extinct in the wild and was only brought back from the brink thanks to 
extraordinary efforts under the ESA. Saving the black-footed ferret 
from the fate of extinction was a herculean task that required science, 
hard work and funding. The black-footed ferret is the ultimate 
Lazarus--from 18 captive animals that I had the privilege of filming in 
a zoo many years ago, it is now a recovering population that has helped 
restore an important Great Plains ecosystem. We take success stories 
and habitat restorations like this for granted rather than seeing them 
for what they are--tangible examples of how our conservation efforts 
under the ESA and other laws have paid off.
    I have also seen how human-caused threats can harm individual 
animals to the detriment of the species. In this case, the species in 
question was the critically endangered California condor--a magnificent 
bird with a wingspan of over 9\1/2\ feet. I joined biologists from the 
U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (FWS) near Big Sur to help rescue a 
California condor in extreme distress. We brought the condor into the 
Los Angeles zoo to conduct a lead test and found that it had high 
levels of lead in its system. While this was just one individual animal 
that was affected, that condor represented roughly \1/500\th of the 
entire remaining population. The United States started the work to save 
this species from the brink of extinction. We owe it to future 
generations to continue that work for the condor and all species 
threatened with extinction. Wildlife conservation is an ongoing 
process. We cannot afford to be complacent and take for granted that 
our country's magnificent natural heritage will be here for our 
children without our continued, sustained commitment.
    I'm concerned that instead of rising to meet the current challenges 
we face, the bills that are the subject of today's hearing would 
collectively turn the U.S. government's back on the hard work that is 
required to save species for future generations. These five bills and 
numerous other measures that have been introduced this Congress 
demonstrate an unwillingness to do more to conserve imperiled species. 
Instead, the bills seek to do less. Each of these bills would harm 
threatened and endangered species and erode our most important tool to 
save them from extinction--the ESA.
 description of h.r. 424, h.r. 717, h.r. 1274, h.r. 2603 and h.r. 3131
    H.R. 424 (``Gray Wolf State Management Act of 2017'') would block 
Federal Endangered Species Act protections for gray wolves in the Great 
Lakes states and Wyoming. Specifically, this bill--which would be more 
aptly named the ``War on Wolves Act''--would overturn a Federal 
District Court decision and remove existing Endangered Species Act 
protections for gray wolves in Michigan, Minnesota, and Wisconsin. It 
would also codify a recent D.C. Circuit Court of Appeals decision that 
stripped Endangered Species Act protections for wolves in Wyoming. 
Further, the bill would prohibit future judicial review of both 
legislative wolf de-listings. In doing so, this legislation would not 
only undermine the ESA's science-based decision-making process, but 
also set a dangerous precedent for the rule of law and citizens' access 
to the courts more broadly. This bill continues a damaging precedent of 
allowing politicians to interfere with science-based listing decisions 
and encourages other insidious legislative attacks on the ESA.
    H.R. 717 (``Listing Reform Act'') puts a price on species 
conservation by enabling the FWS to determine that a species that would 
normally be listed as threatened would not receive protections if there 
are negative economic impacts associated with the listing. It would 
also completely gut the citizen petition process for listing species by 
removing all the deadlines that have historically allowed citizens to 
have their petitions ruled on in a timely fashion. The ESA was written 
to ensure that listing decisions are based on the best available 
science--not politics. Yet this bill would wrongly prioritize politics 
over science in determining whether or not our Nation's most endangered 
wildlife deserves protection.
    H.R. 1274 (``State, Tribal, and Local Species Transparency and 
Recovery Act'') would subvert the ESA's science-based listing process 
by allowing any information provided by states, tribes, or counties to 
constitute ``best available science.'' By automatically assuming such a 
broad swath of information to be defined as such without any scientific 
input or review, the bill would contradict the meaning of ``best 
available science.'' Moreover, H.R. 1274 would direct the Federal 
Government to utilize state and local data in its listing decisions, 
regardless of whether the data is based in science. H.R. 1274 is not 
only contradictory, but duplicative: under the ESA, the Federal 
Government already works extensively with the states, considers state 
and local data when making listing decisions, and notifies affected 
states of proposed listing determinations.
    H.R. 2603 (``Saving America's Endangered Species Act'') would strip 
ESA protections for non-native species within the United States. It 
would eliminate Federal protections for individual animals of listed 
foreign species in the United States, including chimpanzees, tigers, 
elephants, addax, several species of antelope, several species of 
parrots, pangolins and giant pandas. The legislation would obstruct the 
FWS's ability to regulate illegal wildlife trafficking or issue permits 
for exhibitors of foreign endangered and threatened species. Despite 
this bill's misleading name, eliminating permitting requirements for 
foreign species under the ESA will not benefit American species--it 
would only harm some of the most severely endangered species in the 
world and contribute to the decline of foreign species on the brink of 
extinction.
    H.R. 3131 (``Endangered Species Litigation Reasonableness Act'') 
would undercut citizen engagement and enforcement of the ESA by 
impeding citizens' ability to obtain counsel and challenge illegal 
government actions. Under H.R. 3131, citizens who successfully 
challenge illegal government actions under the ESA would be subject to 
fee recovery restrictions that could make it difficult for them to 
obtain counsel. In doing so, H.R. 3131 would make it more difficult for 
citizens from across the political spectrum to engage in the 
implementation of this fundamentally democratic law and to hold Federal 
agencies accountable for complying with it.
                               conclusion
    We cannot afford to lose focus on the importance of protecting 
wildlife and habitat for ours and future generations. We have not 
inherited our natural world from our parents; we are simply borrowing 
it from our children. We have a moral responsibility to be good 
stewards of our environment and ensure our children have something 
worthwhile when we are gone. The future of our planet rests squarely in 
our hands and the United States is in a particularly good position to 
take action before it's too late. Thanks to our visionary conservation 
laws like the Endangered Species Act, our native wildlife and their 
habitat have fared better than those in most countries. We must remain 
committed to the conservation values we hold dear and focus on positive 
initiatives to keep our natural heritage intact for future generations. 
We can and should lead the world in addressing the global extinction 
crisis. Now is the chance for us to step up and not lose the momentum 
of the last 50 years to protect nature's most endangered species from 
extinction.
    Although I recognize that I appear before you today as an expert 
with a career that is based in nature, I am here because, like many of 
you, I am a father. My job as a parent to my two amazing daughters is 
to ensure they have a healthy future. I must feed them well, teach them 
kindness and hope, encourage them to take risks, and show them how to 
be kind to their fellow human beings. The preservation of our landscape 
and the wildlife that inhabit it is a huge part of that. How we protect 
our planet sets an example for our children. I want them to have a 
future where wild animals roam free, special places remain undisturbed 
and our natural heritage continues to be our greatest asset.
    We must ensure that the laws designed to protect endangered and 
threatened species--along with the resources needed to enforce them--
remain intact.
    As a father, my job is to ensure my kids have a healthy future.
                                 ______
 Questions Submitted for the Record to Jeff Corwin, Biologist and Host 
               of ABC's ``Ocean Treks with Jeff Corwin''
                   Questions Submitted by Rep. Bishop
    Question 1. Please disclose the years in which you served on the 
Board of Directors for the Defenders of Wildlife.
    Answer. I was elected to serve on the Board of Directors for 
Defenders of Wildlife in 2004 and served until 2016.
    Question 2. Please describe the duties, obligations, and 
responsibilities you assumed as a member of the Board of Directors of 
Defenders of Wildlife. Please also describe in detail all duties, 
responsibilities, or obligations that your current association with the 
group entails.
    Answer. The Defenders of Wildlife board of directors controls and 
administers the affairs and funds of the organization. As a member of 
the board, I had the following general responsibilities:
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; All board members are expected at all times to vote and 
            act with Defenders' best interests in mind.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; The board is responsible for ensuring that Defenders meets 
            legal requirements and that it is operating in accordance 
            with its mission and for the purpose for which it was 
            granted tax-exemption.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; The board is responsible for ensuring the proper and 
            effective operation of Defenders of Wildlife.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; In accordance with their individual capabilities, all 
            board members are expected to assist in making sure that 
            Defenders is provided with the financial and other 
            resources it needs.
    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt; I served on the board's Communications &amp;amp; Publications 
            Committee (later renamed Marketing &amp;amp; Communications), which 
            advises the board on proposed marketing and communications 
            strategies, from 2006-2013. I also served on the Executive 
            Committee, which exercises the authority of the board 
            during intervals between meetings of the board, from 2010-
            2011.
    As I am no longer a board member of Defenders of Wildlife and 
therefore have no formal association with the group, I have no duties, 
responsibilities or obligations to Defenders of Wildlife.
    Question 3. Please disclose all Endangered Species Act related 
cases that Defenders of Wildlife filed, and/or was party to while you 
served on its Board.
    Answer. I did not sit on the Defenders of Wildlife board's 
litigation committee, which is charged with reviewing and approving all 
litigation conducted by the organization. Although the board was 
generally briefed on legal developments, it has been more than a year 
since I've left the board, and I do not recall the specific Endangered 
Species Act-related cases that Defenders of Wildlife filed and/or was 
party to while I served on its Board. I understand, however, that Ya-
Wei Li, Defenders' Vice President for Endangered Species Conservation, 
recently provided a comprehensive list of such litigation to the 
Oversight &amp;amp; Investigations Subcommittee of this Committee.
    Question 4. Please disclose the amount of attorney's fees paid to 
the Defenders of Wildlife under the Equal Access to Justice Act, or the 
Justice Fund, for each case filed, and/or for each case for which 
Defenders of Wildlife was a party while you served on its Board.
    Answer. As I noted, I was not a member of the board's litigation 
committee. Although the board was generally briefed on legal 
developments, I do not recall the details of attorney's fees paid to 
Defenders of Wildlife.
                                 ______
    The  Chairman. Thank you.
    Mr. Willms.
</option>
    <option>                           MATT MEAD
    Mr.  Willms. Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, 
members of the Committee on Natural Resources, thank you for 
the invitation to share Governor Mead's and Wyoming's 
perspective on the Endangered Species Act.
    The civic duty and moral responsibility to conserve our 
Nation's wildlife and the ecosystems upon which they rely 
transcends politics. Congress said as much when it nearly 
unanimously passed the Endangered Species Act in 1973. Yet for 
the past several decades, divisive partisan rhetoric has 
politicized wildlife management. In the meantime, both wildlife 
and people suffer.
    To move forward, we must acknowledge that the Endangered 
Species Act both succeeds and fails. We must celebrate its 
successes, but recognize and seek to remedy its failures in a 
way that allows the ESA to better serve wildlife and people.
    This mind-set led Governor Mead to launch the Species 
Conservation and Endangered Species Act initiative when he 
became Chair of the Western Governors Association in the summer 
of 2015. Using a transparent, inclusive, and bipartisan 
process, Governor Mead brought a diverse group of thought 
leaders together from around the country to discuss ways to 
improve the Endangered Species Act and species conservation, 
more generally.
    After 2 years, Western Governors adopted a series of 
recommendations that described specific funding, regulatory, 
and statutory recommendations to further strengthen the 
Endangered Species Act and enhance species conservation. These 
recommendations identify and seek to address many of the issues 
identified in the bills you are considering today.
    Western Governors recommended additional funding in certain 
areas. Governor Mead supports these recommendations, as well as 
recommendations that deliver more direct funding to states for 
species conservation. However, before making large 
appropriations for Endangered Species Act implementation, it 
makes sense to identify and rectify procedural inefficiencies 
within the ESA that unnecessarily strain existing U.S. Fish and 
Wildlife resources.
    After correcting these inefficiencies, the Fish and 
Wildlife Service and Congress will better understand where they 
can redistribute existing funding, and where additional funding 
may be appropriate.
    For example, the deadlines in Section 4 of the ESA invites 
uncontrolled procedural and legal gambits intentionally 
designed to cripple the Fish and Wildlife Service's ability to 
implement the ESA. This, in turn, erodes support from many of 
the stakeholders necessary for species conservation.
    However, the deadlines are not sacrosanct. When Congress 
adopted the ESA in 1973, it did not include deadlines. In 1982, 
after complaints that the Fish and Wildlife Service 
intentionally delayed listing decisions, Congress amended the 
ESA, adding the current 90-day and 12-month deadlines. Rather 
than being rooted in science, these deadlines were politically 
motivated to spur the Administration into taking timely action 
on potential species listings.
    However, Congress could not anticipate the strategic 
onslaught of species petitions and related litigation that 
would strain the agency decades later. After 35 years, let us 
admit that existing deadlines in Section 4 have outlived their 
usefulness. In addition to the petitions and litigation 
problems, the compressed deadlines discourage innovative and 
voluntary conservation, and may limit Fish and Wildlife Service 
access to valuable scientific data that could otherwise inform 
listing determinations.
    Through their June 2017 recommendations, Western Governors 
identified two possible ways to address these issues, which are 
attached and described in detail in my written testimony. 
Wyoming supports both.
    Our current system also makes recovering species and 
removing ESA protections for them difficult. Currently, roughly 
30 percent of all listed species have no recovery plan. On the 
other extreme, species like grizzly bears and gray wolves in 
Wyoming exceeded recovery plan objectives for more than 15 
years before returning to state management, with the constant 
threat of litigation looming. This needs to change to maintain 
the integrity and support for the ESA from the varied 
stakeholders upon which it depends.
    States already play a significant role in species recovery. 
As described in detail in my written testimony, willing states 
should be allowed to lead recovery teams and develop recovery 
plans for listed species. States have already contributed to 
the recovery of some of the Nation's most iconic species.
    For example, Wyoming spent more than $42 million recovering 
grizzly bears, including research, public education, and 
landowner incentives. They can do more. Further, to facilitate 
successful state management upon de-listing, judicial review of 
a de-listing rule should be delayed until the completion of the 
statutory post de-listing monitoring period. This would not 
jeopardize recently de-listed species.
    Fish and Wildlife Service has never, to my knowledge, 
relisted a species that it successfully de-listed due to 
recovery. This underscores the seriousness with which the 
states accept their responsibility to develop and implement 
management plans that ensure recovered species into the 
foreseeable future.
    In conclusion, Governor Mead supports the Endangered 
Species Act. The ESA is responsible for igniting some of the 
most remarkable species recoveries ever documented, and 
continues to facilitate the recovery of other imperiled 
species. However, it is far from perfect. It can and should 
work better, both for wildlife and for people. The 
recommendations put forward by Western Governors through 
Governor Mead's initiative are both reasonable and achievable 
solutions.
</option>
    <option>   Prepared Statement of David J. Willms, Policy Advisor to the Hon. 
                  Matthew H. Mead, Governor of Wyoming
    Mr. Chairman and members of the Committee, thank you for the 
invitation to testify today. I have worked on endangered species issues 
for my entire career, first as a Senior Assistant Attorney General for 
the state of Wyoming, and then in private practice. Today, I am a 
natural resources policy advisor for Wyoming Governor Matthew H. Mead, 
and teach a graduate course on the Endangered Species Act at the 
University of Wyoming. I appreciate the opportunity to share Governor 
Mead's, and Wyoming's perspective on the Endangered Species Act.
    The civic duty and moral responsibility to conserve our Nation's 
wildlife and the ecosystems upon which they rely transcends politics. 
Congress said as much when it nearly unanimously passed the Endangered 
Species Act (ESA) in 1973. Yet for the past several decades, divisive 
partisan rhetoric has politicized wildlife management. In the meantime, 
both wildlife and people suffer. To move forward, we must acknowledge 
that the ESA both succeeds and fails. We must celebrate its successes, 
but recognize, and seek to remedy its failures in a way that allows the 
ESA to better serve wildlife and people.
    This mind-set led Governor Mead to launch the Species Conservation 
and Endangered Species Act Initiative (Initiative) when he became the 
chair of the Western Governors' Association (WGA) in the summer of 
2015. Using a transparent, inclusive, and bipartisan process, Governor 
Mead brought a diverse group of thought leaders together from around 
the country to discuss ways to improve the ESA, and species 
conservation more generally. Over 2 years, the Initiative hosted nine 
facilitated work sessions, six webinars, multiple surveys and 
questionnaires that produced two reports outlining opportunities to 
strengthen the ESA. This work led to a resolution that Governors 
unanimously adopted in June of 2016. The National Governor's 
Association adopted a similar resolution in early 2017. Then last 
month, Western Governors adopted a new series of recommendations that 
describe specific statutory, regulatory, and funding recommendations to 
further strengthen the ESA, and enhance species conservation.
    Governor Mead hopes this Committee finds these bipartisan 
recommendations helpful as you consider updating the ESA. You will find 
that several of the challenges Western Governors identified with the 
ESA's current implementation are consistent with the challenges 
underlying many of the bills you are considering today. For 
illustration, I would like to explain from Wyoming's perspective, how 
the WGA recommendations address common criticisms of the ESA including, 
(1) funding shortfalls, (2) reducing procedural litigation, and (3) a 
more robust recovery planning process.
                                funding
    Groups routinely argue that inadequate funding serves as an 
impediment to successful ESA implementation. Some of these arguments 
have merit. Western Governors recommended additional funding in certain 
areas including: (1) to address the current backlog of recovered 
species awaiting down-listing or de-listing; and (2) to enhance 
incentive based conservation efforts for listed and non-listed species. 
Governor Mead supports these recommendations, as well as 
recommendations that deliver more direct funding to states for species 
conservation. Other funding may also be appropriate; however, those 
funding discussions are, in some cases, premature.
    Before making large appropriations for ESA implementation, it makes 
sense to identify and rectify procedural inefficiencies within the ESA 
that unnecessarily strain existing U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (FWS) 
resources.\1\ After correcting these inefficiencies, the FWS and 
Congress will better understand where they can redistribute existing 
funding, and where additional funding may be appropriate.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \1\ The Secretaries of the Interior and Commerce have authorities 
under the ESA, which manifest through the Fish and Wildlife Service and 
National Marine Fisheries Service. For purposes of my testimony, I 
refer to the FWS because Wyoming interacts with them exclusively.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
                         procedural litigation
    For example, the current structure of Section 4 of the ESA invites 
uncontrolled procedural and legal gambits intentionally designed to 
cripple the FWS's ability to implement the ESA. This in turn erodes 
support from many of the stakeholders necessary for species 
conservation. Section 4 establishes the protocols for listing and de-
listing species. Under this section, a person may submit a petition to 
the FWS requesting ESA protection for a species as either threatened or 
endangered. Within 90 days, the FWS must determine whether the petition 
contains enough information to warrant a more detailed analysis. If it 
does, then the FWS must make a final determination about the species 
within 12 months. These deadlines are the source of the greatest 
acrimony in ESA implementation. However, they are not sacrosanct.
    When Congress adopted the ESA in 1973, it did not direct the FWS to 
act on petitions it received in a specific time frame. In 1978, 
Congress amended the ESA, and gave the FWS 2 years to make a final 
determination on whether or not to list a species. Under the 1978 
amendment, if the FWS failed to act within 2 years, it was required to 
withdraw the rulemaking until it received new information about the 
species.
    In 1982, after complaints that the FWS intentionally delayed 
listing decisions, Congress again amended the ESA adding the current 
requirement that the FWS make an initial 90-day finding, and that it 
act on a substantial 90-day finding within 12 months of the date it 
receives a petition. Congress did not establish these deadlines using 
any scientific rationale. Instead, Congress imposed a politically 
concocted, arbitrary deadline to spur the Administration into taking 
timely action on potential species listings.
    However, Congress did not anticipate the strategic onslaught of 
species petitions and related litigation that would strain the agency 
decades later. Prior to 2003, the FWS never received more than 25 
species listing petitions in a single year. Since then, species 
petitions have skyrocketed. In 2007, the Services received petitions to 
list 695 species, and another 432 in 2010--nearly all of which 
originated from two non-governmental organizations. These two groups 
attempt to overwhelm the FWS with so many species petitions that the 
FWS is unable to respond within the statutory time frames. Then, these 
two groups litigate, in hopes that the FWS will acquiesce to their 
demands. We should not allow two groups to dictate the policy of an 
entire agency because we are afraid to acknowledge and address the 
problem.
    After 35 years, let us admit that the politically motivated 
deadlines in Section 4 have outlived their usefulness. In addition to 
the problems discussed above, the compressed deadlines discourage 
innovative and voluntary conservation, and may limit FWS access to 
valuable scientific data that could otherwise inform a listing 
determination.
    Through their June 2017, recommendations, Western Governors 
identified two possible ways to address these issues. Wyoming supports 
both. Congress could amend Section 4 to give the FWS greater 
flexibility to prioritize petitions it receives, but with an 
understanding that it must still make a decision by a specific date. 
Alternatively, Congress could amend Section 4 to give the FWS 
discretion to defer listing determinations up to 5 years if the species 
meets certain conditions. For example, the FWS could defer a listing 
decision to allow state-led conservation efforts an opportunity to 
succeed, or to allow the completion of ongoing scientific studies 
related to the petitioned species.
    In addition to alleviating the agency workload, these pragmatic 
changes have other benefits. They would allow the FWS to ensure that 
the most imperiled species receive immediate attention, thus reducing 
the likelihood of extinction. They would encourage more creative and 
collaborative conservation efforts like those undertaken for greater 
sage grouse and lesser prairie chicken. They would ensure that listing 
decisions are based on the best available science. Finally, they would 
significantly reduce litigation, allowing agency personnel to spend 
more time developing and implementing strategies for recovering listed 
species.
                           recovery planning
    The ESA envisions recovering a species to the point that its 
protections are no longer necessary. Yet, our current system makes 
removing protections for recovered species difficult. This must change. 
Currently, 493 species, or roughly 30 percent of all listed species 
have no recovery plan. This means species like Canada lynx, which the 
FWS listed as threatened more than 17 years ago, sit in purgatory with 
no discernible path to recovery. On the other extreme, species like 
grizzly bears and gray wolves exceeded recovery plan objectives for a 
generation before returning to state management.
    Grizzly bears first met their ESA prescribed recovery objectives in 
2003--an event that would presumably trigger de-listing. Yet, the FWS 
took 4 more years before publishing a de-listing rule in 2007. 
Ultimately, the rule failed to survive judicial review on a procedural 
technicality. Grizzly bears continued to increase in population and 
expand their range, yet it took until June of this year before the FWS 
issued a new de-listing rule addressing the 9th Circuit's lone concern. 
Instead of celebrating grizzly bear recovery as an ESA success story, 
hosts of organizations have already issued notices of intent to sue the 
FWS over its de-listing rule. They allege procedural deficiencies in 
the rule as well as hypothetical, unsubstantiated, prospective harm.
    Fundamentally, these groups do not want to see grizzly bears de-
listed because they do not trust states to manage wildlife within their 
borders. However, they fail to recognize two important facts. First, 
states played a significant role in recovering grizzly bears. Since the 
early 1980s, Wyoming has spent more than $42 million on grizzly bear 
recovery--including contributing to research that makes this population 
of grizzly bears perhaps the most studied mammalian population on the 
planet. Wyoming also funds public education and landowner incentive 
programs that engender support for grizzly bears on a multiple-use 
landscape. Second, the FWS has never relisted a species that it 
successfully de-listed due to recovery. This fact underscores the 
seriousness with which the states accept their responsibility to 
develop and implement management plans that ensure a recovered species 
into the foreseeable future.
    For these reasons, Governor Mead encourages Congress to consider 
the WGA recommendation that would encourage willing states to lead 
recovery teams and develop recovery plans for listed species. Those 
recovery plans should contain discrete, achievable goals that when met 
satisfy all of the de-listing criteria under Section 4 of the ESA. When 
the species meets the recovery goals established in the recovery plan, 
the FWS should immediately initiate a status review of the species for 
purposes of considering de-listing or down-listing of the species. 
Finally, once the FWS de-lists a species, states should manage the 
species. To allow states an opportunity to succeed, Congress should 
consider delaying judicial review of a de-listing rule until the 
completion of the post de-listing monitoring period established through 
the de-listing rule pursuant to statute.
                                 wolves
    I briefly want to address this Committee's efforts to ensure wolves 
in Wyoming remain under state management. Earlier this year, after a 
protracted legal battle, the Federal Circuit Court in Washington, DC 
issued a mandate that reinstated a 2012 FWS rule de-listing gray wolves 
in Wyoming. Today, Wyoming is managing wolves pursuant to a federally 
approved wolf management plan that ensures a recovered wolf population 
in Wyoming for the foreseeable future. The provision of the bill 
protecting the FWS wolf de-listing rule from further judicial review 
provides the states with needed predictability while still ensuring a 
recovered wolf population.
    Regardless of the mechanism, any measure that ensures state 
management predictability into the future provides the most pragmatic 
and reasonable solution for both the gray wolf population and Wyoming 
citizens. The ESA preserves the responsibility for the FWS to relist 
Wyoming's gray wolf population if it becomes threatened or endangered 
in the future. The current draft of this bill does not affect this ESA 
requirement.
                               conclusion
    Governor Mead supports the Endangered Species Act, as evidenced by 
his leadership of the Species Conservation and Endangered Species Act 
Initiative through the Western Governors' Association. The ESA is a 
valuable tool for ensuring that our suite of wildlife remains for the 
enjoyment of future generations. The ESA is responsible for igniting 
some of the most remarkable species recoveries ever documented, and 
continues to facilitate the recovery of other imperiled species. 
However, it is far from perfect. It can, and should work better, both 
for wildlife and for people. The recommendations put forward by Western 
Governors through Governor Mead's Initiative are both reasonable and 
achievable solutions that warrant serious consideration.
    Thank you again for this opportunity to share Wyoming's perspective 
on ways to strengthen the ESA and enhance species conservation.
                                 *****
                               ATTACHMENT
WGA Species Conservation and the Endangered Species Act Initiative Year 
                          Two Recommendations
Preamble
    The Western Governors' Association (WGA), under the leadership of 
then-Chairman Wyoming Governor Matt Mead, launched the Western 
Governors' Species Conservation and Endangered Species Act Initiative 
(Initiative) in 2015. Since the Initiative's inception, WGA has hosted 
numerous workshops, webinars, and work sessions to create a forum for a 
diverse coalition of stakeholders to share best practices in species 
management, promote the role of states in species conservation, and 
explore options to improve the efficacy of the Endangered Species Act 
(ESA).
    While the Initiative has closely examined the ESA, the effort goes 
well beyond consideration of the Act alone. Governors also are seeking 
to encourage voluntary conservation--through early identification of 
sensitive species and establishment of institutional frameworks that 
incentivize collaborative voluntary conservation--thus avoiding the 
need to list species in the first place.
    The first year of the Initiative (2015-2016) resulted in approval 
of WGA Resolution 2016-08: Species Conservation and the Endangered 
Species Act--an expansive resolution encapsulating Governors' 
principles informed by the Initiative. The Resolution instructs WGA 
staff to develop a multi-year workplan to further Governors' policy 
principals on Species Conservation and the ESA. What followed in the 
first year of workplan implementation (2016-2017) was a continuation of 
the transparent, inclusive, and stakeholder driven process to refine 
and examine avenues for implementation of Governors' policy statements 
expressed in the Resolution.
    A suite of recommendations addressing proactive and incentive based 
voluntary conservation species and ESA implementation emerged from year 
two work sessions. Work session participants were not expected to reach 
full consensus on recommendations forwarded by the Governors. However, 
comity among work session participants gave rise to significant 
progress toward conceptual agreement and helped inform the Governors' 
deliberations on the recommendations contained in this document.
    As interest within Congress and the Administration in examining the 
ESA builds, Western Governors' submit these bipartisan statutory, 
regulatory and funding-related recommendations consistent with 
implementation of the principles forwarded in WGA Resolution 2016-08, 
Species Conservation and the Endangered Species Act.
    Importantly, with respect to statutory recommendations, Western 
Governors' acknowledge any congressional effort to amend the ESA will 
be complicated and spark diverse opinions. WGA's ESA initiative enjoyed 
diverse stakeholder input and broad consensus; these resulting 
recommendations represent bipartisanship at this stage. Each Governor 
reserves judgment on whether to support congressional action, based 
upon unknown future legislative language.
Statutory
  1.  (A) Amend Section 4 of the Endangered Species Act to create 
            flexibility for the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (FWS) 
            and National Marine Fisheries Service (NMFS) (collectively, 
            ``Services'') to create a prioritization schedule for 
            petitions received. The Services must assign a petitioned 
            species a listing priority within 12 months of a positive 
            90-day finding. Species in immediate risk of extinction 
            will receive highest priority, while species with ongoing 
            conservation efforts or species for which listing would 
            provide limited conservation benefit within the foreseeable 
            future will be placed in a lower priority category.
      (B) Amend Section 4 of the Endangered Species Act to create a 
            statutory exception for the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 
            (FWS) and National Marine Fisheries Service (NMFS) 
            (collectively, ``Services'') to defer 12-month findings for 
            a species under the ESA when: (1) a conservation plan is 
            either being developed or implemented to meet the 
            conservation needs of the species. In the case of species 
            that range across multiple states, this refers to a plan in 
            each state or a range-wide plan. The Services may renew the 
            deferral every five years so long as they have worked with 
            states to complete a determination that the conservation 
            plan continues to meet the conservation needs of the 
            species; (2) a delay will allow time to complete data 
            collection or complete studies relating to the petitioned 
            species; (3) species for which listing would provide 
            limited conservation benefit within the foreseeable future.
  2.  Require the Secretary to make a determination on whether or not 
            to designate critical habitat for a species. The Secretary 
            shall designate critical habitat if he or she determines 
            such a designation is necessary to recover the species. If 
            the Secretary determines that such designation is not 
            critical to recovery of the species, the Secretary may 
            decline to designate critical habitat for a species. If the 
            Secretary designates critical habitat, it must link such 
            designation to recovery objectives and plans. For many 
            species, recovery planning cannot occur until years after a 
            listing, leaving a lot of time for critical habitat to be 
            compromised in the meantime. When necessary, critical 
            habitat should continue to be designated at the time of 
            listing, and re-evaluated as part of the recovery planning 
            process. The Secretary will retain current authority to 
            permit exclusions from critical habitat designations for 
            discrete purposes.
  3.  Upon listing, the Services will convene a recovery team within 12 
            months. States will have the option to lead and develop 
            that team. The Recovery Team shall create a recovery plan, 
            and lead its implementation. The recovery plan shall 
            include criteria, that when met, would require the Recovery 
            Team to recommend de-listing or down-listing to the 
            Services. Whenever necessary, the recovery plan should be 
            updated to include the best available science and 
            strategies to address all recognized threats to recovering 
            the species. Upon receipt of the recommendation to de-list 
            or down-list a species from the Recovery Team, the Service 
            shall initiate a status review of the species for purposes 
            of considering de-listing or down-listing. Once the 
            Services issue a de-listing rule, they shall develop a post 
            de-listing monitoring plan in a timely fashion, and 
            judicial review of the delisting rule will be delayed until 
            the completion of the post de-listing monitoring review 
            period so long as a federally endorsed conservation plan is 
            in place.
Regulatory/Administrative
  1.  Examine the possibility of providing assurances on public land to 
            minimize the disincentive to enrolling in Candidate 
            Conservation Agreements with Assurances (CCAAs) for 
            permitted public land users with operations spanning both 
            federal and private land. Assurances provided may not come 
            in the form of incidental take permit associated with 
            CCAAs, but rather a suite of assurances such as increased 
            AUMs or extended grazing lease renewal periods for 
            operators providing conservation actions on public lands, 
            providing the assurances would not compromise the intent of 
            the CCAA to recover the species to the point that ESA 
            listing is not necessary.
  2.  When a landowner implements conservation measures as a part of a 
            federally endorsed conservation agreement, the Services may 
            exclude private land covered under the agreement from any 
            critical habitat designation. This authority currently 
            exists under the ESA, but needs further clarification and 
            guidance.
  3.  When making listing determinations, the Secretary must take into 
            account conservation efforts to protect species, including 
            efforts by states, federal agencies, and private 
            landowners.
  4.  The Services should work with states to develop templates for 
            voluntary conservation programs and conservation tools that 
            are intended to incentivize voluntary conservation for a 
            variety of species and habitats. These templates would 
            provide a more streamlined process of implementing 
            voluntary conservation programs for candidate and listed 
            species.
  5.  Encourage the Service to develop Species Status Assessments to 
            help inform a listing determination. If listing is deemed 
            warranted, use this same assessment to inform development 
            of a recovery plan blueprint so stakeholders are able to 
            implement effective recovery actions prior to the release 
            of a formal species recovery plan.
  6.  Given the Services' new policy of using Species Status 
            Assessments (SSAs) as a routine part of listing and 
            recovery decisions made under the ESA, recommend the 
            Services promulgate regulations to ensure the SSAs serve 
            their intended function of collecting and analyzing 
            foundational science on a species and updating that 
            information promptly when new data or analysis becomes 
            available. Give state wildlife agencies a leadership role 
            on SSA teams commensurate with their position as the 
            repository of the bulk of the data and expertise on many 
            species. Most critically, provide an adequate internal 
            appeals process for challenging the conclusions of an SSA, 
            either to Ecological Services leadership or to the Regional 
            Director, to ensure that a misguided determination does not 
            become embedded in multiple future decisions about a 
            species.
  7.  Develop a national policy for the implementation of 4(d) rules 
            that details best practices and incentivizes strong local 
            input.
  8.  Clarify or emphasize existing authority under the ESA for states 
            to exercise concurrent jurisdiction with the Services to 
            implement the ESA, including management of threatened 
            species and issuance of Section 10 take permits, if states 
            demonstrate a desire and capacity to do so.
  9.  If states decline to develop and lead a recovery team, as 
            described in Statutory Recommendation #3, the Services 
            shall still seek sufficient participation from states to 
            assemble recovery teams. States maintain strong wildlife 
            management expertise, relationships with their regulated 
            communities, and are able to better identify those 
            individuals and entities that can best contribute to the 
            recovery planning process.
 10.  Establish an informative ``playbook'' to inform citizens on how 
            to engage throughout various steps of the ESA process.
 11.  In the case of species which are listed as threatened or 
            endangered where listing provides limited conservation 
            benefit within the foreseeable future, concurrent with the 
            listing, Services should issue a 4(d) rule that emphasizes 
            regulatory flexibility. Services should also consider 
            delaying critical habitat designations, as well as modify 
            the way in which they conducts consultations.
Funding
  1.  Pair economic incentives with critical habitat and priority 
            conservation designations on private land and public land 
            permitted users to alleviate the burden of critical habitat 
            designations on private land while rewarding stewardship of 
            quality habitat. Incorporate a scoring system--similar to, 
            but not duplicative of, farm bill incentive scoring 
            system--developed by stakeholders and including states, for 
            private land conservation priority to assign varying 
            economic incentives.
  2.  The Services' budget should include specific line items directing 
            funding to assist stakeholders interested in seeking 
            assurance agreements and other voluntary conservation 
            efforts.
  3.  The Services currently allocate very little of their recovery 
            budget to de-listing or down-listing recovered species, 
            which causes species to remain listed as threatened or 
            endangered longer than the ESA intends. Congress should 
            allocate money to the Services through a specific line-item 
            in their budgets to enable the Services to timely de-list 
            or down-list species.
  4.  Congress should allocate additional funding to the Services' to 
            implement the ESA. Western Governors believe that adoption 
            of these recommendations will improve the efficacy of the 
            ESA, but recognize that the Services and states require 
            adequate funding to ensure successful implementation of the 
            Act. Governors will work with Congress to identify 
            priorities for funding that will facilitate voluntary 
            species conservation efforts and improve the efficacy of 
            the ESA.
                                 ______
 Questions Submitted for the Record to Davis Willms, Policy Advisor to 
                       Wyoming Governor Matt Mead
                   Questions Submitted by Rep. Bishop
    Question 1. You mentioned in your written statement that 493, or 
roughly 30 percent of listed species have no recovery plan--for 
example, the Canadian Lynx has been listed for 17 years with no plan.
    1a. Please explain how the lack of recovery planning has impacted 
states and the species?
    Answer. Delayed recovery planning negatively impacts wildlife and 
people in several ways. First, it complicates land management planning 
documents. When Federal agencies update their land use documents, they 
must address threats to listed species. In the absence of recovery 
plans, agencies lack the requisite detail to understand where to manage 
for the benefit of listed species, and where to allow multiple uses on 
the landscape. This can delay planning processes and create unnecessary 
disruptions to other uses of Federal land.
    Second, it discourages states from investing financially in species 
recovery. Canada lynx were listed as threatened 17 years ago, but have 
no recovery plan. Consequently, Wyoming spent only $8,209 on Canada 
Lynx in 2016. Other species with active recovery plans receive far more 
resources. In 2016, Wyoming spent $2,606,261 on grizzly bear recovery, 
$265,107 on black-footed ferret recovery, and $25,376 on Preble's 
meadow jumping mouse recovery. Even unlisted species with active 
conservation plans received more financial investment than lynx. For 
example, Wyoming spent $2,770,262 on sage grouse conservation and 
$332,764 on black-tailed prairie dog management in 2016.
    Third, species recovery takes longer without a recovery plan. 
Consequently, the costs and delays of Endangered Species Act (ESA) 
compliance continue longer. This includes completing Section 7 
consultations for projects with a Federal nexus, and developing a 
conservation plan to acquire an incidental take permit under Section 
10. In each instance, these processes can delay project implementation, 
increase costs, and in rare instances stop the project. The longer a 
species remains listed, the longer people must endure these burdensome 
steps.
    Finally, one of the stated purposes of the ESA is to recover 
species to the point that the ESA's protections are no longer 
necessary. It requires the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (FWS) develop 
a recovery plan to achieve this purpose. Species with recovery plans 
recover faster and more effectively than those without a plan. So, the 
FWS's failure to develop recovery plans for roughly 30 percent of 
listed species potentially jeopardizes those species' long-term 
survival.
    1b. How would state-led recovery teams benefit recovery efforts?
    Answer. States have the local relationships and species knowledge 
to lead an effort that will expedite species recovery. States can 
leverage their relationships with landowners to facilitate conservation 
on private lands. States can also utilize their species data to best 
articulate and implement a road-map to species recovery. Both of these 
factors will lead to quicker and more effective species recovery.
    Quicker species recovery has many benefits. It ensures species 
survival, engenders support for the ESA from the regulated community, 
and allows wildlife managers to turn their attention to other imperiled 
species. Further, with states leading recovery efforts, the FWS may 
have increased flexibility to spend limited resources on species with 
greater need. This benefits all species, and gives the regulatory 
certainty they desire.
    Western Governors identified ways Congress and the FWS can improve 
the recovery planning process. The specific recommendations are 
described in my written testimony and the WGA Species Conservation and 
the Endangered Species Act Initiative Year Two Recommendations, which 
is attached to my written testimony.
    1c. Please elaborate on the importance of state-led conservation 
efforts and how allowing them time to work benefits the species, our 
economy, and our communities.
    Answer. Wildlife and people benefit when the protections of the ESA 
are not needed. State-led conservation efforts frequently preclude the 
need to list species. This benefits people, and the species that the 
conservation efforts target. For example, Wyoming developed a 
conservation strategy for greater sage grouse that ultimately helped 
ensure that it would not require ESA protections, while protecting 
Wyoming's economy. Wyoming's conservation strategy will cost its 
economy roughly $1 billion annually and 5,495 jobs. However, if the FWS 
listed sage grouse as threatened or endangered, Wyoming would suffer 
economic harm of $1.5 to $5.3 billion annually and a loss of up to 
24,000 jobs. (Temple Stoellinger, David Taylor, A Report on the 
Economic Impact to Wyoming's Economy From a Potential Listing of the 
Sage Grouse, University of Wyoming, 2016).
    Wyoming's efforts to conserve sage grouse succeeded because it had 
time to develop and implement its strategy. This time allowed Wyoming 
to solicit participation from a diverse group of stakeholders to 
develop a framework that worked for sage grouse, and people.
    State led conservation efforts benefit listed species too. The FWS 
does not have the resources to recover every listed species. If states 
are implementing conservation plans that preclude the need to list 
species, the FWS can invest more time and money in recovering truly 
imperiled species.
    The rigid timelines in Section 4 of the ESA can hinder creative 
conservation efforts. Western Governors recognized this, and endorsed 
creating flexibility in the ESA to encourage greater prelisting 
conservation. Those recommendations are included as part of my written 
testimony.
    Question 2. The Gray Wolf State Management Act would protect the 
wolf de-listing rule from further judicial review and lend more 
stability and predictability to state management efforts.
    2a. How did years of uncertainty impact the State of Wyoming and 
why is certainty in the de-listing process important to states?
    Answer. When wolves reached their recovery objectives of 10 
breeding pairs and 100 wolves in 2002, Wyoming and its citizens 
anticipated that the state would soon begin managing wolves. However, 
years of litigation and disagreements about state management plans 
followed. Wyoming entered its first of five lawsuits related to wolf 
de-listing in 2004, and resolved its last lawsuit earlier this year.
    In 2009 and 2012, the FWS returned management to the state only to 
have a Federal judge reinstate protections. In the meantime, wolf 
populations rose to nearly 400, and local support for wolves waned.
    For years, Wyoming sportsmen have invested in wolf recovery. 
Through the Game and Fish Department, sportsmen compensate livestock 
producers who suffer losses from wolf depredation. Last year, the Game 
and Fish Department compensated landowners for $390,000 in sheep and 
cattle losses attributed to wolves, which is an increase of $80,000 
over the prior year. Without state management, this number will only 
increase, and sportsmen will grow increasingly frustrated along with 
landowners.
    Earlier this year, the Federal Circuit Court in Washington, DC 
reinstated Wyoming's 2012 de-listing rule. Since then, Wyoming has 
managed wolves pursuant to its management plan. State management should 
result in decreased human/livestock conflict, fewer sportsmen dollars 
going to damage compensation, and increased support for wolves on the 
landscape. The state management plan also ensures a recovered wolf 
population for the foreseeable future. Yet, the threat of litigation 
continues, which perpetuates distrust from the public, and skepticism 
from the state.
    2b. Short of additional acts of Congress to de-list recovered 
species and protect them from years of litigation, how would you 
suggest we improve the de-listing process to lend more certainty and 
predictability to state management efforts?
    Answer. Western Governors identified two specific ways to improve 
the de-listing process, which are detailed in WGA Species Conservation 
and the Endangered Species Act Initiative Year Two Recommendations, 
attached to my written testimony. First, give states the opportunity to 
lead the development of a recovery team, and implementation of a 
recovery plan. The recovery plan should contain criteria, that when 
met, would trigger a status review for potential de-listing or down-
listing.
    Second, once the FWS de-lists a species, consider delaying judicial 
review until the end of the post de-listing monitoring period. This 
would allow states to implement FWS endorsed management plans for a 
minimum of 5 years without the threat of litigation. At that time, 
litigants would have to base their challenge to the de-listing rule on 
realized, rather than theoretical harm. Since no species that FWS 
successfully de-listed due to recovery has ever been relisted, adding 
this provision will not negatively impact wildlife. However, it will 
provide greater certainty to states, and the regulated communities 
impacted by perpetual litigation.
    Question 3. The Listing Reform Act allows for threatened species 
designations to be precluded due to economic factors, and allows for 
reconsideration of precluded threatened species listings only if the 
Secretary determines that there is a danger of species extinction, or 
if the Service receives a new petition that includes alternative 
actions that can be taken to avoid the economic impacts of listing.
    3a. Should economic factors be considered in threatened species 
designations, and if so, why?
    Answer. The impacts of a listing can devastate local economies. 
Governor Mead recognizes this, as do other Western Governors. That is 
one of the reasons that so many states, local governments, landowners, 
industries, and conservationists came together to conserve the greater 
sage grouse. We should encourage more creative, collaborative 
conservation efforts to obviate the need to list species. This creates 
healthier wildlife populations, and ensures that state and local 
economies do not suffer from species listings.
    Western Governors identified two potential statutory solutions to 
incentivize earlier species conservation. Both involve amending Section 
4 of the Endangered Species Act in a way that recognizes and rewards 
state-led, voluntary conservation efforts through deadline flexibility. 
Western Governors also identified a number or regulatory suggestions 
for enhancing voluntary conservation. The specific recommendations are 
described in my written testimony, and attached as the WGA Species 
Conservation and the Endangered Species Act Initiative Year Two 
Recommendations. If implemented, these recommendations should greatly 
reduce the number of threatened listings, thus making consideration of 
economic factors in threatened species designations unnecessary.
    3b. From your perspective, would the ability to preclude threatened 
species listings due to economic factors facilitate higher-quality 
listing decisions that benefit both species and our Nation?
    Answer. The WGA Species Conservation and the Endangered Species Act 
Initiative Year Two Recommendations, attached to my written testimony, 
identify several ideas to alleviate the economic consequences of a 
threatened species listing.
                                 ______
    The  Chairman. Thank you. Mr. Holsinger for 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>    Mr.  Holsinger. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, members of the 
Committee. It is an honor to be here today to testify on these 
important issues.
    It has been since 1988 that the Endangered Species Act was 
substantively amended. If you look back at that time, the 
Soviet Union was a superpower. I was probably listening to Def 
Leppard on a Sony Walkman. Updates to the ESA are long, long 
overdue. And, as Mr. Willms testified, that is probably why the 
Western Governors Association (WGA) has put forth specific 
recommendations for change.
    I cannot underscore the significance here: 19 Western 
Governors, 3 U.S. territories, never before in my career has 
WGA expressly supported specific amendments to this Act. They 
do today, and for very good reason.
    If you step back from the five bills we are talking about 
today, there is a common theme. And that theme, a small number 
of radical litigants are gaming the system at taxpayer expense. 
And, as a result, they are wasting the scarce resources that we 
should be putting forth for species that are truly in need of 
protection and for on-the-ground conservation efforts.
    As the Daily Caller has reported from data from a GAO 
report that the Ranking Member actually ordered, 90 percent of 
ESA settlements have gone to environmental groups. More than 50 
percent of those to two groups: WildEarth Guardians and the 
Center for Biological Diversity (CBD). Those two groups have 
litigated innumerable times. In fact, from 2000 to 2009, CBD 
has filed suit 409 times; WildEarth Guardians, 180; from 2009 
to 2012, CBD 117 lawsuits, WildEarth Guardians, 55.
    Since 1990, we scrutinized Federal court records and found 
that these two groups alone have filed over 1,500 lawsuits--
most against the Department of the Interior and Agriculture, 
most raising ESA as an issue. These groups are gaming the 
system. They are creating the very logjams they sue over.
    Section 4 of the Endangered Species Act allows any person 
to petition to list a species. These groups are petitioning to 
list hundreds at a time. And that simply cannot be done. So, as 
a result, the agencies miss deadlines, and these groups then 
litigate over those deadlines. They sue, they settle, they 
collect their attorney's fees--as you heard, often at 
exorbitant rates--and they rinse and repeat and do it over and 
over again. It is disgraceful, it is wasting our resources, and 
it has to stop.
    What is worse, these habitual litigators are even 
collecting government grants for the privilege. In 2016, 
WildEarth Guardians collected $800,000 from the Federal 
Government, up from $500,000 in 2015. As a result of this 
litigation, we are strangling in red tape, with severe economic 
consequences to hardworking families, local communities, and 
wildlife conservation itself.
    The ESA was passed in 1973 with visions of grizzly bears 
and bald eagles. Who could have foreseen the listings, the 
litigation, the controversy over 32 northwest mollusks, or the 
Chiricahua scurf pea, the alkaligrass? It is time that we re-
prioritize to species that are truly in need.
    We listen to the states and the local governments that 
often have the best information on wildlife. The states have 
been managing wildlife successfully and recognized by the 
courts in doing so since 1896 in the U.S. Supreme Court case of 
Gear v. Connecticut.
    I urge the Committee to adopt these important measures, and 
also consider delegating ESA authority to the states, much like 
we do the Clean Air Act. Listings for full species only, so 
that we can concentrate on our efforts on those truly in need 
of protection.
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
</Hearing>
