<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="24297">
    <intro>    <info>House Hearing, 115 Congress</info>
    <info>From the U.S. Government Publishing Office</info>
    <info>                          H.A.S.C. No. 115-2</info>
    <info>                     CONSIDERATION OF THE COMMITTEE</info>
    <info>                         OVERSIGHT PLAN FOR THE</info>
    <info>                             115TH CONGRESS</info>
    <info>                               __________</info>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES</committee_name>
    <option>                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                              MEETING HELD
                            FEBRUARY 2, 2017
GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT
                               __________
                      U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
24-297                      WASHINGTON : 2017                      
__________________________________________________________________________________________
For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing Office, 
http://bookstore.gpo.gov. For more information, contact the GPO Customer Contact Center, 
U.S. Government Publishing Office. Phone 202-512-1800, or 866-512-1800 (toll-free). 
E-mail, gpo@custhelp.com.  
</option>
</intro>
    <committeeComposition>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES</comitteeM_name>
    <Chairman>
        <Cname>                     One Hundred Fifteenth Congress</Cname>
        <Clocation>                     One Hundred Fifteenth Congress</Clocation>
    </Chairman>
    <people>
        <Pname>WILLIAM M. ``MAC'' THORNBERRY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>WALTER B. JONES</Cname>
        <Clocation> North Carolina</Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>ADAM SMITH</Cname>
        <Clocation> Washington</Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOE WILSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> South Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROBERT A. BRADY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>FRANK A. LoBIONDO</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Jersey</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SUSAN A. DAVIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROB BISHOP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Utah</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JAMES R. LANGEVIN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Rhode Island</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MICHAEL R. TURNER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RICK LARSEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Washington</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE ROGERS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM COOPER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Tennessee</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TRENT FRANKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MADELEINE Z. BORDALLO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Guam</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BILL SHUSTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOE COURTNEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Connecticut</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>K. MICHAEL CONAWAY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>NIKI TSONGAS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Massachusetts</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DOUG LAMBORN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Colorado</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOHN GARAMENDI</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROBERT J. WITTMAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JACKIE SPEIER</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DUNCAN HUNTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARC A. VEASEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE COFFMAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Colorado</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TULSI GABBARD</Pname>
        <Plocation> Hawaii</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>VICKY HARTZLER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Missouri</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BETO O'ROURKE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>AUSTIN SCOTT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Georgia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DONALD NORCROSS</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Jersey</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MO BROOKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RUBEN GALLEGO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PAUL COOK</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SETH MOULTON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Massachusetts</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM BRIDENSTINE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oklahoma</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>COLLEEN HANABUSA</Pname>
        <Plocation> Hawaii</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRAD R. WENSTRUP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CAROL SHEA-PORTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Hampshire</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRADLEY BYRNE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JACKY ROSEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nevada</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SAM GRAVES</Pname>
        <Plocation> Missouri</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>A. DONALD McEACHIN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ELISE M. STEFANIK</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SALUD O. CARBAJAL</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARTHA McSALLY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ANTHONY G. BROWN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Maryland</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEPHEN KNIGHT</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEPHANIE N. MURPHY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEVE RUSSELL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oklahoma</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RO KHANNA</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SCOTT DesJARLAIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Tennessee</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SCOTT H. PETERS</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RALPH LEE ABRAHAM</Pname>
        <Plocation> Louisiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PETE AGUILAR</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TRENT KELLY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Mississippi</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOAQUIN CASTRO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE GALLAGHER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Wisconsin</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MATT GAETZ</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DON BACON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nebraska</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM BANKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Indiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>LIZ CHENEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Wyoming</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Robert L. Simmons II</Pname>
        <Plocation> Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Zach Steacy</Pname>
        <Plocation> Legislative Operations</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CONSIDERATION OF THE COMMITTEE OVERSIGHT PLAN FOR THE 115TH CONGRESS</Pname>
        <Plocation>CONSIDERATION OF THE COMMITTEE OVERSIGHT PLAN FOR THE 115TH CONGRESS</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>House of Representatives</Pname>
        <Plocation>House of Representatives</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Committee on Armed Services</Pname>
        <Plocation>Committee on Armed Services</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Washington</Pname>
        <Plocation> 2017.</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>The committee met</Pname>
        <Plocation> in room </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Thornberry (chairman of the committee) presiding.</Pname>
        <Plocation>Thornberry (chairman of the committee) presiding.</Plocation>
    </people>
</committeeComposition>
    <Statement>
    <opening>OPENING STATEMENT OF HON. WILLIAM M. ``MAC'' THORNBERRY, A</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="HON. WILLIAM M. ``MAC'' THORNBERRY">    REPRESENTATIVE FROM TEXAS, CHAIRMAN, COMMITTEE ON ARMED 
</paragraph>
    <speaker>The Chairman. The committee will come to order</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">A quorum is
now present, although I know some of our members are stuck on a 
bus coming back from a late prayer breakfast.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">Let me welcome everyone. The plan today is to consider and 
vote on the committee oversight plan. We will then immediately 
adjourn and go upstairs for a classified briefing with the 
Defense Intelligence Agency to follow up on our hearing 
yesterday about the state of the world.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">Before we get to that, it is a tradition in this committee 
that we specifically introduce and welcome each of the new 
members to our committee. So let me do that on this side of the 
aisle right quick and then turn to Mr. Smith to introduce the 
members that he has so far on the other side of the aisle.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">First I want to welcome Dr. Scott DesJarlais, representing 
Tennessee's Fourth District, whose constituents are part of the 
workforce of Arnold Air Force Base, Oak Ridge National 
Laboratory, and Redstone Arsenal. Fourth term member, he has 
worked closely with this committee on force protection issues, 
especially after the shooting at the Chattanooga Naval Reserve 
Center.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">Next to him is Dr. Ralph Abraham. So if we have any medical 
problems in our late night markup, we are set. Dr. Abraham 
represents Louisiana's Fifth District, a voice for Louisiana's 
military installations. He is not only a medical doctor, he is 
also a veterinarian, and served in the Army National Guard and 
is currently a Coast Guard auxiliary pilot.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">The chair next to him is filled by Trent Kelly, who 
represents Mississippi's First District. A colonel in the 
Mississippi Army National Guard, he served for 30 years as an 
engineer, including multiple tours in Iraq. It is good to see 
Mississippi represented again on this committee.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">Next to him is--oh, no. Kelly is--I am sorry. I didn't see 
you. Trent Kelly is here.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">The seat next to him, who is not here, is Dr. Mike 
Gallagher, another kind of doctor, he has a Ph.D. from 
Georgetown, representing Wisconsin's Eighth District. Mike 
served 7 years as a Marine Corps intelligence officer, 
including tours in Iraq, and has focused his work on 
counterterrorism, Middle East policy, including time at the 
National Counterterrorism Center, and unfortunately the Senate 
Foreign Relations Committee, which we will have to work out of 
him as soon as we can.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">Now, next to him on the end is Matt Gaetz representing 
Florida's First District, home of one of the largest military 
districts in the country, including Naval Air Station Pensacola 
and Eglin Air Force Base. Matt is a recovering lawyer, and 
joins us from his service in the Florida State legislature.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">I think on the bus coming back from the prayer breakfast is 
Don Bacon, who represents Nebraska's Second Congressional 
District. He is a retired Air Force brigadier general, 
commanded twice at the wing level at Offutt Air Force Base and 
at Ramstein. He deployed four times to the Middle East.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">Next is Jim Banks, who represents Indiana's Third District, 
home of the 122nd Fighter Wing of the Indiana National Guard. A 
naval supply officer, he has very recently completed a tour in 
Afghanistan, and also chaired the Indiana State Senate Veterans 
and Military Committee.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">And, finally, we have Liz Cheney, who represents Wyoming, 
home of F.E. Warren Air Force Base. Liz, of course, has served 
multiple policy roles in the State Department, including the 
second ranked official on U.S. policy in the Middle East. She 
is an accomplished author and commentator on American 
exceptionalism and national security, and has provided 
assistance to this committee even before she was elected to 
Congress.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="The Chairman. The committee will come to order">So we are very pleased at each of the new members on our 
side of the aisle, as we are with all new members to this 
committee.</paragraph>
</Statement>
    <Statement>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF HON. ADAM SMITH, A REPRESENTATIVE FROM WASHINGTON,</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="HON. ADAM SMITH">Let me yield to Mr. Smith for any comments and 
introductions.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="HON. ADAM SMITH">          RANKING MEMBER, COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Smith</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Smith">Well, thank you, Mr. Chairman.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Smith">We have eight new members, we have three more coming, which 
as I understand it, the Steering and Policy Committee will 
finalize tomorrow. So we will introduce them when the time is 
appropriate, but we do have eight new members, six of whom, I 
believe, are here. So we will start with a couple who have been 
on this committee before and welcome them back.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Smith">Colleen Hanabusa, who represents Hawaii's First District, 
which includes Camp H.M. Smith, headquarters of the United 
States Pacific Command. She is a lawyer by profession. As Mr. 
Thornberry said, we won't hold that against anyone. I am a 
lawyer by profession; fortunately got over it. She returns to 
Congress and the Armed Services Committee, having previously 
served in three Congresses: 112th, 113th, 114th. So we welcome 
back her expertise. And certainly, Hawaii is a critical part of 
our national security team. So welcome back.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Smith">Also returning is Carol Shea-Porter, who represents New 
Hampshire's First District, which includes Pease Air Force 
National Guard Base and Portsmouth Naval Shipyard. She is also 
returning to Congress, having served in the 110th, 111th, and 
113th; is the daughter of a Navy World War II veteran and was a 
military spouse while her husband served in the Army during 
Vietnam. Welcome back.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Smith">We now have freshmen members, who are brand-new to the 
committee, starting with Jacky Rosen, who represents Nevada's 
Third District, which is just south of Las Vegas. And just 
north of her district is Nellis and Creech Air Force Bases. And 
she comes to the committee with experience as a software 
developer and computer programmer for a variety of businesses 
in Nevada. Welcome.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Smith">And we have Donald McEachin, who represents Virginia's 
Fourth District, which includes Fort Lee, with the Navy 
installations in Norfolk and Newport News area just outside the 
district. He is the son of an Army veteran and a lawyer by 
profession. He joins the committee having previously served in 
the Virginia House of Delegates and the Virginia Senate.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Smith">Next, we have Salud Carbajal, who represents California's 
24th District, which includes Vandenberg Air Force Base, Camp 
Roberts, and has Naval Base Ventura County and Fort Hunter 
Liggett nearby. He served 8 years in the Marine Corps Reserve, 
including active service during the 1991 Gulf war, and 
previously served on the Santa Barbara County Board of 
Supervisors for 12 years. Thank you for joining us.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Smith">Next, we have Anthony Brown, not far from here, 
representing Maryland's Fourth District, which borders Fort 
Meade and the U.S. Naval Academy. He is a retired colonel. He 
served in the Army from 1984 to 1989, in the Army Reserves from 
1989 to 2014, and was the recipient of the Bronze Star while 
deployed in Iraq in 2004. He served in the Maryland House of 
Delegates for 8 years and as lieutenant governor for another 8 
years. It is great to have your experience on the committee.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Smith">Two more members who are not yet here, but I will introduce 
them anyway. Stephanie Murphy, who represents Florida's Seventh 
District, which includes Naval Support Activity Orlando, which 
is involved in a range of research and development programs 
supporting the Department of Defense. She also served as a 
national security specialist in the Office of the Secretary of 
Defense, where she worked on a wide range of security issues 
from counterterrorism, foreign military relations, to strategic 
planning for the Department.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Smith">And last, we have Ro Khanna, who represents California's 
17th District, a district that includes a number of technology 
companies doing work with the Department of Defense. He served 
in the Obama administration as the Deputy Assistant Secretary 
of Commerce for International Trade and recently taught 
economics at Stanford University.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Smith">And let me just say in sum in agreeing with the chairman, 
we have a remarkable amount of talent on both sides of the 
aisle, as you can hear. I mean, the breadth of experience from 
military to technology, and on, I think, is going to serve this 
committee very well. So we welcome all of you and look forward 
to working with you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Smith">    I yield back.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>The Chairman. Very well said</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="The Chairman. Very well said">I completely agree.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="The Chairman. Very well said">Now we will go to our business, which is adoption of the 
oversight plan. This is required by House Rules. We sent it to 
everybody a couple days ago, so that you have had a chance to 
look at it. Obviously, we touch on a number of topics in the 
oversight plan, but we also try to leave flexibility so that we 
can adjust to changes that happen over the course of the next 2 
years.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="The Chairman. Very well said">So we have worked on this collaboratively with Mr. Smith, 
and hopefully this can be adopted with the committee.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="The Chairman. Very well said">What? Painlessly, he says. So I am all for that as well.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="The Chairman. Very well said">    Do you have any other comments you would like to make?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Smith</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. Smith"> No, Mr. Chairman. Thank you.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>The Chairman. Great</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="21" speaker="The Chairman. Great">So let me officially call up Committee
Resolution No. 4 regarding the committee oversight plan for the 
115th Congress. The clerk shall read the resolution.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="22" speaker="The Chairman. Great">    Dr. Bright. Committee Resolution No. 4. Resolved, that the 
Committee on Armed Services, U.S. House of Representatives, 
adopt the committee oversight plan for the 115th Congress, a 
copy of which has been distributed to each member.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>The Chairman. Following consultation with Mr</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="23" speaker="The Chairman. Following consultation with Mr">Smith, I ask
unanimous consent the resolution be considered as read and open 
for amendment at any point.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="24" speaker="The Chairman. Following consultation with Mr">    Without objection, it is so ordered.
</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="24" speaker="The Chairman. Following consultation with Mr">    The Chairman. Is there any discussion on the oversight </paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="25" speaker="The Chairman. Following consultation with Mr">Without objection, it is so ordered.
plan?</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="26" speaker="The Chairman. Following consultation with Mr">Are there any amendments to the oversight plan?</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="27" speaker="The Chairman. Following consultation with Mr">    If not, the chair recognizes the gentleman from Utah for 
the purpose of offering a motion.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Bishop</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="28" speaker="Mr. Bishop"> Mr. Chairman, I move to adopt the Committee
Resolution No. 4, concerning the committee oversight plan.
</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="28" speaker="Mr. Bishop">    The Chairman. The question now occurs on the motion from </paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="29" speaker="Mr. Bishop">Mr. Chairman, I move to adopt the Committee
Resolution No. 4, concerning the committee oversight plan.
the gentleman from Utah. So members in favor will say aye.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="30" speaker="Mr. Bishop">Those opposed, say no.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="31" speaker="Mr. Bishop">In the opinion of the chair, the ayes have it. The ayes 
have it, a quorum being present. The motion is adopted. And 
without objection, a motion to reconsider is laid upon the 
table. Without objection, committee staff is authorized to make 
technical and conforming changes to reflect the action of the 
committee in adopting Committee Resolution No. 4.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="32" speaker="Mr. Bishop">And I think that is all the business we have. Again, we 
will start immediately upstairs in 2212 with our classified 
briefing with the Defense Intelligence Agency.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="33" speaker="Mr. Bishop">The committee stands adjourned.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="34" speaker="Mr. Bishop">Whereupon, at 10:24 a.m., the committee was adjourned.</paragraph>
</Statement>
</Hearing>
