<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="26739">
    <intro>    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <info>                         [H.A.S.C. No. 115-54]</info>
    <info>                                HEARING</info>
    <info>                                   ON</info>
    <info>                   NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT</info>
    <info>                          FOR FISCAL YEAR 2018</info>
    <info>                                  AND</info>
    <info>              OVERSIGHT OF PREVIOUSLY AUTHORIZED PROGRAMS</info>
    <info>                               BEFORE THE</info>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES</committee_name>
    <option>                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                         FULL COMMITTEE HEARING
                                   ON
                          THE FISCAL YEAR 2018
                     NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION
                        BUDGET REQUEST FROM THE
                         DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                             JUNE 12, 2017
                           _________ 
                U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
 26-739                 WASHINGTON : 2018      
</option>
</intro>
    <committeeComposition>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES</comitteeM_name>
    <Chairman>
        <Cname>                     One Hundred Fifteenth Congress</Cname>
        <Clocation>                     One Hundred Fifteenth Congress</Clocation>
    </Chairman>
    <people>
        <Pname>WILLIAM M. ``MAC'' THORNBERRY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>WALTER B. JONES</Cname>
        <Clocation> North Carolina</Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>ADAM SMITH</Cname>
        <Clocation> Washington</Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOE WILSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> South Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROBERT A. BRADY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>FRANK A. LoBIONDO</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Jersey</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SUSAN A. DAVIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROB BISHOP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Utah</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JAMES R. LANGEVIN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Rhode Island</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MICHAEL R. TURNER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RICK LARSEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Washington</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE ROGERS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM COOPER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Tennessee</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TRENT FRANKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MADELEINE Z. BORDALLO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Guam</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BILL SHUSTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOE COURTNEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Connecticut</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>K. MICHAEL CONAWAY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>NIKI TSONGAS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Massachusetts</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DOUG LAMBORN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Colorado</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOHN GARAMENDI</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROBERT J. WITTMAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JACKIE SPEIER</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DUNCAN HUNTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARC A. VEASEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE COFFMAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Colorado</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TULSI GABBARD</Pname>
        <Plocation> Hawaii</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>VICKY HARTZLER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Missouri</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BETO O'ROURKE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>AUSTIN SCOTT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Georgia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DONALD NORCROSS</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Jersey</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MO BROOKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RUBEN GALLEGO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PAUL COOK</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SETH MOULTON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Massachusetts</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM BRIDENSTINE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oklahoma</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>COLLEEN HANABUSA</Pname>
        <Plocation> Hawaii</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRAD R. WENSTRUP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CAROL SHEA-PORTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Hampshire</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRADLEY BYRNE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JACKY ROSEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nevada</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SAM GRAVES</Pname>
        <Plocation> Missouri</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>A. DONALD McEACHIN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ELISE M. STEFANIK</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SALUD O. CARBAJAL</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARTHA McSALLY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ANTHONY G. BROWN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Maryland</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEPHEN KNIGHT</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEPHANIE N. MURPHY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEVE RUSSELL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oklahoma</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RO KHANNA</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SCOTT DesJARLAIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Tennessee</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TOM O'HALLERAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RALPH LEE ABRAHAM</Pname>
        <Plocation> Louisiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>THOMAS R. SUOZZI</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TRENT KELLY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Mississippi</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE GALLAGHER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Wisconsin</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MATT GAETZ</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DON BACON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nebraska</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM BANKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Indiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>LIZ CHENEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Wyoming</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jenness Simler</Pname>
        <Plocation> Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Tim Morrison</Pname>
        <Plocation> Counsel</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>William S. Johnson</Pname>
        <Plocation> Counsel</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Britton Burkett</Pname>
        <Plocation> Clerk</Plocation>
    </people>
</committeeComposition>
    <Directory>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <Speakers>STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>Hon Adam Smith</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative from Washington Ranking Member</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon William M ``Mac Thornberry</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>'' a Representative from Texas Chairman</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <Witness>Gen Joseph F Dunford</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Jr USMC</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon James N Mattis</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Secretary of Defense US Department of Defense</peopleinfo>
    <option>APPENDIX</option>
    <Speakers>Prepared Statements:</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>Gen Joseph F Dunford</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Jr Mattis Hon James N Smith</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker>July  Documents Submitted for the Record: Senate Testimony of Under Secretary of State for Arms Control Rose Gottemoeller</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>July</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker>Committee on Armed Services Witness Responses to Questions Asked During the Hearing: Dr Abraham Mr Byrne Mr Carbajal Mr Langevin Mr Moulton Ms Speier Questions Submitted by Members Post Hearing: Mr Bridenstine Mr Hunter Mr Langevin Mr O'Rourke Ms Rosen Mr Scott Mr Smith Ms Speier Ms Tsongas THE FISCAL YEAR  NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION BUDGET REQUEST FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE  House of Representatives</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Washington DC</peopleinfo>
    <option>    REPRESENTATIVE FROM TEXAS, CHAIRMAN, COMMITTEE ON ARMED 
                            SERVICES
    The Chairman. The committee will come to order.
    The committee meets to receive the testimony of the 
Secretary of Defense and the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of 
Staff on the administration's fiscal year 2018 budget request. 
We welcome Secretary Mattis for the first time before our 
committee, and we welcome Chairman Dunford back.
    The question today, as it is each year for this hearing, is 
how well the administration's proposal meets the security needs 
of the Nation, factoring in both the external threats and the 
current state of our military.
    This committee has repeatedly heard testimony over the past 
2 years that our country faces more serious, complex security 
challenges now than we have ever faced before. And the hearings 
and briefings we have held on the current state of our military 
have been disturbing.
    The administration's budget request of $603 billion for 
base requirements is 6 percent above the 2017 enacted level and 
3 percent above the last Obama administration budget proposal. 
It is also $37 billion below what this committee assessed last 
fall was needed and about $58 billion below the fiscal year 
2012 Gates budget, which was independently validated by the 
bipartisan National Defense Panel.
    But, of course, the issue is not about numbers. The issue 
is about what those numbers provide for the men and women who 
serve and what security the budget provides to the Nation. It 
is about whether we can defend the United States and our allies 
against North Korean missiles, for example. It is about whether 
we have the number of ships and planes and other military 
capability to deter aggression and maintain peace.
    It is about doing right by our most valuable asset: our 
people. The men and women who serve deserve the best weapons 
and equipment our country can provide, and I am afraid today 
they are not getting it.
    It is always tempting to divert this discussion into a 
broader budget debate about taxes and other spending issues. 
Those issues are not within the jurisdiction of this committee 
or of these witnesses. But, regardless of our views on those 
other issues, we cannot wait until we solve our budget problems 
to adequately fund our military. We cannot wait until we 
perfect our acquisition system to have planes that fly and 
ships that sail. The world is not stopping and waiting on us to 
get our act together. It moves on, and it is moving on in a 
dangerous direction.
    2018 is a key decision point. We have spent 6 years just 
getting by, asking more and more of those who serve, and 
putting off the choices that have to be made. We cannot keep 
piling missions on our service members without ensuring they 
have all they need to succeed.
    Does the administration's budget proposal accomplish that 
goal? That is the question we intend to examine tonight.
    I yield to the ranking member, Mr. Smith, for any comments 
he would like to make.
</option>
    <option>the Appendix on page 81.]
</option>
    <option>          RANKING MEMBER, COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES
    Mr. Smith. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    And I agree with much of what you said, and I think the 
best way to sum it up is what you said about putting off 
choices. That is what we have done for quite a while, and not 
just on the defense budget but on our tax reform, on all 
aspects of the budget as well.
    And I think the impact on the military is as the chairman 
describes. And the real problem we have right now is a major 
disconnect between what we would like to do and the amount of 
money that we are prepared to do it.
    As the chairman mentioned, even the President's budget at 
$603 billion does not match what our committee assessed was 
needed. I think even more tellingly, it does not match what the 
President has said he is going to do. In fact, it is very, very 
distant from that.
    If you talk about a 350-ship Navy and, I think, 570,000-
person Army, you talk about all the planes, all the nuclear 
modernization that they want to do, I do not even begin to know 
what the yearly number would be to get to that. I am suspecting 
it is well north of $700 billion, $800 billion.
    So we have all these grand ideas of what we want. We do not 
have the money to get there. And who is left in the lurch? The 
people that you serve. The men and women of the military are 
left with missions that they do not have the resources to 
fulfill.
    And I think we have to start making choices. And I have got 
a bit of a preview with your opening remarks, and I agree with 
you. Certainly, the House of Representatives is in no position 
to lecture you about making choices. We do not have a budget. 
It is the middle of June. I have been here 20 years; we have 
never gone this long without providing numbers for the basic 
appropriations bills, defense being chief among them.
    So we continue to stall, I think, in hopes that the money 
will magically appear or we will figure out some way to spend 
money that does not count, something. But we have got to make 
choices. We have got to decide what we are going to fund.
    And I will disagree with the chairman on one issue, and 
that is the notion that somehow as the Armed Services 
Committee, everything else that goes on in the budget really 
does not have anything to do with us and we should not worry 
about it. One thing most certainly does, and that is revenue. 
Because how much money you have, in my experience anyway, has a 
profound impact on how much money you are able to spend.
    You know, I will skip for the moment the argument about the 
Department of Homeland Security and how important the State 
Department is--well, I lied. I did not skip it. But I think all 
of those things are important.
    But if you just want to get right down to the basics, even 
if you just want to say forget about all that, all we are 
concerned about is the Armed Services Committee and providing 
for the men and women in our military the resources that they 
need, the planes, the ships, the equipment, the training, the 
readiness, all of that, it is nonsensical to say that the 
amount of revenue we have available does not impact that. It 
absolutely does.
    And if we are talking about putting together--and I use 
``we'' loosely here--a tax reform proposal that is going to 
further cut taxes by $2 trillion to $3 trillion, and if there 
are members of this committee who want to support that and then 
want to keep coming back to this committee and talking about 
how terrible it is that we do not fund our military, I think 
that is a huge inconsistency that we need to reconcile.
    We have clear needs in the Defense Department. Let us make 
sure we provide the money for them. If we are not prepared to 
provide the money for them, then we need to come up with a 
different set of strategies, which I agree with the chairman: 
It will be very difficult. We have a very complex threat 
environment, from North Korea to Iran to Russia to a rising 
China to--not to mention the terrorist groups that are still 
out there and active. So it would be difficult to redo that 
strategy. But we would be better off doing that than to have a 
strategy that we have no intention of funding, and right now, 
that is kind of what the executive branch looks like they are 
doing. They have a strategy that they have no intention of 
funding. We have to fix that.
    Just two quick things, and I will ask questions about this 
when we get the chance. I think countering what Russia is doing 
is an enormously important step for us. They are in a very 
comprehensive effort to undermine the very values that our 
country has fought for in the post-World War II environment. 
They have an incredibly complicated cyber effort, propaganda 
effort. They are doing all of this stuff to basically foster 
authoritarian regimes at the expense of democracies and to 
undermine alliances that the United States has relied on in 
that post-World War II world to maintain peace and security and 
to protect our interests. I think we need a strategy on that.
    And I will be very curious to get your take on exactly what 
we are doing in Qatar. We hear what the Secretary of State says 
about it, and mere hours later, the President says something 
diametrically opposed to that. It is a very destabilizing 
situation right now in the Middle East.
    I agree with the Secretary of State. We should be finding 
ways to solve that problem, not ways to throw gasoline on the 
fire. But I am just not clear what the administration's 
strategy is.
    And considering the fact that CENTCOM [U.S. Central 
Command] is located in Qatar, I would think that, Mr. 
Secretary, you would have some opinions on what we ought to do 
to try to resolve that situation. And I would look forward to 
that comment.
    And, with that, I yield back and look forward to your 
testimony.
</option>
    <option>Appendix on page 83.]
    The Chairman. The committee is pleased to welcome the 
Honorable James Mattis, Secretary of Defense; General Joseph F. 
Dunford, Jr., Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff; and Mr. 
David Norquist, the Under Secretary and Comptroller, who has 
been on the job, I think, about a week.
    So, welcome, all of you, to the committee.
    Without objection, any written comments you would like to 
make will be included in the record.
    Mr. Secretary, the floor is yours.
</option>
    <option>                     DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE
    Secretary Mattis. Well, Chairman Thornberry, Ranking Member 
Smith, and members of the committee, I appreciate the 
opportunity to testify in support of the President's budget 
request for fiscal year 2018. And I appreciate the committee 
accepting my written statement for the record.
    I am joined by Chairman Dunford and the Department's new 
Comptroller, Under Secretary of Defense David Norquist. As 
noted by the chairman, he is new, but he will be vital to 
gaining your confidence that we know where our money is going 
once you give it to us through a good audit.
    This budget request holds me accountable to the men and 
women of the Department of Defense. Every day, more than 2 
million service members and nearly 1 million civilians do their 
duty honoring previous generations of veterans and civil 
servants who have sacrificed for our country, and it is a 
privilege to serve alongside them.
    We in the Department of Defense are keenly aware of the 
sacrifices made by the American people to fund our military. 
Many times in the past, we have looked reality in the eye, met 
challenges with the help of congressional leadership, and built 
the most capable warfighting force in the world.
    There is no room for complacency, however, and we have no 
God-given right to victory on the battlefield. Each generation 
of Americans, from the halls of Congress to the battlefields, 
earns victory through commitment and sacrifice. And, yet, for 4 
years, the Department of Defense has been subject to or 
threatened by automatic across-the-board cuts as a result of 
sequester, a mechanism meant to be so injurious to the military 
it would never go into effect. But it did go into effect, and 
as forecast by then-Secretary of Defense Panetta, the damage 
has been severe.
    In addition, during 9 of the past 10 years, Congress has 
enacted 30 separate continuing resolutions to fund the 
Department of Defense, thus inhibiting our readiness and 
adaptation to new challenges. We need bipartisan support for 
this budget request.
    In the past, by failing to pass the budget on time or 
eliminate the threat of sequestration, Congress sidelined 
itself from its active constitutional oversight role. 
Continuing resolutions coupled with sequestration blocked new 
programs, prevented service growth, stalled industry 
initiative, and placed troops at greater risk.
    Despite the tremendous efforts of this committee, Congress 
as a whole has met the present challenge with lassitude not 
leadership. I retired from military service 3 months after 
sequestration took effect. Four years later, I have returned to 
the Department, and I have been shocked by what I have seen 
about our readiness to fight.
    While nothing can compare to the heartache caused by the 
loss of our troops during these wars, no enemy in the field has 
done more to harm the combat readiness of our military than 
sequestration. We have only sustained our ability to meet 
America's commitments abroad because our troops have stoically 
shouldered a much greater burden. But our troops' stoic 
commitment cannot reduce the growing risk. It took us years to 
get into this situation. It will require years of stable 
budgets and increased funding to get out of it.
    I urge members of this committee and Congress to achieve 
three goals: first, fully fund our request, which required an 
increase to the defense budget caps; second, pass a fiscal year 
2018 budget in a timely manner to avoid yet another harmful 
continuing resolution; and, third, eliminate the threat of 
future sequestration cuts so we can provide a stable budgetary 
planning horizon.
    Stable budgets and increased funding are necessary because 
of four external forces acting on the Department at the same 
time. The first force that we must recognize is 16 years of 
war. When Congress approved the All-Volunteer Force in 1973, 
our country never envisioned sending our military to war for 
more than a decade without pause or conscription. America's 
long war has placed a heavy burden on men and women in uniform 
and their families.
    A second concurrent force acting on the Department is the 
worsening global security situation. We must look reality in 
the eye. Russia and China are seeking veto power over the 
economic, diplomatic, and security decisions on their 
periphery. North Korea's reckless rhetoric and provocative 
actions continue despite United Nations' censure and sanctions, 
while Iran remains the largest long-term challenge to Mideast 
stability. All the while, terrorist groups murder the innocent 
and threaten peace in many regions and target us.
    A third force acting on the Department is adversaries 
actively contesting America's capabilities. For decades the 
United States enjoyed uncontested or dominant superiority in 
every operating domain or realm. We could generally deploy our 
forces when we wanted, assemble them where we wanted, and 
operate how we wanted. Today, every operating domain, including 
outer space, air, sea, undersea, land, and cyberspace, is 
contested.
    A fourth concurrent force is rapid technological change. 
Among the other forces noted thus far, technological change is 
one that necessitates new investment, innovative approaches, 
and new program starts that have been denied us by law when we 
have been forced to operate under continuing resolution.
    Each of these four forces--16 years of war, the worsening 
security environment, contested operations in multiple domains, 
and the rapid pace of technological change--requires stable 
budgets and increased funding to provide for the protection of 
our citizens and for the survival of our freedoms.
    I reiterate that security and solvency are my watchwords as 
Secretary of Defense. The fundamental responsibility of our 
government is to defend the American people, providing for our 
security, and we cannot defend America and help others if our 
Nation is not both strong and solvent.
    So we in the Department of Defense owe it to the American 
public and to the Congress to ensure we spend every dollar 
wisely. President Trump has nominated for Senate approval 
specific individuals who will bring proven skills to discipline 
our Department's fiscal processes to ensure we do so.
    This first step to restoring readiness is underway, thanks 
to Congress' willingness to support the administration's 
request for an additional $21 billion in resources for fiscal 
year 2017 to address vital warfighting readiness shortfalls. 
Your support put more aircraft in the air, more ships to sea, 
and more troops in the field to train. However, we all 
recognize that it will take a number of years of higher funding 
delivered on time to restore readiness.
    To strengthen the military, President Trump requested a 
$639 billion top line for the 2018 defense budget. This budget 
reflects five priorities:
    The first priority is continuing to improve warfighter 
readiness begun in fiscal year 2017, filling in the holes from 
tradeoffs made during 16 years of war, 9 years of continuing 
resolutions, and Budget Control Act caps.
    The second priority is increasing capacity and lethality 
while preparing for future investment, driven by results from 
the National Defense Strategy. Our 2018 budget request ensures 
the Nation's current nuclear deterrent will be sustained and 
supports continuation of its much-needed modernization process.
    The third priority is reforming how the Department does 
business. I am devoted to gaining full value from every 
taxpayer dollar spent on defense, thereby earning the trust of 
Congress and the American people. We have begun implementation 
of a range of reform initiatives directed by the 2017 National 
Defense Authorization Act and are on track to enter into a full 
agency-wide financial statement audit as required by statute. I 
urge Congress to support the Department's request for authority 
to conduct the 2021 Base Realignment and Closure, or BRAC, 
round. I recognize the careful deliberation that members must 
exercise in considering it. But BRAC is one of the most 
successful and significant efficiency programs. We forecast 
that a properly focused base closure effort will generate $2 
billion or more annually over a 5-year period, enough to buy 
300 Apache attack helicopters, 120 F-18s, or 4 Virginia-class 
submarines.
    The fourth priority in the fiscal year 2018 budget request 
is keeping faith with service members and the families. 
Talented people are the Department's most valuable asset, but 
we must continually balance these requirements against other 
investments critical to readiness, equipment, and modernization 
to ensure the military is the most capable warfighting force in 
the world. Investment in military compensation, blended 
retirement, the military health system, and family programs are 
essential to fielding the talent we need to sustain our 
competitive advantage on the battlefield.
    The fifth priority is support for overseas contingency 
operations. The fiscal year 2018 President's budget requests 
$64.6 billion, focusing on operations in Afghanistan, Iraq, and 
Syria, increasing efforts to sustain NATO's [North Atlantic 
Treaty Organization's] defenses to deter aggression and global 
counterterrorism operations. ISIS [Islamic State of Iraq and 
Syria] and other terrorist organizations represent a clear and 
present danger, and I am encouraged by the willingness of our 
allies and partners to share the burden of this campaign.
    Moving forward, the fiscal year 2019 budget informed by the 
new National Defense Strategy will have to make hard choices as 
we shape the fiscal year 2019 to 2023 defense program. The 
Department will work with President Trump, Congress, and this 
committee to ensure future budget requests are sustainable and 
provide the Commander in Chief with viable military options 
that support America's security.
    I am keenly aware that each of you understand the 
responsibility we share to ensure our military is ready to 
fight today and in the future. I need your help to inform your 
fellow Members of Congress about the reality facing our 
military and the need for Congress as a whole to pass the 
budget on time.
    Thank you for your strong support over many years and for 
ensuring our troops have the resources and equipment they need 
to fight and win on the battlefield. I pledge to collaborate 
closely with you for the defense of our Nation and our joint 
effort to keep our Armed Forces second to none.
    Chairman Dunford is prepared to discuss the military 
dimensions of the budget request.
</option>
    <option>the Appendix on page 86.]
    The Chairman. Mr. Chairman.
</option>
    <option>                        CHIEFS OF STAFF
    General Dunford. Chairman Thornberry, Ranking Member Smith, 
distinguished members of the committee, it is an honor to join 
Secretary Mattis and Under Secretary Norquist here tonight.
    I am honored to represent your men and women in uniform, 
and it is because of them I can begin by saying with confidence 
that your Armed Forces today are the most capable in the world. 
However, the competitive advantage that the United States 
military has long enjoyed is eroding.
    A number of factors have contributed to that erosion. Since 
9/11, an extraordinarily high operational tempo has accelerated 
the wear and tear of our weapons and equipment. Meanwhile, 
budget instability and the Budget Control Act have forced the 
Department to operate with far fewer resources than required 
for the strategy of record. As a consequence, we prioritize 
near-term readiness at the expense of replacing aging equipment 
and capability development. We have also maintained a force 
that consumes readiness as fast as we build it. We lack 
sufficient capacity to meet current operational requirements 
while rebuilding and maintaining full-spectrum readiness.
    You know, the Secretary and the service chiefs have 
addressed that dynamic in their testimonies, and I fully concur 
with their assessments, but beyond the current readiness, we 
are confronted with another significant challenge that I assess 
to be near term. While we have been primarily focused on the 
threat of violent extremism, our adversaries and potential 
adversaries have developed advanced capabilities and 
operational approaches, and these are specifically designed to 
limit our ability to project power. They recognize that our 
ability to project power is the critical capability necessary 
to defend the homeland, advance our interests, and meet our 
alliance commitments.
    Secretary Mattis alluded to it today: Russia, China, and 
Iran field a wide range of cyber, space, aviation, maritime, 
and land capabilities. And these are specifically designed to 
limit our ability to deploy, employ, and sustain our forces.
    Russia and China have also modernized their nuclear arsenal 
while North Korea has been on a relentless path to field a 
nuclear ICBM [intercontinental ballistic missile] that can 
reach the United States. In just a few years, if we do not 
change the trajectory, we will lose our qualitative and 
quantitative competitive advantage. The consequences will be 
profound. It will adversely affect our nuclear deterrence, our 
conventional deterrence, and our ability to respond if 
deterrence fails.
    Alternatively, we can maintain our competitive advantage 
with sustained, sufficient, and predictable funding. To that 
end, the fiscal year 2018 budget is an essential step. However, 
this request alone will not fully restore readiness or arrest 
the erosion of our competitive advantage. Doing this will 
require a sustained investment beyond fiscal year 2018.
    Specific recommendations for fiscal year 2019 and beyond 
will be informed by the forthcoming strategy development. 
However, we know now that continued growth in the base budget 
for at least 3 percent above inflation is the floor necessary 
to preserve today's relative competitive advantage.
    We ask for your support, and while we do that, we recognize 
the responsibility to maintain the trust of the American 
taxpayer. We take that seriously and will continue to eliminate 
redundancies and achieve efficiencies where possible.
    Thank you again for the opportunity to appear before you. 
And, more importantly, thanks for ensuring that America's sons 
and daughters are never in a fair fight. With that, I am ready 
for your questions.
</option>
</Directory>
</Hearing>
