<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="25089">
    <intro>    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <info>                         [H.A.S.C. No. 115-23]</info>
    <info>                                 HEARING</info>
    <info>                                   ON</info>
    <info>                   NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT</info>
    <info>                          FOR FISCAL YEAR 2018</info>
    <info>                                  AND</info>
    <info>              OVERSIGHT OF PREVIOUSLY AUTHORIZED PROGRAMS</info>
    <info>                               BEFORE THE</info>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES</committee_name>
    <option>                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
</option>
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON READINESS HEARING</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                                   ON
                THE CURRENT STATE OF THE U.S. AIR FORCE
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                             MARCH 22, 2017
[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
                                __________
                    U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE                    
25-089                       WASHINGTON : 2018                     
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------
For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing Office, 
http://bookstore.gpo.gov. For more information, contact the GPO Customer Contact Center, 
U.S. Government Publishing Office. Phone 202-512-1800, or 866-512-1800 (toll-free).
E-mail, gpo@custhelp.com.  
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON READINESS</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                  JOE WILSON, South Carolina, Chairman
ROB BISHOP, Utah                     MADELEINE Z. BORDALLO, Guam
AUSTIN SCOTT, Georgia                JOE COURTNEY, Connecticut
STEVE RUSSELL, Oklahoma              TULSI GABBARD, Hawaii
MIKE ROGERS, Alabama                 CAROL SHEA-PORTER, New Hampshire
VICKY HARTZLER, Missouri             A. DONALD McEACHIN, Virginia
ELISE M. STEFANIK, New York          SALUD O. CARBAJAL, California
MARTHA McSALLY, Arizona, Vice Chair  ANTHONY G. BROWN, Maryland
SCOTT DesJARLAIS, Tennessee          STEPHANIE N. MURPHY, Florida
TRENT KELLY, Mississippi             RO KHANNA, California
MIKE GALLAGHER, Wisconsin
                Margaret Dean, Professional Staff Member
                Brian Garrett, Professional Staff Member
                          Jodi Brignola, Clerk
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <Directory>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <Speakers>STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>Hon Madeleine Z Bordallo</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Delegate from Guam Ranking Member</peopleinfo>
</Directory>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomittee_name>Subcommittee on Readiness......................................     1</subcomittee_name>
    <Witness>Hon Joe Wilson</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative from South Carolina Chairman</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <Witness>Lt Gen Maryanne Miller</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>USAF Chief of Air Force Reserve</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Lt Gen L Scott Rice</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>USAF Director</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Maj Gen Scott D West</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>USAF Director of Current Operations</peopleinfo>
    <option>APPENDIX</option>
    <Speakers>Prepared Statements:</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>Lt Gen L Scott Rice</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Lt Gen L Scott</peopleinfo>
    <option>Subcommittee on Readiness,</option>
    <option>                         Washington, DC, Wednesday, March 22, 2017.
    The subcommittee met, pursuant to call, at 2:13 p.m., in 
room 2118, Rayburn House Office Building, Hon. Joe Wilson 
(chairman of the subcommittee) presiding.
</option>
    <option>      SOUTH CAROLINA, CHAIRMAN, SUBCOMMITTEE ON READINESS
    Mr. Wilson. Ladies and gentlemen, I call this hearing of 
the Readiness Subcommittee of the House Armed Services 
Committee to order.
    I am pleased to welcome everyone here today for an 
unclassified session on the current state of the U.S. Air 
Force. The purpose of this hearing is to clarify the 
information we have heard repeatedly over the past several 
weeks and months. We have received briefings and hearings from 
leading national security experts, testimony from all of the 
service vice chiefs, the Department of Defense's quarterly 
readiness report to Congress, and the Government Accountability 
Office assessment of the military's readiness recovery.
    We have also recently heard from both the U.S. Army and the 
U.S. Navy on those services' current state of readiness. Each 
briefing and hearing further confirms that our services are 
indeed in a readiness crisis.
    I reiterate my belief that the first responsibility of the 
Federal Government is to provide for the security of its 
nations, to accomplish for citizens what they cannot do by 
themselves.
    Therefore, it is our responsibility as members of the 
subcommittee to continue to better understand the readiness 
situation of the U.S. Air Force, to understand where we 
continue to take risks and to understand the plan to recover 
readiness ability.
    I would like to welcome the distinguished panel of senior 
leaders of the U.S. Air Force, the U.S. Air National Guard, and 
the Air Force Reserve present today. This afternoon, we are 
honored to have with us Lieutenant General L. Scott Rice, U.S. 
Air Force, Director, Air National Guard; Lieutenant General 
Maryanne Miller, U.S. Air Force, Chief of Air Force Reserve, 
and Commander, Air Force Reserve Command; and Major General 
Scott D. West, U.S. Air Force, Director of Current Operations 
and Deputy Chief of Staff for Operations, Headquarters, U.S. 
Air Force.
    I thank each of you for testifying today and look forward 
to your thoughts and insights as you highlight the current 
state of the U.S. Air Force.
    I now turn to our ranking member, Delegate, Congresswoman 
Madeleine Bordallo of Guam, for any remarks she may have.
</option>
    <option>           RANKING MEMBER, SUBCOMMITTEE ON READINESS
    Ms. Bordallo. Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman. And thank 
you to the witnesses for being here this afternoon.
    General Rice, I would also like to thank you again for your 
January visit to the territory of Guam.
    And welcome to General Miller and General West.
    We have had airmen from all squadrons deployed over the 
past year. And as you know, our men and women of the Guam Air 
National Guard are keeping busy, and I know they appreciate 
your support. And of course, there is significant investment 
and activity at Andersen Air Force Base, which will require 
continued attention as the most strategic American base in the 
Pacific region.
    I would also like to note my appreciation that each 
component of the Air Force is represented today, given that we 
had to reschedule the Reserve Component discussion last year.
    While some challenges, such as critical skills shortages, 
affect each component, they do so differently. So it is 
essential that we receive perspectives from each of you to 
fully understand the Air Force's state of readiness.
    This is the third in a series of hearings we have held in 
this subcommittee on the state of the military departments. 
However, the Air Force is unique in that the demand for its 
units has increased in recent years while the service has 
shrank.
    While we will certainly discuss pilot shortages, I am also 
interested to learn about where recruiting and retention 
challenges are facing other critical specialties.
    The new administration has proposed a significant increase 
in military spending, the majority of which is, theoretically, 
to help build back readiness in the short term. However, it is 
not clear that the Department of Defense has a coherent view to 
do so in the long term. And I will be interested to hear about 
the Air Force's plan to meet both its near- and long-term 
readiness and what methods are in place to guide your progress.
    I am concerned that without careful attention, existing 
challenges could be compounded, as we are likely to continue to 
sustain high operational tempos.
    So again, ladies and gentlemen, I look forward to our 
discussion here today. And I, again, thank you to our witnesses 
for being here and for your service to our great country.
    Mr. Chairman, I yield back.
    Mr. Wilson. And thank you, Congresswoman Bordallo, for your 
extraordinary service.
    We will now have opening statements beginning with General 
Rice and proceed. And we look forward to your testimony today.
</option>
    <option>              GUARD, HEADQUARTERS, U.S. AIR FORCE
    General Rice. Thank you, sir. Chairman Wilson and Ranking 
Member Bordallo and the distinguished members of the committee, 
thank you for inviting me here today to join the Active 
Component and the Air Force Reserve in the discussion about the 
United States Air Force readiness.
    First, I would like to express my sincere appreciation to 
the men and women of the Air National Guard for their hard 
work, professionalism, and dedication to serving this great 
Nation. Day in and day out, we have 105,700 uniformed Guard 
airmen as well as civilians serving with great distinction and 
patriotism as they help defend the homeland and support 
America's national security interests around the world.
    I also want to thank you for your support of the Air 
National Guard and its important mission.
    Today, the Air National Guard, as an operational Reserve, 
continues to be exceptionally capable and effective in its 
global warfare, warfight, and domestic roles. The complexities 
and uncertainties of the strategic environment underscore the 
importance of ensuring that the Air National Guard is resourced 
to respond successfully to the Nation's growing reliance on its 
capabilities.
    We ask a lot of our people and it is my job to ensure our 
airmen have the resources and training to do the jobs we ask 
them. Readiness is my first priority, followed second by 21st 
century Guard airmen, with modernization and recapitalization 
third.
    Our lines of effort in these areas will enable the 
successful accomplishment of the National Guard's core mission 
sets of fighting America's wars, protecting and defending the 
homeland, and building domestic and global partnerships.
    Readiness is more than an isolated priority within the Air 
National Guard. Improved readiness implicitly includes 
advancement in my two other priorities. The Air National Guard 
is undertaking two lines of effort to improve readiness.
    First, we are working to increase end strength and 
effective manning. As you know, end strength alone does not 
tell an accurate story about readiness. A better indicator of 
readiness is effective manning or measuring the amount of fully 
qualified Guard airmen who occupy positions within their career 
field.
    I need your support for a wide variety of recruiting and 
retention initiatives in order to ensure I have the right 
airmen in the right positions. I would also ask for your 
support to take advantage of opportunities to recruit new 
members into the Air National Guard, including those separating 
from the Active Component.
    My second line of effort to improve readiness is maximizing 
training opportunities and the funding to support it. Right 
now, the total force faces a training shortfall in many 
critical areas. There simply is not enough initial training 
slots to meet demand. Numerous unit conversions, churn, endured 
by the Air National Guard over the past 15 years have increased 
the demand for training, which decreases the value of 
experience.
    We also need continuation training, the training in which 
our fully qualified Guard airmen must engage to remain current. 
Two ways to increase readiness to meet the continuation 
training demands are funding both a second-shift maintenance in 
order to make additional aircraft available and authorizing and 
funding the additional full and drill status positions.
    This committee's interest, knowledge, support, and time is 
vital to increasing the readiness of the Air National Guard. 
Together, we must ensure the men and women of the Air National 
Guard have the support they need as they balance 
responsibilities at home, civilian careers, patriotic domestic 
service, and their responsibility that this commitment is to 
our national security. We must ensure they are prepared for the 
tasks we expect them to perform.
    Thank you for inviting me here today, and I look forward to 
your questions.
    [The joint prepared statement of General Rice, General 
Miller, and General West can be found in the Appendix on page 
27.]
    Mr. Wilson. Thank you very much, General Rice.
    General Miller.
</option>
    <option>             RESERVE, HEADQUARTERS, U.S. AIR FORCE
    General Miller. Chairman Wilson, Congresswoman Bordallo, 
and members of the subcommittee, I thank you very much for the 
opportunity to address you on the readiness of the Air Force 
Reserve.
    For 69 years, this Nation has called on the Air Force 
Reserve to support national security objectives and all types 
of military operations all over the globe. Today, the Air Force 
Reserve balances the operational agility needed for today's 
fight while simultaneously providing the strategic depth needed 
to respond to the unexpected and emerging threats of our 
Nation.
    Combatant commanders benefit from the capabilities and 
experiences our Reserve citizen airmen bring to the joint 
fight. On any given day, there are approximately 6,000 Air 
Force Reservists on Active Duty orders operating in air, space, 
and cyber domains, supporting overseas contingency efforts and 
operations around the globe.
    Ready airmen ensure the capability of a unit to accomplish 
its designed mission to meet the demands of the National 
Military Strategy when called upon. Over the past few years, 
shrinking defense budgets and lack of fiscal stability have 
stressed our readiness levels, threatening our ability to reach 
and sustain full readiness. Congress' efforts to assist with 
our budget shortfalls have helped, but permanent relief from 
the BCA [Budget Control Act] caps is crucial to a steady and 
enduring full readiness recovery.
    As I measure the state of readiness within the Air Force 
Reserve, I assess across the spectrum of people, equipment, 
training, and the demands of the operational tempo. As you 
know, our people are our greatest asset to ensuring global 
vigilance, global reach, and global power.
    In order to support emerging mission requirements of the 
Air Force while continuing to support enduring combat missions, 
I need a slight growth in manpower over the next few years.
    With respect to our personnel readiness challenges, I am 
focused on three main areas, the first being the pilot 
shortage, the second, the shortfalls in full-time support, and 
finally, critical skills manning.
    The readiness and modernization of our aircraft and 
equipment are essential to maintaining an agile, combat-
capable, and interoperative Air Force. The Air Force Reserve 
leverages the National Guard and Reserve equipment 
appropriation to increase capability and ensure 
interoperability within the joint fight. This account is 
particularly important in this fiscally constrained 
environment, and I want to thank you all for your tremendous 
support of that account.
    Training is our number one job when not engaged in the 
fight. To maximize our training successes, we need predictable, 
reliable funding and training allocations in order to match our 
resources to our Reservists' availability.
    Over the last 26 years of being engaged across the globe in 
exercises, contingencies, and operations, we have successfully 
adjusted to an operational Reserve. Portions of our force are 
stressed, but our airmen are resilient, engaged, and honored to 
serve.
    Thank you for your tremendous support of the Air Force 
Reserve and for the opportunity to discuss our readiness. I 
look forward to your questions.
    Mr. Wilson. Thank you, General Miller.
    We now proceed to General West.
</option>
</subcomitteeComposition>
</Hearing>
