<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="24676">
    <intro>    <info>House Hearing, 115 Congress</info>
    <info>From the U.S. Government Publishing Office</info>
    <Doc-title>H.A.S.C. No. 115-4 THE STATE OF THE MILITARY</Doc-title>
    <option>                       THE STATE OF THE MILITARY
                               __________
</option>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES</committee_name>
    <option>                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                            FEBRUARY 7, 2017
                           _________ 
                U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
 24-676                 WASHINGTON : 2017       
____________________________________________________________________
 For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing Office,
Internet:bookstore.gpo.gov. Phone:toll free (866)512-1800;DC area (202)512-1800
  Fax:(202) 512-2104 Mail:Stop IDCC,Washington,DC 20402-001     
</option>
</intro>
    <committeeComposition>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES</comitteeM_name>
    <Chairman>
        <Cname>                     One Hundred Fifteenth Congress</Cname>
        <Clocation>                     One Hundred Fifteenth Congress</Clocation>
    </Chairman>
    <people>
        <Pname>WILLIAM M. ``MAC'' THORNBERRY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>WALTER B. JONES</Cname>
        <Clocation> North Carolina</Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>ADAM SMITH</Cname>
        <Clocation> Washington</Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOE WILSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> South Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROBERT A. BRADY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>FRANK A. LoBIONDO</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Jersey</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SUSAN A. DAVIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROB BISHOP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Utah</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JAMES R. LANGEVIN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Rhode Island</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MICHAEL R. TURNER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RICK LARSEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Washington</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE ROGERS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM COOPER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Tennessee</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TRENT FRANKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MADELEINE Z. BORDALLO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Guam</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BILL SHUSTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOE COURTNEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Connecticut</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>K. MICHAEL CONAWAY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>NIKI TSONGAS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Massachusetts</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DOUG LAMBORN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Colorado</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOHN GARAMENDI</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROBERT J. WITTMAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JACKIE SPEIER</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DUNCAN HUNTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARC A. VEASEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE COFFMAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Colorado</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TULSI GABBARD</Pname>
        <Plocation> Hawaii</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>VICKY HARTZLER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Missouri</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BETO O'ROURKE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>AUSTIN SCOTT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Georgia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DONALD NORCROSS</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Jersey</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MO BROOKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RUBEN GALLEGO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PAUL COOK</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SETH MOULTON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Massachusetts</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM BRIDENSTINE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oklahoma</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>COLLEEN HANABUSA</Pname>
        <Plocation> Hawaii</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRAD R. WENSTRUP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CAROL SHEA-PORTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Hampshire</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRADLEY BYRNE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JACKY ROSEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nevada</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SAM GRAVES</Pname>
        <Plocation> Missouri</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>A. DONALD McEACHIN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ELISE M. STEFANIK</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SALUD O. CARBAJAL</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARTHA McSALLY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ANTHONY G. BROWN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Maryland</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEPHEN KNIGHT</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEPHANIE N. MURPHY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEVE RUSSELL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oklahoma</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RO KHANNA</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SCOTT DesJARLAIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Tennessee</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TOM O'HALLERAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arizona</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RALPH LEE ABRAHAM</Pname>
        <Plocation> Louisiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>THOMAS R. SUOZZI</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TRENT KELLY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Mississippi</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE GALLAGHER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Wisconsin</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MATT GAETZ</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DON BACON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nebraska</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JIM BANKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Indiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>LIZ CHENEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Wyoming</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Robert L. Simmons II</Pname>
        <Plocation> Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Kari Bingen</Pname>
        <Plocation> Professional Staff Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>William S. Johnson</Pname>
        <Plocation> Counsel</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Britton Burkett</Pname>
        <Plocation> Clerk</Plocation>
    </people>
</committeeComposition>
    <Directory>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <Speakers>STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker> Cooper Hon Jim</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo> a Representative from Tennessee Committee on Armed Services</peopleinfo>
    <Witness> Thornberry Hon William M ``Mac</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>'' a Representative from Texas Chairman</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <Witness> Allyn GEN Daniel B</Witness>
    <peopleinfo> USA Vice Chief of Staff of the Army Moran</peopleinfo>
    <Witness> Walters Gen Glenn M</Witness>
    <peopleinfo> USMC Assistant Commandant of the Marine Corps</peopleinfo>
    <Witness> Wilson Gen Stephen W</Witness>
    <peopleinfo> USAF Vice Chief of Staff of the Air Force</peopleinfo>
    <option>APPENDIX</option>
    <Speakers>Prepared Statements:</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker> Allyn GEN Daniel B Moran</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo> ADM William F Smith Hon Adam</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> Documents Submitted for the Record: There were no Documents submitted Witness Responses to Questions Asked During the Hearing: Mr Kelly Ms McSally Mr Wittman Questions Submitted by Members Post Hearing: Mr Brooks Mr Graves Ms Hanabusa Mr Lamborn Mr Langevin Mr Scott Mr Shuster Ms Speier Ms Stefanik Mr Turner THE STATE OF THE MILITARY  House of Representatives Committee on Armed Services</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo> Washington DC</peopleinfo>
    <option>    REPRESENTATIVE FROM TEXAS, CHAIRMAN, COMMITTEE ON ARMED 
                            SERVICES
    The Chairman. The committee will come to order.
    Last week, the committee held classified and unclassified 
sessions on the state of the world or, more accurately, the 
state of the world environment in which the American military 
must operate and U.S. national security must be protected. I 
was struck by the essential point General Petraeus made that we 
face many threats, and can overcome any of them, except perhaps 
what we do to ourselves.
    Today, we turn to the state of the U.S. military. I 
continue to be concerned and sometimes even disturbed by 
evidence that is accumulating on the damage inflicted upon our 
military in recent years and the stresses our forces are under. 
That damage comes from a variety of factors, including budget 
cuts of 20 percent, continuing resolutions, the failure to 
recognize or at least admit and then address mounting readiness 
problems, as well as the shrinking size of the force, while 
keeping the tempo of operations high.
    There is certainly plenty of blame to go around between 
both parties and both the executive and legislative branches 
for this state of affairs. But now with a new administration 
and a new Congress, we have an opportunity to begin the 
repairs. To do that, we need a clear understanding of the state 
of our military and the immediate trends that challenge us. For 
that, we turn to the vice chiefs of each of our services, and 
we ask that each of you provide this committee your best 
professional military judgment in answering the questions we 
pose.
    As was emphasized last week, the world situation is 
dangerous and complex. This is no time to exaggerate or to 
underplay the challenges before us. Only by facing them 
squarely can we meet the obligations all of us have to the 
Constitution, to the men and women who serve, and to the 
American public.
    I will now yield to the distinguished acting ranking 
member, the gentleman from Tennessee, for any comments he would 
like to make.
</option>
    <option>    Mr. Cooper. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    I would like to ask unanimous consent that the opening 
statement of the real ranking member, Mr. Smith, be inserted in 
the record.
    The Chairman. Without objection.
    The prepared statement of Mr. Smith can be found in the 
Appendix on page 57.
    Mr. Cooper. And speaking on my own behalf, I think we all 
realize that few subjects are more important for the future of 
the Nation than the readiness of our military forces. I hope 
that we all know that few things are more detrimental to that 
readiness than sequestration.
    So I share the chairman's hope, and I am not ready to be 
optimistic yet, but I hope that we can deal with sequestration 
this year and end it permanently. So it is going to be up to 
the folks on this committee, the largest committee in the House 
of Representatives, to make sure that our impact is felt in 
ending sequestration.
    So thank you, Mr. Chairman. I look forward to the testimony 
of the witnesses.
    The Chairman. Thank you, sir.
    I am pleased to welcome each of our witnesses today and 
also to express, I know, the committee's appreciation for your 
service in this job and for each of your service to the 
country. Without objection, your complete written statements 
will be made part of the record.
    And let me just briefly introduce General Daniel Allyn, 
Vice Chief of Staff of the Army; Admiral William Moran, Vice 
Chief of Naval Operations; General Stephen Wilson, Vice Chief 
of Staff of the Air Force; and General Glenn Walters, Assistant 
Commandant of the Marine Corps. Again, thank you all for being 
here.
    We would be interested in any opening comments each of you 
would like to make.
    We will start with you, General Allyn.
</option>
    <option>                            THE ARMY
    General Allyn. Thank you, Chairman Thornberry and 
Congressman Cooper, distinguished members of the committee. 
Thank you for the opportunity to testify on the state of your 
United States Army. I appreciate your support and demonstrated 
commitment to our soldiers, Army civilians, families, and 
veterans, and look forward to discussing the strength of our 
Army with you today.
    This is a challenging time for our Nation and certainly for 
our Army. The unipolar moment is over and replacing it is a 
multipolar world characterized by competition and uncertainty. 
Today, the Army is globally engaged with more than 182,000 
soldiers supporting combatant commanders in over 140 worldwide 
locations.
    My recent travel, I visited our soldiers in 15 countries 
since Veterans Day, reinforces that the Army is not about 
programs. It is all about people; our people executing security 
missions all around the globe. The strength of the All-
Volunteer Force truly remains our soldiers. These young men and 
women are trained, ready, and inspired. And we must be 
similarly inspired to provide for them commensurate with their 
extraordinary service and sacrifice.
    To meet the demands of today's unstable global security 
environment and maintain the trust placed in us by the American 
people, the Army requires sustained, long-term, and predictable 
funding.
    Absent additional legislation, the caps set by the Budget 
Control Act BCA of 2011 will return in fiscal year 2018, 
forcing the Army to once again draw down our end strength, 
reduce funding for readiness, and increase the risk of sending 
undertrained and poorly equipped soldiers into harm's way, a 
preventable risk our Nation must not accept.
    We thank all of you for recognizing that plans to reduce 
the Army to 980,000 soldiers would threaten our national 
security. And we appreciate all your work to stem the drawdown. 
Nevertheless, the most important actions you can take, steps 
that will have both positive and lasting impact, will be to 
immediately repeal the 2011 Budget Control Act and ensure 
sufficient funding to train, man, and equip the fiscal year 
2017 NDAA National Defense Authorization Act authorized 
force. Unless this is done, additional top-line and OCO 
Overseas Contingency Operations funding, though nice in the 
short term, will prove unsustainable, rendering all your hard 
work for naught.
    In this uncertain environment, readiness remains our 
number-one priority. Sufficient and consistent funding is 
essential to build and sustain current readiness, to progress 
towards a more modern, capable force sized to reduce risk for 
contingencies and to recruit and train the best talent within 
our ranks. Readiness remains paramount because the Army does 
not have the luxury of taking a day off. We must stand ready at 
a moment's notice to defend the United States and its 
interests.
    With your assistance, the Army will continue to resource 
the best-trained, best-equipped, and best-led fighting force in 
the world. We thank you for the steadfast support of our 
outstanding men and women in uniform. And please accept my 
written testament for the record. And I look forward to your 
questions.
    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    The prepared statement of General Allyn can be found in 
the Appendix on page 59.
    The Chairman. Thank you.
    Admiral.
</option>
    <option>                           OPERATIONS
    Admiral Moran. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    And good morning to the members of the committee. It is a 
privilege to be here with my fellow vice chiefs to talk about 
the readiness of our military.
    It is easiest for me to talk to you in terms of simple 
supply and demand. As many of you know, the ongoing demand for 
naval forces far exceeds our long-term supply. And that need 
continues to grow with no end in sight. Supply is best summed 
up in one fact: Your Navy today is the smallest it has been in 
99 years.
    That said, we are where we are, which makes it urgent to 
adequately fund, fix, and maintain the fleet that we do have. 
And by the way, we have never been busier. A quick snapshot 
around the globe and you will see the Navy is the Nation's 
primary deterrence policy in places like the Arabian, 
Mediterranean, and South China Seas.
    Over the past 5 or 6 years, this call for deterrence and to 
be ready to take action has grown, principally because of the 
aggressive growth from expanding naval competitors like Russia 
and China. And when you add threats from Iran, North Korea, 
ISIS Islamic State of Iraq and Syria, and others, it is a 
very, very busy time for your Navy.
    Our sailors have always risen to the occasion, answering 
the call no matter the circumstances and no matter the 
resources. From providing food, water, and medical assistance 
in Haiti, to striking hostile sites in Yemen, to Navy SEALs 
Sea, Air, Land teams taking down terrorist leaders, we are 
getting it done, because that is who we are, that is what makes 
us the best navy in the world. But the unrelenting pace, 
inadequate resources, and small size are taking their toll.
    Our testimony today may seem like a broken record. Our Navy 
faces increased demand without the size and resources required 
to properly maintain and train for our future. And every year 
we have had to make tough choices, often choosing to sacrifice 
long-term readiness to make sure we could be ready to answer 
the call today.
    We are in fact putting our first team on the field, but we 
lack serious depth on the bench. This didn't happen overnight; 
readiness declines tend to be insidious. From year to year we 
have all learned to live with less and less. We have certainly 
learned to execute our budget inefficiently with nine 
consecutive continuing resolutions, but this has forced us to 
repeatedly take money from cash accounts that are the lifeblood 
of building long-term readiness in our Navy. It is money for 
young lieutenants to fly high and fast, and who need air under 
their seats to perfect their skills in the future. It is money 
for spare parts so sailors can fix the gear that they have. It 
is money for sailors to operate at sea in all kinds of 
conditions to build instincts that create the best warfighters 
in the world. With your help we have the opportunity to change 
this.
    It starts by strengthening our foundation. Let's ensure the 
ships and aircraft that we do have are maintained and 
modernized so they provide the full measure of combat power. 
Then let's fill in the holes by eliminating inventory 
shortfalls in ships, submarines, and aircraft throughout the 
fleet. And together by taking these steps, we can achieve the 
ultimate goal of sizing the Navy to meet the strategic demands 
of this dynamic and changing world.
    Mr. Chairman, thank you for the opportunity to be here, and 
I look forward to your questions.
    The prepared statement of Admiral Moran can be found in 
the Appendix on page 69.
    The Chairman. General Wilson.
</option>
    <option>                        OF THE AIR FORCE
    General Wilson. Thank you Chairman Thornberry, Congressman 
Cooper, distinguished members of the committee.
    On behalf of the Secretary of the Air Force and our chief 
of staff, it is an honor to be with you today and to be with my 
fellow vice chiefs to talk to you about the state of our Air 
Force and readiness.
    Your American airmen are proud to be part of the most 
powerful joint force warfighting team in its history. Together 
we provide leaders with a broad range of options to protect our 
country and its interests both home and abroad. For the past 70 
years, responsive, flexible, and agile American airpower has 
been our Nation's first and most sustainable solution in both 
crisis and conflict underwriting every other instrument of 
power. We provide the Nation with unrelenting Global Vigilance, 
Global Reach, and Global Power.
    In short, your Air Force is always in demand and always 
there. Look no further than 2 weeks ago when your Air Force 
executed a precision strike in Sirte, Libya, killing over 100 
violent extremists. This was a textbook transregional 
multidomain, multifunction mission. Air Force space, cyber, and 
ISR intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance warriors 
provided precision navigation and timing while monitoring enemy 
communication and movement.
    Simultaneously, two B-2 bombers took off from Missouri, 
flew 17 hours one way, refueled with numerous tankers and 
teamed with two MQ-9s to employ precision munitions within 10 
seconds of their designated time over target. They then flew 
another 17 hours home and landed safely back in the United 
States.
    Meanwhile, airmen operate 60 persistent remotely piloted 
aircraft patrols, 24/7/365. They are the blinking eye for 
combatant commanders. They remotely fly missions from the 
continental United States, teaming with nearly 20,000 forward 
deployed airmen to support operations like the recent events in 
Raqqa and Mosul where our RPA remotely piloted aircraft 
fighters and bombers have conducted 92 percent of the strikes 
against ISIS.
    We did this all while simultaneously ensuring two-thirds of 
our nuclear triad and 75 percent of our nuclear command and 
control remain robust, reliable, flexible, and survivable 
options for the nations. During the allotted time of this 
hearing, an average of 65 mobility aircraft will take off; 
430,000 cyber connections will be blocked; 5 homeland defense 
missions will fly; and 3 strikes against ISIS will occur. Each 
of these actions are enabled by airmen providing space-based 
position, navigation, and timing and communication for our 
military, while also providing GPS Global Positioning System 
capability to the world's 3 billion users.
    The capabilities of our airmen provided to our Nation and 
our allies have never been more vital and the global demand for 
American airpower will only grow in the future. American airmen 
remain professional, innovative, and dedicated; quite frankly, 
the envy of the world. However, we are out of balance. The 
demand for our mission and our people exceed the supply. The 26 
years of continuous combat has limited our ability to prepare 
for the future against advanced future threats, scenarios with 
the lowest margin of error and the highest risk to national 
security.
    This nonstop combat, paired with the budget instability and 
lower-than-planned top lines, has made the United States Air 
Force the smallest, oldest equipped, and least ready in our 
history. We have attempted to balance risk across the force to 
maintain readiness. And we have been forced to make 
unacceptable trades between readiness, force structure, and 
modernization.
    Today's global challenges require an Air Force ready not 
only to defeat violent extremism, but an Air Force prepared to 
modernize for any threat the Nation may face.
    Mr. Chairman, I will close by quoting General Douglas 
MacArthur. He sent the following cable as he escaped the 
Philippines in 1942. He said, ``The history of failure in war 
can be summed up in two words: too late. Too late in 
comprehending the deadly purpose of a potential enemy, too late 
in realizing the moral danger, too late in preparedness.''
    Distinguished members of the committee, preparedness or 
readiness cannot be overlooked. Your Air Force needs 
congressional support to repeal the Budget Control Act and 
provide stable, predictable funding. It is critical to 
rebuilding our military's full-spectrum readiness, which is the 
number-one priority for the Secretary of Defense. We need to 
act now, before it is too late.
    On behalf of the chief of staff and the Secretary of the 
Air Force and the 660,000 Active, Guard, Reserve, and civilian 
airmen who serve our Nation, thank you for your tireless 
support for us.
    I look forward to your questions.
    The prepared statement of General Wilson can be found in 
the Appendix on page 75.
    The Chairman. General Walters.
</option>
</Directory>
</Hearing>
