<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9E510352103E46A09FBAE524A2C1BC4D" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 3889 EH: To amend title 38, United States Code, to require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to conduct a longitudinal study of the vocational rehabilitation programs administered by the Secretary.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">110th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 3889</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to conduct a longitudinal study of the vocational rehabilitation programs administered by the Secretary.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" style="OLC" id="H5E1AE4F1E4AF43439981F77FF9B819C4"> 
<section id="H9854938574AF4C72BCF8454FD76D5C42" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Longitudinal study of Department of Veterans Affairs vocational rehabilitation programs</header> 
<subsection id="H048C8A0E2DC44C108D025EE1D691E4F2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/31">Chapter 31</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9A7E9DE955964C4BB373ADC6F29F799B" style="USC">
<section id="H52DBFD1FD96B497FA67F849143E3EBE8"><enum>3122.</enum><header>Longitudinal study of vocational rehabilitation programs</header> 
<subsection id="H4F79AC6D83854EDA92323F81F94DDDAC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study required</header> 
<paragraph id="H82456E3166514856B3D53AFE0FA003D" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Subject to the availabilty of appropriated funds, the Secretary shall conduct a longitudinal study of a statistically valid sample of each of the groups of individuals described in paragraph (2). The Secretary shall study each such group over a period of at least 20 years.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD9BF13E906134494BF6F22703D9204A8" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The groups of individuals described in this paragraph are the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB52651A628764A04AC77DA82C37FEA60"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Individuals who begin participating in a vocational rehabilitation program under this chapter during fiscal year 2009.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H658C658C0E8E4C5795B6DD9D51BB058"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Individuals who begin participating in such a program during fiscal year 2011.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA3DEE1046833486D83AA246C3D3B11"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Individuals who begin participating in such a program during fiscal year 2014.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H293CAEC029C84DB88926D0BAC7B178D7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">By not later than July 1 of each year covered by the study required under subsection (a), the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives a report on the study during the preceding year.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6B021471579642FAA7B8F13E27419DE6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contents of report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall include in the report required under subsection (b) any data the Secretary determines is necessary to determine the long-term outcomes of the individuals participating in the vocational rehabilitation programs under this chapter. The Secretary may add data elements from time to time as necessary. In addition, each such report shall contain the following information:</text> 
<paragraph id="H4A64E27F3FE34BCC8E1FF232659E1FC8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of individuals participating in vocational rehabilitation programs under this chapter who suspended participation in such a program during the year covered by the report.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H557EAEA79B9D4C5B83D2EF7C7228F823"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The average number of months such individuals served on active duty.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H63F231B7C76442479998848454493069"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The distribution of disability rating of such individuals.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H511FEE4535A449489B88A732F6B5327B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The types of other benefits administered by the Secretary received by such individuals.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF8E4907119E142D99E27D86227393678"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The types of social security benefits received by such individuals.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE0BD4887F4D841C398A4207164002900"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any unemployment benefits received by such individuals.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9854927113674A6295A999EBE2F8605F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The average number of months such individuals were employed during the year covered by the report.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1AC5CD99F3B04B4F934228189ECABF8"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The average annual starting and ending salaries such individuals who were employed during the year covered by the report.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H06B7D0B0D2204F7B87AEC9037ECBD54B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The number of such individuals enrolled in an institution of higher learning, as that term is defined in section 3452(f) of this title.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA4DFFE5DDB1A4EE4916FB685005EBDFB"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The average number of academic credit hours, degrees, and certificates obtained by such individuals during the year covered by the report.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0015FE16678649BEBD7B00D81704D081"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The average number of visits such individuals made to Department medical facilities during the year covered by the report.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8EA3F7B2843D4910AA6E724BC259CAD"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The average number of visits such individuals made to non-Department medical facilities during the year covered by the report.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H05C10649362A4498AF53A200BCC03508"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The average annual income of such individuals.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H90F987A56F644A649BB1628904146F71"><enum>(14)</enum><text>The average total household income of such individuals for the year covered by the report.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD2F2A3193AF54322A14BE7B8045F42C3"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The percentage of such individuals who own their principal residences.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE8A3CDFF7EFD4A1581BD5B7559C77616"><enum>(16)</enum><text>The average number of dependents of each such veteran.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9A789F394CF3454AB91EAD9E16124946"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H727BE3A553174C91AF33B7A844B7292E" style="USC">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">3122. Longitudinal study of vocational rehabilitation programs.</toc-entry></toc> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20080520" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives May 20, 2008.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 


