<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" dms-id="HBB36566612FE4EF084987300994DC611" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>109 HR 5252 EH: Communications Opportunity, Promotion, and Enhancement Act of 2006</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">109th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5252</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To promote the deployment of broadband networks and services.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H8FF36D4B66CF44B3B30574ADD9F325E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H144BB85308524ADFB1C9E1DB59F600A4" section-type="section-one" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header> 
<subsection id="H87D254CA37144EAB9E6B84B94261A1C3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Communications Opportunity, Promotion, and Enhancement Act of 2006</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7BE85DA49A70453A907DC2888ED230DA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header> 
<toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"> 
<toc-entry idref="H144BB85308524ADFB1C9E1DB59F600A4" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HC6302DBFB53040689F9FE2B7FF93296B" level="title">Title I—National Cable Franchising</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HC6E214A03DA447D489F4CE0400A4C9D" level="section">Sec. 101. National cable franchising.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H876BE958C3A84F00A7F0648E916F05FF" level="section">Sec. 102. Definitions.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HF61C8A96B3AE441F8914475386A8C800" level="section">Sec. 103. Monitoring and reporting.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HD14A756F7DCD467BA9032F8F006B1911" level="section">Sec. 104. Rule of construction.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HBD0F393A30334272B034FA87D4994170" level="title">Title II—Enforcement of Broadband Policy Statement</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HD7EADDF1898840E0AEF469B474F551D" level="section">Sec. 201. Enforcement of broadband policy statement.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H006B6DE983BF4EBD82D95BC601D34F22" level="title">Title III—VOIP/911</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H1B63BCEEFC174EED9E789499D2B13C7F" level="section">Sec. 301. Emergency services; interconnection.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HE34C1BDD1A354FC28752DCCA0429F6C2" level="section">Sec. 302. Compensation and contribution.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H2DD67FFFA4304648811BF93252EA3C94" level="title">Title IV—Municipal provision of services</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H90D994BFFE22427CB94F684BE22CECD7" level="section">Sec. 401. Government authority to provide services.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H3FA2D596E9A4463DA32E353BFCF3864D" level="title">Title V—Broadband Service</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H8E98C197F2AF42C2A0D0B2E7F7000790" level="section">Sec. 501. Stand-alone broadband service.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H8AB728AD53244877BD004635D854D073" level="section">Sec. 502. Study of interference potential of broadband over power line systems.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H0FAC4D25C39A442681A958594FE149A" level="title">Title VI—Seamless Mobility</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H31B919D8585943C09D6949AF7FDA7746" level="section">Sec. 601. Development of seamless mobility.</toc-entry> </toc></subsection></section> 
<title id="HC6302DBFB53040689F9FE2B7FF93296B"><enum>I</enum><header>National Cable Franchising</header> 
<section id="HC6E214A03DA447D489F4CE0400A4C9D"><enum>101.</enum><header>National cable franchising</header> 
<subsection id="H6FD4D64995884FDDAD108E6D4E434716"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part III of title VI of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/541">47 U.S.C. 541 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H69A2EE3A34CD42E180CF00C4036C008E" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H7B2F31428F2643DFB8C0E30000D65F03"><enum>630.</enum><header>National cable franchising</header> 
<subsection id="H78C15B7CEADC48FD00164F6BF42FE2C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National franchises</header> 
<paragraph id="HB177740D9D014FEBB4719EEEF4063B76" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Election</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person or group that is eligible under <internal-xref idref="HDD9B56C7EECE4616BE1F88D2CC8FC59" legis-path="630.(d)">subsection (d)</internal-xref> may elect to obtain a national franchise under this section as authority to provide cable service in a franchise area in lieu of any other authority under Federal, State, or local law to provide cable service in such franchise area. A person or group may not provide cable service under the authority of this section in a franchise area unless such person or group has a franchise under this section that is effective with respect to such franchise area. A franchising authority may not require any person or group that has a national franchise under this section in effect with respect to a franchise area to obtain a franchise under section 621 or any other law to provide cable service in such franchise area.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H96DF0EB4BD944E4695924BFE19637655"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>To obtain a national franchise under this section as authority to provide cable service in a franchise area, a person or group shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0A8D62F3EAF44E79B800C7EABE005411"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> file with the Commission a certification for a national franchise containing the information required by <internal-xref idref="HB784C54702364D42876D012DD8FB9DA1" legis-path="630.(a)(3)">paragraph (3)</internal-xref> with respect to such franchise area, if such person or group has not previously obtained a national franchise; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H72A2034D3F02464E9B595E758E40217C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>file with the Commission a subsequent certification for additional franchise areas containing the information required by <internal-xref idref="HB784C54702364D42876D012DD8FB9DA1" legis-path="630.(a)(3)">paragraph (3)</internal-xref> with respect to such additional franchise areas, if such person or group has previously obtained a national franchise.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB784C54702364D42876D012DD8FB9DA1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contents of certification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such certification shall be in such form as the Commission shall require by regulation and shall contain—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2D80AED3A8D849B1B5EF888BC4FBD2BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the name under which such person or group is offering or intends to offer cable service; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8B6F3E99A54E48F286B3AE83D7D3E79D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the names and business addresses of the directors and principal executive officers, or the persons performing similar functions, of such person or group; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA1F9DC81F3764E8C9643BE73BFBAAED2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the location of such person or group’s principal business office; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8130CEA874EC4FC299C5CBE799991581"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the name, business address, electronic mail address, and telephone and fax number of such person or group’s local agent; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBF95C371EB1E48928015ADF930FE6041"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a declaration by such person or group that such person or group is eligible under subsection (d) to obtain a national franchise under this section; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3EF9164156924C4B998DBDAFF5B74100"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an identification of each franchise area in which such person or group seeks authority to offer cable service pursuant to such certification, which franchise area shall be—</text> 
<clause id="HA33884030FCB4007B93EF4006DBEAD10"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the entirety of a franchise area in which a cable operator is, on the date of the filing of such certification, authorized to provide cable service under section 621 or any other law (including this section); or </text></clause> 
<clause id="H4BBC7CFA68184CCCBA9591A0F68CBDE9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a geographic area that covers the entirety of the jurisdiction of a unit of general local government, except that—</text> 
<subclause id="H0FFD25A8B11640D2A431335E83546559"><enum>(I)</enum><text>if the geographic area overlaps with a franchise area in which a cable operator is, on such date, authorized to provide cable service under section 621 or any other law, the geographic area identified in the certification under this clause as a franchise area shall not include the overlapping area; and </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HE75CED6E41B4428DA31F1BCFD220B6A2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if such geographic area includes areas that are, respectively, within the jurisdiction of different franchising authorities, the certification shall specify each such area as a separate franchise area;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC423FD10F33D40F28DB296CBD1321C19"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a declaration that such person or group transmitted, or will transmit on the day of filing such declaration, a copy of such certification to the franchising authority for each franchise area for which such person or group is filing a certification for authority to offer cable service under this section;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF6D8E6F8308844D19C8FB2BEF3104FC0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a declaration by the person or group that the person or group will comply with the rights-of-way requirements of the franchising authority in accordance with <internal-xref idref="HE85CCA3AFB164D7200878812F1A1D72B" legis-path="630.(f)">subsection (f)</internal-xref>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB37D9A391C3E493990F861CC5F88BDCE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a declaration by the person or group that—</text> 
<clause id="H9D5800ED54D14CCDA4E1DCAC25794FB7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the person or group will comply with all Commission consumer protection and customer service rules under section 632(b) (including the rules adopted under section 632(b) pursuant to subsection (g) of this section); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2045FCC266CE4AF983D1D51E74377CD1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the person or group agrees that such standards may be enforced by the Commission or by the franchising authority in accordance with <internal-xref idref="H7E3256E565F44CE59CADA5F8E0147B2E" legis-path="630.(g)">subsection (g) of this section</internal-xref>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H09E8DD7E97C94D06884713FD33B65181"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Local notification; preservation of opportunity to negotiate</header> 
<subparagraph id="H6957CAB022AE4EAF9C19669C3C65BF5D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Copy to franchising authority</header><text>On the day of filing any certification under <internal-xref idref="H0A8D62F3EAF44E79B800C7EABE005411" legis-path="630.(a)(2)(A)">paragraph (2)(A)</internal-xref> or <internal-xref idref="H72A2034D3F02464E9B595E758E40217C" legis-path="630.(a)(2)(B)">(B)</internal-xref> for a franchise area, the person or group shall transmit a copy of such certification to the franchising authority for such area.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBA67BEBEEF554438AF9D21C92D103823"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Negotiated franchise agreements permitted</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall prevent a person or group from negotiating a franchise agreement or any other authority to provide cable service in a franchise area under section 621 or any other law. Upon entry into any such negotiated franchise agreement, such negotiated franchise agreement shall apply in lieu of any national franchise held by that person or group under this section for such franchise area.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H739172A71BB84880ACBA41C9637D1318"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Updating of certifications</header><text>A person or group with a certification under this section shall update any information contained in such certification that is no longer accurate and correct.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCAA1F5A9475749269275737708E9A240" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Public availability of certifications</header><text>The Commission shall provide for the public availability on the Commission’s Internet website or other electronic facility of all current certifications filed under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAF642CC371344C32BE1141A16F18CCE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effectiveness; duration</header> 
<paragraph id="H3334214480A14CFCBB64FFF10092387C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Effectiveness</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A national franchise under this section shall be effective with respect to any franchise area 30 days after the date of the filing of a completed certification under <internal-xref idref="H0A8D62F3EAF44E79B800C7EABE005411" legis-path="630.(a)(2)(A)">subsection (a)(2)(A)</internal-xref> or <internal-xref idref="H72A2034D3F02464E9B595E758E40217C" legis-path="630.(a)(2)(B)">(B)</internal-xref> that applies to such franchise area.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H589E68E1BF9744669CD71B481B6E00D4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duration</header> 
<subparagraph id="HDD298F7787224CAD9697E00049E00307"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A franchise under this section that applies to a franchise area shall be effective for that franchise area for a term of 10 years.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD25E40D5F3F6430D85F41EF29E5BA9F7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Renewal</header><text>A franchise under this section for a franchise area shall be renewed automatically upon expiration of the 10-year period described in <internal-xref idref="HDD298F7787224CAD9697E00049E00307" legis-path="630.(b)(2)(A)">subparagraph (A)</internal-xref>.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAF347EBD1D0044CB0089000166C54CE6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Public hearing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the request of a franchising authority in a franchise area, a cable operator authorized under this section to provide cable service in such franchise area shall, within the last year of the 10-year period applicable under <internal-xref idref="HDD298F7787224CAD9697E00049E00307" legis-path="630.(b)(2)(A)">subparagraph (A)</internal-xref> to the cable operator’s franchise for such franchise area, participate in a public hearing on the cable operator’s performance in the franchise area, including the cable operator’s compliance with the requirements of this title. The hearing shall afford the public the opportunity to participate for the purpose of identifying cable-related community needs and interests and assessing the operator’s performance. The cable operator shall provide notice to its subscribers of the hearing at least 30 days prior to the hearing. The Commission shall by rule specify the methods by which a franchising authority shall notify a cable operator of the hearing for which its participation is required under this subparagraph.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF2BE4795F0024EE7854B496E0571448E" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Revocation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A franchise under this section for a franchise area may be revoked by the Commission—</text> 
<clause id="H652DADB46F464DC8B16B8CE2F071072" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for willful or repeated violation of any Federal or State law, or any Commission regulation, relating to the provision of cable service in such franchise area;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0C2D073009D14D5D8C01F1EF57189E8D" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for false statements or material omissions knowingly made in any filing with the Commission relating to the provision of cable service in such franchise area;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5DE34BDACF1241C98613AC9D0441E745" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for willful or repeated violation of the rights-of-way management laws or regulations of any franchising authority in such franchise area relating to the provision of cable service in such franchise area; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8235842B92884B4BACCF2661CBE7CEE8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for willful or repeated violation of the antidiscrimination requirement of <internal-xref idref="HDB42AAE435E34D26005645CA3831B1E8" legis-path="630.(h)">subsection (h)</internal-xref> with respect to such franchise area.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB3B1A4F575EE4C7E9E2FAEB33CE5879B"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Notice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall send a notice of such revocation to each franchising authority with jurisdiction over the franchise areas for which the cable operator’s franchise was revoked.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2DDF6D4707D740F5A673EEA1131F57A0" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Reinstatement</header><text>After a revocation under <internal-xref idref="HF2BE4795F0024EE7854B496E0571448E" legis-path="630.(b)(2)(D)">subparagraph (D)</internal-xref> of a franchise for a franchise area of any person or group , the Commission may refuse to accept for filing a new certification for authority of such person or group to provide cable service under this section in such franchise area until the Commission determines that the basis of such revocation has been remedied.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0FD4B3D6B21541B59C489BBB27B9F2D5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Return to local franchising if cable competition ceases</header> 
<clause id="H9C118788737E496599949E4916835E19"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If only one cable operator is providing cable service in a franchise area, and that cable operator obtained a national franchise for such franchise area under <internal-xref idref="H3FE64DE69D8B48629B00B5B8F1280073" legis-path="630.(d)(2)">subsection (d)(2)</internal-xref>, the franchising authority for such franchise area may file a petition with the Commission requesting that the Commission terminate such national franchise for such franchise area. </text></clause> 
<clause id="H48CF7FEB112A4759881FC2CE0031D56E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Commission shall provide public notice and opportunity to comment on such petition. If it finds that the requirements of <internal-xref idref="H9C118788737E496599949E4916835E19" legis-path="630.(b)(2)(F)(i)">clause (i)</internal-xref> are satisfied, the Commission shall issue an order granting such petition. Such order shall take effect one year from the date of such grant, if no other cable operator offers cable service in such area during that one year. If another cable operator does offer cable service in such franchise area during that one year, the Commission shall rescind such order and dismiss such petition. </text></clause> 
<clause id="HD6C60C635BB04FDEAD7FB87CF6E3E695"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A cable operator whose national franchise is terminated for such franchise area under this subparagraph may obtain new authority to provide cable service in such franchise area under this section, section 621, or any other law, if and when eligible.</text></clause></subparagraph> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H18427321B42B460691DFF54D5E00D900"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements of national franchise</header><text>A national franchise shall contain the following requirements:</text> 
<paragraph id="HA1CCDE71585F45A7ACC606204FB8279E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Franchise fee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A cable operator authorized under this section to provide cable service in a franchise area shall pay to the franchising authority in such franchise area a franchise fee of up to 5 percent (as determined by the franchising authority) of such cable operator’s gross revenues from the provision of cable service under this section in such franchise area. Such payment shall be assessed and collected in a manner consistent with section 622 and the definitions of gross revenues and franchise fee in this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H87BDE7B41FE642D2000000F3375E9058"><enum>(2)</enum><header>PEG/I-NET requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A cable operator authorized under this section to provide cable service in a franchise area shall comply with the requirements of <internal-xref idref="H18517A528D8B4ACB83A8CE24BFE65DC7" legis-path="630.(e)">subsection (e).</internal-xref></text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCCD4C58694C244129B3004BD2C1E75AB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rights-of-way</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A cable operator authorized under this section to provide cable service in a franchise area shall comply with the rights-of-way requirements of the franchising authority under <internal-xref idref="HE85CCA3AFB164D7200878812F1A1D72B" legis-path="630.(f)">subsection (f)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H055FD11CF997455D8C14B8C4472FD3BA" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Consumer protection and customer service standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A cable operator authorized under this section to provide cable service in a franchise area shall comply with the consumer protection and customer service standards established by the Commission under section 632(b).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8E74FAE40814401BA969DAFEADF7FE7F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Child pornography</header><text>A cable operator authorized under this section to provide cable service in a franchise area shall comply with the regulations on child pornography promulgated pursuant to <internal-xref idref="HC61C7AC650B34AE0B115D1B23F9E93EA" legis-path="630.(i)">subsection (i)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDD9B56C7EECE4616BE1F88D2CC8FC59"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligibility for National Franchises</header><text>The following persons or groups are eligible to obtain a national franchise under this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H878C60B8969C48978436BBEB74104D5E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commencement of service after enactment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person or group that is not providing cable service in a franchise area on the date of enactment of this section under section 621 or any other law may obtain a national franchise under this section to provide cable service in such franchise area.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3FE64DE69D8B48629B00B5B8F1280073"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Existing providers of cable service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person or group that is providing cable service in a franchise area on the date of enactment of this section under section 621 or any other law may obtain a franchise under this section to provide cable service in such franchise area if, on the date that the national franchise becomes effective, another person or group is providing cable service under this section, section 621, or any other law in such franchise area.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H18517A528D8B4ACB83A8CE24BFE65DC7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Public, educational, and governmental use</header> 
<paragraph id="H2463F9F349E945898780CFA9DDAF59"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to <internal-xref idref="HCB99503126F04A7EAA24DB1E769B29D8" legis-path="630.(e)(3)">paragraph (3)</internal-xref>, a cable operator with a national franchise for a franchise area under this section shall provide channel capacity for public, educational, and governmental use that is not less than the channel capacity required of the cable operator with the most subscribers in such franchise area on the effective date of such national franchise. If there is no other cable operator in such franchise area on the effective date of such national franchise, or there is no other cable operator in such franchise area on such date that is required to provide channel capacity for public, educational, and governmental use, the cable operator shall provide the amount of channel capacity for such use as determined by Commission rule.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD9040494780F4617A83BE3123BC53340"><enum>(2)</enum><header>PEG and I–NET financial support</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A cable operator with a national franchise under this section for a franchise area shall pay an amount equal to 1 percent of the cable operator’s gross revenues (as such term is defined in this section) in the franchise area to the franchising authority for the support of public, educational, and governmental use and institutional networks (as such term is defined in section 611(f)). Such payment shall be assessed and collected in a manner consistent with section 622, including the authority of the cable operator to designate that portion of a subscriber’s bill attributable to such payment. A cable operator that provided cable service in a franchise area on the date of enactment of this section and that obtains a national franchise under this section shall continue to provide any institutional network that it was required to provide on the day before its national franchise became effective in such franchise area under section 621 or any other law. Notwithstanding section 621(b)(3)(D), a franchising authority may not require a cable operator franchised under this section to construct a new institutional network.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCB99503126F04A7EAA24DB1E769B29D8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Adjustment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Every 10 years after the commencement of a franchise under this section for a franchise area, a franchising authority may require a cable operator authorized under such franchise to increase the channel capacity designated for public, educational, or governmental use, and the channel capacity designated for such use on any institutional networks required under <internal-xref idref="HD9040494780F4617A83BE3123BC53340" legis-path="630.(e)(2)">paragraph (2)</internal-xref>. Such increase shall not exceed the higher of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF227EB99F7594DC69B0000E2C13FC78E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>one channel; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4163F7313B92444DBCF67C33FDC4B9EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>10 percent of the public, educational, or governmental channel capacity required of that operator prior to the increase.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H07FB2BCA856D4C0DAB9397EE41D1CFA1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Transmission and production of programming</header> 
<subparagraph id="HCE24970D9BD54E2986486C1313C57C9C"><enum>(A) </enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A cable operator franchised under this section shall ensure that any public, educational, or governmental programming carried by the cable operator under this section within a franchise area is available to all of its subscribers in such franchise area.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEE08E2BFA1FB448CB3977EFA01EDD31E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The production of any programming provided under this subsection shall be the responsibility of the franchising authority.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1305BD45EEFB4F10B5E7A9822B804400"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A cable operator franchised under this section shall be responsible for the transmission from the signal origination point (or points) of the programming, or from the point of interconnection with another cable operator under <internal-xref idref="HD25E9CC95B7647E39EAE2EFF303E10FB" legis-path="630.(e)(4)(D)">subparagraph (D)</internal-xref>, to the cable operator’s subscribers, of any public, educational, or governmental programming produced by or for the franchising authority and carried by the cable operator pursuant to this section.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD25E9CC95B7647E39EAE2EFF303E10FB"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Unless two cable operators otherwise agree to the terms for interconnection and cost sharing, such cable operators shall, if at least one of the operators is providing cable service in the franchise area pursuant to a franchise under this section, comply with regulations prescribed by the Commission providing for—</text> 
<clause id="HF66F0ACED5A043708DD6CACBDDE1739F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the interconnection between two cable operators in a franchise area for transmission of public, educational, or governmental programming, without material deterioration in signal quality or functionality; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5C6BC293DF1748E8BFBFF331D727A6CB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the reasonable allocation of the costs of such interconnection between such cable operators.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4AD2D9FB341B4C1C91C35B5FC8FCCC1E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A cable operator shall display the program information for public, educational, or governmental programming carried under this subsection in any print or electronic program guide in the same manner in which it displays program information for other video programming in the franchise area. The cable operator shall not omit such public, educational, or governmental programming from any navigational device, guide, or menu containing other video programming that is available to subscribers in the franchise area.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE85CCA3AFB164D7200878812F1A1D72B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rights-of-Way</header> 
<paragraph id="H99E54B891CB441FAB12D3E9E78DEC011"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority to use</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any franchise under this section for a franchise area shall be construed to authorize the construction of a cable system over public rights-of-way, and through easements, which is within the area to be served by the cable system and which have been dedicated for compatible uses, except that in using such easements the cable operator shall ensure that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA2049D03D5DB4E869F1800088354CC06"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the safety, functioning, and appearance of the property and the convenience and the safety of other persons not be adversely affected by the installation or construction of facilities necessary for a cable system;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD4CB65980E034DC68F1BF9588B2CE1BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the cost of the installation, construction, operation, or removal of such facilities be borne by the cable operator or subscriber, or a combination of both; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6D93D436FA884AA600A8ECE37614EE7F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the owner of the property be justly compensated by the cable operator for any damages caused by the installation, construction, operation, or removal of such facilities by the cable operator.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H70F8FF68F63C4C7A804E5CB6F251EF50" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Management of Public Rights-Of-Way</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section affects the authority of a State or local government (including a franchising authority) over a person or group in their capacity as a cable operator with a franchise under this section to manage, on a reasonable, competitively neutral, and non-discriminatory basis, the public rights-of-way, and easements that have been dedicated for compatible uses. A State or local government (including a franchising authority) may, on a reasonable, competitively neutral, and non-discriminatory basis—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFE4C49BF2A89485AA33F18755BC4EB9F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>impose charges for such management; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HABB4248DA768430A99F7D6D9C0099FCB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>require compliance with such management, such charges, and <internal-xref idref="HA2049D03D5DB4E869F1800088354CC06" legis-path="630.(f)(1)(A)">paragraphs (1)(A)</internal-xref>, <internal-xref idref="HD4CB65980E034DC68F1BF9588B2CE1BF" legis-path="630.(f)(1)(B)">(B)</internal-xref>, and <internal-xref idref="H6D93D436FA884AA600A8ECE37614EE7F" legis-path="630.(f)(1)(C)">(C)</internal-xref>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7E3256E565F44CE59CADA5F8E0147B2E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Consumer Protection and Customer Service</header> 
<paragraph id="H088618E8E1ED417CB08CD5234394B1B9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>National standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 632(d), no State or local law (including any regulation) shall impose on a cable operator franchised under this section any consumer protection or customer service requirements other than consumer protection or customer service requirements of general applicability.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H098D75CE6E14414C9CF7B4757BFE69EF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Proceeding</header><text>Within 120 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Commission shall issue a report and order that updates for cable operators franchised under this section the national consumer protection and customer service rules under section 632(b), taking into consideration the national nature of a franchise under this section and the role of State and local governments in enforcing, but not creating, consumer protection and customer service standards for cable operators franchised under this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H637C7869AD764F29AB9F3D96B377E5BD" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Requirements of new rules</header> 
<subparagraph id="HA9FFAABCA4C445EC95CB81FB52ACD6E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such rules shall, in addition to the requirements of section 632(b), address, with specificity, no less than the following consumer protection and customer service issues:</text> 
<clause id="HE8D2EF4BCAD2491981E368120081C179"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Billing, billing disputes, and discontinuation of service, including when and how any late fees may be assessed (but not the amount of such fees).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0E306CD734964A3E943997799085FCE1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Loss of service or service quality.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H3F457268ACCF4FC595EBE7F3BBB861CC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Changes in channel lineups or other cable services and features.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1C23E0F9E23040DEA28C2F9DD2DEDE24"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Availability of parental control options.</text></clause> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H060BD6076F074D449DAD3C395703313"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission’s revised consumer protection rules shall provide for forfeiture penalties, or customer rebates, refunds or credits, or both, and shall establish forfeiture, rebate, refund, and credit guidelines with respect to violations of such rules. Such guidelines shall—</text> 
<clause id="H8527C417893A45709C01F9413D8EB792"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide for increased forfeiture penalties for repeated violations of the standards in such rules; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA6A7FE13198540EDB4AF3BA3BFD9B21E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish procedures by which any forfeiture penalty assessed by the Commission under this subsection shall be paid by the cable operator directly to the franchising authority affected by the violation.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD659FEC6B5354DF787CF149C8DAF554C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Complaints</header> 
<subparagraph id="H555F5EE8751146CA93EE996F1500AD03"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any person may file a complaint with respect to an alleged violation of the Commission’s revised consumer protection rules in a franchise area by a cable operator franchised under this section—</text> 
<clause id="H46EFDFD2B6C44B1F90D3C317C6E7E3C5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with the franchising authority in such area; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBF4F57D043A941A69F00D85137E889AF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with the Commission.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H59B4ABC67BD244CCA28942C273E1A14E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Local franchising authority procedure</header><text>On its own motion or at the request of any person, a franchising authority for a franchise area may—</text> 
<clause id="H00DF95965C634B25A41CB7F45C0100C8"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">initiate its own complaint proceeding with respect to such an alleged violation; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF73527ABEB5D4A6D892F89B8F0FD3BE8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>file a complaint with the Commission regarding such an alleged violation.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB8D4FD19759D4040A9032BC523D3BDC3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>The Commission or the franchising authority conducting a proceeding under this paragraph shall render a decision on any complaint filed under this paragraph within 90 days of its filing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H734B030C9CCD43DAADF492FC529DC484" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Local franchising orders</header> 
<subparagraph id="HED7243FAB1904F30A7001EDB84F2165"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Requiring compliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In a proceeding commenced by a franchising authority, a franchising authority may issue an order requiring compliance with the Commission’s revised consumer protection rules, but a franchising authority may not create any new standard or regulation, or expand upon or modify the Commission’s revised consumer protection rules.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0B9BBF39ED9141508FEB747FC92D8E6B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Access to records</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In such a proceeding, the franchising authority may issue an order requiring the filing of any data, documents, or records (including any contract, agreement, or arrangement between the subscriber and the cable operator) that are directly related to the alleged violation.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF71D7B02210F4C798B62820064B7A470"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Cost of franchising authority orders</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A franchising authority may charge a cable operator franchised under this section a nominal fee to cover the costs of issuing orders under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA905F7BCC5214F749DD5E600C6A39EB4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Commission remedies; appeals</header> 
<subparagraph id="H6508DEC959DB4F7C8679791731FB98E8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Remedies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An order of a franchising authority under this subsection shall be enforced by the Commission under this Act if—</text> 
<clause id="H5478D3A9AAC8450B8B37CF6816341611"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the order is not appealed to the Commission;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H39B95EF9F5904F028C698B6100E328B1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Commission does not agree to grant review during the 30-day period described in <internal-xref idref="H8FF36D4B66CF44B3B30574ADD9F325E" legis-path="(6)(B)">subparagraph (B)</internal-xref>; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB7C11CC6EEFA430389F62F5FD6A766FD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the order is sustained on appeal by the Commission.</text> </clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H832CBA11738B4906B5006B64CC49009E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Appeals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any party may file a notice of appeal of an order of a franchising authority under this subsection with the Commission, and shall transmit a copy of such notice to the other parties to the franchising authority proceeding. Such appeal shall be deemed denied at the end of the 30-day period beginning on the date of the filing unless the Commission agrees within such period to grant review of the appeal.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1DA7E3BB17B945E180E77DD4DAFECA9"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After the filing of a notice of appeal under subparagraph (B), if such notice is not denied by operation of such subparagraph, the Commission shall render a decision within 90 days of such filing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFCF64D3247F447ABB3FB46FC00E4749C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Annual report</header> 
<subparagraph id="H3D39A3C41F7A45C9ACFA00B5972D73DD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the Commission shall submit a report to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate on the implementation of this subsection, including the following:</text> 
<clause id="HCE968D65794044ED974D68D3F7ECB6C2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The number of complaints filed with franchising authorities under <internal-xref idref="H8FF36D4B66CF44B3B30574ADD9F325E" legis-path="(4)(A)(i)">clause (4)(A)(i)</internal-xref>.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD32A69AF3E7947489397DA24BAAAB2F0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Any trends concerning complaints, such as increases in the number of particular types of complaints or in new types of complaints.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6B979649CE0E4183A46FA4421747E490"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The timeliness of the response of such franchising authorities and the results of the complaints filed with such franchising authorities, if not appealed to the Commission.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF97C687DC31D43168226B0B9F9897098"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The number of complaints filed with the Commission under <internal-xref idref="H8FF36D4B66CF44B3B30574ADD9F325E" legis-path="(4)(A)(ii)">clause (4)(A)(ii)</internal-xref>.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDF142A27948E42008BEB297B8CEE90D"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of appeals filed with the Commission under <internal-xref idref="H8FF36D4B66CF44B3B30574ADD9F325E" legis-path="(6)(B)">paragraph (6)(B)</internal-xref> and the number of such appeals which the Commission agreed to hear.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC69BBEDBBA3B425CB77D65DFCAEFE459"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>The timeliness of the Commission’s responses to such complaints and appeals.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HEC025A165B8F406E9B8F7C997467D38B"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>The results of such complaints and appeals filed with the Commission.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2EDE8EF59FC64054B2A100CFFCAAB5F9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Submission of information by franchising authorities</header><text>The Commission may request franchising authorities to submit information about the complaints filed with the franchising authorities under <internal-xref idref="H8FF36D4B66CF44B3B30574ADD9F325E" legis-path="(4)(A)(i)">subparagraph (4)(A)(i)</internal-xref>, including the number of such complaints and the timeliness of the response and the results of such complaints.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA58B12CF420247D29C86B2AE09EE080" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>Commission’s revised consumer protection rules</term> means the national consumer protection and customer service rules under section 632(b) as revised by the Commission pursuant to paragraph (2) of this subsection.</text></paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HDB42AAE435E34D26005645CA3831B1E8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Antidiscrimination</header> 
<paragraph id="H79D12FE1528F4021A5AFB3B9A3021346"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A cable operator with a national franchise under this section to provide cable service in a franchise area shall not deny access to its cable service to any group of potential residential cable service subscribers in such franchise area because of the income of that group.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD24347C1E5C048838B1CDD0206C47BD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Enforcement</header> 
<subparagraph id="HAE733199108846B6A7D4C1CA529C47C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Complaint</header><text>If a franchising authority in a franchise area has reasonable cause to believe that a cable operator is in violation of this subsection with respect to such franchise area, the franchising authority may, after complying with subparagraph (B), file a complaint with the Commission alleging such violation.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H784590CB45184067ABFBA691DD45A13"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notice by franchising authority</header><text>Before filing a complaint with the Commission under <internal-xref idref="HAE733199108846B6A7D4C1CA529C47C" legis-path="630.(h)(2)(A)">subparagraph (A)</internal-xref>, a franchising authority—</text> 
<clause id="H41559812307F41AFAAFE03E653F47332"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall give notice of each alleged violation to the cable operator;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE217F1E583B94A7B85F82ED03857A15C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall provide a period of not less than 30 days for the cable operator to respond to such allegations; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC23244C0C8E34D87A0B04E0034520900"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>during such period, may require the cable operator to submit a written response stating the reasons why the operator has not violated this subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H57E98637EF964757A9389E04C6021503"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Biannual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A cable operator with a national franchise under this section for a franchise area, not later than 180 days after the effective date of such national franchise, and biannually thereafter, shall submit a report to the Commission and the franchising authority in the franchise area—</text> 
<clause id="H1917D879C29349DBBE384286AA993300"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identifying the geographic areas in the franchise area where the cable operator offers cable service; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFE218066C51B4FFDB2AD9900E2E6658B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>describing the cable operator’s progress in extending cable service to other areas in the franchise area.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H91DA4E0FFBEA4C36BE941BDEA88C0079"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Notice by Commission</header><text>Upon receipt of a complaint under this paragraph alleging a violation of this subsection by a cable operator, the Commission shall give notice of the complaint to the cable operator.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H68A61E5843DF468AB6BD005FCBAAC0DA"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Investigation</header><text>In investigating a complaint under this paragraph, the Commission may require a cable operator to disclose to the Commission such information and documents as the Commission deems necessary to determine whether the cable operator is in compliance with this subsection. The Commission shall maintain the confidentiality of any information or document collected under this subparagraph.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H32F54516D27C47C7B94840E054FDE200"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Deadline for resolution of complaints</header><text>Not more than 60 days after the Commission receives a complaint under this paragraph, the Commission shall issue a determination with respect to each violation alleged in the complaint.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1F4D998F2A244D42A9A9C227D3A1A100"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Commission determines (in response to a complaint under this paragraph or on its own initiative) that a cable operator with a franchise under this section to provide cable service in a franchise area has denied access to its cable service to a group of potential residential cable service subscribers in such franchise area because of the income of that group, the Commission shall ensure that the cable operator extends access to that group within a reasonable period of time.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6BCA2A59FBA344149BAFCEDD417D5F51"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Remedies</header> 
<clause id="H227C591C29FD404A9BA5426016F90612"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>This subsection shall be enforced by the Commission under titles IV and V.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB2EC8145552849149E6F56D24051C61"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Maximum forfeiture penalty</header><text>For purposes of section 503, the maximum forfeiture penalty applicable to a violation of this subsection shall be $750,000 for each day of the violation.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H76E2328E348244B68F4C48B4B8D6C5B9"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Payment of penalties to franchising authority</header><text>The Commission shall order any cable operator subject to a forfeiture penalty under this subsection to pay the penalty directly to the franchising authority involved.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC61C7AC650B34AE0B115D1B23F9E93EA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Child pornography</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Commission shall promulgate regulations to require a cable operator with a national franchise under this section to prevent the distribution of child pornography (as such term is defined in section 254(h)(7)(F)) over its network.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H070A3BB7ABE2452A98005C69CBD0C738" commented="no"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Leased access</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provisions of section 612(i) regarding the carriage of programming from a qualified minority programming source or from any qualified educational programming source shall apply to a cable operator franchised under this section to provide cable service in a franchise area. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA9D918D22FB34CF7A6DC5FAAF39FD6F"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Applicability of Other Provisions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provisions of this title that apply to a cable operator shall apply in a franchise area to a person or group with a national franchise under this section to provide cable service in such franchise area, except that the following sections shall not apply in a franchise area to a person or group franchised under this section in such franchise area, or confer any authority to regulate or impose obligations on such person or group in such franchise area: Sections 611(a), 611(b), 611(c), 613(a), 617, 621 (other than subsections (b)(3)(A), (b)(3)(B), (b)(3)(C), and (c)), 624(b), 624(c), 624(h), 625, 626, 627, and 632(a).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H67A78D8144B94BE1B9ED8B05E6D690BB"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Emergency alerts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit a State or local government from accessing the emergency alert system of a cable operator with a franchise under this section in the area served by the State or local government to transmit local or regional emergency alerts.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5BAE45E1352A4CE6A7F1C546CAD82F9C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Reporting, records, and audits</header> 
<paragraph id="H16D345EDDCEE4C1ABDD8F8D981E9C4EF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>A cable operator with a franchise under this section to provide cable service in a franchise area shall make such periodic reports to the Commission and the franchising authority for such franchise area as the Commission may require to verify compliance with the fee obligations of <internal-xref idref="HA1CCDE71585F45A7ACC606204FB8279E" legis-path="630.(c)(1)">subsections (c)(1)</internal-xref> and <internal-xref idref="HD9040494780F4617A83BE3123BC53340" legis-path="630.(e)(2)">(e)(2)</internal-xref>. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H19BDCDCE8BEF43C98171F71E447D33B6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability of books and records</header><text>Upon request under <internal-xref idref="HCA4238C695E94705979C5566D4CA9B04" legis-path="630.(m)(3)">paragraph (3)</internal-xref> by a franchising authority for a franchise area, and upon request by the Commission, a cable operator with a national franchise for such franchise area shall make available its books and records to periodic audit by such franchising authority or the Commission, respectively. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCA4238C695E94705979C5566D4CA9B04"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Franchising authority audit procedure</header><text>A franchising authority may, upon reasonable written request, but no more than once in any 12-month period, review the business records of such cable operator to the extent reasonably necessary to ensure payment of the fees required by <internal-xref idref="HA1CCDE71585F45A7ACC606204FB8279E" legis-path="630.(c)(1)">subsections (c)(1)</internal-xref> and <internal-xref idref="HD9040494780F4617A83BE3123BC53340" legis-path="630.(e)(2)">(e)(2)</internal-xref>. Such review may include the methodology used by such cable operator to assign portions of the revenue from cable service that may be bundled or functionally integrated with other services, capabilities, or applications. Such review shall be conducted in accordance with procedures established by the Commission. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2B1B51A5B2A7445BAC19F5F78E00EB2B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Cost recovery</header> 
<subparagraph id="H976C784ED98B4766928C4BF3B22CC4BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent that the review under <internal-xref idref="HCA4238C695E94705979C5566D4CA9B04" legis-path="630.(m)(3)">paragraph (3)</internal-xref> identifies an underpayment of an amount meeting the minimum percentage specified in <internal-xref idref="HB5DFE6DEC9B145AB9C9F84E6BEEC97B6" legis-path="630.(m)(4)(B)">subparagraph (B)</internal-xref> of the fee required under <internal-xref idref="HA1CCDE71585F45A7ACC606204FB8279E" legis-path="630.(c)(1)">subsection (c)(1)</internal-xref> or <internal-xref idref="HD9040494780F4617A83BE3123BC53340" legis-path="630.(e)(2)">(e)(2)</internal-xref> for the period of review, the cable operator shall reimburse the franchising authority the reasonable costs of any such review conducted by an independent third party, as determined by the Commission, with respect to such fee. The costs of any contingency fee arrangement between the franchising authority and the independent reviewer shall not be subject to reimbursement.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB5DFE6DEC9B145AB9C9F84E6BEEC97B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Commission shall determine by rule the minimum percentage underpayment that requires cost reimbursement under <internal-xref idref="H976C784ED98B4766928C4BF3B22CC4BB" legis-path="630.(m)(4)(A)">subparagraph (A)</internal-xref>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H14366324F2EA43FCAFBFD1BF747DBA7E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Any fee that is not reviewed by a franchising authority within 3 years after it is paid or remitted shall not be subject to later review by the franchising authority under this subsection and shall be deemed accepted in full payment by the franchising authority.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H637308434E854653A0FFA0923CB9D282"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Fee Dispute Resolution</header> 
<subparagraph id="H699B0100DEC343C481BA00C5F57D20F1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Complaint</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A franchising authority or a cable operator may file a complaint at the Commission to resolve a dispute between such authority and operator with respect to the amount of any fee required under subsection (c)(1) or (e)(2) if—</text> 
<clause id="H30DF6A44C825422E91B84B5B33FC63A1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the franchising authority or the cable operator provides the other entity written notice of such dispute; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7B6AE63171FC4D19B9B25168FDF53750"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the franchising authority and the cable operator have not resolved the dispute within 90 calendar days after receipt of such notice.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H904410977B2943B4A6599770E99B292C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>Within 30 calendar days after receipt of notice of a dispute provided pursuant to subparagraph (A)(i), representatives of the franchising authority and the cable operator, with authority to resolve the dispute, shall meet to attempt to resolve the dispute.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H051A5459E7D84CAB843827D9D2E3DAB9"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>A complaint under subparagraph (A) shall be filed not later than 3 years after the end of the period to which the disputed amount relates, unless such time is extended by written agreement between the franchising authority and cable operator.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1652B82D75394CA7969E4DE3D1923509"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Resolution</header><text>The Commission shall issue an order resolving any complaint filed under subparagraph (A) within 90 days of filing.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC775318D76C74795A4B730C8AC41AD9B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Access to Programming for Shared Facilities</header> 
<paragraph id="HDF970851A6A740159B1BAC09926649D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>A cable programming vendor in which a cable operator has an attributable interest shall not deny a cable operator with a national franchise under this section access to video programming solely because such cable operator with a national franchise uses a headend for its cable system that is also used, under a shared ownership or leasing agreement, as the headend for another cable system.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE5DAF2D1B2234B279BF74D2C838BFCF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>cable programming vendor</quote> means a person engaged in the production, creation, or wholesale distribution for sale of video programming which is primarily intended for the direct receipt by cable operators for their retransmission to cable subscribers.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4A4DE9F322C149F08E2D6D1CDB9F0215"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Gross revenues</header><text>As used in this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H37D0D85ADF0642D4A9D1AD99C3EA0056"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to <internal-xref idref="HE0AFA2AF1D26456884FBA7A8AC82D8D5" legis-path="630.(o)(2)">paragraphs (2)</internal-xref> and <internal-xref idref="HCFEE432C4DF0449A9200FE5000EAD9B5" legis-path="630.(o)(3)">(3)</internal-xref>, the term <term>gross revenues</term> means all consideration of any kind or nature, including cash, credits, property, and in-kind contributions (services or goods) received by the cable operator from the provision of cable service within the franchise area.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE0AFA2AF1D26456884FBA7A8AC82D8D5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Included items</header><text>Subject to <internal-xref idref="HCFEE432C4DF0449A9200FE5000EAD9B5" legis-path="630.(o)(3)">paragraph (3)</internal-xref>, the term <term>gross revenues</term> shall include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEE9F6AFD76C24E94B4D8E5B2BB91852F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>all charges and fees paid by subscribers for the provision of cable service, including fees attributable to cable service when sold individually or as part of a package or bundle, or functionally integrated, with services other than cable service;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5404884A84964F128FDF8586EBBC8BBD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any franchise fee imposed on the cable operator that is passed on to subscribers; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFB7F5B0523A54F9E983475633B5CFC6"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">compensation received by the cable operator for promotion or exhibition of any products or services over the cable service, such as on <quote>home shopping</quote> or similar programming; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCA34C963DBC64A02A965471E2C053D7D"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">revenue received by the cable operator as compensation for carriage of video programming or other programming service on that operator’s cable service;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCAC3B159BE964A4AB016E88D44D34D1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>all revenue derived from the cable operator’s cable service pursuant to compensation arrangements for advertising; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H809D2AF00A2B40B1801912D797EF0858"><enum>(F)</enum><text>any advertising commissions paid to an affiliated third party for cable services advertising.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCFEE432C4DF0449A9200FE5000EAD9B5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Excluded items</header><text>The term <term>gross revenues</term> shall not include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD28172F59BF942F9B3B35E0732D99C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any revenue not actually received, even if billed, such as bad debt net of any recoveries of bad debt; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9595936A543B49C28CA28B4E656027C4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>refunds, rebates, credits, or discounts to subscribers or a municipality to the extent not already offset by <internal-xref idref="HD28172F59BF942F9B3B35E0732D99C2" legis-path="630.(o)(3)(A)">subparagraph (A)</internal-xref> and to the extent such refund, rebate, credit, or discount is attributable to the cable service;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6FA8E55B77D64FFAB26CF99CFB9BF236"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subject to <internal-xref idref="HF9E9D3888D4840E583485FDDC6A4C051" legis-path="630.(o)(4)">paragraph (4)</internal-xref>, any revenues received by the cable operator or its affiliates from the provision of services or capabilities other than cable service, including telecommunications services, Internet access services, and services, capabilities, and applications that may be sold as part of a package or bundle, or functionally integrated, with cable service; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFA867F89CDE3497184EF5BB5AD064F88"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any revenues received by the cable operator or its affiliates for the provision of directory or Internet advertising, including yellow pages, white pages, banner advertisement, and electronic publishing;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7A949863C8BD4AABBCA992DD11685F00"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any amounts attributable to the provision of cable service to customers at no charge, including the provision of such service to public institutions without charge;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H83AEBD75371F4C3A8B0076D197BBF8F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any tax, fee, or assessment of general applicability imposed on the customer or the transaction by a Federal, State, or local government or any other governmental entity, collected by the provider, and required to be remitted to the taxing entity, including sales and use taxes and utility user taxes;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE649ACE0B1D24BD781818BF1995C9D8C"><enum>(G)</enum><text>any forgone revenue from the provision of cable service at no charge to any person, except that any forgone revenue exchanged for trades, barters, services, or other items of value shall be included in gross revenue; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB2918E86569C47DCBEE8C60C5933407"><enum>(H)</enum><text>sales of capital assets or surplus equipment;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1CD5063ADE7F49C2B4486F8CF6E761E1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>reimbursement by programmers of marketing costs actually incurred by the cable operator for the introduction of new programming; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H57280838E58449D58133815C1FA1CD74"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the sale of cable services for resale to the extent the purchaser certifies in writing that it will resell the service and pay a franchise fee with respect thereto.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF9E9D3888D4840E583485FDDC6A4C051"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Functionally integrated services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a cable service that is bundled or integrated functionally with other services, capabilities, or applications, the portion of the cable operator’s revenue attributable to such other services, capabilities, or applications shall be included in gross revenue unless the cable operator can reasonably identify the division or exclusion of such revenue from its books and records that are kept in the regular course of business.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8FEC7DAB310C4414AE42B90090A5AD4F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Affiliate revenue</header><text>Revenue of an affiliate shall be included in the calculation of gross revenues to the extent the treatment of such revenue as revenue of the affiliate has the effect (whether intentional or unintentional) of evading the payment of franchise fees which would otherwise be paid for cable service.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H518C510585114B29AF7D8B52288FCAFE"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Affect on other law</header><text>Nothing in this section is intended to limit a franchising authority’s rights pursuant to section 622(h).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1188FC00958047EB8776EE936E1EB9FB" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Additional Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H6872C10BD9254FD8AF1DC18FBFE39EBD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Cable operator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>cable operator</quote> has the meaning provided in section 602(5) except that such term also includes a person or group with a national franchise under this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5BAA6A330B4B446D93CA598217E22C2C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Franchise fee</header> 
<subparagraph id="H32C17CA5302247E6A493D4C1E6EA85A9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>franchise fee</quote> includes any fee or assessment of any kind imposed by a franchising authority or other governmental entity on a person or group providing cable service in a franchise area under this section, or on a subscriber of such person or group, or both, solely because of their status as such. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H902B1DBF08E3446FBC548DA82D031C6B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <quote>franchise fee</quote> does not include—</text> 
<clause id="HC0233B36AF494439BE08BB5DF665554C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any tax, fee, or assessment of general applicability (including any such tax, fee, or assessment imposed on both utilities and a person or group providing cable service in a franchise area under this section (or the services of such person or group) but not including a fee or assessment which is unduly discriminatory against such person or group or the subscribers of such person or group); </text></clause> 
<clause id="H7E94332EDE6346B2B8DE6E23D8FDE47"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any fee assessed under subsection (e)(2) for support of public, educational, and governmental use and institutional networks (as such term is defined in section 611(f)); </text></clause> 
<clause id="H46DF096230314B2284662CB8E3D83035"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>requirements or charges under subsection (f)(2) for the management of public rights-of-way, including payments for bonds, security funds, letters of credit, insurance, indemnification, penalties, or liquidated damages; or </text></clause> 
<clause id="H08E4EABF3B5D49C38C211E172CD5A97"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any fee imposed under title 17, United States Code.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8199E70187BC4BB6AF3BB01F88ED86B8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Internet access service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Internet access service</quote> means a service that enables users to access content, information, electronic mail, or other services offered over the Internet.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF12E18805F1C43D680E582A75F82CF51"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Unit of general local government</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>unit of general local government</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8C28BB8B9121470D91AAE76C33A2D183"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a county, township, city, or political subdivision of a county, township, or city;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H92DE7A0F231C4B9AB3B35D8BC450F663"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the District of Columbia; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBA00E0CDEE4C4968A64F773B51D1C41"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the recognized governing body of an Indian tribe or Alaskan Native village that carries out substantial governmental duties and powers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H533704E2872048B0804EE57BE5E0234B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementing Regulations</header><text>The Federal Communications Commission shall prescribe regulations to implement the amendment made by <internal-xref idref="H6FD4D64995884FDDAD108E6D4E434716" legis-path="101.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> within 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H876BE958C3A84F00A7F0648E916F05FF" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>102.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Section 602 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/522">47 U.S.C. 522</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC8C01D103ADF4425AA00ADA855C9E800"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by inserting before the semicolon at the end the following: <quote>, or its equivalent as determined by the Commission</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H501E6CEF2F9C47D2887096390400F3F4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)(A), by inserting <quote>(regardless of whether such person or group provides such service separately or combined with a telecommunications service or information service)</quote> after <quote>over a cable system</quote>; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H093F926309A74B3FA976D467B227A3D0"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking paragraph (6) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5856ECA60A5B425A84564117057BC784" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H27EECC8ACE224C648B3CAC54A5A6A04C"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>cable service</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF3821498CC7444A09DC92739D7F67887"><enum>(A)</enum> 
<clause id="H6756B3FBE2DB400993FC7641EFDAEAD" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the one-way transmission to subscribers of (I) video programming, or (II) other programming service; and </text></clause> 
<clause id="H92EFE24356E54EB4B14C482C80AD6BF1" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>subscriber interaction, if any, which is required for the selection or use of such video programming or other programming service; or </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB2D4DC28B3C9412900B5E5EF9C390000" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the transmission to subscribers of video programming or other programming service provided through wireline facilities located at least in part in the public rights-of-way, without regard to delivery technology, including Internet protocol technology, except to the extent that such video programming or other programming service is provided as part of—</text> 
<clause id="HD54AF36DA8174A12835EB48500D91B2E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a commercial mobile service (as such term is defined in section 332(d)); or </text></clause> 
<clause id="H7C4ACCE371724F628BFF556BB338C82"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an Internet access service (as such term is defined in section 630(p));</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H61DFE1F536704A228F4EEF129507C18B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in paragraph (7)(D), by inserting after <quote>section 653 of this title</quote> the following; <quote>except in a franchise area in which such system is used to provide cable service under a national franchise pursuant to section 630</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H82FA1850B5814F2F9FCE8D3FACCA59B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in paragraph (9)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCA8BC99F9DA642F0826583B4D4E44900"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(A)</quote> after <quote>means</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4D4BAE1FA80B499B915DC448B9C003E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting before the semicolon at the end the following: <quote>; and (B) a national franchise that is effective under section 630 on the basis of a certification with the Commission</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBFB61C8153E6429F0010187D28A15F6E"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (10), by inserting before the semicolon at the end the following: <quote>, but does not include the Commission with respect to a national franchise under section 630</quote>. </text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HF61C8A96B3AE441F8914475386A8C800" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>103.</enum><header>Monitoring and reporting</header> 
<subsection id="H83EC7A1C4B7E4241BDBCB9D69DA78D6F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report on cable service deployment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Communications Commission shall, commencing not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, issue a report annually on the deployment of cable service pursuant to the amendments made by this title. In its report, the Commission shall describe in detail—</text> 
<paragraph id="H8182377A9BBF47C28C77DEC2F02B8B4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with respect to deployment by new cable operators—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB7986543E8B541EC89D9C047AAC778DF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the progress of deployment of such service within the telephone service area of cable operators, if the operator is also an incumbent local exchange carrier, including a comparison with the progress of deployment of broadband services not defined as cable services within such telephone service area;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDC7013D926D64D00B726756944265C7C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of franchise areas in which such service is being deployed and offered;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCDF1444242CE44DC005F42D399AE2877"><enum>(C)</enum><text>where such service is not being deployed and offered; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA57B16B5622C437FB724CD9B34669C26"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number and locations of franchise areas in which the cable operator is serving only a portion of the franchise area, and the extent of such service within the franchise area;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB708251BE0C046B7885F3C643D563601"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number and locations of franchise areas in which a cable operator with a franchise under section 621 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/541">47 U.S.C. 541</external-xref>) on the date of enactment of this Act withdraws service from any portion of the franchise area for which it previously offered service, and the extent of such withdrawal of service within the franchise area;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2C175378B7334059B5DF6F52DF39FAF8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the rates generally charged for cable service;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5D3A805889FC4592956FFED330193E6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the rates charged by overlapping, competing multichannel video programming distributors and by competing cable operators for comparable service or cable service;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H91B2F2E38F284F9985ED190547FC5D7B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the average household income of those franchise areas or portions of franchise areas where cable services is being offered, and the average household income of those franchise areas, or portions of franchise areas, where cable service is not being offered; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H838C8A2F7DB1439C92D425C65FE5C002" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the proportion of rural households to urban households, as defined by the Bureau of the Census, in those franchise areas or portions of franchise areas where cable service is being offered, and the proportion of rural households to urban households in those franchise areas or portions of franchise areas where cable service is not being offered, including a State-by-State breakdown of such data and a comparison with the overall ratio of rural and urban households in each State; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC2D6E81D14E146C7BA178ED8F1179FE9"><enum>(7)</enum><text>a comparison of the services and rates in areas served by national franchisees under section 630 of the Communications Act of 1934 (as added by section 101 of this Act) and the services and rates in other areas. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8A3BD977E89545F3956560DE4602EE1F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Cable operator reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Communications Commission is authorized—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCBDA2B7735494788AD4825D783860641"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to require cable operators to report to the Commission all of the information that the Commission needs to compile the report required by this section; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE7E67D1E9A0C4E9AA85690AD7C1700E5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to require cable operators to file the same information with the relevant franchising authorities and State commissions. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HD14A756F7DCD467BA9032F8F006B1911" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>104.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act or the amendments made by this Act shall affect the application or interpretation of section 224 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/224">47 U.S.C. 224</external-xref>).</text></section></title> 
<title id="HBD0F393A30334272B034FA87D4994170"><enum>II</enum><header>Enforcement of Broadband Policy Statement</header> 
<section id="HD7EADDF1898840E0AEF469B474F551D" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>201.</enum><header>Enforcement of broadband policy statement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title VII of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/601">47 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H0FE61BE5AD7C44B991D9C8B4A111E8A8"> 
<section id="H55F34BF80F784F65BF7E6FF5286F3825"><enum>715.</enum><header>Enforcement of broadband policy statement</header> 
<subsection id="H3091354F9DD6434BAC1E724C7974E1E3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>The Commission shall have the authority to enforce the Commission’s broadband policy statement and the principles incorporated therein.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H790CA2FAB0764BBB87056D6B43EFA279" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Enforcement</header> 
<paragraph id="H7438340B862A4661937B90596468646C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section shall be enforced by the Commission under titles IV and V. A violation of the Commission’s broadband policy statement or the principles incorporated therein shall be treated as a violation of this Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3FF1D243649B4FB786E76EC91700CB40" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maximum forfeiture penalty</header><text>For purposes of section 503, the maximum forfeiture penalty applicable to a violation described in <internal-xref idref="H7438340B862A4661937B90596468646C" legis-path="715.(b)(1)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref> of this subsection shall be $500,000 for each violation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFFB272EF60A646AE93F6FD72868D6325"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Adjudicatory Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall have exclusive authority to adjudicate any complaint alleging a violation of the broadband policy statement and the principles incorporated therein. The Commission shall complete an adjudicatory proceeding under this subsection not later than 90 days after receipt of the complaint. If, upon completion of an adjudicatory proceeding pursuant to this section, the Commission determines that such a violation has occurred, the Commission shall have authority to adopt an order to require the entity subject to the complaint to comply with the broadband policy statement and the principles incorporated therein. Such authority shall be in addition to the authority specified in <internal-xref idref="H7438340B862A4661937B90596468646C" legis-path="715.(b)(1)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref> to enforce this section under titles IV and V. In addition, the Commission shall have authority to adopt procedures for the adjudication of complaints alleging a violation of the broadband policy statement or principles incorporated therein.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD0CCAF9446FC475F9220304BF263B862"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding <internal-xref idref="H7438340B862A4661937B90596468646C" legis-path="715.(b)(1)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref>, the Commission's authority to enforce the broadband policy statement and the principles incorporated therein does not include authorization for the Commission to adopt or implement rules or regulations regarding enforcement of the broadband policy statement and the principles incorporated therein, with the sole exception of the authority to adopt procedures for the adjudication of complaints, as provided in <internal-xref idref="HFFB272EF60A646AE93F6FD72868D6325" legis-path="715.(b)(3)">paragraph (3)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H38DF20249BB44A00A6EE85DAE176FA3E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Commission shall conduct, and submit to the House Committee on Energy and Commerce and the Senate Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation, a study regarding whether the objectives of the broadband policy statement and the principles incorporated therein are being achieved.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HA8C9CE95CF734EDA0099F6F5B3E7FD3" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum>
<paragraph id="HDB4AD4F0F4694F8198A55F8BEB01BA00" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to modify, impair, or supersede the applicability of the antitrust laws or the jurisdiction of the district courts of the United States to hear claims arising under the antitrust laws. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBB7CAD6928914D43B086338ED24DE182" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition of antitrust laws</header><text>The term <quote>antitrust laws</quote> has the meaning given it in subsection (a) of the first section of the Clayton Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/12">15 U.S.C. 12(a)</external-xref>), except that such term includes section 5 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45</external-xref>) to the extent that such section 5 applies to unfair methods of competition.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDB1EFA575C904AC200AACDFCBEB72B7F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>Commission’s broadband policy statement</term> means the policy statement adopted on August 5, 2005, and issued on September 23, 2005, In the Matters of Appropriate Framework for Broadband Access to the Internet over Wireline Facilities, and other Matters (FCC 05–151; CC Docket No. 02–33; CC Docket No. 01–337; CC Docket Nos. 95–20, 98–10; GN Docket No. 00–185; CS Docket No. 02–52).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></title> 
<title id="H006B6DE983BF4EBD82D95BC601D34F22"><enum>III</enum><header>VOIP/911</header> 
<section id="H1B63BCEEFC174EED9E789499D2B13C7F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>301.</enum><header>Emergency services; interconnection</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title VII of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/601">47 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>) is further amended by adding after section 715 (as added by section 201 of this Act) the following new sections:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HB4FA1F2237F043B1851B282874EF297F"> 
<section id="HFB2543E6EEFB46839950FF29C8FB3B3" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>716.</enum><header>Emergency services</header> 
<subsection id="H5BD8A68B0F3D4502885E366B7B7DE5E8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>911 and E–911 services</header> 
<paragraph id="HAA5DE63E1DCB4478B0A912BCDE93C7AA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each VOIP service provider has a duty to ensure that 911 and E-911 services are provided to subscribers of VOIP services.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H361FB86C6DE242E289967FA1A02EFF13" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of existing regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A VOIP service provider that complies with the Commission’s regulations requiring providers of VOIP service to supply 911 and E911 capabilities to their customers (Report and Order in WC Docket Nos. 04-36 and 05-196) and that are in effect on the date of enactment of this section shall be considered to be in compliance with the requirements of this section, other than <internal-xref idref="H5369011E130F48FEAA4CEB48F4F1B920" legis-path="716.(c)">subsection (c)</internal-xref>, until such regulations are modified or superseded by subsequent regulations.</text></paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HD03E8796F78642480002BF38701B9E6D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Non-discriminatory access to capabilities</header> 
<paragraph id="HEB7288A4AE80438D9B3135987ECBA2A2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Access</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each incumbent local exchange carrier (as such term is defined in section 251(h)) or government entity with ownership or control of the necessary E–911 infrastructure shall provide any requesting VOIP service provider with nondiscriminatory access to such infrastructure. Such carrier or entity shall provide access to the infrastructure at just and reasonable, nondiscriminatory rates, terms, and conditions. Such access shall be consistent with industry standards established by the National Emergency Number Association or other applicable industry standards organizations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8BDF7967A26F4869B6F6A2158B76E598"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission or a State commission may enforce the requirements of this subsection and the Commission’s regulations thereunder. A VOIP service provider may obtain access to such infrastructure pursuant to section 717 by asserting the rights described in such section.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5369011E130F48FEAA4CEB48F4F1B920" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>New customers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A VOIP service provider shall make 911 service available to new customers within a reasonable time in accordance with the following requirements:</text> 
<paragraph id="H78E818A2C9DB4607976FA8785BF19FC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Connection to selective router</header><text>For all new customers not within the geographic areas where a VOIP service provider can immediately provide 911 service to the geographically appropriate PSAP, a VOIP service provider, or its third party vendor, shall have no more than 30 days from the date the VOIP provider has acquired a customer to order service providing connectivity to the selective router so that 911 service, or E911 service where the PSAP is capable of receiving and processing such information, can be provided through the selective router. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H761CB4A57C9B496DA94D5CBB057565E6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Interim service</header><text>For all new customers not within the geographic areas where the VOIP service provider can immediately provide 911 service to the geographically appropriate PSAP, a VOIP service provider shall provide 911 service through—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB60148FE337F478FB48FCDAE179400D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an arrangement mutually agreed to by the VOIP service provider and the PSAP or PSAP governing authority; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAD2134AC4B9A4B3B932D1139715C55D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an emergency response center with national call routing capabilities. </text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">Such service shall be provided 24 hours a day from the date a VOIP service provider has acquired a customer until the VOIP service provider can provide 911 service to the geographically appropriate PSAP.</continuation-text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD9D568F54D4E44D785DFA94BD43CB0B0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>Before providing service to any new customer not within the geographic areas where the VOIP service provider can immediately provide 911 service to the geographically appropriate PSAP, a VOIP service provider shall provide such customer with clear notice that 911 service will be available only as described in <internal-xref idref="H761CB4A57C9B496DA94D5CBB057565E6" legis-path="716.(c)(2)">paragraph (2)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC47686AD0CE145999664F8A2F996682"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Restriction on acquisition of new customers</header><text>A VOIP service provider may not acquire new customers within a geographic area served by a selective router if, within 180 days of first acquiring a new customer in the area served by the selective router, the VOIP service provider does not provide 911 service, or E911 service where the PSAP is capable of receiving and processing such information, to the geographically appropriate PSAP for all existing customers served by the selective router.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB95502E7A2FB414196F9EC25740422F4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Enforcement: no first warnings</header><text>Paragraph (5) of section 503(b) shall not apply to the assessment of forfeiture penalties for violations of this subsection or the regulations thereunder.</text></paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HF103FE9438A948FDA6B9D7697508DC36"><enum>(d)</enum><header>State authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act or any Commission regulation or order shall prevent the imposition on or collection from a VOIP service provider, of any fee or charge specifically designated or presented as dedicated by a State, political subdivision thereof, or Indian tribe on an equitable, and non-discriminatory basis for the support of 911 and E–911 services if no portion of the revenue derived from such fee or charge is obligated or expended for any purpose other than support of 911 and E–911 services or enhancements of such services. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA6E76CBE05B74C8496180881D287A4F6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Feasibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing requirements or obligations under <internal-xref idref="H5BD8A68B0F3D4502885E366B7B7DE5E8" legis-path="716.(a)">subsections (a)</internal-xref> and <internal-xref idref="HD03E8796F78642480002BF38701B9E6D" legis-path="716.(b)">(b)</internal-xref>, the Commission shall ensure that such standards impose requirements or obligations on VOIP service providers and entities with ownership or control of necessary E–911 infrastructure that the Commission determines are technologically and operationally feasible. In determining the requirements and obligations that are technologically and operationally feasible, the Commission shall take into consideration available industry technological and operational standards.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1775A86F162B4DB8BAA009004BA8E0C1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Progress reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent that the Commission concludes that it is not technologically or operationally feasible for VOIP service providers to comply with E-911 requirements or obligations, then the Commission shall submit reports to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate on the progress in attaining and deploying E–911 service. Such reports shall be submitted semiannually until the Commission concludes that it is technologically and operationally feasible for all VOIP service providers to comply with E-911 requirements and obligations. Such reports may include any recommendations the Commission considers appropriate to encourage the migration of emergency services to TCP/IP protocol or other advanced services.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEEF451F8980C4ADAB86992CFC8009DCA"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Access to information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall have the authority to compile a list of PSAP contact information, testing procedures, and classes and types of services supported by PSAPs, or other information concerning the necessary E-911 infrastructure, for the purpose of assisting providers in complying with the requirements of this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H71B24955DDA44701990000653DCCAA24" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Emergency Routing Number Administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 30 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Federal Communications Commission shall establish an emergency routing number administrator to enable VOIP service providers to acquire non-dialable pseudo-automatic number identification numbers for 9-1-1 routing purposes on a national scale. The Commission may adopt such rules and practices as are necessary to guide such administrator in the fair and expeditious assignment of these numbers.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6737A581AB8944D38F507443D68462D2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Emergency response systems</header> 
<paragraph id="HAED117BA0A464B02B8ED8267DD002687"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice prior to installation or number activation of voip service</header><text>Prior to installation or number activation of VOIP service for a customer, a VOIP service provider shall provide clear and conspicuous notice to the customer that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCCEC7C9D608649CEB45271BF1E16DAFB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such customer should arrange with his or her emergency response system provider, if any, to test such system after installation;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0007E963924945FD88DF9056A5925DC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such customer should notify his or her emergency response system provider after VOIP service is installed; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H59909BB06D1A4058B215BDA94FB8DCE7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a battery backup is required for customer premises equipment installed in connection with the VOIP service in order for the signaling of such system to function in the event of a power outage.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H88B688D3082F4627A76B4B00A836696D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this subsection:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE98A894464304B499DB2B62F58A8A54"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <quote>emergency response system</quote> means an alarm or security system, or personal security or medical monitoring system, that is connected to an emergency response center by means of a telecommunications carrier or VOIP service provider.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA4BDD6AC504742CF815664E31F037442"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <quote>emergency response center</quote> means an entity that monitors transmissions from an emergency response system.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H65BCFE4041BD43899940C0BD8679C4B9"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Migration to IP-enabled emergency network</header> 
<paragraph id="H1EA1C796C6484892B54528E91E4CF880"><enum>(1)</enum><header>National report</header><text>No more than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this section, the National 911 Implementation and Coordination Office shall develop a report to Congress on migrating to a national IP-enabled emergency network capable of receiving and responding to all citizen activated emergency communications. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H91275E48A7364FFBA2BE30FE9043BB00"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents of report</header><text>The report required by <internal-xref idref="H1EA1C796C6484892B54528E91E4CF880" legis-path="716.(j)(1)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref> shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H44408752489D45CC000035FB9BA6C36D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>outline the potential benefits of such a migration; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1029AB53B64F428A89C63C7B308527DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify barriers that must be overcome and funding mechanisms to address those barriers; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF84E65B126284F08A08407D01FF96839"><enum>(C)</enum><text>include a proposed timetable, an outline of costs and potential savings; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2A5FC2E4699E497BA0C22BA29E764EA7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provide recommendations on specific legislative language, </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0DD40C3D6DB4418F83007FE6A8C7C300"><enum>(E)</enum><text>provide recommendations on any legislative changes, including updating definitions, to facilitate a national IP-enabled emergency network; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3D2BEBB53CD44811B4B8598571B184B8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>assess, collect, and analyze the experiences of the PSAPs and related public safety authorities who are conducting trial deployments of IP-enabled emergency networks as of the date of enactment of this section. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0250F2066A67407398D6D48624393769"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In developing the report required by <internal-xref idref="H1EA1C796C6484892B54528E91E4CF880" legis-path="716.(j)(1)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref>, the Office shall consult with representatives of the public safety community, technology and telecommunications providers, and others it deems appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H774B5265D50D4606BA0042517024DED7"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Implementation</header> 
<paragraph id="H437BFE7472C6400480AF66D5C48F1E9C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall prescribe regulations to implement this section within 120 days after the date of enactment of this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEBCD66405F3440CAABAD547000D387E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to permit the Commission to issue regulations that require or impose a specific technology or technological standard.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA68A7743E1A1474EAC31DE234E313EE9"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H929CA975BE4D4DA1BE37FB41B4D0A7EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>VOIP service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>VOIP service</term> means a service that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA9EA14E3328143C99039317501AC813"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides real-time 2-way voice communications transmitted through customer premises equipment using TCP/IP protocol, or a successor protocol (including when the voice communication is converted to or from TCP/IP protocol by the VOIP service provider and transmitted to the subscriber without use of circuit switching), for a fee or without a fee;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2BDE704A577F4385943B8CDC88951379"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is offered to the public, or such classes of users as to be effectively available to the public (whether part of a bundle of services or separately); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD17B7D9CA3D84A2D00B49DE3006DF77"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has the capability so that the service can originate traffic to, and terminate traffic from, the public switched telephone network.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB199CD8D52F24D9E9EE7712394E556AB" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header> VOIP service provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>VOIP service provider</term> means any person who provides or offers to provide a VOIP service.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H71465FA08250409D854FAE5DF1C4C47E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Necessary E–911 infrastructure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term ‘necessary E–911 infrastructure’ means the originating trucks to the selective routers, selective routers, databases (including automatic location information databases and master street address guides), trunks, or other related facilities necessary for the delivery and completion of 911 and E–911 calls, or other 911 and E-911 equipment, facilities, databases, interfaces, and related capabilities specified by the Commission.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2711ACF60D7B4A7880F5CF69675F542C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Non-dialable pseudo-automatic number identification number</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>non-dialable pseudo-automatic number identification number</quote> means a number, consisting of the same number of digits as numbers used for automatic number identification, that is not a North American Numbering Plan telephone directory number and that may be used in place of an automatic number identification number to convey special meaning. The special meaning assigned to the non-dialable pseudo-automatic number identification number is determined by nationally standard agreements, or by individual agreements, as necessary, between the system originating the call, intermediate systems handling and routing the call, and the destination system.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H8C0FB3C0FBAB421C007205AC2E13D9AA" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>717.</enum><header>Rights and obligations of VOIP service providers</header> 
<subsection id="HB5D1392F83F745E9BE412403DDC6CBD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> 
<paragraph id="HCFAED7BEBA034DCD8880002406EEF7B2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Facilities-based voip service providers</header><text>A facilities-based VOIP service provider shall have the same rights, duties, and obligations as a requesting telecommunications carrier under sections 251 and 252, if the provider elects to assert such rights.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBBE01C2F97834231AEFF296110EDFC70"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Voip service providers</header><text>A VOIP service provider that is not a facilities-based VOIP service provider shall have only the same rights, duties, and obligations as a requesting telecommunications carrier under sections 251(b), 251(e), and 252, if the provider elects to assert such rights.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAF3001E4B659476894C7BB05CB6994C9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Clarifying treatment of VOIP service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A telecommunications carrier may use interconnection, services, and network elements obtained pursuant to sections 251 and 252 from an incumbent local exchange carrier (as such term is defined in section 251(h)) to exchange VOIP service traffic with such incumbent local exchange carrier regardless of the provider originating such VOIP service traffic, including an affiliate of such telecommunications carrier.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA2AB083395B64E24975B0049CC06D66F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Disabled access</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A VOIP service provider or a manufacturer of VOIP service equipment shall have the same rights, duties, and obligations as a telecommunications carrier or telecommunications equipment manufacturer, respectively, under sections 225, 255, and 710 of the Act. Within 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission, in consultation with the Architectural and Transportation Barriers Compliance Board, shall prescribe such regulations as are necessary to implement this section. In implementing this subsection, the Commission shall consider whether a VOIP service provider or manufacturer of VOIP service equipment primarily markets such service or equipment as a substitute for telecommunications service, telecommunications equipment, customer premises equipment, or telecommunications relay services.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE8D0A33799C0414084DA0020C2F4F136"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="HFA16A2D7CE7F4CB3A7C298D622DAE8CD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Facilities-based VOIP service provider</header><text>The term <quote>facilities-based VOIP service provider</quote> means an entity that provides VOIP service over a physical facility that terminates at the end user’s location and which such entity or an affiliate owns or over which such entity or affiliate has exclusive use. An entity or affiliate shall be considered a facilities-based VOIP service provider only in those geographic areas where such terminating physical facilities are located.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8DED121F07094BE09F49BA88A7B500AB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Voip service provider; voip service</header><text>The terms <quote>VOIP service provider</quote> and <quote>VOIP service</quote> have the meanings given such terms by section 716(l).</text></paragraph></subsection> </section> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HE34C1BDD1A354FC28752DCCA0429F6C2" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>302.</enum><header>Compensation and contribution</header> 
<subsection id="HB2B76B00E1344FD7BF81AE1E2E5DE753"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act (including the amendments made by this Act) shall be construed to exempt a VOIP service provider from requirements imposed by the Federal Communications Commission or a State commission on all VOIP service providers to—</text> 
<paragraph id="HEF521BD8C0B24F5C9E7403CEE0F6A6E8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>pay appropriate compensation for the transmission of a VOIP service over the facilities and equipment of another provider; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H547737FE2F13461596C8E107FEF3700"><enum>(2)</enum><text>contribute on an equitable and non-discriminatory basis to the preservation and advancement of universal service.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8D55563F2F3A40E19CBDBCFAA6534348"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>As used in this section—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF7CB658A200944FDACC5878FE2A04FF2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the terms <quote>VOIP service provider</quote> and <quote>VOIP service</quote> have the meanings given such terms in section 716(h) of the Communications Act of 1934, as added by section 301 of this Act; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC9EF1DAEECCA4410A064EDAFF733B2E2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>State commission</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/153">47 U.S.C. 153</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title> 
<title id="H2DD67FFFA4304648811BF93252EA3C94"><enum>IV</enum><header>Municipal provision of services</header> 
<section id="H90D994BFFE22427CB94F684BE22CECD7"><enum>401.</enum><header>Government authority to provide services</header> 
<subsection id="H1F52840F06C84C159870C9BE93B58D26"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Neither the Communications Act of 1934 nor any State statute, regulation, or other State legal requirement may prohibit or have the effect of prohibiting any public provider of telecommunications service, information service, or cable service (as such terms are defined in sections 3 and 602 of such Act) from providing such services to any person or entity.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC05444BCB3FE49C1B65401B9DBEC6BF9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Competition Neutrality</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any State or political subdivision thereof, or any agency, authority, or instrumentality of a State or political subdivision thereof, that is, owns, controls, or is otherwise affiliated with a public provider of telecommunications service, information service, or cable service shall not grant any preference or advantage to any such provider. Such entity shall apply its ordinances, rules, and policies, including those relating to the use of public rights-of-way, permitting, performance bonding, and reporting without discrimination in favor of any such provider as compared to other providers of such services.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H084B3901802C40DFA71FCF05E8083BE9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Compliance with other laws Not affected</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall exempt a public provider from any law or regulation that applies to providers of telecommunications service, information service, or cable service.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7816085777684631B569639C22AD46C2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Federal Communications Commission shall submit to the Congress a report on the status of the provision of telecommunications service, information service, and cable service by States and political subdivisions thereof.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8A38380EDFA247E50060C6C7005736BE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definition of public provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <term>public provider</term> means a State or political subdivision thereof, or any agency, authority, or instrumentality of a State or political subdivision thereof, that provides telecommunications service, information service, or cable service, or any entity that is owned, controlled, or is otherwise affiliated with such State or political subdivision thereof, or agency, authority, or instrumentality of a State or political subdivision thereof.</text></subsection></section></title> 
<title id="H3FA2D596E9A4463DA32E353BFCF3864D"><enum>V</enum><header>Broadband Service</header> 
<section id="H8E98C197F2AF42C2A0D0B2E7F7000790"><enum>501.</enum><header>Stand-alone broadband service</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title VII of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/601">47 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>) is further amended by adding after section 717 (as added by section 301 of this Act) the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H45EF7538948147E593C1BF015DFC0234" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="HD13D6A4CE94449FC95A671FE2350B9F6"><enum>718.</enum><header>Stand-alone broadband service</header> 
<subsection id="HA357299F68D04825BDD5F4086621BCC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A broadband service provider shall not require a subscriber, as a condition on the purchase of any broadband service the provider offers, to purchase any cable service, telecommunications service, or VOIP service offered by the provider.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD1E8014297B24E7A0093A3A050A36241"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H4BB883FFCB2E4109A6F6CC7BADE2BEEE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term ‘broadband service’ means a two-way transmission service that connects to the Internet and transmits information at an average rate of at least 200 kilobits per second in at least one direction.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE76574AB0C8148F7AC115EAE90D26751"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term ‘broadband service provider’ means a person or entity that controls, operates, or resells and controls any facility used to provide broadband service to the public, by whatever technology and whether provided for a fee, in exchange for an explicit benefit, or for free.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H57C56946F04641EEA7BDF84ABE3F300"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <quote>VOIP service</quote> has the meaning given such term by section 716(l).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H8AB728AD53244877BD004635D854D073"><enum>502.</enum><header>Study of interference potential of broadband over power line systems</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Within 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Federal Communications Commission shall conduct, and submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, a study of the interference potential of broadband over power line systems.</text></section></title> 
<title id="H0FAC4D25C39A442681A958594FE149A"><enum>VI</enum><header>Seamless Mobility</header> 
<section id="H31B919D8585943C09D6949AF7FDA7746"><enum>601.</enum><header>Development of seamless mobility</header> 
<subsection id="H2DA41A5E17124815B3A4EAFC8210514F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Streamlined review</header> 
<paragraph id="H9C40D58D08ED4F4A92C953875E2D63D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Commission shall further the development of seamless mobility.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H99750115AD2A421A83A9ACA6EF95008E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Within 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall implement a process for streamlined review and authorization of multi-mode devices that permit communication across multiple Internet protocol-enabled broadband platforms, facilities, and networks. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCDE6C7B58C7640E7B762578366007158"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Commission shall undertake an inquiry to identify barriers to the achievement of seamless mobility. Within 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall report to the Congress on its findings and its recommendations for steps to eliminate those barriers. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H55460BAFCD7F40F696930826DAA6FF33"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term ‘‘seamless mobility’’ means the ability of a communications device to select between and utilize multiple Internet protocol-enabled technology platforms, facilities, and networks in a real-time manner to provide a unified service.</text></subsection></section></title> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20060609" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives June 8, 2006.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Karen L. Haas</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation> 
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement> 
</bill> 


