<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HDA058465694443A797C4A23817542D78" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 2192 EH: To amend title 38, United States Code, to establish an Ombudsman within the Department of Veterans Affairs.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">110th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 2192</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to establish an Ombudsman within the Department of Veterans Affairs.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" style="OLC" id="H76ADDA78104047A1AAE8029E65793290"> 
<section id="H2D11EC86873B4B189D2BF5A00078AA6C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Establishment of Office of the Ombudsman in Veterans Health Administration</header> 
<subsection id="H1C8ACAD537A44A8B9DEAEC00CC8491FB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Office of the Ombudsman</header> 
<paragraph id="H54B4B5A3A6294BB28B55C79BDC731F53"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/73">chapter 73</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H2725F4E2E40640EAB78000A4CEB6A49F" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<section id="H3A9EF9E6682548C493C1928432B6E0CF"><enum>7309.</enum><header>Office of the Ombudsman</header> 
<subsection id="H1BCE3B3FD3B0436485CC41AB00310001"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Office; Directors</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Veterans Health Administration an Office of the Ombudsman (in this section referred to as the <quote>Office</quote>). The Office shall be headed by a Director appointed by the Secretary. The Director shall report directly to the Secretary.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFA3946D837C248709FE138A92743441"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties of office</header><text>The Office shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6C72D209EB464132AA19005B01F74166"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be responsible for ensuring—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7EBA22BA8A8449A28D045DABAC0382D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>all matters referred to the Office are handled in a confidential manner; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H40FB136F0EFD4E1986A0F08C3BC41EC9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any action taken by the Administration with respect to such a matter does not negatively affect the ability of any veteran to receive health care or benefits under a law administered by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H09B69CEC7177426FBBD7A038EB4C526E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>serve as a last resort for complaints and issues that cannot be resolved at a local or regional level in the Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H77ED0F18827C44A3A2EA9C04C2A7BAE9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties of director</header><text>The Director shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7AA2C437A21940A5951C2373B3F221C0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be responsible for overseeing the efforts of patient advocates in the Administration;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCAD74333D41B466E9F6DA5C7D3C2DD00"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop and make available to local offices of the Administration tools for monitoring the work of such patient advocates and standards to evaluate the work of such patient advocates;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H987FC161E4454AD70034837EAE80C1F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>determine trends, in terms of numbers, topics, and facility locations, in patient issues and complaints;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H660989DC25C44D3082B5165D157CEDB5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>participate in such national quality conferences of the Administration as the Under Secretary for Health may designate;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H54043EA244F94EB48C002FA2EF331769"><enum>(5)</enum><text>help coordinate assistance for veterans who need assistance from the Administration in more than one region of the Administration; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBB7DDEDDBF324422956D5DF090797CE8"><enum>(6)</enum><text>maintain a public Web site with links to contact information for each patient advocate at each medical center of the Department.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4D55523358704186A3396024FB06DFF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Regional administrators</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall appoint three regional administrators to support facilities of the Administration and veterans integrated service networks in their patient advocacy work, to identify best practices for patient advocacy work and inform such facilities and networks of such best practices, and to receive and refer to the board established under subsection (e) appeals from veterans in their respective regions who are not satisfied with the efforts of their local medical center of the Department and veteran integrated service network.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H311765048A56463D9ED420E8B8A3C432"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Board</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall establish a board composed of the Director and the three regional administrators appointed under subsection (d) to hear appeals referred to the board by a regional administrator under subsection (d) and issue a letter explaining the board’s decision regarding such appeal and outlining possible steps for resolving issues raised in such appeal.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB17E270128B5429886D1E2350832D1AD"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitation on statutory construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed as affecting the authority and responsibility of coordinators of patient advocates for severely injured veterans of Operation of Enduring Freedom and severely injured veterans of Operation Iraqi Freedom.</text></subsection></section> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD34AA41E4BE54898B600A623FE17DDBF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 7308 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3D822F82AAA24196977F4FF0D35B3EBA" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">7309. Office of the Ombudsman.</toc-entry></toc> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC4397E005C7D42510015D3CCDAE0D723" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deadline for designation of Ombudsman</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall designate an individual to serve as the Ombudsman of the Veterans Health Administration under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/7309">section 7309</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20080729" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives July 29, 2008.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 


