<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H46DD769C963D47C0AE9B38B8F6D7309" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 3286 IH: To amend title 38, United States Code, to reduce the period of time for which a veteran must be totally disabled before the veteran’s survivors are eligible for the benefits provided by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs for survivors of certain veterans rated totally disabled at time of death.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-08-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
<session>1st Session</session>
<legis-num>H. R. 3286</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070801">August 1, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000116">Mr. Filner</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to reduce the period of time for which a veteran must be totally disabled before the veteran’s survivors are eligible for the benefits provided by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs for survivors of certain veterans rated totally disabled at time of death.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H50CF4E0AC89E4C0EB3E887F854940403" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB850F649524446F99901A43080CE9031" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Reduction of period of time for which veterans must be totally disabled for purposes of benefits provided by Secretary of Veterans Affairs for survivors of certain veterans rated totally disabled at time of death</header>
<subsection id="H3F6F2EB19CBB405BB707BB4BE9417C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Expansion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1318">Section 1318(b)</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>if—</quote> and all that follows through the period at the end and inserting the following: <quote>if the disability was continuously rated totally disabling for a period of not less than one year immediately preceding death.</quote>.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H4344F8E5D5414556807655B9A76EF78C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall apply with respect to deaths occurring on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


