<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H8EA603EDD09546939EB494C56F9E3768" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>109 HR 5341 IH: To amend section 5313 of title 31, United States Code, to
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2006-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>109th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>2d Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 5341</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20060510">May 10, 2006</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000013">Mr. Bachus</sponsor> (for
			 himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000339">Mr. Frank of Massachusetts</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="H001036">Mr. Hensarling</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M001140">Mr. Moore of Kansas</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="R000574">Mr. Renzi</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M000087">Mrs. Maloney</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="D000603">Mr. Davis of Kentucky</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="D000602">Mr. Davis of Alabama</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="S001144">Mr. Shays</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="H000762">Ms. Hooley</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="J000255">Mr. Jones of North Carolina</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M001142">Mr. Matheson</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="B001232">Mrs. Biggert</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="H000636">Mr. Hinojosa</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="G000548">Mr. Garrett of New Jersey</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="W001159">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="N000182">Mr. Neugebauer</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="C001049">Mr. Clay</cosponsor>, and
			 <cosponsor name-id="M000309">Mrs. McCarthy</cosponsor>) introduced the
			 following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial
			 Services</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To amend <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/5313">section 5313</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code, to
		  reform certain requirements for reporting cash transactions, and for other
		  purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H3F53B49DC66247459F322D21A510A9B" style="OLC">
		<section id="HC7683C2ACB4C457685621C49DC3F55A3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote>Seasoned
			 Customer CTR Exemption Act of 2006</quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H1132E0D1589844308100D38FB3CBC827"><enum>2.</enum><header>Exception from
			 currency transaction reports for seasoned customers</header>
			<subsection id="H90317FCDE6FE484792FA8C005FBF3DD2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Congress finds as follows:</text>
				<paragraph id="HB28273B68108421EA6BAA1B183F91995"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The completion of
			 and filing of currency transaction reports under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/5313">section 5313</external-xref> of title 31,
			 United States Code, poses a compliance burden on the financial industry.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HB71A9A4EC5EE4908ABCF7F70F4CA5F9F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Due to the nature
			 of the transactions or the persons and entities conducting such transactions,
			 some reports as currently filed may not be relevant to the detection,
			 deterrence, or investigation of financial crimes, including money laundering
			 and the financing of terrorism.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H3EB6D69D30B84B8088C1F9AD00BD7409"><enum>(3)</enum><text>However, the data
			 contained in such reports can provide valuable context for the analysis of
			 other data derived pursuant to subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 31, United
			 States Code, as well as investigative data, which provide invaluable and
			 indispensable information supporting efforts to combat money laundering and
			 other financial crimes.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H096D88943FE54353AC36A1ADCE0C6DF"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An appropriate exemption process from the
			 reporting requirements for certain currency transactions that are of little or
			 no value to ongoing efforts of law enforcement agencies, financial regulatory
			 agencies, and the financial services industry to investigate, detect, or deter
			 financial crimes would continue to fulfill the compelling need to produce and
			 provide meaningful information to policy-makers, financial regulators, law
			 enforcement, and intelligence agencies, while potentially lowering the
			 compliance burden placed on financial institutions by the need to file such
			 reports.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HE44392835A9F4B88ADEC9E44EE1144A8"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury has by
			 regulation, and in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/5313">section 5313</external-xref> of title 31, United States
			 Code, implemented a process by which institutions may seek exemptions from
			 filing certain currency transaction reports based on appropriate circumstances;
			 however, the financial industry has not taken full advantage of these
			 provisions and has contended that they are unduly burdensome.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HEB579822E2214C7DBB7C04EDEEBA4EDB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The act of
			 providing notice to the Secretary of the Treasury of designations of
			 exemption—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H8039751A883A4A558C23837D00A079B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provides
			 meaningful information to law enforcement officials on exempt customers and
			 enables law enforcement to obtain account information through appropriate legal
			 process; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19FA4E4A6FD945178FA4CA93FB3D2F86"><enum>(B)</enum><text>complements other
			 sections of title 31, United States Code, whereby law enforcement can locate
			 financial institutions with relevant records relating to a person of
			 investigative interest, such as information requests made pursuant to
			 regulations implementing section 314(a) of the USA PATRIOT Act of 2001.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H952C9BF0261547ADBA5289A0CA09689E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A
			 designation of exemption has no effect on requirements for depository
			 institutions to apply the full range of anti-money laundering controls required
			 under subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code, and related
			 provisions of law, including the requirement to apply the customer
			 identification program pursuant to section 5326 of such title, and the
			 requirement to identify, monitor, and, if appropriate, report suspicious
			 activity in accordance with section 5318(g) of such title.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HD918807658A94A98A82E384CFFD5B470"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The Federal
			 banking agencies and the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network have recently
			 provided guidance through the Federal Financial Institutions Examination
			 Council Bank Secrecy Act/Anti-Money Laundering Examination Manual on applying
			 appropriate levels of due diligence and identifying suspicious activity by the
			 types of cash-intensive businesses that generally will be subject to
			 exemption.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0AB8F3FA90994986AF02B3E6B13B207B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Seasoned
			 customer exemption</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/5313">Section 5313(e)</external-xref> of title 31, United States
			 Code, is amended to read as follows:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H955A6404417940AE98CC169239C5FC3E" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="HFF658986EF03466FA3B16BF607B3C7B8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Qualified
				customer exemption</header>
						<paragraph id="HFE008F79E7874F9F906F68004487D9E2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before the end of the
				270-day period beginning on the date of the enactment of the Seasoned Customer
				CTR Exemption Act of 2006, the Secretary of the Treasury shall prescribe
				regulations that exempt any depository institution from filing a report
				pursuant to this section in a transaction for the payment, receipt, or transfer
				of United States coins or currency (or other monetary instruments the Secretary
				of the Treasury prescribes) with a qualified customer of the depository
				institution.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="HEFC5D8F996EA4F0FBD5F2BAF4D85BEC3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified
				customer defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes
				of this section, the term <quote>qualified customer</quote>, with respect to a
				depository institution, has such meaning as the Secretary of the Treasury shall
				prescribe, which shall include any person that—</text>
							<subparagraph id="H1B4072D900914FE586AD1F1964F5BE50"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is incorporated or organized under the laws
				of the United States or any State, including a sole proprietorship (as defined
				in 31 C.F.R. 103.22(d)(6)(vii), as in effect on May 10, 2006), or is registered
				as and eligible to do business within the United States or a State;</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6501DA44D3A45328550157BD38519A7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has maintained a
				deposit account with the depository institution for at least 12 months;
				and</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7146DE1EFAF14A62AFF22EBA00823D8B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has engaged, using
				such account, in multiple currency transactions that are subject to the
				reporting requirements of subsection (a).</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HFB83A4ECECD34935A65B30034F69B9D4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Regulations</header>
							<subparagraph commented="no" id="HE1C6384CC5E949008C58AC17BB35B8D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall prescribe regulations
				requiring a depository institution to file a 1-time notice of designation of
				exemption for each qualified customer of the depository institution.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HBFA355FB04994A4582F4EA648BA97294"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Form and content
				of exemption notice</header><text>The Secretary shall by regulation prescribe
				the form, manner, content, and timing of the qualified customer exemption
				notice and such notice shall include information sufficient to identify the
				qualified customer and the accounts of the customer.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB66D3E82E956422CA0EFA9C0B00DC1F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Authority of
				secretary</header>
								<clause commented="no" id="HF5ED3849D1024AF7B0253DC387BD678"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text>The Secretary may suspend, reject, or revoke any
				qualified customer exemption notice, in accordance with criteria prescribed by
				the Secretary by regulation.</text>
								</clause><clause commented="no" id="H189A1C04150441B891B5095D3F066D00"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Conditions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may establish conditions, in
				accordance with criteria prescribed by regulation, under which exempt qualified
				customers of an insured depository institution that is merged with or acquired
				by another insured depository institution will continue to be treated as
				designated exempt qualified customers of the surviving or acquiring
				institution.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HB61825CD24F34AEEAA16CA0314AB81B2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>3-year review
			 and report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before the end of
			 the 3-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the
			 Secretary of the Treasury, in consultation with the Attorney General, the
			 Secretary of Homeland Security, the Federal banking agencies, the banking
			 industry, and such other persons as the Secretary deems appropriate, shall
			 evaluate the operations and effect of the provisions of the amendment made by
			 subsection (a) and make recommendations to Congress as to any legislative
			 action with respect to such provision as the Secretary may determine to be
			 appropriate.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


