<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0A33AA9657734D02B44DA30000FC8708" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>108th CONGRESS</congress> <session>2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 4996</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20040722">July 22, 2004</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000822">Mr. Stearns</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To enhance Federal Trade Commission enforcement against cross-border fraud and deception.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body style="OLC" id="H86E7A90614E149EEAE9B00FBFE6C32EE"> 
<section id="HE2B12C5A3F0042008EA8C0981448BA45" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be referred to as the <quote>International Consumer Protection Act of 2004</quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HA886BE4398D14E4EA97EE102AE4100FC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Foreign law enforcement agency defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 4 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/44">15 U.S.C. 44</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF00D724850874BF29EA5BD4FDEC412A8" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H334E0DA707CB4FAFBD6B42600500D0D8" indent="up1"><enum></enum><text><quote>Foreign law enforcement agency</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5650CFFF91E044DDA35422F91E842883"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any agency or judicial authority of a foreign government, including a foreign state, a political subdivision of a foreign state, or a multinational organization constituted by and comprised of foreign states, that is vested with law enforcement or investigative authority in civil, criminal, or administrative matters; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5E678E091E7E4FA7B531205210DB6144"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any multinational or multiagency organization to the extent that it is acting on behalf of an entity described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph> </paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H4D027C7D9FAB4843A3EB65B1D5A061A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Availability of remedies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 5(a) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="traditional" id="HF383872E3CD745F682FA38535C2D53AB" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HA62768F625DF44909EAA1F95B6AF469D" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum> 
<subparagraph id="HC42041C0096947198575B878945CB85C" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text> For purposes of this subsection, the term <quote>unfair or deceptive acts or practices</quote> shall include such acts or practices involving foreign commerce that—</text> 
<clause id="H709FD8091AFD4809B663A100C0D5684F" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>cause or are likely to cause reasonably foreseeable injury within the United States; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF48D2BEFCDF74318B247F96290045EC" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>involve material conduct occurring within the United States.</text> </clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5B78A02A652140FBB164C3522220A215" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>All remedies available to the Commission with respect to unfair and deceptive acts or practices shall be available for acts and practices described in this paragraph, including restitution to domestic or foreign victims.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HA4F1D8AE4AD748C000456400E64BD4EC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Powers of the Commission</header> 
<subsection id="HFD4DC883159347EE8510C8198868C329"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Publication of information; reports</header><text>Section 6(f) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/46">15 U.S.C. 46(f)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF48F320A324044CB9EBECD32E0C896BB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(1)</quote> after <quote>such information</quote> the first place it appears; and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB0DDC19602734256B5E202BAA328E15C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>purposes.</quote> and inserting <quote>purposes, and (2) to any officer or employee of any foreign law enforcement agency under the same circumstances that making material available to foreign law enforcement agencies is permitted under section 21(b).</quote>.</text></paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H62E84ADC5D254179A94BB2E3203241D6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Other Powers of the Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 6 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/46">15 U.S.C. 46</external-xref>) is further amended by inserting after subsection (i) and before the proviso the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3E2F03CC5D8E45BFB99670D1B9009DA5" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H6DC546CFB93042628CCFB7775EDE9C54"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Investigative assistance for foreign law enforcement agencies</header> 
<paragraph id="HE2AAC7A0B20A456DA4BDA7F426203C22"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon a written request from a foreign law enforcement agency to provide assistance in accordance with this subsection, if the requesting agency states that it is investigating, or engaging in enforcement proceedings against, possible violations of laws prohibiting fraudulent or deceptive commercial practices, or other practices substantially similar to practices prohibited by any provision of the laws administered by the Commission, other than Federal antitrust laws (as defined in section 12(5) of the International Antitrust Enforcement Assistance Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/6211">15 U.S.C. 6211(5)</external-xref>)), the Commission may provide the assistance described in paragraph (2) without requiring that the conduct identified in the request constitute a violation of the laws of the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H682DF20EAA1D4C0CB0E26D604E4623E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Type of assistance</header><text>In providing assistance to a foreign law enforcement agency under this subsection, the Commission may—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H277A9C7AC3CB4410999397E1BEC2A6E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conduct such investigation as the Commission deems necessary to collect information and evidence pertinent to the request for assistance, using all investigative powers authorized by this Act; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H20A2F82D4A944587BBF15B9CF3001EBF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>when the request is from an agency acting to investigate or pursue the enforcement of civil laws, or when the Attorney General refers a request to the Commission from an agency acting to investigate or pursue the enforcement of criminal laws, seek and accept appointment by a United States district court of Commission attorneys to provide assistance to foreign and international tribunals and to litigants before such tribunals on behalf of a foreign law enforcement agency pursuant to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/28/1782">section 1782</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3FCB699DA56D4E8B91693FF19E48347"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Criteria for determination</header><text>In deciding whether to provide such assistance, the Commission shall consider all relevant factors, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCB575693E4BB434385E434BCF11A724"><enum>(A)</enum><text>whether the requesting agency has agreed to provide or will provide reciprocal assistance to the Commission; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB283C595809F49F0B78265AFA1008866"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whether compliance with the request would prejudice the public interest of the United States; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1FC7F94AB06B47D19B009E7E9487FB2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>whether the requesting agency’s investigation or enforcement proceeding concerns acts or practices that cause or are likely to cause injury to a significant number of persons.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4CD9CEA31C2A41D7B3D0FDB630003597"><enum>(4)</enum><header>International agreements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a foreign law enforcement agency has set forth a legal basis for requiring execution of an international agreement as a condition for reciprocal assistance, or as a condition for provision of materials or information to the Commission, the Commission, with prior approval and ongoing oversight of the Secretary of State, and with final approval of the agreement by the Secretary of State, may negotiate and conclude an international agreement, in the name of either the United States or the Commission, for the purpose of obtaining such assistance, materials, or information. The Commission may undertake in such an international agreement to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB60DC03147C140F8BF1984D1E0C5014F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide assistance using the powers set forth in this subsection;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H002783B28E63439899F1E09073DF77F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>disclose materials and information in accordance with subsection (f) and section 21(b); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H335023544CF04C0C979FD5EF873CAE6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>engage in further cooperation, and protect materials and information received from disclosure, as authorized by this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9E1E4E7A50C9468FBA3163FB68B3C360"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Additional authority</header><text>The authority provided by this subsection is in addition to, and not in lieu of, any other authority vested in the Commission or any other officer of the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H902A5AD2551C4C6C810018B62EBC3D50"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authority granted by this subsection shall not authorize the Commission to take any action or exercise any power with respect to a bank, a savings and loan institution described in section 18(f)(3) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(f)(3)</external-xref>), a Federal credit union described in section 18(f)(4) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(f)(4)</external-xref>), or a common carrier subject to the Act to regulate commerce, except in accordance with the proviso following the last designated subsection of section 6 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/46">15 U.S.C. 46</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H41986CB5836D4D28B913A400EC708866"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Assistance to certain countries</header><text>The Commission may not provide investigative assistance under this subsection to a foreign law enforcement agency from a foreign state that the Secretary of State has determined, in accordance with section 6(j) of the Export Administration Act of 1979 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/50/2405">50 U.S.C. App. 2405(j)</external-xref>), has repeatedly provided support for acts of international terrorism, unless and until such determination is rescinded pursuant to section 6(j)(4) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/50/2405">50 U.S.C. App. 2405(j)(4)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA9CBB78DA14D4EEEB644734EFAA8A183"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Referral of evidence for criminal proceedings</header> 
<paragraph id="H914158D46DA1444CA11E6EEA847B2200"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Whenever the Commission obtains evidence that any person, partnership, or corporation, either domestic or foreign, has engaged in conduct that may constitute a violation of Federal criminal law, the Commission may transmit such evidence to the Attorney General, who may institute criminal proceedings under appropriate statutes. Nothing in this paragraph affects any other authority of the Commission to disclose information.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7681596109BF4339898B00FD7DFFD142"><enum>(2)</enum><header>International information</header><text>The Commission shall endeavor to ensure, with respect to memoranda of understanding and international agreements it may conclude, that material it has obtained from foreign law enforcement agencies acting to investigate or pursue the enforcement of foreign criminal laws may be used for the purpose of investigation, prosecution, or prevention of violations of United States criminal laws.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H63AE20B6DDD54295ADEC9C3B4937D3C1"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Expenditures for cooperative arrangements</header><text>The Commission may expend appropriated funds for—</text> 
<paragraph id="H442D92A0D05F4ED900DC4F00052CB4A9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>operating expenses and other costs of bilateral and multilateral cooperative law enforcement groups conducting activities of interest to the Commission and in which the Commission participates; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBAAFB20D4E0A4557AB004DE0744BB3F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>expenses for consultations and meetings hosted by the Commission with foreign government agency officials, members of their delegations, appropriate representatives and staff to exchange views concerning developments relating to the Commission’s mission, development and implementation of cooperation agreements, and provision of technical assistance for the development of foreign consumer protection or competition regimes, such expenses to include necessary administrative and logistic expenses and the expenses of Commission staff and foreign invitees in attendance at such consultations and meetings including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF705454EF6144AD186219600FFC82B13"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such incidental expenses as meals taken in the course of such attendance;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2BAEC0388CF2450900593FAE97F99EFC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any travel and transportation to or from such meetings; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H76476B1BBFA741FEB5EDD0BD6BF38B4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other related lodging or subsistence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H88F7EBC27E994C70B8A3008C45ECCEEA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header><text>The Federal Trade Commission is authorized to expend appropriated funds not to exceed $100,000 per fiscal year for purposes of section 6(l) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/46">15 U.S.C. 46(l)</external-xref>) (as added by subsection (b) of this Act), including operating expenses and other costs of the following bilateral and multilateral cooperative law enforcement agencies and organizations:</text> 
<paragraph id="H66C6A3836E334360ADD2B12350CDCC9E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The International Consumer Protection and Enforcement Network. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H70E017E5F6BA4925B700F7002BD64DBD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The International Competition Network. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF0F2E434A9374056A1BE23348C85F8A0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Mexico-U.S.-Canada Health Fraud Task Force. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H327DA9A3CC8348D7BF00CD8CD53DA32C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Project Emptor. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H15FD9B156A1E4A508EA9FFBFC6D96800"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Toronto Strategic Partnership and other regional partnerships with a nexus in a Canadian province.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA2E324C88F7344238D11DCA91D7D13AD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 6 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/46">15 U.S.C. 46</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>clauses (a) and (b)</quote> in the proviso following subsection (l) (as added by subsection (b) of this section) and inserting <quote>subsections (a), (b), and (j)</quote>. </text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HE25304E88BE44869BC044B687901F605"><enum>5.</enum><header>Representation in Foreign Litigation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 16 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/56">15 U.S.C. 56</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H967C63EFDBD44A84884EEAC5D4B8C4B4" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H00054ADB3F144EA48717E2C7A93EFF7F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Foreign litigation</header> 
<paragraph id="HA465993D31F540E6B54F6DF0B3007E47"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commission attorneys</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With the concurrence of the Attorney General, the Commission may designate Commission attorneys to assist the Attorney General in connection with litigation in foreign courts on particular matters in which the Commission has an interest.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H707BFD67972F485BB3A81E293E65CB4C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reimbursement for Foreign Counsel</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission is authorized to expend appropriated funds, upon agreement with the Attorney General, to reimburse the Attorney General for the retention of foreign counsel for litigation in foreign courts, and for expenses related to litigation in foreign courts in which the Commission has an interest.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2C55F579A0A541D8828DBB90A9609D7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation on use of funds</header><text>Nothing in this subsection authorizes the payment of claims or judgments from any source other than the permanent and indefinite appropriation authorized by <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/1304">section 1304</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2A65839CD71743AEB869A817C0842988"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Other authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authority provided by this subsection is in addition to any other authority of the Commission or the Attorney General.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HDB3379FD4FA14A7A9311AC141C6335F7"><enum>6.</enum><header>Sharing information with foreign law enforcement agencies</header> 
<subsection id="H6A822D7496B54E8099778600F2607150"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Material obtained pursuant to compulsory process</header><text>Section 21(b)(6) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57b-2">15 U.S.C. 57b–2(b)(6)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H061A2B809192449DA5296EB111007FAF" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The custodian may make such material available to any foreign law enforcement agency upon the prior certification of an appropriate official of any such foreign law enforcement agency, either by a prior agreement or memorandum of understanding with the Commission or by other written certification, that such material will be maintained in confidence and will be used only for official law enforcement purposes, if—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7C958E61A2A54CD8B6BB9FDB1FB09BF9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the foreign law enforcement agency has set forth a bona fide legal basis for its authority to maintain the material in confidence;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC7D7BFFDC91649FD9FE97F1ED1A2EE56"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the materials are to be used for purposes of investigating, or engaging in enforcement proceedings related to, possible violations of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7D02AB5BFFEC4944A4A146B2E29D676F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>foreign laws prohibiting fraudulent or deceptive commercial practices or other practices substantially similar to practices prohibited by any law administered by the Commission; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H00A58C1F824F47919305892E8ED4AE61"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a law administered by the Commission, if disclosure of the material would further a Commission investigation or enforcement proceeding; or </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H91AF5EA97EF54249B8BD0061FF87D386"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>with the approval of the Attorney General, other foreign criminal laws, if such foreign criminal laws are offenses defined in or covered by a criminal mutual legal assistance treaty in force between the government of the United States and the foreign law enforcement agency’s government;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1D112533790B4E44AE268498A4D5E5B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the appropriate Federal banking agency (as defined in section 3(q) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813(q)</external-xref>)) or, in the case of a Federal credit union, the National Credit Union Administration, has given its prior approval if the materials to be provided under subparagraph (B) are requested by the foreign law enforcement agency for the purpose of investigating, or engaging in enforcement proceedings based on, possible violations of law by a bank, a savings and loan institution described in section 18(f)(3) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(f)(3)</external-xref>), or a Federal credit union described in section 18(f)(4) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(f)(4)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7B852AFD92BC47618118272F744F7ED7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the foreign law enforcement agency is not from a country that the Secretary of State has determined, in accordance with section 6(j) of the Export Administration Act of 1979 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/50/2405">50 U.S.C. App. 2405(j)</external-xref>), has repeatedly provided support for acts of international terrorism, unless and until such determination is rescinded pursuant to section 6(j)(4) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/50/2405">50 U.S.C. App. 2405(j)(4)</external-xref>). </text><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">Nothing in the preceding sentence authorizes the disclosure of material obtained in connection with the administration of the Federal antitrust laws or foreign antitrust laws (as defined in paragraphs (5) and (7), respectively, of section 12 of the International Antitrust Enforcement Assistance Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/6211">15 U.S.C. 6211</external-xref>)) to any officer or employee of a foreign law enforcement agency.</continuation-text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H60E254E68AFD4793A648A9E0DBB37481"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Information supplied by and about foreign sources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 21(f) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57b-2">15 U.S.C. 57b–2(f)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows—</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H07A8C337221F4D5CBA113E5E419C48D5" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H190C0C958867494F009F36EA585927AB"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Exemption from public disclosure</header> 
<paragraph id="HFEB163552CC142A9B93D53BBD9997E60"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any material which is received by the Commission in any investigation, a purpose of which is to determine whether any person may have violated any provision of the laws administered by the Commission, and which is provided pursuant to any compulsory process under this Act or which is provided voluntarily in place of such compulsory process shall not be required to be disclosed under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/552">section 552</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, or any other provision of law, except as provided in paragraph (2)(B) of this section. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCFE08BE9A758447AB190F77770BA4B32"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Material obtained from a foreign source</header> 
<subparagraph id="H8FE61BFEAC0D417FB63CB0641780075B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subparagraph (B) of this paragraph, the Commission shall not be required to disclose under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/552">section 552</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, or any other provision of law—</text> 
<clause id="H37D357F2D8FA48FCBAA46E843BC1B9BF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any material obtained from a foreign law enforcement agency or other foreign government agency, if the foreign law enforcement agency or other foreign government agency has requested confidential treatment, or has precluded such disclosure under other use limitations, as a condition of providing the material; </text></clause> 
<clause id="HE6A3D970DA2A45ECBD68053BF9E638B2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any material reflecting a consumer complaint obtained from any other foreign source, if that foreign source supplying the material has requested confidential treatment as a condition of providing the material; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8E4776AF27D64057BA1E0853C4A700BA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any material reflecting a consumer complaint submitted to a Commission reporting mechanism sponsored in part by foreign law enforcement agencies or other foreign government agencies. </text></clause> 
<clause id="HDF08380F6670443CA164290144CF9D92" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Nothing in this subsection shall authorize the Commission to withhold information from the Congress or prevent the Commission from complying with an order of a court of the United States in an action commenced by the United States or the Commission.</text></clause></subparagraph> </paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H1916C889A0D14E168F00E1F40CB4DA2"><enum>7.</enum><header>Confidentiality, delayed notice of process</header> 
<subsection id="HCAF73A6E9C544FC4856700C7F15E29A6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 21 the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H519FF988FFED4612A236DFDB177EAB7D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H5488C6BB1AE745E2A569199DD834D9C1"><enum>21A.</enum><header>Confidentiality and delayed notice of compulsory process for certain third parties</header> 
<subsection id="H05A1979E59CA43AC83B85145B6DCAF1E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Application with other laws</header><text>The Right to Financial Privacy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3401">12 U.S.C. 3401 et seq.</external-xref>) and <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/121">chapter 121</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, shall apply with respect to the Commission, except as otherwise provided in this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB4720A25E91B492A9F8C488EF2551262"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Procedures for delay of notification or prohibition of disclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The procedures for delay of notification or prohibition of disclosure under the Right to Financial Privacy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3401">12 U.S.C. 3401 et seq.</external-xref>) and <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/121">chapter 121</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, including procedures for extensions of such delays or prohibitions, shall be available to the Commission, provided that, notwithstanding any provision therein—</text> 
<paragraph id="H66388F559131477F93BEA2ED626C01FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a court may issue an order delaying notification or prohibiting disclosure (including extending such an order) in accordance with the procedures of section 1109 of the Right to Financial Privacy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3409">12 U.S.C. 3409</external-xref>) (if notification would otherwise be required under that Act), or <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/18/2705">section 2705</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, (if notification would otherwise be required under chapter 121 of that title), if the presiding judge or magistrate judge finds that there is reason to believe that such notification or disclosure may cause an adverse result, as defined in subsection (g); and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H43DD653933D84326AD0251DEAEEBEFE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if notification would otherwise be required under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/121">chapter 121</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, the Commission may delay notification (including extending such a delay) upon the execution of a written certification in accordance with the procedures of section 2705 of that title if the Commission finds that there is reason to believe that notification may cause an adverse result, as defined in subsection (g).</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF430152A1D5A45BDB300CC2EF80551F2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Ex Parte Application by Commission</header> 
<paragraph id="HBF09B560AA0A4554B3F3AACE922397D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If neither notification nor delayed notification by the Commission is required under the Right to Financial Privacy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3401">12 U.S.C. 3401 et seq.</external-xref>) or <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/121">chapter 121</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, the Commission may apply ex parte to a presiding judge or magistrate judge for an order prohibiting the recipient of compulsory process issued by the Commission from disclosing to any other person the existence of the process, notwithstanding any law or regulation of the United States, or under the constitution, or any law or regulation, of any State, political subdivision of a State, territory of the United States, or the District of Columbia. The presiding judge or magistrate judge may enter such an order granting the requested prohibition of disclosure for a period not to exceed 60 days if there is reason to believe that disclosure may cause an adverse result, as defined in subsection (g). The presiding judge or magistrate judge may grant extensions of this order of up to 30 days each in accordance with this subsection, except that in no event shall the prohibition continue in force for more than a total of 9 months.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB8534F0BAAA4433FAD0000542E00DDB3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This subsection shall apply only in connection with compulsory process issued by the Commission where the recipient of such process is not a subject of the investigation or proceeding at the time such process is issued.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC11D4DF7AB52454B951F4C344BFE39B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>No order issued under this subsection shall prohibit any recipient from disclosing to a Federal agency that the recipient has received compulsory process from the Commission. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB5FD2FF316344B5F88B3C034593B6019"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No Liability for failure to notify</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If neither notification nor delayed notification by the Commission is required under the Right to Financial Privacy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3401">12 U.S.C. 3401 et seq.</external-xref>) or <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/121">chapter 121</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, the recipient of compulsory process issued by the Commission under this Act shall not be liable under any law or regulation of the United States, or under the constitution, or any law or regulation, of any State, political subdivision of a State, territory of the United States, or the District of Columbia, or under any contract or other legally enforceable agreement, for failure to provide notice to any person that such process has been issued or that the recipient has provided information in response to such process. The preceding sentence does not exempt any recipient from liability for—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA136DB8FE1FD409EBE00ED3008669416"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the underlying conduct reported;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8687F8231B564B2CBDB107EB5F80C28E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a failure to comply with the record retention requirements under section 1104(c) of the Right to Financial Privacy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3404">12 U.S.C. 3404</external-xref>), where applicable; or </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H19077A68F07E442EBCF41EE8F8B860AA"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any failure to comply with any obligation the recipient may have to disclose to a Federal agency that the recipient has received compulsory process from the Commission or intends to provide or has provided information to the Commission in response to such process. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAC775FCD4AA64B32AEDE084BB6C55100"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Venue and Procedure</header> 
<paragraph id="H371082F5C3E14DA9AFC2F6566BE3A4B6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All judicial proceedings initiated by the Commission under the Right to Financial Privacy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3401">12 U.S.C. 3401 et seq.</external-xref>), <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/121">chapter 121</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, or this section may be brought in the United States District Court for the District of Columbia or any other appropriate United States District Court. All ex parte applications by the Commission under this section related to a single investigation may be brought in a single proceeding. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFE021A9F34C2413600684BDBF0871FEF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>In camera proceedings</header><text>Upon application by the Commission, all judicial proceedings pursuant to this section shall be held in camera and the records thereof sealed until expiration of the period of delay or such other date as the presiding judge or magistrate judge may permit.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6B3E69BD55B84F2CA3AD6D91001600D3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Section Not To Apply to Antitrust Investigations or Proceedings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section shall not apply to an investigation or proceeding related to the administration of Federal antitrust laws or foreign antitrust laws as defined in paragraphs (5) and (7), respectively, of section 12 of the International Antitrust Enforcement Assistance Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/6211">15 U.S.C. 6211</external-xref>). </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA3F0CFDDFCE6414CBD2682A5AF8E9F9E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Adverse Result Defined</header><text>For purposes of this section the term <quote>adverse result</quote> means—</text> 
<paragraph id="H628BEF3AF8A6447AB5F17E5FF65EDB8E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">endangering the life or physical safety of an individual; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBC197608675D469195BE47CFC1A2A913"><enum>(2)</enum><text>flight from prosecution; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H32595591F5E24C22AB7147F0768E05B6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the destruction of, or tampering with, evidence; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H930E1545DEF2408398433473DE00CB1F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the intimidation of potential witnesses; or </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8AA0F67DA09A4A26845800E2A0574526"><enum>(5)</enum><text>otherwise seriously jeopardizing an investigation or proceeding related to fraudulent or deceptive commercial practices or persons involved in such practices, or unduly delaying a trial related to such practices or persons involved in such practices, including, but not limited to, by—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE5454D6FEE9E431992767397876CB22C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the transfer outside the territorial limits of the United States of assets or records related to fraudulent or deceptive commercial practices or related to persons involved in such practices; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0FF6D35B6DC547D98FD4BBE8F1F212C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>impeding the ability of the Commission to identify persons involved in fraudulent or deceptive commercial practices, or to trace the source or disposition of funds related to such practices; or </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H44D67E3F1DB24B36BE3D32FC5369896E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the dissipation, fraudulent transfer, or concealment of assets subject to recovery by the Commission.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection></section> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8B95CBD078B54E37B186E97E0276DDFA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 16(a)(2) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/56">15 U.S.C. 56(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H190D5668CCBE423387EE9B6BA3DAB578"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C) by striking <quote>or</quote> after the semicolon; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0B7BE5DFBB3B4310970073C37D6000CC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D) by inserting <quote>or</quote> after the semicolon; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H870B4EC0E0584E628047392E6060B60"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (D) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H48679CEC2FA74DBC975FB3524637B200" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="H6B8CDF37B57A405FA203E2E75EE0F335"><enum>(E)</enum><text>under section 21A of this Act;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H8A20BC85B11E46E2B308214CB9032B00"><enum>8.</enum><header>Protection for Voluntary Provision of information</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) is further amended by adding after section 21A (as added by section 7 of this Act) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA1CE5DD536DA4D2B874B7945D8B89A1" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H8C7AB310655C443894FC5693EEBA675E"><enum>21B.</enum><header>Protection for voluntary provision of information</header> 
<subsection id="H6B02A9ED75A04E4F9D38FD3D25E161E6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header> 
<paragraph id="H822864DA23CE405EB5E329559763EE6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>No liability for providing certain material</header><text>An entity described in paragraphs (2) or (3) of subsection (d) that voluntarily provides material to the Commission that such entity reasonably believes is relevant to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3FDB9FAED07E4E9499BF7E4FFE7813D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a possible unfair or deceptive act or practice, as defined in section 5(a) of this Act; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H864220142058484DADBAD583E1C35D6D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>assets subject to recovery by the Commission, including assets located in foreign jurisdictions;</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">shall not be liable to any person under any law or regulation of the United States, or under the constitution, or any law or regulation, of any State, political subdivision of a State, territory of the United States, or the District of Columbia, for such provision of material or for any failure to provide notice of such provision of material or of intention to provide material. </continuation-text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H524B926AA9074142B29BC28BAFCA04C9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to exempt any such entity from liability—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF8DB7ABFCF1A4233868C81976C43DB93"><enum>(A)</enum><text> for the underlying conduct reported; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB73AEB177AEB4E0EA02C66E124E845EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to any Federal agency for providing such material or for any failure to comply with any obligation the entity may have to notify a Federal agency prior to providing such material to the Commission.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H61DBAF7AEC4541E78C4500FCE1840439" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum></enum></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF2FC32D9B7FB40A0B4EEF7ACAF008E90"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certain financial institutions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity described in paragraph (1) of subsection (d) shall, in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/5318">section 5318(g)(3)</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code, be exempt from liability for making a voluntary disclosure to the Commission of any possible violation of law or regulation, including—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCFC1474489BC4DC5AD26657FE1907CEE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a disclosure regarding assets, including assets located in foreign jurisdictions—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9D3A173505A540F8B524F3D74662663B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>related to possibly fraudulent or deceptive commercial practices; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD88313AEF8AE43408672C38BFF88029"><enum>(B)</enum><text>related to persons involved in such practices; or </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD6258371568B4CDFA572DE2788FEB400"><enum>(C)</enum><text>otherwise subject to recovery by the Commission; or </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5C010D07C9F5445D90F3133E00832314"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a disclosure regarding suspicious chargeback rates related to possibly fraudulent or deceptive commercial practices.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBD1423E3B2DD484A98F781B6BC732B66"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consumer Complaints</header><text>Any entity described in subsection (d) that voluntarily provides consumer complaints sent to it, or information contained therein, to the Commission shall not be liable to any person under any law or regulation of the United States, or under the constitution, or any law or regulation, of any State, political subdivision of a State, territory of the United States, or the District of Columbia, for such provision of material or for any failure to provide notice of such provision of material or of intention to so provide material. This subsection shall not provide any exemption from liability for the underlying conduct.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H80475C3B8D11465799BAAD94AC44E6F9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application</header><text>This section applies to the following entities, whether foreign or domestic:</text> 
<paragraph id="H1CDA983774E14B750097EDB2CFE05052"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A financial institution as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/5312">section 5312</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC5E5F20AC72F4A6091C699AF4BCC9025"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To the extent not included in paragraph (1) a bank or thrift institution, a commercial bank or trust company, an investment company, a credit card issuer, an operator of a credit card system, and an issuer, redeemer, or cashier of travelers’ checks, money orders, or similar instruments.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA650F5B24C804AD7ADA4B57904ED9049"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A courier service, a commercial mail receiving agency, an industry membership organization, a payment system provider, a consumer reporting agency, a domain name registrar or registry acting as such, and a provider of alternative dispute resolution services.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE0B4B80BD4474B38AF58952E7B4390AE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An Internet service provider or provider of telephone services.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HAE43F632B3C145F19C95BC9D14A469D9"><enum>9.</enum><header>Staff Exchanges</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding after section 25 the following new section: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H636E9FF326044AFBADBB2CC567642E00" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="HE3B7BB8D0CE94824BE763D1D44B930F6"><enum>25A. </enum><header>Staff Exchanges</header> 
<subsection id="H8B409614321A463484F71351AE61C858"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>The Commission may—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF372CE417FAB4F6B9CCAE9ADCC809625"><enum>(1)</enum><text>retain or employ officers or employees of foreign government agencies on a temporary basis as employees of the Commission pursuant to section 2 of this Act, or section <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/3101">3101</external-xref> or section <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/3109">3109</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0A826201EC5D4891B16DF3CD923C909"><enum>(2)</enum><text>detail officers or employees of the Commission to work on a temporary basis for appropriate foreign government agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE40A4D2A0CAA451BA153C1EB3D92B704"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reciprocity and reimbursement</header><text>The staff arrangements described in subsections (a) need not be reciprocal. The Commission may accept payment or reimbursement, in cash or in kind, from a foreign government agency to which this section is applicable, or payment or reimbursement made on behalf of such agency, for expenses incurred by the Commission, its members, and employees in carrying out such arrangements.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H211774FD1CA84B74B0E8331D38A4DE88"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Standards of Conduct</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person appointed under subsection (a)(1) shall be subject to the provisions of law relating to ethics, conflicts of interest, corruption, and any other criminal or civil statute or regulation governing the standards of conduct for Federal employees that are applicable to the type of appointment.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H2BCBD71F05C8496B807D4DF7B8ACEB9B"><enum>10.</enum><header>Information sharing with financial regulators</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1112(e) of the Right to Financial Privacy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3412">12 U.S.C. 3412(e)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>the Federal Trade Commission,</quote> after <quote>the Securities and Exchange Commission,</quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HBA660EAF368E4841B99E67934EDB4CCD"><enum>11.</enum><header>Preservation of existing authority</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The authority provided by this Act, and by the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) and the Right to Financial Privacy Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/3401">12 U.S.C. 3401 et seq.</external-xref>), as such Acts are amended by this Act, is in addition to, and not in lieu of, any other authority vested in the Federal Trade Commission or any other officer of the United States.</text></section> 
<section id="H3115B81E35CB4251BCBAF1B63D09878"><enum>12.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Federal Trade Commission shall transmit to Congress a report describing its use of and experience with the authority granted by this Act, along with any recommendations for additional legislation. The report shall include—</text> 
<paragraph id="H31433B446DC94745A3C5AA08A77149E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of cross-border complaints received by the Commission;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H427BFB6BD96F45969DEB8F5042E1FB6D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identification of the foreign agencies to which the Commission has provided nonpublic investigative information under this Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBE0A53CB12664960B128B96612E6C0EE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the number of times the Commission has used compulsory process on behalf of foreign law enforcement agencies pursuant to section 6 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/46">15 U.S.C. 46</external-xref>), as amended by section 4 of this Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H89631E0D5F9B4252854E00FBA1D6901"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a list of international agreements and memoranda of understanding executed by the Commission that relate to this Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H07AD81D13817450C968863D828E38E39"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of times the Commission has sought delay of notice pursuant to section 21A of the Federal Trade Commission Act, as added by section 7 of this Act, and the number of times a court has granted a delay;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H43C9B1979AF043DFB7A9F2162583829"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a description of the types of information private entities have provided voluntarily pursuant to section 21B of the Federal Trade Commission Act, as added by section 8 of this Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8F7B9A4952764073A049BC526C4D42FD"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the results of cooperation with foreign law enforcement agencies under section 21 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57-2">15 U.S.C. 57–2</external-xref>) as amended by section 6 of this Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H403AFA49B13643D689AB67D8F6B7E3BB"><enum>(8)</enum><text>an analysis of whether the lack of an exemption from the disclosure requirements of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/552">section 552</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, with regard to information or material voluntarily provided relevant to possible unfair or deceptive acts or practices, has hindered the Commission in investigating or engaging in enforcement proceedings against such practices; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H074010EA9E254B6F9B99A0468E17C1B9"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of Commission litigation brought in foreign courts. </text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


