<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB5094C61418A475DADE273B27D43F8E2" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 3051 IH: Heroes at Home Act of
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-07-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 3051</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20070716">July 16, 2007</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001158">Mr. Salazar</sponsor> (for
			 himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="E000288">Mr. Ellison</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M000404">Mr. McDermott</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M000309">Mrs. McCarthy of New York</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M000590">Mr. McNulty</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="P000149">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="C001049">Mr. Clay</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000172">Mrs. Emerson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr.
			 Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000627">Mr.
			 Hinchey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="K000336">Mr. Kucinich</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="S001169">Mr. Sestak</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="B001227">Mr. Brady of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="L000554">Mr. LoBiondo</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="K000365">Mr. Kagen</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="E000287">Mr. Emanuel</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="S001174">Ms. Sutton</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="R000053">Mr. Rangel</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="H001039">Mr. Hall of New York</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="B000911">Ms. Corrine Brown of Florida</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M000933">Mr. Moran of Virginia</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="H000762">Ms. Hooley</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Linda T. Sánchez of California</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="S001165">Mr. Sires</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="U000039">Mr. Udall of New Mexico</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="W000215">Mr. Waxman</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Al Green of Texas</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="W000738">Ms. Woolsey</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="P000593">Mr. Perlmutter</cosponsor>, and
			 <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the
			 following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name>, and in
			 addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed
			 Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the
			 Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the
			 jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To improve the diagnosis and treatment of traumatic brain
		  injury in members and former members of the Armed Forces, to review and expand
		  telehealth and telemental health programs of the Department of Defense and the
		  Department of Veterans Affairs, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H2B7CDCF199B34188865BF8EE2580375B" style="OLC">
		<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCBA124CBDC914E6ABEB202F28B291D86" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Heroes at Home Act of
			 2007</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H6DF6765DB36B41BCA0356550E853B9C8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Training and
			 certification program for family caregiver personal care attendants for
			 veterans and members of the Armed Forces with traumatic brain injury</header>
			<subsection id="H484D310051D044A1B423B5D34B9D62D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program on
			 training and certification of family caregiver personal care
			 attendants</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall establish a
			 program on training and certification of family caregivers of veterans and
			 members of the Armed Forces with traumatic brain injury as personal care
			 attendants of such veterans and members.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H772B59E288CB47668D27E19B669800A7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Location</header><text>The
			 program required by subsection (a) shall be located in each of the medical
			 centers of the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H7C27CD3271D54791B53C2493F1369E6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Training
			 curricula</header>
				<paragraph id="H281CB411130E4C8AB333C0AF4DD280BC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall, in collaboration
			 with the Secretary of Defense, develop curricula for the training of personal
			 care attendants described in subsection (a). Such curricula shall incorporate
			 applicable standards and protocols utilized by certification programs of
			 national brain injury care specialist organizations.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H1EEDFDEFAA7849B294B727090351F75E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of existing
			 curricula</header><text>In developing the curricula required by paragraph (1),
			 the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall, to the extent practicable, utilize and
			 expand upon training curricula developed pursuant to section 744(b) of the John
			 Warner National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2007 (Public Law
			 109–364; 120 Stat. 2308).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBE706B14F4124ED08BCAECE6FFAF4C76"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Program
			 participation</header>
				<paragraph id="HE016A151833D471DB052C91843B14800"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall determine the
			 eligibility of a family member of a veteran or member of the Armed Forces for
			 participation in the program required by subsection (a).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H6FF70B32468A45F6BA0065B750922BF2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Basis for
			 determination</header><text>A determination made under paragraph (1) shall be
			 based on the clinical needs of the veteran or member of the Armed Forces
			 concerned, as determined by the physician of such veteran or member.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HA9229F4B6C1343F9A5632307BA007571"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Eligibility for
			 compensation</header><text>A family caregiver of a veteran or member of the
			 Armed Forces who receives certification as a personal care attendant under this
			 section shall be eligible for compensation from the Department of Veterans
			 Affairs for care provided to such veteran or member.</text>
			</subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H4EF26191A6894D68AC437FC8445FCF7E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Costs of
			 training</header>
				<paragraph commented="no" id="H1C6356E6C6D644F5B211B7A0AC534E87"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Training of
			 families of veterans</header><text>Any costs of training provided under the
			 program under this section for family members of veterans shall be borne by the
			 Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H84157C54B9D44101AEB10D3B24D3219"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Training of
			 families of members of the Armed Forces</header><text>The Secretary of Defense
			 shall reimburse the Secretary of Veterans Affairs for any costs of training
			 provided under the program under this section for family members of members of
			 the Armed Forces. Amounts for such reimbursement shall be derived from amounts
			 available for Defense Health Program for the TRICARE program.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HAAD2D183DBEE471D9416E4BBF7F54C2"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>Nothing
			 in this section shall be construed to require or permit the Secretary of
			 Veterans Affairs to deny reimbursement for health care services provided to a
			 veteran with a brain injury to a personal care attendant who is not a family
			 member of such veteran.</text>
			</subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC72668A26B154081B1093CB0392EE1EA" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Outreach and public
			 awareness</header>
			<subsection id="H27FFC6DAF76D4A5AACC4F52762C990D8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Outreach
			 required</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct
			 comprehensive outreach to enhance the awareness of veterans and the general
			 public about the symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder and traumatic brain
			 injury and the services provided by the Department of Veterans Affairs to
			 veterans with such symptoms.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HBA356335F79D49B8B7E19803F4FF7B9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Provision of best
			 practices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of
			 Veterans Affairs shall make available to non-Department of Veterans Affairs
			 health practitioners the best practices developed by the Department for the
			 treatment of traumatic brain injury and post-traumatic stress disorder.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HA8142CA928D84F67B3F300230520C266"><enum>4.</enum><header>Telehealth and
			 telemental health services of the Department of Defense and the Department of
			 Veterans Affairs</header>
			<subsection id="HB4F02E1BF9C74E9887F8F6C0A402E800"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Telehealth and
			 telemental health demonstration project</header>
				<paragraph id="H733395422267429ABBE936A749668C56"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans
			 Affairs shall jointly establish a demonstration project to assess the
			 feasibility and advisability of using telehealth technology to assess cognitive
			 (including memory) functioning of members and former members of the Armed
			 Forces who have sustained head trauma, in order to improve the diagnosis and
			 treatment of traumatic brain injury.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H474E25F47323461BB5FC2127CF6B0408"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Location</header>
					<subparagraph id="H403FF948E7194EB89E5EC94D8C00CF7B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans
			 Affairs shall carry out the demonstration project required by paragraph (1) at
			 one or more locations selected by the Secretaries for purposes of the
			 demonstration project.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H71D98CCF8B7440C5A4ED0088497D2C5C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Priority for
			 rural areas</header><text>In selecting locations to carry out the demonstration
			 project required by paragraph (1), the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary
			 of Veterans Affairs shall give priority to locations that would provide service
			 in a rural area.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0ACB82567C8F4CDEAC008EEEF54E13E1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The
			 demonstration project required by paragraph (1) shall include the
			 following:</text>
					<subparagraph id="H476CCC7593AC4505AB137F9B728F364D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The use of
			 telehealth technology to assess the cognitive (including memory) functioning of
			 a member or former member of the Armed Forces, including the following:</text>
						<clause id="H23DD28AAD7874102947E002712898D44"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Obtaining
			 information regarding the nature of any brain injury incurred by such member or
			 former member.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H639CB177FBC14F89B3285DDB0668B96"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Assessing any
			 symptoms of traumatic brain injury in such member or former member.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF46F60F9BCE84A9390B7E0DAABC6EEA4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The use of
			 telehealth technology to rehabilitate members or former members of the Armed
			 Forces who have traumatic brain injury, and the use, to the extent practicable,
			 of applicable standards and protocols used by certification programs of
			 national brain injury care specialist organizations in order to assess progress
			 in such rehabilitation.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08EC145309694FAFB6AB3CB956E3600"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The use of
			 telehealth technology to disseminate education material to members and former
			 members of the Armed Forces and the family members of such members on
			 techniques, strategies, and skills for caring for and assisting such members,
			 and to the extend practicable, such education materials shall incorporate
			 training curricula developed pursuant to section 744(b) of the John Warner
			 National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/364">Public Law 109–364</external-xref>;
			 120 Stat. 2308).</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB96EF0C25EED4E68AAED6CCF18479DD5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Use of proven
			 technologies</header><text>Any assessment administered as a part of the
			 demonstration project required by paragraph (1) shall incorporate telemental
			 health technology that has proven effective in the diagnosis and treatment of
			 mental health conditions associated with traumatic brain injury.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H8231C4A17E6A4E32A026574B39B343AC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Administration</header>
					<subparagraph id="H3B44330BF23C4264BDC3C539F1ACD8DE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The demonstration project required by paragraph (1) shall
			 be administered under the joint incentives program and carried out pursuant to
			 <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/8111">section 8111(d)</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F85B0077A444486900012DFB680425F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>Amounts
			 to carry out the demonstration project shall be derived from amounts in the
			 DOD–VA Health Care Sharing Incentive Fund established under paragraph (2) of
			 such section.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF06EE67BC34C4417BAC8D51CC24F0CF"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Report</header>
					<subparagraph id="HBE759B3FEB514FABAE00E920949FDB90"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans
			 Affairs shall jointly submit to Congress a report on the demonstration project
			 required by paragraph (1).</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57BC7B1206FA4B37A7008876084CD8DA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Submission with
			 annual joint report</header><text>The report required by subparagraph (A) shall
			 be submitted to Congress at the same time as the annual joint report required
			 by <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/8111">section 8111(f)</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, for the fiscal year
			 following the fiscal year of the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0FB3E93BBB954692ABFC06A50407096F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ongoing study on
			 telehealth and telemental health services</header>
				<paragraph id="H8A764E70035F4ADCB160A439337EB430"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of
			 Defense and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall, through the Joint
			 Executive Council (JEC) of the Department of Defense and the Department of
			 Veterans Affairs, conduct an ongoing study of all matters relating to the
			 telehealth and telemental health services of the Department of Defense and the
			 Department of Veterans Affairs.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H84A40AC3C6404D3E80F56B003F5DE2A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matters
			 studied</header><text>The matters studied under paragraph (1) shall include the
			 following:</text>
					<subparagraph id="H5279BD689A4A4F74B3325D34A03101D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The number of
			 members and former members of the Armed Forces who have used telehealth or
			 telemental health services of the Department of Defense or the Department of
			 Veterans Affairs.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB9C284C9BAB47929EE3BD5FA8FECCDD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The extent to
			 which members of the National Guard and the Reserves are utilizing telehealth
			 or telemental health services of the Department of Defense or the Department of
			 Veterans Affairs.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB120C6905531406F90DD2EC3FF4F7EA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The ways in which
			 the Department of Defense and the Department of Veterans Affairs can improve
			 the integration of telehealth and telemental health services with clinical
			 medicine.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C75D33BE2974E83B6E84FCB45C7CB2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The extent to which
			 telehealth and telemental health services of the Department of Defense and the
			 Department of Veterans Affairs are provided in rural settings and through
			 community-based outpatient clinics (CBOCs).</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15495854754F43A79FFD5F9B035E2B2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Best practices of
			 civilian mental health providers and facilities with respect to the provision
			 of telehealth and telemental health services, including how such practices can
			 be adopted to improve telehealth and telemental health services of the
			 Department of Defense and the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8293532764C64746A9F1FB47483E265E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The feasability
			 and advisability of partnering with civilian mental health facilities to
			 provide telehealth and telemental health services to members and former members
			 of the Armed Forces.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFCCD80A4F8AD46379DD651B1F9E8FA7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Annual
			 reports</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment
			 of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Defense and the
			 Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall jointly submit to Congress a report on the
			 findings of the Joint Executive Counsel under this subsection during the
			 preceding year.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H095CF9A2D8134AEBA263DA8300342E26"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
			<paragraph id="H5722C9A0CE914A668D4328C11353DF74"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>national brain injury care specialist organization</term> means a
			 national organization or association with demonstrated experience in providing
			 training, education, and technical assistance in the provision of care for
			 individuals with brain injury.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HAEC27E70F979459B8E459CEABB47066"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>neurocognitive</term> means of, relating to, or involving the central
			 nervous system and cognitive or information processing abilities (thinking,
			 memory, and reasoning), as well as sensory processing (sight, hearing, touch,
			 taste, and smell), and communication (expression and understanding).</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HE88E06AA34A74F4DB7781D05325BA59E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>traumatic brain injury</term> means an acquired injury to the brain,
			 including brain injuries caused by anoxia due to trauma and such other injuries
			 as the Secretary considers appropriate, except that such term excludes brain
			 dysfunction caused by—</text>
				<subparagraph id="H3E754FC2C71046A5B13CDC33192902EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>congenital or
			 degenerative disorders; or</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H516D1847A5FA4B1DA4DFC9BA23A31F61"><enum>(B)</enum><text>birth
			 trauma.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body>
</bill>


