<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB2C7B4244A6F4FC0A1F23B963617A448" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>109 HR 1207 IH: Department of Veterans Affairs Work-Study Act of 2005</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2005-03-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>109th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 1207</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20050309">March 9, 2005</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001148">Mr. Simpson</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to provide additional work-study opportunities for eligible veterans, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H7B1D03B50D7D4DE8853B70E3316ACBE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA6760413B4F8463C8B6E00BEE000FCD9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Department of Veterans Affairs Work-Study Act of 2005</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H08041E6BB0764F7BAA6133E734958068" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Provision of additional areas of work-study for veterans</header> 
<subsection id="H6D1555018A3A48C48600C4A7574D4DDA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (a)(4) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/3485">section 3485</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraphs:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H37E13A0E15AB4E6A94CAA92FEE673963"> 
<subparagraph indent="up1" id="H980F28950CE149AEA47367B517E3B96C"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The provision of placement services described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/3104">section 3104(a)(5)</external-xref> of this title at an educational institution carried out under the supervision of a Department employee.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph indent="up1" id="H0BF3680FCAE84E5089DE2627F37076BE"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The provision of counseling and assistance in identifying employment and training opportunities, help in obtaining such employment and training, and other related information and services to members of the Armed Forces who are being separated from active duty, and the spouses of such members, under the Transition Assistance Program and Disabled Transition Assistance Program established in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1144">section 1144</external-xref> of title 10, carried out under the supervision of disabled veterans’ outreach program specialists or local veterans’ employment representatives under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/41">chapter 41</external-xref> of this title.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0F4DFC77EF5C437CB527605D814756BB" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Any activity approved by the Secretary in support of a Senior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps program at an educational institution or on a military installation carried out under the supervision of an administrator or instructor referred to in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2111">section 2111</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB4B9B3D1C49842959EADF41018787BB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to agreements entered into under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/3485">section 3485</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HF5AD8A84D3A4480284F7089E5B3C8BB7" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>5-year pilot program for on-campus work-study positions</header> 
<subsection id="H192DE2836C4B472DA62B147E64FA8606" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of pilot program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct a five-year pilot project to test the feasibility and advisability of expanding the scope of qualifying work-study activities under subsection (a)(4) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/3485">section 3485</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, to include work-study positions available on site at educational institutions.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD2E45FF3913E4BB187DE74362D4C6705" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Type of work-study positions</header><text>The work-study positions referred to in subsection (a) may include positions in academic departments (such as tutors or research, teaching, and lab assistants) and in student services (such as career centers, financial aid, campus orientation, cashiers, admissions, records and registration).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE057FB4B19564828B8942699D7122F77" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements</header> 
<paragraph id="H084A48F2E358404D983FEAFCA71DCDCE" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Approval of position by the secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No payment may be made under the pilot project for a work-study position referred to in subsection (a) unless the Secretary of Veterans Affairs has approved the work-study position offered by educational institution based on an application submitted to the Secretary by the institution for such purpose containing such information and meeting such requirements as the Secretary may specify.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H69121DE7C12849B8879818C6B5579800" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>All other qualifying work-study activities are filled</header><text>Before a work-study position referred to in subsection (a) may be filled by an applicant under the pilot project, the applicant shall demonstrate to the Secretary that there is no position in a qualifying work-study activity under subparagraphs (A) through (I) of section 3845(a)(4) of such title in which the applicant may work during the applicable agreement period.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H72FDA2638B0F4E138FD26E9CC17566FC" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation on number of positions</header><text>In conducting the pilot program, the Secretary shall ensure that no more than 10 percent of all work-study agreements under section 3485 of such title at any time are for work-study positions provided for under the pilot project.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC2900AC1F3524D93ABFA516C67F3B00" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Maintenance of numbers and types of work-study opportunities offered by educational institutions</header><text>The Secretary may not enter into an agreement for a work-study position referred to in subsection (a) unless the educational institution involved demonstrates that the number and types of work-study positions offered by the educational institution during the year preceding the year in which the Secretary conducts the pilot project is not less than such number and type offered during the pilot project.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0FECE872C60C40368F7B66B6D0A7BD46" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall prescribe regulations to carry out the pilot project under this section, including regulations providing for the supervision of work-study positions referred to in subsection (a) by appropriate personnel.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1731415C3188432195E40013E936E41D" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary $1,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2006 through 2010 to carry out the pilot project under this section.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H5C43856212E245F4BD447C8FEE70C93B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Technical corrections</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/3484">Section 3484</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HAEBD4FC42E9145B4A3A94EDA00FABC54"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1)(E), by inserting <quote>or 1607</quote> after <quote>chapter 1606</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF6BDB374616142E4BEEB9F1843DA6915"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>chapter 106</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 1606 or 1607</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H21FE8AAFE9C041CA94B27EFB10B6C004"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC97B740A11DA4CAD0035D50568B74834"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>services of the kind described in clauses (A) through (E) of subsection (a)(1) of this section</quote> and inserting <quote>a qualifying work-study activity described in subsection (a)(4)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7122EA76F85947A1965E8F4C2344FF2E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>chapter 106</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 1606 or 1607</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


