<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H37885ECA6D614237B7E2F200701DDDBA" public-private="public" star-print="no-star-print">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 2768 EH: S–MINER Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 2768</legis-num>
		<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF
		  REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To establish improved mandatory standards
		  to protect miners during emergencies, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="HB42E0B23D59D492395AF474359C42675" style="OLC">
		<section id="HD5EC187C2AEC4EBA922811FF3FBE0009" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of
			 contents</header>
			<subsection id="HE1FFBF6CD0B4438A96E0A140CCCC58CB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short
			 title</header><text>This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supplemental Mine Improvement and New Emergency Response
			 Act of 2007</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>S–MINER Act</short-title></quote>.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HA1F96428A8E54F7DBA588C47F753A3A2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of
			 contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
				<toc container-level="legis-body-container" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration">
					<toc-entry idref="HD5EC187C2AEC4EBA922811FF3FBE0009" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H530E80C3ACF84484AE26EC9427C0184D" level="section">Sec. 2. Findings.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H071CD48F20534B8BB15642E36E125336" level="section">Sec. 3. Definitions; references.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H9A13E5CBFD1C42B099164E35E994B8F1" level="section">Sec. 4. Supplementing emergency response plans.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H58125A8F411A4F078331347225979BDE" level="section">Sec. 5. Supplementing enforcement authority.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HF72547EBB4CF41748DAE23267B685153" level="section">Sec. 6. Supplementing rescue, recovery, and incident
				investigation authority.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H047E3E03A4B3447C871282E650E61877" level="section">Sec. 7. Respirable Dust Standards.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HC66D19920934487700DB80D2AE7C00" level="section">Sec. 8. Other health requirements.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HE2F364ACFCE3402B91B733F87D5EA85" level="section">Sec. 9. Mine safety program fund.</toc-entry>
				</toc>
			</subsection></section><section id="H530E80C3ACF84484AE26EC9427C0184D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text>
			<paragraph id="H711E8F52581C4CAF8F7166C58439D875"><enum>(1)</enum><text>while the MINER
			 Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/236">Public Law 109–236</external-xref>) was an essential first step in addressing the
			 many health and safety hazards that miners still face, supplemental action is
			 necessary and feasible to better protect miners in coal and other mines;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H20188DF09B5E40B4AAF8E47017938747"><enum>(2)</enum><text>essential
			 standards to protect miner health established by the Federal Mine Safety and
			 Health Act of 1977 are out of date after 40 years, posing a significant threat
			 to miner health; and</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H44A1E4877E184548AF1123B77ED546D9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Secretary of
			 Labor has failed in recent years to adequately fulfill the Secretary’s
			 obligations under the Federal Mine Safety and Health Act of 1977 (30 U.S.C. 801
			 et seq.), additional Congressional intervention is needed.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H071CD48F20534B8BB15642E36E125336"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions;
			 references</header>
			<subsection id="H0D659AC324AF40E28519B1283D70D32"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>As
			 used in this Act—</text>
				<paragraph id="H93CB4518753A4B49B3471660558742CC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term
			 <term>Secretary</term> refers to the Secretary of Labor; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HB754CFFA4B96473593A0D8B78443A800"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any other term
			 used in this Act that is defined in section 3 of the Federal Mine Safety and
			 Health Act of 1977 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/802">30 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>) shall have the meaning given the term in
			 such section.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H252FF827300848CA997FFD23B168F14F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>References</header><text>Except
			 as otherwise expressly provided, whenever in this Act an amendment or repeal is
			 expressed in terms of an amendment to, or repeal of, a section or other
			 provision, the reference shall be considered to be made to a section or other
			 provision of the Federal Mine Safety and Health Act of 1977 (30 U.S.C. 801 et
			 seq.).</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H9A13E5CBFD1C42B099164E35E994B8F1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Supplementing
			 emergency response plans</header>
			<subsection id="HFB30FE547D9E46559DC69DC50004AC25"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Post accident
			 communications</header><text>Section 316(b)(2)(F)(ii) (30 U.S.C.
			 876(b)(2)(F)(ii)) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="HBA6273192EA9441FBB98D735000510E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>Not later than</quote> and inserting the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H98AC9852B338444A894ECC62A4785BEF" style="OLC">
						<subclause id="H619C020DCF7E4427BB1CD877488C26B0"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later
				than</text>
						</subclause><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H5FC5694E5C3B44F4BCA20C7CBBD1F68"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by
			 inserting after the clause designation the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBF83286A2BCD46DCA9E9DBA7762D51B6" style="OLC">
						<subclause id="H92573712926E4B60A37700C0C9CBAD96"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Not later than 120
				days after the enactment of the S–MINER Act, a plan shall, to be in approved
				status, provide for a post accident communication system between underground
				and surface personnel, and for an electronic tracking system permitting surface
				personnel to determine the location of any persons trapped underground, that
				utilizes a system at least as effective as a <quote>leaky feeder</quote> or
				wireless mesh type communication and tracking system currently in use in the
				industry. These systems shall be enhanced physically, electronically, or
				redundantly, to improve their survivability in the event of a mine disaster. In
				addition, to be in approved status, an emergency response plan must be revised
				promptly to incorporate new technology which the National Institute for
				Occupational Safety and Health certifies can be added to the existing system to
				improve its ability to facilitate post-accident communication with or tracking
				of miners. No miner shall be disciplined based on information obtained from an
				electronic communications and tracking
				system.</text>
						</subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H994797483A7543E9B3B087D18D86D6E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Underground
			 refuges</header><text>Section 316(b)(2)(E) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/876">30 U.S.C. 876(b)(2)(E)</external-xref>) is
			 amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H54E73DBE955E4020BADC88337634A479"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause
			 (iii)(I), by inserting before the semicolon the following: <quote>and such
			 requirement may not be satisfied by placement of an order with any company for
			 future delivery of a portable refuge chamber or other means of providing such
			 emergency supplies of breathable air</quote>; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H9D6F187478414A2B86B304E0DFC0D592"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the
			 end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="HA562EBA2923C4460A7B97533F8BDE6F" style="OLC">
						<clause id="H9F7517ABBD8C406894E61303D3BA1751"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than June 15, 2008, the Secretary
				shall issue interim final regulations, consistent with the design criteria
				recommended by National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health in its
				report pursuant to section 13(b)(1) of the MINER Act, and subject to the
				requirements of the next sentence, requiring each emergency response plan to
				provide for the installation of portable rescue chambers meeting National
				Institute for Occupational Safety and Health design criteria; refuge shelters
				carved out of the mine workings and sealed with bulkheads meeting National
				Institute for Occupational Safety and Health design criteria; or other refuge
				designs recommended by National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health
				that provide miners with equivalent or better protection, in the working areas
				of underground coal mines within 60 days following plan approval. The
				regulations shall further provide that in all cases a portable refuge chamber
				shall be installed and maintained within 500 feet of the nearest working face
				in each working section of an underground coal
				mine.</text>
						</clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0F4BBBF899F24732BD6FA73009EDCB9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Improvements to
			 seals, ventilation controls, and rock dusting to limit the damage from
			 explosions</header>
				<paragraph id="H5DAFFEAA8FA2492AB13BE474E8832CE0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Repeal</header><text>The
			 MINER Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/801">30 U.S.C. 801</external-xref> note) is amended by striking section 10 (concerning
			 sealing of abandoned areas).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H1F7D900536104463958D3B4858E4C7FF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Seals</header><text>Section
			 303(z) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/863">30 U.S.C. 863(z)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H15391C21A2F94700B24B6838E1006045" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="HB2B47819E13742D192835FDA82B63099" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H71F4F0F62E8746C880821EFE680051EE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall inspect all seals under
				construction after the date of enactment of the S–MINER Act, during at least
				part of their construction, to ensure the mine operator is complying with the
				approved seal plan, and shall develop an inspection protocol for this
				purpose.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6390B377FAEF483E836C6C577CF16384" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Not later than 3 months of the date
				of enactment of the S–MINER Act, the Secretary shall issue final rules
				regarding approval, design, construction, inspection, maintenance and
				monitoring of underground coal mine seals which shall meet the requirements of
				this paragraph. Except as otherwise provided by this paragraph, these
				regulations shall implement the most recent recommendations of the National
				Institute of Occupational Safety and Health concerning seal design,
				construction, inspection, maintenance and monitoring. The regulations shall
				also provide that all seals in a mine shall be monitored if they are not
				designed or installed to withstand a constant total pressure of 240 pounds per
				square inch, using a static structural analysis. Monitoring of seals shall be
				done by continuous monitoring devices within one year of the date of enactment
				of this Act, and prior thereto by qualified personnel at such intervals as the
				Secretary determines are adequate to ensure safety. The Secretary shall require
				mine operators to utilize a tamper-resistant method to retain records of all
				such monitoring and ensure they are available for examination and verification
				by the agency. Monitoring of seals shall be done both by—</text>
								<clause id="H1121CE7F952E468084A247DC1354691"><enum>(i)</enum><text>sampling through at least 1 seal in
				each bank of seals; and</text>
								</clause><clause id="HD666BDE9A6D94ED4BF7E146EBE7107E0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for new seals, unless infeasible due
				to property rights, sampling through a sufficient number of boreholes from the
				surface to the sealed areas underground to effectively determine the gas
				concentrations within the area.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H858A1F2555F74CB6B19743AB85E06518" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition, the regulations shall provide
				that—</text>
								<clause id="H2241AC61B6A84185833198986B69721F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>seal sampling pipes shall be composed
				of materials that minimize the risk of transmitting any electrical charge, and
				no conductive materials may be used to line boreholes within three feet of the
				surface;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HA206D67EC1934CF2878F28BAC32955F9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an action plan for sealing and repair
				be established that will, among any other requirements, include specific
				actions the mine operator will take to protect miners during the critical time
				period immediately after sealing or repair takes place, and which shall be
				reviewed by personnel from the Mine Safety and Health Administration who have
				the required expertise prior to approval; and</text>
								</clause><clause id="H9D79321B16C64517B976BDBCDF3CEBE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>methane pressures behind any seal
				required to be monitored shall be maintained in such a manner as ensure that
				normal pressure variations that can be reasonably anticipated in the area of
				the seal do not bring the methane-air mixture into an appropriate safety range
				surrounding the known explosive range of such
				mixtures.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HB61BAA5D30E647308B40F2811BED006E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Ventilation
			 controls</header><text>Section 303(c) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/863">30 U.S.C. 863</external-xref>) is amended by inserting
			 at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H0E97A5A9F1B14B57B29E8393C8E777E4" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="H3EFDC194C3D540C19762918BAA97C43E" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Not later than 1 year after the date
				of enactment of the S–MINER Act, the Secretary shall publish interim final
				regulations to enhance the survivability of underground mine ventilation
				controls. The Secretary shall require that stoppings be constructed using solid
				concrete blocks laid wet and sealed with an appropriate bonding agent on at
				least the side subjected to the velocity of the intake air coursing through the
				entry, except that in the case of stoppings constructed during barrier
				reduction and pillar removal operations, such stoppings may be constructed
				using hollow block and an appropriate bonding
				agent.</text>
						</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H106C4FD39A7B42A99B1D69AE14002345"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rock
			 dusting</header><text>Section 304(d) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/864">30 U.S.C. 864</external-xref>) is amended by adding at
			 the end the following: <quote>Not later than June 15, 2009, the National
			 Institute for Occupational Safety and Health shall issue recommendations as to
			 whether changes to these requirements are necessary to ensure an equivalent
			 level of protection in light of any changes to the size and composition of coal
			 dust since these requirements were established, and the Secretary of Labor
			 shall take appropriate action, including the issuance of an emergency temporary
			 standard if warranted, to respond to these recommendations.</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD2F4B4188C7140C3B16D50D667639F76"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limiting
			 conveyor belt risks</header>
				<paragraph id="H16C8969DCD01460EBF02E288F4AE54AF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Flame resistant
			 conveyor belts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 311(h)
			 is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H10D0072A9BD4431F857E21C083E38CC4" style="OLC">
						<text>Not later than 90 days after the date of
			 enactment of the S–MINER Act, the Secretary shall publish interim final rules
			 to revise the requirements for flame resistant conveyor belts to ensure that
			 they meet the most recent recommendations from the National Institute for
			 Occupational Safety and Health, and to ensure such belts are designed to limit
			 smoke and toxic emissions. A conveyor belt need not meet the requirements of
			 the preceding sentence if—</text><subparagraph id="HD9D4C1169FAF4C86892BF9D5BF3BA1FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>it was ordered, in
				a mine’s inventory, or installed prior to the date of enactment of the S–MINER
				Act, or it was ordered after the date of enactment of the S–MINER Act and the
				Secretary certifies that the mine operator was unable to obtain a belt meeting
				the requirements of the preceding sentence; or</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1768C7A252B345F39EF330588CE5AC00"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of any
				such belt that has been in use for more than 5 years in any capacity in any
				mine, such belt has received an annual inspection by a certified professional
				to ensure that the belt is free from visible defects that could cause failure
				or possible
				ignition.</text>
						</subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HD8DC0341F0C148308FC7F8069DF6F867"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Belt
			 air</header><text>Section 303(y) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/863">30 U.S.C. 863</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the
			 end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H1A18C5D06889464A9DD1DCC4F7145FBB" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="H25598C21A9104DB2BA518D4406487875" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Not later than June 20, 2008, the
				Secretary shall revise the regulations prescribed pursuant to this section to
				require, in any coal mine, regardless of the date on which it was opened, that
				belt haulage entries not be used to ventilate active working places. The
				Secretary may agree to a modification of this requirement, pursuant to the
				procedures of section 101(c), if and only if—</text>
							<subparagraph id="HA6AA32BBA3644A948515EE91C830AD72"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the mine operator establishes to the
				satisfaction of the Secretary that significant safety constraints require such
				usage; and</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09EA3745E0B84DB7BE35C3C662AF2073"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the mine operator agrees to comply
				with criteria established by the Secretary which shall, at a minimum, include
				the conditions recommended by the Technical Study Panel established under
				section 514.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H96967CC126364BE3003728F6DEC0CA7F" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Plans that have been approved by the
				Secretary prior to the date of enactment of the S–MINER Act that permit the use
				of belt-air to ventilate active working places in a mine are permitted to
				remain in use to complete current mining up until the date of issuance of the
				regulation required pursuant to paragraph
				(3).</text>
						</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8A481D69614E4F6D9D57CA40245F31D7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Pre-shift review
			 of mine conditions</header><text>Section 303(d) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/863">30 U.S.C. 863(d)</external-xref>) is amended
			 by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block id="HB6C62851E4BE44A59044827E5D73E8F1" style="OLC">
					<paragraph id="HD59F89B76AA64D0298464F439E278EBA" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of
				enactment of the S–MINER Act, all mine operators shall be required to implement
				a communication program at each of such operators’ facilities to ensure that
				each person entering the operation is made aware at the start of that person’s
				shift of the current conditions of the mine in general and of that person’s
				specific worksite in particular. In an effort to facilitate these
				communications, all agents of the operator who are responsible for ensuring the
				safe and healthful working conditions at the mine, including mine foremen,
				assistant mine foremen, and mine examiners, shall, upon exiting the mine or
				workplace, communicate with those replacing them on duty to verbally update
				them on the conditions they observed during their shift, including any
				conditions that are abnormal or hazardous. Prior to entering the mine or other
				workplace the on-coming agent of the operator shall meet with all members of
				the crew they are responsible for and inform them of the general conditions at
				the operation and in their specific work area. This process shall be completed
				prior to the start of each shift at the operation and recorded in a book
				designated for that purpose and available for inspection by all interested
				parties. In the event the operation is idle prior to the start of any shift the
				agent of the operator shall meet with the individual or individuals who were
				responsible for examining the mine to obtain the necessary
				information.</text>
					</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H9E3CFF84D14C47EEA9C4E7E7BACBB7C6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Atmospheric
			 monitoring systems</header><text>Section 317 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/877">30 U.S.C. 877</external-xref>) is amended by
			 adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="HD43A863572894553ABB2F10A800E32B" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="HE33D9E11C33243649DB8001F477E3396"><enum>(u)</enum><text>Not later than May
				1, 2008, an operator of an underground mine shall install atmospheric
				monitoring systems in all underground areas where miners normally work and
				travel that provide real-time information regarding carbon monoxide levels, and
				that can, to the maximum extent possible, withstand explosions and
				fires.</text>
					</subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HDBEBF42D9F994784A2A3D5B400777E5E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Methane
			 monitors</header><text>Section 303(h) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/863">30 U.S.C. 863(h)</external-xref>) is amended by
			 redesignating paragraph (2) as paragraph (3), and inserting after paragraph (1)
			 the following new paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block id="HF1699BC817FA4B8A8D3F61088514C1B5" style="OLC">
					<paragraph id="H4F4C1EAFF1EB48B7AB9800080067AC90" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each miner who is working alone for
				part of a shift shall be equipped with a multi-gas detector that measures
				current levels of methane, oxygen, and carbon
				monoxide.</text>
					</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H2940C10633E8430488ACAE899648E43B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Lightning study
			 by national academy of sciences</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the
			 date of enactment of this Act, the National Academy of Sciences shall submit to
			 the Secretary and to Congress recommendations on—</text>
				<paragraph id="H52C21C0A36F743DE9D00BE2DC2FE6F89"><enum>(1)</enum><text>actions that need
			 to be taken to strengthen existing requirements in law or regulations to ensure
			 that miners are protected, to the fullest extent permitted, from the risks of
			 lightning strikes near a mine;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HFBE792D7BA114A9E0038654FE8106CD2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations
			 for adopting any existing technology to the mining environment to minimize any
			 such risks; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HF861D981B46A427FB53FC36EA3C71617"><enum>(3)</enum><text>research needed
			 for improved technology.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H492893BB98F947EBB0ED65ED8BE7FB40"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Roof and rib
			 support, barrier reduction and pillar extraction, special attention to deep
			 mining</header>
				<paragraph id="H646B3FFBE5B54D11A6A3BA1436DF00C5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amendments to
			 existing law</header><text>Section 302 is amended—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H8ED554FBB0104F7A930091AF0167AB10"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by amending the
			 section heading to read <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="traditional">Roof and rib support, barrier reduction and pillar
			 extraction, special attention to deep mining</header-in-text></quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H928404BEE333433682EE78EE329CB4CD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (a),
			 by inserting after the second sentence the following: <quote>The Secretary
			 shall by regulation ensure the appropriate use of roof screen in belt entries,
			 travelroads, and designated intake and return escapeways in accordance with the
			 requirements of subsection (g).</quote>; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57C9AF9ED5894C38B82E40A72E4FE1B4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting at
			 the end the following:</text>
						<quoted-block id="H9C1391BDC56F4CF9B8AE4377B2E73AD" style="OLC">
							<subsection id="HED27B73B02A347D2BA710422A3EB4118"><enum>(g)</enum><text>Where screening is
				required, at least forty percent of the width of the exposed roof shall be
				screened. Screening to meet the requirements of this section must have a load
				bearing capacity at least equivalent to a load of 2.5 tones between bolts on a
				4 foot pattern.</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="H049BD424E8994E4C9BF5EEE5FAD1F21"><enum>(h)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5D0913D07D4449E2B7A6C232F3528320"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An operator shall be
				required to have a current and approved barrier reduction or pillar extraction
				plan, or both, before performing such activities. The Secretary shall only
				approve a barrier reduction or pillar extraction plan if it provides adequate
				protection and minimizes the risks for miners engaged in the activity,
				reflecting appropriate engineering analysis, computer simulations, and
				consultations with technical experts in the agency, in the National Institute
				for Occupational Safety and Health, and in the Bureau of Land Management for
				any mines leasing Federal coal resources, and only if the plan complies with
				any specific requirements that may be adopted by the Secretary for barrier
				reduction or pillar extraction activities including requirements related to the
				depth of the mine, geology of the mine, mine height and methods, and emergency
				response capabilities.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HF481D10C48584550BF889F4D5264DC17" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A
				copy of a proposed barrier reduction or pillar extraction plan, or both, shall
				be provided to the authorized representative of miners at least 10 days prior
				to submission to the Secretary for approval. The authorized representative of
				miners may provide comments to the Secretary who shall respond thereto.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HAB33EEB78C064DFE9C81AFB0A34367F4" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Secretary shall establish a
				special internal review process for operator plans to protect miners from the
				risks addressed by this section when working at depths of more than 1500 feet
				and in other mines with a history of mountain bumps.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H614A6C4311E642E0009C0052BD3E3D5B"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 week before the
				commencement of any barrier reduction or pillar extraction operations, the mine
				operator shall notify the appropriate representative of the Secretary of his
				intention to begin or resume barrier reduction or pillar extraction. The
				Secretary shall document such notification in writing, and shall, before
				barrier reduction or pillar extraction operations begin, take action to ensure
				that every person who will be participating in such operations is trained in
				the operator’s barrier reduction and/or and pillar extraction plan. The
				Secretary shall observe the barrier reduction or pillar extraction operations
				for a sufficient period of time to ensure that the mine operator is fully
				complying with the barrier reduction or pillar extraction plan. The Secretary
				may preclude the commencement of such operations or halt such operations at any
				time the safety of miners comes into
				question.</text>
							</subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BD20D75DB0B465080ACB601E2A26774"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of
			 enactment of this Act, the National Academy of Sciences shall, in consultation
			 with the National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health, submit to the
			 Secretary and to Congress recommendations for—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HD838AA97987846E196731FE74BB17200"><enum>(A)</enum><text>actions that need
			 to be taken to strengthen existing requirements in law or regulations to ensure
			 that miners are protected, to the fullest extent permitted, from ground control
			 hazards, including the special hazards associated with barrier reduction and
			 pillar extraction;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC18787833E6B495A91775734D257138B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>adopting any
			 existing technology to the mining environment to improve miner protections
			 during barrier reduction and pillar extraction, and on research needed for
			 improved technology to improve miner protections during such operations;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08C0EF98EF284007AC5E6F00F1BE3852"><enum>(C)</enum><text>adopting any
			 existing technology to the mining environment to improve miner protections
			 during mining at depths below 1000 feet, and on research needed for improved
			 technology to improve miner protections during such operations; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E32C912AD654A4E94B8FEC303D3BB3B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>adopting any
			 existing technology to the mining environment to improve miner protections
			 during secondary mining of coal resources, and on research needed for improved
			 technology to improve miner protections during such operations.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDCD5C03E63D9484498221DBD4550DDE5"><enum>(j)</enum><header>SCSR inspection
			 program</header>
				<paragraph id="H10A6707A3F884F968C6D85F44FE52E8C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary
			 shall—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H2C259BE49CED473597ED556D174301E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish a
			 program to randomly remove and have tested by the National Institute for
			 Occupational Safety and Health field samples of each model of self-rescue
			 device used in an underground coal mine in order to ensure that the self-rescue
			 devices in coal mine inventories are working in accordance with the approval
			 criteria for such devices;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A694A83A2494CA29FF041EBE54C659B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>require a
			 manufacturer of a self-rescue device and the mine operator who owns a device to
			 contact the Secretary immediately upon notification of any potential problem
			 with any such device, and provide a copy of such notice to the representative
			 of miners at the affected operation; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F4AA0D8F4604BE79B2E10D68542E693"><enum>(C)</enum><text>notify immediately
			 all operators of underground coal mines if the Secretary detects or is advised
			 of any problems with the self-rescue devices.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2659269C194453FB0E32172AE93D240"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of paragraph (1)(A), the
			 National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health shall determine the
			 number of field samples of each device to be removed for testing, and the mines
			 from which the samples are to be drawn to ensure a random sample is obtained,
			 and shall provide mine operators with self-rescue devices to replace any
			 removed for random testing. Should this testing reveal a potential problem with
			 a device that requires additional testing, the Secretary shall remove such
			 additional samples from such mines as may be requested by the National
			 Institute for Occupational Safety and Health, and it shall be the obligation of
			 mine operators to provide self-rescue devices to promptly replace any removed
			 as a result of such additional testing.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H62E7FDB1A6154E128273682B857DED84"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Application to
			 underground metal and nonmetal mines</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title II is amended by adding at the end
			 the following new section:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAE53E7C312D141DFA94C8502551D2541" style="OLC">
					<section id="H0A4309053FB94307A5D828B0C9FE59E4"><enum>207.</enum><header>Application to
				underground metal and nonmetal mines</header>
						<subsection id="H4D22DE5D58234126A591E4FDD9251253"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Conveyor
				belts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements of
				section 311(h) concerning conveyor belts in underground coal mines, including
				the exceptions and limitations in connection therewith, shall also apply to
				conveyor belts in underground metal and nonmetal mines.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H36D99E5E6DD24B30BFB7F9F44BDB3F71"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Seals</header><text>The
				regulations to be issued pursuant to section 303(z)(2) concerning the approval,
				design, construction, inspection, maintenance and monitoring of underground
				coal mine seals shall make the same rules applicable to seals in underground
				metal and nonmetal mines which have been classified by the Secretary as a
				category I, III, or V mine pursuant to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/57">section 57.22003</external-xref> of title 30, Code of
				Federal Regulations, because they naturally emit defined quantities of
				methane.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H4E003979CBBF40A8AD942541D6DB4DF1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Advisory
				committee</header><text>Promptly after the date of enactment of the S–MINER Act
				The Secretary shall establish an advisory committee to provide recommendations
				as to the need to revise the regulations applicable to underground metal and
				nonmetal mines to ensure that miners in such mines are as protected in
				emergency situations as will be underground coal miners following the full
				implementation of the MINER Act, the provisions of the S–MINER Act, and related
				actions by the Secretary. The advisory committee shall be established pursuant
				to the Advisory Committee Act, and shall provide recommendations to the
				Secretary and to Congress not later than 21 months after the date of enactment
				of this Act, including recommendations as to any action by Congress that could
				facilitate the goal of providing equivalent protections to miners in
				underground metal and nonmetal
				mines.</text>
						</subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H8B132DE2583D44A392F03EB23BEB06D"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Approval center
			 priorities</header><text>The Secretary shall expedite the process for approving
			 any—</text>
				<paragraph id="H53FF624E0158452593F2008F4476F3E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>self-rescue device
			 that permits the replenishment of oxygen without requiring the device user to
			 remove the device; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HC1D5A848463F496BA5C9EC62D7068FF3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>underground
			 communication device that provides for communication between underground and
			 surface personnel via a wireless two-way medium.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5EC6CD2BA8FF44DEA7E1E3CB86A011D5"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Technology and
			 mine emergency health and safety research priorities</header><text>In
			 implementing its research activities in the 5-year period beginning on the date
			 of enactment of this Act, the National Institute for Occupational Safety and
			 Health shall give due consideration to new technologies, and existing
			 technologies that could be adapted for use in underground coal or other mines,
			 that could facilitate the survival of miners in a mining emergency. Such
			 technologies include—</text>
				<paragraph id="H494081D7EB9D4E45BCB0413F33C533E9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>self-contained
			 self-rescue devices capable of delivering enhanced performance;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H1CCD38630AE34554A0BAE5734BDC2B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>improved battery
			 capacity and common connection specifications to enable emergency communication
			 devices for miners to be run from the same portable power source as a headlamp,
			 continuous dust monitor, or other device carried by a miner;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H0E0387E37E574F15B500ED3C6FAFAF94"><enum>(3)</enum><text>improved
			 technology for assisting mine rescue teams, including devices to enhance vision
			 during rescue or recovery operations;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HE342A59CD0B34459BDA00741DAC36BE3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>improved
			 technology, and improved protocols for the use of existing technologies, to
			 enable conditions underground to be assessed promptly and continuously in
			 emergencies, so as to facilitate the determination by appropriate officials of
			 the instructions to provide both to miners trapped underground and to mine
			 rescue teams and others engaged in rescue efforts;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H74D2FD23361049929CEF151EBAF0A12"><enum>(5)</enum><text>improvements to
			 underground mine ventilation controls separating mine entries to be more
			 resistant to mine fires and explosions, particularly in those entries used for
			 miner escapeways;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H150EB2DA71064205BC33E680E73D7D5D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>mine-wide
			 monitoring systems and strategies that can monitor mine gases, oxygen, air
			 flows, and air quantities at strategic locations throughout the mine that would
			 be functional during normal mining operations and following mine fires,
			 explosions, roof falls, and mine bursts, including systems utilizing monitoring
			 sensors that transfer data to the mine surface and the installation of tubing
			 to draw mine gas samples that are distributed throughout the mine and can
			 quickly deliver samples to the mine surface; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HE8611303D82343AABA7C5EA6447245A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>protective
			 strategies for the placement of equipment, cables, and devices that are to be
			 utilized during mine emergencies such as communication systems, oxygen
			 supplies, and mine atmosphere monitoring systems, to protect them from mine
			 fires, roof falls, explosions, and other damage.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H58125A8F411A4F078331347225979BDE"><enum>5.</enum><header>Supplementing
			 enforcement authority</header>
			<subsection id="H99B68E7410F848E5977FCDD6EEF0BB78"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority of
			 inspectors</header><text>Section 103(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/813">30 U.S.C. 813(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding
			 at the end the following: <quote>No person shall limit or otherwise prevent the
			 Secretary from entry on a coal or other mine, or interfere with the Secretary’s
			 inspection activities, investigative activities, or rescue or recovery
			 activities.</quote>.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H1835D4E0A64947FF9772F659152ED5AC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transition to a
			 new generation of inspectors</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 505 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/954">30 U.S.C. 954</external-xref>) is
			 amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H7D72D61C063C4B4FA8A498F1DF392D3B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>The Secretary</quote> the first place it appears and inserting
			 <quote>(a) The Secretary</quote>; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HAA2407C914584EB7AEA10960D6200038"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the
			 end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H7764E245BF344F66A5CACF947C49327C" style="OLC">
						<subsection id="H90507C01803045A9B23429C1E974D0EE"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Within 270 days of
				the enactment of the S–MINER Act, the Secretary shall establish a Master
				Inspector program to ensure that the most experienced and skilled employees in
				the Nation have the incentive, in terms of responsibilities and pay, to serve
				as mine safety and health inspectors in this Nation’s mines.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="HC973E107C92F4256B634C0D8F000C9EA"><enum>(c)</enum><text>In order to ensure
				that the Secretary has adequate time to provide that a sufficient number of
				qualified and properly trained inspectors of the Mine Safety and Health
				Administration are in place before any inspectors employed as of the date of
				enactment of the S–MINER Act retire, any ceilings on the number of personnel
				that may be employed by the Administration with respect to mine inspectors are
				abolished for the 5-year period beginning on the date of enactment of such
				Act.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="HDF7C16C151E24E7889D300FE8BF1634"><enum>(d)</enum><text>In the event that,
				notwithstanding the actions taken by the Secretary to hire and train qualified
				inspectors, the Secretary is temporarily unable, at any time during the 5-year
				period beginning on the date of enactment of the S–MINER Act, to employ the
				number of inspectors required to staff all district offices devoted to coal
				mines at the offices’ highest historical levels without transferring personnel
				from supervisory or plan review activities or diminishing current inspection
				resources devoted to other types of mines, the Administration is authorized to
				hire retired inspectors on a contractual basis to conduct mine inspections, and
				the retirement benefits of such retired inspectors shall not be reduced as a
				result of such temporary contractual employment.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H65172A631B8D488CB379BE493528D2E9"><enum>(e)</enum><text>During the 5-year
				period beginning on the date of enactment of the S–MINER Act, the Secretary
				shall issue a special report to the appropriate committees of Congress each
				year, or at such more frequent intervals as the Secretary or any such committee
				may consider appropriate, providing information about the actions being taken
				under this section, the size and training of the inspector workforce at the
				Mine Safety and Health Administration, the level of enforcement activities, and
				the number of requests by individual operators of mines for compliance
				assistance.</text>
						</subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H30D7CAAA82F04808823750A63B2BF221"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Office of Miner
			 ombudsman</header><text>Title V is amended by adding at the end the
			 following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5E531AA19A834AABA4B9F3DCDD85745B" style="OLC">
					<section id="HF56DF75C5C18479B009057A918492799"><enum>516.</enum><header>Office of miner
				ombudsman</header>
						<subsection id="H5BCF833BD79D4771A74347F2B2072706"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of
				miner ombudsman</header><text>There shall be established, within the Office of
				the Inspector General of the Department of Labor, the position of Miner
				Ombudsman. The President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate,
				shall appoint an individual with expertise in mine safety and health to serve
				as the Miner Ombudsman. The Ombudsman shall have authority to hire such
				personnel as are required to administer his duties in accordance with
				applicable law, provided they meet any general requirements for employment
				within the Office of the Inspector General.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="HD411675A15124E82B1B9B9127420F16"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The
				Miner Ombudsman shall—</text>
							<paragraph id="H8A0C9A23CBE94CDFBF07EF5E9565816D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>recommend to the
				Secretary appropriate practices to ensure the confidentiality of the identity
				of miners, and the families or personal representatives of the miners, who
				contact mine operators, authorized representatives of the miners, the Mine
				Safety and Health Administration, the Department of Labor, or others with
				information about mine accidents, incidents, injuries, illnesses, possible
				violations of mandatory health or safety standard violations or plans or other
				mine safety and health concerns;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H3DF4A1FB9CC94BD1BA68D3EEE962C479"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish a
				toll-free telephone number and appropriate Internet website to permit
				individuals to confidentially report mine accidents, incidents, injuries,
				illnesses, possible violations of mandatory health or safety standard
				violations or plans or other mine safety and health concerns, and provide
				plastic wallet cards, refrigerator magnets, or similar devices to all mine
				operators, which mine operators shall distribute to all current and new miners,
				with contact information for such confidential reports, and also provide
				supplies of these devices to miner communities;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HAFD06C6DA6DB4FBD860000660501194B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>collect and
				forward information concerning accidents, incidents, injuries, illnesses,
				possible violations of mandatory health or safety standard violations or plans
				or other mine safety and health concerns to the appropriate officials of the
				Mine Safety and Health Administration for investigation, or to appropriate
				officials within the Office of Inspector General for investigation or audit, or
				both, while establishing practices to protect the confidentiality of the
				identify of those who provide such information to the Ombudsman; and</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HF979F608EF20441EAA73D9E64DBB92D5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>monitor the
				Secretary of Labor’s efforts to promptly act upon complaints filed by miners
				under section 105(c) of the Act or pursuant to other programs administered by
				the Department to protect whistleblowers, and report to Congress any
				recommendations that would enhance such rights or protections.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H495B3BFD9231469ABE003C1F5D5569B8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>All
				complaints of operator violations of any section of this Act or regulations
				prescribed under this Act that are reported to the Secretary shall be forwarded
				to the Ombudsman for logging and appropriate action, except that this
				requirement shall be implemented in such a way as to avoid interference in any
				way with the ability of the Assistant Secretary for Mine Safety and Health to
				take prompt actions that may be required in such situations. This shall include
				complaints submitted in writing, via any phone system, or orally, along with
				all relevant information available regarding the complainant. All such
				information shall be retained in a confidential manner pursuant to the Privacy
				Act of 1974. The Ombudsman shall use such information to monitor the actions
				taken to ensure that miners’ complaints are addressed in a timely manner and in
				compliance with the appropriate statutes and regulations. The Ombudsman shall
				refer to appropriate personnel within the Office of the Inspector General for
				further review any case which he determines was not handled in such
				fashion.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="HD81ED18ADA4145BA92C9870867A852D1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of
				appropriations</header><text>There are hereby authorized to be appropriated to
				the Ombudsman such sums as may be required for the implementation of his duties
				out of the sums otherwise made available to the Mine Safety and Health
				Administration for its
				activities.</text>
						</subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HCBD7D5E8277545BBB600AA803622738C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Pattern of
			 violations</header>
				<paragraph id="H74B41BBAEEF04C2AA41220EB4D76017"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prompt
			 identification of pattern</header><text>Not later than 3 months after the date
			 of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall revise the regulations issued by
			 the Secretary under section 104(e) of the Federal Mine Safety and Health Act of
			 1977 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/814">30 U.S.C. 814(e)</external-xref>) as in effect on the day before such date of enactment,
			 so that the regulations provide that—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HB6296DE8BD3F4CCEBAF157B100006BA2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>when a potential
			 pattern of violations is identified by any inspector or district manager of the
			 Mine Safety and Health Administration, the operator of the coal or other mine
			 and the authorized representative of miners for the mine shall be notified by
			 the inspector or district manager not later than 10 days after such
			 identification; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D9D9DBFC79443C886CCE5C950E50D2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>after receiving the
			 notification described in subparagraph (A), the appropriate official of the
			 Mine Safety and Health Administration shall promptly review any such potential
			 pattern of violations and, not later than 45 days after receiving such
			 notification, make a final decision as to whether a citation for a violation of
			 section 104(e) of such Act should be issued in light of the gravity of the
			 violations and the operator’s conduct in connection therewith.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE2F75FD78024ECFB8C610FD60D2F29"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Identification of
			 pattern</header><text>Section 104(e)(1) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/814">30 U.S.C. 814(e)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by
			 inserting after the first sentence the following: <quote>In determining whether
			 a pattern of violations exists, the Secretary shall give due consideration to
			 all relevant information, such as the gravity of the violations, operator
			 negligence, history of violations, the number of inspection shifts the
			 Secretary or her agents have spent at the operation, and the frequency of
			 violations per number of inspection days spent at the
			 operation.</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H5C72E41AC5914043ACA3E0228FD474D4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Termination of
			 pattern</header><text>Section 104(e)(3) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/814">30 U.S.C. 814(e)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by
			 adding at the end the following: <quote>In addition, if an operator subject to
			 paragraphs (1) and (2) demonstrates objective evidence that they are correcting
			 the problems that gave rise to the pattern of violations, and the violation
			 frequency rate for such operator declines significantly for a period of 180
			 days, the withdrawal order provisions of paragraphs (1) and (2) shall no longer
			 apply.</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H9361C707FB9E4352848E0014B5233DC5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Fine for a
			 pattern of violations</header><text>Section 110 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/820">30 U.S.C. 820</external-xref>) is
			 amended—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HC28A758F704B4DEEB7E0ED08EA7128E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating
			 subsections (i) through (l) as subsections (j) through (m), respectively;
			 and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2AE1F94AB8234D4BAA59C8D862364600"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after
			 subsection (h) the following:</text>
						<quoted-block id="HB0F4815BD46244D9996636ABE4D2CCDC" style="OLC">
							<subsection id="HE35A02B27818406C99C323FF0832F23D"><enum>(i)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HB12B906BB0974C71802DD808CF2B1B4F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>If the Secretary
				determines that a pattern of violations under section 104(e) exists, the
				Secretary shall assess a penalty, in addition to any other penalty authorized
				in this Act for a violation of such section, of not less than $50,000 nor more
				than $250,000. All operators of the mine, including any corporate owners, shall
				be jointly and severally liable for such penalty. The amount of the assessment
				under this paragraph shall be designed to ensure a change in the future conduct
				of the operators and corporate owners of such mine with respect to mine safety
				and health, given the overall resources of such operators. Notwithstanding
				subsection (k) or section 113, a penalty assessed by the Secretary under this
				paragraph may not be reduced by the Commission.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H3307AE423278413DA9F63E7B1F58A5" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In addition to the authority to
				withdraw miners from an area of a coal or other mine pursuant to section
				104(e), the Secretary shall withdraw all miners from the entire mine when any
				pattern of violations has been determined to exist until such time as the
				Secretary certifies that all identified violations have been corrected and the
				operator has agreed to abide by a written plan approved by the Mine Safety and
				Health Administration to ensure that such a pattern of conduct will not
				recur.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H552C637A9CC94DF7B1F3F64C8629914"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Notification of
			 abatement</header><text>Section 104(b) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/814">30 U.S.C. 814(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H80874FA1AE2C40BC90DC8C289E8E6672"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating
			 paragraphs (1) and (2) as subparagraphs (A) and (B), respectively;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H19D1442F68084C7E94AC008EAFD4686C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>If,</quote> and inserting:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBA1CE640A4EA428782735D96187F1463" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="H9008345E7D6945F6AC53B400A9308FC4" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If,</text>
						</paragraph><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H93E54058C06548B2BEFF843B1FD9D89B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after
			 the subsection designation the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="HA3C5F754F5224EBAAE799EA37D929CA" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="H5972EB313EAC447F92A3D88E5F03F75C" indent="up1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An operator issued a citation
				pursuant to subsection (a) shall notify the Secretary that the operator has
				abated the violation involved. If such operator fails to provide such a notice
				to the Secretary within the abatement time as provided for in the citation, the
				Secretary shall issue an order that requires the operator (or the agent of the
				operator) to immediately cause all persons, except those persons referred to in
				subsection (c), to be withdrawn from, and to be prohibited from entering, such
				area as the Secretary determines until an authorized representative of the
				Secretary determines that such violation has been abated. Notwithstanding any
				operator notice, no violation shall be determined to be abated until an
				authorized representative of the Secretary visits the site and determines such
				violation has been fully
				abated.</text>
						</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6B3D7F8ADE30488DB55B007E10D049D9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Failure to
			 timely pay penalty assessments</header><text>Section 105(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/815">30 U.S.C. 815(a)</external-xref>)
			 is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="HBA11A83A4AE842069C23079C3679D392"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting
			 <quote>(1)</quote> after the subsection designation; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H0E63DD39AE1846F393F06CA35DABA349"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting at
			 the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="HE6A00F9D9E1E44A99CFC3BA2E4ECCC77">
						<paragraph id="HD34645C4F4E647EE8CEC6451744C381D" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8BFCC2BA0A9C475391A612B18648E206"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall maintain a list of
				delinquent operators who fail to timely pay final assessments. Any operator
				placed on that list for the first time shall be subject to the requirements of
				this paragraph only until such time as the Secretary determines that the
				operator is no longer in arrears. Any operator placed on that list for a
				subsequent time shall remain on the list until such time as the Secretary
				determines the operator is committed to timely payment of final assessments.
				Any operator who believes he or she has been placed or retained on the list in
				error may file with the Commission a request for consideration of
				decision.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H34A2C983EDA34B6987EB75DF6076665E" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An operator on the list maintained pursuant
				to paragraph (A) shall, not later than 30 days from the receipt of the
				notification of a citation issued by the Secretary, notify the Secretary that
				the operator intends to contest the citation or proposed assessment of a
				penalty, and the operator shall place in escrow with the Secretary the amount
				of the proposed assessment. The Secretary shall place any escrow submitted by a
				mine operator for this purpose into an interest bearing account and shall
				release the funds to the operator, including interest accrued, upon the payment
				of any final assessment determination. If notification and proof of escrow is
				not provided to the Secretary, the citation and the proposed assessment of
				penalty shall be deemed a final order of the Commission and not subject to
				review by any court or agency.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1EDB35F1F405490BBEC600E6C458D4D" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>In the event that a mine operator
				refuses to comply with a final order of the Commission to pay civil monetary
				penalties and statutory interest, the Secretary shall have the authority to
				issue an order requiring the mine operator to cease production under such final
				orders of the Commission have been paid in
				full.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFB012CFF6189498DB27FAE9626304122"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Maximum and
			 minimum penalties</header><text>Section 110(a)(1) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/820">30 U.S.C. 820(a)(1)</external-xref>) is
			 amended by striking <quote>more than $50,000 for each such violation.</quote>
			 and inserting <quote>less than $500 or more than $100,000 for each such
			 violation, except that, in the case of a violation of a mandatory health or
			 safety standard that could significantly and substantially contribute to the
			 cause and effect of a coal or other mine health or safety hazard, the penalty
			 shall not be less than $1,000 or more than $150,000, for each such
			 violation.</quote>.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HD1574F8E1B1E4AAB8728E999A3F13B9"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Factors in
			 assessing penalties</header><text>The Federal Mine Safety and Health Act of
			 1977 is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H8674DED6A62644F3AE7D33E2C227C004"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 105(b)(1)(B)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H8293CAF051464C6BB70769C66274CEC2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking:
			 <quote>the size of the business of the operator charged</quote> and inserting
			 <quote>the combined size of the business of the operator and any controlling
			 entity</quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01E37E803A2549549CD558C9B9975773"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>the effect on the operator’s ability to continue in business,</quote>;
			 and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3727075EA88C4EA497C6249D4B091023"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the
			 end the following: <quote>In settling cases, the Secretary shall utilize the
			 same point system as that utilized to propose penalties, so as to ensure
			 consistency in operator penalty assessments.</quote>; and</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EB058A3323145B0A8697EC86CD55D5E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 110(j)
			 (as redesignated by subsection (a)(4))—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H40390E9D8107440AB39D71007BDD0089"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking:
			 <quote>the size of the business of the operator charged</quote> and inserting
			 <quote>the combined size of the business of the operator and any controlling
			 entity</quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C536C08142D40DABF4972C7F494C238"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>the effect on the operator’s ability to continue in business,</quote>;
			 and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40CB6A87513442E296038C229D90A12B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the
			 end the following: <quote>In any review requested by a mine operator, or in
			 settling cases, the Commission shall utilize the same point system as that
			 developed by the Secretary for proposed assessments so as to ensure consistency
			 in operator penalty assessments.</quote>.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9D4F7F87D7FF445BA2B641313E072184"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Civil penalty
			 for interference or discrimination</header><text>Section 110 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/820">30 U.S.C. 820</external-xref>) is
			 further amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="HAA6E6DE132E74EABB109BEDB30F0BB01" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H502394F93314483288C905FB04EF8618"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Civil penalty
				for interference or discrimination</header><text>Any operator who is found to
				be in violation of section 105(c), or in violation of section 103(a) (as
				amended by this Act) shall be subject to a civil penalty of not less than
				$10,000 nor more than $100,000 for each occurrence of such
				violation.</text>
					</subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H364ABD5C2628443A8C60DEF3658249CA"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Withdrawal
			 order</header><text>Section 107(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/817">30 U.S.C. 817(a)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting
			 after the first sentence the following: <quote>In addition, in the event of any
			 violation of section 315 or section 316, or regulations issued pursuant to such
			 sections, such representative shall determine the extent of the area of such
			 mine throughout which the danger exists and issue an order requiring the
			 operator of such mine to cause all persons, except those referred to in section
			 104(c), to be withdrawn from, and to be prohibited from entering, such area
			 until an authorized representative of the Secretary determines that the
			 violations have been abated.</quote>.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H591BB9641F904FDF9CACF571F68C4200"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Clarifications
			 of intent in the 1977 Act</header><text>The Federal Mine Safety and Health Act
			 of 1977 is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H72D5431AA2EF487FB6A59028A8146520"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 3(d) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/802">30 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H4B090B1CF22943D0A315BB2421BA02DC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting
			 <quote>mineral</quote> before <quote>owner</quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB1C0CA0A50E443CB8BC24E9D8743F9C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting
			 <quote>mineral</quote> before <quote>lessee</quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1CB1084FB1984035B39817528C9272B9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>or any independent</quote> and inserting <quote>and any
			 independent</quote>; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H58F9D895C95D467BB8B9C992BDDB00D6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting
			 before the semicolon the following: <quote>, and no operator may, by contract
			 or other agreement, limit any liability under this Act through transfer of any
			 responsibilities to another person</quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB20573F6C92C43C397EDDBC519C8B0FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 103 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/813">30 U.S.C. 813</external-xref>)—</text>
					<subparagraph commented="no" id="H24A6D472C3504739A73566A8650059CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)—</text>
						<clause commented="no" id="HC189078D3E964446B594F7C619D7DFEA"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking the first sentence and
			 inserting the following: <quote>For the purpose of enabling the Secretary to
			 perform the functions under this Act, the Secretary may, after notice, hold
			 public hearings and sign and issue subpoenas for the attendance and testimony
			 of witnesses and the production of information, including but not limited to
			 relevant data, papers, books, documents and items of physical evidence, and
			 administer oaths, whether or not in connection with a public hearing.</quote>;
			 and</text>
						</clause><clause commented="no" id="HF056B3DF119E4F0399F5E2B3602D7647"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the last
			 sentence by striking <quote>documents</quote> and inserting <quote>information,
			 including data, papers, books, documents, and items of physical
			 evidence</quote>; and</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16DFC9595A894C68B112D092F1349807"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (h),
			 in the first sentence, by striking <quote>information</quote> and inserting
			 <quote>data, papers, books, documents, and items of physical
			 evidence</quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B7688B14F7A4BDDAEFA19403EA70066"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 104 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/814">30 U.S.C. 814</external-xref>)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HF3D229CDF19D4EA796FB9BE6729D7102"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsections
			 (d)(1), (e)(1), (e)(2), (e)(3), and (e)(4), as amended by this Act, by
			 inserting <quote>or any provision of this Act</quote> after
			 <quote>standard</quote> or <quote>standards</quote> each place either such term
			 appears; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF2BF547EDC9401991F5D0D766360012"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (d)(1), as amended by this Act, by striking <quote>while the conditions created
			 by such violation do not cause imminent danger,</quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB560E180E96541658100CBB9B153B6E7"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 105 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/815">30 U.S.C. 815</external-xref>)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HB168845C9DB3443DA622619463A5B61B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a),
			 in the first sentence, by striking <quote>, within a reasonable time after the
			 termination of such inspection or investigation,</quote>;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8670EE526E694714957CD382DC5142CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (c)—</text>
						<clause id="HC6A5B2452FD14ADDAA00F132BDD8C1AD"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1)—</text>
							<subclause id="H65056CAE520544B09111774CCF844879"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting
			 <quote>or an injury or illness in a coal or other mine or that may be
			 associated with mine employment,</quote> after <quote>of an alleged danger or
			 safety or health violation in a coal or other mine,</quote>; and</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H4ECFF766E37147B6B2A478C5E13B65D9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting at
			 the end the following: <quote>No miner shall be required to work under
			 conditions he has reasonable grounds to believe to be abnormally and
			 immediately dangerous to himself beyond the normal hazards inherent in the
			 operation which could reasonably be expected to cause death of serious physical
			 harm before such condition or practice can be abated.</quote>; and</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause id="H33C0850C617F4B3C94554EC8E5D04CF1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in
			 paragraph (2), by inserting after the fifth sentence the following: <quote>No
			 investigation or hearing authorized by this paragraph may be stayed to await
			 resolution of a related grievance proceeding</quote>; and</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC647B4971BCC4F28A871A3E8D3496700"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the
			 end the following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9A86BF0B6090439894BC03DA1DBB5B8" style="OLC">
							<subsection id="H96FD8DFBCC4747A1BD1BF66865576337"><enum>(e)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Attorneys representing the Secretary are
				authorized to contact any miner or non-managerial employee of a mine operator
				for the purposes of carrying out the Secretary’s functions under this Act and
				no attorney representing the Secretary shall be disbarred or disciplined by any
				State bar or State court for making such contacts. No attorney representing a
				mine operator in a matter under this Act may concurrently represent individual
				miners in the same matter.</text>
							</subsection><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC165D76574C42499741CEF7A6A8D1EA"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 110 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/820">30 U.S.C. 820</external-xref>)—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H9CFA1D19EEDC408392D8C6C24FBDA132"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (b)(2), by striking <quote>under</quote> and inserting <quote>of subsections
			 (a) through (h) of</quote>; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8132F8FE713E47860000006FE408AAF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection
			 (c)—</text>
						<clause id="H511CA5B204C5420DAB38699400EF7614"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by
			 striking <quote>Whenever a corporate operator</quote> and inserting
			 <quote>Whenever a mine operator</quote>;</text>
						</clause><clause id="H4D05C708C6154C299BFC191724A9B424"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by
			 striking <quote>safety standard</quote> and inserting <quote>safety standard or
			 requirement of this Act</quote>;</text>
						</clause><clause id="H77E5E38C38D94A3D9CF1CD5D977729B4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by
			 inserting <quote>partner, owner,</quote> after <quote>director,</quote>;
			 and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H4929B1BBBAE44E51A196BB47B05F082"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by
			 striking <quote>such corporation</quote> and inserting <quote>such mine
			 operator</quote>.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H45BFD3A65D444F56950019B904DFCDE"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Federal
			 licensing</header><text>The Secretary shall promptly establish an advisory
			 committee to provide recommendations as to whether the Federal Mine Safety and
			 Health Act of 1977 should provide for Federal licensing of mines, mine
			 operators, mine controllers, or various mine personnel in order to ensure that
			 those engaged in mining activities are not frequent violators of safety and
			 health requirements, and establish a national registry in connection therewith.
			 The advisory committee shall be established pursuant to the Advisory Committee
			 Act, and shall conduct a review of existing State licensing requirements and
			 registries, assess their effectiveness, and shall provide its recommendations
			 to Congress not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this
			 Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HF72547EBB4CF41748DAE23267B685153"><enum>6.</enum><header>Supplementing
			 rescue, recovery, and incident investigation authority</header>
			<subsection id="H2A7B45D165704CA794997D6C6DA6EAF6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Emergency call
			 center</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this
			 Act, the Secretary shall establish, within the Mine Safety and Health
			 Administration, a central communications emergency call center for all coal or
			 other mine operations that shall be staffed and operated 24 hours per day, 7
			 days per week, by 1 or more employees of the Mine Safety and Health
			 Administration. All calls placed to the emergency call center shall be answered
			 by an individual with adequate experience and training to handle emergency mine
			 situations. A single national phone number shall be provided for this purpose
			 and the Secretary shall ensure that all miners and mine operators are issued
			 laminated cards with emergency call center information.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H43EB8BE3144A49C7B9E3D1EFAB2A894"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contact
			 information</header><text>The Secretary shall provide the emergency call center
			 with a contact list, updated not less often than quarterly, that
			 contains—</text>
				<paragraph id="H6DCF9AB7B4A94D66ABFCE05EBE055D80"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the contact phone
			 numbers, including the home phone numbers, for the members of each mine rescue
			 team responsible for each coal or other mine;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HCA4AC3474C1A4873B754796EB041B6AA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the phone numbers
			 for the local emergency and rescue services unit that is located nearest to
			 each mine;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HC2FBA3108D4F41AB9F3DAB404CF6F3B8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the contact phone
			 numbers, including the home phone number, for the operator of each mine;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H4EA4F30152784EDD93815DB996193D01"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the contact phone
			 numbers, including the home phone numbers, for the national and district
			 officials of the Mine Safety and Health Administration;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H2003FC8E1832464CA8B2E3CBD36BADFA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the contact phone
			 numbers, including the home phone numbers, for the State officials in each
			 State who should be contacted in the event of a mine emergency in such State;
			 and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HBA996465C00C4709B60093008E8C51D8"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the contact phone
			 numbers, including the home phone number, for the authorized representative of
			 the miners at each mine.</text>
				</paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">Each mine
			 operator shall ensure that the Secretary is provided with completely current
			 information required to be maintained by the Secretary pursuant to paragraphs
			 (1), (3), and (6). The Secretary shall give due consideration to the
			 information collected by the joint government-industry Mine Emergency
			 Operations database.</continuation-text></subsection><subsection id="HB2633B52DFD747FFA65295662205332F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Mine locations;
			 repository of mining maps</header>
				<paragraph id="H70087B84684A47B4933C55DE00218835"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Mine
			 locations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall
			 establish, maintain, and keep current, on the Department of Labor’s website, a
			 detailed map or set of maps showing the exact geographic location of each
			 operating or abandoned mine in the United States, as determined by a global
			 positioning system. Such map or maps shall—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HF92D29E3C6F04C5C88859BF1E1E8F900"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be presented,
			 through links within the website, in such a way as to make the location of a
			 mine instantly available to the emergency personnel responding to the
			 mine;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E6465F97722441D95ACFA39500825B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>be available to
			 members of the public;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE43E59EB8C414DDDAE4D5248355E0233"><enum>(C)</enum><text>allow a user to
			 find the geographic location of a particular mine, or the geographic locations
			 of all mines of a particular type in a county, congressional district, State,
			 or other commonly used geographic region; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1A19E6819114280A73DFD806CD19DF1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provide the
			 geographic location of any mining waste impoundments with links to associated
			 emergency contact information and available emergency response plans.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7AFC339319B5409FB34386E600EFD93F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Repository of
			 mining maps</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a national repository
			 for preserving a digital archive of mining maps to be accessible directly and
			 without delay from the Department’s web site. The mining maps shall include
			 copies of all historic maps that can be obtained, as well as copies of
			 currently approved mining maps, which the Secretary shall arrange to copy and
			 preserve in digital form. The Secretary may coordinate the operation of such
			 repository with the Secretary of the Interior provided the other requirements
			 of this paragraph are observed. In addition, the Secretary shall include in
			 this repository copies of the most currently available mine emergency response
			 plan, roof plans, ventilation plans, and such other plans required for any type
			 of mine, following any required approval, so that they may be immediately
			 accessed in an emergency, in a manner consistent with the requirements of
			 section 312(b) of the Act.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDC4BCA54D9CD4EF900D891338B01C5D6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Required
			 notification of emergencies and serious incidents</header><text>Section 103(j)
			 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/813">30 U.S.C. 813(j)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H51BB88E5BB1A46F5A1342B06943C7D35"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the first
			 sentence, by inserting <quote>or reportable event</quote> after
			 <quote>accident</quote>;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HE1D1656B20844979BC555F4D548D0523"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the second
			 sentence—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H9CDDEDB23ED04A4EB4DCD579B9826B41"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting
			 <quote>of accidents</quote> after <quote>the notification</quote>; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A9A4333262B496EBE1D0061A1D8DE7E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting
			 <quote>, or in the case of a reportable event that is not required to be
			 reported as an accident, within 1 hour of the time at which the operator
			 realizes that the event has occurred</quote> before the period; and</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3DA160B2DAC74C4BA87DC1EFA8387E00"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting at
			 the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H89BDF803D3F94E61A0ACCD42EAA22EB0" style="OLC">
						<text>For the purposes of this
			 subsection, a reportable event shall include—</text><paragraph id="H878FD565D5B64A099231321C485EC9DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a fire not
				required to be reported more promptly;</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H3EBA65B3603343529B2402E6DA43364"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a sudden change in
				mine atmospheric conditions in a sealed area;</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H6BB6A5B356E646F99ED2D637E769D7B6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a coal or rock
				outburst that causes the withdrawal of miners; or</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H622AE1022933441380242C024E21D8FA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any other event,
				as determined in regulations promulgated by the Secretary, that needs to be
				reported within 1 hour in order for the Secretary to determine if the working
				conditions in the mine are
				safe.</text>
						</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDE5FA015EDEF43789C058E1D417FDBF2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Enhancing the
			 capabilities of mine rescue teams</header>
				<paragraph id="H653D8EA5DC1A4E60BC3421F0075ECA00"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amendment to
			 FMSHA</header><text>Section 115(e)(2)(B) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/825">30 U.S.C. 825(e)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by
			 adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="HCBEB5EB6F3074334A89955C8489C606F" style="OLC">
						<clause id="H050FDBD4C3734BD6BC25CA4451B07700" indent="up3"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The provision of uniform credentials
				to mine rescue team members, support personnel, or vehicles for immediate
				access to any mine site.</text>
						</clause><clause id="HF2F3E681185B4470B5623CEDD9B8F107" indent="up3"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>The plans required at each mine to
				ensure coordination with local emergency response personnel and to ensure that
				such personnel receive adequate training to offer necessary assistance to mine
				rescue teams in the event such assistance is requested. Such local emergency
				response personnel shall not perform the duties of any mine rescue team.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H17C55780D7D84D8E9D2737421FCA4CCD" indent="up3"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Requirements to ensure that operators are
				prepared to facilitate the work of mine rescue teams during an emergency
				by—</text>
							<subclause id="HDA7FBAEED9F24846A4F4C102404D209"><enum>(I)</enum><text>storing necessary equipment not
				brought on site by mine rescue teams in locations readily accessible to mine
				rescue teams;</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H4E06004FD99C44D4824B2C674543DFE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>providing mine rescue teams with a
				parking and staging area adequate for their needs;</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H9CAEB4A7C4AF4C52822877B002BD1400"><enum>(III)</enum><text>identifying a space appropriate for
				coordinating emergency communications with the mine rescue team; and</text>
							</subclause><subclause id="H5D4A632F5EAF4F2C811E2722E4C84802"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>identifying and maintaining separate
				spaces for family members, community members, and press to assemble during an
				emergency so as to facilitate communications with these groups while ensuring
				the efforts of the mine rescue teams are not
				hindered.</text>
							</subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H180E232896C148A28FDAC300561D2055"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Research</header><text>Section
			 22(h)(5)(A) of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (29 U.S.C.
			 671(h)(5)(A)) is amended by adding before the period at the end thereof:
			 <quote>including advanced drilling technologies, and any special technologies
			 required for safety or rescue in mining more than 1,500 feet in
			 depth</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H93533797BF194A3A8D745FEEE38CAE30"><enum>(f)</enum><text>Title I of the Act
			 is amended by adding at the end thereof a new section:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA78C74C317634CC485091DDFBF154CC" style="OLC">
					<section id="H6C8EEB5E175C434995009196663CDFF7"><enum>117.</enum><header>Emergency
				preparedness plan</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later
				than 6 months of the enactment of the S–MINER Act, the Secretary shall
				establish and disseminate guidelines for rescue operations that will: (1)
				establish clear lines of authority within the agency for such operations; (2)
				establish clear lines of demarcation so private sector and State responders can
				properly implement their responsibilities; (3) be appropriate for rescue in
				various types of conditions reasonably likely to be encountered in the United
				States, including such factors as the depth of the mining, ground stability,
				ground slope, remoteness from major roads, surface ownership and access
				problems, and the availability of necessary communications linkages. The
				Secretary shall consult with States, rescue teams and other responders in
				developing such guidelines, and shall update them from time to time based upon
				experience.</text>
					</section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H34ADF245B82E497EA8D66E92EBCCF077"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authority of
			 Secretary during rescue operations</header><text>Section 103 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/813">30 U.S.C. 813</external-xref>) is
			 further amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="H1CB5A3B66FEA4E3C8B80CBCC1B649649"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (j),
			 by adding at the end thereof:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4EF1A4D2EB8842E3A3453F66A7AFF67C" style="OLC">
						<quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="subsection">If the
				representative of the Secretary supervises and directs the rescue and recovery
				activities in such mine, the operator shall comply with the requests of the
				authorized representative of the Secretary to facilitate rescue and recovery
				activities including the provision of all equipment, personnel, and other
				resources required to perform such activities in accordance with the schedule
				and requirements established by the representative of the Secretary for this
				purpose, and failure of the operator to comply in this regard shall be
				considered an egregious violation of this
				Act.</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H88718CEF387049478513F6298FAD6F07"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (k),
			 by striking <quote>, when present,</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7034F407ADAD41B0B1C13BC3DABCE9BD"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Rescue
			 communications</header>
				<paragraph id="H393C2E6CBDAF4D9E81BF678BFA85909C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Repeal</header><text>The
			 MINER Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/801">30 U.S.C. 801</external-xref> note) is amended by striking section 7, redesignating
			 sections 8 and 9 as sections 7 and 8, and sections 11 through 14 as sections 9
			 through 12, respectively.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H9EB540261740456BB690C7569BEA2F32"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amendment to
			 FMSHA</header><text>Title I of the Act is further amended by adding at the end
			 the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDB54AF19A1FC420CB98FB543DDA33B00" style="OLC">
						<section id="H331D75E000C14009A7D5A1A959173DCA"><enum>118.</enum><header>Family Liaisons
				Requirement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary
				shall—</text>
							<paragraph id="H6C168A678AED447300ADED3BC07CFD45"><enum>(1)</enum><text>designate a
				full-time permanent employee of the Mine Safety and Health Administration to
				serve as a Family Liaison, who shall, at least in instances where multiple
				miners are trapped, severely injured or killed, act as the primary
				communication with the families of the miners concerning all aspects of the
				rescue operations, including the location or condition of miners, and assist
				the families in getting answers to their questions, and otherwise serve as a
				liaison to the families, and provide for the temporary reassignment of other
				personnel who may be required to assist the Family Liaison in connection with a
				particular incident;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H3D87363A7A634FE893B3ECD5C3AE0217"><enum>(2)</enum><text>require the Mine
				Safety and Health Administration to be as responsive as possible to requests
				from the families of such miners for information relating to the mine accident,
				and waive any fees required for the production of documents pursuant to 5
				U.S.C. 552(a)(3) in connection with a request from a family member, or
				authorized representative of miners, for documents relating to a mine fatality,
				notwithstanding any conditions for fee waivers law that may otherwise be
				imposed by law; and</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H17F79608FE6A40DBA5A287F8D342FE7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>designate a highly
				qualified representative of the Secretary with experience in public
				communications to be present at mine accident sites where rescues are in
				progress during the entire duration of such rescues, to serve as the primary
				communicator with the press and the public concerning all aspects of the rescue
				operations, including the location or condition of
				miners.</text>
							</paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HFFC7CC5E4997429395906067C8DF9600"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conforming
			 amendments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Act is
			 amended—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H9BC01447ABF2463E8C0701DC67EB5000"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 103(f),
			 by inserting before the period at the end of the first sentence the following:
			 <quote>, and to participate in any accident investigation pursuant to the
			 requirements of this Act. Any family member of a miner trapped or otherwise
			 unable to execute a designation of a miner representative on his or her own
			 behalf may do so on behalf of the miner for any and all purposes</quote>;
			 and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB399D94DA0FC4FB18CF997A8ED40F1A5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section
			 316(b)(2)(E)(vi) (as added by this Act), by adding at the end the following:
			 <quote>The plan shall also set forth the operator’s plans for assisting the
			 Secretary in the implementation of section 118.</quote>.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1E7F4E30BDFA40958FACAD7D395FEC5"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Recovery</header><text>Section
			 103 is amended by adding at the end thereof—</text>
				<quoted-block id="H69280581902047BF918D81941DAC4E80" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="HFBC1A95FE07F41AE9E4E5CB49D13EB81"><enum>(l)</enum><text>Rescue efforts for
				trapped miners shall not cease as long as there is any possibility that miners
				are alive, unless such efforts pose a serious danger to rescue or other
				workers, and the decision to cease a rescue shall be made by the
				Secretary<quote>s representative. Thereafter, efforts to recover the remains of
				miners shall continue unless such efforts pose a serious danger to recovery
				workers, and the decision to cease such recovery efforts shall be made by the
				Secretary</quote>s
				representative.</text>
					</subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HA86CA6EB6E0241BFA100BA1F2816446C"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Accident and
			 incident investigations</header><text>Section 103(b) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/813">30 U.S.C. 813(b)</external-xref>, as
			 amended by section 5(k)(2) of this Act, is further amended—</text>
				<paragraph id="HD31E69893E434EB89334B081E1C86CE8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking
			 <quote>For the purpose</quote> and inserting the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA650E4D2F4664B26B8821B66AD7FE5B2" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="H3899A1022C454F77A85EBBBB934D9188" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the
				purpose</text>
						</paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H991905055D2E416D007BDFC082827E52"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after
			 the subsection designation the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H039C7B404E6B435284C75B7EB614F1A9" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="HBD4E28CB5D9548CF9524363DA700AF00" indent="up1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>For all accident and incident
				investigations under this Act, the Secretary shall determine why the accident
				or incident occurred; determine whether civil or criminal requirements were
				violated and, if so, issue citations and penalties, and make recommendations to
				avoid any recurrence. The Secretary shall also determine whether the conduct or
				lack thereof by Agency personnel contributed to the accident or
				incident.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="HB53E819397E24C909C00A85D00D8BBDA" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H89443F9258E64E25A67C003674D9B9D5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For any accidents or
				incidents involving multiple serious injuries or deaths, or multiple
				entrapments, there shall also be an independent investigation to consider why
				the accident or incident occurred, make recommendations to avoid a recurrence,
				and determine whether the conduct or lack thereof by agency personnel
				contributed to the accident or incident.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HABECC4D949C04C3DAE85A7063E9E9ED6" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of
				enactment of the S–MINER Act, the Secretary shall initiate rulemaking activity
				to establish rules on the procedures that will be used to investigate accidents
				and incidents involving multiple serious injuries or deaths, or multiple
				entrapments, and shall directly contact and solicit the participation
				of—</text>
								<clause id="H60A4F9E4BAB04576BC5000FCECF38C27"><enum>(i)</enum><text>individuals identified by the
				Secretary as family members of miners who perished in mining accidents of any
				type during the preceding 10-year period;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H096596EE8DBD4F60957D92D043A383FB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>organizations representing
				miners;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HEEB23F02BAD14F79A2E27DEA2B96650"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>mine rescue teams;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H0F7B685C6CA346D78E1BA3D3A8A33C7C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Federal, State, and local
				investigation and prosecutorial authorities; and</text>
								</clause><clause id="HF176B1C6792A403F997034D3C294CEE6"><enum>(v)</enum><text>others whom the Secretary determines
				may have information relevant to this rulemaking.</text>
								</clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">Such
				rulemaking shall be completed by October 1, 2008.</continuation-text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3C383DE94EE4ABBB9D04690CCEE9062" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The rules for the investigation of
				accidents or incidents involving multiple serious injuries or deaths, or
				multiple entrapments, shall provide for the appointment and operations of any
				such independent investigation team in accordance with the requirements of this
				paragraph. An independent investigation team shall be appointed by the Director
				of the National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health as soon as
				possible after a qualifying accident or incident. The members shall consist
				of—</text>
								<clause id="HFE80B8F4DE7B4053B16237291962433E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a representative from the National
				Institute for Occupational Safety and Health who shall serve as the
				Chairman;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HC51CB56881C34A4194CDDA5D003D3008"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a representative of mine operators
				with familiarity with the type of mining involved;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H94403CC45CBE47C5A320F2CBC6371ECD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a representative of mine workers
				with familiarity with the type of mining involved, who shall be the workers’
				certified bargaining representative at the mine or, if there is no certified
				representative at the mine, then a workers’ representative jointly selected by
				organized labor organizations:</text>
								</clause><clause id="HD03AAF80A0524CF4A4374DA4A92921F1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>an academic with expertise in mining;
				and</text>
								</clause><clause id="H343C21CD9CA5426AA095A03BDF008109"><enum>(v)</enum><text>a representative of the State in which
				the accident or incident occurred to be selected by the Governor.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE7A58EDD997948EEBE2FD61EABFFC6EC" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such rules shall include procedures to
				ensure that the Secretary will be able to cooperate fully with the independent
				investigation team and will use the powers of the Secretary under this section
				to help obtain information and witnesses required by the independent
				investigation team, procedures to ensure witnesses are not coerced and to avoid
				conflicts of interest in witness representation, procedures to ensure
				confidentiality if requested by any witness, and procedures to enable the
				independent investigation team to conduct such public hearings as it deems
				appropriate. Such rules shall also require that upon completion of any accident
				or incident investigation of accidents or incidents involving multiple serious
				injuries or deaths, or multiple entrapments, the independent investigation team
				shall—</text>
								<clause id="HC8A500D696D749689E42DBF771E79E7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>issue findings as to the actions or
				inactions which resulted in the accident or incident;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H6DF3672C66E94D6ABAFCC4F30051511F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>make recommendations as to policy,
				regulatory, enforcement or other changes, including statutory changes, which in
				the judgment of the independent investigation team would best prevent a
				recurrence of such actions or inactions at other mines; and</text>
								</clause><clause id="H77EFB3D2DC89492898DDFB1CED00B500"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>promptly make all such findings and
				recommendations public (except findings and recommendations that must be
				temporarily withheld in connection with a criminal referral), including
				appropriate public hearings to inform the mining community of their respective
				findings and recommendations.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE93A3C2EEC2B41D9BA00A4B50062B425" indent="up1"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As part of the Secretary’s annual report to
				Congress pursuant to section 511(a), the Secretary shall report on
				implementation of recommendations issued by any independent investigation teams
				in the preceding 5 years.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;
				and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H65ED547A7AB04F019B74386EA2223476"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H964C7CCE84E3423E9D932080469090D7" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="HAAD6E6A07BC04809AEA4A37B6E361EAD" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall be construed to
				limit the authority of the Chemical Safety and Hazard Investigation Board to
				conduct an independent investigation of the accident or incident or the events
				or factors resulting therein, nor with the authority of the Office of the
				Inspector General to conduct an investigation of the conduct of DOL personnel
				in connection with an accident or incident or the events or factors resulting
				therein, and the Secretary shall cooperate in full with any such investigation.
				Such investigation shall be in addition to any investigation authorized by
				section
				103(b).</text>
						</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H047E3E03A4B3447C871282E650E61877"><enum>7.</enum><header>Respirable Dust
			 Standards</header>
			<subsection id="H01965124323A47E500D6E37E2072FCC5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Respirable dust;
			 respirable silica dust</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 202 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/842">30 U.S.C. 842</external-xref>) is amended to
			 read as follows:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1417E898542B41229D1CD2B3E5A77700" style="OLC">
					<section id="HC863818B83404690B0DD43129434D7C4"><enum>202.</enum><header>Dust standard
				and respiratory equipment</header>
						<subsection id="H149BE47AD15C44FEAE5249C635318935"><enum>(a)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9CE98961C70D4BCAA8622F00B342F3B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Effective on the date of
				enactment of the S–MINER Act, each coal mine operator shall continuously
				maintain the concentration of respirable dust in the mine atmosphere during
				each shift to which each miner in the active workings of such mine is exposed
				at or below a time-weighted average of 1.00 milligrams of respirable dust per
				cubic meter of air averaged over 10 hours or its dose-equivalent for shorter or
				longer period of time. For purposes of this paragraph, ‘a dose-equivalent’
				means the amount of dust that a miner would inhale during his work shift as if
				he were working for 10 hours, and the term ‘shift’ means portal-to-portal for
				underground coal mines and ‘bank to bank’ for other coal mines.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H05F59EFAC16B407F8ECF97623E531B9B" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At regular intervals to be prescribed by
				the Secretary and the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Secretary
				will take accurate samples of the amount of respirable dust in the coal mine
				atmosphere to which each miner in the active workings of such mine is exposed
				in order to determine compliance with the requirements of paragraph (a)(1) of
				this section. In addition, the Secretary shall cause to be made such frequent
				spot inspections as he deems appropriate of the active workings of coal mines
				for the purpose of obtaining compliance with the provisions of this title. All
				samples by the Secretary shall be taken by a personal dust monitor that
				measures, records and displays in real time the concentration of respirable
				dust to which the miner wearing the device is exposed, and shall include the
				sampling of areas, occupations or persons. There is authorized to be
				appropriated to the Secretary $30,000,000 to purchase personal dust monitors
				for the purposes of the preceding sentence. For the purposes of determining
				compliance with the exposure limit for respirable dust, only a single sample
				shall be required to determine non-compliance, and there shall be no adjustment
				for measurement error in the measured level of respirable dust.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H4B150EE1AB0F41288469AB069790D61C" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>At intervals established by the
				Secretary, each operator of a coal mine shall take accurate samples of the
				amount of respirable dust in the mine atmosphere to which each miner in the
				active workings of such mine is exposed to identify sources of exposure so that
				the operator can take corrective action and assure that the exposure of each
				mine is below the exposure limit. Under the provisions of this Act, all such
				samples shall be taken by a personal dust monitor that measures, records and
				displays the concentration of respirable dust to which the miner wearing the
				device is exposed, and may include samples of less than a full shift. The
				results of such sampling shall be transmitted to the Secretary in a manner
				established by him, and recorded by him in a manner that will assure
				application of the provisions of this section of the Act.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HE9E61BCB59064FD989521962FBF59FE4" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Each miner shall be equipped with a
				personal dust monitor that measures, records and displays in real time the
				concentration of respirable dust to which the miner wearing the device is
				exposed. Each miner shall be permitted to adjust his work activities whenever
				necessary to keep his exposure to respirable coal dust, as measured, recorded
				and displayed by such device, at all times at or below the permitted
				concentration.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H753D03EF9DD74AA6888666251B11FD00"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Effective on the
				date of enactment of the S–MINER Act, each operator of a coal or other mine
				shall continuously maintain the concentration of respirable silica dust in the
				mine atmosphere during each shift to which each miner in the active workings of
				such mine is exposed at or below a time-weighted average of 0.05 milligrams of
				respirable silica dust per cubic meter of air averaged over ten hours or its
				dose-equivalent for shorter or longer period of time. For the purposes of this
				paragraph, compliance shall be determined by the sampling of areas, occupations
				or persons, only a single sample shall be required to determine non-compliance,
				and there shall be no adjustment for measurement error in the measured level of
				respirable silica dust. For the purposes of this paragraph, a ‘dose-equivalent’
				means the amount of dust that a miner would inhale during his work shift as if
				he were working for 10 hours, and the term ‘shift’ means portal-to-portal for
				underground mines and ‘bank to bank’ for other mines.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H9C70583652F34D55B116DF2CCE8337A8"><enum>(c)</enum><text>Respiratory
				equipment approved by the Secretary and the Secretary of Health and Human
				Services shall be made available to all persons whenever exposed to
				concentrations of respirable dust or silica in excess of the levels required to
				be maintained under this section. Use of respirators shall not be substituted
				for environmental control measures in the active workings. Each operator shall
				maintain a supply of respiratory equipment adequate to deal with occurrences of
				concentrations of respirable dust and silica in the mine atmosphere in excess
				of the levels required to be maintained under this section.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H6545793046484674A8E99D24C7E8CF64"><enum>(d)</enum><text>Each operator
				shall report and certify to the Secretary at such intervals as the Secretary
				may require as to the conditions in the active workings of a coal mine,
				including, the average number of working hours worked during each shift, the
				quantity and velocity of air regularly reaching the working faces, the method
				of mining, the amount and pressure of the water, if any, reaching the working
				faces, and the number, location, and type of sprays, if any,
				used.</text>
						</subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H17C9DC687C004D3BAA55CD3D46AAC295"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming
			 amendment</header><text>Section 205 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/845">30 U.S.C. 845</external-xref>) is repealed.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H74B5A81E2B164CB1B700B61076C201F9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Assessment on
			 program operations of cumulative impact of external requirements added since
			 1977</header><text>The Secretary shall request the National Academy of Sciences
			 to conduct a study of the impact on the mine safety and health responsibilities
			 of the Department of Labor of various statutes, executive orders, and memoranda
			 applicable to the issuance of rulemaking and guidance and to enforcement. The
			 study shall include an assessment of the Equal Access to Justice Act, the
			 Regulatory Flexibility Act, the Small Business Regulatory Enforcement Fairness
			 Act, the Data Quality Act, the Paperwork Reduction Act, the Unfunded Mandates
			 Reform Act, the Federal Advisory Committee Act, the Congressional Review Act,
			 Executive Order 12866, Executive Order 13422, and memoranda from the Office of
			 Management and Budget on guidance, risk assessment and cost analysis. The
			 Secretary shall request that the National Academy of Sciences consult widely
			 with experts in administrative law and other disciplines knowledgeable about
			 such requirements, and to quantify to the extent possible the costs to miners
			 of the aforementioned requirements. The Secretary shall further request that
			 recommendations be included in the report, and that such report and
			 recommendations be completed, and forwarded to the Congress, no later than 21
			 months after the date of enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HC66D19920934487700DB80D2AE7C00"><enum>8.</enum><header>Other health
			 requirements</header>
			<subsection id="H11F86A83E05141D5AA94F7334882009E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Air
			 contaminants</header><text>Section 101 of (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/811">30 U.S.C. 811</external-xref>) is amended by adding
			 at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H45821E3B2B8043A1AC4DE74E4BDB9ED8" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H4CE887FD169C4754BBF85191DBD439BA"><enum>(f)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding the other requirements of
				this section, not later than 30 days of the enactment of the S–MINER Act, the
				National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health shall forward to the
				Secretary its Recommended Exposure Limits (RELs) for chemical and other hazards
				to which miners may be exposed, along with the research data and other
				necessary information. Within 30 days of receipt of this information, the
				Secretary shall to adopt such recommended exposure limits as the Permissible
				Exposure Limits (PELs) for application in the mining industry. The National
				Institute of Occupational Safety and Health shall annually submit to the
				Secretary any additional or revised recommended exposure limits for all
				chemicals and other hazards to which miners may be exposed, and the Secretary
				shall be obligated to adopt such exposure limits as PELs for application in the
				mining industry within 30 days of receipt of such information. Upon petition
				from miners or mine operators providing credible evidence that feasibility may
				be an issue for the industry as a whole, the Secretary may review the
				feasibility of any PEL established pursuant to this paragraph before placing it
				into effect and, following public notice and comment, make necessary
				adjustments thereto, provided that the adjusted standard is as protective as is
				feasible, and that the PEL shall go into effect as required by the other
				provisions of this paragraph if such action is not completed within one year.
				Moreover, upon petition from miners or mine operators providing credible
				evidence that a REL issued by the National Institute of Occupational Safety and
				Health lacks the specificity required to serve as a PEL pursuant to this Act,
				the Secretary may defer implementation of the requirements of this paragraph
				and shall promptly request National Institute of Occupational Safety and Health
				to recommend a sufficiently detailed REL, at which time the provisions of this
				paragraph shall be implemented. Nothing in this subsection shall limit the
				ability of the National Institute of Occupational Safety and Health to make
				such recommendations more frequently than 1 time per year, nor limit the
				Secretary from establishing requirements for chemical and other substances or
				health hazards in the mining industry that are more comprehensive and
				protective than those established pursuant to this subsection and in accordance
				with the other requirements of this
				section.</text>
					</subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H45F766733AA14A09BE8BD3FCCFB581D1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Asbestos</header><text>Section
			 101 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/811">30 U.S.C. 811</external-xref>) is further amended by adding at the end the
			 following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H19D530FE48B140998B0096864DB38003" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H2C8A35D4B00D4C6DAA5BE1D9BD74A36D"><enum>(g)</enum><text>The health
				standard for asbestos established by the Occupational Safety and Health
				Administration that is set forth in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1910">section 1910.1001</external-xref> of title 29, Code of
				Federal Regulations, or any subsequent revision of that regulation, shall be
				adopted by the Secretary for application in the mining industry not later than
				30 days of the enactment of the S–MINER Act. Nothing in this paragraph shall
				preclude the Secretary from adopting regulations to address asbestos hazards to
				miners not covered by the regulations of the Occupational Safety and Health
				Administration.</text>
					</subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HDDD725D397BC49FA8D0016EFFBC0B764"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Hazard
			 communication</header><text>Section 101 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/811">30 U.S.C. 811</external-xref>) is further amended by
			 adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="HD2AF6B1AF1B648E396F9629066678FE4" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H94E48C2EEA9D405BBF6CA9A47E5E98BD"><enum>(h)</enum><text>Unless and until
				there is additional rulemaking pursuant to the requirements of this section,
				the Secretary shall apply the provisions of the interim final rule of October
				3, 2000, concerning hazard communication, in lieu of the final rule of June 21,
				2002, concerning hazard
				communication.</text>
					</subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HD5E0908097E943E987D0813F00E65D54"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Study on Miner
			 substance abuse issues that pose safety risks</header>
				<paragraph id="H9287B4D3DB47480DA554732B2443E9E8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The
			 Secretary of Labor shall conduct a study providing expert review and
			 recommendations of policies designed to deal with substance abuse by miners,
			 including the causes, nature, and extent of such abuse, its impact on mine
			 safety and health, best practices for treatment, rehabilitation, and substance
			 abuse testing policies, and the adequacy of State laws and approaches. In
			 conducting such study, the Secretary shall solicit the views of and consult
			 with all interested parties, including miners, miners’ representatives, mine
			 operators, appropriate State agencies, and public health and substance abuse
			 experts.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H34F6238BEE1D49708E009E62250077CA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not
			 later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary
			 shall report the findings and recommendations of the study to the Committee on
			 Education and Labor of the House of Representatives and the Committee on
			 Health, Education, Labor and Pensions of the Senate.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H9125A0F29DA54249AEDEF57F776500A3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional
			 authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If, as a result of
			 the study, the Secretary determines it to be feasible and effective, the
			 Secretary shall be authorized to establish a program, in consultation with the
			 parties described in paragraph (1), within the Mine Safety and Health
			 Administration to provide for substance abuse testing of miners as well as
			 rehabilitation and treatment of miners suffering from substance abuse.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDBC22E517EF94A3485C7D84CD3E90B8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grants for
			 rehabilitation</header>
				<paragraph id="H83749D442CA540018347AF28CA6FC17E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Secretary of Labor, in consultation with the
			 Secretary of Health and Human Services, is authorized to award grants to
			 appropriate entities and programs for the purpose of providing rehabilitation
			 services to current and former miners suffering from mental health impairments,
			 including drug addiction and substance abuse issues, which may have been caused
			 or exacerbated by their work as miners. The Secretary shall ensure such funds
			 are directed to those regions of the country most in need of such
			 assistance.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HC137CAA854DF4334814872735DE5F793"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorization of
			 Appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the
			 Secretary of Labor $10,000,000 to carry out the grant program authorized by
			 this subsection.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE2F364ACFCE3402B91B733F87D5EA85"><enum>9.</enum><header>Mine safety
			 program fund</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title I is
			 further amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H75BF20D867BB4250BDEDEE2DBDCD196" style="OLC">
				<section id="HEFC5D5647BA04F6E98AAB400B3DC3CED"><enum>117.</enum><header>Mine safety
				program fund</header>
					<subsection id="HF807AA3A3273493B97B430B9EE674F84"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Treasury a
				separate account to be known as the <quote>Mine Safety Program Fund</quote> (in
				this section referred to as the <quote>Fund</quote>).</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="H71928E29680E4E998BC675807FC9252"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transfers to the
				Fund</header><text>There shall be deposited in the Fund—</text>
						<paragraph id="HBFDC5AB36BFF41BA861779C4F73EF8BE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>all penalties
				collected under section 110; and</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HD0AA8B5899C3482E8B00CEC1E501BDC5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any gifts,
				bequests, or donations to the Fund from private entities or individuals, which
				the Secretary of the Treasury is authorized to accept for deposit into the
				Fund, except that the Secretary is not authorized to accept any such gift,
				bequest, or donation that—</text>
							<subparagraph commented="no" id="HBB6AF739E6C1405E882660C78B204541"><enum>(A)</enum><text>attaches
				conditions inconsistent with applicable laws or regulations; or</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC5EB0FFC2C104CC9BAC3122E83E2532"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is conditioned upon
				or would require the expenditure of appropriated funds that are not available
				to the Secretary of Labor.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6FE6CC2F640940D09B83E6939428544D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Expenditures</header><text>Amounts
				in the Fund shall be available, as provided in appropriations Acts, only for
				inspections and investigations conducted pursuant to section
				103.</text>
					</subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body>
	<attestation>
		<attestation-group>
			<attestation-date chamber="House" date="20080116">Passed the House of
			 Representatives January 16, 2008.</attestation-date>
			<attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor>
			<role>Clerk.</role>
		</attestation-group>
	</attestation>
	<endorsement display="yes">
	</endorsement>
</bill>


