<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H8C71DFE7D65F421BA2344DCECF0B514" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 6221 EH: Improving Veterans’ Opportunity in Education and Business Act of 2008</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 6221</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to include in each contract the Secretary enters for the acquisition of goods and services a provision that requires the contractee to comply with the contracting goals and preferences for small business concerns owned or controlled by veterans, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HB73092DFA7BC48E8B8B369B2CC7D3CE9" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HFBC8C54B2A7D470F85A46B79D87C9145" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Veterans’ Opportunity in Education and Business Act of 2008</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H9BB637E2B7E141718D1201D700B2252C" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Contracting goals and preferences for veteran-owned small business concerns</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/8127">Section 8127</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB16A3066D9B0459ABFE30097C84F1CB2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (j) and (k) as subsections (k) and (l), respectively; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H54C4FD1CCD754018A77D00A3856529E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (i) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE6FCBE989D2E4344AEAFE4F7F5D0E4FD"> 
<subsection id="H34F876F7E3F6438B8C48B351CC35A85F"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Applicability of requirements to contracts</header> 
<paragraph id="H9F835BC2E3ED4382932BAB28E18168A3" commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>If the Secretary enters, on or after June 1, 2007, into a contract, memorandum of understanding, agreement, or other arrangement with any governmental entity or person to acquire goods or services, or both, the Secretary shall include in such contract, memorandum, agreement, or other arrangement a requirement that the entity or person will comply with the provisions of this section in acquiring such goods or services, or both.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H92487CA3403F4DBEBBF000323774C7F" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Secretary shall take such action as may be necessary to ensure that the efforts to comply with this section of the Department and governmental entities and persons to which paragraph (1) applies are coordinated.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0801E24F301C405BA0E2107EA36DA345" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall modify contracts, memoranda of understanding, agreements, and other arrangements of the Department in effect on the date of enactment of the Improving Veterans’ Opportunity in Education and Business Act of 2008 to comply with this subsection.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCA8386D7D0294E8D893E83A39188FCF3" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to supersede or otherwise affect the authorities provided by and under the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/631">15 U.S.C. 631 et seq.</external-xref>)</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H1918E2AFA21A4CE6B6F226740038007F" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Five-year pilot program for on-campus workstudy positions</header> 
<subsection id="HD3F9563FAC784B2700259514CAB78142"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of Pilot Program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct a five-year pilot project to test the feasibility and advisability of expanding the scope of qualifying workstudy activities for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/3485">section 3485(a)(4)</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, including workstudy positions available on site at educational institutions.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H920DECBCDED8452C8BD1364CDC2CBC4C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Type of Workstudy Positions</header><text>The workstudy positions referred to in subsection (a) may include positions in academic departments (including positions as tutors or research, teaching, and lab assistants) and in student services (including positions in career centers and financial aid, campus orientation, cashiers, admissions, records, and registration offices).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4E2D1C5126764B31BABB11CB461CC626"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary shall issue regulations to carry out the pilot project under this section, including regulations providing for the supervision of workstudy positions referred to in subsection (a) by appropriate personnel of the Department.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB774EBB8833B444F92FF5352E76A52B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2009 through 2013 to carry out the pilot project under this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEE16EFE63BB94E8086AA269D264FCEA8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, this section shall not be carried out with any funds provided for or under any authority of the Readjustment benefits program described by the list of Appropriated Entitlements and Mandatories for Fiscal Year 1997 contained in the Conference Report to accompany H.R. 2015 of the 105th Congress, the Balanced Budget Act of 1997 (H. Report 105-217). Instead, no funds shall be obligated for the purpose of carrying out this section except discretionary funds appropriated specifically for the purpose of carrying out this section in appropriation Acts enacted after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H13147AF7E95844FFB785FA7862182709" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Military occupational specialty transition (MOST) program</header> 
<subsection id="H5887790CE6CE4F48B33F335EEC40B4B7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/36">chapter 36</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/3687">section 3687</external-xref> the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7F73C6EE54564E61A44D6544E5CB2B02"> 
<section id="H2A04AB923BA14045AE6EA41FC5814F02"><enum>3687A.</enum><header>Military occupational specialty transition (MOST) program</header> 
<subsection id="H638841CE94804567B756FEAB03A5591D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment; eligibility</header> 
<paragraph id="H0DE0C6E3AFD643BF9136ED769C7ECCFA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Secretary shall carry out a program of training to provide eligible veterans with skills relevant to the job market.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB4B2F836237A472AA79DB0C9ABC60063"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible veteran</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <quote>eligible veteran</quote> means any veteran if—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF5B8DE4251744ED28E6D9352006B0028"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such veteran’s military occupational specialty at the time of discharge is determined by the Secretary to have limited transferability to the civilian job market;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4E95D03F8FB5458787E53536B40A9DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such veteran is not otherwise eligible for education or training services under this title;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2CA2AC24A1E84D549392A2C67D5CA4D6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>such veteran has not acquired a marketable skill since leaving military service;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H08AC6D72189747C6004C5D863BD99CF6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such veteran was discharged under conditions not less than general under honorable conditions; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE56E98956A7C4DB983D3AD8F631FCA10"><enum>(E)</enum> 
<clause id="H29AF5F36A9EE40EA8D58F34D7A6B717" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such veteran has been unemployed for at least 90 of the 180 days preceding the date of application for the program established under this section; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC3D248A3869D4C50B600E300F2E724B6" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the maximum hourly rate of pay of such veteran during such 180-day period is not more than 150 percent of the Federal minimum wage.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H48FD968D90FC4481AA0009ECBD7E10CA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>MOST program</header><text>The program established under this section shall provide for payments to employers who provide for eligible veterans a program of apprenticeship or on-the-job training if—</text> 
<paragraph id="H99A1779BB8654899ACB9E3903883338C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such program is approved as provided in paragraph (1) or (2) of section 3687(a) of this title;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H814C5116981C47248897AE0019AA5217"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the rate of pay for veterans participating in the program is not less than the rate of pay for nonveterans in similar jobs; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H87A976C834B046228FDBE2AB635C2137" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Secretary reasonably expects that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H66B619BC42AA45DCB42C7C24FCA42512"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the veteran will be qualified for employment in that field upon completion of training; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB9DA0A0F43014F020002BE78C22F9F6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the employer providing the program will hire the veteran at the completion of training.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H67BF6F1BFFAC47D0A394EE86A8005CE2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Payments to employers</header> 
<paragraph id="HDC84A1AD734D46CD8D4EA0A1725092BA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Secretary shall enter into contracts with employers to provide programs of apprenticeship or on-the-job training which meet the requirements of this section. Such contract shall provide for the payment of the amounts described in subsection (b) to employers whose programs meet such requirements.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0AEEF8FB96AC47AA877723874DDA32A1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount of payments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount paid under this section with respect to any eligible veteran for any period shall be 50 percent of the wages paid by the employer to such veteran for such period. Wages shall be calculated on an hourly basis.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H678E81A690354C98BDE48007B72D74D9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Amount and duration of payments</header> 
<subparagraph id="HB01983E5E7E44CBFAC8EE8FEC2A6D881"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B)—</text> 
<clause id="HACACED30116247DB0073C4A27C0145B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the amount paid under this section with respect to a veteran participating in the program established under this section may not exceed $20,000 in the aggregate and $1,666.67 per month; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1541535EE2BE4B10AC79C6B5519E786F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such payments may only be made during the first 12 months of such veteran’s participation in the program.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7607E639458A4E55B435617E5BAA442C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Veterans participating on less than full-time basis</header><text>In the case of a veteran participating in the program on a less than full-time basis, the Secretary may extend the number of months of payments under subparagraph (A) and proportionally adjust the amount of such payments, but the maximum amount paid with respect to a veteran may not exceed the maximum amount of $20,000 and the maximum amount of such payments may not exceed 24 months.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H668BDA4F12514BACBF9D04E9B2586EFB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Payments made on quarterly basis</header><text>Payments under this section shall be made on a quarterly basis. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCF571E2105B04E3388D3C2E8465313A1"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Employer report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each employer providing a program of apprenticeship or on-the-job training pursuant to this section shall submit to the Secretary on a quarterly basis a report certifying the wages paid to eligible veterans under such program (which shall be certified by the veteran as being correct) and containing such other information as the Secretary may specify. Such report shall be submitted in the form and manner required by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFC3768DBA6FC4CBCB5A74842E5452D57"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated $60,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2009 through 2018 to carry out this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H15250FE3CE7D43B1B54D084FE740B4C1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall include a detailed description of activities carried out under this section in the annual report prepared by the Veterans Benefits Administration.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0AD859BBAC904FF6AC5CE6A6D4D3603E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Separate accounting</header><text>The Department shall have a separate line item in budget proposals of the Department for funds to be appropriated to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H125ACB75CF364BFD9377508304B9D6DD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 3687 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1E6CB0E12654455D840029D672B8403E"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">3687A. Military occupational specialty transition (MOST) program.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5A7D86A6879A46D4ABA93419088811D9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header> 
<paragraph id="H18D4F55C5FA04AA78EBDD86281F48B00" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (a)(1) of section 3034 of such title is amended by striking <quote>and 3687</quote> and inserting <quote>3687, and 3687A</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H15CC167B30DA449F8D51959539C91468" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Subsections (a)(1) and (c) of section 3241 of such title are each amended by striking <quote>section 3687</quote> and inserting <quote>sections 3687 and 3687A</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA5E3B85D9AB34090B75049392BCAF3AF" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Subsection (d)(1) of section 3672 of such title is amended by striking <quote>and 3687</quote> and inserting <quote>3687, and 3687A</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB2D96D80293A4925BE50AC6800A8117D" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (3) of section 4102A(b) of such title is amended by striking <quote>section 3687</quote> and inserting <quote>section 3687 or 3687A</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20080729" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives July 31, 2008.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 


