<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H25F8D2C0A97345CB9124CB3EE0AFFFB2" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 251 EH: Truth in Caller ID Act of 2007</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 251</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Communications Act of 1934 to prohibit manipulation of caller identification information, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H36F6052F066F4F67B9B3EA04419B139" style="OLC"> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB20C95DBCCB24B59A602515F1863E946" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Truth in Caller ID Act of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text></section>
<section id="H9FF22D5D13B5443A8F5B9C6BB9EB1FD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition regarding manipulation of caller identification information</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 227 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/227">47 U.S.C. 227</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H84DB9183F9354257A22FFCDEA27DE2A0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (e), (f), and (g) as subsections (f), (g), and (h), respectively; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H00B88A3B850048798C4E25D97E66E700"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (d) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HADFBE91A128E4D39854B20A204BDF8CB" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HD096D5A6BE094F33A6DAC0DB1DCA4576"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prohibition on provision of deceptive caller identification information</header> 
<paragraph id="H3DCF8067223F44B79C28A1007D99C709"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful for any person within the United States, in connection with any telecommunications service or VOIP service, to cause any caller identification service to transmit misleading or inaccurate caller identification information, with the intent to defraud or cause harm.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H147897CA8311476B83FDEDC8FE712D79"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Protection for blocking caller identification information</header><text>Nothing in this subsection may be construed to prevent or restrict any person from blocking the capability of any caller identification service to transmit caller identification information.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H661CE23E1BF7439E8F4635000090DB90"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Regulations</header> 
<subparagraph id="HBF1C66AD4D414CA0B24C6ED7F3DFC486"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the enactment of this subsection, the Commission shall prescribe regulations to implement this subsection.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFF01B7E8B73E480698C7B5295FD2892"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consideration of related regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In conducting the proceeding to prescribe the regulations required by subparagraph (A) of this paragraph, the Commission shall examine whether the Commission’s regulations under subsection (b)(2)(B) of this section should be revised to require non-commercial calls to residential telephone lines using an artificial or pre-recorded voice to deliver a message to transmit caller identification information that is not misleading or inaccurate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3EA30D3BCF3740708B03C0113179E6A4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Effect on other laws</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to authorize or prohibit any investigative, protective, or intelligence activities performed in connection with official duties, and in accordance with all applicable laws, by a law enforcement agency of the United States, a State, or a political subdivision of a State, or by an intelligence agency of the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H095C4300D35548D38EAA000501178E32"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Savings provision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except for paragraph (3)(B), nothing in this subsection may be construed to affect or alter the application of the Commission’s regulations regarding the requirements for transmission of caller identification information, issued pursuant to the Telephone Consumer Protection Act of 1991 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/102/243">Public Law 102–243</external-xref>) and the amendments made by such Act.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAF31775E09DB499C9C69CA22657F00B1"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this subsection:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAF8E82D1A4614E11B1C4CD1E07F70784"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Caller identification information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>caller identification information</quote> means information provided to an end user by a caller identification service regarding the telephone number of, or other information regarding the origination of, a call made using a telecommunications service or VOIP service.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2D04F1B70F734B4CAF39AE28EF275843"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Caller identification service</header><text>The term <quote>caller identification service</quote> means any service or device designed to provide the user of the service or device with the telephone number of, or other information regarding the origination of, a call made using a telecommunications service or VOIP service. Such term includes automatic number identification services.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF23C6779353E4F69971166CE8269649"><enum>(C)</enum><header>VOIP service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>VOIP service</term> means a service that—</text> 
<clause id="H4C86562A809A414C8BCB1D089695B467"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides real-time voice communications transmitted through end user equipment using TCP/IP protocol, or a successor protocol, for a fee or without a fee;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8EFE7E487DD542C2BE6CF94DBF39C3C3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is offered to the public, or such classes of users as to be effectively available to the public (whether part of a bundle of services or separately); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5CAB9BD3EDD94397A475A2561D8E40FA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>has the capability to originate traffic to, or terminate traffic from, the public switched telephone network.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section>
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20070612" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives June 12, 2007.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 


