<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8894DB29560149DEAD444F7CA09C100" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 2346 IH: To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to establish a process for determining whether a geographic area is sufficiently served by the national cemeteries located in that geographic area.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-05-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
<session>1st Session</session>
<legis-num>H. R. 2346</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070516">May 16, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000440">Mr. Fossella</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to establish a process for determining whether a geographic area is sufficiently served by the national cemeteries located in that geographic area.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HA83EA1BE98774486002BA51399B66FF" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HCCA77C08C24E402B8DFA49872F5E44AE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Determination by Secretary of Veterans Affairs of whether a geographic area is served by national cemeteries located in that area</header> 
<subsection id="H1692E196A0504ED8A69CF669C013693"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Process required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall establish a process for determining whether a geographic area is sufficiently served by the national cemeteries located in that geographic area. Such process shall take into account each of the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HE2606E0C249C4F6295291C2E9B8F0100"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of veterans living in the geographic area.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5450CC3BEBA54E648B37E57F007F7038"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The average distance a resident of the geographic area must travel to reach the nearest national cemetery.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE299E2FCB3FE4286897B865E8EA7571D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The population density of the geographic area.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H18AA158D0EEE455D879307B27FEA994F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The average amount of time it takes a resident of the geographic area to travel to the nearest national cemetery.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H666775DB3B4042B185232942C936283B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The availability of public transportation for purposes of traveling to national cemeteries located in the geographic area.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H28F41A7ADE164A8B90F1530010267F77"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The average amount of any fees charged to an individual traveling on the major roads leading to the national cemeteries located in the geographic area.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H263FBC90CC904D7B8BD9E00000DAF661"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consideration of alternatives</header><text>In the case of a geographic area in which sufficient land is not available to the Secretary for the establishment of a cemetery, the Secretary shall consider alternatives to establishing a cemetery, including establishing a mausoleum.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


