<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HAD9A9B9E5BFD4C1BA85138504F30FB7B" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 1102 IH: Total Force Educational Assistance Enhancement and Integration Act of 2007</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-02-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 1102</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070215">February 15, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000672">Mr. Snyder</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001236">Mr. Boozman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001037">Ms. Herseth</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000030">Ms. Loretta Sanchez of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000569">Mr. Reynolds</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000111">Mr. Latham</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to recodify as part of that title certain educational assistance programs for members of the reserve components of the Armed Forces, to improve such programs, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H711F3AD34BCA4E45894F44C083590200" style="OLC"> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H081BBD1813774398B484BFC6F6CFE33B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Total Force Educational Assistance Enhancement and Integration Act of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text> </section>
<section id="H450D7DB33EC54FDBA542FEE81260BF46"><enum>2.</enum><header>Recodification in title <enum-in-header>38</enum-in-header>, United States Code, and improvement of certain educational assistance programs for members of the Reserve components</header> 
<subsection id="H614E757A989E4BA89301A42DBF2521AF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this section is to recodify in title 38, United States Code, the provisions of chapters 1606 and 1607 of title 10, United States Code, relating to educational assistance for members of the reserve components of the Armed Forces, and to make certain improvements in such provisions as so recodified.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H796FEAD832784BBDA3562D76406D1F8C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recodification and Improvement of Educational Assistance Programs</header> 
<paragraph id="HDA7C96DFEE024289AD4B307FD3528EF9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Part III of title 38, United States Code, is amended by inserting after chapter 32 the following new chapter:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H7990DB6360E6489D9283B08B80003A" style="USC"> 
<chapter id="HF6FC09A483D34AD29663EA72FD88E15B"><enum>33</enum><header>EDUCATIONAL ASSISTANCE FOR MEMBERS OF THE RESERVE COMPONENTS</header> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="subchapter">Subchapter I—Members of the Selected Reserve</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3301. Educational assistance program: purpose.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3302. Eligibility.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3302A. Eligibility of individuals entitled to educational assistance under former <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1606">chapter 1606</external-xref> of title 10.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3303. Amount.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3304. Termination of assistance.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3305. Failure to participate satisfactorily; penalties.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3306. Reports to Congress.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="subchapter">Subchapter II—Reserve Component Members Supporting Contingency Operations and Certain Other Operations</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3321. Purpose.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3322. Educational assistance program.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3323. Eligibility.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3323A. Eligibility of individuals entitled to educational assistance under former <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1607">chapter 1607</external-xref> of title 10.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3324. Amount.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3325. Time limitation for use of entitlement.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3326. Termination of assistance.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="subchapter">Subchapter III—Administrative Matters</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3341. Administration of programs.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">3342. Funding.</toc-entry> </toc> 
<subchapter id="H3C4265D9A90A4EF0BF165800286F8C93"><enum>I</enum><header>Members of the Selected Reserve</header> 
<section id="H44C2677A5C91479B9E91EC1FC1E1AAE3"><enum>3301.</enum><header>Educational assistance program: purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">To encourage membership in units of the Selected Reserve of the Ready Reserve, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Homeland Security, with respect to the Coast Guard when it is not operating as a service in the Navy, shall carry out under this subchapter a program to provide educational assistance to members of the Selected Reserve of the Ready Reserve of the Armed Forces who agree to remain members of the Selected Reserve for a period of not less than six years.</text> </section>
<section id="H84FB2AA478CD445DA5E52DFB88C1E301"><enum>3302.</enum><header>Eligibility</header> 
<subsection id="H48BA6BDACC7747B7B0EF978F69882F78"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>A person is entitled to educational assistance under the program of educational assistance under this subchapter if the person—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC000E2D7649E48F0B3E4CB42AD25AED2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>after October 1, 2008—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE5D4AC825ACF4D71B7E25F367F956F4E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enlists, reenlists, or extends an enlistment as a Reserve for service in the Selected Reserve for a period of not less than six years; or</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC8B24135396545EA993F62AFBA5CE577"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is appointed as, or is serving as, a reserve officer and agrees to serve in the Selected Reserve for a period of not less than six years in addition to any other period of obligated service in the Selected Reserve to which the person may be subject; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD71F14FC2A7840DD00E83163AADCCF00"><enum>(2)</enum><text>before applying for benefits under this subchapter, has completed the requirements of a secondary school diploma (or an equivalency certificate).</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HEC3EEE08D2F7426AA92780E246B547B7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Completion of Active Duty for Training</header><text>Educational assistance may not be provided to a member under this subchapter until the member has completed the initial period of active duty for training required of the member.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HCA37777376DF4E159CC8BC67D7E67BD5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Notice on Entitlement</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HCE9846D9F7884D88AE875FEF62C98418"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Each person who becomes entitled to educational assistance under subsection (a) shall at the time the person becomes so entitled be given a statement in writing summarizing the provisions of this subchapter and stating clearly and prominently the substance of sections 3304 and 3305 of this title as such sections may apply to the person.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC8A47245DFBB4EF7984647109ED24900" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In accordance with a memorandum of understanding entered into between the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of Defense shall transmit a notice of entitlement for each member so entitled to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H75E3CC855857459F99D5A242125C7618"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Inapplicability of Certain Duty Toward Entitlement</header><text>A person may not receive credit under this subchapter for service (in any grade) on full-time active duty or full-time National Guard duty for the purpose of organizing, administering, recruiting, instructing, or training the reserve components in a position which is included in the end strength required to be authorized each year by <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/115">section 115(a)(1)(B)</external-xref> of title 10.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HB1B312AEEDCF49B694AF70D8C8B0D832"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Bar to Duplication of Educational Assistance</header><text>The provisions of section 3033(a) of this title, relating to a bar on duplication of receipt of certain educational assistance benefits, apply with respect to the receipt of educational assistance under this subchapter.</text> </subsection></section>
<section id="H8AD9546B676543AB88E3EF533C60786E"><enum>3302A.</enum><header>Eligibility of individuals entitled to educational assistance under former chapter <enum-in-header>1606</enum-in-header> of title <enum-in-header>10</enum-in-header></header> 
<subsection id="H855E10AE70014085A20036FFBA223CBA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>Subject to the provisions of this section, any individual entitled to educational assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1606">chapter 1606</external-xref> of title 10 as of October 1, 2008, shall be entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter thereafter for the programs of education, in the amounts, and subject to the conditions and limitations provided in sections 3303 through 3305 of this title.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H971BB6AD098A40CE9BD2BFF0209D71A5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation on Months of Entitlement</header><text>The number of months of entitlement to educational assistance under this subchapter of an individual described in subsection (a) by reason of this section as of October 1, 2008, shall be equal to the number of months of entitlement of such individual to educational assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1606">chapter 1606</external-xref> of title 10 that remain unutilized by such individual as of that date.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H4C3F95D6BD4F46D0B51B9E90809EB026"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Time Limitation for Use of Entitlement</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9D62637C02B1419FB5A9F3854B75E168"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the provisions of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/16133">section 16133</external-xref> of title 10, as in effect on September 30, 2008, shall apply to the time for the use by an individual described in subsection (a) of entitlement to educational assistance under this subchapter by reason of this section.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H257853855B8D46EE97F8AA5C45B5BEB2" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Clause (1) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/16133">section 16133(a)</external-xref> of title 10, as in effect on September 30, 2008, shall not apply to the time for the use by an individual described in subsection (a) of entitlement to educational assistance under this subchapter by reason of this section.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H8657D40E780F494088404329596E5244"><enum>3303.</enum><header>Amount</header> 
<subsection id="H7D98A7839A214BDC9CC0C6449FDCAEDB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H333653EC35AC49BD990075005E19DEB9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Subject to the provisions of this section, the Secretary shall provide for payment to each person entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter who is pursuing a program of education described by subsection (b) of an educational assistance allowance at the following rates:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9E9F20FA542C4C38B2B82E26E3DBBD21" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$309 (as increased from time to time under paragraphs (2) and (3)) per month for each month of full-time pursuit of a program of education.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5B467ED5A3F64FF79D91FF5454AB1D5E" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$231 (as increased from time to time under paragraphs (2) and (3)) per month for each month of three-quarter-time pursuit of a program of education.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H54DB1EF8DBE649EFBB55377B0419FED0" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>$153 (as increased from time to time under paragraphs (2) and (3)) per month for each month of half-time pursuit of a program of education.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFFA4824BA74740BDB8C2C63EA00D627" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>$77.25 (as increased from time to time under paragraphs (2) and (3)) per month for each month of less than half-time pursuit of a program of education, except that no payment may be made to a person for less than half-time pursuit if tuition assistance is otherwise available to the person for such pursuit from the military department concerned.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H708EEEAD432240FC9EEC273B0018A3BF" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>With respect to any fiscal year, the Secretary shall provide a percentage increase (rounded to the nearest dollar) in the rates payable under subparagraphs (A) through (D) of paragraph (1) equal to the percentage increase provided under subsection (h) of section 3015 of this title to the rates payable under subsection (a) of that section.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H657ACD15756244F8821B6D4D0169421B" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In the event of any increase by law (other than an increase under paragraph (2)) in the rates of basic educational assistance payable under section 3015(a) of this title, effective for months beginning on or after the month in which such increase goes into effect the Secretary shall provide a percentage increase (rounded to the nearest dollar) in the rates payable under subparagraphs (A) through (D) of paragraph (1) equal to such percentage increase in such rates of basic educational assistance by law.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H679201E7410F4897A2001D1967DA8EA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorized Education Programs</header><text>Educational assistance may be provided under this subchapter for pursuit of any program of education that is an approved program of education for purposes of chapter 30 of this title.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H40E9D6C8F7764AB79BB375C502FD3042"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Maximum Months of Assistance</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H6E1BB7FBCCAB49E7ABF96EFDFB29D5DE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Subject to section 3695 of this title, the maximum number of months of educational assistance that may be provided to any person under this subchapter is 36 (or the equivalent thereof in part-time educational assistance).</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H172D43DA10014994B06B379E4D8FD400" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD274413362A14A659901970217A532D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this subchapter or chapter 36 of this title, any payment of an educational assistance allowance described in subparagraph (B) shall not—</text> 
<clause id="HFFAF6E4A1DD14BFFBC0300FD23B32086" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be charged against the entitlement of a person under this subchapter; or</text> </clause>
<clause id="HA680AB277D244F7284BB419BBE3B4E0" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>be counted toward the aggregate period for which section 3695 of this title limits a person’s receipt of assistance.</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB405832434734AB3BDDA7209235420BC" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The payment of an educational assistance allowance referred to in subparagraph (A) is the payment of such an allowance to a person for pursuit of a course or courses under this subchapter if the Secretary finds that the person—</text> 
<clause id="HCDE74B6F3C584F9A9C9FB676B1E9FDF2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>had to discontinue such course pursuit as a result of being ordered to serve on active duty under section 12301(a), 12301(d), 12301(g), 12302, or 12304 of title 10; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="HEAC833153A224331842923C2BE5E7380"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>failed to receive credit or training time toward completion of the person’s approved educational, professional, or vocational objective as a result of having to discontinue, as described in clause (i), the person’s course pursuit.</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0CABD3C5E3EF43D100AF3B83949E08D" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The period for which, by reason of this paragraph, an educational assistance allowance is not charged against entitlement or counted toward the applicable aggregate period under section 3695 of this title shall not exceed the portion of the period of enrollment in the course or courses for which the person involved failed to receive credit or with respect to which such person lost training time, as determined under subparagraph (B)(ii).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H29F4818E48124EB4B286004DBAECB61C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Apprenticeships; On-Job Training</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HFD266BE9831942579BBF009D248D8584"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Educational assistance is payable under this subchapter to a person entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter for pursuit of a full-time program of apprenticeship or other on-job training.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H91F616E116C74DBFA2B0A08644682937" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HB3F86962C25543878416D1F02D46AA5B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For purposes of this subchapter, the rate of payment of educational assistance allowances, and the charge against entitlement for receipt of such allowances, under this subsection shall be governed by the provisions of section 3032(c) of this title.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9D68DF04E2BB4C68006C0069ABED836C" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In the administration of the provisions referred to in subparagraph (A) for purposes of this subchapter—</text> 
<clause id="H02F8CC9DB715475BACC400CCCDFE8EF3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>an individual</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to a person entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter;</text> </clause>
<clause id="H1C344749ACA5498D83C0AAA8E40452F9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>this chapter</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to this subchapter; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="H2F037A483B5E4E46874C77CF67E6B00"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>the monthly educational assistance allowance otherwise payable to such individual</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to the monthly educational assistance allowance otherwise payable to the person concerned under this subchapter (including any such allowance under subsection (a) and any such allowance under subsection (i)).</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HCB569579DEF5443B9DD5DA3122BDB55E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Correspondence Courses</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H208F3BAB2AB5406085009D0000223EE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Educational assistance is payable under this subchapter to a person entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter who enters into an agreement to pursue, and pursues, a program of education exclusively by correspondence.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6E374B6F82124F379652C7E8DD417C90" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H357F1D46B71C419FA637052F221E8B71"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For purposes of this subchapter, the rate of payment of educational assistance allowances, and the charge against entitlement for receipt of such allowances, under this subsection shall be governed by the provisions of section 3032(d) of this title.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7B9F581E995447BA9DC56CD9002E001C" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In the administration of the provisions referred to in subparagraph (A) for purposes of this subchapter—</text> 
<clause id="HA7A219520FA34158BD35897F06560745"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a reference <quote>an individual</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to a person entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter;</text> </clause>
<clause id="HCA097807FF634AFAABAD9E53CCC554E2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>this chapter</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to this subchapter; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="H5AD2503ED2F643CA94AC27889CD3620"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>the amount of monthly assistance the individual would otherwise be eligible to receive for full-time pursuit of an institutional course</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to the monthly educational assistance allowance otherwise payable to the person concerned under this subchapter (including any such allowance under subsection (a) and any such allowance under subsection (i)).</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC2BB5DA08F2642C79D15635C959B304E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Flight Training</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HCC722454DBA24481A6FFFD21EFC27500"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Educational assistance is payable under this subchapter to a person entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter for pursuit of a program of education consisting of exclusively of flight training approved under section 3034(d) of this title, subject to the conditions specified in paragraphs (2) and (4) of section 3032(e) of this title.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEA78728401F04150B1324C36B1F1A8B7" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H17507DEE330745B5A98B6854A4543C90"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For purposes of this subchapter, the rate of payment of educational assistance allowances, and the charge against entitlement for receipt of such allowances, under this subsection shall be governed by the provisions of section 3032(e) of this title.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD135C4811F1C46DA99F777F900E398A8" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In the administration of the provisions referred to in subparagraph (A) for purposes of this subchapter—</text> 
<clause id="H4633A5B9E1C442DB9E423EECE955FA6F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>an individual</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to a person entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter;</text> </clause>
<clause id="HD418C821E6C448A2838FCEA0E6DB25E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>this chapter</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to this subchapter; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="H31B547B62E5B4A9D8CA13BAD09A3C722"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>the monthly rate of education assistance which such individual would otherwise be paid</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to the monthly amount of educational assistance otherwise payable to the person concerned under this subchapter (including any such allowance under subsection (a) and any such allowance under subsection (i)).</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H26A1EF40E24C4EED0045C6E8B7BFA63"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Licensing and Certification Tests</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H36CD8663655E47CF83804F00009FEBC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Educational assistance is payable under this subchapter to a person entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter for a licensing or certification test described in section 3452(b) of this title.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA5664E7333024534A8D1E7EDF6AC48EB" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H753C4E2BE1C047B28CA7991BFACD18ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For purposes of this subchapter, the amount payable for a licensing or certification test, the charge against entitlement for receipt of such payment, and the effect of expiration of entitlement on payments, under this subsection is governed by the provisions of section 3032(f) of this title.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H064045DF13B84AF0B3B45E9DBE52C600" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In the administration of the provisions referred to in subparagraph (A) for purposes of this subchapter—</text> 
<clause id="H541C3A0F24AD4F00ABDA93E390625186"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>an individual</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to a person entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter;</text> </clause>
<clause id="H18269EBAA9A246BA8326F0A6D981D8CF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>this chapter</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to this subchapter; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="HFF2075AA2F074EF099A779B51ECB285D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>the full-time monthly institutional rate of educational assistance which such individual would otherwise be paid</quote> shall be deemed to a reference to the monthly amount of educational assistance allowance otherwise payable to the person concerned under this subchapter (including any such allowance under subsection (a) and any such allowance under subsection (i)).</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HFD8D09A3D29D4AA4ADEAFDB1409058F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Individualized Tutorial Assistance</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HEC975A97578B4A1292856100244BA551"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A person entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter is entitled to individualized tutorial assistance in accordance with the provisions of section 3492 of this title, subject to the conditions applicable to an eligible veteran under that section.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF644FC658B7E41770041CB5DA811B33E" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The amount of individualized tutorial assistance provided under this subsection shall be governed by the provisions of section 3019(b) of this title.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCB6245FEBADF4C18A0DB1495131DC99B" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7198C133C77842EBBB45FD0016383C4D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For purposes of this subchapter, the charge against entitlement of individualized tutorial assistance received under this subsection shall be governed by the provisions of section 3019(c) of this title.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA28C7AA2945C4F6EA3D48C37E6EB1872" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In the administration of the provisions referred to in subparagraph (A) for purposes of this subchapter—</text> 
<clause id="H133308A9F06A4F618C40A8B0649531BC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>an individual</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to a person entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter;</text> </clause>
<clause id="H93E76A6761E648BC9889235DF5DFCC0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>this chapter</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to this subchapter; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="H658CA8A1B2A54D5DA026BBA51B199013"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>the amount of monthly assistance which the individual is otherwise eligible to receive for full-time pursuit of an institutional course</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to the monthly amount of educational assistance allowance otherwise payable to the person concerned under this subchapter (including any such allowance under subsection (a) and any such allowance under subsection (i)).</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HEF9FCF3F33584FE2A38448AAA138B532"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Increased Rate of Assistance for Persons With Certain Skills</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4FE59A5A14D3428DA1AB401F6F467B12"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the case of a person who has a skill or specialty designated by the Secretary of Defense as a skill or specialty in which there is a critical shortage of personnel or for which it is difficult to recruit or, in the case of critical units, retain personnel, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs may increase the rate of the educational assistance allowance applicable to that person to such rate in excess of the rate prescribed under subparagraphs (A) through (D) of subsection (a)(1) as the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretary of Defense jointly consider appropriate, but the amount of any such increase may not exceed $350 per month.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3803E85B019344068C8C00CF63FD6E74" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In the case of a person who has a skill or specialty designated by the Secretary of Defense as a skill or specialty in which there is a critical shortage of personnel or for which it is difficult to recruit or, in the case of critical units, retain personnel, who is eligible for educational benefits under chapter 30 (other than section 3012) of this title and who meets the eligibility criteria specified in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of section 3302(a)(1) of this title, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs may increase the rate of the educational assistance allowance applicable to that person to such rate in excess of the rate prescribed under section 3015 of this title as the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretary of Defense jointly consider appropriate, but the amount of any such increase may not exceed $350 per month.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE7DB0903B2F14BC19186D3B915F1FF9B" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The authority provided by paragraphs (1) and (2) shall be exercised by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs under regulations prescribed jointly by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretary of Defense.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H886D3499D750438B87BB378CE78B370"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Continuation of Entitlement During Quarter or Semester of Exhaustion</header><text>The provisions of section 3031(f) of this title shall apply to the period of entitlement of a person to educational assistance under this subchapter.</text> </subsection></section>
<section id="H8DA2FDD5849942B895ABB22FCD323B"><enum>3304.</enum><header>Termination of assistance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Educational assistance may not be provided under this subchapter—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCD238B33AD2348D9B6773FC7C7D7B2C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to a member receiving financial assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2107">section 2107</external-xref> of title 10 as a member of the Senior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps program; or</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFFD99486C95D4B899D41B7EE15AEA997"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to a member who fails to participate satisfactorily in required training as a member of the Selected Reserve.</text> </paragraph></section>
<section id="HBD41C7DA18F54407A915120433956249"><enum>3305.</enum><header>Failure to participate satisfactorily; penalties</header> 
<subsection id="H315CCA5A143D4893968029C58903114F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>At the option of the Secretary of the military department concerned, a member of the Selected Reserve of an Armed Force who does not participate satisfactorily in required training as a member of the Selected Reserve during a term of enlistment or other period of obligated service that created entitlement of the member to educational assistance under this subchapter, and during which the member has received such assistance, may—</text> 
<paragraph id="HEE90E310FD1C47EC84FA598F267478FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be ordered to active duty for a period of two years or the period of obligated service the person has remaining under section 3302 of this title, whichever is less; or</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC2BEA668FFB643F2807B61FD00FD46C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be subject to the repayment provisions under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/37/303a">section 303a(e)</external-xref> of title 37.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA8F60AEF05134FFCAB8B8EC5B3C9D24F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effect of Repayment</header><text>Any repayment under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/37/303a">section 303a(e)</external-xref> of title 37 shall not affect the period of obligation of a member to serve as a Reserve in the Selected Reserve.</text> </subsection></section>
<section id="HA9D288573EAA4AC1B486CF9924510076"><enum>3306.</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header> 
<subsection id="HFED2E2BA15A54949A0DE83181093746F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Biennial Reports</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8DD9206BB7B9430B863E294527E5A922"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall submit to Congress, not later than March 1 of each odd-numbered year, a report on the operation of the educational assistance program carried out under this subchapter during the preceding two fiscal years.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3632E3CECC154BB98D7C47F180825889" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each report under paragraph (1) shall include the number of members of the Selected Reserve of the Ready Reserve of each Armed Force receiving, and the number of such members entitled to receive, educational assistance under this subchapter during each fiscal year covered by such report.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H5FA4BDBD35624F63B5ACB629D0A3D279"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Modification of Report Frequency and Report Coverage</header><text>The Secretary may submit the report otherwise required by subsection (a) more frequently than is otherwise required by that subsection and adjust the period covered by the report accordingly.</text> </subsection></section></subchapter>
<subchapter id="HE66822F1AB7F4F928F667791531FEE9F"><enum>II</enum><header>Reserve Component Members Supporting Contingency Operations and Certain Other Operations</header> 
<section id="HA977DA97721D4A9BA7E2208199FB81E2"><enum>3321.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this subchapter is to provide educational assistance to members of the reserve components called or ordered to active service in response to a war or national emergency declared by the President or Congress, in recognition of the sacrifices that those members make in answering the call to duty.</text> </section>
<section id="H5D4430EBEAC748C1B1D8D480E8B73167"><enum>3322.</enum><header>Educational assistance program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Homeland Security with respect to the Coast Guard when it is not operating as a service in the Navy, shall carry out under this subchapter a program to provide educational assistance to members of the Ready Reserve of the Armed Forces for the purpose specified in section 3321 of this title.</text> </section>
<section id="H9A08ABC4A0A34D6F82A1B298C19BC7C8"><enum>3323.</enum><header>Eligibility</header> 
<subsection id="HDE8502102BDA4B9A80ECBC2F3104FAE3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>On or after October 1, 2008, a member of a reserve component is entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter if the member—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD9CE09C0D44F451DB8425FAAE63ED587"><enum>(1)</enum><text>serves on active duty in support of a contingency operation for 90 consecutive days or more; or</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE3BAA31B9E524925AFBE009675E29EE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of a member of the Army National Guard of the United States or Air National Guard of the United States, performs full time National Guard duty under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/32/502">section 502(f)</external-xref> of title 32 for 90 consecutive days or more when authorized by the President or Secretary of Defense for the purpose of responding to a national emergency declared by the President and supported by Federal funds.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H8F01683BB60F42B3B98CB888E15E30D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notice on Entitlement</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H84BBD040321C4ECAA515BBCC92A8C127"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Each member who becomes entitled to educational assistance under subsection (a) shall be given a statement in writing prior to release from active service that summarizes the provisions of this subchapter and states clearly and prominently the substance of sections 3325 and 3326 of this title as such sections may apply to the member.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8B6B9C9B228944EA852B05D41540E29C" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In accordance with a memorandum of understanding entered into between the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of Defense shall transmit a notice of entitlement under subsection (a) for each member so entitled to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7054BEB80F9845FC93018ED38647945D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability of Certain Service Toward Eligibility</header><text>A member who qualifies for educational assistance under this subchapter may not receive credit for service under both the program established by chapter 30 of this title and the program established by this subchapter, but shall make an irrevocable election (in such form and manner as the Secretary may prescribe) as to the program to which such service is to be credited.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HE0D65DCE74D745E48F6F88984609A812"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Bar to Duplication of Educational Assistance</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9A7352BF7AE14E91BEB997A85F8C43C9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the provisions of section 3033(a) of this title, relating to a bar on duplication of receipt of certain educational assistance benefits, apply with respect to the receipt of educational assistance under this subchapter.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA3847B8120E14534845380A7B14305F7" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Paragraph (1) does not apply with respect to the entitlement of a member to educational assistance under section 3303(i) of this title.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H596C62935B884E2092F4427C8FDD00D3"><enum>3323A.</enum><header>Eligibility of individuals entitled to educational assistance under former chapter <enum-in-header>1607</enum-in-header> of title <enum-in-header>10</enum-in-header></header> 
<subsection id="H2904F36B1BDA4988A4FB5225261018FE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>Subject to the provisions of this section, any individual entitled to educational assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1607">chapter 1607</external-xref> of title 10 as of October 1, 2008, shall be entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter thereafter for the programs of education, in the amounts, and subject to the conditions and limitations provided in sections 3324 through 3326 of this title.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H109708C329824E54A2A902C2B49F8296"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation on Months of Entitlement</header><text>The number of months of entitlement to educational assistance under this subchapter of an individual described in subsection (a) by reason of this section as of October 1, 2008, shall be equal to the number of months of entitlement of such individual to educational assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1607">chapter 1607</external-xref> of title 10 that remain unutilized by such individual as of that date.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HA342E617FBF24EE08F5D7226ED7BFBEB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Time Limitation for Use of Entitlement</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5850FEC725E74C6987418F33E5C1A719"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the provisions of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/16164">section 16164</external-xref> of title 10, as in effect on September 30, 2008, shall apply to the time for the use by an individual described in subsection (a) of entitlement to educational assistance under this subchapter by reason of this section.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7F38962A610648FE8EA85703A9AADB00" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The provisions of section 3325(a)(2) of this title shall apply to the duration of the entitlement of an individual described by subsection (a) to educational assistance under this subchapter by reason of this section.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HA5E6BEA6E26B4047A6C3841959DE0306"><enum>3324.</enum><header>Amount</header> 
<subsection id="H126B0AB3F5D241AA8E00F77B7D289205"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE591984CC2AE4BEE96152329C958B506"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The educational assistance program under this subchapter shall provide for payment by the Secretary of an educational assistance allowance to each member entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5E4D4F9679624ABF9C7DBC6421FE4EB6" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>if the member is pursuing a program of education authorized under subsection (b) on a full-time basis, at the monthly rate of—</text> 
<clause id="H7A41AF7A5B0749C0841E73009D465838"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for months occurring during fiscal year 2009, the monthly rate payable under section 3015(a)(1)(D) of this title for that fiscal year; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="HEEA19D4F93F94540856E875E26048BA4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for months occurring during a subsequent fiscal year, the amount for months occurring during the previous fiscal year as increased under paragraph (2); or</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC6D0AAB303DE4AB5B0F1DFA2F5A430AC" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if the member is pursuing a program of education authorized under subsection (b) on less than a full-time basis, at an appropriately reduced monthly rate, as determined under regulations prescribed by the Secretary.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H320F1DC4C9DD4B8292EB00BE632300E3" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H053AB01E7CC145A280CBDDAB693764DC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>With respect to any fiscal year, the Secretary shall provide a percentage increase (rounded to the nearest dollar) in the rate payable under paragraph (1)(A) equal to the percentage by which—</text> 
<clause id="H58FC47C10EB64FF98132658FA4EC5950" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Consumer Price Index (all items, United States city average) for the 12-month period ending on the June 30 preceding the beginning of the fiscal year for which the increase is made, exceeds</text> </clause>
<clause id="H14134B3BBC0E454ABED14283007D9FB6" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such Consumer Price Index for the 12-month period preceding the 12-month period described in clause (i).</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1328FA8F8EB548469D9D067FA6FCAB95" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Any rounding under subparagraph (A) shall be subject to the provisions of section 3015(h)(2) of this title.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H031F4865D00540EE8677EFE1A0E5EF78"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorized Education Programs</header><text>Educational assistance may be provided under this subchapter for pursuit of any program of education that is an approved program of education for purposes of chapter 30 of this title.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HEACF0B94FAFF418199A6E2E4D3AB3495"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Treatment of Certain Duty as Counting Toward Entitlement</header><text>Any month of active duty, or full time National Guard duty, served by a member that contributes under section 3323(a) of this title to the entitlement of the member to educational assistance under this subchapter shall be counted as a month for which the member is entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H2512FC49C61E4F19A9694E869D4B00EE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Maximum Months of Assistance</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4C9BDE2D7F6A4DC98742EF3831B8573E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Subject to section 3695 of this title, the maximum number of months of educational assistance that may be provided to any member under this subchapter is 36 (or the equivalent thereof in part-time educational assistance).</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8160EC7D3DF84783928DD970E400EE82" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE231C3BB7CA14176A86E5B222E00956D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this subchapter or chapter 36 of this title, any payment of an educational assistance allowance described in subparagraph (B) shall not—</text> 
<clause id="H60C1DC28C8844F83A9C9DEA3D70092B2" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be charged against the entitlement of any member under this subchapter; or</text> </clause>
<clause id="HB5A7E4C4411C4F470034FEB457CB35EF" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>be counted toward the aggregate period for which section 3695 of this title limits a member’s receipt of assistance.</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9F743CE623B74D2FA969E1DB2C375BD6" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The payment of an educational assistance allowance referred to in subparagraph (A) is the payment of such an allowance to a member for pursuit of a course or courses under this subchapter if the Secretary finds that the member—</text> 
<clause id="H0A0DEFAE1CA44F5EB4C2E2704EFE98A7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>had to discontinue such course pursuit as a result of being ordered to serve on active duty under section 12301(a), 12301(d), 12301(g), 12302, or 12304 of title 10; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="H706B72F17BF444548458B044790632A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>failed to receive credit or training time toward completion of the member’s approved educational, professional, or vocational objective as a result of having to discontinue, as described in clause (i), the member’s course pursuit.</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA2FC7B7298EA4B4A9907F900273D541C" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The period for which, by reason of this subsection, an educational assistance allowance is not charged against entitlement or counted toward the applicable aggregate period under section 3695 of this title shall not exceed the portion of the period of enrollment in the course or courses for which the member involved failed to receive credit or with respect to which such member lost training time, as determined under subparagraph (B)(ii).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H5699B56977F84D8384446F0055A364AD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Flight Training</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H516A8CCE25EA47C5B748F214C100D32E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Educational assistance is payable under this subchapter to a person entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter for pursuit of a program of education consisting of exclusively of flight training approved under section 3034(d) of this title, subject to the conditions specified in paragraphs (2) and (4) of section 3032(e) of this title.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD4F1029330164C24A26E13AE11A3971F" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0671497681F44F8E9F83380092BD0082"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For purposes of this subchapter, the rate of payment of educational assistance allowances, and the charge against entitlement for receipt of such allowances, under this subsection shall be governed by the provisions of section 3032(e) of this title.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4AB5912FA0414D10A5E04EB95B7919D" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In the administration of the provisions referred to in subparagraph (A) for purposes of this subchapter—</text> 
<clause id="H845E9702E17E46F4B6C4E66C7D5185B8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>an individual</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to a member entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter;</text> </clause>
<clause id="H542CD0F8F7F64891BFFC139B002861"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>this chapter</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to this subchapter; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="H14F47C5A97EF429BB6A171A85C16E39E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>the monthly rate of education assistance which such individual would otherwise be paid</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to the monthly amount payable under subsection (a)(1)(A).</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H632665920FCE4DA983FC52BB223D7F9C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Licensing and Certification Tests</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H753BD6721DAE4982B0E3538CCC31C4AA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Educational assistance is payable under this subchapter to a member entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter for a licensing or certification test described in section 3452(b) of this title.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF2068A030D8747ECA54F37B9D2F6E63" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H82BDB1161C224DAE9E5CC41CDEB30046"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For purposes of this subchapter, the amount payable for a licensing or certification test, the charge against entitlement for receipt of such payment, and the effect of expiration of entitlement on payments, under this subsection is governed by the provisions of section 3032(f) of this title.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF16145FE81EB48728473BA8B009997EC" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In the administration of the provisions referred to in subparagraph (A) for purposes of this subchapter—</text> 
<clause id="H4406EF8E1DFF421AAEBC758F71CECCA1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>an individual</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to a member entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter;</text> </clause>
<clause id="H1A97959EB07842B0AD398D1300AFA87D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>this chapter</quote> shall be deemed to be a reference to this subchapter; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="HD2B1E0CA12F94022A11D5F1FFD78D3A4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a reference to <quote>the full-time monthly institutional rate of educational assistance which such individual would otherwise be paid</quote> shall be deemed to a reference to the monthly amount payable under subsection (a)(1)(A).</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H0382044679CC47958203CA62F3B0F6D3"><enum>3325.</enum><header>Time limitation for use of entitlement</header> 
<subsection id="H42D112CC870545D692414DD4AAEA6FEB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Duration of Entitlement</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b), a member remains entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5D24CAD531694C9095F291D4AD30E225"><enum>(1)</enum><text>while the member is serving—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7DD2FA7697A24F0ABB528400302879F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the Selected Reserve of the Ready Reserve, in the case of a member called or ordered to active service while serving in the Selected Reserve; or</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBBF984BC5BFD4A2B8227C3BC60FFBCF7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the Ready Reserve, in the case of a member ordered to active duty while serving in the Ready Reserve (other than the Selected Reserve); and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2D449B62402E4F668102AC6323B0FC33"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of a member who separates from the Ready Reserve upon the completion of a service contract under other than dishonorable conditions, and, if applicable, the fulfillment of an existing military service obligation in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/651">section 651</external-xref> of title 10, during the ten-year period beginning on the date on which the member separates from the Ready Reserve.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE734E003CB5846ADA82ECF657B15749C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duration of Entitlement for Disabled Members</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HAB0EB617455D4B78B3E5B5C5D1789EDE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the case of a person who is separated from the Ready Reserve because of a disability which was not the result of the person’s own willful misconduct incurred on or after the date on which such person became entitled to educational assistance under this subchapter, the person’s entitlement to educational assistance expires at the end of the 10-year period beginning on the date on which the person became entitled to such assistance.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD74D142FB4DB470CAF7600C934A3731B" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The provisions of subsections (d) and (f) of section 3031 of this title shall apply to the period of entitlement prescribed by paragraph (1).</text> </paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HBE205DAB85FC41979300D2300696500"><enum>3326.</enum><header>Termination of assistance</header> 
<subsection id="HA0FE921225034EEE8F00D6069B03F6CB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b), educational assistance may not be provided under this subchapter, or if being provided under this subchapter, shall be terminated—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD0B530B65B17488F89CCB79547D71FC4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>if the member is receiving financial assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2107">section 2107</external-xref> of title 10 as a member of the Senior Reserve Officers’ Training Corps program; or</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9F2993AC2C3646D8B872973982183548"><enum>(2)</enum><text>when the member separates from the Ready Reserve, as provided for under subparagraph (A) or (B) of paragraph (1) of section 3325(a) of this title, as applicable, unless the member is otherwise covered by paragraph (2) of such section.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HB8ADCFDDEF6B4660B8D53EB5410069A4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Under regulations prescribed by the Secretary of Defense, educational assistance may be provided under this subchapter to a member of the Selected Reserve of the Ready Reserve who incurs a break in service in the Selected Reserve of not more than 90 days if the member continues to serve in the Ready Reserve during and after such break in service.</text> </subsection></section></subchapter>
<subchapter id="HF114479BA46F4F1CB2DA0000E53582EF"><enum>III</enum><header>Administrative Matters</header> 
<section id="H8097485342C1477D859E7E7E06B5FC7B"><enum>3341.</enum><header>Administration of programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The provisions of sections 3470, 3471, 3474, 3476, 3482(g), 3483, and 3485 of this title and the provisions of subchapters I and II of chapter 36 of this title (with the exception of sections 3686(a), 3687, and 3692) shall be applicable to the provision of educational assistance under subchapters I and II of this chapter. In the application of such provisions for purposes of subchapter I or II of this chapter, the terms <term>eligible veteran</term> and <term>a person</term>, as used in such provisions, shall be deemed to refer to a person or member eligible for educational assistance under the applicable subchapter.</text> </section>
<section id="H9432B47641054D10ACC2EE5E2447ACDD"><enum>3342.</enum><header>Funding</header> 
<subsection id="HD13F3AA6DE474F28AE670141A96233F7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Funding for benefits accruing after October 1, 2008</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1B84566A4A524F44A9495F34A12DC5E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Payments for educational assistance under this chapter for persons entitled to such assistance under section 3302 or 3323 of this title shall be made from funds appropriated or otherwise made available to the Department of Veterans Affairs for the payment of readjustment benefits.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA6C0D66466C241F1BFEB47E99516C95" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Payments for training and rehabilitation under section 3323(b) of this title shall be made from funds appropriated or otherwise made available to the Department of Veterans Affairs for the payment of readjustment benefits.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA4D0B6FC5A88485A87FD884D397608E9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Funding for benefits accruing before October 1, 2008</header><text>Payments for educational assistance under this chapter for persons entitled to such assistance under section 3302A or 3323A of this title shall be made from amounts in the Department of Defense Education Benefits Fund under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2006">section 2006</external-xref> of title 10 that are attributable to armed forces education liabilities under chapters 1606 and 1607 of title 10 that accrue before October 1, 2008. Amounts for such payments shall be made available to the Secretary in accordance with the provisions of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2006">section 2006(d)</external-xref> of title 10.</text> </subsection></section></subchapter></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H241328EBC8F148DA838F77EF66214D59"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header><text>The tables of chapters at the beginning of title 38, United States Code, and at the beginning of part III of such title, are each amended by inserting after the item relating to chapter 32 the following new item:</text> 
<table line-rules="no-gen" table-type="subformat"> 
<tgroup cols="2"> 
<tbody> 
<row><entry colname="I60"><bold>“33. Educational Assistance for Members of the Reserve Components</bold></entry><entry colname="I52"><bold>3301</bold>”.</entry> </row> </tbody> </tgroup> </table> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD8593A73D4C842C58B05A221C064237C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming Amendments on Bar on Dual Eligibility for Benefits</header> 
<paragraph id="HC19AF678419B4DE48002E767DA453546"><enum>(1)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/3033">Section 3033</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2C65FF9CA4F243B39FAFF169911F00D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1), by striking <quote>chapter 106 or 107 of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>under subchapter I or subchapter II of chapter 33 of this title, under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/107">chapter 107</external-xref> of title 10</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H83FCD99AAB8A407381AB00865E159B7D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by striking <quote>chapter 106 of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>subchapter I of chapter 33 of this title</quote>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDECC6B8798B2440FBADD22B1DD2261EC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Section 3221(f) of such title is amended by striking <quote>chapter 106 of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>subchapter I of chapter 33 of this title</quote>.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDFBD120106A94A71A53256D7EA0050BC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Section 3681 of such title is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF7C83510F77349EF8DDC0F2FEBA3297"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>34, 35, or 36 of this title or 106 or 107 of title 10,</quote> and inserting <quote>33, 34, 35, or 36 of this title</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEF69A4459BCC4169AEEE5452B2BAE09D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> 
<clause id="H488B6F2E8B8A4F47AAF9C96BE6681DF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting before the period the following: <quote>, and subchapters I and II of chapter 33 of this title</quote>; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="HC7077C2785B44E199819198BA9B9DE11"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>Chapters 106 and</quote> and inserting <quote>Chapter 107</quote>.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H98257687B3294B61BA1B86B09EFA0506"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Conforming Amendments Relating to Department of Defense Education Benefits Fund</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2006">Section 2006(b)</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H62C8BF159EEF4C69B03EBBD5C9D7479"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>and chapters 1606 and 1607</quote>; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB53E3FDCA5124CD288CA6B62CABC5345"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDE358B39931C40769F19D132C9D8F19"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (C); and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8EC4781DADB741E3A81EAD5CA4139CA8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (D) and (E) as subparagraphs (C) and (D), respectively.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC85EFC7372AC4E3786A28700D15D7973"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Cross-Reference Amendments</header> 
<paragraph id="H56D4AF10F7F54C66B9D2A7E6100123C4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Chapter <enum-in-header>106</enum-in-header> of title <enum-in-header>10</enum-in-header>, united states code</header> 
<subparagraph id="HA98664D9FA054546A6BB9C4987C3CCEC"><enum>(A)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2131">Section 2131</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HCCC90C5E1E594C86BDED495BD376ECA" style="USC"> 
<section id="HB80B098D59B04F59BC97303243F9BDCE"><enum>2131.</enum><header>Reference to subchapter <enum-in-header>I</enum-in-header> of chapter <enum-in-header>33</enum-in-header> of title <enum-in-header>38</enum-in-header></header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Provisions of law related to educational assistance for members of the Selected Reserve under the Montgomery GI Bill program, as formerly set forth in this chapter and <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1606">chapter 1606</external-xref> of this title, are set forth in subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 38 (beginning with <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/3301">section 3301</external-xref> of title 38).</text> </section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H12058844427D4E0DBE6C00971F8F7D4D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 106 of such title is amended by striking the item relating to section 2131 and inserting the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H082727E2F8614C53A75D82E83E14992F" style="OLC"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">2131. Reference to subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 38.</toc-entry> </toc> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC928F45172D54C6CA867181D10BF5CF9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Chapter <enum-in-header>1606</enum-in-header> of title <enum-in-header>10</enum-in-header>, united states code</header><text>Chapter 1606 of such title is amended by striking all after the chapter heading and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HC4FA711988E54A0CBABF63A072AA2401" style="USC"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">16131. Reference to subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 38.</toc-entry> </toc> 
<section id="H3CE5A52FEB37419E8700353B07E07E54"><enum>16131.</enum><header>Reference to subchapter <enum-in-header>I</enum-in-header> of chapter <enum-in-header>33</enum-in-header> of title <enum-in-header>38</enum-in-header></header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Provisions of law related to educational assistance for members of the Selected Reserve under the Montgomery GI Bill program, as formerly set forth in this chapter, are set forth in subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 38 (beginning with section 3301 of that title).</text> </section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC257F2A880154074B1F68D0024F2DAC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Chapter <enum-in-header>1607</enum-in-header> of title <enum-in-header>10</enum-in-header>, united states code</header><text>Chapter 1607 of such title is amended by striking all after the chapter heading and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HA62E873C80634CB7006BE1EB2058E88D" style="USC"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">16161. Reference to subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 38.</toc-entry> </toc> 
<section id="H80D73CA248294DEDA1C203A4BFD8DC78"><enum>16161.</enum><header>Reference to subchapter <enum-in-header>II</enum-in-header> of chapter <enum-in-header>33</enum-in-header> of title <enum-in-header>38</enum-in-header></header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Provisions of law related to educational assistance for members of the reserve components of the armed forces supporting contingency operations and certain other operations, as formerly set forth in this chapter, are set forth in subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 38 (beginning with section 3321 of that title).</text> </section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H8F33BE571CBB46BD8F1D7F7424A85D88"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Additional Conforming Amendments</header> 
<paragraph id="HBE3F73A4674F455FBB753BD62676A69"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Title 38, united states code</header> 
<subparagraph id="H0412DA1BFD5948238600645935DD23C1"><enum>(A)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/3485">Section 3485</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<clause id="HF207BB9BD4F8475DB773DCCF2D14E28E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(4)(E), by striking <quote>chapter 1606 or 1607 of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 33 of this title</quote>;</text> </clause>
<clause id="H7D832E8E06C0438CB1168309C737ABED"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>chapter 30, 31, 32, or 34 of this title or chapter 1606 or 1607 of title 10,</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 30, 31, 32, 33, or 34 of this title</quote>; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="HF817F15B86744D478300FEDA82817E36"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(1)—</text> 
<subclause id="HA12343ECC63740AABE1B7600D5DC7774"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>, chapter 30, 31, 32, 35, or 36 of this title, or chapter 1606 or 1607 of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>or chapter 30, 31, 32, 33, 35, or 36 of this title</quote>; and</text> </subclause>
<subclause id="H9AC3C785C63E45A283780077C9C10047"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>section 2135 of such title</quote> and inserting <quote>section 3305 of this title</quote>.</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD6FA561477714481AB72104E02B91EBC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Section 3672(c) of such title is amended—</text> 
<clause id="H8B4A91735A234FCCBAB1633800A3F357"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)(A), by striking <quote>chapters 30 and 35 of this title and <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1606">chapter 1606</external-xref> of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>chapters 30, 33, and 35 of this title</quote>; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="H4EA680B298FB415BB783B2EC2212AA9E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>chapter 30 or 35 of this title, or <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1606">chapter 1606</external-xref> of title 10, as the case may be</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 30, 33, or 35 of this title</quote>.</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8BE335D3732B460C867C00F8F0B04E9F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Section 3680A(d)(1) of such title is amended—</text> 
<clause id="HDC7ED8AE19DE4F6EBE46D401ADE03BC5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/106">chapter 106</external-xref> of title 10</quote> the first place it appears; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="HE6E40DC2CCC64252B9CCBABC43932D98"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or chapter 30, 31, 32, or 35 of this title or under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/106">chapter 106</external-xref> of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>or chapter 30, 31, 32, 33, or 35 of this title</quote>.</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC07454CDA492467EA125E7A9B672F669"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Section 3684A(a)(1) of such title is amended by striking <quote>chapter 30 or 32 of this title or in <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/106">chapter 106</external-xref> of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 30, 32, or 33 of this title</quote>.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H84B6B1AB70B74A4DAE7EEC52F5BC4445"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Section 3688(b) of such title is amended by striking <quote>, chapter 30, 32, or 35 of this title, or <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/106">chapter 106</external-xref> of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>or chapter 30, 32, 33, or 35 of this title</quote>.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H890E3E11ECBF42368CB593D085D0B7CF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Section 3689 of such title is amended by inserting <quote>33,</quote> after <quote>32,</quote> each place it appears.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3AD2CB187D8342E7B98FADBE8EF2BBA7"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Section 3692 of such title is amended—</text> 
<clause id="HFB7F6B0A531E442AB77F842F6292C4E2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>or 35 of this title and <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1606">chapter 1606</external-xref> of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>33, or 35 of this title</quote>; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="H8B30BCF24F8444178ED967D1319BD5B5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>, chapters 30, 32, and 35 of this title, and <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1606">chapter 1606</external-xref> of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>and chapters 30, 32, 33, and 35 of this title</quote>.</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA9C8216A67324E1F96FA175986EC34C6"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Section 3695(a) of such title is amended—</text> 
<clause id="H734EADE71F314E6CAC782F326EF13930"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (4) and inserting the following new paragraph (4):</text> 
<quoted-block id="H9FBC67FB583846F1AF833232651C6287" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="HCB084BAB97034E90A7F1D83835CFBD53"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Chapters 30, 32, 34, 35, and 36 of this title and subchapters I and II of chapter 33 of this title.</text> </paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </clause>
<clause id="H0C65DEF9CDFF447D8BACA400625CEE9D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by striking <quote>, 1606, 1607,</quote>.</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8CB9E7A79B254CCFAF58A9EFF6F857C9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Section 3697(a) of such title is amended by striking <quote>chapter 30, 32, 34, or 35 of this title, or <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/106">chapter 106</external-xref> of title 10,</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 30, 32, 33, 34, or 35 of this title</quote>.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H653DCF0A84EA4111ADF8EF8FA100B047"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Section 3697A(b)(1) of such title is amended by striking <quote>or 32 of this title or chapter 106 or 107 of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>32, or 33 of this title</quote>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD7C99EA2C7E94B0499D89CF25D21015"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Title <enum-in-header>10</enum-in-header>, united states code</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/510">Section 510(h)</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6ABB9DB8E1BB4E85B435277D60C17E4E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> 
<clause id="H6CA5E6B74694494FA7D6CB71E0067D6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>additional educational assistance under chapter 1606 of this title or to basic educational assistance under subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/30">chapter 30</external-xref> of title 38</quote> and inserting <quote>basic educational assistance under subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/30">chapter 30</external-xref> of title 38 or educational assistance under subchapter I of chapter 33 of that title</quote>; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="H863E0F1C5FC2495DBFA02C6D18947911"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text> 
<subclause id="HA3C24B631E1647E600B6B2BBC23B6FE2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>chapter 1606 of this title or <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/30">chapter 30</external-xref> of title 38</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 30 or subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 38</quote>; and</text> </subclause>
<subclause id="H72A5A142D8C345E5B2390963AF9915A5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>either such chapter</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>either such provisions</quote>; and</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HACC1C4AF08DB4289A834C73235BEE8F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)(A), by striking <quote>educational assistance under chapter 1606 of this title</quote> and all that follows through <quote>as the case may be</quote> and inserting <quote>basic educational assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/30">chapter 30</external-xref> of title 38 or educational assistance under subchapter I of chapter 33 of that title from an entitlement to such basic educational assistance under chapter 30 of that title or educational assistance under subchapter I of chapter 33 of that title, as the case may be</quote>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7D898FF7C6CA4B6CAA8306ECFA203B4C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Elementary and secondary education act of 1965</header><text>Section 2304(g) of the <act-name parsable-cite="ESEA">Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6674">20 U.S.C. 6674(g)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>chapter 30 of title 38 or <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1606">chapter 1606</external-xref> of title 10</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 30 or 33 of title 38</quote>.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBA7E95CE946946789CF19E4C3EB46D6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Internal Revenue Code of <enum-in-header>1986</enum-in-header></header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/25A">Section 25A(g)(2)(B)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>chapter 30, 31, 32, 34, or 35 of title 38, United States Code, or under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/1606">chapter 1606</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, or 35 of title 38, United States Code</quote>.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H259D54D02A01465282F64EF4BAAC23F"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Effective Date</header> 
<paragraph id="H5B8ABE7069DC4E28BB0734AAAD8D7EF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>This section and the amendments made by this section shall take effect on October 1, 2008.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF89692B6ACBB4767B5245F7E51E5F111"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No adjustment in assistance amounts for fiscal year 2009</header><text>The adjustment in amounts of educational assistance otherwise required for fiscal year 2009 under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/3303">section 3303(a)(2)</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code (as amended by subsection (b)), shall not be made.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section>
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


