<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA216762B0FE9426B802201C1A74F00E3" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 1448 IH: VA Hospital Quality Report Card Act of 2007</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-03-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
<session>1st Session</session>
<legis-num>H. R. 1448</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070309">March 9, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000480">Mrs. Lowey</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="E000063">Mr. Edwards</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to establish a Hospital Quality Report Card Initiative to report on health care quality in Department of Veterans Affairs hospitals.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HA199356F6CF64B0088DE89D210E269B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H17A83A11DB58406AA346C0390996F216" section-type="section-one" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>VA Hospital Quality Report Card Act of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HD5B85614DBFE458FA975287DC0A48968"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to establish the Hospital Quality Report Card Initiative under title 38, United States Code, to ensure that quality measures data for hospitals administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs are readily available and accessible in order to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7122310CCFB845F8A879922DF3722BAE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>inform patients and consumers about health care quality in such hospitals;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEE4AA7ED3CAB4D929369820000A38D49"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assist Department of Veterans Affairs health care providers in identifying opportunities for quality improvement and cost containment; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF82990026B98409E9DB6FD2C9D213FA1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>enhance the understanding of policy makers and public officials of health care issues, raise public awareness of hospital quality issues, and help constituents of such policy makers and officials identify quality health care options.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H81A2DA562E3C44F39ECEBE720088D829" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Department of Veterans Affairs hospital quality report card initiative</header> 
<subsection id="H3B07BDF87E54495DA991D73EE8AA37D2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subchapter III of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/17">chapter 17</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF89786EAA1274BDEB74E342649193B01" style="USC"> 
<section id="H84F2C29E0ABD4188BF897619E3E85961" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>1730A.</enum><header>Hospital Quality Report Card Initiative</header> 
<subsection id="HB503046E54F44135008C1E5909E75649"><enum>(a)</enum><text>The Secretary shall establish and implement a Hospital Quality Report Card Initiative (in this section referred to as the <quote>Initiative</quote>) to report on health care quality in Department hospitals.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H81B9498E9BA646D594286900F206A965"><enum>(b)</enum> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4A1678EE197E4B8CBE5EE065DB7BC894"><enum>(1)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5A9DFD4527A34115B093656E63EDC25F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Not less than 2 times each year, the Secretary shall publish and distribute, in accordance with subparagraph (F), reports on Department hospital quality. The reports shall include quality measures data that allow for an assessment of health care—</text> 
<clause id="HB3B1AC23E7EA490DB189739D9F7C2FD0" indent="up2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>effectiveness;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HEF62BE39987C4A8EACD8C283CD4F9BAF" indent="up2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>safety;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H092DE444D7A3457DAA9900E19CC4F600" indent="up2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>timeliness;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5D538C10ADC8413196135400925EE400" indent="up2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>efficiency;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA165366312D54274BF5E7D8C0025EB10" indent="up2"><enum>(v)</enum><text>patient-centeredness; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H974CB167EA8C4659BFBDDD59E9CD06D8" indent="up2"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>equity.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCD841C36A18B44B087DEBF00069EC1FC" indent="up2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In collecting and reporting data as provided for under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall include Department hospital information, as possible, relating to—</text> 
<clause id="HB02F29E345184E798D2ECE28A5144390"><enum>(i)</enum><text>staffing levels of nurses and other health professionals, as appropriate;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H53D2921D4AFE43649B632EC89262D284"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>rates of nosocomial infections;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE833949210164725A017AE0008E82F1D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the volume of various procedures performed;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H21A1ED8E5DA84C3B86F6AB3F26579EE5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>hospital sanctions and other violations;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H51DC6D51993C4D7F968572FFB600A629"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the quality of care for various patient populations, including female, geriatric, disabled, rural, homeless, mentally ill, and racial and ethnic minority populations;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HCAB97009175F4B96A3F3F7497F4F550"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the availability of emergency rooms, intensive care units, maternity care, and specialty services;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H12C5509AC8DE4722A919BF7FC8C83563"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the quality of care in various hospital settings, including inpatient, outpatient, emergency, maternity, and intensive care unit settings;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDBEA7DDE801D4636938C4757F05EDAEB"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>ongoing patient safety initiatives; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H920E68A439594489B5BD3675C71D5B97"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>other measures determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE82C6DC56075424ABB511721B81FB884" indent="up2"><enum>(C)</enum> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H2808622536DA469E8DC5880400306368"><enum>(i)</enum><text>In reporting data as provided for under subparagraph (A), the Secretary may risk adjust quality measures to account for differences relating to—</text> 
<subclause id="H7BCCA36DA1B7492CB8F6B16B0E38CE9" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the characteristics of the reporting Department hospital, such as licensed bed size, geography, and teaching hospital status; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H1FE28E71B63D4379A7A7DF300BF00EA" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>patient characteristics, such as health status, severity of illness, and socioeconomic status.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H05254ACC49D7413FBEA998AF6FE8E5B1" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>If the Secretary reports data under subparagraph (A) using risk-adjusted quality measures, the Secretary shall establish procedures for making the unadjusted data available to the public in a manner determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3DE6D344D449417BB406DE9429AA53D7" indent="up2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Under the Initiative, the Secretary may verify data reported under this paragraph to ensure accuracy and validity.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H97799FDCEFF7413E893F072D89B93274" indent="up2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Secretary shall disclose the entire methodology for the reporting of data under this paragraph to all relevant organizations and Department hospitals that are the subject of any such information that is to be made available to the public prior to the public disclosure of such information.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H34014B935CD54411B234DEE5A47EE49F" indent="up2"><enum>(F)</enum> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5E14C916CEEE4BB5BC5F8D707923D17E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Secretary shall submit each report to the appropriate committees of Congress.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC6C788C4503B47539E801E038B719D11" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Secretary shall ensure that reports are made available under this section in an electronic format, in an understandable manner with respect to various populations (including those with low functional health literacy), and in a manner that allows health care quality comparisons to be made with local hospitals or regional hospitals, as appropriate.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5CD19D18C2B04173A337CB08ED4C7C6" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The Secretary shall establish procedures for making report findings available to the public, upon request, in a non-electronic format, such as through a toll-free telephone number.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9A8067577DB24A57B7F86EA27EBB269C" indent="up2"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The analytic methodologies and limitations on data sources utilized by the Secretary to develop and disseminate the comparative data under this section shall be identified and acknowledged as part of the dissemination of such data, and such dissemination shall include the appropriate and inappropriate uses of the data.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1AF312C74714449B9E1BB4CEE9DD0A2" indent="up2"><enum>(H)</enum><text>On at least an annual basis, the Secretary shall compare quality measures data submitted by each Department hospital with data submitted in the prior year or years by the same hospital in order to identify and report actions that would lead to false or artificial improvements in the hospital’s quality measurements.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H23F06D38697249CEBF27AD26AD535872" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H901F43978D064885AED6709EB207BEA2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Secretary shall develop and implement effective safeguards to protect against the unauthorized use or disclosure of Department hospital data that is reported under this section.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9187387F0AEF4A7A958BA9EFBA88F41E" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Secretary shall develop and implement effective safeguards to protect against the dissemination of inconsistent, incomplete, invalid, inaccurate, or subjective Department hospital data.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDBB1F3A158E04E7C006600A5A9713D22" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Secretary shall ensure that identifiable patient data shall not be released to the public.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC136A6EF62584AD0B18B4D85EE51ED62"><enum>(c)</enum> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H6A262D45A3604DCDAE39AEFD43C2B387"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall evaluate and periodically submit a report to Congress on the effectiveness of the Initiative, including the effectiveness of the Initiative in meeting the purpose described in section 2 of the <short-title>VA Hospital Quality Report Card Act of 2007</short-title>. The Secretary shall make such reports available to the public.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD7643F46FF144821A95373F900EFE55E" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary shall use the outcomes from the evaluation conducted pursuant to paragraph (1) to increase the usefulness of the Initiative.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1E1F65964A224180AD6EDACBE5E3700"><enum>(d)</enum><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2008 through 2017.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC007F9ACD6514332B504D6AABFCCA754"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 17, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 1730 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4965BF32500D465F9DED10943343EA7C" style="OLC"> 
<toc> 
<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">1730A. Hospital Quality Report Card Initiative.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H403BF5A7B815414BB01B94D7111D2E00"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1730A">Section 1730A</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), shall take effect not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 

