<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HFD8A35F3765C428394F82401C5414A23" public-private="public">
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code>
		<calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 290</calendar>
		<congress display="yes">111th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 3993</legis-num>
		<associated-doc display="yes" role="report">[Report No.
		  111–507]</associated-doc>
		<current-chamber display="yes">IN THE HOUSE OF
		  REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20091103">November 3, 2009</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000179">Mr. Engel</sponsor> introduced
			 the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HIF00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Energy and
			 Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20100615">June 15, 2010</action-date>
			<action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="B001149">Mr.
			 Burton of Indiana</cosponsor> and <cosponsor name-id="T000465">Ms.
			 Tsongas</cosponsor></action-desc>
		</action>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20100615">June 15, 2010</action-date>
			<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of
			 the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be
			 printed</action-desc>
			<action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert
			 the part printed in italic</action-instruction>
			<action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as
			 introduced on November 3, 2009</action-instruction>
		</action>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-desc display="yes"><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To require accurate and reasonable
		  disclosure of the terms and conditions of prepaid telephone calling cards and
		  services.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body changed="added" committee-id="HIF00" display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="H5F99FFD7DFE54FADA6631A9AC90D9F8B" reported-display-style="italic" style="OLC">
		<section id="H4F71D6453C8446F2853B7700AB0838B9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Calling Card Consumer Protection
			 Act</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section commented="no" id="H24DB136036674ECFB1F664863A281A30"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this Act, the following
			 definitions apply:</text>
			<paragraph commented="no" id="HE6A6D89437A1485FB435215625CDA9FC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Commission</term> means the
			 Federal Trade Commission.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H79A74D954AE842779E374F10A94F3293"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>prepaid
			 calling card</term> has the meaning given the term <term>prepaid calling
			 card</term> by section 64.5000(a) of the Federal Communications Commission’s
			 regulations (47 C.F.R. 64.5000(a)). Such term shall also include calling cards
			 that use VoIP service or a successor protocol. Such term shall also include an
			 electronic or other mechanism that allows users to pay in advance for a
			 specified amount of calling. Such term shall not include—</text>
				<subparagraph commented="no" id="HBE0ED0AE38644FDF98E0036E84F0F2FC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>calling cards or other
			 rights of use that are provided for free or at no additional cost as a
			 promotional item accompanying a product or service purchased by a
			 consumer;</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC3484756EC1E43D0A6B3BE1AB0B72248"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any card, device, or other right of use,
			 the purchase of which establishes a customer-carrier relationship with a
			 provider of wireless telecommunications service or wireless hybrid service, or
			 that provides access to a wireless telecommunications service or wireless
			 hybrid service account wherein the purchaser has a pre-existing relationship
			 with the wireless service provider; or</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB8A9FE858FC481D804D88E948300953"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">payphone service, as that term is defined
			 in section 276(d) of the Communications Act of 1934 (47 U.S.C. 276(d)).</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H9318E54859214B3F920E184CA2DB8605"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>prepaid calling card
			 provider</term> has the meaning given the term <term>prepaid calling card
			 provider</term> by section 64.5000(b) of the Federal Communications
			 Commission’s regulations (47 C.F.R. 64.5000(b)). Such term shall also
			 include—</text>
				<subparagraph id="H004301D5E58240D28A8BBB1A84446BD5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a provider of a prepaid
			 calling card that uses VoIP service or a successor protocol; and</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD639CAF7A5984DABBE7A292C3CE8ADCA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a provider of a prepaid
			 calling card that allows users to pay in advance for a specified amount of
			 minutes through an electronic or other mechanism.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HEF6050869F4E43389A8F1A7FD5208D73"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>prepaid calling card
			 distributor</term> means any entity or person that purchases prepaid calling
			 cards from a prepaid calling card provider or another prepaid calling card
			 distributor and sells, re-sells, issues, or distributes such cards to one or
			 more distributors of such cards or to one or more retail sellers of such cards.
			 Such term shall not include—</text>
				<subparagraph id="HDAADFE840F874ECD9E3BE4D19F09FD25"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any retail seller whose only activity with
			 respect to the sale of prepaid calling cards is point-of-sale transactions with
			 end-user customers; or</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D6FE57A7B314A19B509CF0C8CBD0449"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any person whose only
			 activity with respect to the sale of prepaid calling cards is the transport or
			 delivery of such cards.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HB63B6BD07AA94613AE39E91B66EF6F34"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>wireless hybrid
			 service</term> is defined as a service that integrates both commercial mobile
			 radio service (as defined by section 20.3 of the Federal Communications
			 Commission’s regulations (47 C.F.R. 20.3)) and VoIP service.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H7ACF5012C0C640FB8AEB5876AF666273"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The term <term>VoIP
			 service</term> has the meaning given the term <term>interconnected Voice over
			 Internet protocol service</term> by section 9.3 of the Federal Communications
			 Commission’s regulations (47 C.F.R. 9.3). Such term shall include any voice
			 calling service that utilizes a voice over Internet protocol or any successor
			 protocol in the transmission of the call.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H9449F2C815E74946AE967CD8D1626AF6"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>fees</term> includes all
			 charges, fees, taxes, or surcharges applicable to a prepaid calling card that
			 are—</text>
				<subparagraph commented="no" id="HDE29F6B459A949E28C51A80D9E433A51"><enum>(A)</enum><text>required by Federal law
			 or regulation or order of the Federal Communications Commission or by the laws
			 and regulations of any State or political subdivision of a State; or</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H6FF6788AA8114256882138FE57F4D5F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expressly permitted to be assessed under
			 Federal law or regulation or order of the Federal Communications Commission or
			 under the laws and regulations of any State or political subdivision of a
			 State.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H7BF743E1EE5946BABB8030061982D395"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The term <term>additional
			 charge</term> means any charge assessed by a prepaid calling card provider or
			 prepaid calling card distributor for the use of a prepaid calling card, other
			 than a fee or rate.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE9951CE8CE9C4AE18B55672EC474A0B3"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The term
			 <term>international preferred destination</term> means one or more specific
			 international destinations named on a prepaid calling card or on the packaging
			 material accompanying a prepaid calling card.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H1B6C75474B7B4AB7BB2212B7A254AAFD"><enum>3.</enum><header>Required disclosures of
			 prepaid calling cards</header>
			<subsection id="H806CBA504A9E41EC94E5D92D47E8875F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Required
			 disclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any prepaid
			 calling card provider or prepaid calling card distributor shall accurately
			 disclose the following information relating to the terms and conditions of the
			 prepaid calling card:</text>
				<paragraph id="HA15F1B55B6114AAAB8DA3456EFC4B583"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The name of the prepaid calling card
			 provider and such provider’s customer service telephone number and hours of
			 service, except that the hours of service may not be required to be disclosed
			 if the provider’s customer service is provided and available 24 hours a day, 7
			 days per week.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H2AEBB832DB294C56A6559F54D19EACE1"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H833DB2617C884B4583D9D45327A3422A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of domestic interstate minutes
			 available from the prepaid calling card and the number of available minutes for
			 all international preferred destinations served by the prepaid calling card at
			 the time of purchase; or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph changed="added" committee-id="HIF00" id="HCA5C329CDC4F479A95EDC8F50A57A556" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the dollar value of the prepaid calling
			 card, the domestic interstate rate per minute provided by such card, and the
			 applicable per minute rates for all international preferred destinations served
			 by the prepaid calling card at the time of purchase.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA430779ED0234A00810A36E5DEF7857A"><enum>(3)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC2AEBFFD14DF48A2BB5DB8FD03692998"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The applicable per
			 minute rate for all individual international destinations served by the card at
			 the time of purchase; or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph changed="added" committee-id="HIF00" id="H5E22DABBF9AB47E2BED4358A5BA36837" indent="up1" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a toll-free customer service number and
			 website (if the provider maintains a website) where a consumer may obtain the
			 information described in subparagraph (A) and a statement that such information
			 may be obtained through such toll-free customer service number and
			 website.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC88432A947D4CADBCB7403510E2207E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The following terms and
			 conditions pertaining to, or associated with, the use of the prepaid calling
			 card:</text>
					<subparagraph commented="no" id="HF2C12A04278B485AAC28BC6CE6713CF4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any applicable fees associated with the use
			 of the prepaid calling card.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C3AAE4B9A77478284988FB2CF8008DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of any
			 additional charges associated with the use of the prepaid calling card and the
			 amount of such charges.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HECDFDEF318EF4DFEA204CCFF97709731"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any limitation on the use
			 or period of time for which the promoted or advertised minutes or rates will be
			 available.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H55210E3BA5244639BEB909EF00A6EAFD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A description of the
			 applicable policies relating to refund, recharge, and any predetermined
			 decrease in value of such card over a period of time.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A843F10210F4CB691452096E1F93CFE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Any expiration date
			 applicable to the prepaid calling card or the minutes available with such
			 calling card.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA1673903797D400B80625E3CCB98A53F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Location of disclosure
			 and language requirement</header>
				<paragraph id="H51817D1D9B4749989C0404CDD56BAB23"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Clear and
			 conspicuous</header>
					<subparagraph id="H3F6A7E35FA1B40B3B844C59E34DAAD2D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Cards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The disclosures required under subsection
			 (a) shall be printed in plain English language (except as provided in paragraph
			 (2)) in a clear and conspicuous manner and location on the prepaid calling
			 card, except as the Commission may provide under paragraph (3). If the card is
			 enclosed in packaging that obscures the disclosures on the card, such
			 disclosures also shall be printed on the outside packaging of the card.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB0C712E6B984EE3A3244A50B95E7C90"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Online
			 services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to the
			 requirements under subparagraph (A), in the case of a prepaid calling card that
			 consumers purchase via the Internet, the disclosures required under subsection
			 (a) shall be displayed in plain English language (except as provided in
			 paragraph (2)) in a clear and conspicuous manner and location on the Internet
			 website that the consumer must access prior to purchasing such card.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H355F40CBD1C24C3D86E43188F7587F80"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Advertising and other
			 promotional material</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any
			 advertising or other promotional material for a prepaid calling card that
			 contains any representation, expressly or by implication, regarding the dollar
			 value, the per minute rate, or the number of minutes provided by the card shall
			 include in a clear and conspicuous manner and location all the disclosures
			 described in subsection (a), except as the Commission may provide under
			 paragraph (3).</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H097DE95417134EEDB640A51B96CC6DAC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign
			 languages</header><text>If a language other than English is prominently used on
			 a prepaid calling card, its packaging, or in point-of-sale advertising,
			 Internet advertising, or promotional material for such card, the disclosures
			 required by this section shall be disclosed in that language on such card,
			 packaging, advertisement, or promotional material.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HB7CD373157804CEFBBCB50DE25E70A66"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Different location of
			 certain information as determined by Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding the requirements of
			 paragraph (1), the Commission may determine that some of the information
			 required to be disclosed pursuant to subsection (a) does not need to be
			 disclosed on the prepaid calling card, advertising, or other promotional
			 material, if the Commission by regulation—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HE4D96B6C9AA9450295DF576FC3E772BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>requires the information
			 to be otherwise disclosed and available to consumers; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF4D14580C90486BB6F496D80B0165B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>determines that—</text>
						<clause id="HDE83FF0FB9B84FB68AF3E5AFBB78381E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such disclosures provide
			 for easy comprehension and comparison by consumers; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H41A57B4B28664591A239F7F3E0F68F84"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the remaining disclosures on the prepaid
			 calling card, advertising, or other promotional material, include sufficient
			 information to allow a consumer to effectively inquire about or seek
			 clarification of the services provided by the calling card.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H9A6ECCC3B032446CB62C94DCA15AF341"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Minutes announced,
			 promoted, or advertised through voice prompts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any information provided to a consumer by
			 any voice prompt given to the consumer at the time the consumer uses the
			 prepaid calling card relating to the remaining value of the calling card or the
			 number of minutes available from the calling card shall be accurate, taking
			 into account the application of the fees and additional charges required to be
			 disclosed under subsection (a).</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H47D9C693778B40FA86A5683DC488883E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Disclosures required
			 upon purchase of additional minutes</header><text>If a prepaid calling card
			 permits a consumer to add value to the card or purchase additional minutes
			 after the original purchase of the prepaid calling card, any changes to the
			 rates or additional charges required to be disclosed under subsection (a) shall
			 apply only to the additional minutes to be purchased and shall be disclosed
			 clearly and conspicuously to the consumer before the completion of such
			 purchase.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H772494210F7947F7840DBBCBB70E95C3"><enum>(e)</enum><header>No false, misleading,
			 or deceptive disclosures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No
			 prepaid calling card, packaging, advertisement, or other promotional material
			 containing a disclosure required pursuant to this section shall contain any
			 false, misleading, or deceptive representations relating to the terms and
			 conditions of the prepaid calling card.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HCDBAC78ED72E4FDEBD81439BBCF15C31"><enum>4.</enum><header>Federal Trade Commission
			 Authority</header>
			<subsection id="HC8DD4810E6844A5B87588493B136A12C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Unfair and deceptive
			 act or practice</header><text>A violation of section 3 shall be treated as a
			 violation of a rule defining an unfair or deceptive act or practice prescribed
			 under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (15 U.S.C.
			 57a(a)(1)(B)).</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H22052C8B60604BA2ACBD00C54C22C8CE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authority of the
			 commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission
			 shall enforce this Act in the same manner and by the same means as though all
			 applicable terms and provisions of the Federal Trade Commission Act were
			 incorporated into and made a part of this Act. Notwithstanding any provision of
			 the Federal Trade Commission Act or any other provision of law and solely for
			 purposes of this Act, common carriers subject to the Communications Act of 1934
			 (47 U.S.C. 151 et seq.) and any amendment thereto shall be subject to the
			 jurisdiction of the Commission.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HBAF9E4CD53A64A319D8582D9B0279CE1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rulemaking
			 authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1
			 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall, in
			 consultation with the Federal Communications Commission and in accordance with
			 section 553 of title 5, United States Code, issue regulations to carry out this
			 Act. In promulgating such regulations, the Commission shall—</text>
				<paragraph id="HD6F580A68764401C920FB463A9F30997"><enum>(1)</enum><text>take into consideration
			 the need for clear disclosures that provide for easy comprehension and
			 comparison by consumers, taking into account the size of prepaid calling cards;
			 and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HFCC0591A45DA4FD58A7E3FA6573789FA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>give due consideration to
			 the views of the Federal Communications Commission with regard to matters for
			 which that Commission has particular expertise and authority and shall take
			 into consideration the views of States.</text>
				</paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">In
			 promulgating such regulations, the Commission may prescribe requirements
			 concerning the order, format, presentation, and design of disclosures required
			 by this Act and may establish and require the use of uniform terms, symbols, or
			 categories to describe or disclose fees and additional charges, if the
			 Commission finds that such requirements will assist consumers in making
			 purchasing decisions and effectuate the purposes of this Act. The Commission
			 shall not issue regulations that otherwise specify the rates, terms, and
			 conditions of prepaid calling cards.</continuation-text></subsection><subsection id="HA61941B90B92466AAE2DBA772B087B82"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Savings
			 provision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act
			 shall be construed to limit the authority of the Commission under any other
			 provision of law. Except to the extent expressly provided in this Act, nothing
			 in this Act shall be construed to alter or affect the exemption for common
			 carriers provided by section 5(a)(2) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (15
			 U.S.C. 45(a)(2)). Nothing in this Act is intended to limit the authority of the
			 Federal Communications Commission.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H07CFE950EDCE4338ADAC2EC0ACFAB98B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Federal Communications Commission
			 initiates a rulemaking proceeding to establish requirements relating to the
			 disclosure of terms and conditions of prepaid calling cards, the Federal
			 Communications Commission shall coordinate with the Federal Trade Commission to
			 ensure that any such requirements are not inconsistent with the requirements of
			 this Act and the regulations issued under subsection (c).</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H0FD68D5B598D433493C8849A9D0F5C09"><enum>5.</enum><header>State
			 enforcement</header>
			<subsection id="H79A81C5A27ED42F0B41738017CEAAAF2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header>
				<paragraph id="H6985CC6756724F458E0A506853212445"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Civil
			 actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In any case in which
			 the attorney general of a State, a State utility commission, or other consumer
			 protection agency has reason to believe that an interest of the residents of
			 that State has been or is threatened or adversely affected by the engagement of
			 any person in a practice that is prohibited under this Act, the State utility
			 commission or other consumer protection agency, if authorized by State law, or
			 the State, as parens patriae, may bring a civil action on behalf of the
			 residents of that State in a district court of the United States of appropriate
			 jurisdiction, or any other court of competent jurisdiction to—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HFFE2735DF38247689298C8C7AA26D1E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enjoin that
			 practice;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF64528370764EA695FC099BAC015D0D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enforce compliance with
			 this Act;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE8B9E46248440CC8726108E14718374"><enum>(C)</enum><text>obtain damage,
			 restitution, or other compensation on behalf of residents of the State;
			 or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D65135307DD479B97F27637A62859BE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>obtain such other relief
			 as the court may consider to be appropriate.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD694996A990443188840522F44AA1BEE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice to the
			 Commission</header>
					<subparagraph id="HFD04632FF0484AA8B422BBEF3D178F5A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before filing an
			 action under paragraph (1), the State shall provide to the Commission—</text>
						<clause id="HC7D0EEF2FEC24E0DA73C32DA65A35FA4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>written notice of the
			 action; and</text>
						</clause><clause id="H331233A4222C43A4B9C486AC14F15D57"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a copy of the complaint
			 for the action.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H210C6010CFE44969BC496732E869567B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exemption</header>
						<clause id="H9E083AD280064776AFDF96FFA80A18BF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subparagraph (A)
			 shall not apply with respect to the filing of an action by a State under this
			 subsection, if the attorney general or other appropriate officer determines
			 that it is not feasible to provide the notice described in that subparagraph
			 before the filing of the action.</text>
						</clause><clause id="H93421B93A1004BCEA8AFCFC1E2AF3299"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In an action described in clause (i), the
			 State shall provide notice and a copy of the complaint to the Commission at the
			 same time as the State files the action.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H83F21DED514B47C08C953179E15367C9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Intervention by
			 Commission</header>
				<paragraph id="HC3080F12DB0D4D80B1D5E81783F67ACB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>On receiving notice under subsection (a)(2), the
			 Commission shall have the right to intervene in the action that is the subject
			 of the notice.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HDF422435D85346A794F0002FDF1E544F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effect of
			 intervention</header><text>If the Commission intervenes in an action under
			 subsection (a), it shall have the right—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H399502C1B46844C895F7BE40BC411283"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to be heard with respect
			 to any matter that arises in that action;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B3DECC0DDEE4DF2AA9AEDAC7448FD65"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to remove the action to
			 the appropriate United States District Court; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6FEC503AA0304D1297F97EB4B728947E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to file a petition for
			 appeal.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8967D95F2FC446EB97B77696BD727CBE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of bringing any civil action
			 under subsection (a), nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent an
			 attorney general of a State, a State utility commission, or other consumer
			 protection agency authorized by State law from exercising the powers conferred
			 on the attorney general or other appropriate official by the laws of that State
			 to—</text>
				<paragraph id="HC2169E2FDD8A40CF8D1A79192485AE1E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct
			 investigations;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HF8FC45B86B514763B79A695784D614B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>administer oaths or
			 affirmations;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H6582EEFC5D6E4E95ABA7E4783559C6FE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>compel the attendance of
			 witnesses or the production of documentary and other evidence; or</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H40EC6180DD4643FB97B24FF3F8F81602"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enforce any State law.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H95BF2DA6B1314722B5AB23BBED4E4D9F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Action by the
			 Commission may preclude State action</header><text>In any case in which an
			 action is instituted by or on behalf of the Commission for violation of this
			 Act, or any regulation issued under this Act, no State may, during the pendency
			 of that action, institute an action under subsection (a) against any defendant
			 named in the complaint in that action for violation of this Act or
			 regulation.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H927CBF06CE3D4467AF1D86885356CC22"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Venue; service of
			 process</header>
				<paragraph id="H2960BABC37B949E7A8CC4B613644CE9D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Venue</header><text>Any
			 action brought under subsection (a) may be brought in the district court of the
			 United States that meets applicable requirements relating to venue under
			 section 1391 of title 28, United States Code.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HB5E3B6BBD5724BC290C58B7A3980E4D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Service of
			 process</header><text>In an action brought under subsection (a), process may be
			 served in any district in which the defendant—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HBD034848E12641708419FF4546E229A3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is an inhabitant;
			 or</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC17E69785A0A43C69C06880703CCAAE9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may be found.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA8FBEE68C5FB48C9836A9233B9BE4892"><enum>6.</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act shall apply to—</text>
			<paragraph id="H479E073D21F8488BA2EE858F7C143EDA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any prepaid calling card
			 issued or placed into the stream of commerce beginning 180 days after the date
			 on which final regulations are promulgated pursuant to section 4(c); and</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H457173A38C404AEABB58FCCA583BB298"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any advertising, promotion, point-of-sale
			 material or voice prompt regarding a prepaid calling card that is disseminated
			 beginning 180 days after the date on which final regulations are promulgated
			 pursuant to section 4(c).</text>
			</paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="H90E36F8EE0ED4072AFC3194A8A357D82"><enum>7.</enum><header>Effect on State
			 laws</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">After the date on which
			 final regulations are promulgated pursuant to section 4(c), no State or
			 political subdivision of a State may establish or continue in effect any
			 provision of law that contains requirements regarding disclosures to be printed
			 on prepaid calling cards or packaging unless such requirements are identical to
			 the requirements of section 3.</text>
		</section><section id="H449543DDC41C4E0696742BCA839F69C2"><enum>8.</enum><header>Studies</header>
			<subsection id="HFEEE086389E34D14BC62D66B195902B3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>GAO Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning 2 years after the date on which
			 final regulations are promulgated pursuant to section 4(c), the Comptroller
			 General shall conduct a study of the effectiveness of this Act and the
			 disclosures required under this Act and shall submit a report of such study to
			 Congress not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HA08B3C8AF1E0469780ABD7AEA7BCF0F0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>FTC Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall, in consultation with
			 the Federal Communications Commission, conduct a study of the extent to which
			 the business practices of the prepaid calling card industry intended to be
			 addressed by this Act exist in the prepaid wireless industry and shall submit a
			 report of such study, including recommendations, if any, to Congress not later
			 than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
	<endorsement display="yes">
		<action-date date="20100615">June 15, 2010</action-date>
		<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of
		  the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be
		  printed</action-desc>
	</endorsement>
</bill>
