<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HBF6EA7B444D74171A0BB95E95F9E96DB" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 3195 EH: ADA Amendments Act of 2008</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">110th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 3195</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To restore the intent and protections of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="H8578A96C114B42F5A3D315E73150DE62" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HDBF1A65A0075455FAF5350E16F270830" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>ADA Amendments Act of 2008</short-title></quote>.</text> </section>
<section id="HE8987082A4F74A5CAEA2CE5F2055A561"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings and purposes</header> 
<subsection id="H4BEB6A5B0E32453AB1E3FA124B901CEA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1B1B693D7B204BB6ACE8E7BA3044E447"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in enacting the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (ADA), Congress intended that the Act <quote>provide a clear and comprehensive national mandate for the elimination of discrimination against individuals with disabilities</quote> and provide broad coverage;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBBBDC69EFE19455997B0813184B2918F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in enacting the ADA, Congress recognized that physical and mental disabilities in no way diminish a person’s right to fully participate in all aspects of society, but that people with physical or mental disabilities are frequently precluded from doing so because of prejudice, antiquated attitudes, or the failure to remove societal and institutional barriers;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6AF5EA548DEA4CE1B9F0F7DA9CD02D14"><enum>(3)</enum><text>while Congress expected that the definition of disability under the ADA would be interpreted consistently with how courts had applied the definition of handicap under the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, that expectation has not been fulfilled;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6875BD554DC84FB786B2F81477283ED5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the holdings of the Supreme Court in Sutton v. United Airlines, Inc., 527 U.S. 471 (1999) and its companion cases, and in Toyota Motor Manufacturing, Kentucky, Inc. v. Williams, 534 U.S. 184 (2002) have narrowed the broad scope of protection intended to be afforded by the ADA, thus eliminating protection for many individuals whom Congress intended to protect; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB8371D17D7D5423A8D4E5EE0BD411EC1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>as a result of these Supreme Court cases, lower courts have incorrectly found in individual cases that people with a range of substantially limiting impairments are not people with disabilities.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2751E5225C1E4C0F8836AF88B9F402D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of this Act are—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC4569D0247654CFF96F947D180A755C3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to carry out the ADA’s objectives of providing <quote>a clear and comprehensive national mandate for the elimination of discrimination</quote> and <quote>clear, strong, consistent, enforceable standards addressing discrimination</quote> by reinstating a broad scope of protection to be available under the ADA;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H27E6F07E4AF94FC588E796CB0700F14C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to reject the requirement enunciated by the Supreme Court in Sutton v. United Airlines, Inc., 527 U.S. 471 (1999) and its companion cases that whether an impairment substantially limits a major life activity is to be determined with reference to the ameliorative effects of mitigating measures;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC86EA7C57C5446DEA7C25B114C12208D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to reject the Supreme Court’s reasoning in Sutton v. United Airlines, Inc., 527 U.S. 471 (1999) with regard to coverage under the third prong of the definition of disability and to reinstate the reasoning of the Supreme Court in School Board of Nassau County v. Arline, 480 U.S. 273 (1987) which set forth a broad view of the third prong of the definition of handicap under the Rehabilitation Act of 1973;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE6FEFD04E8434533AAD300F431869432"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to reject the standards enunciated by the Supreme Court in Toyota Motor Manufacturing, Kentucky, Inc. v. Williams, 534 U.S. 184 (2002), that the terms <term>substantially</term> and <term>major</term> in the definition of disability under the ADA <quote>need to be interpreted strictly to create a demanding standard for qualifying as disabled,</quote> and that to be substantially limited in performing a major life activity under the ADA <quote>an individual must have an impairment that prevents or severely restricts the individual from doing activities that are of central importance to most people’s daily lives</quote>; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB58B421A869545FD9208D66CC6C55571"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to provide a new definition of <quote>substantially limits</quote> to indicate that Congress intends to depart from the strict and demanding standard applied by the Supreme Court in Toyota Motor Manufacturing, Kentucky, Inc. v. Williams and by numerous lower courts.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HBF6C52E8AAD54D90BF4BF270355366B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Codified findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2(a) of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB6DA4E9A6B9942F4A66EDAE4DB50BB7F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending paragraph (1) to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HA0577157DAD84CB782A919C1AACD560" style="OLC">
<paragraph id="HF30552969BC1486181567E15D991932B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>physical or mental disabilities in no way diminish a person’s right to fully participate in all aspects of society, yet many people with physical or mental disabilities have been precluded from doing so because of discrimination; others who have a record of a disability or are regarded as having a disability also have been subjected to discrimination;</text> </paragraph> <after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H40A536B58F924F199CFCDBC00D1C073"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (7).</text> </paragraph></section>
<section id="H5D08E9DF888147939EFA7743BF077100"><enum>4.</enum><header>Disability defined and rules of construction</header> 
<subsection id="HD0DE6121D21941228F298E943800C897"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of disability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12102">42 U.S.C. 12102</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE42D9759784A427DA992E2F2A8958FB3" style="OLC">
<section id="H5963E7F9FA234A17BDDDF1BD3EA7B3B9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definition of disability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">As used in this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HAD8DC9B149B74BA98EA3FC57017792BC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Disability</header><text>The term <term>disability</term> means, with respect to an individual—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD2C914985AF5429E962903C8EE498B1D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a physical or mental impairment that substantially limits one or more major life activities of such individual;</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H507E961B51924FEAA200C1F3A6979C2F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a record of such an impairment; or</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2C6989879AFF420C862914B2ECBECE5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>being regarded as having such an impairment (as described in paragraph (4)).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HA8767676C1DB4192B51523328D2B4756"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Substantially limits</header><text>The term <term>substantially limits</term> means materially restricts.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6B3F505C85664B02B84F32BD2F5624BC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Major life activities</header> 
<subparagraph id="HF61B686CAB104647B429AEDF78BB225"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), major life activities include, but are not limited to, caring for oneself, performing manual tasks, seeing, hearing, eating, sleeping, walking, standing, lifting, bending, speaking, breathing, learning, reading, concentrating, thinking, communicating and working.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD9C92084D75042B18CBEFD8D907C7807"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Major bodily functions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of paragraph (1), a major life activity also includes the operation of a major bodily function, including but not limited to, functions of the immune system, normal cell growth, digestive, bowel, bladder, neurological, brain, respiratory, circulatory, endocrine, and reproductive functions.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4AFC16C18EA741A6B1CACDEA63287DBC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Regarded as having such an impairment</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1)(C):</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1E6FB1A011B74BF390B3384FA31E3344"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An individual meets the requirement of <quote>being regarded as having such an impairment</quote> if the individual establishes that he or she has been subjected to an action prohibited under this Act because of an actual or perceived physical or mental impairment whether or not the impairment limits or is perceived to limit a major life activity.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA87939D8E67C48E39E88D0CD187FF751"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (1)(C) shall not apply to impairments that are transitory and minor. A transitory impairment is an impairment with an actual or expected duration of 6 months or less.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H21132F8153A44311866238379B32DA36"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Rules of construction regarding the definition of disability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The definition of <quote>disability</quote> in paragraph (1) shall be construed in accordance with the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD0D4FB91542B4F0CA2E9149BF6204EF7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To achieve the remedial purposes of this Act, the definition of <quote>disability</quote> in paragraph (1) shall be construed broadly.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HFCF0AA44571F478BAA0918003DE74B51"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An impairment that substantially limits one major life activity need not limit other major life activities in order to be considered a disability.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HBE1390E0499D4B85BC92ACD279BAB7E3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An impairment that is episodic or in remission is a disability if it would substantially limit a major life activity when active.</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H2E95788811C6499090E727412699D2B8"><enum>(D)</enum>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9F01CCB4C0A2424DAF59B3B7698C1BA3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The determination of whether an impairment substantially limits a major life activity shall be made without regard to the ameliorative effects of mitigating measures such as—</text> 
<subclause commented="no" id="HA34B952DECC54E8F89C6CBE0C5326DF3" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>medication, medical supplies, equipment, or appliances, low-vision devices (which do not include ordinary eyeglasses or contact lenses), prosthetics including limbs and devices, hearing aids and cochlear implants or other implantable hearing devices, mobility devices, or oxygen therapy equipment and supplies;</text> </subclause>
<subclause commented="no" id="H5592E79F6EA545889B73D654C6DEA191" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>use of assistive technology;</text> </subclause>
<subclause commented="no" id="H690B4A75A5C3435988313E051F6C14ED" indent="up1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>reasonable accommodations or auxiliary aids or services; or</text> </subclause>
<subclause commented="no" id="H90F2EA4B5AE4454A9F40A02464727105" indent="up1"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>learned behavioral or adaptive neurological modifications.</text> </subclause></clause>
<clause id="H0E5C7B638D8B49CC9E88CC28613F8C73" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The ameliorative effects of the mitigating measures of ordinary eyeglasses or contact lenses shall be considered in determining whether an impairment substantially limits a major life activity.</text> </clause>
<clause commented="no" id="H832BAE1628EB46EA8199BEB18C7EA39" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>As used in this subparagraph—</text> 
<subclause id="HF422A691E8AA43A593859800D18771FE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the term <term>ordinary eyeglasses or contact lenses</term> means lenses that are intended to fully correct visual acuity or eliminate refractive error; and</text> </subclause>
<subclause id="H7AD86AEC9E5D4C3B9D4600D67017A847"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the term <term>low-vision devices</term> means devices that magnify, enhance, or otherwise augment a visual image.</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection>
<subsection id="H0A8F827954D44595A519B900D4CCA3DC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>) is further amended by adding after section 3 the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCB3D5F0B2BD54BDF8F93B0ED355C10D2" style="OLC">
<section id="HF95C94C1BCFA4CBFA5C34EF684B20832"><enum>4.</enum><header>Additional definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">As used in this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H6D58C1B3C2784335AFA054787262ABE7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Auxiliary aids and services</header><text>The term <term>auxiliary aids and services</term> includes—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC35A2029C2AB4DDCACF2768FDB9FFDA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>qualified interpreters or other effective methods of making aurally delivered materials available to individuals with hearing impairments;</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1185F6300DF94620AC129B3451041F05"><enum>(B)</enum><text>qualified readers, taped texts, or other effective methods of making visually delivered materials available to individuals with visual impairments;</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H76C16D82423245BE00295C4F01204603"><enum>(C)</enum><text>acquisition or modification of equipment or devices; and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD1DB5F5F541D46E9BF749D827691601D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>other similar services and actions.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H898D6EA08722407FBD30752455CBA401"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, Guam, American Samoa, the Virgin Islands, the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands.</text> </paragraph></section> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection>
<subsection id="H1772EA3C531443C4B4661F84B7D1C4ED"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Amendment to the table of contents</header><text>The table of contents contained in section 1(b) of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 is amended by striking the item relating to section 3 and inserting the following items:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE878A3EA94CE4F999332037844F9457E" style="OLC">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 3. Definition of disability.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 4. Additional definitions.</toc-entry> </toc> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection></section>
<section id="HF10C5D72479242C5AE7E003153993BEE"><enum>5.</enum><header>Discrimination on the basis of disability</header> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HECD88B6EAF474042B33953FD6397A34B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>On the basis of disability</header><text>Section 102 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12112">42 U.S.C. 12112</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HB38E364E7A3F49C8B5E9D3964227F6F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>with a disability because of the disability of such individual</quote> and inserting <quote>on the basis of disability</quote>; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H63AAAD7759224213B0B7515B0087F6F1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b) in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>discriminate</quote> and inserting <quote>discriminate against a qualified individual on the basis of disability</quote>.</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H23A75A0146EE49B69E312397DDED04E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualification standards and tests related to uncorrected vision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 103 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12113">42 U.S.C. 12113</external-xref>) is amended by redesignating subsections (c) and (d) as subsections (d) and (e), respectively, and inserting after subsection (b) the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H767E7BB0B3994701B7AD26C800DCCA81" style="OLC">
<subsection commented="no" id="H6C10D22BA4E54069AD4BBED36500005C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Qualification standards and tests related to uncorrected vision</header><text>Notwithstanding section 3(5)(D)(ii), a covered entity shall not use qualification standards, employment tests, or other selection criteria based on an individual’s uncorrected vision unless the standard, test, or other selection criteria, as used by the covered entity, is shown to be job-related for the position in question and consistent with business necessity.</text> </subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection>
<subsection id="H9607BBCBB8274AC998C9179B00EB3D6C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 101(8) of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12111">42 U.S.C. 12111(8)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9F274491E05048479344F71E8FDE3602"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the paragraph heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">with a disability</header-in-text></quote>; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2DE57A38E96441EC929C8F4BDDDFB041"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>with a disability</quote> after <quote>individual</quote> both places it appears.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H47956F2F5BF145F4B400E1FD01263101"><enum>6.</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title V of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12201">42 U.S.C. 12201</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HDC36BCAE30CF4BE7AEE13C8F432F83C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by adding at the end of section 501 the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4AC78BFAC6D74FCAB1FB058167A6C1D1" style="OLC">
<subsection id="HE2CD0315CE744AA7B3202CBAF0284159"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Benefits under state worker’s compensation laws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act alters the standards for determining eligibility for benefits under State worker’s compensation laws or under State and Federal disability benefit programs.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H601C21DD60484274B0CAEE257D00D085"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Claims of no disability</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall provide the basis for a claim by a person without a disability that he or she was subject to discrimination because of his or her lack of disability.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H18629CEC8E964F1C9CD3BBE85B03AE1"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Reasonable accommodations and modifications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered entity under title I, a public entity under title II, and any person who owns, leases (or leases to), or operates a place of public accommodation under title III, need not provide a reasonable accommodation or a reasonable modification to policies, practices, or procedures to an individual who meets the definition of disability in section 3(1) solely under subparagraph (C).</text> </subsection> <after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0BDAF0D4FA764882B7E424FF51A1D85B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating section 506 through 514 as sections 507 through 515, respectively, and adding after section 505 the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE53D3E62A68447918F29364C6B97ADD6" style="OLC">
<section commented="no" id="HEA45C1AD400C4AE6888982FFC11401C3"><enum>506.</enum><header>Rule of construction regarding regulatory authority</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The authority to issue regulations granted to the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, the Attorney General, and the Secretary of Transportation under this Act includes the authority to issue regulations implementing the definitions contained in sections 3 and 4.</text> </section> <after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9572D99B6EA140AEAE876840608D2657"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in the table of contents contained in section 1(b), by redesignating the items relating to sections 506 through 514 as sections 507 through 515, respectively, and by inserting after the item relating to section 505 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H44CA2E3A16EC48DF878229801CB325B1" style="OLC">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 506. Rule of construction regarding regulatory authority.</toc-entry> </toc> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></section>
<section id="HDFD39A851B8648E28FE59B5EADBDBFE8"><enum>7.</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 7 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/705">29 U.S.C. 705</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H160CCB188A694AD0AC62E6C4366448E8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (9)(B), by striking <quote>a physical</quote> and all that follows through <quote>major life activities</quote>, and inserting <quote>the meaning given it in section 3 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990</quote>; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6CF7DF45C2A7467B9774F885FE99B19E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (20)(B), by striking <quote>any person who</quote> and all that follows through the period at the end, and inserting <quote>any person who has a disability as defined in section 3 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990.</quote>.</text> </paragraph></section>
<section id="HB1C675CF8DCB4A7EAC07B4E62200D254"><enum>8.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act and the amendments made by this Act shall become effective on January 1, 2009.</text> </section>
</legis-body> 
<legis-body changed="added" committee-id="HJU00" display-enacting-clause="no-display-enacting-clause" id="H8C85B99C553146FE8F6650203CFABF9B" reported-display-style="boldface-roman" style="OLC">
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20080625" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives June 25, 2008.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 


