<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H5CC4B834570E4E389D938DF51CECC083" public-private="public"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code> 
<calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 265</calendar>
<congress display="yes">111th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 3125</legis-num>
<associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 111–462]</associated-doc> 
<current-chamber display="yes">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20090708">July 8, 2009</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000215">Mr. Waxman</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B000657">Mr. Boucher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000213">Mr. Barton of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000822">Mr. Stearns</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000355">Mr. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000133">Mr. Markey of Massachusetts</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000482">Mr. Doyle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000309">Mr. Gordon of Tennessee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001173">Mr. Space</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001166">Mr. McNerney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000026">Mr. Inslee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001045">Mr. Stupak</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001203">Mr. Buyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000800">Mr. Welch</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="U000031">Mr. Upton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00" added-display-style="italic" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<action>
<action-date date="20100413">April 13, 2010</action-date>
<action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="T000459">Mr. Terry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000380">Mrs. Christensen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000572">Mr. Rogers of Michigan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001228">Mrs. Bono Mack</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001251">Mr. Butterfield</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001036">Mrs. Capps</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001155">Mr. Sullivan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000128">Mr. Van Hollen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001243">Mrs. Blackburn</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. Scott of Georgia</cosponsor></action-desc>
</action>
<action>
<action-date date="20100413">April 13, 2010</action-date>
<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc>
<action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction>
<action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on July 8, 2009</action-instruction>
</action>
<action display="yes">
<action-desc display="yes"><pagebreak/></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To require an inventory of radio spectrum bands managed by the National Telecommunications and Information Administration and the Federal Communications Commission.<pagebreak/></official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HIF00" reported-display-style="italic" id="HB4043B0E2F37438F938A756F21BAD757">
<section id="H51845A0C2D044A52B7F724E217BA364C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Radio Spectrum Inventory Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section>
<section id="HE0B222B762AF43618844AB3EBA0476B8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Spectrum inventory</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part B of title I of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration Organization Act (47 U.S.C. 921 et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H78F4C7AD3E6641B8BAC662C40F9D5B77" style="OLC">
<section id="HE98A747C4D214507A4AE24AFD299B06D"><enum>119.</enum><header>Spectrum inventory</header>
<subsection id="H453C46D127D5460DBE4F994D3BAD5279"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Radio spectrum inventory</header><text>In order to promote the efficient use of the electromagnetic spectrum, the NTIA and the Commission shall coordinate and carry out each of the following activities not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H9A20FD1AE6E6461A903C23C47751FE9E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (e), create an inventory of each radio spectrum band of frequencies listed in the United States Table of Frequency Allocations, from 225 megahertz to, at a minimum, 3.7 gigahertz, and to 10 gigahertz unless the NTIA and the Commission determine that the burden of expanding the inventory outweighs the benefit, that includes—</text>
<subparagraph id="H69EFD06986EF4D56BD6C206DE2D32966"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the radio services authorized to operate in each band of frequencies;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4E8220429CBD4AA89762F77782B34F42"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the identity of each Federal or non-Federal user within each such radio service authorized to operate in each band of frequencies;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDDEB95AEA79444A38BDADCA1D44FC1B9"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the activities, capabilities, functions, or missions (including whether such activities, capabilities, functions, or missions are space-based, air-based, or ground-based) supported by the transmitters, end-user terminals or receivers, or other radio frequency devices authorized to operate in each band of frequencies; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9D27270C88C646AEB553D4734844A270"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total amount of spectrum, by band of frequencies, assigned or licensed to each Federal or non-Federal user (in percentage terms and in sum) and the geographic areas covered by their respective assignments or licenses;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF6E8E03DE3A8455192A400499A11D86D"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the approximate number of transmitters, end-user terminals or receivers, or other radio frequency devices authorized to operate, as appropriate to characterize the extent of use of each radio service in each band of frequencies;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2232672943CB4570AA25BF60976A1A47"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an approximation of the extent to which each Federal or non-Federal user is using, by geography, each band of frequencies, such as the amount and percentage of time of use, number of end users, or other measures as appropriate to the particular band and radio service; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB1FF7DE6ADE24231A008984A714A0FED"><enum>(G)</enum><text>to the greatest extent possible—</text>
<clause id="H1488EE111268424D8721CE6BC2A8B5D2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>contour maps or other information that illustrate the coverage area, receiver performance, and other parameters relevant to an assessment of the availability of spectrum in each band; </text></clause>
<clause id="H037FA605218F43729F2D83AF2E9C2C06"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each band or range of frequencies, the identity of each entity offering unlicensed services and the types and approximate number of unlicensed intentional radiators verified or certified by the Commission that are authorized to operate; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HCA56EA6137784F29A233791C696C5115"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>for non-Federal users, any commercial names under which facilities-based service is offered to the public using the spectrum of the non-Federal user, including the commercial names under which the spectrum is being offered through resale.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1E1A01743E9443508969AA4BE5DA6945"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Except as provided in subsection (e), create a centralized portal or Web site to make the inventory of the bands of frequencies required under paragraph (1) available to the public.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H0A807D94156840788041DCC7040ECB9A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of agency resources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In creating the inventory described in <internal-xref idref="H9A20FD1AE6E6461A903C23C47751FE9E" legis-path="119.(a)(1)">subsection (a)(1)</internal-xref>, the NTIA and the Commission shall first use agency resources, including existing databases, field testing, and recordkeeping systems, and only request information from Federal and non-Federal users if such information cannot be obtained using such agency resources.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HF073506D6B2744559DF93A29B6E0BB78"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports</header>
<paragraph id="HEB880C7DC70F4A20911FCC821413580F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (e), not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this section and biennially thereafter, the NTIA and the Commission shall submit a report to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives containing—</text>
<subparagraph id="H397160AA8D5A44619F0636695278573C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the results of the inventory created under <internal-xref idref="H9A20FD1AE6E6461A903C23C47751FE9E" legis-path="119.(a)(1)">subsection (a)(1)</internal-xref>, including any update to the information in the inventory pursuant to subsection (d);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H04FBC0610A6B41D7B52E60E0B15ACCE7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of any information the NTIA or the Commission determines is necessary for such inventory but that is unavailable; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7FE001CC313F457B897E4ABFF2C5E0C9"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of any information not provided by any Federal or non-Federal user in accordance with <internal-xref idref="H0FC599B50D8F462B82E2208A658E05CE" legis-path="119.(e)">subsections (e)(1)(B)(ii) and (e)(2)(C)(ii).</internal-xref></text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4418947BB4F74714B5D6FC5BC07BBCFC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Relocation report</header>
<subparagraph id="H07331DA31732475EA7133A6B335D0FC6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (e), the NTIA and the Commission shall submit a report to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives containing a recommendation of which spectrum, if any, should be reallocated or otherwise made available for shared access and an explanation of the basis for that recommendation.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0D7A309920234D439FB1267E5E2CEC2C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Deadlines</header><text>The report required under <internal-xref idref="H07331DA31732475EA7133A6B335D0FC6" legis-path="119.(c)(3)(A)">subparagraph (A)</internal-xref> shall be submitted not later than 4 years after the date of enactment of this section and every 4 years thereafter.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H43A7ABA9BDC24A85ADDEE684E387070E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Inventory report</header><text>If the NTIA and the Commission have not conducted an inventory under subsection (a) to 10 gigahertz at least 90 days before the third report required under paragraph (1) is submitted, the NTIA and the Comission shall include an evaluation in such report and in every report thereafter of whether the burden of expanding the inventory to 10 gigahertz outweighs the benefit until such time as the NTIA and the Commission have conducted the inventory to 10 gigahertz.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD5B77F9069A04EAEA66CD1DC85C5EC6B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Maintenance and Updating of Information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After the creation of the inventory required by <internal-xref idref="H9A20FD1AE6E6461A903C23C47751FE9E" legis-path="119.(a)(1)">subsection (a)(1)</internal-xref>, the NTIA and the Commission shall make all reasonable efforts to maintain and update the information required under such subsection on a quarterly basis, including when there is a transfer or auction of a license or a change in a permanent assignment or license.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H0FC599B50D8F462B82E2208A658E05CE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>National security and public safety information</header>
<paragraph id="H3987FACC1FA24D6BAB12F0BA75C2CE29"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Nondisclosure</header>
<subparagraph id="H6372F823A64A4DA9AF395276C0444019"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the head of an executive agency of the Federal Government determines that public disclosure of certain information held by that agency or a licensee of non-Federal spectrum and required by subsection (a), (c), or (d) would reveal classified national security information or other information for which there is a legal basis for nondisclosure and such public disclosure would be detrimental to national security, homeland security, or public safety, the agency head shall notify the NTIA of that determination and shall include descriptions of the activities, capabilities, functions, or missions (including whether they are space-based, air-based, or ground-based) supported by the information being withheld.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H37435090823745D496051B276C8EAA07"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Information provided</header><text>The agency head shall provide to NTIA—</text>
<clause id="HB08D22AC1B3648FBB1CE1A44E2CD6AEB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the publicly releasable information required by <internal-xref idref="H9A20FD1AE6E6461A903C23C47751FE9E" legis-path="119.(a)(1)">subsection (a)(1)</internal-xref>;</text></clause>
<clause id="HD0C8FBD7E90B403389FBFDCF684B6C14"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable, a summary description, suitable for public release, of the classified national security information or other information for which there is a legal basis for nondisclosure; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H46D6E0CC8B3F4D09A25AF24DB7FAA17C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a classified annex, under appropriate cover, containing the classified national security information or other information for which there is a legal basis for nondisclosure that the agency head has determined must be withheld from public disclosure.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H67CA1891B5A84247A14982E771214F63"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public safety nondisclosure</header>
<subparagraph id="HAF743330A9FF41E6A72E3149E1CE90EA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a licensee of non-Federal spectrum determines that public disclosure of certain information held by that licensee and required to be submitted by subsection (a), (c), or (d) would reveal information for which public disclosure would be detrimental to public safety, or the licensee is otherwise prohibited by law from disclosing the information, the licensee may petition the Commission for a partial or total exemption from inclusion on the centralized portal or Web site under subsection (a)(2) and in the report required by subsection (c).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD99459F4E7CA4595AB08BFF61B741431"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Burden</header><text>The licensee seeking an exemption under this paragraph bears the burden of justifying the exemption and shall provide clear and convincing evidence to support such an exemption.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H901A037A1DA84D01B4913B446541BFC6"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Information required</header><text>If an exemption is granted under this paragraph, the licensee shall provide to the Commission—</text>
<clause id="HB8253775AA884C56AEA3BF1766FB2294"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the publicly releasable information required by subsection (a)(1) for the inventory;</text></clause>
<clause id="H20968DE69B414105BA2872632C4F1456"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the maximum extent practicable, a summary description, suitable for public release, of the information for which public disclosure would be detrimental to public safety or the licensee is otherwise prohibited by law from disclosing; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H419FCBF9D95549B7B2D22CB068C1CE98"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an annex, under appropriate cover, containing the information that the Commission has determined should be withheld from public disclosure.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3B8A5471EEFD46E4AECB7D1FE17B941E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional disclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The annexes required under <internal-xref idref="H46D6E0CC8B3F4D09A25AF24DB7FAA17C" legis-path="119.(e)(1)(C)">paragraphs (1)(B)(iii)</internal-xref> and (2)(C)(iii) shall be provided to the congressional committees listed in <internal-xref idref="HF073506D6B2744559DF93A29B6E0BB78" legis-path="119.(c)">subsection (c)</internal-xref>, but shall not be disclosed to the public under <internal-xref idref="H453C46D127D5460DBE4F994D3BAD5279" legis-path="119.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> or <internal-xref idref="HD5B77F9069A04EAEA66CD1DC85C5EC6B" legis-path="119.(d)">subsection (d)</internal-xref> or provided to any unauthorized person through any other means.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H05517752542D4B5C9F73BF36C973E7B8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>National Security Council consultation</header><text>Prior to the release of the inventory under subsection (a), any updates to the inventory resulting from subsection (d), or the submission of a report under subsection (c)(1), the NTIA and the Commission shall consult with the National Security Council for a period not to exceed 30 days for the purposes of determining what additional information, if any, shall be withheld from the public.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD0EB956FEAB14DBAABA3B097FD8AD25F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Proprietary information</header><text>In creating and maintaining the inventory, centralized portal or Web site, and reports under this section, the NTIA and the Commission shall follow their rules and practice regarding confidential and proprietary information. Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to compel the Commission to make publicly available any confidential or proprietary information.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
</legis-body> 
<endorsement display="yes">
<action-date date="20100413">April 13, 2010</action-date>
<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement>
</bill> 
