<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H3C38887B18BA40D49CA0031192D91410" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 4463 IH: Veterans Health Care Quality
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-12-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 4463</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20071212">December 12, 2007</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000794">Mr. Costello</sponsor> (for
			 himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001167">Mr. Mitchell</cosponsor>,
			 <cosponsor name-id="S000364">Mr. Shimkus</cosponsor>, and
			 <cosponsor name-id="W000413">Mr. Whitfield</cosponsor>) introduced the
			 following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name>, and in
			 addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and
			 Government Reform</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined
			 by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall
			 within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to improve the
		  quality of care provided to veterans in Department of Veterans Affairs medical
		  facilities, to encourage highly qualified doctors to serve in hard-to-fill
		  positions in such medical facilities, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H38D7CDB7E58B40E6B8FC9E5EB006FD8" style="OLC">
		<section id="HBEDEFC310A534921B618BFDF68948C81" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Veterans Health Care Quality
			 Improvement Act</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="HFBF3D13DA3B8415797511289FC912173"><enum>2.</enum><header>Standards for
			 appointment and practice of physicians in Department of Veterans Affairs
			 medical facilities</header>
			<subsection id="HD129AEB080634C74B57CD2FEFAEC172"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Standards</header>
				<paragraph id="H56BE690F838E46328C004936E1EEE186"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/74">chapter 74</external-xref> of title 38, United States
			 Code, is amended by inserting after section 7402 the following new
			 section:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H03B1A06127DC41F283A9D44196C2691C" style="USC">
						<section id="H865978250347402995D919D8D3D4C987"><enum>7402A.</enum><header>Appointment
				and practice of physicians: standards</header>
							<subsection id="HFB4249ED9FF34650A34741053D734DAE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
				general</header><text>The Secretary shall, acting through the Under Secretary
				for Health, prescribe standards to be met by individuals in order to qualify
				for appointment in the Administration in the position of physician and to
				practice as a physician in medical facilities of the Administration. The
				standards shall incorporate the requirements of this section.</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="H92ED619AFD794BC7901D8B5DBA9B8326"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Disclosure of
				certain information before appointment</header><text>Each individual seeking
				appointment in the Administration in the position of physician shall do the
				following:</text>
								<paragraph id="H5552A88FD3C24F30A2D835A524A17BEC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Provide the
				Secretary a full and complete explanation of the following:</text>
									<subparagraph id="HC3663A6654D84EF6A4E30147DA00DC77"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Each lawsuit,
				civil action, or other claim (whether open or closed) brought against the
				individual for medical malpractice or negligence (other than a lawsuit, action,
				or claim closed without any judgment against or payment by or on behalf of the
				individual).</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD685667CC2854CA2925380F2861DEFB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Each payment made
				by or on behalf of the individual to settle any lawsuit, action, or claim
				covered by subparagraph (A).</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01265712149749F0A1CFB6F349D3DB1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Each investigation
				or disciplinary action taken against the individual relating to the
				individual's performance as a physician.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H04FA26D5AB4B4D10AD37116533285217"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Submit a written
				request and authorization to the State licensing board of each State in which
				the individual holds or has held a license to practice medicine to disclose to
				the Secretary any information in the records of such State on the
				following:</text>
									<subparagraph id="H1DFB3468A69E4E3E99FEC88FC980075"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Each lawsuit, civil
				action, or other claim brought against the individual for medical malpractice
				or negligence covered by paragraph (1)(A) that occurred in such State.</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1678A26D5C1146C395F26FE1254954AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Each payment made
				by or on behalf of the individual to settle any lawsuit, action, or claim
				covered by subparagraph (A).</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB182E4DCCC74C65A73870D9AD2937D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Each medical
				malpractice judgment against the individual by the courts or administrative
				agencies or bodies of such State.</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8FCAFA38FF224BA98D1584D86C426046"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Each disciplinary
				action taken or under consideration against the individual by an administrative
				agency or body of such State.</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H245A93503FDE41CF8CD626D55F9795F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Any change in the
				status of the license to practice medicine issued the individual by such State,
				including any voluntary or nondisciplinary surrendering of such license by the
				individual.</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7E8580E325F64894836DA1EAA2D1C23"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Any open
				investigation of the individual by an administrative agency or body of such
				State, or any outstanding allegation against the individual before such an
				administrative agency or body.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4CF07ECD625A4AFD9C6ED23AB9DAC67"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Disclosure of
				certain information following appointment</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H12C65A90E4B84EAA9DD48C4EE03479FB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Each individual
				appointed in the Administration in the position of physician after the date of
				the enactment of the Veterans Health Care Quality Improvement Act shall, as a
				condition of service under the appointment, disclose to the Secretary, not
				later than 30 days after the occurrence of such event, the following:</text>
									<subparagraph id="H65DE0BFE783F4F40B3A0A34FE47639CD" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A judgment against the individual for
				medical malpractice or negligence.</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C95FF57893145FCAFC11FC4D0552059" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A payment made by or on behalf of the
				individual to settle any lawsuit, action, or claim disclosed under paragraph
				(1) or (2) of subsection (b).</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5FEE5AC154147C580C36F55E35DAD" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any disposition of or material change
				in a matter disclosed under paragraph (1) or (2) of subsection (b).</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F237B8B69C9449B80EB1DF3EC756D88" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each individual appointed in the
				Administration in the position of physician as of the date of the enactment of
				the Veterans Health Care Quality Improvement Act shall do the following:</text>
									<subparagraph id="H0E786A7F051D491EAB0018FB52E0665C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Not later than the end of the 60-day
				period beginning on the date of the enactment of that Act and as a condition of
				service under the appointment after the end of that period, submit the request
				and authorization described in subsection (b)(2).</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A30E09437944DBA92A8D5E920852D8D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Agree, as a condition of service under
				the appointment, to disclose to the Secretary, not later than 30 days after the
				occurrence of such event, the following:</text>
										<clause id="H87CAE75A1D3A4A44A47FC2AFEBB01D8E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A judgment against the individual
				for medical malpractice or negligence.</text>
										</clause><clause id="H5E61EB612DB744EAA29386E02B50F7B5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A payment made by or on behalf of
				the individual to settle any lawsuit, action, or claim disclosed pursuant to
				subparagraph (A) or under this subparagraph.</text>
										</clause><clause id="HA9BB71F3DDEF4CEC8D55EA9F1B713075"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Any disposition of or material
				change in a matter disclosed pursuant to subparagraph (A) or under this
				subparagraph.</text>
										</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AA365AEFFE44DA4A5375B3E70636E06" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Each individual appointed in the
				Administration in the position of physician shall, as part of the biennial
				review of the performance of the physician under the appointment, submit the
				request and authorization described in subsection (b)(2). The requirement of
				this paragraph is in addition to the requirements of paragraph (1) or (2), as
				applicable.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6030A3D4813841F1861F2790C4433263"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Investigation of
				disclosed matters</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H60B15EF057064994B2EFAC88B200EFB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Regional Director of
				the Veterans Integrated Services Network (VISN) in which an individual is
				seeking appointment in the Administration in the position of physician shall
				perform a comprehensive investigation (in such manner as the standards required
				by this section shall specify) of each matter disclosed under subsection (b)
				with respect to the individual.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HC3532A2D60474F79927733FCFEA07097" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Regional Director of the Veterans
				Integrated Services Network in which an individual is appointed in the
				Administration in the position of physician shall perform a comprehensive
				investigation (in a manner so specified) of each matter disclosed under
				subsection (c) with respect to the individual.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HD2326F33325D493D90B4D7C77DBF5E6E" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The results of each investigation
				performed under this subsection shall be fully documented.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD448A67254D647B49207A2C927BC6DD8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Approval of
				appointments by Regional Directors of VISNs</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H74CE9F95FD8F460291E49C3FB5CB93D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An individual may not be
				appointed in the Administration in the position of physician without the
				approval of the Regional Director of the Veterans Integrated Services Network
				in which the individual will first serve under the appointment.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HC8152D7C389848E680369F3B9D9F0444" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In approving the appointment under
				this subsection of an individual for whom any matters have been disclosed under
				subsection (b), a Regional Director shall—</text>
									<subparagraph id="H3A1E733868C541BEBC0027EF007D2480"><enum>(A)</enum><text>certify in writing the completion of
				the performance of the investigation under subsection (d)(1) of each such
				matter, including the results of such investigation; and</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD166B8B0684472BB946DA38D70053AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide a written justification why
				any matters raised in the course of such investigation do not disqualify the
				individual from appointment.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0A1C0CA9070A4605A58144DA2846987"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Board
				certification</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC959266914404D7C009EAD1282243CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Except as provided in
				paragraph (2), an individual may not be appointed in the Administration in the
				position of physician unless the individual is board certified in the
				specialties in which the individual will practice under the appointment.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HBCED82787ABC4ECCB6C9C47D19B21353" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A Regional Director may waive the
				limitation in paragraph (1) with respect to any individual who has completed a
				residency program within the two-year period ending on the date of such waiver
				if the individual provides satisfactory evidence (as determined in accordance
				with the standards required by this section) of an intent to become board
				certified. The period of any waiver under this paragraph may not exceed one
				year.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA47736EFD7844160AF4E00B3AE51275F"><enum>(g)</enum><header>State license
				required for practice in in-State VA medical facilities</header><text>Each
				physician practicing at a medical facility of the Department in a State,
				whether under an appointment in the Administration or through the extension of
				privileges of practice, shall, as a condition of such practice, hold a license
				to practice medicine in the State within one year of appointment.</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="HD7E7134B8AE64BA3A592861B19643580"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Enrollment of
				physicians with practice privileges in Proactive Disclosure
				Service</header><text>Each medical facility of the Department at which
				physicians are extended the privileges of practice shall enroll each physician
				extended such privileges in the Proactive Disclosure Service of the National
				Practitioners Data
				Base.</text>
							</subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H0F198DC077B04B668F7B5EBD452C3F5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical
			 amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 74 of
			 such title is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 7402 the
			 following new item:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H91BDC92480BE4E3CA6BE891E48A300DA" style="USC">
						<toc>
							<toc-entry idref="H865978250347402995D919D8D3D4C987" level="section">7402A. Appointment and practice of physicians:
				standards.</toc-entry>
						</toc>
						<after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBAE45C9044DF4568A947AAD617EE53D6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date
			 and applicability</header>
				<paragraph id="HE5A3B060E8154AA2821C412CEF33812B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Effective
			 date</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the amendments made by
			 subsection (a) shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this
			 Act.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H7CD64389AA374340A3EBCA86C569D360"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability of
			 certain requirements to physicians practicing on effective
			 date</header><text>In the case of an individual appointed to the Veterans
			 Health Administration in the position of physician as of the date of the
			 enactment of this Act—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H86C478FDFDDF444EAECBA2BEF40080DF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the requirements
			 of subsections (f) and (g) of section 7402A, United States Code, as added by
			 subsection (a) of this section, shall take effect on the date that is one year
			 after the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70381C1B0CB941B28B922BE959EAD563"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the requirements
			 of subsection (h) of such section 7402A, as so added, shall take effect on the
			 date that is 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H6CA974688CB64877AE1DF3C44BD69C75"><enum>3.</enum><header>Enhancement of
			 quality assurance by the Veterans Health Administration</header>
			<subsection id="H6BACA3A9D20D4B5DAF49D92B34A77C45"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Enhancement of
			 quality assurance through quality assurance officers</header>
				<paragraph id="H8D0C0D62ED7A4FA4868D50FFDCE6AA40"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/73">chapter 73</external-xref> of title 38, United States
			 Code, is amended by inserting after section 7311 the following new
			 section:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1EF65EB07464495AFB4AA68A7EFE33" style="USC">
						<section id="H3E0CFCE0821444FBAD1EC3E074F52E3"><enum>7311A.</enum><header>Quality
				assurance officers</header>
							<subsection id="HA8423B695CC44A8BB9653E8FEE09144B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National quality
				assurance officer</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HCF1A5E6A531C41F6A590C66E8DD4126"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Under Secretary of
				Health shall designate an official of the Administration to act as the
				principal quality assurance officer for the quality-assurance program required
				by section 7311 of this title. The official so designated may be known as the
				<quote>National Quality Assurance Officer of the Veterans Health
				Administration</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>National
				Quality Assurance Officer</quote>).</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HEB186AE5412C41F0810073A1AC8FCB1B" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The National Quality Assurance
				Officer shall report directly to the Under Secretary for Health in the
				discharge of responsibilities and duties of the Officer under this
				section.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H72A030C55BF2498C0000D2EB0047AF0" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The National Quality Assurance
				Officer shall be the official within the Administration who is principally
				responsible for the quality-assurance program referred to in paragraph (1). In
				carrying out that responsibility, the Officer shall be responsible for—</text>
									<subparagraph id="HFCB87C0DBCD2452CAF9436ECE55277BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establishing and enforcing the
				requirements of that program; and</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72307F9F9DFA4B6F9EC85721F560713C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>carrying out such other
				responsibilities and duties relating to quality assurance in the Administration
				as the Under Secretary for Health shall specify.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5BF697BB417F489EA9066C220975BD97" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The requirements under paragraph (3)
				shall include requirements regarding the following:</text>
									<subparagraph id="H4B48EA4DCD714B9E865134A630E140A9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A confidential system for the
				submittal of reports by Administration personnel regarding quality assurance at
				Administration facilities.</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0325C70B04EE454CB7C12BF084045DE2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Mechanisms for the peer review of the
				actions of individuals appointed in the Administration in the position of
				physician.</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C29C9E666D44787B03F5829C236EF5F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Mechanisms for the accountability of
				the facility director and chief medical officer of each Administration medical
				facility for the actions of physicians in such facility.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H55DDC4DDA58745A48288005B62C4DA59"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Quality
				assurance officers for VISNs</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7F9CE98EE2A44656A3938C29124E71C2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Regional Director of
				each Veterans Integrated Services Network (VISN) shall appoint an official of
				the Network to act as the quality assurance officer of the Network.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HAC289BF43AE14AB4BF3FEED27205B57" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each official appointed as a quality
				assurance officer under this subsection shall be a board-certified
				physician.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HFEF48F416F944EE5AD1CDAA15D0408A" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The quality assurance officer for a
				Veterans Integrated Services Network shall report to the Regional Director of
				the Veterans Integrated Services Network, and to the National Quality Assurance
				Officer, regarding the discharge of the responsibilities and duties of the
				officer under this section.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H66AEA6453C914CB19644734C85F9F848" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The quality assurance officer for a
				Veterans Integrated Services Network shall—</text>
									<subparagraph id="H56510710BA764BE5B7A038B8C77D2EC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>direct the quality assurance office in
				the Network; and</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA21CF9353E504BF48200E92398994809"><enum>(B)</enum><text>coordinate, monitor, and oversee the
				quality assurance programs and activities of the Administration medical
				facilities in the Network in order to ensure the thorough and uniform discharge
				of quality assurance requirements under such programs and activities throughout
				such facilities.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H16FFE8F94C3E4AF0834333882827C5DC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Quality
				assurance officers for medical facilities</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA31C6DE18E44447DB51405D665A6A5AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The director of each
				Administration medical facility shall appoint a quality assurance officer for
				that facility.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HFE98475F2D6F453E90616FBF293B2CC3" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each official appointed as a quality
				assurance officer under this subsection shall be a board-certified
				physician.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HA06B89A59DDD4C09926C16C245977418" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The official appointed as a quality
				assurance officer for a facility under this subsection shall be a practicing
				physician at the facility. If the official appointed as quality assurance
				officer for a facility has other clinical or administrative duties, the
				director of the facility shall ensure that those duties are sufficiently
				limited in scope so as to ensure that those duties do not prevent the officer
				from effectively discharging the responsibilities and duties of quality
				assurance officer at the facility.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H583A84583D364A9EB07D736CA2EF021" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The quality assurance officer for a
				facility shall report directly to the director of the facility, and to the
				quality assurance officer of the Veterans Integrated Services Network in which
				the facility is located, regarding the discharge of the responsibilities and
				duties of the quality assurance officer under this section.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H2EAC282A9E654F4095BF80A69D92C3FB" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The quality assurance officer for a
				facility shall be responsible for designing, disseminating, and implementing
				quality assurance programs and activities for the facility that meet the
				requirements established by the National Quality Assurance Officer under
				subsection
				(a).</text>
								</paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H871721B4EF4A47FCBB36FEEE9D8EBF51"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical
			 amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 73 of
			 such title is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 7311 the
			 following new item:</text>
					<quoted-block id="HBB3C78FCEBF8492C8CFDD58663B5C9C5" style="USC">
						<toc>
							<toc-entry idref="H3E0CFCE0821444FBAD1EC3E074F52E3" level="section">7311A. Quality assurance
				officers.</toc-entry>
						</toc>
						<after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD0C552E60D9E4835A815F35FE0398404"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Board-certified
			 physician requirement for individuals appointed as Under Secretary for
			 Health</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/305">Section 305(a)(2)</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is
			 amended by inserting <quote>shall be a board-certified physician and</quote>
			 before <quote>shall be</quote>.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HE015EB62E91141D0ABA33417C5001C27"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports on
			 quality concerns under quality-assurance program</header><text>Section 7311(b)
			 of such title is amended by adding at the end the following new
			 paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H70D0C1418E5544468B75DCA3F3B741D" style="OLC">
					<paragraph id="H68264B1B4B664E47A2ABE093BD11375F" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>As part of the quality-assurance
				program, the Under Secretary for Health shall establish mechanisms through
				which employees of Administration facilities may submit reports, on a
				confidential basis, on matters relating to quality of care in Administration
				facilities to the quality assurance officers of such facilities under section
				7311A(c) of this title and to the quality assurance officers of the Veterans
				Integrated Services Networks (VISNs) in which such facilities are located under
				section 7311A(b) of this title. The mechanisms shall provide for the prompt and
				thorough review of any reports so submitted by the receiving
				officials.</text>
					</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HED9B9AF7A7C04DD1A1BD7C00A0FB8EE5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Review of
			 current health care quality safeguards</header>
				<paragraph id="H8B2156A75F464E6CBB825400B8A56650"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct a
			 comprehensive review of all current policies and protocols of the Department of
			 Veterans Affairs for maintaining health care quality and patient safety at
			 Department of Veterans Affairs medical facilities. The review shall include a
			 review and assessment of the National Surgical Quality Improvement Program
			 (NSQIP), including an assessment of—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H2206474F4BD84CA69C4D6D49A18005D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the efficacy of the
			 quality indicators under the program;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2E84F47AF66488E8B0008E6DBC1E6B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the efficacy of the
			 data collection methods under the program;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E867CADEBEE481A95C3CD606D6E3F3D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the efficacy of
			 the frequency with which regular data analyses are performed under the program;
			 and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3D3708F7141F430ABA56925963325364"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the extent to
			 which the resources allocated to the program are adequate to fulfill the stated
			 function of the program.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB4844AA9F28402F90A8D618726583E1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not
			 later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary
			 shall submit to Congress a report on the review conducted under paragraph (1),
			 including the findings of the Secretary as a result of the review and such
			 recommendations as the Secretary considers appropriate in light of the
			 review.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3DDE9965E2C94CFA99534C0400F0D4D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Incentives to
			 encourage high-quality physicians to serve in the Veterans Health
			 Administration</header>
			<subsection id="H13F6780987054C37BDF0207ECDB096C5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Incentives
			 required</header>
				<paragraph id="H4BFBFBF76EA24B3FA2EC7CC34BB5EFD4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text>Subchapter III of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/74">chapter 74</external-xref> of title 38, United States
			 Code, is amended by inserting after section 7431 the following new
			 section:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H54F7CEC512214288B852E6D3E6002C3B" style="USC">
						<section id="H322B92C0722D4E9184FB96FF9213071"><enum>7431A.</enum><header>Physicians:
				additional incentives for service in hard-to-fill positions </header>
							<subsection id="H5A13B2CBD812418A9EA76852A78BC88D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Loan repayment
				for physicians who serve in hard-to-fill positions</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H3564A2B5BDE34151B140146FC8002FE0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In order to recruit and
				retain physicians in the Administration in hard-to-fill positions (as
				designated by the Secretary for purposes of this subsection), the Secretary
				shall repay, for each individual who agrees to serve as a physician for a
				period of not less than three years in an Administration facility in such a
				position, any loan of such individual as follows:</text>
									<subparagraph id="H00A5CC92B57F4D3AAB12727E6D6174D" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Any loan of the individual described
				in paragraphs (1) through (4) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/16302">section 16302(a)</external-xref> of title 10.</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9CB02F56E1C140E6963F0869A85C4E00" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Any other loan of the individual
				designated by the Secretary for purposes of this subsection the proceeds of
				which were used by the individual to finance education leading to the medical
				degree of the individual.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0FBBEC827B44116BCE3C9D2F643005D" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each individual seeking repayment of
				loans under paragraph (1) shall enter into an agreement with the Secretary
				regarding the repayment of loans. Under the agreement, the individual shall
				agree—</text>
									<subparagraph id="H4A3E992D52B1450FA4034400CEF674B0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to perform satisfactory service in a
				physician position specified in the agreement in an Administration facility
				specified in the agreement for such period of years as the agreement shall
				specify; and</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCAAC208A9369495E8274C3FBF557BC97"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to possess and retain for the period
				of the agreement such professional qualifications as are necessary for the
				service specified under subparagraph (A).</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB94D0F55A77C4D19AEC796F84CDCAFB7" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Repayment of loans under this
				subsection shall be made on the basis of complete years of service under the
				agreement under this subsection. The amount to be repayed under an agreement
				under this subsection for a complete year of service specified in the agreement
				shall be such amount, not to exceed $30,000, for each complete year of service
				as the agreement shall specify.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4855291987824F37B9F7DD87ECD4E71B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Tuition
				reimbursement for physician students who agree To serve in hard-to-fill
				positions</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HDE4708C51106498B982E21A596B0305"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In order to recruit and
				retain physicians in the Administration in hard-to-fill positions (as
				designated by the Secretary for purposes of this subsection), the Secretary
				shall reimburse individuals who are enrolled in a course of education leading
				toward board certification as a physician for the tuition charged for pursuit
				of such course of education if such individuals agree to serve as a physician
				in an Administration facility in such a position.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H8D85D48B7FDC401DAFD2DFA6900E98B" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each individual seeking tuition
				reimbursement under paragraph (1) shall enter into an agreement with the
				Secretary regarding such tuition reimbursement. Under the agreement, the
				individuals shall agree—</text>
									<subparagraph id="HC27F9F2771A64909B1BE7100E8BC672D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to satisfactorily complete the course
				of education of the individual described in paragraph (1); and</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94C38E0BFC6D4C298D60C2B8D7885C7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>upon completion of the course of
				education, to become board-certified as a physician; and</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE60BD526D5E74E8088A42E1671C7C947"><enum>(C)</enum><text>upon completion of the matters
				referred to in subparagraphs (A) and (B)—</text>
										<clause id="H40A55CCDE252462080A4FAE055E0C1C2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to perform satisfactory service in
				a physician position specified in the agreement in an Administration facility
				specified in the agreement for such period of years as the agreement shall
				specify; and</text>
										</clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA51F51FF289A4F318C064CBAB6CA9EE9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to possess and retain for the
				period of the agreement such professional qualifications as are necessary for
				the service specified under clause (i).</text>
										</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD4E0D15265A244B3A7CFCF152DC02900" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The amount of reimbursement payable
				to an individual under paragraph (1) for a year may not exceed $30,000.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4706943B5D3042B29800CC802200DEAA" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Any individual receiving tuition
				reimbursement under paragraph (1) who does not satisfy the requirements of the
				agreement under paragraph (2) shall be subject to such repayment requirements
				as the Secretary shall specify in the agreement.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HACE3AC8461014713B900304CD513F0EC" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An individual receiving tuition
				reimbursement under paragraph (1) for pursuit of a course of education shall
				also be paid a stipend in the amount of $5,000 for each academic year of
				pursuit of such course of education after entry into an agreement under
				paragraph (2).</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H43F7A67CCC334938B1D8A7DB36F6DCC9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Participation in
				FEHBP of physicians who serve part-time in hard-to-fill positions</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HDCC339F9B896457E8543EC9E21CCFD09"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In order to recruit and
				retain physicians in the Administration in hard-to-fill positions (as
				designated by the Secretary for purposes of this subsection), an individual not
				otherwise eligible for health insurance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/89">chapter 89</external-xref> of title 5 who agrees
				to serve as a physician in an Administration facility in such a position for
				not less than five days per month (of which two days must occur in each 14-day
				period) shall be eligible for enrollment in the health benefit plans under
				<external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/89">chapter 89</external-xref> of title 5 on a self only or self and family basis (as
				applicable).</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEE23CED42EB747269291DDD99EAB45B" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary shall administer this
				subsection in consultation with the Director of the Office of Personnel
				Management.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H944861E2B370404D9438F36CE297A7EE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Additional
				programs</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the Secretary should
				undertake active and on-going efforts to establish additional incentive
				programs to encourage individuals to serve in the position of physician in the
				Administration, or otherwise practice in the Administration, in hard-to-fill
				positions, including, in particular, incentive programs to encourage more
				experienced physicians to serve or practice in such positions.</text>
							</subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H25C72D2116F64764A512CEFCE874E1FE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>The
				incentives required under this section are in addition to any other special
				pays or benefits to which the individuals covered by this section are eligible
				or entitled under
				law.</text>
							</subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HD89D4B3803004DF0958438A851ABF7A4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical
			 amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 74 of
			 such title is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 731 the
			 following new item:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H8C1D91E5D37C4608B728113B753787EC" style="USC">
						<toc>
							<toc-entry idref="H322B92C0722D4E9184FB96FF9213071" level="section">7431A. Physicians: additional incentives for service in
				hard-to-fill
				positions.</toc-entry>
						</toc>
						<after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7CC63063E82942BDA093AF5F293094E8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Affiliation of
			 Department of Veterans Affairs medical facilities with medical
			 schools</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall, to the extent
			 practicable, require each medical facility of the Department of Veterans
			 Affairs to seek to establish an affiliation with a medical school within
			 reasonable proximity of such medical facility.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H07BE02BC9398427196C18E773FDA8B85"><enum>5.</enum><header>Reports to
			 Congress</header>
			<subsection id="H8F031CCAA071403CBB2E34B6DADDCF96"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than December 15, 2009, and each
			 year thereafter through 2012, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to
			 the congressional veterans affairs committees a report on the implementation of
			 this Act and the amendments made by this Act during the preceding fiscal year.
			 Each report shall include, for the fiscal year covered by such report, the
			 following:</text>
				<paragraph id="H2A23111561F04F47BF148FC3638B2FE8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A
			 comprehensive description of the implementation of this Act and the amendments
			 made by this Act.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HE444A2561BBB45C184F1208EE2CB583C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Such
			 recommendations as the Secretary considers appropriate for legislative or
			 administrative action to improve the authorities and requirements in this Act
			 and the amendments made by this Act or to otherwise improve the quality of
			 health care and the quality of the physicians in the Veterans Health
			 Administration.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H93004174CE07461D8636694BC647F3C1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Congressional
			 veterans affairs committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term
			 <term>congressional veterans affairs committees</term> means—</text>
				<paragraph id="H0659D411E7BF4A9480CCAFD86E68DAA4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committees on
			 Veterans' Affairs and Appropriations of the Senate; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H25FFCA5DD53D46E484009D8915E6D260"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committees on
			 Veterans' Affairs and Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


