<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0C6FC3E267C64382B38B89A800C5700" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 1273 IH: To amend title 38, United States Code, to direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to restore plot allowance eligibility for veterans of any war and to restore the headstone or marker allowance for eligible persons.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 1273</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070301">March 1, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001231">Ms. Berkley</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to restore plot allowance eligibility for veterans of any war and to restore the headstone or marker allowance for eligible persons.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H8B9F67BA0267465EB5B2B071515C7C69" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H54BE63014EBE4D8CA333B481DFF400B7" section-type="section-one" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header>Restoration of veteran plot allowance eligibility and headstone or marker allowance</header> 
<subsection id="H82BCC6D8D4CE4807B8D6D443BBFA2F19"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Restoration of plot allowance eligibility for veterans of any war</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/2303">Section 2303(b)</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0067B33B8DA14D5E9E84873C00DB1F2F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>subsection (a) of this section</quote> and all that follows through <quote>and who</quote> and inserting the following: <quote>subsection (a), in the case of a veteran who is eligible for a burial allowance under such subsection or under section 2302 of this title, who was discharged from the active military, naval, or air service for a disability incurred or aggravated in the line of duty, or who is a veteran of any war and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC60980068C0A401A00BF6B4BB496FC78"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEDB1695EF2AD4B1D859225E524D5F39D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>is eligible for a burial allowance under section 2302 of this title or under subsection (a) of this section, or was discharged from the active military, naval, or air service for a disability incurred or aggravated in line of duty, and such veteran</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H69D48DA5F27147D3BD2D86D7797AE93"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>clause (1) of this subsection</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraph (1)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H36BBF92B23594854A37C559E09E5479D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Restoration of headstone or marker allowance</header> 
<paragraph id="HEF448D6E9A62485CA86EB55053D4704E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Allowance</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/2306">Section 2306</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H3CDF5BE886224733B355939CFC055CB2" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H9B4217AD935C4AC10057BC337E1327FE"><enum>(h)</enum><text>In lieu of furnishing a headstone or marker under subsection (a)(2) or (b), the Secretary, in the Secretary’s discretion, having due regard for the circumstances in each case, may reimburse the person entitled to request such headstone or marker for the cost of acquiring a non-Government headstone or marker for placement in any cemetery other than a national cemetery in connection with the burial or memorialization of the deceased individual.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8BF1D34A31424130AE15C94FB94C4859"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Subsection (g) of such section is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H347D487A67994E8000DE4E7F899E5E99" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H70F4BD8B23DC41888BB3063EE5C31347" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Reimbursement may not be provided under subsection (h) for the cost of acquiring a non-Government headstone or marker in connection with the burial or memorialization of a person described in section 2411(b) of this title.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H28BF744A9E924B0AA0B3442DFECAA518" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply with respect to deaths occurring on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


