<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA47B45FB3DCC4F418E61F073498A8856" public-private="public" stage-count="1"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">112th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 910</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Clean Air Act to prohibit the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency from promulgating any regulation concerning, taking action relating to, or taking into consideration the emission of a greenhouse gas to address climate change, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="HB46B7D6F76F24D85900BFC770C6B9AB3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE17282529C244C3E97895394DCF09B17" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Energy Tax Prevention Act of 2011</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> 
<section id="H8B1546FC58B74135B546C041A7EC53FE"><enum>2.</enum><header>No Regulation of emissions of greenhouse gases</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title III of the Clean Air Act (42 U.S.C. 7601 et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HEA0ED140AF9841A49E1B80409345020E"> 
<section id="H70395F0791D24A6D820C953B12B45B07"><enum>330.</enum><header>No Regulation of emissions of greenhouse gases</header> 
<subsection id="HAE178DEDF2AC4AD49831C4738C1580AC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>greenhouse gas</term> means any of the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H8457D4317BF84D418AA93D18F0E3C3C8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Water vapor.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA9A63AE0FAF34A268F811C31CFDA9E78"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Carbon dioxide.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7590B736D63C4EFFBE6940735752FC93"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Methane.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H993C91CD67634EF3AD854247B6CFA19C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Nitrous oxide.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA1FB17B347BD45018ABCD56B429B4A50"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Sulfur hexafluoride.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEC9C1C8FC42F462E8F90F8349968CDAA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Hydrofluorocarbons.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4D56576B39984089A0FA0B2E3FAD7E72"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Perfluorocarbons.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H513CF5A23C544D1A94DEF8B928CE0B45"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Any other substance subject to, or proposed to be subject to, regulation, action, or consideration under this Act to address climate change.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2283B28E42C54B9ABEBA22E6E3DB7065"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation on agency action</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H1A5E9F01C4954D2A9E9C52E18591698F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Limitation</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H95B7DFD98B914E52A2371AE2F24FAF04"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator may not, under this Act, promulgate any regulation concerning, take action relating to, or take into consideration the emission of a greenhouse gas to address climate change.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H80CA1F354A5147E683BCFA42A9B72C26"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Air pollutant definition</header><text>The definition of the term <term>air pollutant</term> in section 302(g) does not include a greenhouse gas. Notwithstanding the previous sentence, such definition may include a greenhouse gas for purposes of addressing concerns other than climate change.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1C4769E26C2D4670ABDEF7733FA36DBA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>Paragraph (1) does not prohibit the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H45517D9B2A8942BAABC9EC78BA75A5FD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding paragraph (4)(B), implementation and enforcement of the rule entitled <quote>Light-Duty Vehicle Greenhouse Gas Emission Standards and Corporate Average Fuel Economy Standards</quote> (as published at 75 Fed. Reg. 25324 (May 7, 2010) and without further revision) and finalization, implementation, enforcement, and revision of the proposed rule entitled <quote>Greenhouse Gas Emissions Standards and Fuel Efficiency Standards for Medium- and Heavy-Duty Engines and Vehicles</quote> published at 75 Fed. Reg. 74152 (November 30, 2010).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HE4DA9DD3D54540A1B3C932D2866216FA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Implementation and enforcement of section 211(o).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD84508F8180644D6A1895160F2C7264B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Statutorily authorized Federal research, development, demonstration programs and voluntary programs addressing climate change.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7C9C9DB2246F469A9BBDE00FADDCE409"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Implementation and enforcement of title VI to the extent such implementation or enforcement only involves one or more class I substances or class II substances (as such terms are defined in section 601).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB7DC4FE7BFD545BAA282EC152FD45637"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Implementation and enforcement of section 821 (42 U.S.C. 7651k note) of Public Law 101–549 (commonly referred to as the <quote>Clean Air Act Amendments of 1990</quote>).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H50176DCDFA5D4F22845EB5AD1718CE05"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Inapplicability of provisions</header><text>Nothing listed in paragraph (2) shall cause a greenhouse gas to be subject to part C of title I (relating to prevention of significant deterioration of air quality) or considered an air pollutant for purposes of title V (relating to permits).</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCB9147E440DF4FF29BF14042595F5CF7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Certain prior agency actions</header><text>The following rules and actions (including any supplement or revision to such rules and actions) are repealed and shall have no legal effect:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB270E6EA49BC442290DF12D07D47A9C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text><quote>Mandatory Reporting of Greenhouse Gases</quote>, published at 74 Fed. Reg. 56260 (October 30, 2009).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF1059DBD875742ED9FB9BF634BE8D237"><enum>(B)</enum><text><quote>Endangerment and Cause or Contribute Findings for Greenhouse Gases Under Section 202(a) of the Clean Air Act</quote>, published at 74 Fed. Reg. 66496 (December 15, 2009).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3590AB8FB9B84EC983A2C0A108772BF1"><enum>(C)</enum><text><quote>Reconsideration of Interpretation of Regulations That Determine Pollutants Covered by Clean Air Act Permitting Programs</quote>, published at 75 Fed. Reg. 17004 (April 2, 2010) and the memorandum from Stephen L. Johnson, Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Administrator, to EPA Regional Administrators, concerning <quote>EPA’s Interpretation of Regulations that Determine Pollutants Covered by Federal Prevention of Significant Deterioration (PSD) Permit Program</quote> (December 18, 2008).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9EBD19B0038C4296A059F7397691EEC3"><enum>(D)</enum><text><quote>Prevention of Significant Deterioration and Title V Greenhouse Gas Tailoring Rule</quote>, published at 75 Fed. Reg. 31514 (June 3, 2010).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBC12662D823043CAAE7AF62BAEE87377"><enum>(E)</enum><text><quote>Action To Ensure Authority To Issue Permits Under the Prevention of Significant Deterioration Program to Sources of Greenhouse Gas Emissions: Finding of Substantial Inadequacy and SIP Call</quote>, published at 75 Fed. Reg. 77698 (December 13, 2010).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0172EF232BC94B07A0D4A647DEBFE445"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><quote>Action To Ensure Authority To Issue Permits Under the Prevention of Significant Deterioration Program to Sources of Greenhouse Gas Emissions: Finding of Failure To Submit State Implementation Plan Revisions Required for Greenhouse Gases</quote>, published at 75 Fed. Reg. 81874 (December 29, 2010).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1EB17E624A2A4849804A0E3C46C99E17"><enum>(G)</enum><text><quote>Action to Ensure Authority To Issue Permits Under the Prevention of Significant Deterioration Program to Sources of Greenhouse Gas Emissions: Federal Implementation Plan</quote>, published at 75 Fed. Reg. 82246 (December 30, 2010).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD8B396722F4E49A7ADBF471CD4867A4D"><enum>(H)</enum><text><quote>Action to Ensure Authority to Implement Title V Permitting Programs Under the Greenhouse Gas Tailoring Rule</quote>, published at 75 Fed. Reg. 82254 (December 30, 2010).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H94036B45B0A548F0B07240C235E20AED"><enum>(I)</enum><text><quote>Determinations Concerning Need for Error Correction, Partial Approval and Partial Disapproval, and Federal Implementation Plan Regarding Texas Prevention of Significant Deterioration Program</quote>, published at 75 Fed. Reg. 82430 (December 30, 2010).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H32118510E7984D5BBA6D83AF021BEFA7"><enum>(J)</enum><text><quote>Limitation of Approval of Prevention of Significant Deterioration Provisions Concerning Greenhouse Gas Emitting-Sources in State Implementation Plans</quote>, published at 75 Fed. Reg. 82536 (December 30, 2010).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3A035E898A7440C4883999F9E2E58B0A"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><quote>Determinations Concerning Need for Error Correction, Partial Approval and Partial Disapproval, and Federal Implementation Plan Regarding Texas Prevention of Significant Deterioration Program; Proposed Rule</quote>, published at 75 Fed. Reg. 82365 (December 30, 2010).</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEA45475FB7C24B73881A1F5A97379314"><enum>(L)</enum><text>Except for actions listed in paragraph (2), any other Federal action under this Act occurring before the date of enactment of this section that applies a stationary source permitting requirement or an emissions standard for a greenhouse gas to address climate change.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3F7FEC612EFB452C9ACAA697F9E422A5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State action</header> 
<subparagraph id="H5B5E5F5454D741E7A8794E71ACF2BC74"><enum>(A)</enum><header>No limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section does not limit or otherwise affect the authority of a State to adopt, amend, enforce, or repeal State laws and regulations pertaining to the emission of a greenhouse gas.</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1694D8D6A19B47DD82A0846D449A7C8A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header> 
<clause id="H0ED3AD39F9B1487EA0E0FBF7DAF1E940"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Rule</header><text>Notwithstanding subparagraph (A), any provision described in clause (ii)—</text> 
<subclause id="H2E4329A372284A28A95D22EAC556632B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is not federally enforceable;</text> </subclause> 
<subclause id="HFE88B1CF2EB0421C932B3362540294ED"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is not deemed to be a part of Federal law; and</text> </subclause> 
<subclause id="H5F297143BC1C4382B5D67DE948951B4A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>is deemed to be stricken from the plan described in clause (ii)(I) or the program or permit described in clause (ii)(II), as applicable.</text> </subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HE580D0ECB8FC40109D511770999A3ECB"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Provision defined</header><text>For purposes of clause (i), the term <term>provision</term> means any provision that—</text> 
<subclause id="H4AC759CAE7CF4CE2BE5E330BE8D3AB9D"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is contained in a State implementation plan under section 110 and authorizes or requires a limitation on, or imposes a permit requirement for, the emission of a greenhouse gas to address climate change; or</text> </subclause> 
<subclause id="HC8F72E477D17453E9D18FAAEE833CA61"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is part of an operating permit program under title V, or a permit issued pursuant to title V, and authorizes or requires a limitation on the emission of a greenhouse gas to address climate change.</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H98B2A5317B1144AB8ECF9BCA70B94654"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Action by Administrator</header><text>The Administrator may not approve or make federally enforceable any provision described in subparagraph (B)(ii).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> 
<section id="H3F42E8C8EE5348FABFA8D44EE9514316"><enum>3.</enum><header>Preserving one national standard for automobiles</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 209(b) of the Clean Air Act (42 U.S.C. 7543) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H86AEA6201A09485996FC7BC2298797AB" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H477132106DED4ED98818781B7B45EFF7" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to standards for emissions of greenhouse gases (as defined in section 330) for model year 2017 or any subsequent model year new motor vehicles and new motor vehicle engines—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1A2BD53383C345CA9B5E17EB8557943C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Administrator may not waive application of subsection (a); and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8D37ABA738404C0A801B1EC4A596CE6D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>no waiver granted prior to the date of enactment of this paragraph may be construed to waive the application of subsection (a).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> 
<section id="H34515487739E4B1DB45E22798670F651"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of the Congress that—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF0E82945559947D980958506485324ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>there is established scientific concern over warming of the climate system based upon evidence from observations of increases in global average air and ocean temperatures, widespread melting of snow and ice, and rising global average sea level;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC7303056311A4929A906A75A087CF289"><enum>(2)</enum><text>addressing climate change is an international issue, involving complex scientific and economic considerations;</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD00FEFDB84084F84B7C1C66615E14EAD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the United States has a role to play in resolving global climate change matters on an international basis; and</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1AB77E818C874C0E8AEAB7DD57D94DF9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Congress should fulfill that role by developing policies that do not adversely affect the American economy, energy supplies, and employment.</text> </paragraph></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20110407" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives April 7, 2011.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Karen L. Haas,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation> 
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement> 
</bill> 
