<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H4F72B6B8DFE24B19B9B036AF8CB9F4B" public-private="public" stage-count="1"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>111th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 1084</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To require the Federal Communications Commission to prescribe a standard to preclude commercials from being broadcast at louder volumes than the program material they accompany.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H44E2D3B39C4543279C34E726FA80514C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H97DDC6946C404A0CADB9E9FAFD7B1807" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Commercial Advertisement Loudness Mitigation Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>CALM Act</quote>.</text></section>
<section id="H471A32737EA54513B1BE007AF097B372"><enum>2.</enum><header>Rulemaking on loud commercials required</header>
<subsection id="H79C1A877189B4A1DA75F5D4107817756"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Regulation Required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Federal Communications Commission shall prescribe pursuant to the Communications Act of 1934 (47 U.S.C. 151 et seq.) a regulation that is limited to incorporating by reference and making mandatory (subject to any waivers the Commission may grant pursuant to subsection (b)(2)) the <quote>Recommended Practice: Techniques for Establishing and Maintaining Audio Loudness for Digital Television</quote> (A/85), and any successor thereto, approved by the Advanced Television Systems Committee, only insofar as such recommended practice concerns the transmission of commercial advertisements by a television broadcast station, cable operator, or other multichannel video programming distributor.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H061DA9006FAB4B99BAB820DED773396E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation</header>
<paragraph id="H9ED46ABBDC14485795BE1E88075FA5F4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Effective Date</header><text>The Federal Communications Commission shall prescribe that the regulation adopted pursuant to subsection (a) shall become effective 1 year after the date of its adoption.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB8D068CE03B044ABB1373E4E3D529084"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>For any television broadcast station, cable operator, or other multichannel video programming distributor that demonstrates that obtaining the equipment to comply with the regulation adopted pursuant to subsection (a) would result in financial hardship, the Federal Communications Commission may grant a waiver of the effective date set forth in paragraph (1) for 1 year and may renew such waiver for 1 additional year. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H8A11ECA12CE844CDBD43850041EEBF0B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section—</text>
<paragraph id="HABE0EB192ADC42A39B9A265BA18414A1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>television broadcast station</term> has the meaning given such term in section 325 of the Communications Act of 1934 (47 U.S.C. 325); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9813763852B6433F807F67ADF79667D5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the terms <term>cable operator</term> and <term>multichannel video programming distributor</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 602 of Communications Act of 1934 (47 U.S.C. 522).</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20091215" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives December 15, 2009.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 
