<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HBED00522E9604A539238081673020010" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 2452 EH: Sewage Overflow Community Right-to-Know Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 2452</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Water Pollution Control Act to ensure that publicly owned treatment works monitor for and report sewer overflows, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HFC4EDCF798314F76B9003E637C26007B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3F7A3A7F123D40458CAFA6BE200095F9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Sewage Overflow Community Right-to-Know Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H29F6BC7DB6284E0F97F5B8551AA65C0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 502 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1362">33 U.S.C. 1362</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H9F1DED1CAC1341B5B6282630C0E19F67" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H9153D5C79D5145E28F39D54796ECC54F"><enum>(25)</enum><header>Sanitary sewer overflow</header><text>The term <quote>sanitary sewer overflow</quote> means an overflow, spill, release, or diversion of wastewater from a sanitary sewer system. Such term does not include municipal combined sewer overflows or other discharges from a municipal combined storm and sanitary sewer system and does not include wastewater backups into buildings caused by a blockage or other malfunction of a building lateral that is privately owned. Such term includes overflows or releases of wastewater that reach waters of the United States, overflows or releases of wastewater in the United States that do not reach waters of the United States, and wastewater backups into buildings that are caused by blockages or flow conditions in a sanitary sewer other than a building lateral.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCFA3362FD6F94E6A8B3C18E7C64D1D15" commented="no"><enum>(26)</enum><header>Treatment works</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>treatment works</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 212.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H39DEC84C877F4695A7C5B9E992DD905C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Monitoring, reporting, and public notification of sewer overflows</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 402 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1342">33 U.S.C. 1342</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H3148663B9C484559883BC6F667F15FEA" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H2973F745E8954704B83B61BC5F491EEE"><enum>(r)</enum><header>Sewer Overflow Monitoring, Reporting, and Notifications</header> 
<paragraph id="HF86E4AB95B404F089E8F9F2F8B3F676C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>General requirements</header><text>After the last day of the 180-day period beginning on the date on which regulations are issued under paragraph (4), a permit issued, renewed, or modified under this section by the Administrator or the State, as the case may be, for a publicly owned treatment works shall require, at a minimum, beginning on the date of the issuance, modification, or renewal, that the owner or operator of the treatment works—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAAD21A3507864A9F8864256CA192CB64"><enum>(A)</enum><text>institute and utilize a feasible methodology, technology, or management program for monitoring sewer overflows to alert the owner or operator to the occurrence of a sewer overflow in a timely manner;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAD49F34C923444629400B442E714B929"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a sewer overflow that has the potential to affect human health, notify the public of the overflow as soon as practicable but not later than 24 hours after the time the owner or operator knows of the overflow;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA7B8870B224647E8A2EDA2438185A6B1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a sewer overflow that may imminently and substantially endanger human health, notify public health authorities and other affected entities, such as public water systems, of the overflow immediately after the owner or operator knows of the overflow;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5E848EB5C8D84148AE7E00D518A7F367"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">report each sewer overflow on its discharge monitoring report to the Administrator or the State, as the case may be, by describing—</text> 
<clause id="HE9685A049FBD42688013EB25D5A63336"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the magnitude, duration, and suspected cause of the overflow;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H54EAB6960D384429B8888E0993204DA3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the steps taken or planned to reduce, eliminate, or prevent recurrence of the overflow; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC67A2177126D4B02A26639DB49003ED8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the steps taken or planned to mitigate the impact of the overflow; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HADE681E86384416F907E073083F74290"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">annually report to the Administrator or the State, as the case may be, the total number of sewer overflows in a calendar year, including—</text> 
<clause id="H99D708F91DDD4C2F866384949537D98F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the details of how much wastewater was released per incident;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD629B16F73AC4C0E85C883D033BB9994"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the duration of each sewer overflow;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H641ED7DC19FE4F4C9E76B945C7ABBA00"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the location of the overflow and any potentially affected receiving waters;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD2FA13FF95064A459600AB9FBB82D6C2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the responses taken to clean up the overflow; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBAF6B571A58B40839200AAA3C28942C6"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the actions taken to mitigate impacts and avoid further sewer overflows at the site.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7BB57FA455EE42DB92D47B538E194E8C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header> 
<subparagraph id="H3F3C3025D0A74DE1BF00B79D9E02C44E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Notification requirements</header><text>The notification requirements of paragraphs (1)(B) and (1)(C) shall not apply a sewer overflow that is a wastewater backup into a single-family residence.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE40831BB9C384A69B4A62DB5D706103E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><text>The reporting requirements of paragraphs (1)(D) and (1)(E) shall not apply to a sewer overflow that is a release of wastewater that occurs in the course of maintenance of the treatment works, is managed consistently with the treatment works’ best management practices, and is intended to prevent sewer overflows.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3CD0A15FF99F4AEB8257AA66EF278726"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report to EPA</header><text>Each State shall provide to the Administrator annually a summary of sewer overflows that occurred in the State.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC70F807D6DE24D30A7B2AB45B2B4AD61"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rulemaking by EPA</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Administrator, after providing notice and an opportunity for public comment, shall issue regulations to implement this subsection, including regulations to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H07E3590FA0C34B2F8313917B7D1300D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish a set of criteria to guide the owner or operator of a publicly owned treatment works in—</text> 
<clause id="HCBF8272F642E4E83AFDA614D30788100"><enum>(i)</enum><text>assessing whether a sewer overflow has the potential to affect human health or may imminently and substantially endanger human health; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H00263A3C8BC7409286C4196DFA4BC777"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>developing communication measures that are sufficient to give notice under paragraphs (1)(B) and (1)(C); and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAA2BC60B59E546CD8278953CE8941D6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>define the terms <quote>feasible</quote> and <quote>timely</quote> as such terms apply to paragraph (1)(A), including site specific conditions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD821C7C2557D44550000B47000BB9DF1"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Approval of State notification programs</header> 
<subparagraph id="H3BA7388B2A3348AFB4581B67A3BAC67B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Requests for approval</header> 
<clause id="HFAA8E5EE5D8040EDBCE6C460CFB800C8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>After the date of issuance of regulations under paragraph (4), a State may submit to the Administrator evidence that the State has in place a legally enforceable notification program that is substantially equivalent to the requirements of paragraphs (1)(B) and (1)(C).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFBDCC9988E1846949E91E69008EA875B"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Program review and authorization</header><text>If the evidence submitted by a State under clause (i) shows the notification program of the State to be substantially equivalent to the requirements of paragraphs (1)(B) and (1)(C), the Administrator shall authorize the State to carry out such program instead of the requirements of paragraphs (1)(B) and (1)(C).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H24CC130D884949F291E5676FA3489BEA"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Factors for determining substantial equivalency</header><text>In carrying out a review of a State notification program under clause (ii), the Administrator shall take into account the scope of sewer overflows for which notification is required, the length of time during which notification must be made, the scope of persons who must be notified of sewer overflows, the scope of enforcement activities ensuring that notifications of sewer overflows are made, and such other factors as the Administrator considers appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H37A78F49425842DEA15BAF683303FAC3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Review period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a State submits evidence with respect to a notification program under subparagraph (A)(i) on or before the last day of the 30-day period beginning on the date of issuance of regulations under paragraph (4), the requirements of paragraphs (1)(B) and (1)(C) shall not begin to apply to a publicly owned treatment works located in the State until the date on which the Administrator completes a review of the notification program under subparagraph (A)(ii).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC573AA5F6CD446F08E81A7369E4822EA"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Withdrawal of authorization</header><text>If the Administrator, after conducting a public hearing, determines that a State is not administering and enforcing a State notification program authorized under subparagraph (A)(ii) in accordance with the requirements of this paragraph, the Administrator shall so notify the State and, if appropriate corrective action is not taken within a reasonable time, not to exceed 90 days, the Administrator shall withdraw authorization of such program and enforce the requirements of paragraphs (1)(B) and (1)(C) with respect to the State.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H74B431E5F3494CD8919DB3A7FE73F1D3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Special rules concerning application of notification requirements</header><text>After the last day of the 30-day period beginning on the date of issuance of regulations under paragraph (4), the requirements of paragraphs (1)(B) and (1)(C) shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H02520976F27344B091C541A78E6CAA3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>apply to the owner or operator of a publicly owned treatment works and be subject to enforcement under section 309, and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA2B94231AABD47EAA27B19981E04E2EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supersede any notification requirements contained in a permit issued under this section for the treatment works to the extent that the notification requirements are less stringent than the notification requirements of paragraphs (1)(B) and (1)(C), </text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">until such date as a permit is issued, renewed, or modified under this section for the treatment works in accordance with paragraph (1).</continuation-text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H42CE71BD4BC84B87A6F4C4F735D77C4C"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the following definitions apply:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF158E436D65B4D6A8837FBB328A545AB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Sewer overflow</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>sewer overflow</quote> means a sanitary sewer overflow or a municipal combined sewer overflow.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDD76BEFDC5BC40788D3D30EBBE65B5F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Single-family residence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>single-family residence</quote> means an individual dwelling unit, including an apartment, condominium, house, or dormitory. Such term does not include the common areas of a multi-dwelling structure. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HFF1A0D552DE3490AACB79023638C4733"><enum>4.</enum><header>Eligibility for assistance</header> 
<subsection id="H4CA75802B8EA4BA9B605268BDBA7CFF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose of State Revolving Fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 601(a) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1381">33 U.S.C. 1381(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H8553D06D532E4A42A2EE834E29D96D98"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> the first place it appears; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H31C8F268245944CA998532CEE660C53D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after <quote>section 320</quote> the following: <quote>, and (4) for the implementation of requirements to monitor for sewer overflows under section 402</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0CB1BB015A2C4A0488461B717165DB16" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Water Pollution Control Revolving Loan Funds</header><text>Section 603(c) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1383">33 U.S.C. 1383(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE3F7F3EC53574678889BD800274D09E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> the first place it appears; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H47F0820554F94FD700C5F2A41D3FA34F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after <quote>section 320 of this Act</quote> the following: <quote>, and (4) for the implementation of requirements to monitor for sewer overflows under section 402</quote>.</text></paragraph> </subsection></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20080623" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives June 23, 2008.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 


