<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" dms-id="H42D62B0734D7423C85CF6E9A14017E52" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>112th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 2</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To repeal the job-killing health care law and health care-related provisions in the Health Care and Education Reconciliation Act of 2010.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H82443E2E0000438D95BC48CBCAD266C3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H22BE97ED31724BB88759329BB690BDEB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Repealing the Job-Killing Health Care Law Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> 
<section id="H2FBAA5A48E564FB88746E5D3CE52CB25"><enum>2.</enum><header>Repeal of the job-killing health care law and health care-related provisions in the Health Care and Education Reconciliation Act of 2010</header> 
<subsection id="H37DAFA719C1A4866B80055DE03DA79E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Job-Killing health care law</header><text>Effective as of the enactment of Public Law 111–148, such Act is repealed, and the provisions of law amended or repealed by such Act are restored or revived as if such Act had not been enacted.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H52B259EDD0214B12B44374B4B62CC36A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Health care-Related provisions in the Health Care and Education Reconciliation Act of 2010</header><text>Effective as of the enactment of the Health Care and Education Reconciliation Act of 2010 (Public Law 111–152), title I and subtitle B of title II of such Act are repealed, and the provisions of law amended or repealed by such title or subtitle, respectively, are restored or revived as if such title and subtitle had not been enacted.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H826AF063C0204F149AE5D7ACE577D9E1" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Budgetary effects of this Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The budgetary effects of this Act, for the purpose of complying with the Statutory Pay-As-You-Go Act of 2010, shall be determined by reference to the latest statement titled <quote>Budgetary Effects of PAYGO Legislation</quote> for this Act, submitted for printing in the Congressional Record by the Chairman of the Committee on the Budget of the House of Representatives, as long as such statement has been submitted prior to the vote on passage of this Act.</text></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20110107" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives January 19, 2011.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation> 
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement> 
</bill> 
