<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HEF3B12C0F54546F78C61139D352700A0" public-private="public"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code> 
<calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 404</calendar> 
<congress display="yes">111th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 476</legis-num> 
<associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 111–678]</associated-doc> 
<current-chamber display="yes">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20090113">January 13, 2009</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Al Green of Texas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Waters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000288">Mr. Ellison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001049">Mr. Clay</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000636">Mr. Hinojosa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001148">Mr. Meek of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000557">Mr. Larson of Connecticut</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001165">Mr. Sires</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000248">Mr. Serrano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000099">Mr. Pastor of Arizona</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000290">Ms. Edwards of Maryland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000933">Mr. Moran of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001060">Mr. Carnahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000544">Mr. Gonzalez</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00" added-display-style="italic" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20101209">December 9, 2010</action-date> 
<action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="S001174">Ms. Sutton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000180">Ms. Kilpatrick of Michigan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001037">Mr. Capuano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000324">Mr. Hastings of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001034">Mr. Honda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001166">Mr. McNerney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000602">Mr. Davis of Alabama</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000287">Mr. Lewis of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000116">Mr. Filner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001177">Mr. Sablan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000535">Mr. Gutierrez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000339">Mr. Frank of Massachusetts</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000327">Mr. Dicks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000913">Mr. Abercrombie</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000738">Ms. Woolsey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000410">Mr. Gene Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001079">Mr. Cao</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000410">Mr. Berman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001227">Mr. Brady of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000336">Mr. Kucinich</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000577">Mr. Ryan of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000455">Ms. Fudge</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000053">Mr. Rangel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000794">Ms. Watson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000107">Mr. Ortiz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000126">Ms. Eddie Bernice Johnson of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000149">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000515">Mr. Rush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000486">Ms. Roybal-Allard</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001171">Mr. Maffei</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001042">Ms. Hirono</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001234">Mr. Baca</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson of Indiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000207">Mr. Watt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000593">Mr. Perlmutter</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000283">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor></action-desc> 
</action> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-desc display="yes"><pagebreak/></action-desc> 
</action> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20101209">December 9, 2010</action-date> 
<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc> 
<action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction> 
<action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on January 13, 2009</action-instruction> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To authorize funds to prevent housing discrimination through the use of nationwide testing, to increase funds for the Fair Housing Initiatives Program, and for other purposes.<pagebreak/></official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HBA00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H79C211FC22414B8489E19693D2EC48F2"> 
<section id="HB89146DACBC54EB39D5BA53592BA11D5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans, Women, Families with Children, and Persons With Disabilities Housing Fairness Act of 2010</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H0714EF9CAB7A4247B3E46A87C75E34A4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Testing for discrimination</header> 
<subsection id="H253FD44894054A2A9E3939A6B60AB401"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall conduct a nationwide program of testing to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H55C308CF6A5346C381E75DA7253D11CF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>detect and document differences in the treatment of persons seeking to rent or purchase housing or obtain or refinance a home mortgage loan, and measure patterns of adverse treatment because of the race, color, religion, sex, familial status, disability status, or national origin of a renter, home buyer, or borrower; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H58AA8442EFA442DCB2392A3BEDB19B83"><enum>(2)</enum><text>measure the prevalence of such discriminatory practices across the housing and mortgage lending markets as a whole.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H46D1937E32B047A9A2EF366191C68F0F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall enter into agreements with qualified fair housing enforcement organizations, as such organizations are defined under subsection (h) of section 561 of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1987 (42 U.S.C. 3616a(h)), for the purpose of conducting the testing required under subsection (a).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4F09037E54E44DB094234102843485AC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Program requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H15AC7F76125142509304046FD5C933A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to the Congress an evaluation by the Secretary of the effectiveness of the program under this section; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9B1232675ECC42E794DFB5B5566B975F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>issue regulations that require each application for the program under this section to contain—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD35CE043DB9C40899709CCCE4DC7F8BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of the assisted activities proposed to be undertaken by the applicant;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H89CD14D3B19140BEB30D75150728D297"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of the experience of the applicant in formulating or carrying out programs to carry out the activities described in subsection (a); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFB6EDF11DF73427DAE0ACA2072C0A790"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of proposed procedures to be used by the applicant for evaluating the results of the activities proposed to be carried out under the program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H724F3BE7A81C44AB8036111BA6EB0304"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall report to Congress—</text> 
<paragraph id="H616BFD8BE77448BAA19EB596CD5AFD2A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>on a biennial basis, the aggregate outcomes of testing required under subsection (a) along with any recommendations or proposals for legislative or administrative action to address any issues raised by such testing; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H18317E0F66114E30AF4C49C42C1DF7EF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on an annual basis, a detailed summary of the messages received by the Office of Fair Housing and Equal Opportunity of the Department through its 24-hour toll-free telephone hotline, through electronic mail, and through its website.</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">The Secretary may submit the reports required under paragraph (1) of this subsection as part of the reports prepared in accordance with paragraphs (2) and (6) of section 808(e) of the Fair Housing Act (42 U.S.C. 3608(e)) and section 561(j) of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1987 (42 U.S.C. 3616a(j)).</continuation-text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8E587247679A43F1A0FD2B08D4501E44"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of Results</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The results of any testing required under subsection (a) may be used as the basis for the Secretary, or any Federal agency authorized to bring such an enforcement action, or any State or local government or agency, public or private nonprofit organization or institution, or other public or private entity that the Secretary has entered into a contract or cooperative agreement with under section 561 of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1987 (42 U.S.C. 3616a) to commence, undertake, or pursue any investigation or enforcement action to remedy any discriminatory housing practice (as such term is defined in section 802 of the Fair Housing Act (42 U.S.C. 3602)) uncovered as a result of such testing.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE1775F80CD9744749DA7CF111959CD1F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>As used in this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H2CFA502540574F1EA972BB705271F175"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Disability status</header><text>The term <term>disability status</term> has the same meaning given the term <term>handicap</term> in section 802 of the Civil Rights Act of 1968 (42 U.S.C. 3602).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7CD3824450D8468FA3DDD72792618D19"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Familial status</header><text>The term <term>familial status</term> has the same meaning given that term in section 802 of the Civil Rights Act of 1968 (42 U.S.C. 3602).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3540482521114247AFA54EC243160799" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Relationship to other laws</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to amend, alter, or affect any provision of criminal law or the Truth in Lending Act (15 U.S.C. 1601 et seq.).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBF88E8B240A04089910DD9B8209BF2AA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than the expiration of the 180-day period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall issue regulations that establish minimum standards for the training of testers of organizations conducting testing required under subsection (a). Such regulations shall serve as the basis of an evaluation of such testers, which shall be developed by the Secretary, and such regulations shall be issued after notice and an opportunity for public comment in accordance with the procedure under section 553 of title 5, United States Code, applicable to substantive rules (notwithstanding subsections (a)(2), (b)(B), and (d)(3) of such section). </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD46E969BDE894F6EBF0F203D8F851DC7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out the provisions of this section $15,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2011 through 2015.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H40EABC42E86446DDAD6FC64926183E0D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Increase in funding for the Fair Housing Initiatives Program</header> 
<subsection id="H8A694A39BABB40718CF3B7D10C393EEA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 561 of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1987 (42 U.S.C. 3616a) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCF408024D370429B9505CDFF75EEF70E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0036738CEF2F4B98BD9E4D2BFF005A0F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>qualified</quote> before <quote>private nonprofit fair housing enforcement organizations,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H64F42E8010AC45D184A83309ECAF280F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>qualified</quote> before <quote>private nonprofit fair housing enforcement organizations,</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H989705375F90489A8DB31AB6273E876C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsection (g) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HE73A3EDCC5EA49528F78A573F3FD3710" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HEBFF715C23BD486796D501DE7B338257"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header> 
<paragraph id="H4B3803A097734E70982BF2D5C1733A9B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out the provisions of this section $42,500,000 for each of fiscal years 2011 through 2015, of which—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB175A903C7E94FFC8C05F8AC18C37CCA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not less than 75 percent of such amounts shall be for private enforcement initiatives authorized under subsection (b);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC621FB44F58F4EF797D7837A9022A40D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not more than 10 percent of such amounts shall be for education and outreach programs under subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3AB9784434B347F5BADEC75377C3FFE9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any remaining amounts shall be used for program activities authorized under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H94A385BF896548F89631ECD344A79939"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>Any amount appropriated under this section shall remain available until expended to carry out the provisions of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC39D29EF29F34DBA95F28C128F91F6D1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (h), in the matter following subparagraph (C), by inserting <quote>and meets the criteria described in subparagraphs (A) and (C)</quote> after <quote>subparagraph (B)</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4BF529B8A059406A850AD2EB97E3F7CC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5E4BFC43556F483C89A7C1EB2FB6E9E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> 
<clause id="H4051109485C7403A9580CB3EA9B128F2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H826783A5EA564855A6CB61522C3A46BF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD9187EB81FF34612A5A1854838E0637F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding after subparagraph (D) the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H7420D5E1C97B4D7C960E439FC3C46040" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="HAEC444EF4E4047179F94B05C222B61C4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>websites and other media outlets.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAAFF91E2B5814DC99177EBC7667736FD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>or other public or private entities</quote> and inserting <quote>or other public or private nonprofit entities</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAA084326D9A24EA9A50B7A3D3EA41BA6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>or other public or private entities</quote> and inserting <quote>or other public or private nonprofit entities</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7F18BF3ED39C487DBE538881A6E9A8AA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the expiration of the 180-day period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall issue regulations that establish minimum standards for the training of testers of organizations funded with any amounts made available to carry out this section for any of fiscal years 2011 through 2015. Such regulations shall serve as the basis of an evaluation of such testers, which shall be developed by the Secretary, and shall be issued after notice and an opportunity for public comment in accordance with the procedure under section 553 of title 5, United States Code, applicable to substantive rules (notwithstanding subsections (a)(2), (b)(B), and (d)(3) of such section).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HD07E0AAC12E84D7281C35F7CBF604099"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development should—</text> 
<paragraph id="H14FAC525C95D4EB19E7B9F83B0822AB2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>fully comply with the requirements of section 561(d) of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1987 (42 U.S.C. 3616a(d)) to establish, design, and maintain a national education and outreach program to provide a centralized, coordinated effort for the development and dissemination of the fair housing rights of individuals who seek to rent, purchase, sell, or facilitate the sale of a home;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF67D444B60C449F4A6098C8B5F906C28"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expend for such education and outreach programs all amounts appropriated for such programs;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFAF0EB849F9B4A62A2F13864CA1876AC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>promulgate regulations regarding the fair housing obligations of each recipient of Federal housing and community development funds to affirmatively further fair housing, as that term is defined under title VIII of the Civil Rights Act of 1968 (42 U.S.C. 3601 et seq.); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H61F1D50E8C434D71A600DF17793433F7"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fully comply with the requirements of section 810(a) of the Fair Housing Act (42 U.S.C. 3610(a)).</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H2A01918D645844F5800FA136B8F2EE48"><enum>5.</enum><header>Grants to private entities to study housing discrimination</header> 
<subsection id="H26FC5AA885AF429995AA2F384FFB972A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant Program</header><text>The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall carry out a competitive matching grant program to assist public and private nonprofit organizations in—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE205A8BD51D94BD89E1DC1C5BA602C80"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conducting comprehensive studies that examine—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0011399362D743A7BFA59F17F59C29F1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the causes of housing discrimination and segregation;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4B53BC144A99465B8415C2819ABD559A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the effects of housing discrimination and segregation on education, poverty, and economic development; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0B7FD47456C043499A520BEDBBD0A0AE"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the incidences, causes, and effects of housing discrimination and segregation on veterans and military personnel; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H788ED229CF724B59B58DA54ED5CA8F8E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>implementing pilot projects that test solutions that will help prevent or alleviate housing discrimination and segregation.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9AA868013BC6425B802A158837E8C0E8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, a public or private nonprofit organization shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H50635689058C47FB811B5C55E9C20CF1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submit an application to the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, containing such information as the Secretary shall require;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H148F3D1010ED4599B738303E1094B38F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>agree to provide matching non-Federal funds for 50 percent of the total amount of the grant, which matching funds may include items donated on an in-kind contribution basis; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H24D541D463A14170AEEB9358571E4D58"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meet the requirements of a qualified fair housing enforcement organization, as such term is defined in section 561(h) of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1987 (42 U.S.C. 3616a(h)), or subcontract with a qualified fair housing enforcement organization as a primary subcontractor.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H016B5D1D386C4575808C7E17EF47F1D2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall submit a report to the Congress on a biennial basis that provides a detailed summary of the results of the comprehensive studies and pilot projects carried out under subsection (a), together with any recommendations or proposals for legislative or administrative actions to address any issues raised by such studies. The Secretary may submit the reports required under this subsection as part of the reports prepared in accordance with paragraphs (2) and (6) of section 808(e) of the Fair Housing Act (42 U.S.C. 10 3608(e)) and section 561(j) of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1987 (42 U.S.C. 3616a(j)).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB6D64953BAF244698F9BCF9EF55A3318"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out the provisions of this section $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2011 through 2015.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HA3579C5AFBB4450A99F47650F17E49E5"><enum>6.</enum><header>Limitation on use of funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">None of the funds made available under this Act, or the amendments made by this Act, may be used for any political activities, political advocacy, or lobbying (as such terms are defined by Circular A-122 of the Office of Management and Budget, entitled <quote>Cost Principles for Non-Profit Organizations</quote>), or for expenses for travel to engage in political activities or preparation of or provision of advice on tax returns.</text></section> 
</legis-body> 
<endorsement display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20101209">December 9, 2010</action-date> 
<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement> 
</bill> 
