<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9EE0D021E59E456491A343807FF7A9C5" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>109 HR 3200 IH: Servicemembers' Group Life Insurance Enhancement Act of 2005</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2005-07-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>109th CONGRESS</congress>
<session>1st Session</session>
<legis-num>H. R. 3200</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20050711">July 11, 2005</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001144">Mr. Miller of Florida</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001231">Ms. Berkley</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans’ Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to enhance the Servicemembers’ Group Life Insurance program, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H789C06E9643340B497AFE36F8B3DDC72" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H1E11F312C9A04825B38D6803A4C6ABA6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Servicemembers' Group Life Insurance Enhancement Act of 2005</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> 
<section id="H61DFD65C7C98487EBB06445EB389BD8F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Repealer</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Effective as of August 31, 2005, section 1012 of division A of the Emergency Supplemental Appropriations Act for Defense, the Global War on Terror, and Tsunami Relief, 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/13">Public Law 109–13</external-xref>; 119 Stat. 244), including the amendments made by that section, are repealed, and sections 1967, 1969, 1970, and 1977 of title 38, United States Code, shall be applied as if that section had not been enacted.</text></section> 
<section id="H1C7E87792DD242688F58F86FA5036FA" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Increase from $250,000 to $400,000 in automatic maximum coverage under Servicemembers' Group Life Insurance and Veterans' Group Life Insurance</header> 
<subsection id="H45F11FF8AC7B4F08B55928C8DB6D2792"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Maximum Under SGLI</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1967">Section 1967</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4A1015A103024E4499E6DD85596701B8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(3)(A)(i), by striking <quote>$250,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$400,000</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA9C140BD5E2F4456938CD42D4832418D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (d), by striking <quote>of $250,000</quote> and inserting <quote>in effect under paragraph (3)(A)(i) of that subsection</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA44D5C7EFEF7481C93219E2DA2546379"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Maximum Under VGLI</header><text>Section 1977(a) of such title is amended by striking <quote>$250,000</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>$400,000</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB290B3A5A0FE4CFF006EFEE5F0E9EF71"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on September 1, 2005, and shall apply with respect to deaths occurring on or after that date.</text></subsection> </section> 
<section id="H3FBD9B12772643428F351EBC7F6C77DF" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Notification to member’s spouse or next of kin of certain elections under Servicemember's Group Life Insurance program</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">Effective September 1, 2005, <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1967">section 1967</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9A681ABFA4294DBA8973C6A5F616261"> 
<subsection id="HB7DCFFC584574D6F8E46855CC4E63600" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(f)</enum> 
<paragraph id="HCCE6FCC2276F47F59C3DD22DA6993B" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum> 
<subparagraph id="H9DEAB930AECB440BBC03337B67405200" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whenever a member who is eligible for insurance under this section executes a life insurance option specified in subparagraph (B), the Secretary concerned shall notify the member’s spouse or, if the member is unmarried, the member’s next of kin, in writing, of the execution of that option.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9D64734E81C04402B1B6004644F0CB5B" indent="up2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A life insurance option referred to in subparagraph (A) is any of the following:</text> 
<clause id="HA05BA5C7DCE141EDB0BCB0579FA745A6"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An election under subsection (a)(2)(A) not to be insured under this subchapter.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H030FAA21AFAF4CDCB8A3FA905FC7BC66"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An election under subsection (a)(3)(B) for insurance of the member in an amount that is less than the maximum amount provided under subsection (a)(3)(A)(i).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8FD1B1CC9F854BBF8E9D187670A0C17D" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>An application under subsection (c) for insurance coverage under this subchapter or for a change in the amount of such insurance coverage.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1C878149CDAF4F8EA9973F2E3515E0E4" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a married member, a designation under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1970">section 1970(a)</external-xref> of this title of any person other than the spouse or a child of the member as the beneficiary of the member for any amount of insurance under this subchapter.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H64011A367750416BBDEEE78EB4CDECA8" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Whenever an unmarried member who is eligible for insurance under this section marries, the Secretary concerned shall notify the member’s spouse in writing as to whether the member is insured under this subchapter. In the case of a member who is so insured, the Secretary shall include with such notification—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEBFE986905D64D13A03E7CDCC05BAD24"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the member has made an election described in paragraph (1)(B)(ii), notice that the amount of such insurance is less than the maximum amount provided under subsection (a)(3)(A)(i); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6703EAD228284140A8F6000088529ED6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if the member has designated a beneficiary other than the spouse or a child of the member for any amount of such insurance, notice that such a designation has been made.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0AF1E776D65D4DEB869EEFAB3D6832FE" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum> 
<subparagraph id="H7BA1E8C28BE84555A1DF513EC1AD6D" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notification of a spouse under paragraph (1) or (2), or of any other person under paragraph (1), for purposes of this subsection shall consist of a good faith effort to provide information to the spouse or other person at the last address of the spouse or other person in the records of the Secretary concerned.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE378F9195B2646A4BAE7525C5D0068CF" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Failure to provide such notification, or to provide such notification in a timely manner, does not affect the validity of any life insurance option referred to in paragraph (1)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H68144FA3558B4C819FCDD544EEBD1ED"><enum>5.</enum><header>Increments of insurance that may be elected</header> 
<subsection id="H1A65BFF0FE624B58BEC503ADFD467553"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Increase in increment amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (a)(3)(B) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1967">section 1967</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking “member or spouse” in the last sentence and inserting “member, be evenly divisible by $50,000 and, in the case of a member’s spouse,”.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA024C6EC36B841E5AAC8C3B758003D91"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall take effect on September 1, 2005.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H5399F3AA55884F1FA721FD8BEC9CC451"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authority to elect new traumatic injury protection</header> 
<subsection id="H6506D21A1A5C4518AD22C8B05FAF257B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Opt-out authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1980A">Section 1980A</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end of subsection (b) the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HB7128169014D441A8029E853BF9E5D2D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H5D074C750EE34F50B0E0D45D00C03019" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum> 
<subparagraph id="H3C88EBBF94144FFB93521CD6B7002945" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A member may elect in writing not to be insured under this section.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBC756233E15446B18E904D1DD004F77D" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>If a member eligible for insurance under this section is not so insured by reason of an election made under subparagraph (A), the member may thereafter elect to be insured under this section upon written application by the member, proof of good health, and compliance with such other terms and conditions as may be prescribed by the Secretary. Insurance under this section upon such an election is effective upon the date of the receipt by the Secretary of such application and shall apply only with respect to injuries incurred after that date. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H25503A3DBCC84EB3A57EAEDED65FC4BE" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Secretary shall prescribe by regulation conditions as to how and when elections under subparagraph (B) shall be made. Such regulations may include limiting the time for such elections to an annual open season, for a duration each year prescribed by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H28734343B9254BF988FF00FFE142CD88"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by subsection (a) shall take effect immediately after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1980A">section 1980A</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, takes effect pursuant to section 1032(d)(1) of division A of the Emergency Supplemental Appropriations Act for Defense, the Global War on Terror, and Tsunami Relief, 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/13">Public Law 109–13</external-xref>; 119 Stat. 260).</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 

