<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H244EB5337C3C466EBE77A74F00CCF6A5" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 3232 IH: Travel Promotion Act of 2007</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-07-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 3232</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20070731">July 31, 2007</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000210">Mr. Delahunt</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B000575">Mr. Blunt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000030">Mr. Farr</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000589">Mr. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000287">Mr. Emanuel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000213">Mr. Barton of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000725">Mr. George Miller of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000583">Mr. Smith of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000480">Ms. Slaughter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000822">Mr. Stearns</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000030">Ms. Loretta Sanchez of California</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000447">Mr. Feeney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Judiciary</committee-name> and <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To establish a non-profit corporation to communicate United States entry policies and otherwise promote tourist, business, and scholarly travel to the United States.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H1A9B7CD917974416B3E3A38A6A18B01" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H1729D9A711934EDE99FFCC7725EEF8F2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header> 
<subsection id="HF00914DF8CBE4104AECF4389D0DFDF15"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Travel Promotion Act of 2007</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7C5FF47D437D4F5796D26C4D5BBD4FAF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text> 
<toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"> 
<toc-entry idref="H1729D9A711934EDE99FFCC7725EEF8F2" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HF8F57F9E485C47DF00A7B120DCEEAA45" level="section">Sec. 2. Findings.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H956B6080B1CA47E1BF02416425E0B68F" level="section">Sec. 3. The Corporation for Travel Promotion.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HE19BC7CDA6AB4007B1FAC86C5237CEA8" level="section">Sec. 4. Accountability measures.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H0A6FD77355D349EE808CBCE855FAF80" level="section">Sec. 5. Matching public and private funding.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HBC2AD5F85BDC4B1FAC2421974D4705D6" level="section">Sec. 6. Travel Promotion Fund fees.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HFFF960FC0C8E45EC9E24B74B47DB67" level="section">Sec. 7. Investment of Funds.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H187DE89151B944EE86139B87F3E056E3" level="section">Sec. 8. Amendments to the International Travel Act of 1961.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H932A7AEA50E04F2000359D14C7C30001" level="section">Sec. 9. Definitions.</toc-entry> </toc></subsection></section> 
<section id="HF8F57F9E485C47DF00A7B120DCEEAA45"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds as follows:</text> 
<paragraph id="H3016C14A2BDF4A7983AD55B0DB91B6D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Securing the borders of the United States and facilitating international travel to the United States are not mutually exclusive.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3C67322931EF44F3B866FF9658BCB98F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>As part of the effort to protect the people of the United States from attacks by al-Qaeda and other foreign groups opposed to our policies in the predominantly Muslim regions of the world, Congress and the Administration tightened the entry process to the United States after the attacks of September 11, 2001.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H31DF9D4BE7CC4932934FB022FA5615ED"><enum>(3)</enum><text>As confirmed by a large-scale random poll in four Muslim nations in 2007 by the Program on International Policy Attitudes, an improved image of the United States abroad damages the ability of al-Qaeda and similar groups to recruit and to operate.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB2134273FCFD4391A61F12C692AA41FA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Foreign nationals who have visited the United States tend to give more favorable ratings to the United States than foreign nationals who have not visited the United States, with scientific polls by such firms as the Pew Research Center and Zogby International consistently finding a roughly 10 percentage point increase for travelers, and even their friends and family members rate the United States significantly more favorably than do other nonvisitors.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0137B4F2E42748BCADBEE7BA895E2BF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Inviting and facilitating travel to the United States by tourists, business people, students, and scholars will not only help improve our image abroad, but will produce significant domestic economic benefits.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC0BF4578ABBA4B9D00984500C469FEFB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The tightening of the entry process to the United States after September 11, 2001, is partly responsible for the number of international travelers to the United States in the six years from 2001 to 2006, as recorded by the Department of Commerce, being 56,000,000, or 17 percent, lower than the expected number of international travelers during that period, based on the trend from the previous six years.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA3B22BB26E674333BB8665B7F0FB690"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Department of Commerce estimates for spending by international travelers indicate that these 56,000,000 expected travelers would have spent $98,000,000,000 (valued in 2007 dollars) in the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC1A839DF7B5A4C16B3698D29EABC00DE"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Universities in the United States have frequently reported since 2001 that potential foreign enrollees have chosen to study in other countries because of a perception that there would have been delays in visa approval and an unpleasant entry process.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9058A7B5143D4539AD5DC468051FF42F"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Scientists and scholars in the United States have frequently reported since 2001 that international conferences that might have been held in the United States are held elsewhere, because of a perception that participation will be reduced by delays in visa approval and an unpleasant entry process.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H28B41076AC11441082300397BE7C3BB4"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Businesses in the United States have frequently reported since 2001 that delays and denials for visa applications for short-term visits by current and prospective employees, consultants, and investors have significantly hampered their international competitiveness.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5FAB24814973459EBC2C85A47338E3DE"><enum>(11)</enum><text>It is in the national interest of the United States that there be a coordinated effort to identify perceptions regarding the United States entry policy that tend to limit the number of international travelers to the United States, to communicate facts about the entry policy to potential travelers that will encourage them to travel to the United States, and to promote generally travel to the United States by tourists, business people, students, and scholars.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H956B6080B1CA47E1BF02416425E0B68F"><enum>3.</enum><header>The Corporation for Travel Promotion</header> 
<subsection id="HE5743EE140DB46B99478DA9569D16999"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Corporation for Travel Promotion is established as a nonprofit corporation. The Corporation shall not be an agency or establishment of the United States Government. The Corporation shall be subject to the provisions of the District of Columbia Nonprofit Corporation Act (sec. 29–301.01 et seq., D.C. Official Code), to the extent that such provisions are consistent with this section, and shall have the powers conferred upon a nonprofit corporation by that Act to carry out its purposes and activities.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD53B4D2DDAE643C2A4CA00C8AC70D073"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Board of Directors</header> 
<paragraph id="H66FD34252A864CC1914F7862FFCEA700"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Corporation shall have a board of directors of 14 members, appointed by the Secretary of Commerce after consultation with the Secretaries of Homeland Security, State, and Education, each of whom is a United States citizen, and of whom—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0A5586B6009543A8924EFC56A46CD230"><enum>(A)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the hotel accommodations sector;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2B276FCCE7DE4B419BAC18692289CF64"><enum>(B)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the restaurant sector;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBB557301FF3E4DA7B957009700FD13A3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the national-level retail sector;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD88639E076CE446B8012E8F3DCE879BC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the local-level retail sector, or in associations representing that sector;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4DCA799502844E03B71D8E078EEE68C3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the advertising sector;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3CF45C5F7590436A8680AF6162FB8399"><enum>(F)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the attractions sector;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7C08C112C5134C4583CE723ED5EE1761"><enum>(G)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the recreation sector;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7C625829145743A386FC50E7CD195C73"><enum>(H)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the research, development, or manufacturing sector;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0A4FAB9F41B74BF28700602B52A2C16D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the financial services sector;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1EC5EE6C33574CC7965450C75E2D25C"><enum>(J)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the passenger air sector;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0BB5FD4307084A10BDE3C8F200407C67"><enum>(K)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the car rental sector;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6CF3049FC8804000AF18E98CB300E486"><enum>(L)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience as an official at the state and municipal level, or in associations of such officials;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5EDB9A81CAA3453F9FFA6200D6741BEC"><enum>(M)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the higher education sector; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H19D4784FA282446DA7A53CCB066162FA"><enum>(N)</enum><text>one shall have appropriate expertise and experience in the non-profit scientific research sector and in coordinating international scholarly conferences in the United States.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H16BFF9062BA74C46944147F2862C36F7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Incorporation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The members of the initial board of directors shall serve as incorporators and shall take whatever actions are necessary to establish the Corporation under the District of Columbia Nonprofit Corporation Act (sec. 29–301.01 et seq.).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H10308AA59A264AA6955F99C12C7CE73F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Term of office</header><text>The term of office of each member of the board appointed by the Secretary shall be 3 years, except that, of the members first appointed—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H40326208768C43BA97156DDCA3F94D90"><enum>(A)</enum><text>3 shall be appointed for terms of 1 year;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H47429CF79C68497889D123E850889C92"><enum>(B)</enum><text>4 shall be appointed for terms of 2 years; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H14CD359A48BB4487AD53BD07AF63AE3D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>4 shall be appointed for terms of 3 years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H092826D9BF7C42B485E6B2AB4F791C00"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>Any vacancy in the board shall not affect its power, but shall be filled in the manner required by this section. Any member whose term has expired may serve until the member’s successor has taken office, or until the end of the calendar year in which the member’s term has expired, whichever is earlier. Any member appointed to fill a vacancy occurring prior to the expiration of the term for which that member’s predecessor was appointed shall be appointed for the remainder of the predecessor’s term. No member of the board shall be eligible to serve more than 2 consecutive full terms.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE340A29056494B978321C130D3517E3"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Election of chairman and vice chairman</header><text>Members of the board shall annually elect one of their members to be Chairman and elect 1 or more of their members as a Vice Chairman or Vice Chairmen.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0B4DEDDF8B6D4388B1CCF7D9E7008B24"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Status as federal employees</header><text>Notwithstanding any provision of law to the contrary, no member of the board may be considered to be a Federal employee of the United States by virtue of his or her service as a member of the board.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA7A9DE7FB5174332BA5FE922B94363B7"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Compensation; expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No member of the board shall receive any compensation from the Federal government by virtue of his or her service as a member of the board. Each member of the board shall be paid actual travel expenses and per diem in lieu of subsistence expenses when away from his or her usual place of residence, in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/5703">section 5703</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1005E6628D954D6000C2B49BB9C3C377"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Officers and Employees</header> 
<paragraph id="H4A9093A39DB54C9981533B8263E805B2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Corporation shall have a President, and such other officers as may be named and appointed by the board for terms and at rates of compensation fixed by the board. No individual other than a citizen of the United States may be an officer of the Corporation. The corporation may hire and fix the compensation of such employees as may be necessary to carry out its purposes. No officer or employee of the Corporation may receive any salary or other compensation (except for compensation for services on boards of directors of other organizations that do not receive funds from the Corporation, on committees of such boards, and in similar activities for such organizations) from any sources other than the Corporation for services rendered during the period of his or her employment by the Corporation. Service by any officer on boards of directors of other organizations, on committees of such boards, and in similar activities for such organizations shall be subject to annual advance approval by the board and subject to the provisions of the Corporation’s Statement of Ethical Conduct. All officers and employees shall serve at the pleasure of the board.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0F488B4E82834259AF7716EB51D47095"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Nonpolitical nature of appointment</header><text>No political test or qualification shall be used in selecting, appointing, promoting, or taking other personnel actions with respect to officers, agents, or employees of the Corporation.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBDA94FA4C9E6464EBA3DF64EDDFE340"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Nonprofit and Nonpolitical Nature of Corporation</header> 
<paragraph id="HA942F7F0627C4BB690CEC74D78FC41F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Stock</header><text>The Corporation shall have no power to issue any shares of stock, or to declare or pay any dividends.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAC92EC99658A4C118660AB7F3364CFDB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Profit</header><text>No part of the income or assets of the Corporation shall inure to the benefit of any director, officer, employee, or any other individual except as salary or reasonable compensation for services.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H43A3A3FAA2824A58B851763EF60449FF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Politics</header><text>The Corporation may not contribute to or otherwise support any political party or candidate for elective public office.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6B03073AA5B643669E7525DFA656B36"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Duties and Powers</header> 
<paragraph id="H8DB64E764C0B4AB8AB46777F1EB440B5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Corporation shall develop and execute a plan—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAB5F82A83C62444584DFC6E9556CF46"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide useful information to foreign tourists, business people, students, scholars, scientists and others interested in traveling to the United States, including the distribution of material provided by the Federal Government concerning entry requirements, required documentation, fees, and processes, to prospective travelers, travel agents, tour operators, meeting planners, foreign governments, travel media and other international stakeholders;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H24443B9C8ECB463FA6337C8F287026FA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to identify and address perceptions in other countries regarding United States entry policies that tend to limit attempts to travel to the United States; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBECD7A673F8D49C691E700C8808EC505"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to maximize the economic and diplomatic benefits of travel to the United States by promoting the United States of America to world travelers through the use of, but not limited to, all forms of advertising, outreach to trade shows, and other appropriate promotional activities.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9F8C9BE8B8974164BFE16283FBD513A7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Specific powers</header><text>In order to carry out the purposes of this section, the Corporation may—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1A5B2268B3D444C2995C471937A25C18"><enum>(A)</enum><text>obtain grants from and make contracts with individuals and private companies, State, and Federal agencies, organizations, and institutions;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7EF2313814E243DFB42700F4CE470000"><enum>(B)</enum><text>hire or accept the voluntary services of consultants, experts, advisory boards, and panels to aid the Corporation in carrying out its purposes; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7F105A5BC9494B38A9284685B2D79F48"><enum>(C)</enum><text>take such other actions as may be necessary to accomplish the purposes set forth in this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H43E385D80E3946ED889CAB870317DA"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Open Meetings</header><text>Meetings of the board of directors of the Corporation, including any committee of the board, shall be open to the public. The board may, by majority vote, close any such meeting only for the time necessary to preserve the confidentiality of commercial or financial information that is privileged or confidential, to discuss personnel matters, or to discuss legal matters affecting the Corporation, including pending or potential litigation.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3CB0AA7FB96A476DBB4FA7EF00B4BD9F"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Major campaigns</header><text>The board may not authorize the Corporation to obligate or expend more than $25,000,000 on any advertising campaign, promotion, or related effort unless—</text> 
<paragraph id="H98CAB8CBE01244B4966B701F48BA2E29"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the obligation or expenditure is approved by an affirmative vote of at least <fraction>2/3</fraction> of the members of the board present at the meeting;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA0F561EA84AE4EC2A58415A31C5006C1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>at least 8 members of the board are present at the meeting at which it is approved; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBC317E94B2454112958368899DADD8BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>each member of the board has been given at least 3 days advance notice of the meeting at which the vote is to be taken and the matters to be voted upon at that meeting.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H56A9A577CA4F4BFE823D62F4A080822D"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Fiscal accountability</header> 
<paragraph id="H5E6D81AC299648DC8CD08119C19FFCBA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Fiscal year</header><text>The Corporation shall establish as its fiscal year the 12-month period beginning on October 1.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H55B0F8E6A2364969BD43EEEBF486AA9F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Budget</header><text>The Corporation shall adopt a budget for each fiscal year.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFCDA663E53414D9591BD89DB9058EA4B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Annual audits</header><text>The Corporation shall engage an independent accounting firm to conduct an annual financial audit of the Corporation’s operations and shall publish the results of the audit. The Comptroller General shall have full and complete access to the books and records of the Corporation.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HE19BC7CDA6AB4007B1FAC86C5237CEA8"><enum>4.</enum><header>Accountability measures</header> 
<subsection id="HC35F0F61AE22405B97587E8D219C5296"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Objectives</header><text>The Board shall establish annual objectives for the Corporation for each fiscal year subject to approval by the Secretary. The Corporation shall establish a marketing plan for each fiscal year not less than 60 days before the beginning of that year and provide a copy of the plan, and any revisions thereof, to the Secretary.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H343DF17E8ED4438CAFF6F76CA916258"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Budget</header><text>The board shall transmit a copy of the Corporation’s budget for the forthcoming fiscal year to the Secretary no later than August 16 immediately preceding that fiscal year, together with an explanation of any expenditure provided for by the budget in excess of $5,000,000 for the fiscal year. The Corporation shall make a copy of the budget and the explanation available to the public and shall provide public access to the budget and explanation on the Corporation’s website.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4EB131B6F60B42DDBB50041269831735"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Annual Report to Congress</header><text>The Corporation shall submit an annual report for the preceding fiscal year to the Secretary of Commerce for transmittal to the Congress on or before the 15th day of May of each year. The report shall include—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC9C1F2F133D6414195A09D599FD49419"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a comprehensive and detailed report of the Corporation’s operations, activities, financial condition, and accomplishments under this Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBA68D9AD7A7042EBAD7EDA75B781E2F7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a comprehensive and detailed inventory of amounts obligated or expended by the Corporation during the preceding fiscal year;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H619ACCA65AB34C6A842500F650562583"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a detailed description of each in-kind contribution, its fair market value, the individual or organization responsible for contributing, its specific use, and a justification for its use within the context of the Corporation's mission;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2EE9BA2DF7AF4463AA2953FCCA37161F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an objective and quantifiable measurement of its progress, on an objective-by-objective basis, in meeting the objectives established by the board;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H905DF320355541EFA72211EB2B006603"><enum>(5)</enum><text>an explanation of the reason for any failure to achieve an objective established by the board; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H92869E194A4140419E88BD12C2A48477"><enum>(6)</enum><text>such recommendations as the Corporation deems appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H0A6FD77355D349EE808CBCE855FAF80"><enum>5.</enum><header>Matching public and private funding</header> 
<subsection id="H08BD1AB892EA498BBF1790758C1EF4E4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of Travel Promotion Fund</header><text>There is hereby established in the Treasury a fund which shall be known as the <quote>Travel Promotion Fund</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H932943EC216045C996935D312F4E086B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Funding</header> 
<paragraph id="HFCD4281431FC4F868046EDA1D4C62F40"><enum>(1)</enum><header>First year</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For fiscal year 2008, the Corporation may borrow from the Treasury, beginning on October 1, 2007, such sums as may be necessary, but not to exceed $10,000,000, to cover its initial expenses and activities under this Act. At the earliest practicable date, the Corporation shall reimburse the Treasury any such amounts borrowed from the Treasury, with at least 50 percent reimbursed before October 1, 2010, and the remainder reimbursed before October 1, 2012. Reimbursement shall include interest at a rate determined by the Treasury to ensure that there is no loss of real purchasing power to the Treasury from this borrowing due to inflation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H53F116B07D9841F4BFAB8766A2B5E45C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subsequent years</header><text>For each of fiscal years 2009 through 2012, from amounts deposited in the general fund of the Treasury during the preceding fiscal year from fees under section 6, the Secretary of the Treasury shall transfer not more than $100,000,000 to the Fund, which shall be made available to the Corporation, subject to subsection (c), to carry out its functions under this Act. Transfers shall be made at least quarterly on the basis of estimates by the Secretary, and proper adjustments shall be made in amounts subsequently transferred to the extent prior estimates were in excess or less than the amounts required to be transferred.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H439F846091454333B39FDDDBB3AF8DB0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Matching Requirement</header> 
<paragraph id="H9A69F2B5735247A3A7BE493874863269"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No amounts may be made available to the Corporation under this section after fiscal year 2008, except to the extent that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF4A18CEA3FDD4124BC46198FC02225BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for fiscal year 2009, the Corporation provides matching funds from non-Federal sources equal in the aggregate to 50 percent or more of the amount transferred to the Fund under subsection (b); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H48E3B7D4194749A791168831B66BB04C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for any fiscal year after fiscal year 2009, the Corporation provides matching funds from non-Federal sources equal in the aggregate to 100 percent of the amount transferred to the Fund under subsection (b) for the fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC2921CB4AE814C76B7FAC6B9A2DD14CF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Goods and services</header><text>For the purpose of determining the amount of matching funds, other than money, available to the Corporation—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6292F67687104F0F8C7DFB9C5F65EC56"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the fair market value, as determined by the Corporation, of goods and services (including advertising) contributed to the Corporation for use under this Act may be included in the determination; but</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB381CCF34503420AB2149359F5C03FDD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the fair market value of such goods and services may not account for more than 80 percent of the matching requirement for the Corporation in any fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAA72134C9E16442297BB6CAE4000EB48"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Right of refusal</header><text>The Corporation may decline to accept any contribution in kind that it determines to be inappropriate, not useful, or commercially worthless.</text></paragraph> </subsection></section> 
<section id="HBC2AD5F85BDC4B1FAC2421974D4705D6"><enum>6.</enum><header>Travel Promotion Fund fees</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If a fully automated electronic traveler authorization system to collect basic biographical information in order to determine, in advance of travel, the eligibility of an alien to travel to the United States is implemented, the United States Government may charge a fee to an applicant for the use of the system. The amount of any such fee initially shall be at least $10, plus such amounts as may be necessary to cover the cost of operating such a system, but may be reduced thereafter if that amount is not necessary to ensure that the Corporation is fully funded.</text></section> 
<section id="HFFF960FC0C8E45EC9E24B74B47DB67"><enum>7.</enum><header>Investment of Funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Pending disbursement pursuant to a program, plan, or project, the Corporation may invest funds received by the Corporation only in obligations of the United States or any agency thereof, in general obligations of any State or any political subdivision thereof, in any interest-bearing account or certificate of deposit of a bank that is a member of the Federal Reserve System, or in obligations fully guaranteed as to principal and interest by the United States.</text></section> 
<section id="H187DE89151B944EE86139B87F3E056E3"><enum>8.</enum><header>Amendments to the International Travel Act of 1961</header> 
<subsection id="H4BEB439AEA514C9DB10097E161784C02"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Powers and duties of Secretary of Commerce</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 201 of the International Travel Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2122">22 U.S.C. 2122</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE68DFDCE8E074A61B4D82F1B1937DB1F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the first sentence of the matter preceding paragraph (1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H24BFB3D4E3564677955D88A499362D69"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and by the United States National Tourism Organization Act of 1996</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7B3FC21452FC497DBDE9DE705BA63156"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>United States National Tourism Organization</quote> and inserting <quote>Corporation for Travel Promotion (established by section 3 of the Travel Promotion Act of 2007)</quote>; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H449392E00DDE42D6ACFA12CB95D8856D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>United States National Tourism Organization</quote> and inserting <quote>Corporation for Travel Promotion</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H809C1EF5A9F64693A2A5D67B48E95EFF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HDB7034C632EB425E8548B0C573AA20A6" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="section">Such plan may not include a comprehensive international advertising campaign relating to critical tourism functions.</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H956EF282921D4F37A3E867026BBCC6E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Tourism Policy Council</header> 
<paragraph id="H4EF69BEB4B1C4918802900F802E4E800"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>Subsection (b) of section 301 of the International Travel Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2124">22 U.S.C. 2124</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7E4D4246F5E34C8AA096F3BFFADF37FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking paragraphs (8) through (10);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HECCF4654C4F3475288EA67D3EABD3B00"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (11) as paragraph (13);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H60F261EE70874D95972B483B00F75B1D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (7) the following new paragraphs:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3D7A2281A6034E80000294CA411F55E7" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HEB11B77EEA7E4E2D9ED4C17DA905DC16"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB56B76E7C0D74254ADA0F089EEC40155"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection of the Department of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE9A64CF0CE304977A277064FA9B632FD"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The Assistant Secretary of U.S. Customs and Immigration Enforcement of the Department of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H85D54C64FF9640CC91D0077511A05295"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The Secretary of Education.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFAED65A96FE94D57A87CE2752D62348C"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President of the Corporation for Travel Promotion (established by section 3 of the Travel Promotion Act of 2007).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6B037EDCAAEA4BEDA095C3FA9C621018"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (13) (as redesignated by subparagraph (B) of this paragraph), by inserting <quote>, in consultation with other members of the Council</quote> at the end before the period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8AE5A054D9B54048953708D5F000F162"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>Subsection (d) of such section is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6068FC25E4904E24908DBEFCC8F9D5BA" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H4FB7082287E6419984C7F0A212A4A2B4"><enum>(d)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Council shall meet not less than 2 times a year. For the purposes of conducting business, each member of the Council may appoint a designee to represent such member during one or more meetings of the Council.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H705B86B476304ED7808F4EE8E8B50961"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Involvement of Federal agencies and departments</header><text>Subsection (e) of such section is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEB39AE208E8C4201BB363D7340A19129" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HE8DB15DC87CE451286AD2034898905C6" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members of the Council shall provide the Corporation for Travel Promotion with timely information regarding documentation and procedures required for admission to the United States and regarding strategies planned by any Federal department or agency to promote travel to the United States for tourism, business, study, scholarship, scientific exchange, or other purposes, so that the Corporation for Travel Promotion may better conduct its communications and promotion activities.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H16FCC24AF6184492B59D74DC6CD10578"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (g)(3) of such section is amended by striking <quote>United States National Tourism Organization</quote> and inserting <quote>Corporation for Travel Promotion</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7CCB0AD88D3041CD94F5AC12E8FA5E5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Applicability of Federal Advisory Committee Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (h) of such section is amended by striking <quote>President of the United States National Tourism Organization</quote> and inserting <quote>President of the Corporation for Travel Promotion</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB053F833F006461D94008F6CFAA69E2E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Repeal of authorities relating to the United States Travel and Tourism Promotion Advisory Board</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 210 of the Department of Commerce and Related Agencies Appropriations Act, 2003 (contained in title II of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/7">Public Law 108–7</external-xref>; 117 Stat. 78–79; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2122">22 U.S.C. 2122</external-xref> note) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HEE26ED161B164548A892FC235800A06E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking subsections (b) through (d); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H17F02662A9254387A33210286F87732F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (e) as subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H932A7AEA50E04F2000359D14C7C30001"><enum>9.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD9B901B782284F618F299E388C004ED7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Board</header><text>The term <term>Board</term> means the board of directors of the Corporation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5BD29B353F754D06A5B97D5E2E38BE7C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Corporation</header><text>The term <term>Corporation</term> means the Corporation for Travel Promotion established by section 3.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6340FAF54A32402689203E3332E38B08"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Fund</header><text>The term <term>Fund</term> means the Travel Promotion Fund established by section 5.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2BCE729640934501B48EB54D40E3FFA5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>Except as otherwise expressly provided, the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Commerce.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


