<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB08124E00FF54A3A8051918D5D5EF6EC" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 67 IH: Veterans Outreach Improvement Act of
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-01-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 67</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20070104">January 4, 2007</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000485">Mr. McIntyre</sponsor>
			 introduced the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HVR00"> Committee on Veterans'
			 Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To amend title 38, United States Code, to improve the
		  outreach activities of the Department of Veterans Affairs, and for other
		  purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HD41375C970DD4927ADE4E8A6A52E00FA" style="OLC">
		<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDD73A1E5A00E4521899333740711F4BA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Veterans Outreach Improvement Act of
			 2007</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="HD35824E5739A4155A7B922E200B800F8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improvement of
			 outreach activities within Department of Veterans Affairs</header>
			<subsection id="HEDE7559A236D46C39266CE15E04EB7ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/5">Chapter 5</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by
			 adding at the end the following new subchapter:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2150E3CFE4C44D2999D3175708C428CE" style="USC">
					<subchapter id="HCCDFBEC38A164BBB905FED0098F824AC"><enum>IV</enum><header>Outreach
				Activities</header>
						<section id="H93E6C6AE91B2473092EC20EFFBE85C3F"><enum>561.</enum><header>Outreach
				activities: coordination of activities within the Department</header>
							<subsection id="H10522523CD1D42D885786F2B7386ABFC"><enum>(a)</enum><text>The Secretary
				shall establish and maintain procedures for ensuring the effective coordination
				of the outreach activities of the Department between and among the
				following:</text>
								<paragraph id="HCB88F7E2E0794BC0904EC628D468494"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Office of the
				Secretary.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HEB107AD214F7457196E68CD58499589D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Office of
				Public Affairs.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H8AD09A2666C343FA00FE2CB0637467AB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Veterans
				Health Administration.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HB5DD7223FB5A4F67A4456E5F07C4BBDB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Veterans
				Benefits Administration.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H30BFA8A5D3C4448EB95D6DEF55CD88A3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The National
				Cemetery Administration.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H40D0F0228BBF47159D4E34155CA423E4"><enum>(b)</enum><text>The Secretary
				shall—</text>
								<paragraph id="H5093A969E6FF444FB6CD1985097E8549"><enum>(1)</enum><text>annually review
				the procedures in effect under subsection (a) for the purpose of ensuring that
				those procedures meet the requirements of that subsection; and</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H4A01D1A4C404431F91D3E153A6BFA972"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make such
				modifications to those procedures as the Secretary considers appropriate in
				light of such review in order to better achieve that purpose.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H30FEA7134A2D4860BE8976EF920058B9"><enum>562.</enum><header>Outreach
				activities: cooperative activities with States; grants to States for
				improvement of outreach</header>
							<subsection id="H3A29424F7052440AA35ED363A0CF25A8"><enum>(a)</enum><text>It is the purpose
				of this section to provide for assistance by the Secretary to the States in
				carrying out programs within their respective jurisdiction that offer a high
				probability of improving outreach and assistance to veterans, and to the
				spouses, children, and parents of veterans, so as to ensure that such
				individuals are fully informed about, and assisted in applying for, any
				veterans’ and veterans-related benefits and programs (including State veterans’
				programs) for which they may be eligible.</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="HEA046DA416BF4D5A00993B32132E7C71"><enum>(b)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that, as a
				condition of the provision of assistance by the Secretary under this section,
				that such assistance is provided for outreach and assistance under State and
				county veteran service programs referred to in subsection (a) in
				locations—</text>
								<paragraph id="H75B30459E4B8459E98A6CECC7305DE51"><enum>(1)</enum><text>that have
				relatively large concentrations of populations of veterans and other
				individuals referred to in subsection (a); or</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HCA3CB22576CC41E4BF017DDD5D5E912C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that are experiencing growth in the
				population of veterans and other individuals referred to in subsection
				(a).</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H039BDD6683DF4D80AD1415EF6F64B41C"><enum>(c)</enum><text>The Secretary may
				enter into cooperative agreements and arrangements with State veterans agencies
				in order to carry out, coordinate, improve, or otherwise enhance outreach by
				the Department and the States (including outreach with respect to State
				veterans’ programs).</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="HBBDBDCB5DE6A461EB2499664BA02AA22"><enum>(d)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC8643B8D365843F880DB001C09318DAF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary may make
				grants to State veterans agencies in order to achieve the following
				purposes:</text>
									<subparagraph id="H506102E60D884A389378ED67ABD671E1" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To carry out, coordinate, improve, or
				otherwise enhance outreach, including activities pursuant to cooperative
				agreements and arrangements under subsection (c).</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H69B0CC3C262B48659C79E870A44C96F9" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>To carry out, coordinate, improve, or
				otherwise enhance activities to assist in the development and submittal of
				claims for veterans’ and veterans-related benefits, including activities
				pursuant to cooperative agreements and arrangements under subsection
				(c).</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H35D7AC5B6C824F8592E3D26EBE06A883" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A State veterans agency receiving a
				grant under this subsection shall use the grant amount for purposes described
				in paragraph (1) by—</text>
									<subparagraph id="H5275630A464D4ABC8754CB191B7FFDE0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>awarding a portion of such grant
				amount to local governments of that State that provide veterans outreach
				services, to be awarded on the basis of the number of veterans residing in the
				jurisdiction of that local government;</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H96DB0DF9BB684C0C00BB770004D23592"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">awarding a portion of such grant amount to
				local governments in that State seeking to establish a program of outreach
				services; and</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC327B50A734947AD8BB55F24F6265200"><enum>(C)</enum><text>using the remainder for outreach
				activities of that State veterans agency.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H63FA45193A9841AE86452F66FB5D6538" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>No portion of the amount of a grant
				to a State under this subsection may be used at the State level for the purpose
				of administering those funds.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3411941835744AC7BEC2FF89EA4D4311" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Federal funds provided to a State by a
				grant under this subsection may not be used to provide more than 50 percent of
				the total cost of such State and local government activities and shall be used
				to expand existing outreach programs and services, not to supplant existing
				State and local funding. The Secretary shall allocate funds to the States for
				grants under this subsection on the basis of the veteran population of the
				respective States.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H5AFFF61DC2044C8390D3FCCC28FBB3D" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA29D7DEA6B95475E843CC55959B300C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>In a case in which a
				unit of local government does not have a veteran services program, funds from a
				grant under this subsection may be used to establish such a program.</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H24FB6C95E5994A7CAB7F4330394BE988" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In a case in which a unit of local
				government does not have such a program and does not seek to establish such a
				program through assistance from a grant amount under this subsection, the State
				veterans agency may use funds available under this subsection to provide
				outreach services for that local government jurisdiction.</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H987768DF21044FC3A93704252C8F8BC2" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a State in which State and
				local government veteran service programs do not seek to receive a grant amount
				under this subsection, the funds for that State shall be reallocated to those
				States in which local government veteran service programs exist and have chosen
				to seek to receive a grant amount under this subsection.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAAE9CF5011E84A1899072CD79BF4AFDA" indent="up1"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Funds made available through a grant
				under this subsection may be used for education and training for State and
				local government employees who provide (or when trained will provide) veterans
				outreach services in order for those employees to obtain accreditation in
				accordance with procedures approved by the Secretary and, for employees so
				accredited, for purposes of continuing education.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HDF5B178DBCF14087BE5100987732002B" indent="up1"><enum>(7)</enum><text>In this subsection, the term
				<term>State veterans agency</term> means the element of the government of a
				State that has responsibility for programs and activities of that State
				government relating to veterans benefits.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE17C4F91472B47128DB57BC5BB88C87"><enum>563.</enum><header>Outreach
				activities: funding</header>
							<subsection id="HE9C96D373929478D9F35D9CCEC920871"><enum>(a)</enum><text>Amounts for the
				outreach activities of the Department under this subchapter shall be budgeted
				and appropriated through a separate appropriation account.</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="HB11AEC47A02240FF00587B110043E478"><enum>(b)</enum><text>In the budget
				justification materials submitted to Congress in support of the Department
				budget for any fiscal year (as submitted with the budget of the President under
				<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/1105">section 1105(a)</external-xref> of title 31), the Secretary shall include a separate statement
				of the amount requested to be appropriated for that fiscal year for the account
				specified in subsection (a).</text>
							</subsection></section><section id="HF20A2DA4C55D470EA08809005E1B0094"><enum>564.</enum><header>Definition of
				outreach</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this
				subchapter, the term <term>outreach</term> means the act or process of taking
				steps in a systematic manner to provide information, services, and benefits
				counseling to veterans, and the survivors of veterans, who may be eligible to
				receive benefits under the laws administered by the Secretary to ensure that
				those individuals are fully informed about, and assisted in applying for, any
				benefits and programs under such laws for which they may be eligible.</text>
						</section><section id="H5E8ACD600F364A1296198D771BBB001E"><enum>565.</enum><header>Authorization
				of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are
				authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary for the purposes of carrying out
				this subchapter, including the making of grants under section 562(d) of this
				title, the amount of $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2007, 2008, and
				2009.</text>
						</section></subchapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H6012F68BD099496481842C174714F038"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical
			 amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter
			 is amended by adding at the end the following new items:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC08804AA07AC4D6AB459158C27048D37" style="OLC">
					<toc container-level="quoted-block-container" idref="H2150E3CFE4C44D2999D3175708C428CE" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration">
						<toc-entry idref="HCCDFBEC38A164BBB905FED0098F824AC" level="subchapter">Subchapter IV—Outreach Activities</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="H93E6C6AE91B2473092EC20EFFBE85C3F" level="section">561. Outreach activities: coordination of activities within the
				Department.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="H30FEA7134A2D4860BE8976EF920058B9" level="section">562. Outreach activities: cooperative activities with States;
				grants to States for improvement of outreach.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="HE17C4F91472B47128DB57BC5BB88C87" level="section">563. Outreach activities: funding.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="HF20A2DA4C55D470EA08809005E1B0094" level="section">564. Definition of outreach.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="H5E8ACD600F364A1296198D771BBB001E" level="section">565. Authorization of
				appropriations.</toc-entry>
					</toc>
					<after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


