<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB8A35E0D03174D0FA3A3673D0938315C" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 1776 IH: Call Center Consumer’s Right to Know
</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2007-03-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 1776</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action>
			<action-date date="20070329">March 29, 2007</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000362">Mr. Altmire</sponsor>
			 introduced the following bill; which was referred to the
			 <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and
			 Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To require employees at a call center who either initiate
		  or receive telephone calls to disclose the physical location of such
		  employees.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HF5A1A73039EF459183BD5424E46834FF" style="OLC">
		<section id="HD665595A842941BF8487DA0301F24E8B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Call Center Consumer’s Right to Know
			 Act</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H38213C514E24437FA0E767B5DA0712C5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Call center
			 requirements</header>
			<subsection id="H6B9C0FCEE029453AB6D2E5D151556680"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A United States
			 corporation or its subsidiaries that utilizes a call center to initiate
			 telephone calls to, or receive telephone calls from, individuals located in the
			 United States, shall require each employee in the call center to disclose the
			 physical location of such employee at the beginning of each telephone call so
			 initiated or received.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HB7EB67E35E4A488AB18425E546DE16B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification
			 Requirement</header><text>A corporation or subsidiary described in subsection
			 (a) shall annually certify to the Federal Trade Commission whether or not the
			 corporation or subsidiary, and the employees of the corporation or subsidiary
			 at its call centers, have complied with that subsection.</text>
			</subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H202AE63C58724A6EAB3F01F64C4D554D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Noncompliance</header><text>A
			 corporation or subsidiary that violates subsection (a) shall be subject to such
			 civil penalties as the Federal Trade Commission prescribes under section
			 3.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HE1899261A1EE42CA8662510082136CE2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Call Center
			 Defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>call center</term> means
			 a location that provides customer-based service and sales assistance or
			 technical assistance and expertise to individuals located in the United States
			 via telephone, the Internet, or other telecommunications and information
			 technology.</text>
			</subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H58946927C25A4F7CBB12AB3D944F1532"><enum>3.</enum><header>Federal Trade
			 Commission Rules</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later
			 than 9 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Federal Trade
			 Commission shall prescribe rules to provide for effective monitoring and
			 compliance with this Act. The Federal Trade Commission’s rulemaking shall
			 include appropriate civil penalties for noncompliance with this Act.</text>
		</section></legis-body>
</bill>


