<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFB37610164684F02B995BE8DC790D4C0" public-private="public" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>109 HR 3997 IH: Financial Data Protection Act of 2005</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2005-10-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>109th CONGRESS</congress> <session>1st Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 3997</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action> 
<action-date date="20051006">October 6, 2005</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000553">Mr. LaTourette</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="H000762">Ms. Hooley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000243">Mr. Castle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000555">Ms. Pryce of Ohio</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001140">Mr. Moore of Kansas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title>To amend the Fair Credit Reporting Act to provide for secure financial data, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HDAE85427E423432183745B26F9F7DBC1" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H046EF4CCFAE14E29A8F351BDA32FAB3B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Financial Data Protection Act of 2005</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H5E79DB4760E046DFBE65009641A0C29"><enum>2.</enum><header>Data security safeguards</header> 
<subsection id="H108A78D1EF454C5D81BB6DC57FA7DF44"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Fair Credit Reporting Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1681">15 U.S.C. 1681</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H9FCA6672B20D4A499BAC1200FB405241" style="USC"> 
<section id="HD2D7FFAECFDA4D568500E92D1EF1B048"><enum>630.</enum><header>Data security safeguards</header> 
<subsection id="HFC56F9C2324F41BCB1B2AE379200A94B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Security Policies and Procedures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each consumer reporter shall have an affirmative obligation to implement, and a continuing obligation to maintain, reasonable policies and procedures to protect the security and confidentiality of sensitive financial personal information relating to any consumer that is maintained, serviced, or communicated by or on behalf of such consumer reporter against any unauthorized use that is reasonably likely to result in substantial harm or inconvenience to such consumer.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0BE83C37138B403EB66805946BFE15C4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Investigation Requirements</header> 
<paragraph id="H55D1D5AF1E71423981D600D715D3291"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Investigation required</header><text>Whenever any consumer reporter determines or becomes aware of information that would reasonably indicate that a breach of data security has or may have occurred or is reasonably likely to be about to occur, or receives notice under subsection (d), the consumer reporter shall immediately conduct a reasonable investigation to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF9540A14F4C84589AC75269C71FC89F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>assess the nature and scope of the potential breach;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC2121A8803704145B784E4BEDC99B54F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify the sensitive financial personal information involved; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD6CAB1007F144E85BDD1D7AF5085C4CF"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">determine if the potential breach is reasonably likely to result in substantial harm or inconvenience to any consumer to whom the information relates.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2BE31323E9004FE8B70091D184463442"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Scope of investigation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An investigation conducted under paragraph (1) shall be commensurate with the nature and the amount of the sensitive financial personal information that is subject to the breach of data security.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7AE011406E0544048812B5EC0010AF82"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Factors to be considered</header><text>In determining the likelihood under this section that sensitive financial personal information that was the subject of a breach of data security has been or will be misused, the consumer reporter shall consider all available relevant facts, including whether the information that was subject to the breach was encrypted, redacted, required technology to use that is not generally commercially available, or is otherwise unreadable or unusable.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6FE476AB0F344568972BF99FF8A370B7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Investigation notices and system restoration requirements</header><text>If a consumer reporter determines after commencing an investigation under subsection (b) that a potential breach of data security may result in substantial harm or inconvenience to any consumer to whom the sensitive financial personal information involved in such potential breach relates, the consumer reporter shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2A75B5D0408A497AAE5C7F00C43B93D0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>promptly notify the United States Secret Service;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBD44B2709FBA427A00D7B01035CFBE78"><enum>(2)</enum><text>promptly notify the appropriate functional regulatory agency for the consumer reporter;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE0043CF07F15436E830193B61D5C7D27" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>notify as appropriate and without unreasonable delay—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBA10B28472064EEFB283132F09F63E82" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any entity that owns or is obligated on a financial account that may be subject to unauthorized transactions as a result of the breach, to the extent the breach involves related sensitive financial account information, including in such notification information reasonably identifying the nature and scope of the breach and the sensitive financial personal information involved;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H864FB097A6FA444297927F72805DC680" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each nationwide consumer reporting agency, in the case of a breach involving sensitive financial identity information relating to 1,000 or more consumers; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H13F41E0121234323ADEF829600684351" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other appropriate critical third parties—</text> 
<clause id="H85C77382775346B5AA84001F916F39D0" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>whose involvement is necessary to investigate the breach; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDCE1951BADF14A10BF1E7933EDDC36BF" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>who will be required to undertake further action with respect to such information to protect such consumers from resulting fraud or identity theft;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1ED2F7E24CDD43A785002538264F86AE" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent possible and practicable, take reasonable measures to repair the breach and restore the security and confidentiality of the sensitive financial personal information involved to limit further unauthorized use of such information; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2998090EF50244199EDFA857F6333CBE" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">take reasonable measures to restore the integrity of the affected data security safeguards and make appropriate improvements to data security policies and procedures.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1B45F1F0442F4EAE99C805B67B72F221" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Third party duties</header> 
<paragraph id="H9C396471837D415B8225F34D5B4B3616" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coordinated investigation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whenever any consumer reporter that maintains or receives sensitive financial personal information for or on behalf of another party determines, or has reason to believe, that a breach of data security has occurred with respect to such information, the consumer reporter shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7A934F517E7D4A569CB6D38C75DF2771" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promptly notify the other party of the breach;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H70BB7E7465514764916DD2B51DF2A32D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>conduct a coordinated investigation with the other party as described in subsection (b); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDDBDED0CB29341358FDE6468AA7400ED" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ensure that the appropriate notices are provided as required under subsection (e).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDE6E24AC10C14320A391C1D8C7B3F8B4" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contractual obligation required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No consumer reporter may provide sensitive financial personal information to a third party to maintain, receive, or communicate on behalf of the consumer reporter, unless such third party agrees that whenever the third party becomes aware that a breach of data security has occurred or is reasonably likely to have occurred with respect to such information maintained, received, or communicated by such third party, the third party shall be obligated—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6F07D23241E84DB4A1185BCB97551BAE" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to provide notice of the breach to the consumer reporter;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H32B4FD7B360643CC828D4F31D954BD43" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to conduct a coordinated investigation with the consumer reporter to determine the likelihood that such information will be misused against the consumers to whom the information relates in a manner that would cause substantial harm or inconvenience to any such consumers; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC186BCD35C3D4B5F944C006E79465472" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide any consumer notices required under subsection (e), except to the extent that such notices are provided by the consumer reporter in a manner meeting the requirements of such subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H259D1F37FCCF478D81D5E30039437EE4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Consumer notice</header> 
<paragraph id="H5D7BA3F3922A4057B35409EF275C27B5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Potential identity theft risk</header><text>A consumer reporter shall provide a consumer notice in accordance with subsection (f) if, after being required to commence an investigation pursuant to this section, the consumer reporter becomes aware—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H17C8326D6F2F442C9DEB003F00321B21"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that a breach of data security is reasonably likely to have occurred, with respect to sensitive financial identity information maintained, received, or communicated by or on behalf of the consumer reporter;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6E671CA61065444BAA86097FED47CC00"><enum>(B)</enum><text>of information reasonably identifying—</text> 
<clause id="H8911EADC0ED844E89383447B7869DF25"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the nature and scope of the breach, and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD5235EF0B0AD4B7E84C78913C05E6D32"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the sensitive financial identity information involved; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6DAA534B6E654A949CAA663219C71900"><enum>(C)</enum><text>that such information has been or is reasonably likely to be misused in a manner causing substantial harm or inconvenience against the consumers to whom such information relates to commit identity theft.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9553FCF335C547A096327DB16689FD3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Potential fraudulent transaction risk</header> 
<subparagraph id="H090BAE7401594732AC50549DBE3F346D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A consumer reporter shall provide a consumer notice in accordance with subsection (f) if, after being required to commence an investigation pursuant to this section, the consumer reporter becomes aware—</text> 
<clause id="H1F1C077597EC40B898171EC746AA7246"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that a breach of data security is reasonably likely to have occurred, with respect to sensitive financial account information maintained, serviced, or communicated by or on behalf of the consumer reporter;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDCA13D1B1ED6477DBCF6464500FAB151"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>of information reasonably identifying—</text> 
<subclause id="HCA22D5D48BE749D197AB05BC00B8A290"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the nature and scope of the breach, and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HD6917945435B43FAA8A8CB619C2C033"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the sensitive financial account information involved; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H53FEBCF5DBF54774BC566680E7B14EC7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that such information has been or is reasonably likely to be misused in a manner causing substantial harm or inconvenience against consumers to whom such information relates to make fraudulent transactions on such consumers’ financial accounts.</text> </clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3CC97A18646747B690BB2B68495EB72E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Potential delayed determination for information security programs</header><text>In determining the likelihood of misuse of sensitive financial account information under subparagraph (A), the consumer reporter may additionally consider whether any neural networks or security programs used by, or on behalf of, the consumer reporter have detected, or are likely to detect on an ongoing basis over a reasonable period of time, fraudulent transactions resulting from the breach of data security.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8E28864375C049A7818CCBDF8263D355"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Timing, content, and manner of notices</header> 
<paragraph id="HAA6D2CB1578B4125801277E312F97059"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Order of notice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The notices required under this section shall be made promptly to the entities described in paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (c), then promptly to any appropriate third parties, and then without unreasonable delay to any consumers described in subsection (e)(1)(C) or (e)(2)(A)(iii), in accordance with such subsections.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9B1EEC9F77FE4B85B28CBAC0C66E99DF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Delay of notice for law enforcement purposes</header><text>If a consumer reporter receives a written request from an appropriate law enforcement agency indicating that providing a notice under subsection (c)(3) or (e) would impede a criminal or civil investigation by that law enforcement agency, or an oral request from an appropriate law enforcement agency indicating that such a written request will be provided within 2 business days—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3A4E6AD1EFC7491EB60190A71736CBEA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the consumer reporter shall delay, or in the case of a foreign law enforcement agency may delay, providing such notice until—</text> 
<clause id="HBCAD29C352154998BF8F00B17B51AF78"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the law enforcement agency informs the consumer reporter that such notice will no longer impede the investigation; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC16B9E427BFB419E99878CDD00A5165"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the law enforcement agency fails to—</text> 
<subclause id="H8272E10346334977852512C0F282EAFD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>provide a written request within 2 business days following an oral request for a delay; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H77E81518A0EF4C808DC51D4511FBDDF6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>provide within 10 days a written request to continue such delay for a specific time that is approved by a court of competent jurisdiction; </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD75F463ECA9D4B9E96171593489B8E24"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the consumer reporter shall not be liable for any losses that would not have occurred but for the delay provided for under this paragraph or but for the communication of any information provided to any law enforcement agency pursuant to this section, except that nothing in this subparagraph shall be construed as creating any inference with respect to the establishment or existence of any such liability; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC8A7658D42A74478BF9163F41D668324"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the consumer reporter may—</text> 
<clause id="HD4CE5162ACC24A6CB86CCBA99C00A876"><enum>(i)</enum><text>conduct appropriate security measures that are not inconsistent with such request; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBD35001B21374661B7004FD412641589"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>contact any law enforcement agency to determine whether any such inconsistency would be created by such measures.</text> </clause></subparagraph> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFB646FA46706499F8010D3D3C8EAF4F0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Content of consumer notice</header><text>Any notice required to be provided by a consumer reporter to a consumer under paragraph (1) or (2) of subsection (e), and any notice required in accordance with subsection (d)(2)(A), shall be provided in a standardized envelope or transmission, and shall include the following in a clear and conspicuous manner:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAE4A549B1ECD49C98521B986908300E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An appropriate heading or notice title.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H490FB441AC61486EA4009E15588B7DDB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of the nature and type of information that was, or is reasonably believed to have been, subject to the breach of data security.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H84161EE42492439F914986008F56C5B0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The identity and relationship to the consumer of any entity that suffered the breach.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H92059F2F9EC445DCBEA1FCA01DA9F8C5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>If known, the date, or a reasonable approximation of the period of time, on or within which sensitive financial personal information related to the consumer was, or is reasonably believed to have been, subject to a breach.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4C7BA67614C044F791B459EF69921C6B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A general description of the actions taken by the consumer reporter to restore the security and confidentiality of the breached information.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFAC9BF40939E430CBEEED61B041CE500"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A telephone number by which a consumer to whom the breached information relates may call free of charge to obtain additional information about how to respond to the breach.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H362B2C7C75AA4EABBE9500AECCD928AD"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to notices involving sensitive financial identity information, a summary of rights of consumer victims of fraud or identity theft, such as that prepared by the Commission under section 609(d), including any additional appropriate information on how the consumer may—</text> 
<clause id="H2A16E4EE48BC4639008F9F20DDF9844"><enum>(i)</enum><text>obtain a copy of a consumer report free of charge in accordance with section 612;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HEA02E385F75C44639000F000A82EC384"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>place a fraud alert in any file relating to the consumer at a consumer reporting agency under section 605A to discourage unauthorized use; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2D7A0A7937594B25BA7216D643B694BE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>contact the Commission for more detailed information.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H08D3741664DA4FDC8EAF7B8CEA672534"><enum>(H)</enum><text>With respect to notices involving sensitive financial identity information, appropriate instructions to the consumer for obtaining file monitoring mitigation under subsection (g), which shall include a mailing address for the consumer to make a request for such mitigation, and may also include additional contact information, such as an e-mail or website address or a telephone number.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H042B444F659B4264B025B9174DB84BC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The approximate date the notice is being issued.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H46B16FF1C7E4486C9C771B32A289EEE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Other transmission of notice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The notice described in paragraph (3) may be made by other means of transmission (such as electronic or oral) to a consumer only if—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H913DE1C8D7DA474DAEA4E7F613E3F78B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the consumer has previously and expressly agreed to receive notice by such means; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3AA6DFF1B0B3425DAAF3F8B3CCDC9825"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">all of the relevant information in paragraph (3) is communicated to such consumer in such transmission.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC46C99420B194E32A2D264FCE3E7C503"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Duplicative notices</header> 
<subparagraph id="HCE235A0F0FA2483096EE7F49B059DF7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A consumer reporter, whether acting directly or in coordination with another entity—</text> 
<clause id="H10FBC78CC83448338ED68E3CDCD1AED0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall not be required to provide more than 1 notice with respect to any breach of data security to any affected consumer, so long as such notice meets all the applicable requirements of this section, and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H421804AE096E4EC19FC8CF977064F2AD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall not be required to provide a notice with respect to any consumer if a notice meeting the applicable requirements of this section has already been provided by another entity.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8A3B9FCCB3C44C0CA800547900A6D351"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Updating notices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a consumer notice is provided to consumers pursuant only to subsection (e)(2) (relating to sensitive financial account information), and the consumer reporter subsequently becomes aware of a reasonable likelihood that sensitive financial personal information involved in the breach is being misused in a manner causing substantial harm or inconvenience against such consumer to commit identity theft, then an additional notice must be provided to such consumers as well any other appropriate parties under this section, including the summary of rights and file monitoring mitigation instructions under subparagraphs (G) and (H) of subsection (e)(3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBC4434C7E99B44EA9700B5539CA9EDE"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Responsibility and costs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise established by agreement, the entity that suffered a breach of data security shall be—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC4E430FF357E4A1CB6983FB35CE798E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>primarily responsible for providing any consumer notices required under this section with respect to such breach; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC868E411BCCC4E2498EC21B55FBFD2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>responsible for the reasonable actual costs of any notices provided under this section, except as otherwise established by agreement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC2F85B2AE1B34A9DB692E65DFF2EA7C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Financial fraud mitigation</header> 
<paragraph id="H34552DD680FC4900B8002EAB43031B69"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Free file monitoring</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any consumer reporter that is required to provide notice to a consumer under paragraph (1) of subsection (e), or that is deemed to be in compliance with such requirement by operation of subsection (h), if requested by the consumer before the end of the 90-day period beginning on the date of such notice, shall make available to the consumer, free of charge and for at least a 6-month period, a service that monitors nationwide credit activity regarding a consumer from a consumer reporting agency described in section 603(p).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF6EF15E9CCE44464AE3F32C62C9DF09C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Joint rulemaking for safe harbor</header><text>In accordance with subsection (i), the Secretary of the Treasury, the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, and the Commission shall jointly develop standards and guidelines, which shall be issued by all functional regulatory agencies, that, in any case in which—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4F349765EEF94EA6A2B45DF211BBE1D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>free file monitoring is offered under paragraph (1) to a consumer;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H36F8B9CB98934DC788F15458ECDA726"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subsequent to the offer, another party misuses sensitive financial identity information on the consumer obtained through the breach of data security (that gave rise to such offer) to commit identity theft against the consumer; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA95437CA7FFD4681889B76B0C3BED2E2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>at the time of such breach the consumer reporter met the requirements of subsection (a), </text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">exempts the consumer reporter from any liability for any harm to the consumer resulting from such misuse, other than any direct pecuniary loss or loss pursuant to agreement by the consumer reporter, except that nothing in this paragraph shall be construed as creating any inference with respect to the establishment or existence of any such liability.</continuation-text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDF07CB3A01B846798D2B00536BE13601"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Compliance With GLBA</header> 
<paragraph id="H09D8CC8B158448ECBEA099006BD74E9F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the purposes of this section, any person subject to section 501(b) of title V of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act shall be deemed to be in compliance with—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H23C53CEAA5254948B0196053F21E688D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>subsection (a), if—</text> 
<clause id="H5C9634CC57D8430F93D9E9002D10FA75"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the person is obliged to implement appropriate safeguards, with respect to customer records and information, pursuant to regulations, guidelines, or guidance prescribed by or issued by an agency or authority in accordance with such subsection of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H3CE43F9099CF4B7BB854982583C8FF88"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the person is substantially in compliance with such obligation; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2DEFC857532343588966B0CF9BE6847"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the safeguards are being applied by the person with respect to sensitive financial personal information in the same manner as with respect to customer records and information;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5945CC530DF344029988DC28CC964100"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subsection (b), if—</text> 
<clause id="H7AB3D4E49F974D4182D606FBD29B0935"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the person is obliged to conduct investigations of breaches of information security pursuant to regulations, guidelines, or guidance prescribed by or issued by an agency or authority in accordance with such subsection of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H94633B00EA0D406AB34EAE2578A22F03"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the person is substantially in compliance with such obligation; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H40A053620F1A4D1EBA68C0582F124100"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the person conducts such investigations with respect to sensitive financial personal information in the same manner as with other information subject to such regulation, guideline, or guidance; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFC029542D0D24E498870C6F403F88485"><enum>(C)</enum><text>subsections (c), (d), (e), and (f) (other than subsection (f)(3)), if—</text> 
<clause id="HCDFEADE980A14892803732F982B7F00"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the person is obliged to implement a consumer notification program after breaches of such data safeguards pursuant to regulations, guidelines, or guidance prescribed by or issued by an agency or authority in accordance with section 501 of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5D43685E65304FF38162313BB4889F61"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the person is substantially in compliance with such obligation; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8D5328FF32D14B1DA1DCEDE128CE030"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the person implements such consumer notification program with respect to sensitive financial personal information in the same manner as with other information subject to such regulations, guidelines, or guidance.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5187CF4368EC4CFFB9D7C1F83E006505"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coordination with requirements for GSEs</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), if—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA7D78493E47947518F54AA71E5F2AB33"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to any requirement described in subparagraph (A)(i), (B)(i), or (C)(i) of paragraph (1) relating to sensitive financial personal information—</text> 
<clause id="H9520915041EA4D2185A47CD2E62BE86"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an enterprise (as defined in title XIII of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1992) is required to comply with orders, guidance, or regulations issued by the functional regulatory agency set forth in subsection (j)(1)(F); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE6887CCD058F47FDBB4367CC83AF52D0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such orders, guidance, or regulations of such functional regulatory agency are substantially consistent with regulations, guidelines, or guidance prescribed by or issued by an agency or authority in accordance with section 501(b) of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act (without regard to whether such enterprise or functional regulatory agency is subject to such section 501(b)) that relate to any requirement described in subparagraph (A)(i), (B)(i), or (C)(i) of paragraph (1); </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE0EFEA316D56473F8496E3B8B1E352F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the enterprise is substantially in compliance with such requirement relating to sensitive financial personal information; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE8D55B4C4CEA46F6B9027135D2DDEC99"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the enterprise implements any such requirement with respect to sensitive financial personal information in the same manner as with other information subject to the regulations, guidelines, or guidance prescribed or issued by the functional regulatory agency set forth in subsection (j)(1)(F),</text> </subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">the enterprise shall be treated as a person subjection to section 501(b) of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act.</continuation-text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H930DA5F3A2B74B5D9C96269FB9F18367"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Harmonization of GLBA</header> 
<subparagraph id="HFDB44BE6248147E79BD251582CED5485"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent that compliance by any consumer reporter with the requirements of title V of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act shall be deemed, pursuant to this subsection, to be compliance with this section, and the requirements of such title, and any regulations, guidelines, or orders issued or prescribed under such title, differ in any way from this section, it is the sense of the Congress that the applicable regulators shall make every appropriate effort as any relevant regulations are prescribed, reviewed, or updated to reconcile such differences to harmonize the corresponding requirements.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H55CC6FD0B5F44FA0BA6CE0A83B17AF8F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Agencies that have not fully implemented title v of the GLBA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any agency described in subsection (j) that has not issued or prescribed regulations, guidelines, or orders that are required or permitted under title V of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act and that set forth the requirements for compliance with such title, including with respect to providing notice of a breach of data security, shall prescribe such regulations, guidelines, or orders, as appropriate, before the end of the 12-month period beginning on the date of the enactment of the Financial Data Protection Act of 2005, in a manner that—</text> 
<clause id="HB41CCFDFF46F4122BB13CE7D902F4681"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is consistent with this section; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDB0F02417A5E4996B3497F1E08F37651"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>allows, to the extent practical, consistent standards across holding companies with respect to compliance with this section and section 501(b) of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act that is deemed compliance under this subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H519AEF1A16484F768783B1E65C1B2D18"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Agencies that have implemented title v of the GLBA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any agency described in subsection (j) that has issued or prescribed regulations, guidelines, or orders that are required or permitted under title V of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act and that set forth the requirements for compliance with such title shall modify such regulations, guidelines, or orders, as appropriate, before the end of the 12-month period beginning on the date of the enactment of the Financial Data Protection Act of 2005, in a manner that—</text> 
<clause id="H5057D29538EF4E5D98CB002F9F1462FF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is consistent with this section; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H49B5A782AC73476FBFE9BE220216556F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>allows, to the extent practical, consistent standards across holding companies with respect to compliance with this section and section 501(b) of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act that is deemed compliance under this subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7236D58F7EDC40A9ADFE25129E5BCB09"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Coordination under this section</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent practical, any regulations, guidelines, standards, or orders issued or prescribed under this section shall be issued or prescribed in a manner that—</text> 
<clause id="H0AA2DDD42E3E43F09FBD2C61C3D9E775"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is consistent with this section; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD91F425037CF4F9AB6BA2D2849B8778"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>allows, to the extent practical, consistent standards across holding companies with respect to compliance with this section and section 501(b) of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act that is deemed compliance under this subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2084A7D4052446FC8900C6A5D82DB7F7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Uniform security regulations</header> 
<paragraph id="HB120CE48AD244D4F8391784590566939"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Uniform standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury, the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, and the Commission shall jointly develop appropriate standards and guidelines to implement this section (other than subsection (h), including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD3A404D7F5A04CE481A3C65F169D5E39"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prescribing regulations requiring each consumer reporter to establish reasonable policies and procedures implementing such standards and guidelines, consistent, as appropriate, with subsection (h) and section 501(b) of title V of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act, and any regulations, guidelines, or orders issued or prescribed under such section;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF9431C9ECCDA4950B3AEF7FC2E670146"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prescribing specific regulations with respect to subsection (f)(3) setting forth a reasonably unique and, pursuant to paragraph (2)(B), exclusive color and titling of the notice, and standardized formatting of the notice contents described under such subsection to standardize such communications and make them more likely to be reviewed and understood by consumers;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H86B75F366D404731BCED3C2B61CB31B4"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing in such standards and guidelines that the responsibility of a consumer reporter to provide notice under this section—</text> 
<clause id="HCA9C1B1AD67042E895C44BE9F82758C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has been satisfied with respect to any particular consumer, even if the consumer reporter is unable to contact the consumer, so long as the consumer reporter has made reasonable efforts to obtain a current address or other current contact information with respect to such consumer;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC39ED983CA0742F6975772FEF8B0808D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may be made by public notice in appropriate cases where such reasonable efforts have failed; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8FD934B3880E49C895AE88ED60E9D56"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>with respect to paragraph (3) of subsection (c), may be communicated to entities in addition to those specifically required under such paragraph through any reasonable means, such as through an electronic transmission normally received by all of the consumer reporter’s business customers; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF4B01B5D4F944BAD98AC87BDD2BFBF97"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing in such standards and guidelines elaboration on how to determine whether a technology is generally commercially available for the purposes of subsection (b), focusing on the availability of such technology to persons who potentially could seek to breach the data security of the consumer reporter.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6081F76E3AC5440D9FD4B7DD7E417195"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Enforcement</header> 
<subparagraph id="H43CD5393CECE4CF7997CAD89E66B2E7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Each of the functional regulatory agencies shall prescribe such regulations as may be necessary, consistent with the standards in paragraph (1), to ensure compliance with this section with respect to the persons subject to the jurisdiction of such agency under subsection (i).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF17647CBE22F4BEE89F08E1657609FEA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Misuse of unique color and titles of notices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who uses the unique color and titling adopted under paragraph (1)(B) for notices under subsection (f)(3) in a way that is likely to create a false belief in a consumer that a communication is such a notice shall be liable in the same manner and to the same extent as a debt collector is liable under section 813 for any failure to comply with any provision of the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H685A2FFA5928410CAFF80734000078EC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Procedures and deadline</header> 
<subparagraph id="H3C15942C70DC45BA98B894E59DB4814"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Procedures</header><text>Standards and guidelines issued under this subsection shall be issued in accordance with applicable requirements of title 5, United States Code.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H365479D500534CF784304D00DC647FBB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Deadline for initial standards and guidelines</header><text>The standards and guidelines required to be issued under paragraph (1) shall be published in final form before the end of the 12-month period beginning on the date of the enactment of the Financial Data Protection Act of 2005.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H209F9B3D9E8049578DA08EF300DE01D3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Deadline for enforcement regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The standards and guidelines required to be issued under paragraph (2) shall be published in final form before the end of the 6-month period beginning on the date standards and guidelines described in subparagraph (B) are published in final form.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0F7892DE763D4928A1C0EC8E3F41201D"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Authority to grant exceptions</header><text>The regulations prescribed under paragraph (2) may include such additional exceptions to this section as are deemed by the functional regulatory agencies to be consistent with the purposes of this section.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE11101B28923420AB3513EE28F249B70"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Consultation and coordination</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury, the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, and the Commission shall consult and coordinate with the other functional regulatory agencies to the extent appropriate in prescribing regulations under this subsection.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5D73875A4832415D953E368DDA10796F"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Failure to meet deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any agency or authority required to publish standards and guidelines or regulations under this subsection that fails to meet the deadline for such publishing shall submit a report to the Congress within 30 days of such deadline describing—</text> 
<clause id="H789EDA7CBA174001B5AE04A0D3435E00"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the reasons for the failure to meet such deadline;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H02E0C885E5C7487E804C8BC4148241D6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>when the agency or authority expects to complete the publication required; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7FD458F032164EDC95AE84D1E0D81235"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the detriment such failure to publish by the required deadline will have on consumers and other affected parties. </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBCF8A5402F244C12BE23DC6EBC4F7BFE"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Uniform implementation and interpretation</header><text>It is the intention of the Congress that the agencies and authorities described in subsection (j)(1)(G) will implement and interpret their enforcement regulations, including any exceptions provided under subparagraph (D), in a uniform manner.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8FF994EBF0054CE400EE7DEB5799BCC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Appropriate exemptions or modifications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury, the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, and the Commission, in consultation with the Administrator of the Small Business Administration and other functional regulatory agencies, shall provide appropriate exemptions or modifications from requirements of this section relating to sensitive financial personal information for consumer reporters that do not maintain, service, or communicate a large quantity of sensitive financial account information or sensitive financial identity information.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H014C0AA641F743C98214796D57C16E00"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Administrative enforcement</header> 
<paragraph id="H7A67AB9064CE4580AD311208F32864E9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding section 616, 617, or 621, compliance with this section and the regulations prescribed under this section shall be enforced exclusively by the functional regulatory agencies with respect to financial institutions and other persons subject to the jurisdiction of each such agency under applicable law, as follows:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5A9C90F5154A413EB3C577BF7CA00AC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Under section 8 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act, in the case of—</text> 
<clause id="H7A91345930E94BEDB0EDA85C23798C86"><enum>(i)</enum><text>national banks, Federal branches and Federal agencies of foreign banks, and any subsidiaries of such entities (except brokers, dealers, persons providing insurance, investment companies, and investment advisers), by the Comptroller of the Currency;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HABAF1EA32F45486EA50071D16056C3FB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>member banks of the Federal Reserve System (other than national banks), branches and agencies of foreign banks (other than Federal branches, Federal agencies, and insured State branches of foreign banks), commercial lending companies owned or controlled by foreign banks, organizations operating under section 25 or 25A of the Federal Reserve Act, and bank holding companies and their nonbank subsidiaries or affiliates (except brokers, dealers, persons providing insurance, investment companies, and investment advisers), by the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4534979B0EFD4B39001D04A567D507B0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>banks insured by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation (other than members of the Federal Reserve System), insured State branches of foreign banks, and any subsidiaries of such entities (except brokers, dealers, persons providing insurance, investment companies, and investment advisers), by the Board of Directors of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H007E0F63188C4CC0A28698C2E2A841F3"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>savings associations the deposits of which are insured by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, and any subsidiaries of such savings associations (except brokers, dealers, persons providing insurance, investment companies, and investment advisers), by the Director of the Office of Thrift Supervision.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDC76AF6654A1477DBD21C3811892AAA1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Under the Federal Credit Union Act, by the Board of the National Credit Union Administration with respect to any federally insured credit union, and any subsidiaries of such an entity.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCF5276A7419A4748AE1F6504EA016B38"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Under the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, by the Securities and Exchange Commission with respect to any broker, dealer, or nonbank transfer agent.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1BDCB99FCA0E404FB3D59B03CD30079"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Under the Investment Company Act of 1940, by the Securities and Exchange Commission with respect to investment companies.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7A3C9647B09942C4A3B1571E3C69E090"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Under the Investment Advisers Act of 1940, by the Securities and Exchange Commission with respect to investment advisers registered with the Commission under such Act.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2D41590B2C604B16AFC0DB4456239624"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Under the provisions of title XIII of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1992, by the Director of Federal Housing Enterprise Oversight (and any successor to such functional regulatory agency) with respect to the Federal National Mortgage Association, the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation, and any other entity or enterprise (as defined in such title XIII) subject to the jurisdiction of such functional regulatory agency under such title, including any affiliate of any such enterprise.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H500519A817BC47F2BD30F2F7E148088B"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Under State insurance law, in the case of any person engaged in the business of insurance, by the applicable State insurance authority of the State in which the person is domiciled.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDBFFA707C89344D490E2419527EF81A"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Under the Federal Trade Commission Act, by the Commission for any other person that is not subject to the jurisdiction of any agency or authority under paragraphs (1) through (7) of this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFD66872EF38D4075A439FA88B70265DC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exercise of certain powers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of the exercise by any agency referred to in paragraph (1) of its powers under any Act referred to in that subsection, a violation of any requirement imposed under this subchapter shall be deemed to be a violation of a requirement imposed under that Act. In addition to its powers under any provision of law specifically referred to in paragraph (1), each of the agencies referred to in that paragraph may exercise, for the purpose of enforcing compliance with any requirement imposed under this section, any other authority conferred on it by law. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0DE2A47906C644FD8CB511B1060805B4"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section, the following definitions shall apply:</text> 
<paragraph id="H173E0C9D571A4B719E001CE3B1BF1817"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Breach of data security</header><text>The term <quote>breach of data security</quote> means, with respect to sensitive financial personal information that is maintained, serviced, or communicated by or on behalf of any consumer reporter—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9221861FE6E349EB99CB580048FE1466"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an unauthorized acquisition of such information that could be used to commit financial fraud (such as identity theft or fraudulent transactions made on financial accounts); or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB888CD0B562A4B2E863FCA922D1C7175"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an unusual pattern of use of such information indicative of financial fraud.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8B9C2455D86B4821BEA433229322A90"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consumer</header><text>The term <quote>consumer</quote> means an individual. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB64957CB1AF64EA3928BC0A27C392745"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consumer reporter and related terms</header> 
<subparagraph id="HA3C8F90788854D14B22029099F4DEA22"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Consumer report</header><text>The term <quote>consumer report</quote> includes any written, oral, or other communication of any information by a consumer reporter bearing on a consumer’s credit worthiness, credit standing, credit capacity, character, general reputation, personal characteristics, personal identifiers, financial account information, or mode of living.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC60DEA8A7061487A9B5E16E3BCA4B9ED"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consumer reporter</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>consumer reporter</quote> means any consumer reporting agency or financial institution, or any person which, for monetary fees, dues, on a cooperative nonprofit basis, or otherwise regularly engages in whole or in part in the practice of assembling or evaluating consumer reports, consumer credit information, or other information on consumers, for the purpose of furnishing consumer reports to third parties or to provide or collect payment for or market products and services, or for employment purposes, and which uses any means or facility of interstate commerce for such purposes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H05B2F750F24C40EE88794B5EEF1316F0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Financial institution</header><text>The term <quote>financial institution</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC5743260B8E64342828CC35F21059405"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any person the business of which is engaging in activities that are financial in nature as described in or determined under section 4(k) of the Bank Holding Company Act; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8129BBE47E264389ABD1E17D637CA645"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any entity that is primarily engaged in activities that are subject to the Fair Credit Reporting Act; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9FD2DA0E9D054F9A9396B7E4096DA034"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any person that is maintaining, receiving, or communicating sensitive financial personal information on an ongoing basis for the purposes of engaging in interstate commerce.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8EB35DDF901A46088D6C3473BE5EC02B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Functional regulatory agency</header><text>The term <quote>functional regulatory agency</quote> means any agency described in subsection (j) with respect to the financial institutions and other persons subject to the jurisdiction of such agency.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC44DF712FBF9460F9E1743FD719D2806"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Nationwide consumer reporting agency</header><text>The term <quote>nationwide consumer reporting agency</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD33D2B417FC44711995F1B6EABDF625"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a consumer reporting agency described in section 603(p);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8266064FEB9C4D61B02CD3FBB42D8B60"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any person who notifies the Commission that the person reasonably expects to become a consumer reporting agency described in section 603(p) within a reasonable time; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB6A4D1E56AE74931B62C5CFA3B2B3B96"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a consumer reporting agency described in section 603(w) that notifies the Commission that the person wishes to receive breach of data security notices under this section that involve information of the type maintained by such agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA3BD5CCCA65046F79BE8623815D4CA2C" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Neural network</header><text>The term <quote>neural network</quote> means an information security program that monitors financial account transactions for potential fraud, using historical patterns to analyze and identify suspicious financial account transactions.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3AD4345C104149C6878987EB4F20153E"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Sensitive financial account information</header><text>The term <quote>sensitive financial account information</quote> means a financial account number of a consumer, such as a credit card number or debit card number, in combination with any security code, access code, biometric code, password, or other personal identification information that would allow access to the financial account.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCBCA467C3E944D82834012FCC44B88DE"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Sensitive financial identity information</header><text>The term <quote>sensitive financial identity information</quote> means the first and last name, the address, or the telephone number of a consumer, in combination with any of the following of the consumer:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H08B2B1000EAB4FB600E22F72118C1686"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Social Security number.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0F2879159B4747D6B190F78E769698D1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Driver’s license number or equivalent State identification number.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF089276201F049758293D462DA8FD543"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Taxpayer identification number.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H563FC05F18FA402D00EB44EB12BBC4EE"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Sensitive financial personal information</header><text>The term <quote>sensitive financial personal information</quote> means any information that is sensitive financial account information, sensitive financial identity information, or both.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAB498C63C88842D3B4C8D49F44A121EC" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Substantial harm or inconvenience</header><text>The term <quote>substantial harm or inconvenience</quote> with respect to a consumer means material financial loss to or civil or criminal penalties imposed on the consumer or the need for the consumer to expend significant time and effort to correct erroneous information relating to the consumer, including information maintained by consumer reporting agencies, financial institutions, or government entities, in order to avoid material financial loss or increased costs or civil or criminal penalties, due to unauthorized use of sensitive financial personal information relating to such consumer, but does not include other harm or inconvenience that is not substantial, including changing a financial account number or closing a financial account.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6231D54A2AE64B39ABBE001F3317E089"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Relation to State laws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No requirement or prohibition may be imposed under the laws of any State with respect to the responsibilities of any person—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0412B9DCA03B4C028379D515396B001D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to protect the security or confidentiality of information on consumers maintained by or on behalf of the person;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE2595192071246CE95505BA42153F614"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to safeguard such information from potential misuse;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9267486799A3430CAFCC94D2057F158D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to investigate or provide notices of any unauthorized access to information concerning the consumer, or the potential misuse of such information, for fraudulent purposes; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H12DE5ACCECF54BFEBEEB633730916B20"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to mitigate any loss or harm resulting from such unauthorized access or misuse.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB89F6C03B6824094AEC5233D33F00B7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical Amendment</header><text>The table of sections for the Fair Credit Reporting Act is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 629 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HE90FD79F9D354024B3C6F2726E4735EA" style="USC"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">630. Data security safeguards</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD2640FC890FB4A31B7EF8220D3962E71"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective Date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provisions of section 630 of the Fair Credit Reporting Act (as added by this section), other than subsection (h) of such section, shall take effect on the date of publication of the regulations required under paragraph (3) of such subsection, with respect to any person under the jurisdiction of each regulatory agency publishing such regulations.</text> </subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


