<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HD7E1BABFAD494C0B92467898C5DDFF8C" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 6225 EH: Improving SCRA and USERRA Protections Act of 2008</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">110th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 6225</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, relating to equitable relief with respect to a State or private employer, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H295CB3C5BC4447D7B5EA8FB1C2B09F41" style="OLC"> 
</legis-body> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="no-display-enacting-clause" style="OLC" id="H479199439F6643C4B75D58599DC5B2C0"> 
<section id="H10F3F32EB8B843E4BD97176EC3E45296" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving SCRA and USERRA Protections Act of 2008</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HC88F5A75E9614A66947589E14CBEA65"><enum>2.</enum><header>Equity powers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/4323">Section 4323(e)</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>may use</quote> and inserting <quote>shall use, in any case in which the court determines it is appropriate,</quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HDB14AD19D1B04037A95EBA052C3E395D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Relief for students who are members of Armed Forces during period of military service</header> 
<subsection id="HE738E40D64314031B34744CD72A0C9B5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title VII of the Servicemembers Civil Relief Act (50 U.S.C. App. 591 et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0BDC70DBF3CB4356B8822200FCCFE678" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA9BD6CD8D4F6488DAE61E0C8D533675C"><enum>707.</enum><header>Tuition, reenrollment, and student loan relief for postsecondary students called to military service</header> 
<subsection id="H3A2A0CC54CD44257AAA2B2C4493FFC6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Tuition and reenrollment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whenever a servicemember is called, activated, or ordered to military service and withdraws or takes a leave of absence from an institution of higher education in which the servicemember is enrolled, the institution shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H58812F82761342B6BA636052C0742663"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide a credit or refund to the servicemember the tuition and fees paid by the servicemember (other than from the proceeds of a grant or scholarship) for the portion of the program of education for which the servicemember did not receive academic credit after such withdrawal or leave; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2ACA60E8816A4CDAA395EAC1D29F796C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide the servicemember an opportunity to reenroll with the same educational and academic status in such program of education that the servicemember had when activated for military service.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1C302BBA00C1414BB46D00F148D0635D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Institution of higher education defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>institution of higher education</term> means a 2-year or 4-year institution of higher education as defined in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H597B3EA0589D44D28800987B41EAE94F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exemption of student debts from creditor protection based on income level</header><text>Section 207(c) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/50/527">50 U.S.C. App. 527(c)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>This subsection shall not apply with respect to an obligation or liability that is incurred by a servicemember who, at the time the servicemember is called to military service, is a student enrolled within six months of activation at an institution of higher education on a full-time basis, as determined by that institution.</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H586D98A178FA439A9325000924F825A5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1(b) of such Act is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H45A64007D5EF47D0894F457EB78D9EDF" style="OLC"> 
<toc> 
<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 707. Tuition, reenrollment, and student loan relief for postsecondary students called to military service.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB8317EC58B324702B2127DC0B3E42D2D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect for periods of military service beginning after the date of the enactment of this section.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H75F3CDC3DB6E41A700B8DC34C8A76213" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>4.</enum><header>Termination or suspension by servicemembers of certain service contracts entered into before permanent change of station or deployment orders</header> 
<subsection id="H6C15E8C1D756458A80F58DFDB95D787B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>Title III of the Servicemembers Civil Relief Act (50 U.S.C. App. 531 et seq.) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H63A2AA6505B34DCCADEF9662274C375"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating section 308 as section 309; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6E6BC383C70B4A670096937D1E006910"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 307 the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H25A81D2625584A8FA5E2506CA07E3369" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H213D695CFCDD451300CEDF4E826D5523"><enum>308.</enum><header>Termination or suspension of service contracts</header> 
<subsection id="HA91623843B01495CB1DCD320B84D47B5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Termination or suspension by servicemember</header><text>A person in military service who is party to or enters into a contract described in subsection (c) may terminate or suspend, at the person’s option, the contract at any time after the date of the person’s military orders, as described in subsection (c).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAE4852CFD4B24CA482A65EEA8FA2E566"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Special rules</header> 
<paragraph id="H1251010EC8E945DA8BD6054EDF53036D" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A suspension under subsection (a) of a contract by a person in military service shall continue for the length of the person’s deployment pursuant to the person’s military orders.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H619F1226CF5F4B8492E1005CB8217CBA" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A service provider under a contract suspended or terminated under subsection (a) by a person in military service may not impose a suspension fee or early termination fee in connection with the suspension or termination of the contract, other than a nominal fee for the suspension; except that the service provider may impose a reasonable fee for any equipment remaining on the premises of the person in military service during the period of the suspension. The person in military service may defer, without penalty, payment of such a nominal fee or reasonable fee for the length of the person’s deployment pursuant to the person’s military orders.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD7299B6EAF7646158C0041EB4B48456C" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In any case in which the contract being suspended under subsection (a) is for cellular telephone service or telephone exchange service, the person in military service, after the date on which the suspension of the contract ends, may keep, to the extent practicable and in accordance with all applicable laws and regulations, the same telephone number the person had before the person suspended the contract.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD44EA905EC2A41EF98D7153BCD1F32B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Covered contracts</header><text>This section applies to a contract for cellular telephone service, telephone exchange service, multichannel video programming service, Internet access service, water, electricity, oil, gas, or other utility if the person enters into the contract and thereafter receives military orders—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9272F3D2A4A74C03835843BC1C1BB132"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to deploy with a military unit, or as an individual, in support of a contingency operation for a period of not less than 90 days; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H45D2A0998B8344F39C9441C628B9A5D4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for a change of permanent station to a location that does not support the contract.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2CBD5C72B56E4973866847D0AEC9D699"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Manner of termination or suspension</header> 
<paragraph id="HDB21DF9C2BDF449A971500E0832D7C00"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Termination or suspension of a contract under subsection (a) is made by delivery by the person in military service of written notice of such termination or suspension and a copy of the servicemember’s military orders to the other party to the contract (or to that party’s grantee or agent).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7CBE44C934DD45A49CC15DC7001C29CD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Nature of notice</header><text>Delivery of notice under paragraph (1) may be accomplished—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA55D81D281624E84A2109EC36217A8DD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by hand delivery;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H875325D36CA049B6835663A0DC22378D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by private business carrier;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1F4BC356A4B640599F1782F208C3BD9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by facsimile; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2FB878C263CE4D01A5DB6197BDD9DDEC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by placing the written notice and a copy of the servicemember’s military orders in an envelope with sufficient postage and with return receipt requested, and addressed as designated by the party to be notified (or that party’s grantee or agent), and depositing the envelope in the United States mails.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H96501ED345B84D7CA0C0F31CA9318DF2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Date of contract termination or suspension</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Termination or suspension of a service contract under subsection (a) is effective as of the date on which the notice under subsection (d) is delivered.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H95035F9382FC4F3586A957C6AAEB3433"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Other obligations and liabilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The service provider under the contract may not impose an early termination or suspension charge, but any tax or any other obligation or liability of the person in military service that, in accordance with the terms of the contract, is due and unpaid or unperformed at the time of termination or suspension of the contract shall be paid or performed by the person in military service.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H283DB6D80FA64496B4B471D7DCF9AD6B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Fees paid in advance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A fee or amount paid in advance for a period after the effective date of the termination of the contract shall be refunded to the person in military service by the other party (or that party’s grantee or agent) within 60 days of the effective date of the termination of the contract.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5B059872B89A42E8B9CCACEE644F2900"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Relief to other party</header><text>Upon application by the other party to the contract to a court before the termination date provided in the written notice, relief granted by this section to a person in military service may be modified as justice and equity require.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3895189890714EEC9F006927E0C7C61"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Penalties</header> 
<paragraph id="H96378CA7A3F34CD4B128069CE611BBE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Misdemeanor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whoever knowingly violates or attempts to violate this section shall be fined not more than $5,000 in the case of an individual or $10,000 in the case of an organization.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H92FD3EABA16A44388F9F90661EBF9480"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Preservation</header><text>The remedy and rights provided under this section are in addition to and do not preclude any remedy for wrongful conversion otherwise available under law to the person claiming relief under this section, including any award for consequential or punitive damages.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H92974AC56B8C4913A5C36C9BED2589"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Equitable relief</header> 
<paragraph id="H80663F60D9A344EA80AE3088541EEC52"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In addition to any other remedy available under law, if a person in military service has reason to believe that another party to a contract has violated or is violating this section, the person in military service may—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8FFCC5D143864DA7A8DEB76127D4088"><enum>(A)</enum><text>bring an action to enjoin the violation in any appropriate United States district court or in any other court of competent jurisdiction; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8D7651A66AC64FA0B9BFA70017242ED5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>bring an action in any appropriate United States district court or in any other court of competent jurisdiction to recover damages equal to three times the amount for which the other party is liable to the person in military service under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2DF8077618884C578563A2B3269F77A1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Attorney fees</header><text>If a person in military service is awarded damages under an action described under paragraph (1), the person shall be awarded, in addition, the costs of the action and reasonable attorney fees, as determined by the court.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H866F063139344F978FBEBA008BA00FE"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For the purposes of this section, the following definitions apply:</text> 
<paragraph id="H19583AC05C594AFCB3576DCA3DE28C63"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Multichannel video programming service</header><text>The term <quote>multichannel video programming service</quote> means video programming service provided by a multichannel video programming distributor, as such term is defined in section 602(13) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/522">47 U.S.C. 522(13)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB11A870073CD42FEAB7900AB2B43CEB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Internet access service</header><text>The term <quote>Internet access service</quote> has the meaning given that term under section 231(e)(4) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/231">47 U.S.C. 231(e)(4)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB1DCD40701E14E56BED9A033942F7B19"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Cellular telephone service</header><text>The term <quote>cellular telephone service</quote> means commercial mobile service, as that term is defined in section 332(d) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/332">47 U.S.C. 332(d)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H388C40636F5843048BA740F1A4EBD009"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Telephone exchange service</header><text>The term <quote>telephone exchange service</quote> has the meaning given that term under section 3 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/153">47 U.S.C. 153</external-xref>). </text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H563B9F2DC5524C43AE5626F97C7C51F1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents in section 1(b) of such Act is amended by striking the item relating to section 308 and inserting the following new items:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H92929B574E06494700E1B647B5FC44EE" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 308. Termination or suspension of service contracts.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 309. Extension of protections to dependents.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H5F8782029A914024A5E5D510203882F"><enum>5.</enum><header>Penalties for violation of interest rate limitation under Servicemembers Civil Relief Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 207 of the Servicemembers Civil Relief Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/50/527">50 U.S.C. App. 527</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsections:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD770E7BF2D4C45B4AEA5077E29E55345" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H74F63FD4B9564DA498916E47C3274669"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whoever knowingly violates subsection (a) shall be fined not more than $5,000 in the case of an individual or $10,000 in the case of an organization.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2C34CA859D40476D9094C298FA19400"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rights of servicemembers</header> 
<paragraph id="HECEC9EBD8CF2480A80F044721FFDCAB7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Equitable relief</header> 
<subparagraph id="H6DE43B34F6A14D60901000C323BF56FE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In addition to any other remedies as are provided under Federal or State law, if a servicemember has reason to believe that a creditor has violated or is violating this section, the servicemember may—</text> 
<clause id="H5C5EFE1BFBED49E58CB951D89CABC39F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>bring an action to enjoin such violation in any appropriate United States district court or in any other court of competent jurisdiction; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H66B66F021A1443F9989E916ECC17C6AD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>bring an action to recover damages equal to three times the amount of the interest charged in violation of this section (plus interest) for which the creditor is liable to the servicemember under this section as a result of the violation.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H46215CAADE00433DBAF9D185F2719D57"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Determination of number of violations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining the number of violations by a creditor for which a penalty is imposed under subsection (e) or subparagraph (A), the court shall count as a single violation each obligation or liability of a servicemember with respect to which—</text> 
<clause id="HE4E4641F1E3D4456A92F55EFC13F0491"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the servicemember properly provided to the creditor written notice and a copy of the military orders calling the servicemember to military service and any orders further extending military service under subsection (b); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0F36640209294515B602F3544B95E2DD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the creditor failed to treat in accordance with subsection (a). </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF7A3C5EC348F40ED8D2B9751F74D2679"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Attorney fees</header><text>If a servicemember is awarded damages under an action described under paragraph (1), the servicemember shall be awarded, in addition, the costs of the action and reasonable attorney fees, as determined by the court.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3B7A4715840F47C9BDCAFF8E00003F05"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Preservation of other remedies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The rights and remedies provided under subsections (e) and (f) are in addition to and do not preclude any other remedy available under law to a person claiming relief under this section, including any award for consequential or punitive damages.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H5C6427ED3BA747ADB2226487ED00D6B1"><enum>6.</enum><header>Guarantee of residency for spouses of military personnel</header> 
<subsection id="H0DE97936ADC8408E002512B878F36769"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Guarantee of residency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 705 of the Servicemembers Civil Relief Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/50/595">50 U.S.C. App. 595</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4E5F6BB6ADE3431CB200F42C539F8E4B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>For</quote> and inserting <quote>(a) For</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8FB83900DD6946EB8D613100611FF5FC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H999639D365444D5D90A8C36704C77D80" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HC7046FD31A5E4A9C8BF3007DEF068DB3"><enum>(b)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of voting for any Federal office (as defined in section 301 of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/431">2 U.S.C. 431</external-xref>)) or a State or local office, a person who is absent from a State because the person is accompanying the person’s spouse who is absent from that same State in compliance with military or naval orders shall not, solely by reason of that absence—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0FC7E68F71B343CBA4B68E00E38254C9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be deemed to have lost a residence or domicile in that State, without regard to whether or not the person intends to return to that State;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H86F2FE1E55A142DB8E14E8F5CDF095A3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be deemed to have acquired a residence or domicile in any other State; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H313A6038686648CDAFBDEC3F2073591"><enum>(3)</enum><text>be deemed to have become a resident in or a resident of any other State.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H732200CB460B41C9B7545F1774F02EE5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header> 
<paragraph id="H632036039E1C44759E48FE3B01E6BD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The heading for such section is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA1DA991F28974D939E360500AEA75593" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC300194F35914AB4BB811DD22576F82C"><enum>705.</enum><header>Guarantee of residency for military personnel and spouses of military personnel</header></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H45A1D545DFEB4D0CBA1CA98150EBE9DB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The item relating to such section in the table of contents in section 1(b) of such Act is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB460B691D20C4A9E91B082EEB3D4ADF8" style="OLC"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 705. Guarantee of residency for military personnel and spouses of military personnel.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H88C5246672174469B1ED1D59A9B400AE"><enum>7.</enum><header>Residence for tax purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 511(a) of the Servicemembers Civil Relief Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/50/571">50 U.S.C. App. 571(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H97407C24A11C448FA3354360FBB3ACEF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>A servicemember</quote> and inserting the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA8740DD7EBD94BFE935BBD08D4CE24F6" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="HC65CB68B0E3549B1B8917D5025E8409C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Servicemember</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A servicemember</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1ACD7C3C7604494BADD3551EDD71B43D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H495E759B085040668D8E1400E309D99E" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H31658F6E80D3447C8BCC18DEFABC2A6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Spouse of servicemember</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A spouse of a servicemember shall neither lose nor acquire a residence or domicile for purposes of taxation with respect to the person, personal property, or income of the spouse by reason of being absent or present in any tax jurisdiction of the United States solely to be with the servicemember in compliance with the servicemember’s military orders if the residence or domicile, as the case may be, is the same for the servicemember and the spouse.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section>
<section id="H67D9BD72C1D84524B94B300079248BF9" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>8.</enum><header>Spouse’s compensation during military service</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 511 of the Servicemembers Civil Relief Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/50/571">50 U.S.C. App. 571(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H1FE220D31C154CB8BECDC7AE9228B819"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking the subsection designation and heading and all that follows through <quote>Compensation</quote> and inserting the following: </text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H074AEE2971ED46049E6B4455D90079E0" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="HA52BFC058F014F6AAE90E06ECEE989"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Military Service and Spouse’s compensation</header>
<paragraph id="H0E40CEB9B5394B3CAFA22759DC1D13C7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Military service compensation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Compensation</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7B6F9E34CE7B472C97EFBAC4D6B773CD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7FF3C1ABD3934DD09430A513FD2DBB80" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="H67E4BB6CFC77439A9603E37DD047B9B4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Spouse’s compensation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Compensation of a spouse of a servicemember shall not be deemed to be income for services performed or from sources within a tax jurisdiction of the United States if, when the compensation is earned, the spouse of the servicemember is not a resident or domiciliary of the jurisdiction and the jurisdiction is the jurisdiction in which the servicemember is serving in compliance with military orders.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20080729" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives July 31, 2008.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 


