<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HDD4939E7B1BF4F3E958F5F942E04A492" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 5554 EH: Justin Bailey Veterans Substance Use Disorders Prevention and Treatment Act of 2008</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form> 
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">110th CONGRESS</congress> <session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 5554</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to expand and improve health care services available to veterans from the Department of Veterans Affairs for substance use disorders, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" style="OLC" id="HDB071DD27B80440489708B2C76EE7B58"> 
<section id="HA786532DD0614F8EA3BB0E23D3B23FF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Justin Bailey Veterans Substance Use Disorders Prevention and Treatment Act of 2008</short-title></quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HE9A5793B6F22489481BA3111AFB65E59"><enum>2.</enum><header>Expansion of Veterans Substance use Disorder Programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (d) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1720A">section 1720A</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H0ED7C4C858A7401AB06DFAF125ED3CA6" style="OLC">
<paragraph id="HD26EA0366B144CF0879F022012E5E758" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H00B365E76B40408897A4AF9C954BC7F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Each plan under paragraph (1) shall ensure that the medical center provides ready access to a full continuum of care for substance use disorders for veterans in need of such care.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9E6695C0325345D8B8E4E1B5A6DF2BB0" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In this paragraph, the term <quote>full continuum of care</quote> includes all of the following care, treatment, and services:</text> 
<clause id="H262CEEE7D75849818F104BA2D6041E9E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Screening for substance use disorder in all settings, including primary care settings.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6EE466C2E1EA4F60B3D18374431EF62"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Detoxification and stabilization services.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFF5357BB781D43A78567D7C1A4E36BA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Intensive outpatient care services.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB72470BC8CB74BD594C19CC776C492CD"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Relapse prevention services.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5FBEEC7C0273485FBEBAD86028C4A6F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Outpatient counseling services.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBD287D2A45DE46BE8887CC1D76FE74E5"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Residential substance use disorder treatment.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFCA227CB1585498795B027E82C37E619"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Pharmacological treatment to reduce cravings, and opioid substitution therapy referred to in paragraph (2).</text></clause> 
<clause id="HEC72667FC7A140ED9458D008F215887"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Coordination with groups providing peer to peer counseling.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H44551DF6CBCC43A8ABDFA5C597AFE0AD"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Short-term, early interventions for substance use disorders, such as motivational counseling, that are readily available and provided in a manner to overcome stigma associated with the provision of such interventions and related care.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6B7684B4641E4078AE7975AAB2902FD6"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Marital and family counseling.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H234059B59B5C4151B551A4B0F0717DC9" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Secretary shall provide for outreach to veterans who served in Operation Enduring Freedom or Operation Iraqi Freedom to increase awareness of the availability of care, treatment, and services from the Department for substance use disorders.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HE0250A79094248289C21986574B696F7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Requirement for allocation of Department resources to ensure availability for all veterans requiring treatment for substance use disorders</header> 
<subsection id="H2A7A8A7EB489418EB168381352910668"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Equitable allocation of funding; annual report</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1720A">Section 1720A</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, as amended by section 2, is further amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H6C6CFA684E784C96BAE1125D671794E6" style="OLC">
<subsection id="H75E5185A23384B4CBCC5CBABD7A42519"><enum>(e)</enum> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1918E022E76B43D5B752908826DFE2A8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall ensure that amounts made available for care, treatment, and services provided under this section are allocated in such a manner that a full continuum of care (as defined in subsection (d)(3)(B)) is available to veterans seeking such care, treatment, or services, without regard to the location of the residence of any such veterans.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H23AAA74D10324EC19DF00094B750C52" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8266245DCF664985A2AD002BE887E783"><enum>(A)</enum><text>In addition to the report required under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1703">section 1703(c)(1)</external-xref> of this title (relating to furnishing of contract care and services under this section), the Secretary shall include in the budget documents which the Secretary submits to Congress for any fiscal year a detailed report on the care, treatment, and services furnished by the Department under this section during the most recently completed fiscal year.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3AF945FE33F345EFB72D3FC127AFACA8" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Each report under subparagraph (A) shall include data on the following for each medical facility of the Department:</text> 
<clause id="HB71FCA20024A4DE29FC828C615792547"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The number of veterans who have been provided care, treatment, or services under this section at the facility for each 1,000 veterans who have received hospital care (if applicable) or medical services at the facility.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF3507ECD64FD4DE1A7EB26C835DC51D7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The number of veterans for whom substance use disorder screening was carried out under subsection (d)(3)(B)(i) at the facility.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H030B22E647384045BAC6B4379505658D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The number of veterans for whom a substance use disorder was identified after a screening was carried out under subsection (d)(3)(B)(i) at the facility.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H865A439245384B55905F271209CDC801"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The number of veterans who were referred by the facility for care, treatment, or services for substance use disorders under this section.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8F59B87535AA4FA1B5BDA47788276898"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The number of veterans who received care, treatment or services at the facility for substance use disorders under this section.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H3ED449914B6E4C53B42CBD5300A43AD"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Availability of the full continuum of care (as defined in subsection (d)(3)(B)) at the facility.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5BC7FBDC530C47CEB521D0283EC2F1B6" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Each report prepared under subparagraph (A) shall be reviewed by the Committee on Care of Severely Chronically Mentally Ill Veterans authorized by <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/7321">section 7321</external-xref> of this title. The Committee shall provide an independent assessment of the care, treatment, and services furnished directly by the Department under this section to veterans. Such assessment shall include a detailed analysis of the availability, the barriers to access (if any), and the quality of such care, treatment, and services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H223BC687B0EE4C92A393A6BECFE9FAAC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective Date</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall apply to fiscal years beginning on or after October 1, 2009.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H4DD7B2212B5C4521B4D48E069D247B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Pilot program for Internet-based substance use disorder treatment for veterans of Operation Iraqi Freedom and Operation Enduring Freedom</header> 
<subsection id="H7C9662BE546E4BCC90AAC77BA5BDD346"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress makes the following findings:</text> 
<paragraph id="HE9AC31C73C39419CA036D9B2BD3FE1A9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Stigma associated with seeking treatment for mental health disorders has been demonstrated to prevent some veterans from seeking such treatment at a medical facility operated by the Department of Defense or the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC86804B23CFF415FA6D64424DC2524FE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>There is a significant incidence among veterans of post-deployment mental health problems, especially among members of a reserve component who return as veterans to civilian life.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDC01A4DA306D47228E4595F94123CD8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Computer-based self-guided training has been demonstrated to be an effective strategy for supplementing the care of psychological conditions.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H217A2A982288470D8659E75526CF8CA0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Younger veterans, especially those who served in Operation Enduring Freedom or Operation Iraqi Freedom, are comfortable with and proficient at computer-based technology.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H74A2A9573D2A4F0EA02BBE61D6513557"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Veterans living in rural areas find access to treatment for substance use disorder limited.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H973CA21E2ACE43FD88AACBE9D2502B00"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Self-assessment and treatment options for substance use disorders through an Internet website may reduce stigma and provides additional access for individuals seeking care and treatment for such disorders.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCF1CC344CD4B473EA351C7684DD9D071"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than October 1, 2009, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall initiate a pilot program to test the feasibility and advisability of providing veterans who seek treatment for substance use disorders access to a computer-based self-assessment, education, and specified treatment program through a secure Internet website operated by the Secretary. Participation in the pilot program is available on a voluntary basis for those veterans who have served in Operation Enduring Freedom or Operation Iraqi Freedom.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H10A3534441364DB6BFA1C7EFFB4E946"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Elements of Pilot Program</header> 
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBAD007F2B67748EBA4BFFCB461EBC40"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In designing and carrying out the pilot program under this section, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall ensure that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAAEEF0D4BD2046690032B1386C089C86"><enum>(A)</enum><text>access to the Internet website and the programs available on the website by a veteran (or family member) does not involuntarily generate an identifiable medical record of that access by that veteran in any medical database maintained by the Department;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8DF16BD3E94145FCA149FE08A34FE900"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Internet website is accessible from remote locations, especially rural areas; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBC987C3B2D9C46559C6671D6873EB442"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Internet website includes a self-assessment tool for substance use disorders, self-guided treatment and educational materials for such disorders, and appropriate information and materials for family members of veterans.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H67DF4C77E0944226A978C71B9D64F3EB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consideration of similar projects</header><text>In designing the pilot program under this section, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall consider similar pilot projects of the Department of Defense for the early diagnosis and treatment of post-traumatic stress disorder and other mental health conditions established under section 741 of the John Warner National Defense Authorization Act of Fiscal Year 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/364">Public Law 109–364</external-xref>; 120 Stat. 2304).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1EE92574041945ACBCF21051E78B597D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Location of pilot program</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out the pilot program through those medical centers of the Department of Veterans Affairs that have established Centers for Excellence for Substance Abuse Treatment and Education or that have established a Substance Abuse Program Evaluation and Research Center.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7DCF2315A73F4F548BF8137BB2FBEC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Contract authority</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs may enter into contracts with qualified entities or organizations to carry out the pilot program required under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFF6BE7440A6F49E999856F97E63433A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duration of pilot program</header><text>The pilot program required by subsection (a) shall be carried out during the two-year period beginning on the date of the commencement of the pilot program.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8D2F0A02C56042039CD2DA1E637B959F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs $1,500,000 for each of fiscal years 2010 and 2011 to carry out the pilot program under this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H58B3FBFE6B7D4A99A889009B5853B754"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than six months after the completion of the pilot program, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on the pilot program, and shall include in that report an assessment of the feasibility and advisability of the pilot program, of any cost savings or other benefits associated with the pilot program, and recommendations for the continuation or expansion of the pilot program.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H81CFD3836DB54A31889579EA596DD3FF" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report on residential mental health care facilities of the Veterans Health Administration</header> 
<subsection id="H0C189AC013ED41D285F2E9D11BE29572"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review and report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than six months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, acting through the Office of the Medical Inspector of the Department of Veterans Affairs, shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HAD12D641F5564FC8A8FF87A5018845FE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct a review of all residential mental health care facilities, including domiciliary facilities, of the Veterans Health Administration; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H964AC191ACF142F299F467FC7FDF0051"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on the review conducted under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF5BA2C2BDD3648B3BE4625F9BD2800AB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements of report</header><text>The report required by subsection (a)(2) shall include the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H987B3287A09C485E9185A472FF00EA24"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of the availability of care in residential mental health care facilities in each Veterans Integrated Service Network (VISN).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA81731E2D35A40929F401F2FAFD08288"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An assessment of the supervision and support provided in the residential mental health care facilities of the Veterans Health Administration.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC2BD5F92A64341EAA0F665577E59B631"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The ratio of staff members at each residential mental health care facility to patients at such facility.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H22599DBEB7EF4898B500D3AE6516C366"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An assessment of the appropriateness of rules and procedures for the prescription and administration of medications to patients in such residential mental health care facilities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFC2398C1FCFB4ABFA4F80061A4F0FF29"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A description of the protocols at each residential mental health care facility for handling missed appointments.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H47A4821F3F9B407FB8A1BAC89DF100A0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any recommendations the Secretary considers appropriate for improvements to such residential mental health care facilities and the care provided in such facilities.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HE0296DF9BA684096A9CBF21F62085BEE"><enum>6.</enum><header>Tribute to Justin Bailey</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act is enacted in tribute to Justin Bailey, who, after returning to the United States from service as a member of the Armed Forces in Operation Iraqi Freedom, died in a domiciliary facility of the Department of Veterans Affairs while receiving care for post-traumatic stress disorder and a substance use disorder.</text></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20080520" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives May 20, 2008.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 


