<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Referred-in-Senate" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HC979ED2CF1FD4EFFBE09E8553FD73666" public-private="public" stage-count="1"> 
<form> 
<distribution-code display="yes">IIB</distribution-code> 
<congress>111th CONGRESS</congress> <session>2d Session</session> 
<legis-num>H. R. 5320</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="yes">IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber> 
<action>
<action-date date="20100802">August 2, 2010</action-date>
<action-desc>Received</action-desc>
</action>
<action>
<action-date date="20100805">August 5, 2010</action-date>
<action-desc>Read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id=""> Committee on Environment and Public Works</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Safe Drinking Water Act to increase assistance for States, water systems, and disadvantaged communities; to encourage good financial and environmental management of water systems; to strengthen the Environmental Protection Agency’s ability to enforce the requirements of the Act; to reduce lead in drinking water; to strengthen the endocrine disruptor screening program; and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H87BF94EB6DC7424DB50211B042328092" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HDD959894CFCF496AA8480EEF8D39516E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents; references</header> 
<subsection id="HE5B7050B91CD490298275B777D4B3E9E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Assistance, Quality, and Affordability Act of 2010</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7CE04F77243049F3B7ECAE9E024B61FF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents of this Act is as follows:</text> 
<toc container-level="legis-body-container" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry idref="HDD959894CFCF496AA8480EEF8D39516E" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents; references.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H1D7394D38A64421FA273EED5F7700314" level="section">Sec. 2. Technical assistance for small public water systems.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H6993392FF2A1441E80883C2620B470B4" level="section">Sec. 3. Prevailing wages.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H98007073E5FB4E1C8E0E67370BAF815F" level="section">Sec. 4. Use of funds.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HE5B94AD5BBB044DBBCA6002DF7C2CC76" level="section">Sec. 5. Requirements for use of American materials.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HE42A373D59734CD3B118B0F5F02EEEB2" level="section">Sec. 6. Data on variances, exemptions, and persistent violations.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H9A716A9E099240348EDD430DC28C3E83" level="section">Sec. 7. Assistance for restructuring.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H6220606C4CBB46CC8073A539FDCECD21" level="section">Sec. 8. Priority and weight of applications.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H8307409EAF884048A552460B8E3A0FB0" level="section">Sec. 9. Disadvantaged communities.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H5235E013BC3945519D97712E57E2402D" level="section">Sec. 10. Administration of State loan funds.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HB04279DC1333489FB5FB8B36611C0992" level="section">Sec. 11. State revolving loan funds for American Samoa, Northern Mariana Islands, Guam, and the Virgin Islands.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HB1C943DCF9C94876AB9BEFBFA093842E" level="section">Sec. 12. Authorization of appropriations.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H8948D06FD8094C2F954D329ABC93C3DE" level="section">Sec. 13. Negotiation of contracts.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HB01052310A00442A8A6BC5A0813EBEAE" level="section">Sec. 14. Affordability of new standards.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HA14F3A9C0DAE48F297C54AB2B9113551" level="section">Sec. 15. Focus on lifecycle costs.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HB5089F80AFE84949AD6F859011A77F46" level="section">Sec. 16. Enforcement.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H18807724E5DE4D84B1A1B5B7E03805D9" level="section">Sec. 17. Reducing lead in drinking water.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H5CCF21B8FB514A99B80FC7D50F5079A7" level="section">Sec. 18. Endocrine disruptor screening program.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HD02FD4A7375D4D79B3B851DFE5B2B168" level="section">Sec. 19. Presence of pharmaceuticals and personal care products in sources of drinking water.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HCB0DA84448234DE38078B254E44225AC" level="section">Sec. 20. Electronic reporting of compliance monitoring data to the Administrator.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H72810130F9194F0C843DB47BCC77730D" level="section">Sec. 21. Budgetary effects.</toc-entry></toc></subsection> 
<subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB6F566A04F9C4EDC84D8DEA0CEC49501"><enum>(c)</enum><header>References</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise specified, whenever in this Act an amendment is expressed in terms of an amendment to a section or other provision, the reference shall be considered to be made to a section or other provision of the Safe Drinking Water Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300f">42 U.S.C. 300f et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H1D7394D38A64421FA273EED5F7700314" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Technical assistance for small public water systems</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (e) of section 1442 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-1">42 U.S.C. 300j–1(e)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA32E7B1428E843B9ADE3D0A32119FFD0" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HE5E7D07F24FB42C682F60019530851E8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Technical Assistance</header> 
<paragraph id="H527AB0862A8E48978287994B60D15CC9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, directly or through grants or cooperative agreements with nonprofit organizations, may provide technical assistance to small public water systems to enable such systems to achieve and maintain compliance with applicable national primary drinking water regulations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF5F5314A4A63469CB5ED28D4F3C7EB0D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Types of assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Technical assistance under paragraph (1) may include onsite technical assistance and compliance assistance; circuit-rider and multi-State regional technical assistance programs; training; assistance with implementing source water protection programs; assistance with increasing water or energy efficiency; assistance with designing, installing, or operating sustainable energy infrastructure to produce or capture sustainable energy on site or through water transport; assistance with developing technical, financial, and managerial capacity; assistance with long-term infrastructure planning; assistance with applying for funds from a State loan fund under section 1452; and assistance with implementation of monitoring plans, rules, regulations, and water security enhancements.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D4399E1CD3C46BB9FB4A60335F18D70"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In providing assistance under this subsection, the Administrator shall give priority to assistance that will promote compliance with national primary drinking water standards, public health protection, and long-term sustainability of small public water systems. In awarding grants and cooperative assistance under paragraph (1) to nonprofit organizations, the Administrator shall (subject to the preceding sentence) give greater weight to nonprofit organizations that, as determined by the Administrator, are most qualified and most effective and that, as determined by the Administrator using information where available, are providing the types of technical assistance that are preferred by small public water systems.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9278216BAE514C0994E90BA2F25180E5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Competitive procedures</header><text>It is the presumption of Congress that any award of assistance under this subsection will be awarded using competitive procedures based on merit. If assistance is awarded under this subsection using procedures other than competitive procedures, the Administrator shall submit to the Congress, within 90 days of the award decision, a report explaining why competitive procedures were not used.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBFDD55C8EF4D4C19BB5FE713FE8BD319"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Funding</header> 
<subparagraph id="H4752320A9BAE43D1BFD9C2846B2AD01F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this subsection $20,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2011 through 2015.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H00566D6C929844D8A32767E305A67536"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Prohibition on earmarks</header><text>No funds made available under this subsection may be used to carry out a provision or report language included primarily at the request of a Member, Delegate, Resident Commissioner, or Senator providing, authorizing, or recommending a specific amount of discretionary budget authority, credit authority, or other spending authority for a contract, loan, loan guarantee, grant, loan authority, or other expenditure with or to an entity, or targeted to a specific State, locality, or congressional district, other than through a statutory or administrative formula-driven or competitive award process.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE27CD66F615F49078BDADC28E78C7E87"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Lobbying expenses</header><text>No portion of any State loan fund established under section 1452 and no portion of any funds made available under this subsection may be used for lobbying expenses.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1F5410DE45DC4324BE8F1C5063C0D4B8"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Indian tribes</header><text>Of the total amount made available under this section for each fiscal year, 3 percent shall be used for technical assistance to public water systems owned or operated by Indian Tribes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H6993392FF2A1441E80883C2620B470B4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prevailing wages</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (e) of section 1450 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-9">42 U.S.C. 300j–9</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7AE27319223D4C8284813707B5744203" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HAFD881B112FF45D397B77CBD5E82260E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Labor Standards</header> 
<paragraph id="HDD827796519A44268F38CBE619B8A7C8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall take such action as the Administrator determines to be necessary to ensure that each laborer and mechanic employed by a contractor or subcontractor in connection with a construction project financed, in whole or in part, by a grant, loan, loan guarantee, refinancing, or any other form of financial assistance provided under this title (including assistance provided by a State loan fund established under section 1452) is paid wages at a rate of not less than the wages prevailing for the same type of work on similar construction in the immediate locality, as determined by the Secretary of Labor in accordance with subchapter IV of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/40/31">chapter 31</external-xref> of title 40, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5DD2998B6CCE45E69603F7E188C6E244"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority of Secretary of Labor</header><text>With respect to the labor standards specified in this subsection, the Secretary of Labor shall have the authority and functions established in Reorganization Plan Numbered 14 of 1950 (5 U.S.C. App.) and <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/40/3145">section 3145</external-xref> of title 40, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H98007073E5FB4E1C8E0E67370BAF815F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1452(a)(2) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9811D15D7DC74565A3779D06102EB928"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Except as otherwise</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5F07CA16DE2C4CC1A6E210ACA04FA59F" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H4B9A0BAE46FA49AC84FD6C6F96D522F6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H28D055F029774F4EB14657A824953103"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>, or as a source of reserve and security for leveraged loans, the proceeds of which are deposited in a State loan fund established under paragraph (1),</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAD0AEE74EF254093827B3DCB16A407C2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Financial assistance under this section</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H760CB60DBED64B78AF744ED6A8D90B86" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H42E8C566C2634556973D9DDB93674CF0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Permissible expenditures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Financial assistance under this section</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4B038A2EEC2E489CAD6006825614E289"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The funds may also be used</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0D449820E4F346A9BCD636965FF3678C" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H777E64642B5846C8B0856112217C66AE"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Certain loans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Financial assistance under this section may also be used</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H37FBD9EED5194ADAAECFB3AE93265011"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The funds shall not be used</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAA61F12AA6544B2BB1E7FE8FD68902FD" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H5B22FBC921E5462280EE1B64621CF3F4"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Financial assistance under this section shall not be used</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF4A05A20459A4CE290E818981AAD3DA3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Of the amount credited</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC080EBB70BAB43FAB6798D062594A074" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H923469D3439E49A1A6E1BC4CE5B4B3FB"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Set-aside</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the amount credited</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H73AB51614BB146C1B4007932A25AAA27"><enum>(7)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B) (as designated by paragraph (3)) by striking <quote>(not</quote> and inserting <quote>(including expenditures for planning, design, siting, and associated preconstruction activities, for replacing or rehabilitating aging treatment, storage, or distribution facilities of public water systems, or for producing or capturing sustainable energy on site or through the transportation of water through the public water system, but not</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HC152CD45DF524F4BB49C9C30DBC76FA0"><enum>(8)</enum><text>by inserting after such subparagraph (B) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H4D6B437A154344C2801374734C221C67" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H6C6358E3214E4E03B7A396749E867E12"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Sale of bonds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a State issues revenue or general obligation bonds to provide all or part of the State contribution required by subsection (e), and the proceeds of the sale of such bonds will be deposited into the State loan fund—</text> 
<clause id="H5568987F28004A938F222220030C82EA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>financial assistance made available under this section may be used by the State as security for payment of the principal and interest on such bonds; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF64C8E7A55CA413287BBB8BBFFD81C3E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>interest earnings of the State loan fund may be used by the State as revenue for payment of the principal and interest on such bonds.</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">Except as provided in this subparagraph, neither financial assistance made available under this section nor interest earnings of a State loan fund may be used by a State as security for or as revenue for the payment of the principal or interest on any bond, including any tax exempt or tax credit bond issued by a State or any political subdivision thereof.</continuation-text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE5B94AD5BBB044DBBCA6002DF7C2CC76" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>5.</enum><header>Requirements for use of American materials</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1452(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1D07BBFE1FBB4AFA8FC4E21AEF1FF63E" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H3D9418FA272F4AFB86A3C0545B9137AA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Requirements for use of American materials</header> 
<subparagraph id="H3876A08E629C404DA482388D5BAD1E6C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, none of the funds made available by a State loan fund as authorized under this section may be used for a project for the construction, alteration, maintenance, or repair of a public water system unless the steel, iron, and manufactured goods used in such project are produced in the United States.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H606F09B86577415B9CD146E9A968C1C7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply in any case in which the Administrator (in consultation with the Governor of the State) finds that—</text> 
<clause id="H03A12983922E4546A8706D94CF8FC86E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>applying subparagraph (A) would be inconsistent with the public interest;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H85C0C10E9A25423C9F6F4B1664036EEA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>steel, iron, and manufactured goods are not produced in the United States in sufficient and reasonably available quantities and of a satisfactory quality; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H01D3CEF1FB1546018A5ED1C0DCD9DDD7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>inclusion of steel, iron, and manufactured goods produced in the United States will increase the cost of the overall project by more than 25 percent.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC175F16799124264AA7A44E3484CF88A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Public notification and written justification for waiver</header><text>If the Administrator determines that it is necessary to waive the application of subparagraph (A) based on a finding under subparagraph (B), the Administrator shall—</text> 
<clause id="HE711D46BA950416F8B2F1630DDCED5AD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>not less than 15 days prior to waiving application of subparagraph (A), provide public notice and the opportunity to comment on the Administrator’s intent to issue such waiver; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H580D50BC7DA94E76B7583D56C5B21423"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>upon issuing such waiver, publish in the Federal Register a detailed written justification as to why the provision is being waived.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEB0AF1EB9D8E4A448349F55B31857146"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Consistency with international agreements</header><text>This paragraph shall be applied in a manner consistent with United States obligations under international agreements.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HE42A373D59734CD3B118B0F5F02EEEB2"><enum>6.</enum><header>Data on variances, exemptions, and persistent violations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1452(b)(2) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1395D5E378344CFE9A785251565410A8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFD308108556849D59682542A61F98ECD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H24503B365FB448568D95F4C20DED89BE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB07850DE93E24451BB860FC29F9DFBF2" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H5C539DD4A5124F29BE4E58264ECDD920"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a list of all water systems within the State that have in effect an exemption or variance for any national primary drinking water regulation or that are in persistent violation of the requirements for any maximum contaminant level or treatment technique under a national primary drinking water regulation, including identification of—</text> 
<clause id="HA546359843524D8C887F18D781D5D811"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the national primary drinking water regulation in question for each such exemption, variance, or violation; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H50ACE0C17C6744A8AAB5C8A144B836D8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the date on which the exemption or variance came into effect or the violation began.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H9A716A9E099240348EDD430DC28C3E83"><enum>7.</enum><header>Assistance for restructuring</header> 
<subsection id="H5D0B7F1582E74281BE0BEC637B860D9B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1401 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300f">42 U.S.C. 300f</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB5E2D8B8EE1E4808A3FF7F31E5A7709B" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="HFD7D13BFC65B433F9BC0F385E2F86FB5"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Restructuring</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>restructuring</term> means changes in operations (including ownership, management, cooperative partnerships, joint purchasing arrangements, consolidation, and alternative water supply).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HC70AC73D03D2461F98AB97BACD82AF19"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Restructuring</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Clause (ii) of section 1452(a)(3)(B) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12(a)(3)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>changes in operations (including ownership, management, accounting, rates, maintenance, consolidation, alternative water supply, or other procedures)</quote> and inserting <quote>restructuring</quote>.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H6220606C4CBB46CC8073A539FDCECD21"><enum>8.</enum><header>Priority and weight of applications</header> 
<subsection id="H0D6D120A8DE84A6B88E5857F2B5EC9F6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1452(b)(3) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12(b)(3)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H793C8825599248DFA37E3266F6579950"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1328A383A496424D9F60EAA465D47AB0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC8744FCA4A814537820AF3DB78782219"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2299DAACE3A1427286E36705414D5F97"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H56ABECE73CDD41F1BA99B0CA80CB7C19" style="OLC"> 
<clause id="H645DC4CEE8F643D0A4BA1672DA706332"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improve the ability of systems to protect human health and comply with the requirements of this title affordably in the future.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA4BD0FA29CCC44F084FF328DAA3219D6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (B) as subparagraph (D);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H4712FDCFA71F4348B37EFAEB60C787C9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (A) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HD58B6795BED94C89BC949AB4F46D7B84" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HD506092131EF41058CB9D4B868AD5C1A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Affordability of new standards</header><text>For any year in which enforcement begins for a new national primary drinking water standard, each State that has entered into a capitalization agreement pursuant to this section shall evaluate whether capital improvements required to meet the standard are affordable for disadvantaged communities in the State. If the State finds that such capital improvements do not meet affordability criteria for disadvantaged communities in the State, the State’s intended use plan shall provide that priority for the use of funds for such year be given to public water systems affected by the standard and serving disadvantaged communities.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HFEA25832A87647C1BFC7DEFEA4F3D4B8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Weight given to applications</header><text>After determining priority under subparagraphs (A) and (B), an intended use plan shall provide that the State will give greater weight to an application for assistance if the application contains—</text> 
<clause commented="no" id="HDA8AAF8E924F4B9F97EECC74AFF9986C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a description of measures undertaken by the system to improve the management and financial stability of the system, which may include—</text> 
<subclause commented="no" id="H3AE5A74FCAEB48708827573A09DA21A2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an inventory of assets, including a description of the condition of the assets;</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" id="HB8E6C546B45748558FDBF285E8EFDC07"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a schedule for replacement of assets;</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" id="HD83E1A29520D49FAACCF79BAFF1E563F"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an audit of water losses;</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" id="H0ACCB9C366DD45FDB934FED3C7D4BE12"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>a financing plan that factors in all lifecycle costs indicating sources of revenue from ratepayers, grants, bonds, other loans, and other sources to meet the costs; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" id="HABAC465159864E4584B4DC3F0675D457"><enum>(V)</enum><text>a review of options for restructuring;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H03CED9BBC7904A37883762F7D07430AC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a demonstration of consistency with State, regional, and municipal watershed plans;</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H2BDCD82AF2904E62BAE345C57EF1E2A2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a water conservation plan consistent with guidelines developed for such plans by the Administrator under section 1455(a); and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H7C612930F4A14B069DADC1E209DD5C1A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a description of measures undertaken by the system to improve the efficiency of the system or reduce the system’s environmental impact, which may include—</text> 
<subclause commented="no" id="H4D50D435DAE245F2A6211258A80ED355"><enum>(I)</enum><text>water efficiency or conservation, including the rehabilitation or replacement of existing leaking pipes;</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" id="H7F3E220F5E5F4D96A989745BF84E12FD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>use of reclaimed water;</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" id="HB8242FE8583343779F224A4DB5690951"><enum>(III)</enum><text>actions to increase energy efficiency;</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" id="HCFCAACB94E424EF0BD21EF21A0503136"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>actions to generate or capture sustainable energy on site or through the transportation of water through the system;</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" id="H8944BEC527C14BB0A0F6A4D6FBC1B12C"><enum>(V)</enum><text>actions to protect source water;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H9D425F1E82414D4DA5932063948AEAB0"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>actions to mitigate or prevent corrosion, including design, selection of materials, selection of coating, and cathodic protection; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" id="H3B7DAC93E90F4C89B7CC4DCF6D4E2E4A"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>actions to reduce disinfection byproducts.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2F886FD84C074515B7FA91C795F3F2FA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D) (as redesignated by paragraph (2)) by striking <quote>periodically</quote> and inserting <quote>at least biennially</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H50D56CFEEDA64B91B6F27EEF85CD7F75"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1452 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HEB6F027BBACD49B081FB47C5EF9EEACF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (r) as subsection (s); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDA6F1A62D85B469592ED7D317C72110F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (q) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8167A1E9B2F6429F967BCF691CF5AC64" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HF5187EF767D9484ABACB72639AC46540"><enum>(r)</enum><header>Small system guidance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may provide guidance and, as appropriate, tools, methodologies, or computer software, to assist small systems in undertaking measures to improve the management, financial stability, and efficiency of the system or reduce the system’s environmental impact.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H8307409EAF884048A552460B8E3A0FB0"><enum>9.</enum><header>Disadvantaged communities</header> 
<subsection id="HE6FF237358E94B2288CB288E1C2D59E5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Assistance To increase compliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1452(b)(3) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12(b)(3)</external-xref>), as amended, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H869B9CC21A4B4443B5FED2F471F45E7D" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H0F6BE81EBFFC4FEDBDB30AC06B348407"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Assistance to increase compliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State’s intended use plan shall provide that, of the funds received by the State through a capitalization grant under this section for a fiscal year, the State will, to the extent that there are sufficient eligible project applications, reserve not less than 6 percent to be spent on assistance under subsection (d) to public water systems included in the State’s most recent list under paragraph (2)(D).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC2647199FC5545F0933CD0AE5075B313"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Assistance for disadvantaged communities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1452(d) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12(d)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7C1F02227F6E46BFBDEEB6D0D4ACAFCF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1), by adding at the end the following: <quote>Such additional subsidization shall directly and primarily benefit the disadvantaged community.</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA5060E00293646058F9A845D1F157523"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (3), by inserting <quote>, or portion of a service area,</quote> after <quote>service area</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD679A82EFE6642D9AA66ABD5BA0E96BB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Affordability criteria</header><text>Section 1452(d)(3) is amended by adding at the end:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H22AEE4EBC1DF4082ACA23F4EE026BCF4" style="OLC"><text>Each State that has entered into a capitalization agreement pursuant to this section shall, in establishing affordability criteria, consider, solicit public comment on, and include as appropriate—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7D0FC51A30684E8F8946A05C5F261A43"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the methods or criteria that the State will use to identify disadvantaged communities;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBE981B645E7942B390585B38E6A4EDDA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of the institutional, regulatory, financial, tax, or legal factors at the Federal, State, or local level that affect identified affordability criteria; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCAF2B6D501A641029F54A8F21DD3CE94"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of how the State will use the authorities and resources under this subsection to assist communities meeting the identified criteria.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H5235E013BC3945519D97712E57E2402D"><enum>10.</enum><header>Administration of State loan funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1452(g) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12(g)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4711B4B4DCE54268AFE69B95564C1905"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H84F8C4DB68314D6C80214FFB96F778EE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the first sentence, by striking <quote>up to 4 percent of the funds allotted to the State under this section</quote> and inserting <quote>, for each fiscal year, an amount that does not exceed the sum of the amount of any fees collected by the State for use in covering reasonable costs of administration of programs under this section, regardless of the source, and an amount equal to the greatest of $400,000, <fraction>1/5</fraction> of one percent of the current valuation of the State loan fund, or 6 percent of all grant awards to the State loan fund under this section for the fiscal year,</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H77CA6C4A187D44E0B83CB967AEBF780B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>1419,</quote> and all that follows through <quote>1993.</quote> and inserting <quote>1419.</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H242F56B3F20943FAB926B297944CC0FA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in the matter following subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>2 percent</quote> and inserting <quote>4 percent</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5CF038A461E3475C958A511E7592EF6C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF40ADA97E8554D148F21D78BFB12A12D" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="HF23FF0BC76C047FC9EDF902E8B091E77"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Transfer of funds</header> 
<subparagraph id="HBD72423E62E84FCC82039CD813A69DDE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Governor of a State may—</text> 
<clause id="H66503B0E18064F9E9C445777E2B75CAD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>reserve for any fiscal year not more than the lesser of—</text> 
<subclause id="HB22A916653DD4C1BBCBFF98BA52FE4F6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>33 percent of a capitalization grant made under this section; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HCDEC90696B9D449196699218BCDDF90A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>33 percent of a capitalization grant made under section 601 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H938632DC848B4CA1A82087E9832BDB43"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>add the funds so reserved to any funds provided to the State under this section or section 601 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H08C9C7EB4AE84987BE6F27EB2AF483F6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>State matching funds</header><text>Funds reserved under this paragraph shall not be considered for purposes of calculating the amount of a State contribution required by subsection (e) of this section or section 602(b) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB04279DC1333489FB5FB8B36611C0992" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>11.</enum><header>State revolving loan funds for American Samoa, Northern Mariana Islands, Guam, and the Virgin Islands</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1452(j) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12(j)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>0.33 percent</quote> and inserting <quote>1 percent</quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HB1C943DCF9C94876AB9BEFBFA093842E"><enum>12.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (m) of section 1452 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H3704E5AB1FF249128B97E8A8BE9A8A94" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H6AC13E5EC5864C09AE3F7D61A4FC19D5"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header> 
<paragraph id="HD1CD81A17FA14A7D8408F20B477D7B4D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H116FDB909D2443E2A587C1757F4B8966"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$1,400,000,000 for fiscal year 2011;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H640C67D82BE44D4A9EDE0E26494D6E38"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$1,600,000,000 for fiscal year 2012; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H54A086F89D5240BBBA98D68967B7767F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>$1,800,000,000 for fiscal year 2013.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE1C63A30F9D4410D9BB598139BF638BB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>Amounts made available pursuant to this subsection shall remain available until expended.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD3A0109492C84187AB5EA1F675CF05AD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reservation for needs surveys</header><text>Of the amount made available under paragraph (1) to carry out this section for a fiscal year, the Administrator may reserve not more than $1,000,000 per year to pay the costs of conducting needs surveys under subsection (h).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H8948D06FD8094C2F954D329ABC93C3DE"><enum>13.</enum><header>Negotiation of contracts</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1452 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12</external-xref>), as amended, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HA99D8E8B4226488CBD36749D70F320C3" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HBC5B7E0C1E7E48AB8A9FE290012FD348"><enum>(t)</enum><header>Negotiation of Contracts</header><text>For community water systems serving communities with populations of more than 10,000 individuals, a contract to be carried out using funds made available through a capitalization grant under this section for program management, construction management, feasibility studies, preliminary engineering, design, engineering, surveying, mapping, or architectural or related services shall be negotiated in the same manner as—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7A6C13DF39974E24B93D5DD74BEF1130"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a contract for architectural and engineering services is negotiated under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/40/11">chapter 11</external-xref> of title 40, United States Code; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE06D2C44D5A2488287C80AAC995EA345"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a contract subject to an equivalent State or local qualifications-based requirement (as determined by the Governor of the State).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HB01052310A00442A8A6BC5A0813EBEAE"><enum>14.</enum><header>Affordability of new standards</header> 
<subsection id="H2FB67DA12D314AB49780FF56FDD0090D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Treatment technologies for small public water systems</header><text>Clause (ii) of section 1412(b)(4)(E) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300g-1">42 U.S.C. 300g–1(b)(4)(E)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>If no technology, treatment technique, or other means is included in a list under this subparagraph for a category of small public water systems, the Administrator shall periodically review the list and supplement it when new technology becomes available.</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H750F6633CA5E48BBB4E91DD5A7CBC424"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Assistance for disadvantaged communities</header> 
<paragraph id="H7310ECBA900844B0B7A76722032B8FB8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subparagraph (E) of section 1452(a)(1) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H503AD648DCD04548AA8BBE8DDCB21953"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>except that the Administrator may reserve</quote> and inserting</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H08B3D6CFEDEC4FDD81701104B6B5AC0D" style="OLC"><text>except that—</text> 
<clause id="H8EBC88081B6F4F82B4A668482BBE180A"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in any year in which enforcement of a new national primary drinking water standard begins, the Administrator may use the remaining amount to make grants to States whose public water systems are disproportionately affected by the new standard for the provision of assistance under subsection (d) to such public water systems;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2DE808C9372C47FB9C9C0F00D7C8C088"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Administrator may reserve</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1CE921BF571D407CA2A6A4F17A137D2C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and none of the funds reallotted</quote> and inserting</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H91487C8F881D4483841966CB2C758E20" style="OLC"><text>; and</text> 
<clause id="H1D375ED1BABB486182A91AA623854DFF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">none of the funds reallotted</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4D3F92C6F85C4278B5FD068726B54A91"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elimination of certain provisions</header> 
<subparagraph id="H5913C46AA0F54CBCACB16A498677122D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1412(b) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300g-1">42 U.S.C. 300g–1(b)</external-xref>) is amended by striking paragraph (15).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4276DF1CE84B4385803BB7E5B729077D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1415 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300g-4">42 U.S.C. 300g–4</external-xref>) is amended by striking subsection (e).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H644FB2821FFB437B9001619630ED8BF9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Subparagraph (B) of section 1414(c)(1) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300g-3">42 U.S.C. 300g–3(c)(1)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>(a)(2), or (e)</quote> and inserting <quote>or (a)(2)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HA14F3A9C0DAE48F297C54AB2B9113551"><enum>15.</enum><header>Focus on lifecycle costs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1412(b)(4) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300g-1">42 U.S.C. 300g–1(b)(4)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H154ADB5FEB4344CABBE3696206A5402D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>taking cost into consideration</quote> and inserting <quote>taking lifecycle costs, including maintenance, replacement, and avoided costs, into consideration</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H226A238B517048E6AE211DC4A0F6E3E8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the matter preceding subclause (I) in subparagraph (E)(ii), by inserting <quote>taking lifecycle costs, including maintenance, replacement, and avoided costs, into consideration,</quote> after <quote>as determined by the Administrator in consultation with the States,</quote>.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HB5089F80AFE84949AD6F859011A77F46"><enum>16.</enum><header>Enforcement</header> 
<subsection id="H5A7D2C6E4CD04A1E804E388C5446640E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Advice and technical assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1414 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300g-3">42 U.S.C. 300g–3</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA21713D3F03942B8AAC47216D4A00A50"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the matter following clause (ii) in subsection (a)(1)(A), by striking <quote>and provide such advice and technical assistance to such State and public water system as may be appropriate to bring the system into compliance with the requirement by the earliest feasible time</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HABA1FEE38A9E4D658F55D4683E45019A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1), by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF0158FF37DCD44E9B978A74A55392F07" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="HE77D17906F98477A8142827410A31D47" indent="up2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At any time after providing notice of a violation to a State and public water system under subparagraph (A), the Administrator may provide such advice and technical assistance to such State and public water system as may be appropriate to bring the system into compliance with the requirement by the earliest feasible time. In deciding whether the provision of advice or technical assistance is appropriate, the Administrator may consider the potential for the violation to result in serious adverse effects to human health, whether the violation has occurred continuously or frequently, and the effectiveness of past technical assistance efforts.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H26DA9B071228457186E673ED14162934"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional inspections</header> 
<paragraph id="H753F0F6829F5459CA0F57ECFAAA467F5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1414 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300g-3">42 U.S.C. 300g–3</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8B5F455E1A5546DEB5D5CEC6DF8D26D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (d) through (i) as subsections (e) through (j), respectively; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H85F5D070AA0E4C4191BB76D5C8C56C74"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (c) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H67D930B7953E4046A9A2074262D0C828" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H35D0E7DA2782418BAA31D8D8031C458A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Additional inspections following violations</header> 
<paragraph id="H15CD92FB49F548ACBC52212450CD34C1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall, by regulation, and after consultation with the States, prescribe the number, frequency, and type of additional inspections to follow any violation requiring notice under subsection (c). Regulations under this subsection shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA127E0AAD142421D8ABD01DDF8745C60"><enum>(A)</enum><text>take into account—</text> 
<clause id="H6A24FED359B34509A86A4CCB5D882BFC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>differences between violations that are intermittent or infrequent and violations that are continuous or frequent;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE0C3E46D928A45538636746A7F37C1D5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the seriousness of any potential adverse health effects that may be involved; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5D8265B4431B421EB9F51BC5E20D9333"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number and severity of past violations by the public water system; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H91D2742B2BE84C05813EF340B818C9EC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">specify procedures for inspections following a violation by a public water system that has the potential to have serious adverse effects on human health as a result of short-term exposure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H785BBEDC60E048E29DBDCD9D462956BE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State primary enforcement responsibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection shall be construed or applied to modify the requirements of section 1413.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H925548A3123743A3B5B3B87E5721A4C0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header> 
<subparagraph id="HD03557494CFC477CB3393B6CD02DA9CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsections (a)(1)(B), (a)(2)(A), and (b) of section 1414 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300g-3">42 U.S.C. 300g–3</external-xref>) are amended by striking <quote>subsection (g)</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>subsection (h)</quote>.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0CAC992735184644AA6DF77BC861C5A8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Section 1448(a) is amended by striking <quote>1414(g)(3)(B)</quote> and inserting <quote>1414(h)(3)(B)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H18807724E5DE4D84B1A1B5B7E03805D9"><enum>17.</enum><header>Reducing lead in drinking water</header> 
<subsection id="H2A9D6435596D4FE9AC838F78C659A101"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1417 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300g-6">42 U.S.C. 300g–6</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HCBF1F1AD54054376B624C2F0E04BB238"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by adding at the end of subsection (a) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9D62970ED9304DC282E4A10C1A0D4DCF" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H4A15CF2CB5CE406A893A96AD77632748"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Exemptions</header><text>The prohibitions in paragraphs (1) and (3) shall not apply to—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H2B1FFD0F229C46A1A75F75177C433C46"><enum>(A)</enum><text>pipes, pipe fittings, plumbing fittings, or fixtures, including backflow preventers, that are used exclusively for nonpotable services such as manufacturing, industrial processing, irrigation, outdoor watering, or any other uses where the water is not anticipated to be used for human consumption; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HFD656A1DF137476B82B2C583B673DD03"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">toilets, bidets, urinals, fill valves, flushometer valves, tub fillers, shower valves, service saddles, or water distribution main gate valves that are 2 inches in diameter or larger.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H110339035D034E6D8439C1D76863C4A0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by amending subsection (d) to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H2BBBFA1692364AFB801645C84437730A" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HA43061B23B954507ABEF99E97A0C0FA3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definition of lead free</header> 
<paragraph id="H528E288A6F1841A0845B502B17E32EC9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the purposes of this section, the term <term>lead free</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H55ED073CA3D74FB7B0FE3E306E425ED1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not containing more than 0.2 percent lead when used with respect to solder and flux; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H57B1369B4E884ACA976B0D87385DDC7F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not more than a weighted average of 0.25 percent lead when used with respect to the wetted surfaces of pipes, pipe fittings, plumbing fittings, and fixtures.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB355FF6ACF854FB09593D26763BA545A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Calculation</header><text>The weighted average lead content of a pipe, pipe fitting, plumbing fitting, or fixture shall be calculated by using the following formula: For each wetted component, the percentage of lead in the component shall be multiplied by the ratio of the wetted surface area of that component to the total wetted surface area of the entire product to arrive at the weighted percentage of lead of the component. The weighted percentage of lead of each wetted component shall be added together, and the sum of these weighted percentages shall constitute the weighted average lead content of the product. The lead content of the material used to produce wetted components shall be used to determine compliance with paragraph (1)(B). For lead content of materials that are provided as a range, the maximum content of the range shall be used.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H430BCBAC42C24821AC6C14393ECBC3DF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provisions of subsections (a)(4) and (d) of section 1417 of the Safe Drinking Water Act, as added by this section, apply beginning on the day that is 36 months after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H5CCF21B8FB514A99B80FC7D50F5079A7"><enum>18.</enum><header>Endocrine disruptor screening program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1457 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-17">42 U.S.C. 300j–17</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H45341BEC1FBF4F8D825F52ADA831BD5D" style="traditional"> 
<section id="H1FB5C3EC9ED94C37A3FA58EC26FF4229"><enum>1457.</enum><header>Endocrine disruptor screening program</header> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H6314683B74C445B5AF9A1B8BD7FB705A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Testing of substances</header> 
<paragraph id="H51699AB828A742FFA7BC15ED9B6F29ED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the screening program under section 408(p) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, the Administrator shall provide for the testing of substances described in paragraph (2) in addition to the substances described in section 408(p)(3) of such Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H31656CC8D3D0465CBCBCE0B02F7A28A0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered substances</header><text>A substance is subject to testing pursuant to paragraph (1) if—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5923035BAE3648D9B7C3D53AA43F8FF9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the substance may be found in sources of drinking water; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6B86875A711D461E88A30044EB7C2FD4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Administrator determines that a substantial population may be exposed to such substance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H836E49D6761A4B35A7C6EACA8E790714"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Substances already subject to testing</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (2), a substance is not subject to testing pursuant to paragraph (1) if—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H27F1B215F8C2453D941BB801C927AE67"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the substance is already subject to evaluation determined by the Administrator to be equivalent to testing pursuant to paragraph (1); or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA8814B7691A544DE99B07F2A6F5F330E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Administrator has already determined the effect of the substance on the endocrine system.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H65CB27971B874AD88E38DC11541D2B2B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Substances derived from degradation or metabolism of another substance</header><text>If a substance subject to testing pursuant to paragraph (1) (in this paragraph referred to as the <quote>covered substance</quote>) is derived from the degradation or metabolism of another substance, or is used in or generated by the manufacture of another substance, the Administrator shall provide for such testing of the covered substance by the importer or manufacturer of the other substance.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCF3A2D1B6D234BA2B9110F907D76CEAD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Identification and testing of endocrine disrupting substances that may be in drinking water</header> 
<paragraph id="HD49E0352E4D645169B72ECABE56039F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Identification</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Assistance, Quality, and Affordability Act of 2010</short-title>, after opportunity for comment, the Administrator shall publish—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H245731F631514E9386FECAB6B7946171"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a list of no fewer than 100 substances for testing pursuant to subsection (a)(1) (in accordance with the schedule specified in paragraph (3)); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HACA9B749AEB24F53A8F418900B15FBC3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a plan for the identification of additional substances for testing pursuant to subsection (a)(1), and a schedule for issuing test orders for all such additional substances by not later than 10 years after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Assistance, Quality, and Affordability Act of 2010</short-title>, with the goal of testing, at a minimum and consistent with subsection (a), all substances that have been placed on the Drinking Water Preliminary Contaminant Candidate List published pursuant to section 1412(b)(1)(B)(i).</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">In publishing the plan and schedule required by subparagraph (B), the Administrator shall obtain advice and direction from the Science Advisory Board.</continuation-text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H18F2CD8EC0C84F74BC618C217BF45F17"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prioritization; considerations</header><text>In selecting substances for listing under paragraph (1)(A) or identification pursuant to the plan under paragraph (1)(B), the Administrator—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H75BDDBD804EF4A1B9A0F0BAFB45D7B6B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall prioritize the selection of substances that pose the greatest public health concern, using the best available science and taking into consideration (among other factors of public health concern) the effect of such substances on subgroups that comprise a meaningful portion of the general population (such as infants, children, pregnant women, the elderly, individuals with a history of serious illness, and other subpopulations) that are identifiable as being at greater risk of adverse health effects due to exposure to substances in drinking water; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3E9842A9C787423A99E5C6D75649B1BD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall take into consideration—</text> 
<clause id="HD8D5F276BBEC490480FCEC0345E4B360"><enum>(i)</enum><text>available information on the extent of potential public exposures to the substances through drinking water; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB6D061B3FE0B4BEF931794D2B68EA933"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Drinking Water Preliminary Contaminant Candidate List published pursuant to section 1412(b)(1)(B)(i).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H49FFEE305CBA41D793EA46B858B80501"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Schedule</header><text>After publication of the list under paragraph (1)(A), the Administrator shall issue test orders for—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H312C83721B2E4A8393E888F18724B599"><enum>(A)</enum><text>at least 25 substances on the list by the end of each year during the 4-year period following the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Assistance, Quality, and Affordability Act of 2010</short-title>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD316AF70A3D24EE880B7DD62A58265DB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>all substances on the list by the end of such 4-year period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE93A15E65DE448F891A7E4721A6F5709"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Testing protocol process</header> 
<paragraph id="HD0C3E18357C5462BAE617A459CF93223"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Assistance, Quality, and Affordability Act of 2010</short-title>, the Administrator shall, after opportunity for comment, and after obtaining advice and direction from the Science Advisory Board, publish guidance on developing and updating protocols for testing of possible endocrine disruptors that may be found in sources of drinking water. The guidance shall specify—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF62412DB4AA44A3FAD0EAA63E379997F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the manner in which the Administrator will evaluate and, where necessary, revise such protocols;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE6D88033B8304EEFA2E114F55E4B6298"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the manner in which the Administrator will determine when testing of substances will be required; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC0A38B4A0CA145DC80B5F7B1E86D2590"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the procedures by which other scientifically relevant information can be used in lieu of some or all of the information that otherwise would be collected pursuant to testing under section 408(p) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H60B478FAEF50463688FA83C2F862C22A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minimum contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The procedures specified pursuant to paragraph (1)(C) shall ensure that the Administrator may use information that is prepared or provided by any person (including a registrant, manufacturer, or importer of a substance for which testing is required, and any other entity) and shall apply equally with respect to any such person.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8157DE31363A45B995B95A87BEC4EB8B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Amendments</header><text>The Administrator may, after opportunity for comment, and after obtaining advice and direction from the Science Advisory Board, amend any guidance published pursuant to this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA0FCF45516544B59820513CFDDE57D9B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Revision of testing protocols</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Assistance, Quality, and Affordability Act of 2010</short-title>, the Administrator shall, after opportunity for comment, determine whether sufficient scientific information has been developed to warrant updating the screening protocols developed under section 408(p) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act for substances that may be found in sources of drinking water. Not later than 5 years after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Assistance, Quality, and Affordability Act of 2010</short-title> and every 3 years thereafter, the Administrator shall determine, consistent with the guidance published under subsection (c), whether to revise screening protocols under such section for substances that may be found in sources of drinking water based on significant improvements in the sensitivity, accuracy, reliability, reproducibility, or efficiency of such protocols, or a reduction in the number of animals required to conduct such protocols. Whenever the Administrator revises such a protocol, the Administrator shall also determine, after obtaining advice and direction from the Science Advisory Board, whether any substance that has already been subjected to testing should be tested using the revised protocol.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD0A5A937FD974D6E9EDB043FDB91B969"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Valid Scientific Data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any testing protocols pursuant to this section shall be designed to produce scientific results that are based on—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF16CC333EEEF40AFB10A4C21E101BE8E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>verifiable measurements with sufficiently small error rates;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H35F933684F7944DFA13242C2E7E69B3B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>well-controlled measurements whose interpretation is not confounded by extraneous influences; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA9F5B6A2F37A4522A86CF9685F25A4F0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>results that are repeatable by independent scientists.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H07DCFBF688744C5BB138D168EF23268F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Results of testing</header> 
<paragraph id="H74E692E9FF824545994713FBC9565568"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Publication of data evaluation records</header><text>Not later than 6 months after receipt of testing results for a substance that may be found in sources of drinking water, the Administrator shall prepare and, consistent with subsection (g), publish data evaluation records for such results in a publicly searchable database.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0593E2D1CA934BFF8CC3FFF05C1DD860"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative action</header><text>Not later than 6 months after receipt of test results that determine the endocrine-related effects caused by a substance that may be found in sources of drinking water, the Administrator shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7687A7B7E52B48198046D91732A83DE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>determine whether to take action related to the substance pursuant to the agency’s statutory authority; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2F1D5E987C4642BD878AB3378DC8D35E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consistent with subsection (g), publish such determination in a publicly searchable database.</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">Nothing in this section shall be construed to affect the Administrator’s authority to take action under other provisions of law.</continuation-text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCDBE7BBA804442A5B04772BAB3288156"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Structured evaluation framework</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To assess the overall weight of the evidence and relevance to human health of results of testing for substances that may be found in sources of drinking water, the Administrator shall develop and use a structured evaluative framework consisting of science-based criteria, consistent with the protection of public health, for systematically evaluating endocrine mode of action and for determining data relevance, quality, and reliability.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9AC24AB22DB249C1B5CB06D027AC1054"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Public database</header><text>Beginning not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Assistance, Quality, and Affordability Act of 2010</short-title> and consistent with <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/552">section 552</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, the Administrator shall publish, in electronic format, a publicly searchable database that contains information regarding the testing program. Not later than 30 days after the date on which the information becomes available, the Administrator shall ensure that, at a minimum, the database—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5B2B803967BB4081877F6746E1417147"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identifies the substances selected for testing under the program; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H20AA06EAA7F747B4A512CF478227B8E2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes the documents and information pertaining to the status of testing activities for each such substance, including test orders, deadlines for submission, the Environmental Protection Agency’s data evaluation records, any scientific information on which the Administrator based actions under subsection (f), the Administrator’s determination under subsection (f) on whether action will be taken under other statutory authority, and the summary of chemical test results.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9F845627D64E43859DA423966A49BB3A"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Petition for inclusion of a substance in the program</header> 
<paragraph id="H7A0A27429EE04803BAFC7AD1B32427FB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any person may submit a petition to the Administrator to add a substance to the list under subsection (b)(1)(A) or identify a substance pursuant to the plan under subsection (b)(1)(B).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H65FA928D335A4C1FA3CD574DE684EFB8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Specification of facts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any petition under paragraph (1) shall specify the facts that are claimed to establish that an action described in paragraph (1) is warranted.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H24B88333AC4C4850A2E4F21D8CCD0696"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Administrative action</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the filing of a petition described under paragraph (1), the Administrator shall determine whether the petition has established that an action described in paragraph (1) is warranted and shall grant or deny the petition. If the Administrator grants such petition, the Administrator shall promptly add the substance to the list under subsection (b)(1)(A) or identify the substance pursuant to the plan under subsection (b)(1)(B), as applicable. If the Administrator denies the petition, the Administrator shall publish the reasons for such denial in the Federal Register.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2EB38518410E4F098933C4648D0C6FE3"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Coordination with other Federal agencies</header><text>After the Administrator—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD1780E98FB0749BD84C9B7682918BD11"><enum>(1)</enum><text>requires testing of a substance that may be found in sources of drinking water, or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H503A4CDAB2A04E2AB05F0FECF039D0CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">based in whole or in part on the results of testing of such a substance, takes action related to the substance pursuant to the agency’s statutory authority,</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">the Administrator shall give notice of such testing or action to Federal agencies which are authorized by other provisions of law to regulate the substance or products, materials, medications, processes, or practices that use the substance.</continuation-text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H17ABE5C0B7F74563AF3F2D5DCC2737DA"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Reporting requirement</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Assistance, Quality, and Affordability Act of 2010</short-title> and every 3 years thereafter, the Administrator shall provide a report to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate that describes—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA849550A49384EB49D90DCA94C31940A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">progress made in identifying and testing potential endocrine disruptors as well as plans for future activities;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H31F18968F59E46EFBC5DBB41E4013107"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any change in screening or testing methodology and evaluation or criteria for evaluating scientifically relevant information;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE72DCB29AC81411898B96DAC363E3B2A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>actions taken to ensure communication and sharing of scientific information with other Federal agencies and the public; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7896EAA7356A483FBFFEFA58927CF1A3"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any deviations from the plan or schedule published under subsection (b)(1)(B) as well as the reasons therefor.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HB7CF80EA29B84EA29148470B95DF04FA"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Testing consortia, compensation, and compliance</header> 
<paragraph id="H8506C48CC7BB4AED92F58AEF3B06EFF8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any person required by the Administrator to conduct testing of an endocrine disruptor that may be found in sources of drinking water may—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H58575425549E4166BCC31F3B4E0B1E6C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submit, on its own, data in response to an order for such testing; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2E8DDA36A6AC42DDA0BC52FE711A12F1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>form (on a voluntary basis) a consortium in order to satisfy the requirements of one or more orders for such testing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H881DB1AC45354009BA942F7263797743"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reliance on consortium submissions</header><text>Each member of a consortium described in paragraph (1)(B) shall have full rights to rely on all submissions of the consortium to satisfy the requirements of any order for testing, but continues to be individually subject to such requirements.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE6623972242A45228F2CC731F7BE0F22"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Sharing of costs</header> 
<subparagraph id="H4B8E8016684B44F8A98C9E76AE359DBD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each member of a consortium described in paragraph (1)(B) shall share the applicable costs according to appropriate arrangements established by the consortium members.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7DCD7D785C6A4F6B94AC0B0B97FE3EE8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Binding offer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whenever, to satisfy the requirements of one or more orders for testing, any person offers to form or join a consortium described in paragraph (1)(B), or offers compensation to a person that has already submitted data to the Administrator satisfying an order for testing, such offer shall constitute a binding offer to share an appropriate portion of the applicable costs.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8876475C93B44FE5A4DCA20A89FC5D61"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Applicable costs</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>applicable costs</term> includes the costs—</text> 
<clause id="H0EDF070BB14542929D5588F33A34AE48"><enum>(i)</enum><text>incurred to generate and report information to comply with an order for testing; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H05F698CAE17F46F690933DF721BABFC0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>associated with the organization and administration of the consortium.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9F47899E0E1543D9897B6CC15851A78F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Dispute Resolution</header> 
<subparagraph id="HAF5D6702749C4B498BB2040E7BC027F9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the event of any dispute about an appropriate share or a fair method of determining an appropriate share of applicable costs of the testing requirements in a test order, any person involved in the dispute may initiate binding arbitration proceedings by requesting the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service to appoint an arbitrator from the roster of arbitrators maintained by such Service or a hearing with a regional office of the American Arbitration Association. A copy of the request shall be sent to each person from whom the requesting party seeks compensation or who seeks compensation from that party.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFE3629DC68154ADCA1B0550A90917DE3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No review of findings and determination</header><text>The findings and determination of the arbitrator in a dispute initiated pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall be final and conclusive, and no official or court of the United States shall have power or jurisdiction to review any such findings and determination, except in the case of fraud, misrepresentation, or other misconduct by one of the parties to the arbitration or by the arbitrator.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC87391571DD34D7E88860EF457542095"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Payment of fee and expenses</header><text>The parties to arbitration initiated pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall share equally in the payment of the fee and expenses of the arbitrator.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H232C592A95414A4D9CDD52B59E41A798"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text>If the Administrator determines that any person seeking to comply with an order for testing by relying on a submission made by a consortium or an original data submitter has failed to make an offer in accordance with paragraph (3)(B), to participate in an arbitration proceeding under paragraph (4), or to comply with the terms of an agreement or arbitration decision concerning sharing of applicable costs under paragraph (3), that person is deemed to have failed to comply with an order under subparagraph (A) of section 408(p)(5) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act for purposes of subparagraphs (B) and (C) of such section.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H02104D1AED874FAC9487E773725E4D6D"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H9C2F1708D314464F817C4247D856C143"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>endocrine disruptor</term> means an exogenous agent or mixture of agents that interferes or alters the synthesis, secretion, transport, metabolism, binding action, or elimination of hormones that are present in the body and are responsible for homeostasis, growth, neurological signaling, reproduction and developmental process, or any other effect that the Administrator has designated as an <quote>endocrine effect</quote> pursuant to section 408(p)(1) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2A8DBDC06C2D43EFB597128FA396FF93"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>testing</term> means the testing of a substance pursuant to the screening program under section 408(p) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, including a test of a substance that is intended to identify substances that have the potential to interact with the endocrine system or that is intended to determine the endocrine-related effects caused by such substance and obtain information about effects at various doses.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HD9AE4DB0DDE7434B85AFD85BD8DD8036"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2011 through 2015.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HD02FD4A7375D4D79B3B851DFE5B2B168"><enum>19.</enum><header>Presence of pharmaceuticals and personal care products in sources of drinking water</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (a) of section 1442 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-1">42 U.S.C. 300j–1</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H2A6B1C097129417A825ACF9CEC466BAE" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H30F9472EA8AB4B1CBFB017EAE6A49683" indent="up1"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Presence of pharmaceuticals and personal care products in sources of drinking water</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H618F6EDD03B44E759FA86341EC5F82A8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Administrator shall carry out a study on the presence of pharmaceuticals and personal care products in sources of drinking water, which shall—</text> 
<clause commented="no" id="H14D931075E77447D8FC5DC7711843E63"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identify pharmaceuticals and personal care products that have been detected in sources of drinking water and the levels at which such pharmaceuticals and personal care products have been detected;</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H555FEFEDB876478F96D0E4DEE0AAC6DF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identify the sources of pharmaceuticals and personal care products in sources of drinking water, including point sources and nonpoint sources of pharmaceutical and personal care products;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H885EED85EFB846B08F272229CBD39945"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>identify the effects of such products on humans, the environment, and the safety of drinking water; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="HAEF2A83D55B4456BAB06F1A501679D59"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>identify methods to control, limit, treat, or prevent the presence of such products.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H57AAA588B113484C9FF1DD04A7348B32"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Administrator shall conduct the study described in subparagraph (A) in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services (acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs), the Director of the United States Geological Survey, the heads of other appropriate Federal agencies (including the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences), and other interested stakeholders (including manufacturers of pharmaceuticals and personal care products and consumer groups and advocates).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HBFEBA0C4285C4FE6B4EB7CEAB852E094"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, the Administrator shall submit to the Congress a report on the results of the study carried out under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H5C9CA06DC128470FBD03C2C7F3E11E49"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this paragraph:</text> 
<clause commented="no" id="H571FF61CD3274A08B75B364C96F2D67E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The term <term>personal care product</term> has the meaning given the term <term>cosmetic</term> in section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act.</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H51B88571CFA14809A0F86E8D6767AAFE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The term <term>pharmaceutical</term> has the meaning given the term <term>drug</term> in section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HCB0DA84448234DE38078B254E44225AC"><enum>20.</enum><header>Electronic reporting of compliance monitoring data to the Administrator</header> 
<subsection id="H19D4BD1F8CB8456FB80298E1EA1C7708"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1414 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300g-3">42 U.S.C. 300g–3</external-xref>), as amended, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H60EBE16D6ECF42BA9918679A2A3B0850"> 
<subsection id="H2DFD9CD373C3477284840D6055B11263"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Electronic reporting of compliance monitoring data to the Administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall by rule establish requirements for—</text> 
<paragraph id="H278C99831C5441C6A298361FBF165C85"><enum>(1)</enum><text>electronic submission by public water systems of all compliance monitoring data—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCAB005339193489F8AFC72CA257A5EA4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to the Administrator; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H58065E2145D04FE3A143B635BAA2E1FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to public water systems in a State which has primary enforcement responsibility under section 1413, to such State; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H35974C4FBEE34189AD8E18CE97BA6B4A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>electronic submission to the Administrator by each State which has primary enforcement responsibility under section 1413 of all compliance monitoring data submitted to such State by public water systems pursuant to paragraph (1)(B).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H84FDFC64537542B79AADFFC3A251ACD6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Final rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 12 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency shall issue a final rule to carry out section 1414(k) of the Safe Drinking Water Act, as added by subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H72810130F9194F0C843DB47BCC77730D"><enum>21.</enum><header>Budgetary effects</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The budgetary effects of this Act, for the purpose of complying with the Statutory Pay-As-You-Go Act of 2010, shall be determined by reference to the latest statement titled <quote>Budgetary Effects of PAYGO Legislation</quote> for this Act, submitted for printing in the Congressional Record by the Chairman of the House Budget Committee, provided that such statement has been submitted prior to the vote on passage.</text></section> 
</legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20100730" legis-day="20100729" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives July 30 (legislative day July 29), 2010.</attestation-date><attestor display="yes">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role><proxy display="yes">Robert F. Reeves,</proxy><role>Deputy Clerk</role></attestation-group></attestation> 
<endorsement display="no"></endorsement> 
</bill> 
