<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H1753C8FAF2924A36BAEC00A2BFDA8FC4" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>110 HR 1534 EH: Mercury Export Ban Act of 2007</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>0</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
	<form>
		<distribution-code display="no">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">110th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session display="yes">1st Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 1534</legis-num>
		<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF
		  REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To prohibit certain sales, distributions,
		  and transfers of elemental mercury, to prohibit the export of elemental
		  mercury, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="H6902897832D44389BA925E97AAD6DAE4" style="OLC">
		<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H89BB3F76D05D4710BCA80985FDBF09AC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the
			 <quote><short-title>Mercury Export Ban Act of
			 2007</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H0236B05B6A354E99AB003593C9186BD9" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text>
			<paragraph id="H4939F2C78D264B16900366DA104E3676"><enum>(1)</enum><text>mercury is highly
			 toxic to humans, ecosystems, and wildlife;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HCB83FC087F8A4458AE0137B500FF676C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as many as 10
			 percent of women in the United States of childbearing age have mercury in the
			 blood at a level that could put a baby at risk;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H863D643181F342C186D4F4BEF4309499"><enum>(3)</enum><text>as many as 630,000
			 children born annually in the United States are at risk of neurological
			 problems related to mercury;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HC907EDAB5FBA432B8CE925B28D36D800"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the most
			 significant source of mercury exposure to people in the United States is
			 ingestion of mercury-contaminated fish;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H52594756952C41FB91755B16EF184EE9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Environmental
			 Protection Agency reports that, as of 2004—</text>
				<subparagraph id="HE8E2C8B9BC2E4BBFB737E1154DAAF3A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>44 States have
			 fish advisories covering over 13,000,000 lake acres and over 750,000 river
			 miles;</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0B51D162E8D4112BE4BE2BCF16B9992"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in 21 States the
			 freshwater advisories are statewide; and</text>
				</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64C1B2C4BBA54C479560E291B3C44911"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in 12 States the
			 coastal advisories are statewide;</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9022BEC29A264E7CB5AC8799E1F0B3E2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the long-term
			 solution to mercury pollution is to minimize global mercury use and releases to
			 eventually achieve reduced contamination levels in the environment, rather than
			 reducing fish consumption since uncontaminated fish represents a critical and
			 healthy source of nutrition worldwide;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HFB792A8119BC4CC9A200D611B541DBF4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>mercury pollution
			 is a transboundary pollutant, depositing locally, regionally, and globally, and
			 affecting water bodies near industrial sources (including the Great Lakes) and
			 remote areas (including the Arctic Circle);</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H4B5FE60418B04B818BDA0209A19F001B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the free trade of
			 elemental mercury on the world market, at relatively low prices and in ready
			 supply, encourages the continued use of elemental mercury outside of the United
			 States, often involving highly dispersive activities such as artisinal gold
			 mining;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H4357538B7D2541E990694B4E4695ECA5"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the intentional
			 use of mercury is declining in the United States as a consequence of process
			 changes to manufactured products (including batteries, paints, switches, and
			 measuring devices), but those uses remain substantial in the developing world
			 where releases from the products are extremely likely due to the limited
			 pollution control and waste management infrastructures in those
			 countries;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H6B7A6759907C4FB3BF578FF44EACB14"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the member
			 countries of the European Union collectively are the largest source of
			 elemental mercury exports globally;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H21DA009E309047DABDAB68AB58E057BD"><enum>(11)</enum><text>the European
			 Commission has proposed to the European Parliament and to the Council of the
			 European Union a regulation to ban exports of elemental mercury from the
			 European Union by 2011;</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H7DCD071C297A4E78AFC90762ED99A800"><enum>(12)</enum><text>the United States
			 is a net exporter of elemental mercury and, according to the United States
			 Geological Survey, exported 506 metric tons of elemental mercury more than the
			 United States imported during the period of 2000 through 2004; and</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HC246C81FA0D04E88AC9BDE886E12CC88"><enum>(13)</enum><text>banning exports
			 of elemental mercury from the United States will have a notable effect on the
			 market availability of elemental mercury and switching to affordable mercury
			 alternatives in the developing world.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H0216D8A578EB43E4856667DB9EF59079"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on
			 sale, distribution, or transfer of elemental mercury</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6 of the Toxic Substances Control
			 Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/2605">15 U.S.C. 2605</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD8D8D44312344D0F97009FE0CDD2F975" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="HCE3C980BB3EA438D9DEE0967F745B263"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Mercury</header>
					<paragraph id="H25E1229A07834C1D9B19F7BC4CFB0123"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition on
				sale, distribution, or transfer of elemental mercury by Federal
				agencies</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), effective beginning
				on the date of enactment of this subsection, no Federal agency shall convey,
				sell, or distribute to any other Federal agency, any State or local government
				agency, or any private individual or entity any elemental mercury under the
				control or jurisdiction of the Federal agency.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="HEE3F344F10694A79B9DB0051BEE271DF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Paragraph
				(1) shall not apply to a transfer between Federal agencies of elemental mercury
				for the sole purpose of facilitating storage of mercury to carry out this
				Act.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="H0E8334FB531F464E92B0822C937DE300"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibition on
			 export of elemental mercury</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 12 of the Toxic Substances Control
			 Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/2611">15 U.S.C. 2611</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
			<paragraph id="HBD148F52E3494CEBB24F1CD0C1CE6DBE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)
			 by striking <quote>subsection (b)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsections (b)
			 and (c)</quote>; and</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HD4070389C2F8458EA53406BEF2009DA1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the
			 end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC5DD27A571CD4DFB8C9CB33785DFB87F" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H93AE71A70D174C149D74CC989BDB7200"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition on
				export of elemental mercury</header>
						<paragraph id="H274490646DD94333B8F1357953973790"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>Effective
				January 1, 2010, the export of elemental mercury from the United States is
				prohibited.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H995D55412D744029B9872966C07BC122"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inapplicability
				of subsection (<enum-in-header>a</enum-in-header>)</header><text>Subsection (a)
				shall not apply to this subsection.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="HCA986E97E3AD4BE28EEBD489571388F5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report to
				congress on mercury compounds</header>
							<subparagraph id="HC084F7D739194998AC7672D200BFFC00"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not
				later than one year after the date of enactment of the
				<short-title>Mercury Export Ban Act of 2007</short-title>,
				the Administrator shall publish and submit to Congress a report on mercuric
				chloride, mercurous chloride or calomel, mercuric oxide, and other mercury
				compounds, if any, that may currently be used in significant quantities in
				products or processes. Such report shall include an analysis of—</text>
								<clause id="H844A8CC2FD5F40C9B610F16B366924E"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the sources and amounts of each of the
				mercury compounds imported into the United States or manufactured in the United
				States annually;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HC1BF07A643D440EAAEA0583C3629926D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the purposes for
				which each of these compounds are used domestically, the amount of these
				compounds currently consumed annually for each purpose, and the estimated
				amounts to be consumed for each purpose in 2010 and beyond;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H0838EEB82FBE4856A4212DFF4EFCFF5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the sources and
				amounts of each mercury compound exported from the United States annually in
				each of the last three years;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H25CF60CB0C11402986ED62F3D8EB7280"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the potential for
				these compounds to be processed into elemental mercury after export from the
				United States; and</text>
								</clause><clause id="HF8667CDC1C62480EB361844F519B8014"><enum>(v)</enum><text>other relevant
				information that Congress should consider in determining whether to extend the
				export prohibition to include one or more of these mercury compounds.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1811BD68FC1740E089A100B97B8302F0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Procedure</header><text>For
				the purpose of preparing the report under this paragraph, the Administrator may
				utilize the information gathering authorities of this title, including sections
				10 and 11.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF3EF55F2594478494951BB46D00A95B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Essential use
				exemption</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H28A222C5A4D84C19B86511D3F83505D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Any person residing in
				the United States may petition the Administrator for an exemption from the
				prohibition in paragraph (1), and the Administrator may grant by rule, after
				notice and opportunity for comment, an exemption for a specified use at an
				identified foreign facility if the Administrator finds that—</text>
								<clause id="HD8A3838ACC6548D3B3A95337C8944258" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>nonmercury alternatives for the
				specified use are not available in the country where the facility is
				located;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H6126FDE838A34E1DAADC612E5437EF66" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">there is no other source of elemental
				mercury available from domestic supplies (not including new mercury mines) in
				the country where the elemental mercury will be used;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H2FE4B241073142E7A469BE0667514013" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the country where the elemental
				mercury will be used certifies its support for the exemption;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H0350BC7DFEC847FF8E4F84AB1839053C" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the export will be conducted in such a
				manner as to ensure the elemental mercury will be used at the identified
				facility as described in the petition, and not otherwise diverted for other
				uses for any reason;</text>
								</clause><clause id="HA7F3302621654DF9BABBE56CF573ED9D" indent="up1"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the elemental mercury will be used in a
				manner that will protect human health and the environment, taking into account
				local, regional, and global human health and environmental impacts;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H3E8181BF4817496F9E38C5F94B7EA1C" indent="up1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the elemental mercury will be handled and
				managed in a manner that will protect human health and the environment, taking
				into account local, regional, and global human health and environmental
				impacts; and</text>
								</clause><clause id="H5FDED1292D9C42DEB4EE58BF7385A13C" indent="up1"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the export of elemental mercury for the
				specified use is consistent with international obligations of the United States
				intended to reduce global mercury supply, use, and pollution.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE014A912692644AE9B326600D9BF65E7" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each exemption issued by the Administrator
				pursuant to this paragraph shall contain such terms and conditions as are
				necessary to minimize the export of elemental mercury and ensure that the
				conditions for granting the exemption will be fully met, and shall contain such
				other terms and conditions as the Administrator may prescribe. No exemption
				granted pursuant to this paragraph shall exceed three years in duration and no
				such exemption shall exceed 10 metric tons of elemental mercury.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE0A7E86C4AE415F00F9BCD102A18493" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Administrator may by order suspend
				or cancel an exemption under this paragraph in the case of a violation
				described in subparagraph (D).</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H403E72C9FEF54070A30799B3D2F999C" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A violation of this subsection or the
				terms and conditions of an exemption, or the submission of false information in
				connection therewith, shall be considered a prohibited act under section 15,
				and shall be subject to penalties under section 16, injunctive relief under
				section 17, and citizen suits under section 20.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCDEBBA70E1C14430A2946FD871DE42F0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Consistency with
				trade obligations</header><text>Nothing in this subsection affects, replaces,
				or amends prior law relating to the need for consistency with international
				trade obligations.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="HBE15CC98E4634F3D847452F868A799E4"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Export of
				coal</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to prohibit
				the export of
				coal.</text>
						</paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF85098D756BF4D8EA9F37BCBDF25A004" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>5.</enum><header>Long-term
			 storage</header>
			<subsection id="H0F5F397C09234D958466386507DA4703"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of
			 program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than
			 January 1, 2010, the Secretary of Energy (in this section referred to as the
			 <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall accept custody, for the purpose of long-term
			 management and storage, of elemental mercury generated within the United States
			 and delivered to a facility of the Department of Energy designated by the
			 Secretary.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H435108DF6B6A4EFBAFB87E817E00BC00"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Fees</header>
				<paragraph id="HB59B8403C0D24694BF3CE6D4FA018772"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After consultation
			 with persons who are likely to deliver elemental mercury to a designated
			 facility for long-term management and storage under the program prescribed in
			 subsection (a), and with other interested persons, the Secretary shall assess
			 and collect a fee at the time of delivery for providing such management and
			 storage, based on the pro rata cost of long-term management and storage of
			 elemental mercury delivered to the facility. The amount of such fees—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H50F58B038E3440CBB9DA32A207308288"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be made
			 publically available not later than October 1, 2009;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H650AD372A3B8495500A749AE57474229"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may be adjusted
			 annually; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H62B0765FEE974ABA9F262F906B9D7C24"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall be set in an
			 amount sufficient to cover the costs described in paragraph (2).</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AAD3D8C56BB4B4CA53800F18DB8001D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Costs</header><text>The
			 costs referred to in paragraph (1)(C) are the costs to the Department of Energy
			 of providing such management and storage, including facility operation and
			 maintenance, security, monitoring, reporting, personnel, administration,
			 inspections, training, fire suppression, closure, and other costs required for
			 compliance with applicable law. Such costs shall not include costs associated
			 with land acquisition or permitting of a designated facility under the Solid
			 Waste Disposal Act or other applicable law. Building design and building
			 construction costs shall only be included to the extent that the Secretary
			 finds that the management and storage of elemental mercury accepted under the
			 program under this section cannot be accomplished without construction of a new
			 building or buildings.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9A32D432B0EF4EDBBAAFE998A2B4D7FE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the end of
			 each Federal fiscal year, the Secretary shall transmit to the Committee on
			 Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on
			 Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report on all of the costs
			 incurred in the previous fiscal year associated with the long-term management
			 and storage of elemental mercury. Such report shall set forth separately the
			 costs associated with activities taken under this section.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H63845A67BDDC491AA5975500FD671F89"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Management
			 standards for a facility</header>
				<paragraph id="HCA8121C203FD4955ABA900A7EBD75509"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than October 1, 2009, the
			 Secretary, after consultation with the Administrator of the Environmental
			 Protection Agency and all appropriate State agencies in affected States, shall
			 make available, including to potential users of the long-term management and
			 storage program established under subsection (a), guidance that establishes
			 procedures and standards for the receipt, management, and long-term storage of
			 elemental mercury at a designated facility or facilities, including
			 requirements to ensure appropriate use of flasks or other suitable shipping
			 containers. Such procedures and standards shall be protective of human health
			 and the environment and shall ensure that the elemental mercury is stored in a
			 safe, secure, and effective manner. In addition to such procedures and
			 standards, elemental mercury managed and stored under this section at a
			 designated facility shall be subject to the requirements of the Solid Waste
			 Disposal Act, including the requirements of subtitle C of that Act, except as
			 provided in subsection (g)(2) of this section. A designated facility in
			 existence on or before January 1, 2010, is authorized to operate under interim
			 status pursuant to section 3005(e) of the Solid Waste Disposal Act until a
			 final decision on a permit application is made pursuant to section 3005(c) of
			 the Solid Waste Disposal Act. Not later than January 1, 2012, the Administrator
			 of the Environmental Protection Agency (or an authorized State) shall issue a
			 final decision on the permit application.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HF954CA36CBED409DB049346075F53F5D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall conduct operational
			 training and emergency training for all staff that have responsibilities
			 related to elemental mercury management, transfer, storage, monitoring, or
			 response.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H8190AD2EDC984476AFC0D97B6208F3F6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Equipment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that each
			 designated facility has all equipment necessary for routine operations,
			 emergencies, monitoring, checking inventory, loading, and storing elemental
			 mercury at the facility.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H20CF4CA55D0E483298F0AAEE92DA068"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Fire detection
			 and suppression systems</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The
			 Secretary shall—</text>
					<subparagraph id="H10C7046AF117421BA9B85EB2FA2026D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure the
			 installation of fire detection systems at each designated facility, including
			 smoke detectors and heat detectors; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8983EBA4DA814B6BBFABE020D6EAF663"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure the
			 installation of a permanent fire suppression system, unless the Secretary
			 determines that a permanent fire suppression system is not necessary to protect
			 human health and the environment.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0C835291B4544D178DA32B4854CEB88C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Indemnification
			 of persons delivering elemental mercury</header>
				<paragraph id="H5636DB3A244149D0AD6500B778B6A869"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA38DE0D543F3405C859DEB25DF9A344"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Except as provided in
			 subparagraph (B) and subject to paragraph (2), the Secretary shall hold
			 harmless, defend, and indemnify in full any person who delivers elemental
			 mercury to a designated facility under the program established under subsection
			 (a) from and against any suit, claim, demand or action, liability, judgment,
			 cost, or other fee arising out of any claim for personal injury or property
			 damage (including death, illness, or loss of or damage to property or economic
			 loss) that results from, or is in any manner predicated upon, the release or
			 threatened release of elemental mercury as a result of acts or omissions
			 occurring after such mercury is delivered to a designated facility described in
			 subsection (a).</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBD78A7E585240B7A743ED5C693543B" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>To the extent that a person described
			 in subparagraph (A) contributed to any such release or threatened release,
			 subparagraph (A) shall not apply.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E2F85BE6C23435CB2BEFFA0479C009B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conditions</header><text>No
			 indemnification may be afforded under this subsection unless the person seeking
			 indemnification—</text>
					<subparagraph id="HCC574761E8054E2AB0C2A1943123AC7E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>notifies the
			 Secretary in writing within 30 days after receiving written notice of the claim
			 for which indemnification is sought;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9D3D91CDC824CD1BF112DC45978E67E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>furnishes to the
			 Secretary copies of pertinent papers the person receives;</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E4CCA5D46AB4AB7B3AD55F6C86F692"><enum>(C)</enum><text>furnishes evidence
			 or proof of any claim, loss, or damage covered by this subsection; and</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32E755D77780491997A2B07637DDB3C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provides, upon
			 request by the Secretary, access to the records and personnel of the person for
			 purposes of defending or settling the claim or action.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BE119D5DEFE4049BD2F001B36FCA3E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authority of
			 secretary</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE669B2FA79BA468889E5FC7B20001B35"><enum>(A)</enum><text>In any case in which the
			 Secretary determines that the Department of Energy may be required to make
			 indemnification payments to a person under this subsection for any suit, claim,
			 demand or action, liability, judgment, cost, or other fee arising out of any
			 claim for personal injury or property damage referred to in paragraph (1)(A),
			 the Secretary may settle or defend, on behalf of that person, the claim for
			 personal injury or property damage.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H871704AA9A6A439395C11FDABE776C9E" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In any case described in subparagraph
			 (A), if the person to whom the Department of Energy may be required to make
			 indemnification payments does not allow the Secretary to settle or defend the
			 claim, the person may not be afforded indemnification with respect to that
			 claim under this subsection.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCF1DB610EBBB48F6AFF2B01275975679"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Terms,
			 conditions, and procedures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary is authorized to establish
			 such terms, conditions, and procedures as are necessary to carry out this
			 section.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H21F1E7F74BF848D7008B688389BFDC98"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Effect on other
			 law</header>
				<paragraph id="HFCEB732524C2472DB4826EB394ED83AA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In
			 general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in
			 paragraph (2), nothing in this section changes or affects any Federal, State,
			 or local law or the obligation of any person to comply with such law.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H3F11B0EFC2E84D55B87C2B23D39379A9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H932107E5F04D41E1A2D7A891ADEF535F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Elemental mercury that
			 the Secretary is storing on a long-term basis shall not be subject to the
			 storage prohibition of section 3004(j) of the Solid Waste Disposal Act (42
			 U.S.C. 6924(j)). For the purposes of section 3004(j) of the Solid Waste
			 Disposal Act, a generator accumulating elemental mercury destined for a
			 facility designated by the Secretary under subsection (a) for 90 days or less
			 shall be deemed to be accumulating the mercury to facilitate proper treatment,
			 recovery, or disposal.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H65B7B00D94274DA3B95E957D5B9903D6" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Elemental mercury that is stored at a
			 facility with respect to which a permit has been issued under section 3005(c)
			 of the Solid Waste Disposal Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6925">42 U.S.C. 6925(c)</external-xref>) shall not be subject to the
			 storage prohibition of section 3004(j) of the Solid Waste Disposal Act (42
			 U.S.C. 6924(j)) if—</text>
						<clause id="H0DBA45B453414250AE3D696BAA9DC853"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Secretary is unable to accept
			 the mercury at a facility designated by the Secretary under subsection (a) for
			 reasons beyond the control of the owner or operator of the permitted
			 facility;</text>
						</clause><clause id="HF72F88F7A64A4792B085D8402DBB7876"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the owner or operator of the permitted
			 facility certifies in writing to the Secretary that it will ship the mercury to
			 the designated facility when the Secretary is able to accept the mercury;
			 and</text>
						</clause><clause id="HAE770B85D4714BE690FACF71CA453C73"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the owner or operator of the permitted
			 facility certifies in writing to the Secretary that it will not sell, or
			 otherwise place into commerce, the mercury.</text>
						</clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">This
			 subparagraph shall not apply to mercury with respect to which the owner or
			 operator of the permitted facility fails to comply with a certification
			 provided under clause (ii) or (iii).</continuation-text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H99D96DFBDC77401DAB3600E73FDABC5D"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Study</header><text>Not
			 later than July 1, 2011, the Secretary shall transmit to the Congress the
			 results of a study, conducted in consultation with the Administrator of the
			 Environmental Protection Agency, that—</text>
				<paragraph id="H5650171EE3F04C148B0000547E178308"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determines the
			 impact of the long-term storage program under this section on mercury
			 recycling; and</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H97A45871AA7B4C2F99A46D4D53AE45B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>includes proposals,
			 if necessary, to mitigate any negative impact identified under paragraph
			 (1).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE46B5AD1A939409081D77D1140DF6FDA"><enum>6.</enum><header>Report to
			 Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">At least 3 years
			 after the effective date of the prohibition on export of elemental mercury
			 under section 12(c) of the Toxic Substances Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/2611">15 U.S.C. 2611(c)</external-xref>), as
			 added by section 4 of this Act, but not later than January 1, 2014, the
			 Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency shall transmit to the
			 Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the
			 Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report on the global
			 supply and trade of elemental mercury, including but not limited to the amount
			 of elemental mercury traded globally that originates from primary mining, where
			 such primary mining is conducted, and whether additional primary mining has
			 occurred as a consequence of this Act.</text>
		</section></legis-body>
	<attestation>
		<attestation-group>
			<attestation-date chamber="House" date="20071113">Passed the House of
			 Representatives November 13, 2007.</attestation-date>
			<attestor display="no">Lorraine C. Miller,</attestor>
			<role>Clerk.</role>
		</attestation-group>
	</attestation>
	<endorsement display="yes">
	</endorsement>
</bill>


