<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing>
    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <info>  $125 BILLION IN SAVINGS IGNORED: REVIEW OF DOD'S EFFICIENCY STUDY</info>
    <info>=======================================================================</info>
    <info>                                HEARING</info>
    <info>                               BEFORE THE</info>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON OVERSIGHT</committee_name>
    <option>                         AND GOVERNMENT REFORM
                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                             MARCH 21, 2017
                               __________
                           Serial No. 115-19
                               __________
Printed for the use of the Committee on Oversight and Government Reform
[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
         Available via the World Wide Web: http://www.fdsys.gov
                       http://oversight.house.gov
                              __________
                    U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE                    
26-498 PDF                  WASHINGTON : 2017                     
----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing Office, 
http://bookstore.gpo.gov. For more information, contact the GPO Customer Contact Center, 
U.S. Government Publishing Office. Phone 202-512-1800, or 866-512-1800 (toll-free). 
E-mail, gpo@custhelp.com.               
              Committee on Oversight and Government Reform
                     Jason Chaffetz, Utah, Chairman
John J. Duncan, Jr., Tennessee       Elijah E. Cummings, Maryland, 
Darrell E. Issa, California              Ranking Minority Member
Jim Jordan, Ohio                     Carolyn B. Maloney, New York
Mark Sanford, South Carolina         Eleanor Holmes Norton, District of 
Justin Amash, Michigan                   Columbia
Paul A. Gosar, Arizona               Wm. Lacy Clay, Missouri
Scott DesJarlais, Tennessee          Stephen F. Lynch, Massachusetts
Trey Gowdy, South Carolina           Jim Cooper, Tennessee
Blake Farenthold, Texas              Gerald E. Connolly, Virginia
Virginia Foxx, North Carolina        Robin L. Kelly, Illinois
Thomas Massie, Kentucky              Brenda L. Lawrence, Michigan
Mark Meadows, North Carolina         Bonnie Watson Coleman, New Jersey
Ron DeSantis, Florida                Stacey E. Plaskett, Virgin Islands
Dennis A. Ross, Florida              Val Butler Demings, Florida
Mark Walker, North Carolina          Raja Krishnamoorthi, Illinois
Rod Blum, Iowa                       Jamie Raskin, Maryland
Jody B. Hice, Georgia                Peter Welch, Vermont
Steve Russell, Oklahoma              Matthew Cartwright, Pennsylvania
Glenn Grothman, Wisconsin            Mark DeSaulnier, California
Will Hurd, Texas                     John Sarbanes, Maryland
Gary J. Palmer, Alabama
James Comer, Kentucky
Paul Mitchell, Michigan
                   Jonathan Skladany, Staff Director
                    William McKenna, General Counsel
                      Cordell Hull, Senior Counsel
               Brick Christensen, Senior Military Advisor
                    Sharon Casey, Deputy Chief Clerk
                 David Rapallo, Minority Staff Director
</option>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <Witness>Mr David Tillotson III</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Acting Deputy Chief Management Officer US Department of Defense Oral Statement Written Statement</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mr Scott Rutherford</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Senior Partner McKinsey &amp; Company Oral Statement Written Statement</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mr Michael Bayer</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Chairman Defense Business Board Oral Statement Written Statement</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mr Robert ``Bobby'' Stein</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Former Chairman Defense Business Board Oral Statement Written Statement</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mr Kenneth ``Kenny'' Klepper</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Former Board Member Defense Business Board Oral Statement Written Statement</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mr Lawrence J Korb</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>PhD Senior Fellow Center for American Progress Oral Statement Written Statement $ BILLION IN SAVINGS IGNORED: REVIEW OF DOD'S EFFICIENCY STUDY  Tuesday</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Amash</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>DesJarlais Massie Meadows</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hice</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Russell Grothman Hurd</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Norton</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Lynch Connolly Kelly</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Plaskett</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Demings Krishnamoorthi Raskin</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>and Sarbanes Chairman Chaffetz The Committee on Oversight and Government Reform will come to order And</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>without objection the chair is authorized to declare</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>a recess at any time I appreciate you all being here We have an important topic today to talk about the potential of $ billion in savings that has been ignored</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and we're going to</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>have a discussion about the review of the Department of Defense's efficiency study On December th of</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>The Washington Post reported on a</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>noncombat expenses The Post's story detailed the desire of DOD leadership to squelch the findings of the Defense Business Boardsometimes referred to as the DBB</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>but the Defense</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Business Boardfor fear that the Congress would ultimately end up cutting their budget That is the concern The DBB is an advisory board commissioned by the Pentagon to provide independent advice and recommendations with regard to governance and management at the Department of Defense For the study</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the Defense Business Board was charged with finding</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>savings the Pentagon could recapitalize into more troops</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>more</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>ships</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and more planes Enlisting the management consulting</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>firm of McKinsey &amp; Company</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>one of the premier consulting</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>companies we have in this country</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the DBB spent months</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>analyzing the Pentagon's business systems and backoffice operations The result of the report concluded the Department of Defense could save billions from overhauling its backoffice functions</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>including contract management IT business</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>processes</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>real estate and human resource management The</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>savings could be reinvested to better equip our men and women in uniform But the Department of Defense leadership squelched the report In response to the Post's story</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>members of this</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>committee from both sides of the aisle signed a letter to then Secretary Carter asking for answers With the change in administration</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the urgent need for</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>reform at the Pentagon has not changed There are a number of statistics that tend to support the DBB's recommendation for rigorous oversight First</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the Pentagon continues to expand its</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>use of contractors From  to</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the Department of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>government contractors are less likely to be subject to oversight of the Pentagon Some of the government's most effective tools for holding its employees accountable are not available when it comes to contractors Second</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the Pentagon study noted the potential $ billion</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>savings could fund  Army brigades or  Navy carrier strike group deployments or  Air Force F fighter wings So</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>while</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>our troops are engaging the enemy in Iraq and Syria and patrolling the South China Sea and really helping make sure that this world and the United States is a safe place</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Pentagon is resistant to backoffice cuts that would better fund and equip these men and women who are doing the hard work on the front lines Given how dangerous our world is</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>we really truly have to</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>get this right And if we're going to ensure our troops are the best equipped possible</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>it is our responsibility to oversee how</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>this money is expended It is a lot of money It is the single biggest line item in our discretionary spending budget The Constitution delegates the Congress the role of providing the training and equipment of the Army and to</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>quote ``maintain a navy'' end quote It is our job to make sure that</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>our warfighters are getting all the support that they need to do their jobs We have a very astute panel</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and we look forward</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>to having discussions with them about this report and what can be done to save money at the Pentagon With that</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>I will yield my time back and I now recognize</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>the ranking member</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Mr Cummings Mr Cummings Thank you very much Mr Chairman for</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>holding this critical hearing today The Department of Defense is charged with the most serious mission there is: Protecting and defending every man</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>woman child in our country In this</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>dangerous world</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the readiness of our warfighters is essential</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>to national security</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and Congress has a duty to provide our</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>military with all the necessary resources However</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>we also have a duty to ensure that every</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>duplication</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>or fraud is a dollar not available for military</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>training</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>advanced weaponry and salaries and benefits for our</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>uniformed and nonuniformed personnel It is also a dollar we do not have for critical domestic programs like education</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>job</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>training</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and feeding the poor In January  the Defense Business Board a panel that</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>issued a study finding</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and I quote ``a clear path to saving</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>over $ billion in the next  years</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>'' end of quote Last</peopleinfo>
    <peopleinfo>a Washington Post story written by Bob Woodward and</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>his colleagues reported allegations that Pentagon leadership deliberately buried the study amid fears that Congress might reduce the defense budget On December</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>all committee Democrats and  total</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>committee members signed a bipartisan letter requesting information about this report and these allegations The Defense Department disputes the amount in the report</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the $</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>billion over  years</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>but nobody disputes that the Defense</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>issued the following joint statement on the study</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and I quote: ``The Defense Business Board's key findings that the Department of Defense could save as much as $ billion over</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>years by limiting unnecessary backoffice bureaucracy</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>are not</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>a surprise</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>'' end of quote Nor are the problems identified by the Board new We have</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>known for many years that the Department's business practices are archaic and wasteful</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and this inability to pass a clean</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>audit is a longstanding travesty In the United States of America</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>we have one department that just cannot get through an</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>audit That is amazing This is also not new to this committee We have done years of work examining wasteful spending at the Defense Department Just last month</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the Comptroller General of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>the United States testified before us that</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and I quote ``probably a third of the areas on the highrisk list are DOD</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>business management practices</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>'' end of quote The Defense Department is the only Federal agency that has</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>neverneverpassed an independent audit I wonder if they're spending too much money to be able to do an audit And then we hear that the President wants another $ billion</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and here we</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>have a report that says we can save $ billion in  years But President Trump's new budget ignores all of this He proposes boosting defense spending by billions and billions of dollars He proposes funding this increase by slashing dozen of programs that promote our national security and our Nation's most vulnerable communities</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the elderly children and the</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>rural working class The President would slash funding for the State Department and the US Agency for International Development</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>reducing contributions for UN peacekeeping the</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>International Atomic Energy Agency that monitors Iran's compliance with the nuclear agreement</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and the World Bank's</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>antipoverty programs The President would decimate foreign aid for humanitarian efforts in Iraq</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Afghanistan and Nepal as</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>well as antidrug trafficking efforts in Latin America Last month</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>more than  former generals signed a letter</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>to Congress warning</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and I quote ``the State Department</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>USAID</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Millennium Challenge Corporation Peace Corps and other</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>development agencies are critical to preventing conflict and reducing the need to put our men and women in uniform in harm's way'' In</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Defense Secretary James Mattis who was then</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>serving as the Commander of CENTCOM</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>testified and I quote: ``If you don't fully fund the State Department I need to buy</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>more ammunition ultimately The more that we put into the State Department's diplomacy</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>hopefully the less we have to put into</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>a military budget</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>'' end of quote The President's budget also weakens our maritime border</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>and airport security by redirecting billions of dollars from the Coast Guard and TSA to constructing an outrageously expensive wall on the border with Mexico But to me</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the most</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>disturbing cuts are to critical</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>domestic programs The</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>which fund antipoverty programs like Meals on Wheels</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>which</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>veterans</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>and other homebound individuals every year The</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>President would also eliminate funding for the st Century Community Learning Centers</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>which helps fund afterschool</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>programs</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>serving more than  million children across the</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>country</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>many of them in lowincome neighborhoods The</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>President's budget does not effectively serve our national security interests</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>nor does it serve the interests of the</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>everyday American family The United States must invest in a strong national defense to face our global challenges This means not just spending more</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>but spending wisely So I want to thank all of the</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>witnesses for being with us today and for their valuable contributions toward improving the Defense Department's effectiveness and the national security of all of our Americans With that</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>I yield back Chairman Chaffetz The gentleman yields back I will hold the record open for  legislative days for any</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>members who wish to submit a written statement We'll now recognize our panel of witnesses We're pleased to welcome Mr David Tillotson III</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Acting</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Deputy Chief Management Officer</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>from the United States</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Department of Defense; Mr Scott Rutherford</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>senior partner at</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>McKinsey &amp; Company; Mr Michael Bayer</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>current chairman of the</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Defense Business Board; Mr Robert Stein</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>former chairman of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>the Defense Business Board; Mr Kenneth Klepper</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>former board</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>member of the Defense Business Board; and the Honorable Lawrence Korb</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>senior fellow at the Center for American</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Progress We thank you all Pursuant to committee rules</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>all</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>witnesses are to be sworn before they testify So if you will please rise and raise your right hand Do you solemnly swear or affirm that the testimony you are about to give will be the truth</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>the whole truth and nothing</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>but the truth</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>so help you God? Thank you You may be seated Let the record reflect that all the witnesses answered in</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>the affirmative Mr Tillotson</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>we will start with you and we will go right</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>on down the line You'll each be recognized for  minutes If you'd please limit your testimony to those  minutes so members have a chance to ask you questions We have a big panel today Your entire written statement and any attachments will be made part of the official record Mr Tillotson</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>you are now recognized for  minutes WITNESS STATEMENTS</peopleinfo>
    <option>    Mr. Tillotson. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, Ranking Member, 
members of the committee. As my written statement will be 
entered into the record, I will keep my remarks brief in the 
interest of giving you time to ask whatever questions the 
committee chooses to ask. I will say a couple of things very 
quickly, however.
    I think the one thing that I would take unequivocal issue 
with is that the report was in any way suppressed. It was 
actively discussed within the Department at the time. It has 
formed the basis of discussion since that time. It was posted 
in the public record. It was actually discussed with Members of 
the House and Senate back in 2015, shortly after it was issued, 
albeit not with this committee, but with the HASC and SASC. So 
the fact is this has not been suppressed.
    The actions that led to the results of the DBB report, 
among other things, were actually kicked off by the current 
Deputy Secretary of Defense acting through my office. Two 
actions were taken: One, we initiated a contract through the 
DCMO office to Ryan Consulting to do some work on understanding 
where the costs of the Department rested in terms of back-shop 
activity. So this was a deliberate attempt on the part of the 
Department to, in fact, identify the opportunity space, not 
associate with the--directly associated with Defense Business 
Board. Ryan Consulting in turn subcontracted to McKinsey. So 
that's the relationship to that company.
    The second activity was that the Deputy Secretary chartered 
the Defense Business Board at the time to do a corporate-style 
review, looking at the information generated by McKinsey and 
coming up with recommendations about how the Department might 
proceed to address opportunities generated by whatever the cost 
opportunities presented us. So those were the actions that were 
taken.
    The question about moving forward on efficiencies is hardly 
new to the Department. Secretary Gates led a significant 
efficiency initiative that resulted in multiple billions of 
dollars repurposed within the Department. Secretary Hagel 
continued that tradition. Secretary Carter continues to do so.
    After the study was published, several things got 
addressed. There were two concrete areas for recommendations in 
the report and a third recommendation that basically said: Go 
do some more homework. We acted on the two concrete 
recommendations, which were to address some IT efficiencies. We 
have not gone as far as the report would suggest we could. I 
agree with that. We also pushed ahead on some services' 
contract reviews, particularly on the OSD staff, the Defense 
Agencies and Field Activities, an area where, candidly, not as 
much attention had been rendered as needed to have been done in 
the past. When we look at the result of those sets of actions, 
that added an additional $7.9 billion in efficiencies to an 
already double-digit billions of efficiencies that we had put 
in place in prior years.
    Having said all that, there is more to do. There is ample 
opportunity. The DBB report, the supporting McKinsey material 
would suggest there are things we can do.
    There are two challenges to moving forward. I will be 
candid about both. There is an internal challenge. That's our 
job. We will go fight those battles. We have to have those 
discussions internal to the Department, and in some instances, 
we are assisted by actions on the Hill. So, in the most recent 
National Defense Authorization bill, in 2017, there was a very 
specific requirement for us to redirect and look at the 
management of the medical community in the Department of 
Defense. We agree from the DCMO's office that that is worth 
looking at. We certainly would endorse moving forward with 
that, and we appreciate the support of Congress in doing that.
    Having said that, ``efficiencies'' means we take a look at 
moving money and activities from current activities into new 
activities. One of the areas that both the GAO and the DBB 
report and independent DBB reports have all pointed at is our 
use of leased property and owned real property. It's intriguing 
to me that, when we opt to let a lease contract for a building 
lapse--not terminate it, let the contract run out--that we 
spend three trips to a State delegation explaining why we can't 
close that contract. So I'm prepared and the Department is 
prepared to work on this going forward.
    Mr. Korb in a recent article has suggested five steps that 
the Department should build on, including build on the DBB 
report. We agree. But his fifth recommendation is a 
recommendation the Department brings forward with regularity 
and which, candidly, at least one member of this committee in a 
prior testimony has asked me if we thought we needed, and that 
is, do we need a BRAC? And the answer is yes. So there are 
actions that we need to take, working in conjunction with 
Congress. By the way, BRAC is not the only action. I'm going to 
say that right now. It is not the only thing we should do. 
Thank you for your time, Mr. Chairman.
</option>
    <option>    [GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman Chaffetz. Thank you.
    Mr. Rutherford, you're now recognized for 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>    Mr. Rutherford. Chairman Chaffetz, Ranking Member Cummings, 
and members of the committee, my name is Scott Rutherford. I'm 
a senior partner at McKinsey &amp; Company, and I'm the managing 
partner of the Washington, D.C., office. I'm pleased to be here 
today to discuss McKinsey's work for the Department of Defense 
under contract with the Department's Deputy Chief Management 
Officer.
    From the fall of 2014 to the spring of 2015, we were 
engaged by the Department to conduct a comprehensive assessment 
of its spending in six core business functions: human resource 
management; healthcare management; financial flow management; 
logistics and supply chain; acquisitions and procurement; and 
real property management.
    Our work began with the development of what we called a 
cost baseline, which assembled data on existing spending across 
the entire Department in these six areas. To our knowledge, 
that kind of crosscutting analysis of back-office spending at 
the DOD had never before been conducted. McKinsey's work has 
since been used by the Department in a number of important 
ways.
    First, the Deputy Chief Management Officer shared our 
baseline with the DBB, and that baseline was used by the 
Defense Business Board in its own analysis and report released 
in January 2015. Although the McKinsey baseline was a starting 
point for the DBB's efforts--and McKinsey is one of many inputs 
into their approach--the projections, assumptions, and analysis 
of the potential cost savings were those of the DBB.
    Second, McKinsey's work for the DOD continued using the 
cost baseline into what we would call benchmarking, which 
compares the Department against other large companies, and 
roughsizing, which began the process of estimating the 
magnitude of the savings that might be achieved in different 
categories.
    So, in May of 2015, McKinsey estimated that the Department 
could achieve about $4 to $5 billion in new savings per year 
over a 5-year period across the six functional areas we 
examined. That translates into cumulative savings of between 
$62 billion and $84 billion over a 5-year period.
    Third, it's our understanding that the Department has used 
our baseline, our benchmarks, and our cost savings estimates to 
implement changes on its own that are generating actual cost 
savings. The projected cost savings we identified are somewhat 
different than those estimated by the DBB's January 2015 report 
because, while both estimates started with the McKinsey 
baseline, McKinsey had the benefit of working collaboratively 
with the DOD, allowing us to drill down further and do 
additional analytic work for a couple months afterwards. Based 
on that work, we also assumed a somewhat slower pace of change 
than the DBB assumed. This resulted in a lower estimate of how 
much savings could be achieved over the first 5 years relative 
to the DBB's projections.
    We're very proud of our work. We have been helping private 
sector and government agencies identify opportunities to reduce 
costs for many years and have accumulated a body of proprietary 
databases and methodologies that allow us to bring that 
experience to bear in very concrete ways. And in this case, we 
provided the Department with a set of tools and approaches to 
move forward on realizing cost savings opportunities, and we 
believe the Department's potential return on that investment it 
made in our effort is substantial.
    Thank you for the opportunity to be here today, and I'm 
happy to answer any questions you might have.
</option>
    <option>    [GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman Chaffetz. Thank you. I appreciate it.
    Mr. Bayer, you're recognized for 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>    Mr. Bayer. Thank you, and good morning, Chairman Chaffetz 
and Ranking Minority Member Cummings and members of the 
committee.
    My last engagement with this committee was many years ago 
when my then-boss, Bud Brown, was the ranking minority member 
of the then-named Government Operations Committee. But today I 
appear before you as the fifth chairman of the Defense Business 
Board.
    As are all the members of the Business Board, I am a 
private citizen, not a paid government employee. We all 
volunteer our time to serve the Department of Defense by 
offering our collective advice on how to manage the Department 
more efficiently in order to enable the Secretary and the 
Deputy Secretary to maximize the allocation of scarce resources 
for the warfighter.
    The men and women of the Business Board and its sister 
advisory boards, Policy and Science, who donate their time and 
energy to help the Department, each consider it a tremendous 
honor and a great responsibility.
    As I've communicated to you and your staff, I have no 
direct knowledge about the effort at hand. My first meeting 
after returning as chairman of the Defense Business Board was 
in July of 2015, more than 6 months after this study had ended 
and its presentation publicly in January of that year. As this 
was under the direction of a previous chairman and long before 
I became chair, I have no particular insight or access into the 
actions and decisions made about how this effort was conducted 
or delivered.
    I can say in the year and a half since I became chairman, 
the board has been very busy. It has completed eight studies, 
and our most recent effort, ``Focusing a Transition,'' was a 
product of every member of the board, of the Defense Business 
Board, and it was very well received by the Department's 
leadership at the time and the incoming leadership of Secretary 
Mattis' team.
    But there is more work to be done in the months and years 
ahead as we all strive to support Secretary Mattis' priorities, 
particularly his third, and I quote, ``bringing business 
reforms to the Department of Defense,'' which we believe are 
essential for his ability to deliver the other two.
    I will close with saying that this hearing appears from its 
title to be focused on what the Department did or did not do 
with a particular study. And speaking for the Department is an 
inherently governmental function, and I as a private citizen am 
strictly prohibited from assuming that role, which makes 
appearing before you to discuss a study of this which I wasn't 
part of a bit challenging. My duties include speaking for the 
Business Board to the Department and others but not speaking 
for the Department of Defense to anyone.
    Thank you, Mr. Chairman. This concludes my opening remarks, 
and I look forward to your and Mr. Cummings' and the rest of 
the members' questions.
</option>
    <option>    [GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman Chaffetz. Thank you, Mr. Bayer.
    I now recognize Mr. Stein for 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>    Mr. Stein. Chairman, Ranking Member, and members of the 
committee, thank you for inviting me to provide testimony 
today.
    Congressman Cummings, it is great seeing you again since 
our time on the Naval Academy Board of Visitors.
    My name is Bobby Stein, and I'm here to discuss the 
Department of Defense efficiency study commissioned by 
Secretary Hagel and created under my leadership as former 
chairman of the DOD Defense Business Board, known as the DBB.
    I was honored to serve as a member of the DBB between 2010 
and 2014, and chairman from 2014 to 2015. As you know, the DBB 
is an advisory panel comprised of a select group of our 
Nation's business leaders. Our purpose was to provide advice to 
the Secretary and Deputy Secretary of Defense and other senior 
leaders on best practices that could be applied to DOD. My 
priority for the DBB was that members be not selected for any 
partisan reasons, but based on tried and true experience 
results in the business world.
    I was honored to serve because I understood our mission to 
be strengthening the defense of our country. I was appointed as 
chair of the DBB by then-Secretary Hagel in 2014. After 
becoming chair, I went on a listening tour of senior retired 
uniformed and non-uniformed leadership to determine areas where 
the DBB could support the agency.
    During the listening tour, we took note of key facts and 
figures about how money was being spent. It generated concerns 
because, as a retired Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff 
said, the biggest threat to our national security is our 
national debt.
    Key takeaways included our national debt is $20 trillion. 
Our Federal Reserve has taken their balance sheet from 800 
billion to 4.5 trillion. At the Pentagon, overhead and support 
comprise 40 percent of spending, or $240 billion. This equals 
twice the combined total budgets, defense budgets, of France 
and England. The expenses on DOD headquarters alone amounts to 
$40 billion, more than the German defense budget.
    At the same time, since 2001, DOD civilian personnel has 
increased over 15 percent, but military personnel has decreased 
by 5 percent. While everyone wants reform in the Pentagon, the 
status quo remains. The antibodies get you every time. Indeed, 
clean audits and services continue to fail. In some estimates, 
we have spent $6 billion to try to get clean audits in our 
different departments. This listening tour predated the 
commissioning of the efficiency study but highlights the 
importance of the effort. The DBB efficiency study was one of 
many reports undertaken by the DBB under my leadership. This 
study was the first effort ever in DOD history to 
comprehensively evaluate labor cost data and create a picture 
of how much money is being spent on noncombat operations at the 
agency.
    As the chair of the DBB during the study, I felt that my 
role was to help ensure that the study was done accurately so 
we could meet our ultimate goal of identifying inefficiency and 
cost savings that could then be moved to better uses. In 
particular, I helped to identify the people with the right 
experience to handle this type of project. For something like 
this, you need a heart surgeon if you have a heart problem, not 
a country doctor, as said by one of the retired CNOs. And I've 
spent time looking for who that right person is and who can 
help that path to work with the Department of Defense to get 
these savings. And the name that kept coming up was Kenny 
Klepper. Kenny has done this in a Fortune 50 company. He 
understands that the DOD is not a business. It is government, 
and there's not easy efficiency opportunities. So, with that, 
we got Kenny to lead this study.
    The study succeeded in its goal in highlighting 
inefficiency that, if remedied, could generate significant cost 
savings to the Department. This cost savings could then be 
transferred to other priorities, like improving readiness, 
modernizing our defense, and creating jobs.
    The study was presented to the full DBB at public hearing 
January 25 and won a unanimous approval for its findings and 
recommendations.
    The General Accountability Office also reviewed the study 
and found the methodologies and analysis adequate to confirm 
its conclusions. At the completion of the study, along with 
other members of DBB, we were ready to move forward to assist 
the DOD in reviewing the study's findings and recommendations. 
I believe the DBB efficiency study represents a quality 
analysis of costs and inefficiencies at DOD, and it is my hope 
that it will be useful to the agency's efforts to streamline.
    It was an honor to lead the DBB during the creation of the 
study, and I'm proud of the work achieved in support of a 
strong national defense. Thank you for your time, and I'm 
pleased to answer any questions the committee may have.
</option>
    <option>    [GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman Chaffetz. Thank you.
    Mr. Klepper, you're now recognized for 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>    Mr. Klepper. Good morning.
    Chairman Chaffetz. If you can move that microphone up 
close. Just straighten it out. There you go. Thank you.
    Mr. Klepper. Thank you. Good morning, Chairman Chaffetz and 
minority Ranking Member Cummings. It's a pleasure to be here. 
I've served as adviser on the CNO's executive panel for five 
CNOs, and this is a first for me for over a decade. So I am 
happy to be here to tell the story of the work that we have 
done.
    The effort that we embarked on for the Defense Business 
study is something I took very, very seriously. Just briefly, a 
little of my background: I spent 40 years with the tradecraft 
of organizational modernization and change. I spent about 20 
years in chemical plant refinery operations out in Texas. And I 
spent the second 20 years in health care. And I chose in my 
written remarks that I submitted to the panel an example that I 
think has a lot of stark parallels. Even though, as Bobby said, 
I understand that the Defense Department is not a business, 
there are some very strong parallels.
    I was asked to come in and help do a turnaround for a 
company in New York called Empire Blue Cross Blue Shield. It 
was financially insolvent at the time, not enough reserves to 
pay for claims, the largest health plan in the Northeast of the 
United States. One of the things we did as part of the recovery 
of that company was understand that we had no money, and we had 
an obsolete legacy infrastructure running it, and we were 
losing millions of members a year. The company was in a death 
spiral. Since we didn't have cash to spend, the only way we 
could fund the things that urgently needed to be addressed to 
improve the performance of the business was to self-fund those 
things through productivity.
    So we put in place an opportunity to take productivity 
savings as a way to generate the money to invest in the 
platforms and automation and the improvements to recover the 
company, which we did, and we were doing really well. And then, 
on September 11, we were the second-largest tenant in the World 
Trade Center. And through all the things that we did to improve 
speed, agility, optimize our operations for the private sector, 
to improve our service to our members and the physicians, we 
never recognized the inherent ability that it gave us to 
survive a devastating disaster for our facility. We had over 
2,000 people in the building at the time, and with great pride 
I can tell you, if we can separate the human tragedy for just a 
moment--we lost 11 people that day--that when the Tower 
collapsed, we were able to maintain the operation of the 
business. We lost three call centers, two large server farms. 
They all failed over to other operations, and the company 
continued to operate.
    The Kennedy Business School did a case study that we 
included in my written remarks. And the reason I bring that up 
is, when you look at the state of the operation of DOD, the 
obsolescence of the legacy infrastructure is not just a bad 
cost situation and not just creating bad service. I think it 
increases the vulnerability of the operation to other threats. 
Whether it is a kinetic attack, an EMP attack, cyber attack, it 
is almost impossible to harden those types of legacy cores. So 
part of what I hope that we can achieve through the 
modernization of these assets is not just improve the cost 
basis and not just improve the service, but to also harden and 
provide a much more resilient infrastructure for the Department 
of Defense.
    The last thing I would mention is the $125 billion savings. 
We did something that had never been done before--and I give 
great credit to the Deputy Secretary, Bob Work--is, whenever I 
talk to him, that the one thing that we had to have to really 
start was we had to have transparency of where the money was, 
where the cash flows were. He did something I think has never 
been done before. He sponsored presentations by Bobby and 
myself to the DEXCOM, the Defense Executive Committee. He 
described the process of evaluation that we wanted to do and 
that we advised him to do, and to his credit, he got approval 
from all the civilian leadership to let us get the money. And 
we brought in--I actually asked to have McKinsey brought in 
because I've done this study before with them, and they did a 
great job for me. We had over a hundred people pulling data out 
of these systems. And people before that had said: The data is 
not there. The data is no good. The antibodies will get you.
    What we found was the data was there, and the data was not 
perfect, and believe me, the study is not perfect, but I 
believe that the savings that we identified are there with a 
high degree of certainty.
    So I think the debate and the big question for us is, and I 
think it was stated by Mr. Tillotson and Mr. Rutherford, is--
the money is there--it is, can we get the institution out of 
the way to help us do the things that can obviously help us 
improve the operation of the business? And that's the purpose 
of us being here. Thank you.
</option>
    <option>    [GRAPHICS NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]
    Chairman Chaffetz. Thank you.
    Mr. Korb, you're now recognized for 5 minutes.
</option>
</Hearing>
