<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing>
    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <info>                         [H.A.S.C. No. 115-45]</info>
    <info>                                HEARING</info>
    <info>                                   ON</info>
    <info>                   NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT</info>
    <info>                          FOR FISCAL YEAR 2018</info>
    <info>                                  AND</info>
    <info>              OVERSIGHT OF PREVIOUSLY AUTHORIZED PROGRAMS</info>
    <info>                               BEFORE THE</info>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES</committee_name>
    <option>                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
</option>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON SEAPOWER AND PROJECTION FORCES HEARING</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                                   ON
             AMPHIBIOUS WARFARE IN A CONTESTED ENVIRONMENT
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                              MAY 18, 2017
                              _________ 
                   U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
25-838                     WASHINGTON : 2018      
</option>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON SEAPOWER AND PROJECTION FORCES</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                 ROBERT J. WITTMAN, Virginia, Chairman
K. MICHAEL CONAWAY, Texas            JOE COURTNEY, Connecticut
VICKY HARTZLER, Missouri             SUSAN A. DAVIS, California
BRADLEY BYRNE, Alabama, Vice Chair   JAMES R. LANGEVIN, Rhode Island
SCOTT DesJARLAIS, Tennessee          MADELEINE Z. BORDALLO, Guam
MIKE GALLAGHER, Wisconsin            JOHN GARAMENDI, California
DUNCAN HUNTER, California            DONALD NORCROSS, New Jersey
PAUL COOK, California                SETH MOULTON, Massachusetts
JIM BRIDENSTINE, Oklahoma            COLLEEN HANABUSA, Hawaii
STEPHEN KNIGHT, California           A. DONALD McEACHIN, Virginia
RALPH LEE ABRAHAM, Louisiana
                Dave Sienicki, Professional Staff Member
              Phil MacNaughton, Professional Staff Member
                          Jodi Brignola, Clerk
</option>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <Speakers>STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>Hon Joe Courtney</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative from Connecticut Ranking Member</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon Robert J Wittman</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative from Virginia Chairman</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <Witness>Bradley Martin</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Senior Policy Researcher RAND Corporation</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Jesse Sloman</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Analyst Center for Strategic and Budgetary Assessments</peopleinfo>
    <option>APPENDIX</option>
    <Speakers>Prepared Statements:</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>Bradley Sloman Martin</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Jesse Wittman Hon Robert J</peopleinfo>
    <subcomittee_name>Subcommittee on Seapower and Projection Forces,</subcomittee_name>
    <Chairman>
        <Cname>                            Washington</Cname>
        <Clocation> 2017.</Clocation>
    </Chairman>
    <people>
        <Pname>The subcommittee met</Pname>
        <Plocation> in </Plocation>
    </people>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>room 2212</Cname>
        <Clocation> Hon. Robert J. </Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <people>
        <Pname>Wittman (chairman of the subcommittee) presiding.</Pname>
        <Plocation>Wittman (chairman of the subcommittee) presiding.</Plocation>
    </people>
    <option>     FROM VIRGINIA, CHAIRMAN, SUBCOMMITTEE ON SEAPOWER AND 
                       PROJECTION FORCES
    Mr. Wittman. I call to order the House Armed Services 
</option>
    <option>Subcommittee on Seapower and Projection Forces. I want to</option>
    <option>welcome everyone here today. I thank our witnesses for being 
here. We do have votes that will be called at some point. So 
what we are going to try to do is to get through our opening 
statements and the witnesses' opening statements and then take 
a short recess to go vote, and then we will be back.
    Well, again, I want to thank our witnesses for joining us 
today and our members. As the Seapower and Projection Forces 
Subcommittee chairman, I lead a group of my colleagues with 
broad jurisdiction over naval and Air Force programs. And I 
must admit that I have a particular affinity to the United 
States Marine Corps and its amphibious warfare role, because I 
represent Marine Corps Base Quantico in Virginia's First 
Congressional District.
    Because of my district and because of this subcommittee's 
jurisdiction, I am particularly interested in our subject today 
of assessing our Marine Corps' ability to project forces in a 
contested environment.
    Late last year, I was particularly intrigued to read a 
report authored by one of our witnesses today entitled 
``Advancing Beyond the Beach: Amphibious Operations in an Era 
of Precision Weapons.'' In this report, the authors propose 
that the current approach to amphibious operations needed, and 
I quote, ``new operating concepts and capabilities that 
circumvent or defeat increasingly effective coastal defenses.'' 
Their report proposes a new strategic approach that emphasizes 
lighter vehicles, a rebalancing of the surface and aviation 
assault capabilities, an emphasis on surface connectors that 
optimize ocean travel, and improved armament on amphibious 
ships.
    I believe that the Center for Strategic and Budgetary 
Assessment has accurately assessed the problems associated with 
amphibious assault in a contested environment.
    Projecting power in close proximity to shore in a contested 
environment is fraught with challenges which may require a 
shift in our approach. Fundamental changes to the Department of 
Navy's strategic amphibious warfare investments may be 
necessary to move more effectively above--to move Marines 
ashore. I believe that it is incumbent upon the Marine Corps to 
rapidly change their legacy force structure toward a capability 
that is more expeditionary, capable of fighting in the 
littorals, and, when called upon, able to project power ashore 
in even the most challenging of environments.
    To better assess this issue, I am pleased to have two 
respected authors on amphibious warfare with us today: Mr. 
Jesse Sloman, Center for Strategic and Budgetary Assessments; 
and Dr. Brad Martin of the RAND Corporation.
    Gentlemen, thank you for your willingness to testify before 
our subcommittee today, and I look forward to your assessment 
and recommendations to make our Marine Corps forces more lethal 
and effective than ever.
    I now would like to turn to our ranking member, Joe 
Courtney, for any opening remarks that he may have.
</option>
    <option>Appendix on page 27.]
</option>
    <option>   CONNECTICUT, RANKING MEMBER, SUBCOMMITTEE ON SEAPOWER AND 
                       PROJECTION FORCES
    Mr. Courtney. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, for holding this 
hearing on the future of amphibious warfare in a contested 
environment. As you noted, this has definitely been a real 
focus and passion of yours. So, again, we appreciate your 
leadership on this issue.
    As we have heard throughout our hearings this year, the 
U.S. Navy and Marine Corps team must be prepared to meet new 
challenges as our potential adversaries rapidly improve their 
tactics and technologies to counter America's longstanding 
superiority. This challenge is particularly true in examining 
the future of amphibious warfare.
    The United States Navy and Marine Corps team remains the 
most lethal and advanced amphibious force ever put to sea. As 
recent events around the world have shown, however, we cannot 
afford to rest on our laurels. Rather, we must continue to 
adapt and advance new technologies, tactics, and operational 
concepts to maintain our capacity to strike from the sea 
wherever needed and whenever called.
    However, we must also recognize the realities and 
limitations of existing platforms, equipment, and personnel who 
have not engaged in a contested amphibious assault from the sea 
in more than six decades. We must explore not only how these 
platforms can be modernized to maintain relevancy but also to 
examine how new technologies and operational concepts can be 
employed to ensure America's security and to respond to world 
crises.
    Since the cancellation of the expeditionary fighting 
vehicle in 2011--and I was trying to remember how many hearings 
we had on that; yeah, it was at least close to a half dozen 
before, finally, that decision was made--the Navy and Marine 
Corps have wrestled with what is the right distance for the 
Marines to disembark the ship and what type of vehicle that 
should be in. This is not an easy debate and is one I am sure 
we will talk more about today. However, there is more to this 
than just what distance an amphibious ship should launch its 
vehicles or what type of vehicle that should be. Our military 
is a joint force and will always operate that way in any 
contingency so that we need to be talking about how to fully 
integrate our amphibious forces and ensure that they are 
leveraging the technologies that other forces are relying on.
    I have no doubt of the value that our amphibious force 
provides in responding to an array of contingencies, from 
supporting noncombatant evacuation operations to being the on-
the-scene responder to the world's next humanitarian disaster. 
However, I also recognize that modeling, simulation, and 
exercises predicated on uncontested ambitious operations are 
becoming more outdated by the day. We must be trained, ready, 
and equipped to operate in a contested environment.
    Today, we welcome two experts in this field, Dr. Brad 
Martin and, a graduate of Tufts University, Mr. Jesse Sloman--
we don't see too many Jumbos here, so it is great as a graduate 
to see you here, Mr. Sloman--to help us better understand the 
many underlying challenges of operating in a contested littoral 
environment. I thank them for being here today. I look forward 
to your testimony.
    Mr. Wittman. Thank you, Mr. Courtney.
    We are going to go to our witnesses now.
    Dr. Martin, we will begin with your testimony. Then we will 
go to Mr. Sloman.
</option>
    <option>                          CORPORATION
    Dr. Martin. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Chairman Wittman, 
Ranking Member Courtney, I appreciate the opportunity----
    Mr. Wittman. Dr. Martin, just for a second, we will get you 
to pull that microphone closer to you. There you go.
    Dr. Martin. Okay. Well, Chairman Wittman, Ranking Member 
Courtney, I appreciate the chance to testify today.
    Amphibious operations in benign environments are obviously 
something that are of great importance to the Nation. 
Amphibious forces can be used across a range of military 
operations. And, in fact, they are a normally deploying part of 
our Nation's forward presence. They are marked by flexibility, 
mobility, and scalability, and they can be used in a variety of 
threat environments. They bring the virtue of capability that 
is based and sustained at sea with the ability to rapidly 
project various different types of capabilities ashore, ranging 
from the provision of humanitarian assistance, all the way 
through significant kinetic strikes.
    Navy and Marine Corps continue to make investments in force 
structure capabilities that will both improve and sustain these 
capabilities well into the future. However, a variety of actors 
have acquired ways to contest aspects of amphibious forces and 
landing force movement, and these range from the types of 
weapons that nonstate actors have used against forces in Iraq 
and Afghanistan, such as IEDs [improvised explosive devices] or 
explosive boats--or things of that nature, through more 
advanced and sophisticated systems, such as land-based 
missiles, all the way through sophisticated anti-access and 
area denial capabilities.
    In some of these cases, the threats are significant but 
manageable, but in the most stressing environments, those in 
which opponents have significant A2/AD capabilities, anti-
access/area denial capabilities, the challenges are 
significant, and there are some shortfalls that we are going to 
need to address in the near and far term, and much of my 
testimony deals with this.
    However, as we discuss this, it is important to remember as 
context that amphibious forces have always assumed a hostile 
environment requiring that the force overcome opposition. A 
benign environment was not and is not assumed to be necessary 
for operations to take place. Moreover, the threats posed in 
A2/AD environments face all conventional forces. So aircraft 
carrier strike groups, tactical aviation flying from fixed air 
bases, large ground force elements: All of those are things 
that have to be overcome if they are going to operate in a 
place where the enemy is making a significant attempt to deny 
access. So solving some of those problems for the amphibious 
force also assist in solving problems for these other forces.
    Navy and Marine Corps, to their credit, understand the 
challenges and have acted to meet them. The Navy continues to 
develop and purchase amphibious ships and surface connectors. 
The Marine Corps is experiencing significant improvement in its 
aviation capability, which I would describe as being nearly 
revolutionary, with the introduction of the CH-53 Kilo, MV-22 
Osprey, with its many variants, and, in particular, the F-35B. 
Moreover, the joint force continues to seek ways to effectively 
operate in an environment in which sophisticated anti-access/
area denial capabilities exist and need to be neutralized.
    There are, however, places where shortfalls could impact 
the ability to conduct future amphibious operations and warrant 
either additional investment and/or changes in operational 
concepts.
    The top three of these are--I hope we can get into more 
detail on each of them--is, first, the Navy continues to face 
difficulty fielding systems that deal with the threat from 
mines laid at sea and in the surf zone. Mines are relatively 
easy to acquire and deploy, and in some ways, the challenges 
posed are more direct against the amphibious force than they 
are against most others. And while there are promising efforts 
for unmanned solutions, this remains a challenging area as it 
has historically.
    And the second issue is the Marine Corps continues to 
require the movement of amphibious assault vehicles as a lead 
element in an assault echelon. The legacy amphibious assault 
vehicles required that the ships close the beach to 1 to 3 
miles to allow a launch. And this was a movement that both 
exposed the amphibious ship to threats, but perhaps more 
importantly, it telegraphed the force movement in ways it could 
endanger the landing force.
    And the program replacements that Marine Corps are looking 
at are improvement in terms of range and speed, but the most 
fundamental issue here may be requiring these to be among the--
or may be in requiring this type of force to be among the first 
elements ashore during ship-to-shore movement. This may be more 
a matter of changing operational concept and doctrine than 
investment in new capabilities.
    And, finally, while Navy and Marine Corps will be making 
near revolutionary--or Navy and Marine Corps, in particular, 
will be making near revolutionary improvement in its aviation 
capabilities, and while some of these may, in fact, be a big 
part of the solution to some of the challenges we have noted, 
it is not clear that the aviation support platforms that Navy 
is delivering are optimized to take advantage of this 
improvement.
    For example, the Marine Corps insisted that the well deck 
capability that was absent from the LHA 6 and 7 amphibious 
assault ships be put back in LHA 8. And while this was 
understandable, this was done at the expense of aviation 
maintenance and ordnance storage capability, and ship options 
that allow more spots, more ordnance, more aviation fuels and 
stores probably should be looked at as we move into the next--
into further development of the force structure.
    Now, to conclude, amphibious operations have never been 
conceived as occurring absent a threat. Combatant commanders 
value these forces, and Navy and Marine Corps have significant 
and well-thought-out investment strategies to retain many 
capabilities. However, there are some significant challenges--
some of them are very longstanding--that require conditional or 
additional emphasis.
    And so, with that, I will conclude and stand by for 
questions.
</option>
    <option>Appendix on page 29.]
    Mr. Wittman. Thank you, Dr. Martin.
    Mr. Sloman.
</option>
    <option>                     BUDGETARY ASSESSMENTS
    Mr. Sloman. Chairman Wittman, Ranking Member Courtney, and 
distinguished members of the committee, thank you for inviting 
me to testify today on the future of amphibious warfare in a 
contested environment.
    I wanted to make a few quick points regarding the current 
challenges the Navy and Marine Corps are facing and how they 
can overcome those challenges. The margin of superiority that 
the U.S. military can expect to enjoy on the battlefield has 
eroded over the last several decades as potential adversaries 
have developed new capabilities specifically intended to 
counter American strengths.
    Those capabilities mean that, in order to fully contribute 
to a campaign against a capable adversary, amphibious forces 
will need to adopt new concepts of operation and field new 
equipment or use existing equipment in novel ways.
    We also need to move beyond our bifurcated understanding of 
conducting amphibious operations whereby the Navy drives the 
Marines to the shore, then the Marines take over and execute a 
ground fight to one where we also acknowledge the contributions 
the Marine Corps can make to the Navy's fight for sea control. 
One of these new concepts is the use of expeditionary advanced 
bases. Advanced bases are small, temporary outposts that could 
constrain the enemy's freedom of action through anti-air or 
anti-ship attacks. For example, advanced bases positioned along 
island chains can employ anti-ship cruise missiles to form--
fired from mobile launchers to form a barrier to ships 
attempting to reach the open water.
    The Marine Corps should also expand the use of amphibious 
raids, a traditional Marine mission, to support sea control in 
littoral areas by attacking enemy anti-air and anti-ship 
missile batteries. And amphibious forces would be an important 
enabler for blockade operations because they would be able to 
contribute a large forwarding force as well as small craft to 
enable those forwardings.
    To execute these and other operations against future 
threats, the Navy and Marine Corps should prioritize six areas 
for investment.
    First, increase the armament of amphibious ships. 
Amphibious ships today contribute little to the strike capacity 
of U.S. naval forces beyond what is carried by their aircraft. 
The Navy should modify its small deck amphibious ships, so the 
LPD [amphibious transport dock] 17 and the follow-on LXR class, 
to include vertical launch systems so these platforms have a 
greater offensive and defensive capacity.
    Second, increase the size of the amphibious readiness group 
[ARG]. Today, the air element of a Marine expeditionary unit 
would be challenged to provide the volume of fires necessary to 
support the concepts described above. Adding more strike 
aircraft to the big deck ships in an ARG would displace rotary 
and platforms that are needed to allow the Marines to execute 
assault and airlift operations. Expanding the current three-
ship ARG to a four-ship formation that includes a third small 
deck amphibious ship would enable the Marines to field a force 
with more strike aircraft without sacrificing its airlift 
capacity.
    Third, expand the aviation capabilities of the amphibious 
assault ship. The LHA flight zero, LHA 6 and 7, sacrificed a 
well deck to increase their aviation capacity. The Navy and 
Marine Corps added a well deck back in for LHA flight 1 or LHAs 
8 and beyond, albeit at the loss of roughly half the vessel's 
aviation gas storage capacity.
    The only way that you can have a well deck and expanded 
aviation capacity in a ship is to have a bigger ship. One 
option is to lengthen the LHA flight 1 design, which would be 
similar to a course of action the Navy and Marine Corps 
examined in the mid-2000s for a ``plug plus'' variant of the 
LHD 8, which would lengthen the hull by about 80 feet and widen 
the flight deck by 10 feet. Eventually, the United States 
should consider developing a light aircraft carrier that 
potentially includes both a well deck and a catapult and 
arrested recovery system.
    Fourth, optimize surface connectors for ocean transit. 
Minimizing the on-land requirements for connectors would drive 
down costs while allowing the platforms to retain a high water 
speed, a characteristic that will be critical to their 
survivability. It would also drive us away from the problems we 
encountered with the expeditionary fighting vehicle where you 
try to have a high water speed and survivability on land, which 
means you end up with a surface connector that is suboptimal 
for driving on the ocean and a land vehicle that is suboptimal 
for operations on land.
    Fifth, the Marine Corps should acquire lighter vehicles. 
The Corps' ability to move forces ashore has been hampered by 
the steadily growing weight and size of its vehicles. To 
capitalize on the mobility of the V-22 Osprey, the Marines must 
continue to acquire vehicles and fire support systems small 
enough to fit aboard the Osprey. In addition, the Corps should 
prioritize modernizing and upgrading its existing light armored 
vehicles, which is the lightest armored vehicle in the Corps' 
inventory, and begin a new program to replace them with an 
entirely new vehicle that weighs the same amount or less.
    Lastly, the Corps should acquire cross-domain fires. The 
Marine Corps currently lacks the ability to influence the sea 
domain with its ground systems. The Corps should procure a 
multidomain weapon with an anti-ship and land-attack capability 
which can be fired by the Marine Corps HIMARS [high mobility 
artillery rocket system] launchers. The Corps should also 
acquire additional HIMARS launchers to supplement its two 
batteries of missile artillery--two battalions. Sorry.
    That concludes my prepared remarks. I look forward to your 
questions and want to thank you, again, for inviting me to 
speak here today. And go Jumbos.
</option>
</Hearing>
