<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing>
    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <Doc-title>COMPARING 21ST CENTURY TRUST LAND ACQUISITION WITH THE INTENT OF THE 73RD CONGRESS IN SECTION 5 OF THE INDIAN REORGANIZATION ACT</Doc-title>
    <option>      73RD CONGRESS IN SECTION 5 OF THE INDIAN REORGANIZATION ACT
=======================================================================
                           OVERSIGHT HEARING
                               before the
</option>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON INDIAN, INSULAR AND</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                         ALASKA NATIVE AFFAIRS
                                 of the
</option>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES</committee_name>
    <option>                     U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                        Thursday, July 13, 2017
                               __________
                           Serial No. 115-15
                               __________
       Printed for the use of the Committee on Natural Resources
         Available via the World Wide Web: http://www.fdsys.gov
                                   or
          Committee address: http://naturalresources.house.gov
                             _________ 
                U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
 26-253 PDF               WASHINGTON : 2017       
____________________________________________________________________
 For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing Office,
Internet:bookstore.gpo.gov. Phone:toll free (866)512-1800;DC area (202)512-1800
  Fax:(202) 512-2104 Mail:Stop IDCC,Washington,DC 20402-001               
</option>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES</comitteeM_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROB BISHOP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RAUL M. GRIJALVA</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ranking Democratic Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Don Young</Pname>
        <Plocation> AK</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Grace F. Napolitano</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Chairman Emeritus</Pname>
        <Plocation>Chairman Emeritus</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Madeleine Z. Bordallo</Pname>
        <Plocation> GU</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Louie Gohmert</Pname>
        <Plocation> TX</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jim Costa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Chairman</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Gregorio Kilili Camacho Sablan</Pname>
        <Plocation> </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug Lamborn</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CNMI</Pname>
        <Plocation>CNMI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Robert J. Wittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Niki Tsongas</Pname>
        <Plocation> MA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Tom McClintock</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jared Huffman</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Stevan Pearce</Pname>
        <Plocation> NM</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Ranking Member</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Ranking Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Glenn Thompson</Pname>
        <Plocation> PA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Alan S. Lowenthal</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul A. Gosar</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Donald S. Beyer</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Raul R. Labrador</Pname>
        <Plocation> ID</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Norma J. Torres</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Scott R. Tipton</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Ruben Gallego</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug LaMalfa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Colleen Hanabusa</Pname>
        <Plocation> HI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jeff Denham</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Nanette Diaz Barragan</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul Cook</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darren Soto</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Bruce Westerman</Pname>
        <Plocation> AR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>A. Donald McEachin</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Garret Graves</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Anthony G. Brown</Pname>
        <Plocation> MD</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jody B. Hice</Pname>
        <Plocation> GA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Wm. Lacy Clay</Pname>
        <Plocation> MO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Aumua Amata Coleman Radewagen</Pname>
        <Plocation> AS</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vacancy</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vacancy</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darin LaHood</Pname>
        <Plocation> IL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Daniel Webster</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jack Bergman</Pname>
        <Plocation> MI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Liz Cheney</Pname>
        <Plocation> WY</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Mike Johnson</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jenniffer Gonzalez-Colon</Pname>
        <Plocation> PR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Greg Gianforte</Pname>
        <Plocation> MT</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Todd Ungerecht</Pname>
        <Plocation> Acting Chief of Staff</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Lisa Pittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chief Counsel</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>David Watkins</Pname>
        <Plocation> Democratic Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON INDIAN, INSULAR AND ALASKA NATIVE AFFAIRS</subcomittee_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>DOUG LaMALFA</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>NORMA J. TORRES</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ranking Democratic Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Don Young</Pname>
        <Plocation> AK</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Madeleine Z. Bordallo</Pname>
        <Plocation> GU</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jeff Denham</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Gregorio Kilili Camacho Sablan</Pname>
        <Plocation> </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul Cook</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CNMI</Pname>
        <Plocation>CNMI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Aumua Amata Coleman Radewagen</Pname>
        <Plocation> AS</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Ruben Gallego</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darin LaHood</Pname>
        <Plocation> IL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darren Soto</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jack Bergman</Pname>
        <Plocation> MI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Colleen Hanabusa</Pname>
        <Plocation> HI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jenniffer Gonzalez-Colon</Pname>
        <Plocation> PR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Raul M. Grijalva</Pname>
        <Plocation> ex officio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Chairman</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Rob Bishop</Pname>
        <Plocation> ex officio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <table-of-content>CONTENTS</table-of-content>
    <peopleSpeaker>   Hearing held on Thursday</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>July</peopleinfo>
    <Members>Statement of Members:</Members>
    <Speaker>Hon Doug LaMalfa</Speaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of California Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>Statement of Witnesses:</witnesses>
    <Witness>Hon Norma J Torres</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of California Prepared statement of Allyn Hon Fred B</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>James Cason</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Acting Deputy Secretary US Department of the Interior</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon Kirk Francis</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>President United South and Eastern Tribes</peopleinfo>
    <submittedMaterial>Additional Materials Submitted for the Record:</submittedMaterial>
    <SubmittedMaterial>List of documents submitted for the record retained in the Committee's official files Uintah County</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>testimony dated July   submitted for the record by Chairman Bishop</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>OVERSIGHT HEARING ON COMPARING ST CENTURY TRUST LAND ACQUISITION WITH THE INTENT OF THE RD CONGRESS IN SECTION  OF THE INDIAN REORGANIZATION ACT  Thursday</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>US House of Representatives</peopleinfo>
    <subcomittee_name>Subcommittee on Indian, Insular and Alaska Native Affairs</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                     Committee on Natural Resources
                             Washington, DC
                              ----------                              
    The Subcommittee met, pursuant to notice, at 10:07 a.m., in 
room 1324, Longworth House Office Building, Hon. Doug LaMalfa 
[Chairman of the Subcommittee] presiding.
    Present: Representatives LaMalfa, Denham, Radewagen, 
Bergman, Bishop; Torres, Gallego, Soto, Hanabusa, and Grijalva.
    Mr. LaMalfa. The Subcommittee on Indian, Insular and Alaska 
Native Affairs will come to order.
    The Subcommittee is meeting today to hear testimony on 
comparing 21st century trust land acquisition with the intent 
of the 73rd Congress and Section 5 of the Indian Reorganization 
Act.
    Under Committee Rule 4(f) any oral opening statements at 
hearings are limited to the Chairman, the Ranking Minority 
Member, and the Vice Chair. This will allow us to hear from our 
witnesses sooner, and help Members keep to their schedules.
    Therefore, I ask unanimous consent that all other Members' 
opening statements be made part of the hearing record if they 
are submitted to the Subcommittee Clerk by 5:00 p.m. today.
    Without objection, so ordered.
</option>
    <option>             CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA
    Mr. LaMalfa. The purpose of today's hearing is to discuss 
how to resolve Carcieri v. Salazar, and how to address issues 
concerning Federal fee-to-trust policy. Carcieri was a lawsuit 
disputing the scope of the power of the Secretary of the 
Interior to take land into trust for tribes under the Indian 
Reorganization Act of 1934, or the IRA.
    Resolved by the Supreme Court in 2009, a majority of the 
Justices held that the Secretary of the Interior may put land 
into trust for tribes under the IRA only if the tribes were 
under Federal jurisdiction in 1934. This has called into 
question the status of lands previously taken in trust for 
tribes affected by the court's opinion, and it brings up issues 
relating to the Secretary's broad power under this Act. 
Moreover, the meaning of ``under Federal jurisdiction'' was not 
precisely defined by the court.
    Trust land is critical for tribes to exercise their unique 
powers of self-government, making resolution of Carcieri 
critical in order to provide certainty for them as they plan 
their tribal economies and govern their lands and members.
    To begin the discussion, we will hear testimony 
representing a variety of perspectives, beginning with the 
Department of the Interior.
    We will also hear from a witness representing a number of 
federally recognized tribes who say the administrative 
procedures the Secretary imposes on the acquisition of land in 
trust are very rigorous, and that changes to the IRA are not 
justified.
    We will also hear from a mayor of a town in Connecticut 
that has had to deal with the placement of lands in trust in 
his jurisdiction.
    And finally, we will hear from a private attorney who has 
testified before the Committee in the past, and brings his own 
perspective on what Congress intended when it wrote the IRA.
    It is hoped that after today we can consult with tribes and 
other interested parties on how best to resolve the issues 
posed in the Carcieri v. Salazar case.
</option>
    <option>Prepared Statement of the Hon. Doug LaMalfa, Chairman, Subcommittee on 
               Indian, Insular and Alaska Native Affairs
    The purpose of today's hearing is to discuss how to resolve 
Carcieri v. Salazar and how to address issues concerning Federal fee-
to-trust policy.
    Carcieri was a lawsuit disputing the scope of the power of the 
Secretary of the Interior to take land in trust for tribes under the 
Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, or ``IRA.''
    Resolved by the Supreme Court in 2009, a majority of the Justices 
held that the Secretary of the Interior may put land in trust for 
tribes under the IRA only if the tribes were ``under Federal 
jurisdiction'' in 1934.
    This has called into question the status of lands previously taken 
in trust for tribes affected by the Court's opinion, and it brings up 
issues relating to the Secretary's broad power under this Act. 
Moreover, the meaning of ``under Federal jurisdiction'' was not 
precisely defined by the Court.
    Trust land is critical for tribes to exercise their unique powers 
of self-government, making resolution of Carcieri critical in order to 
provide certainty for them as they plan their tribal economies and 
govern their lands and members.
    To begin the discussion, we'll hear testimony representing a 
variety of perspectives, beginning with the Department of the Interior.
    We'll also hear from a witness representing a number of federally 
recognized tribes, who say the administrative procedures the Secretary 
imposes on the acquisition of land in trust are very rigorous, and that 
changes to the IRA are not justified.
    We'll also hear from a mayor of a town in Connecticut that has had 
to deal with the placement of lands in trust in its jurisdiction, and 
we'll finally hear from a private attorney who has testified before the 
Committee in the past, and brings his own perspective on what Congress 
intended when it wrote the IRA.
    It is hoped that after today, we can consult with tribes and other 
interested parties on determining how best to resolve the issues posed 
in Carcieri v. Salazar.
                                 ______
    Mr. LaMalfa. With that, I would like to now recognize our 
Ranking Minority Member, Mrs. Torres, for her statement.
</option>
    <option>             CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA
    Mrs. Torres. Thank you, and good morning, Mr. Chairman. And 
good morning to everyone that has joined us today.
    Throughout our Nation's history, tribes have suffered abuse 
and ongoing indignity at the hands of the Federal Government. 
They have had their lands taken away, communities ripped apart, 
their culture and tribal identity stamped out.
    The shameful allotment and assimilation periods of the late 
19th and 20th century was nothing short of a disastrous time 
for Native people, leading to extreme poverty, poor health 
conditions, horrendous living conditions, not to mention 
addictions.
    In 1934, however, we thankfully changed course. And through 
the Indian Reorganization Act we began to right some of those 
wrongs by putting a stop to the allotment of Indian lands and 
placing lands into trust on behalf of tribes. While we can 
never fully make up for what took place, there is no question 
that the return of land to its rightful owners', the tribes, 
was and continues to be critical to restoring the tribal way of 
life.
    Despite the progress that the IRA accomplished, it still 
has returned less than 10 percent of the roughly 90 million 
acres that were taken from tribes. Some claim the process was a 
free-for-all, but the numbers just don't back that up. And this 
certainly is not about casinos, given that the majority of 
applications aren't for gaming purposes.
    Tribes need this land for self-sustainability, to create 
economic development opportunities, for housing, for hospitals 
and clinics, and for elder care facilities. This land is needed 
to ensure the well-being of the people, to preserve their 
culture, and to pass it down to future generations. This is why 
the Carcieri decision has been so troubling in Indian Country.
    That decision unraveled 75 years of agency practice, and in 
the process, it has created a two-tiered system for Federal-
tribal relationships. Tribes deserve certainty and clarity in 
dealing with the Federal Government, but because of the 
Carcieri decision, this is not possible.
    This could easily be remedied by passage of a clean 
Carcieri fix, such as H.R. 130, introduced by our colleague 
from Oklahoma, Mr. Cole. This bipartisan bill would amend the 
language of the IRA, and re-establish the Secretary's authority 
to take land into trust for all tribes, simply reaffirming what 
the drafters of the IRA intended all along.
    Mr. Chairman, through this process we must ensure that 
tribes are treated with the fairness and dignity they 
rightfully deserve. We must ensure that their input is heard in 
the process, and that land acquisition for tribes remains a 
priority for our Nation. Through our long friendship and 
relationship, I know that you are willing to work together to 
do right by our tribal communities.
    I want to thank you and I want to thank the witnesses for 
being here today. I yield back.
</option>
    <option>    Prepared Statement of the Hon. Norma J. Torres, Ranking Member, 
</option>
    <option>Subcommittee on Indian, Insular and Alaska Native Affairs</option>
    <option>    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    Throughout our Nation's history, tribes have suffered abuse and 
indignity at the hands of the Federal Government. They had their lands 
taken away, communities ripped apart, and culture and tribal identity 
stamped out.
    The shameful Allotment and Assimilation periods of the late 19th 
and 20th century was nothing short of disastrous for Native peoples, 
leading to extreme poverty, poor health conditions, and horrendous 
living conditions.
    In 1934, however, we thankfully changed course and the Indian 
Reorganization Act at least helped to right some of those wrongs by 
putting a stop to the allotment of Indian lands and placing lands into 
trust for tribes.
    While we can never fully make up for what took place, there is no 
question that the return of land to the tribes was and continues to be 
critical to restoring the tribal way of life. Despite the progress that 
the IRA accomplished, it still has only returned less than 10 percent 
of the roughly 90 million acres that were taken from tribes.
    While some claim the process was a free-for-all, the numbers just 
don't back that up, and this most certainly isn't about casinos, given 
that the majority of applications aren't for gaming purposes.
    This is land for other economic development opportunities, for 
housing, for hospitals and clinics, and elder care facilities. This is 
land to ensure the well-being of their people and to pass down to 
future generations.
    This is why the Carcieri decision has been so troubling in Indian 
Country. That decision unwound 75 years of agency practice, and in the 
process it has created a two-tiered system for Federal-tribal 
relationships.
    Tribes deserve certainty and clarity in their dealings with the 
Federal Government regarding these trust lands, but because of the 
Carcieri decision this is not possible.
    This could easily be remedied by passage of a ``clean'' Carcieri 
fix, such as H.R. 130, introduced by our colleague from Oklahoma, Mr. 
Cole.
    This bipartisan bill would amend the language of the IRA to re-
establish the Secretary's authority to take land into trust for all 
tribes, simply reaffirming what the drafters of the IRA intended all 
along.
    Mr. Chairman, we must ensure that tribes are treated with the 
fairness and dignity they rightfully deserve, that their input is heard 
in the process, and that land acquisition for tribes remains a priority 
for our Nation. From our long relationship, I know you are willing to 
work together to do right by our tribal communities.
    I want to thank all our witnesses for taking the time to share 
their thoughts and opinions on these important matters, and I yield 
back the reminder of my time.
                                 ______
    Mr. LaMalfa. Thank you. I am recognizing we have our 
Ranking Member of the Full Committee, Mr. Grijalva, here.
    Do you have a statement you would like to make?
    Mr. Grijalva. No, thank you, Mr. Chair.
    Mr. LaMalfa. OK, all right. Thank you. I will now introduce 
our witnesses here today.
    We have Mr. James Cason, who is Acting Deputy Secretary of 
the U.S. Department of the Interior, thanks for being here once 
again; the Honorable Kirk Francis, President of the United 
South and Eastern Tribes; the Honorable Fred B. Allyn III, 
Mayor of the Town of Ledyard; and Mr. Donald Mitchell, Attorney 
at Law. Thank you for joining us.
    I will remind the witnesses that under Committee Rules they 
must limit their oral statements to 5 minutes. Their entire 
statement will appear in the hearing record.
    Our microphones are not automatic. You know the drill. 
Press the button for on. When you begin your testimony, you 
will have a green light for 4 minutes, a yellow light for 1 
minute, and then a red light, you know what that means. I will 
ask you to complete your statement at that point.
    I will also allow the entire panel to testify before we 
will start questioning the witnesses.
    The Chair will now recognize Mr. Cason to testify for 5 
minutes.
</option>
    <option>           DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR, WASHINGTON, DC
    Mr. Cason. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Chairman LaMalfa, 
Ranking Member Torres, and members of the Subcommittee, my name 
is Jim Cason. I am currently serving as the Acting Deputy 
Secretary for the Department of the Interior. Thank you for the 
opportunity to testify before this Committee on the 
Department's role on the acquisition of trust lands for 
federally recognized tribes across the country.
    Interior believes the process of trust land acquisition for 
on-reservation parcels is an important and routine matter that 
creates economic drivers for tribes. However, taking off-
reservation lands into trust may pose complications for the 
Department, as well as some members of the public, particularly 
when fee-to-trust applications are for gaming purposes.
    Off-reservation lands that are required through the fee-to-
trust process have the potential to create uncertainties in 
local communities, as well as complicate land use planning 
efforts and the provision of services. As a result, the 
Department's off-reservation trust regulations require 
particular attention to issues of jurisdiction and taxation.
    Taking off-reservation land into trust can be further 
complicated by the prospect of Indian gaming. Such acquisitions 
raise the possibility that a tribe may initiate gaming 
operations once the land is held in trust by the Federal 
Government, even though that was not the original plan. Local 
communities that may have supported land into trust may not 
support gaming, and this creates an entirely new predicament, 
requiring a new public input process.
    It is our understanding that Interior generally lacks the 
authority to restrict the use of trust lands, as it would be an 
infringement upon tribal sovereignty and self government. This 
is why Congress will play a pivotal role in shaping the path 
the Department takes in approving future gaming operations.
    Congress has the sole authority to evaluate and amend 
existing statutes and determine if the existing fee-to-trust 
statutes need to be constrained or expanded. The Department 
welcomes the opportunity to work with the Committee to discuss 
Congress' recommendations for reasonable policies, and to 
modernize the broader land-into-trust process.
    Thank you for your time; I am pleased to answer questions 
that you may have. Thanks.
</option>
    <option>   Prepared Statement of James Cason, Acting Deputy Secretary, U.S. 
                       Department of the Interior
    Chairman LaMalfa, Ranking Member Torres, and members of the 
Subcommittee, my name is Jim Cason. I am currently serving as the 
Acting Deputy Secretary of the Department of the Interior (Department 
or Interior). Thank you for the opportunity to testify before this 
Committee on the Department's role in the acquisition of trust lands 
for federally recognized tribes across the country.
    The Indian Reorganization Act (IRA) [48 Stat. 984, 25 U.S.C. 
Sec. 5108 et seq. (June 18, 1934)] provides the Secretary of the 
Department of the Interior with the discretion to acquire trust title 
to land or interests in land for tribes. Congress may also authorize 
the Secretary to acquire title to particular land and interests in land 
into trust under statutes other than the IRA.
    The Secretary bases the decision to make a trust acquisition on the 
evaluation of the criteria set forth in Title 25 Code of Federal 
Regulations (CFR) Part 151, which derive from the Department's 
interpretation of the IRA and its purposes. With the exception of 
certain mandatory acquisitions, the decision to acquire title requires 
approval of the Secretary or his designee.
    Fee-to-trust applications involve the acquisition in trust of whole 
or undivided interests in land held in fee. On-reservation 
Discretionary Trust Acquisitions are governed by 25 CFR Sec. 151.10, 
Off-reservation Discretionary Trust Acquisitions are governed by 25 CFR 
Sec. 151.11, and Mandatory Trust Acquisitions are outlined in 
Department policy. The Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA) staff follow 
procedures outlined in Interior-BIA's ``Acquisition of Title to Land 
Held in Fee or Restricted Fee Status Handbook'' to implement the 
regulations governing Fee-to-Trust transactions.
    When the BIA receives a complete Fee-to-Trust application, the BIA 
Regional Office with jurisdiction over the land issues a ``Notice of 
(Non-Gaming) Land Acquisition Application'' to obtain state and local 
government comments to the application. Regional offices then follow 
the Fee-to-Trust Handbook by providing a period of 30 days for 
collection of comments to the proposed transaction. The BIA forwards 
all comments to the Applicant, who then has 30 days to provide the BIA 
a response. However, the Applicant may decline to provide responses to 
comments and request the Secretary issue a decision.
    Review of the Fee-to-Trust applications requires BIA to consider 
the type of environmental analysis appropriate for the property and its 
intended use. Applications may receive review under a Categorical 
Exclusion, Environmental Assessment, or Environmental Impact Statement.
    The Department plays a critical role in the fee to trust process as 
a means to restore and bolster self-determination and sovereignty in 
Indian Country. The benefits to tribes are twofold. First, restoration 
of tribal land bases reconnects fractionated interests and provides 
protections for important tribal cultures, traditions, and histories. 
Second, the connectivity that occurs when land is placed into trust 
enables tribes to foster economic potential. From energy development to 
agriculture, trust acquisitions provide tribes the flexibility to 
negotiate leases, create business opportunities, and identify the best 
possible means to use and sell available natural resources.
    The examples of successful fee to trust acquisitions, particularly 
on-reservation, are extensive. For instance, the Rosebud Sioux Tribe's 
successfully brought into trust the Mustang Meadows Property, totaling 
18,761.60 acres, on October 23, 2002. The land is now used for 
agricultural and farm pasture purposes and managed by the Tribe's 
Tribal Land Enterprise. The Reno-Sparks Indian Colony of Nevada (RSIC) 
was also extremely successful with its on-reservation Fee-to-Trust 
acquisition for economic development projects. RSIC now has several 
major car dealerships and a Walmart Superstore on its lands in Reno and 
Sparks, Nevada. It also has a modern tribal health center on the land 
to provide services to its members and other urban Indians.
    Interior believes the process of trust land acquisition for parcels 
identified on-reservation is an important and routine matter that 
results in the reconnection of critical land bases, thereby creating 
economic drivers for tribes. We note, however, that taking off-
reservation lands into trust may pose complications for the Department 
as well as some members of the public, particularly when the Fee-to-
Trust application is for gaming purposes, although the Department 
receives only a minor percentage of applications for gaming versus 
other applications.
    Overall, land into trust acquisitions are uncontested transfers 
that often have local support. Off-reservation lands that are acquired 
through the Fee-to-Trust process have the potential to raise 
jurisdictional uncertainties in local communities, as well as 
complicating land-use planning and the provision of services. Moreover, 
non-Indian communities may experience tax revenue consequences 
especially if payments in lieu of taxes are not agreed upon. 
Ultimately, the Department has received comments that taking land 
located off-reservation into trust can introduce economic and other 
conditions that can have significant impacts on the immediate and 
surrounding communities. As a result, the Department's off-reservation 
trust regulations require particular attention to issues of 
jurisdiction and taxation.
    Taking off-reservation land into trust can be further complicated 
by the prospect of Indian gaming. This matter, which I worked on during 
my previous tenure at the Department, continues to complicate and 
isolate some communities near these facilities. Such acquisitions also 
raise the possibility that a tribe may initiate gaming operations once 
the land is held in trust by the Federal Government, even though that 
was not in the original plan. If gaming is initiated once the land is 
held in trust by the Federal Government, it is regulated by the 
National Indian Gaming Commission under the Indian Gaming Regulatory 
Act. Local communities that may have supported land into trust may not 
support gaming, and this could create an entirely new predicament for 
them as they would need to engage in a new public input process.
    This possibility has prompted questions regarding what role the 
Department could play in establishing land use restrictions to halt 
certain lands from being used for gaming. It is our understanding that 
Interior generally lacks the authority to restrict the use of trust 
lands as this would be an infringement upon tribal sovereignty and 
self-government. Therefore, Congress will play a pivotal role in 
shaping the path the Department takes for approving future gaming 
decisions.
    Considering these challenges, Interior acknowledges the original 
legislation intended to address land into trust matters does not always 
meet the 21st century challenges we face. Congress, as the trust 
settlor for all Indian Affairs matters, has the sole authority to 
evaluate and amend existing statutes, including the Indian 
Reorganization Act, to determine if the existing Fee-to-Trust statutes 
need to be constrained or expanded. The Department welcomes the 
opportunity to work with the Committee to discuss Congress' 
recommendations for reasonable policies to modernize the broader land 
into trust process.
    This concludes my written statement. Thank you for your time, and I 
am pleased to answer any questions you may have.
                                 ______
  Questions Submitted for the Record by Chairman Rob Bishop to Acting 
     Deputy Secretary James Cason, U.S. Department of the Interior
Mr. Cason did not submit responses to the Committee by the appropriate 
deadline for inclusion in the printed record.
    Question 1. Based on the Department's actions in the Mashpee Tribe 
matter, it is clear that the current Administration has problems with 
the approach used by the Obama administration in using Section 5 of the 
IRA, as interpreted by the Supreme Court in the Carcieri decision, to 
acquire land in trust for the Mashpee Tribe. What steps will you take 
to bring the principles that govern trust land acquisition into line 
with that decision, including for decisions made under the previous 
administration?
    Question 2. Would you like Congress to establish clear standards on 
how the Secretary's authority under Section 5 of the IRA should be 
applied?
    Question 3. Does the Department plan to revise the Department's 
trust land regulations under 25 CFR Part 151? If so, what type of 
revisions does the Department plan to make?
    Question 4. What criteria does the Department use to determine a 
tribe's need for additional trust land? Please provide examples of 
Departmental findings of insufficient need. What criteria does the 
Department use to determine that tax and jurisdictional impacts to 
local governments are too great to justify a trust acquisition? Please 
provide examples.
    Question 5. In what ways is Solicitor's M-Opinion numbered M-37029 
deficient, given your testimony that its criteria are too ``loose,'' it 
does not respond to the Carcieri decision, and it has no distinguishing 
effect among tribes? Given this testimony, does the Department intend 
to replace the M-Opinion?
    Question 6. What is the Department's authority to take land out of 
trust to correct an error in the decision to acquire land in trust? 
What is the mechanism or instrument to do so?
    Question 7. Given your testimony that the Department may address 
``dual taxation'' in revisions to the Indian Trader regulations, what 
is the Secretary's authority to pre-empt state and local taxation of 
non-Indian economic activities on Indian lands by regulation? Can the 
Secretary by regulation define which government (tribal or non-tribal) 
may exercise authority over anyone engaged in economic activities on 
Indian lands?
                                 ______
    Mr. LaMalfa. All right. Thank you, Mr. Cason.
    The Chair now recognizes Mr. Francis to testify for 5 
minutes.
</option>
    <option>                 EASTERN TRIBES, WASHINGTON, DC
    Mr. Francis. Good morning Chairman, Ranking Member, members 
of the Subcommittee. Thank you for this opportunity to provide 
comments on the intent of the Indian Reorganization Act. I am 
here today in my capacity as President of the United South and 
Eastern Tribes' Sovereignty Protection Fund, an intertribal 
organization representing 26 federally recognized tribal 
nations from Texas across to Florida and up to Maine. I also 
serve as Chief of the Penobscot Nation.
    The Department of the Interior's implementation of its 
trust acquisition authority pursuant to the Indian 
Reorganization Act is fully consistent with the intent of the 
73rd Congress. However, the goals of the IRA remain 
unfulfilled. In the decades since the IRA's 1934 passage, the 
Department has acted consistent with the law to restore tribal 
homelands. But to date, only about 10 percent of the tribal 
lands lost have been restored.
    The IRA was enacted in pursuit of policy goals that are 
still relevant today. Primary among these is to rebuild tribal 
nations' land bases following nearly 200 years of systematic 
dispossession by the United States, so that we may exercise 
jurisdiction over our land and rebuild our economies for the 
benefit of our people. When this happens, surrounding 
communities, and the United States as a whole, benefit from the 
economic prosperity generated.
    In 1491, all 2.3 billion acres of what would become the 
United States was Indian Country. By 1887, tribal nation land 
holdings had fallen to 138 million acres. That year, Congress 
passed the General Allotment Act, which further reduced land 
holdings to 48 million acres by 1934, a loss of 90 million 
acres. And that does not account for the countless millions of 
acres lost prior to 1887 under different state and Federal 
actions.
    This loss of land resulted in tribal nations lacking the 
necessary jurisdiction and economic resources to care for their 
citizens, and left them heavily dependent on the Federal 
Government. According to a 1934 House Report, Congress' goal in 
enacting the IRA was to rehabilitate the Indian's economic 
life, and to give him a chance to develop the initiative 
destroyed by a century of oppression and paternalism. Without 
this law, you would not see the progress that tribes have made 
in recent decades.
    We note that this Subcommittee's priorities include 
economic development, infrastructure, energy dependence for 
tribal nations, none of which can happen without trust land and 
certainty in its status.
    My own tribe, federally recognized in 1976, thanks the 73rd 
Congress and every Congress after that for their practice. We 
have been able to obtain over 120,000 acres of our homeland to 
develop alternative energy projects and create housing 
opportunities for our citizens. It has been invaluable.
    The IRA responded to this devastation of the Allotment Act 
and other past policies, signaling a dramatic shift in Federal 
Indian policy. Congress did not undertake the enactment of the 
IRA lightly. The IRA's enactment was preceded by consultation 
with tribal nations, straw votes among tribal nation 
citizenships, extensive public debate, and lengthy hearings 
before Congress.
    Today, the Department follows a very rigorous process, 
requiring 16 distinct and transparent steps before land is 
taken into trust. This process includes full consideration of 
local interests before a decision is made. For off-reservation 
acquisitions, the further the land being acquired is from the 
reservation, the greater the weight the Department must give to 
concerns raised by non-Indian interests.
    Thus, legitimate local and other considerations can be 
addressed through the administrative process. They do not 
require statutory changes. And any suggested revisions must be 
subject to extensive tribal consultation and dialogue.
    It is important to note that this law was enacted for the 
benefit of tribal nations, and concerns only the relationship 
between the Federal Government and tribal nations. With all due 
respect to my fellow panelists, other interests are not part of 
this sacred relationship.
    The only appropriate change to the IRA at this time is the 
one tribal nations have been requesting for 8 years, one that 
reaffirms the Secretary's authority to take land into trust for 
all federally recognized tribal nations, and affirms the trust 
status of lands already in trust. Representative Cole has 
introduced legislation addressing this fix. This, and not 
unrelated issues, should be the focus of the Subcommittee 
related to the IRA.
    Finally, because the issues being considered here today 
have potential impact on all 567 tribal nations, I urge you all 
to engage with Indian Country in a deep and meaningful dialogue 
on land into trust prior to taking any legislative or 
administrative actions.
    I thank the Subcommittee for taking the time to conduct 
this hearing. The importance of the IRA and its trust land 
provisions to tribal nations today cannot be overstated. I am 
happy to answer any questions. Thank you again.
</option>
    <option> Prepared Statement of the Hon. Kirk Francis, United South and Eastern 
                   Tribes Sovereignty Protection Fund
    Chairman LaMalfa, Vice-Chairman Gonzalez-Colon, Ranking Member 
Torres, and members of the Subcommittee, thank you for this opportunity 
to provide comments on the topic of ``Comparing 21st Century Trust Land 
Acquisition with the Intent of the 73rd Congress in Section 5 of the 
Indian Reorganization Act.''
    The United South and Eastern Tribes Sovereignty Protection Fund 
(USET SPF) is an inter-tribal organization representing 26 federally 
recognized Tribal Nations from Texas across to Florida and up to 
Maine.\1\ Due to their location in the south and eastern regions of the 
United States, the USET SPF-member Tribal Nations have the longest 
continuous direct relationship with the U.S. government, dating back to 
some of the earliest treaties. One great consequence of this 
relationship has been the steady loss of Tribal Nations' land. Indeed, 
USET SPF-member Tribal Nations retain only small remnants of their 
original homelands today. As a result, the trust land acquisition 
authority of the Indian Reorganization Act (IRA) is of particular 
significance and importance to them.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \1\ USET SPF member Tribal Nations include the following: Alabama-
Coushatta Tribe of Texas (TX), Aroostook Band of Micmac Indians (ME), 
Catawba Indian Nation (SC), Cayuga Nation (NY), Chitimacha Tribe of 
Louisiana (LA), Coushatta Tribe of Louisiana (LA), Eastern Band of 
Cherokee Indians (NC), Houlton Band of Maliseet Indians (ME), Jena Band 
of Choctaw Indians (LA), Mashantucket Pequot Indian Tribe (CT), Mashpee 
Wampanoag Tribe (MA), Miccosukee Tribe of Indians of Florida (FL), 
Mississippi Band of Choctaw Indians (MS), Mohegan Tribe of Indians of 
Connecticut (CT), Narragansett Indian Tribe (RI), Oneida Indian Nation 
(NY), Passamaquoddy Tribe at Indian Township (ME), Passamaquoddy Tribe 
at Pleasant Point (ME), Penobscot Indian Nation (ME), Poarch Band of 
Creek Indians (AL), Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe (NY), Seminole Tribe of 
Florida (FL), Seneca Nation of Indians (NY), Shinnecock Indian Nation 
(NY), Tunica-Biloxi Tribe of Louisiana (LA), and Wampanoag Tribe of Gay 
Head (Aquinnah) (MA).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The Department of the Interior (Department) implements the IRA's 
Section 5 trust land acquisition authority in accordance with the 
intent of the 73rd Congress and within the limits defined by the 
Supreme Court. The 73rd Congress' purposes of facilitating Tribal 
Nations' self-governance and self-sufficiency in enacting the IRA's 
trust land acquisition authority are still relevant and necessary 
today. Further, the Department's implementation of its IRA trust land 
acquisition authority complies with the parameters and purposes of the 
IRA, including adequately considering the impacts on local interests 
and properly complying with the Supreme Court's decision in Cariceri v. 
Salazar. Therefore, USET SPF unequivocally opposes any update to the 
IRA's Section 5 trust acquisition authority that would change existing 
standards or criteria, amounting to an attack on the continued vitality 
of the IRA's trust land acquisition authority, and it believes 
administrative procedures rather than statutory procedures should 
implement its enduring purposes. The only appropriate change to the IRA 
at this time would be to amend Section 19's first definition of 
``Indian'' to assure that all Tribal Nations can take land into trust 
on an equal basis and, thus, correct the inequity resulting from the 
Caricieri decision.
              The History and Enduring Purposes of the IRA
    In 1977, after 2 years of study, Representative Young, along with 
his fellow commissioners on the American Indian Policy Review 
Commission, submitted to Congress a final report on the status of 
Indian people in America with recommendations for changes in Federal 
Indian law and policy. In its opening pages, the Commission wrote: ``To 
adequately formulate a future Indian policy it is necessary to 
understand the policies of the past.'' \2\ As this Subcommittee now 
considers the trust land acquisition authority under the IRA, it is 
necessary to look back to the purposes and goals that defined the 
content and design of the IRA. Looking back, we find that the IRA was 
enacted in furtherance of policy goals that are still applicable today, 
and that it was designed to provide powerful tools to address problems 
that persist even now. Chief among these is the need to rebuild Tribal 
Nation land bases following nearly 200 years of systematic 
dispossession, from which Indian Country is still reeling, so that 
Tribal Nations may exercise jurisdiction over their land and provide 
for their people.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \2\ American Indian Policy Review Commission, Final Report 3 (1977) 
(``It has been the fortune of this Commission to be the first in the 
long history of this Nation to listen attentively to the voice of the 
Indian rather than the Indian expert. The findings and recommendations 
which appear in this report are founded on that Indian voice. It can 
only be hoped that this Commission will be seen as a watershed in the 
long and often tarnished history of this country's treatment of its 
original people. What are the explanations for the circumstances in 
which the Indian finds himself today? First and foremost are the 
consistently damaging Federal policies of the past--policies which 
sought through the first three-quarters of the 19th century to remove 
the Indian people from the midst of the European settlers by isolating 
them on reservations; and policies which after accomplishing isolation 
were then directed toward breaking down their social and governmental 
structures and throwing their land, water, timber and mineral resources 
open to exploitation by non-Indians. These policies were repudiated by 
Congress with passage of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, but by 
this time severe damage had been done.'').
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The size of the United States is 2.3 billion acres, which was once 
all Indian Country. In 1887, within the lifetime of our grandparents, 
residual Tribal Nation landholdings, often established by treaty, were 
at 138 million acres. That year, Congress passed the General Allotment 
Act (GAA),\3\ which further reduced Tribal Nation landholdings to 48 
million acres by 1934--a loss of 90 million acres.\4\ Of course, Indian 
Country's dramatic loss of land had an inverse effect of providing an 
extraordinary gain for non-Indians and the surrounding state, county, 
and local jurisdictions, which took control of the land.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \3\ 25 U.S.C. Sec. Sec. 331 et. seq.
    \4\ Cohen's Handbook of Federal Indian Law Sec. 15.07[1][a] (2012 
ed.) (citing Readjustment of Indian Affairs: Hearings on H.R. 7902 
Before the H. Comm. on Indian Affairs, 73d Cong. 2d Sess. 16 (1934) 
(Memorandum of John Collier, Commissioner of Indian Affairs); see also 
73rd Cong. Rec. 11726 (Daily ed. June 15, 1934) (Statement by Rep. 
Howard).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The assimilationist policy characterized by the GAA was designed to 
break up Tribal Nation landholdings in order to ``put an end to tribal 
organization'' and to ``dealings with Indians . . . as tribes.'' \5\ In 
the end, this loss of land resulted in Tribal Nations lacking the 
necessary jurisdiction and economic resources to care for their people 
and left them heavily dependent on the Federal Government. The failure 
of the assimilation and allotment policies was thoroughly documented in 
the 1928 Meriam Report, which revealed that the vast majority of 
Indians were living in extreme poverty and suffered from poor health, 
substandard living conditions, and a lack of access to educational or 
vocational opportunities.\6\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \5\ See United States v. Celestine, 215 U.S. 278, 290 (1909).
    \6\ Institute for Governmental Research, The Problem of Indian 
Administration (Lewis Meriam ed., Johns Hopkins Press 1928).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The IRA, enacted in 1934, was a specific congressional response to 
the impoverishing and limiting effects of the GAA and other past 
policies on Tribal Nations and Indian people, and it signaled a 
dramatic shift in Federal Indian policy.\7\ Congress did not undertake 
enactment of the IRA lightly. The IRA's enactment was preceded by 
consultations with Tribal Nations, straw votes among Tribal Nation 
citizenships, extensive public debate, and lengthy hearings before 
Congress.\8\ For this reason, we have extensive legislative history 
shedding light on the 73rd Congress' intentions in enacting the IRA.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \7\ 25 U.S.C. Sec. Sec. 5101 et seq.
    \8\ Readjustment of Indian Affairs: Hearings on H.R. 7902 Before H. 
Comm. on Indian Affairs, 73d Cong. 2d Sess. (1934); To Grant Indians 
Living Under Federal Tutelage the Freedom to Organize for Purposes of 
Local Self-Government and Economic Enterprise: Hearings on S. 2755 and 
S. 3645, 73d Cong. 2d Sess. (1934). See also S. Rep. No. 73-1080 
(1934); H.R. Rep. No. 73-1804 (1934); H.R. Rep. No. 73-2049 (1934).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The IRA's main purpose was and is to facilitate Tribal Nation self-
governance, self-determination, and self-sufficiency in order to 
improve the lives of Indian people. According to the 73rd Congress, its 
overarching goal in enacting the IRA was ``to rehabilitate the Indian's 
economic life and to give him a chance to develop the initiative 
destroyed by a century of oppression and paternalism.'' \9\ The Supreme 
Court later explained that the IRA was designed with the ``over-riding 
purpose'' of ``establish[ing] machinery whereby Indian tribes would be 
able to assume a greater degree of self-government, both politically 
and economically.'' \10\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \9\ H.R. Rep. No. 1804, 73d Cong., 2d Sess., 6 (1934).
    \10\ Morton v. Mancari, 417 U.S. 535, 542 (1974); see also 
Mescalero Apache Tribe v. Jones, 411 U.S. 145, 151-52 (1973) (quoting 
H.R. Rep. No. 1804, 73d Cong., 2d Sess., 6 (1934)).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    A central feature of the IRA intended to strengthen Tribal Nation 
self-government and self-sufficiency was a set of provisions aimed at 
protecting and rebuilding Tribal Nations' land bases. In Section 5, it 
authorized the Department ``to acquire, through purchase, 
relinquishment, gift, exchange, or assignment, any interest in lands, 
water rights, or surface rights to lands, within or without existing 
reservations, including trust or otherwise restricted allotments, 
whether the allottee be living or deceased, for the purpose of 
providing land for Indians.'' \11\ The IRA provided that title to such 
acquired lands ``shall be taken in the name of the United States in 
trust for the Indian Tribe or individual Indian for which the land is 
acquired, and such lands or rights shall be exempt from state and local 
taxation.'' \12\ In order to maintain and protect lands already held 
for Tribal Nations, the IRA also prohibited any further allotment of 
reservation lands,\13\ extended indefinitely the periods of trust or 
restrictions on individual Indians' trust lands,\14\ provided for the 
restoration of surplus unallotted lands to Tribal Nation ownership,\15\ 
and prohibited any transfer of restricted Tribal Nations' or individual 
Indians' lands, with limited exceptions, other than to the Tribal 
Nation or by inheritance.\16\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \11\ Id. at Sec. 5 (codified at 25 U.S.C. Sec. 5108).
    \12\ Id.
    \13\ Id. at Sec. 1 (codified at 25 U.S.C. Sec. 5101).
    \14\ Id. at Sec. 2 (codified at 25 U.S.C. Sec. 5102).
    \15\ Id. at Sec. 3(a) (codified at 25 U.S.C. Sec. 5103(a)).
    \16\ Id. at Sec. 4 (codified at 25 U.S.C. Sec. 5107).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Regaining a land base is essential to the exercise of Tribal self-
government. When the Federal Government holds land in trust for a 
Tribal Nation, the Tribal Nation is able to exercise jurisdiction over 
the land, including over individuals' actions and over taxation.\17\ 
This jurisdiction allows the Tribal Nation to protect its people and to 
generate economic growth, which in turn encourages the flourishing of 
the Tribal Nation's cultural practices. United States courts have 
determined that, even when a Tribal Nation uses its own funds to 
purchase title to land, the Tribal Nation may not be permitted to 
exercise jurisdiction over the land without something more, often 
taking the form of trust acquisition. Thus, the IRA provides Tribal 
Nations an avenue to gain jurisdiction over their land. Jurisdiction 
over territory is a bedrock principle of sovereignty, and Tribal 
Nations must exercise such jurisdiction in order to fully implement the 
inherent sovereignty they possess. Just as states exercise jurisdiction 
over their land, Tribal Nations must also exercise jurisdiction, 
thereby promoting government fairness and parity between state 
governments and Tribal Nation governments.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \17\ See 18 U.S.C. Sec. 1151 (defining ``Indian Country'').
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Congressional representatives of the 73rd Congress who debated and 
discussed enactment of the IRA uniformly understood that one of the 
main purposes of the IRA was to provide a mechanism whereby the 
Department could acquire land into trust for Tribal Nations.\18\ 
Congress designed the IRA not only to ``prevent further loss of land'' 
but also to gradually acquire additional land, as congressional 
representatives understood ``prevention is not enough'' to undo the 
problems caused by the GAA.\19\ The Supreme Court later emphasized that 
Congress understood when enacting the IRA that the goal of self-
government for Tribal Nations could not be met without ``put[ting] a 
halt to the loss of tribal lands.'' \20\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \18\ See e.g., H.R. 7902, Rep. No. 1804, at 6, 73d Cong. 2d sess. 
(May 28, 1934) (Submitted by Rep. Howard); 73rd Cong. Rec. 11125 (June 
12, 1934) (Statement of Sen. Thomas); 73rd Cong. Rec. 9268 (May 22, 
1934) (Statement of Rep. Hastings).
    \19\ See 73rd Cong. Rec. 11727 (June 15, 1934) (Statement of Rep. 
Howard); see also To Grant To Indians Living Under Federal Tutelage The 
Freedom To Organization For Purposes Of Local Self-Government And 
Economic Enterprise, 73rd Cong. 59 (1934) (Statement by Commissioner 
Collier).
    \20\ Mescalero Apache Tribe v. Jones, 411 U.S. 145, 151 (1973).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Representatives of the 73rd Congress understood Tribal Nations' 
need for land in order to facilitate economic self-sufficiency and thus 
self-government. They noted that, in 1887, Indians were largely self-
supporting, but in 1934, because the ``Indian estate ha[d] dwindled,'' 
many were ``paupers'' reliant on the Federal Government.\21\ They 
understood that, through a ``workable plan of land management and 
development,'' Tribal Nations could ``achieve economic independence.'' 
\22\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \21\ 73rd Cong. Rec. 11128 (June 15, 1934) (Statement by Rep. 
Howard); See also H.R. 3645 Report No. 1080, at 6 (1934) (Submitted by 
Rep. Howard); 73rd Cong. Rec. 11123 (June 12, 1934) (Statement of Sen. 
Wheeler); 73rd Cong. Rec. 11125 (June 12, 1934) (Statement of Rep. 
Thomas).
    \22\ To Grant To Indians Living Under Federal Tutelage The Freedom 
To Organization For Purposes Of Local Self-Government And Economic 
Enterprise, 73rd Cong. 21 (1934) (Statement by Commissioner Collier).
    In a memorandum to Congress upon the consideration of the IRA, its 
primary architect, Commissioner of Indian Affairs John Collier, 
recommended that the new Federal Indian policy include provisions for 
the consolidation and reacquisition of Tribal Nations' lands. Regarding 
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
the effects of the GAA, he wrote:
        Through sales by the Government of the fictitiously designated 
        `surplus' lands; \23\ through sales by allottees after the 
        trust period had ended or had been terminated by administrative 
        act; and through sales by the Government of heirship land, 
        virtually mandatory under the allotment act: Through these 
        three methods, the total of Indian landholdings has been cut 
        from 138,000,000 acres in 1887 to 48,000,000 in 1934.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \23\ It did not escape Commissioner Collier's attention that much 
of the land lost through the GAA had been specifically reserved to 
Tribal Nations by treaty. Readjustment of Indian Affairs: Hearings on 
H.R. 7902 Before the H. Comm. on Indian Affairs, 73d Cong. 2d Sess. 32 
(1934) (Memorandum of John Collier, Commissioner of Indian Affairs).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
        . . .
        Furthermore, that part of the allotted lands which has been 
        lost is the most valuable part. Of the residual lands, taking 
        all Indian-owned lands into account, nearly one-half, or nearly 
        20,000,000 acres, are desert or semidesert lands.
        . . .
        A yet more disheartening picture will immediately follow the 
        above statement. For equally important with the outright loss 
        of land, is the effect of the allotment system in making such 
        lands as remain in Indian ownership unusable.\24\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \24\ Id. at 17.
    In short, Commissioner Collier correctly concluded that the 
dispossession and fractionation of Tribal Nations' and individual 
Indians' landholdings made it nearly impossible for Indian people to 
make a living for themselves. He identified a direct connection between 
the loss of a stable land base and the failure of Indian people to 
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
achieve social and economic security and self-sufficiency.
    Those advocating for passage of the IRA to representatives of the 
73rd Congress also understood that one of the benefits of strengthened 
Tribal Nation self-sufficiency and self-government, as facilitated 
through acquisition of land, is less reliance on the Federal Government 
and reduced bureaucratic oversight. This leads to corresponding 
benefits to the Federal Government such as decreased administrative 
costs and more effective implementation of its trust 
responsibilities.\25\ For example, Commissioner Collier noted the 
increased administrative costs to the government under the GAA era:
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \25\ It is important to note that the IRA in no way reduces the 
Federal Government's trust responsibilities to Tribal Nations, but 
rather the IRA's goal of reduced Tribal Nation reliance on the Federal 
Government is intended to strengthen the Federal Government's ability 
to fulfill these trust responsibilities.
        During this time, when Indian wealth has been shrinking and 
        Indian life has been diminishing, the costs of Indian 
        administration in the identical areas have been increasing. The 
        complications of bureaucratic management have grown steadily 
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
        greater.
        . . .
        The approximately one-third of the Indians who as yet are 
        outside the allotment system are not losing their property; and 
        generally they are increasing in industry and are rising, not 
        falling, in the social scale. The costs of Indian 
        administration are markedly lower in these unalloted areas.\26\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \26\ Readjustment of Indian Affairs: Hearings on H.R. 7902 Before 
the H. Comm. on Indian Affairs, 73d Cong. 2d Sess. 16 (1934) 
(Memorandum of John Collier, Commissioner of Indian Affairs).
    Representatives of the 73rd Congress were well aware of the 
possible negative effects on local interests resulting from acquisition 
of trust land for Tribal Nations. However, the IRA's trust acquisition 
provision was meant to undo past unjust and ineffective Federal Indian 
policies that often benefited non-Indians. In enacting the provision, 
Congress upheld its trust responsibilities to Tribal Nations by 
prioritizing their interests, even if state and local governments may 
occasionally experience negative side effects stemming from its 
application, including a loss of jurisdiction and tax revenue. Thus, 
Congress noted in Section 5 of the IRA that lands acquired into trust 
``shall be exempt from state and local taxation''--thereby stating with 
clarity its understanding that local interests may be harmed but that 
such harm is nonetheless necessary. Representatives of the 73rd 
Congress discussed in great detail the resulting removal of trust land 
from state taxation, knowingly moving forward with enactment.\27\ 
However, it should be noted that, when Tribal Nations are able to 
exercise jurisdiction over their land, surrounding communities and the 
United States as a whole benefit from the economic prosperity 
generated.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \27\ See, e.g., 73rd Cong. Rec. 9268 (Daily ed. May 22, 1934) 
(Statement of Rep. Hastings); To Grant To Indians Living Under Federal 
Tutelage The Freedom To Organization For Purposes Of Local Self-
Government And Economic Enterprise, 73rd Cong. 28 (1934) (Statement by 
Commissioner Collier).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The IRA's underlying policy goals of improving the social and 
economic welfare of Indian people through political and economic 
empowerment are no less valid today. Indian people still lag far behind 
the overall population in terms of health, education, employment, 
income, and other measures of socioeconomic status. The architects of 
the IRA within the 73rd Congress recognized that, in order to address 
these seemingly intractable problems, Federal Indian policy must 
support stronger Tribal Nation self-government and self-sufficiency, 
including by protecting and rebuilding Tribal Nations' land bases.
    While the goals and intent of the IRA remain valid and relevant in 
our current world, in many ways the IRA has yet to be fully 
implemented. With respect to land, only a small portion of the 90 
million acres that were lost following enactment of the GAA have been 
repatriated: less than 10 percent.\28\ And that does not account for 
the countless millions of acres lost prior to 1887 under different, but 
equally damaging, state and Federal policies and actions.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \28\ According to the Bureau of Indian Affairs, approximately 56.2 
million acres of land are currently held in trust by the United States 
for Tribal Nations and individual Indians. Bureau of Indian Affairs 
FAQ, What is a Federal Indian reservation?, http://www.bia.gov/FAQs/ 
(last visited June 5, 2017); see also executive branch Authority to 
Acquire Trust Lands for Indian Tribes: Oversight Hearing Before the S. 
Comm. on Indian Affairs, 111th Cong. (2009) (testimony of the National 
Congress of American Indians); Memorandum from Ken Salazar, Sec'y of 
Indian Affairs, to Larry Echohawk, Assistant Sec'y of Indian Affairs 
(Jun. 18, 2010) (stating 8 percent of lands restored since enactment of 
IRA).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The tools of the IRA are needed now as much as ever before. Broad, 
flexible Federal authority to acquire lands in trust for Tribal Nations 
wherever feasible and appropriate is necessary if we are to achieve the 
honorable goals set forth by the 73rd Congress in the IRA and as 
further reflected in our current policy of supporting Tribal Nations' 
self-determination. As Tribal Nations in large part have to use their 
own resources to purchase land on the open market before requesting the 
Department acquire it into trust, the existing tools of the IRA must 
not be further limited. All Tribal Nations, whatever their historical 
circumstances, need and deserve a stable, sufficient land base--a 
restoration of homelands taken from them under the GAA and previous 
Federal Indian policies--to support robust Tribal Nation self-
government and self-sufficiency.
 Stringent Administrative Requirements that Consider Effects on Local 
Interests and Comply with Carcieri v. Salazar Apply to the Department's 
                        Trust Land Acquisitions
Part 151 is an Extremely Rigorous Administrative Process the Department 
        uses to Determine whether to Acquire Land into Trust
    The Department's administrative process for acquiring land in trust 
under the IRA is found at 25 C.F.R. Part 151 (Part 151). Part 151 is an 
extremely rigorous administrative process the Department uses to 
determine whether to acquire land into trust. Compliance with Part 151 
is costly and time consuming for the Department as well as Tribal 
Nations, and neither undertakes a trust acquisition application 
lightly.
    Section 5 of the IRA broadly authorizes the Department to acquire 
trust rights to lands within or without existing reservations for the 
purpose of providing land for Indians.'' \29\ Reviewing courts have 
upheld this congressional grant of authority to the Department as 
proper, refusing to find that the grant unconstitutionally lacked 
standards.\30\ Despite the relatively broad language and intent of 
Section 5, there is no lack of administrative requirements that must be 
met before the Department will exercise its discretion to acquire land 
in trust on behalf of a Tribal Nation. The Department's Part 151 is 
arduous, time-consuming, and extremely rigorous.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \29\ Pub. L. No. 73-838, Sec. 5 (codified at 25 U.S.C. Sec. 5108).
    \30\ See, e.g., Michigan Gaming Opposition v. Kempthorne, 525 F.3d 
23, 33 (D.C. Cir. 2008); cert. denied 555 U.S. 1137 (2009); South 
Dakota v. U.S. Dep't of Interior, 423 F.3d 790, 796-99 (8th Cir. 2005); 
Shivwits Band of Paiute Indians v. Utah, 428 U. S. 966, 974 (10th Cir. 
2005), cert. denied, 549 U.S. 809 (2006); Carcieri v. Kempthorne, 497 
F.3d 15, (1st Cir. 2007) rev'd on other grounds Carcieri v. Salazar, 
555 U.S. 397 (2009); City of Yreka v. Salazar, 2011 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 
62818 (E.D. Cal. June 13, 2011); Cent. N.Y. Fair Bus. Ass'n v. Salazar, 
2010 WL 786526, at *5 (N.D.N.Y. Mar.1, 2010); Sac &amp; Fox Nation v. 
Kempthorne, 2008 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 69599 (D. Kan. Sept. 10, 2008); Sauk 
County v. U.S. Dep't of Interior, 2008 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 42552 (W.D. 
Wis. May 29, 2008).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    For a Tribal Nation seeking to have land acquired in trust, there 
are separate procedures and criteria the Tribal Nation and Department 
must comply with for on-reservation discretionary trust acquisitions 
(which include land contiguous to a reservation), off-reservation 
discretionary trust acquisitions, and trust acquisitions made mandatory 
by some other law. Generally, they require the Tribal Nation to provide 
and the Department to consider the needs of the Tribal Nation in 
acquiring the trust land, the detriments to local interests, and 
whether the Department is equipped to handle the additional 
responsibilities acquiring the land into trust may bring.\31\ The 
Department's ``Fee-to-Trust Handbook'' describing the criteria and 
procedures to be used is 98 pages long.\32\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \31\ 25 C.F.R. Sec. 151.10 (setting out criteria for on-reservation 
acquisitions); 25 C.F.R. Sec. 151.11 (setting out additional criteria 
for off-reservation acquisitions).
    \32\ Dep't of Interior, Acquisition of Title to Land Held in Fee or 
Restricted Fee Status (Fee-to-Trust Handbook) (June 28, 2016), 
available at https://www.bia.gov/cs/groups/xraca/documents/text/idc1-
024504.pdf.
    First, assembling a ``fee-to-trust application'' is no simple 
matter. In order to fulfill all of the application requirements, a 
Tribal Nation can spend amounts that range into hundreds of thousands 
of dollars on expert technical assistance from environmental 
consultants, realty experts, lawyers, and other professionals in order 
to prove that its application meets the Department's standards and 
requirements. All on-reservation discretionary trust acquisition 
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
applications must include:
    &lt;bullet&gt; A legal land description (conforming to specified 
            requirements);
    &lt;bullet&gt; A description of the need for acquisition of the property 
            (either economic development, self-determination, or non-
            commercial Indian housing);
    &lt;bullet&gt; A description of the purpose for which the property will 
            be used;
    &lt;bullet&gt; Legal verification of current ownership; and
    &lt;bullet&gt; An identification of statutory authority for the trust 
            land acquisition.
    If the application is for an off-reservation parcel, it must also 
include:
    &lt;bullet&gt; Documentation of the location of the land relative to 
            state boundaries;
    &lt;bullet&gt; Its distance from the boundaries of the reservation; and
    &lt;bullet&gt; An ``economic plan'' that specifies the anticipated 
            economic benefits associated with the use of the property, 
            if it is being acquired for business purposes.
    Once the fee-to-trust application is received, including the 
documentation listed above, the Tribal Nation must submit additional 
documentation and information for processing. This includes a 
commitment to issue final title insurance, a qualified Legal 
Description Review that concurs with the legal description, and a 
Warranty Deed with designation of Bureau of Indian Affairs approval.
    In addition to the required application materials, according to the 
Department's procedures, applicants are advised that it is 
``beneficial'' to provide the following:
    &lt;bullet&gt; Any documentation describing efforts taken to resolve 
            identified jurisdictional problems and potential conflicts 
            of land use that may arise as a result of the trust 
            acquisition;
    &lt;bullet&gt; Any signed cooperative agreements relating to the trust 
            acquisition, and a description of agreements for 
            infrastructure development or services (e.g. utilities, 
            fire protection, or solid waste disposal);
    &lt;bullet&gt; Agreements that have been negotiated with the state or 
            local government;
    &lt;bullet&gt; A description of those services not required of the state 
            or local government for the property because they are 
            provided by the Tribal Nation's government;
    &lt;bullet&gt; Any information in support of the Tribal Nation applicant 
            being ``under Federal jurisdiction'' in 1934, if 
            applicable;
    &lt;bullet&gt; Additional information or justification to assist in 
            reaching a decision.
    Needless to say, the process of assembling a fee-to-trust 
application is expensive and time-consuming. It is not something Tribal 
Nations undertake without a sincerely held need for land and belief 
that the land will qualify for trust acquisition.
    In addition to considering the specific criteria of Part 151, the 
Department also undertakes laborious tasks associated with its review. 
Among other prerequisites, the Department conducts a site inspection, 
prepares a Certificate of Inspection and Possession, requests a 
Preliminary Title Opinion from the Department's Solicitor's Office, 
conducts an Environmental Compliance Review and documents National 
Environmental Policy Act (NEPA) compliance in an Environmental 
Compliance Review Memorandum, and ultimately prepares a Notice of 
Decision addressing the criteria for trust acquisition. The 
Department's investment in acquiring land into trust is significant and 
also not undertaken lightly.
    When a Tribal Nation seeks to game on its trust land, there are 
additional criteria and procedures that must be met under the Indian 
Gaming Regulatory Act (IGRA).\33\ Generally, gaming on land acquired 
into trust after IGRA was enacted in 1988 is prohibited.\34\ There are 
very limited instances when the prohibition does not apply, including 
when the trust land is within or contiguous to a Tribal Nation's 1988 
reservation \35\ or its former reservation,\36\ when lands qualify for 
an ``equal footing'' exception available to Tribal Nations newly 
federally recognized or to land acquired under a land claim 
settlement,\37\ or when the state's governor is involved in the 
decision to permit gaming under the ``two-part'' exception.\38\ This 
gaming determination is made separate and apart from a decision to 
acquire land into trust under the standards of the IRA.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \33\ 25 U.S.C. Sec. 2719; 25 C.F.R. Part 292.
    \34\ 25 U.S.C. Sec. 2719(a).
    \35\ 25 U.S.C. Sec. 2719(a)(1).
    \36\ 25 U.S.C. Sec. 2719(a)(2).
    \37\ 25 U.S.C. Sec. 2719(b)(1)(B).
    \38\ 25 U.S.C. Sec. 2719(b)(1)(A).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
The Administrative Requirements Provide Sufficient Opportunity for 
        Local Interests to Comment and for Local Interests to be Fully 
        Considered
    Some have called for a requirement that the Department provide 
notice of a possible trust acquisition under the IRA and the 
opportunity to comment to state and local governments and consider 
possible effects on them. These concepts are already embedded within 
Part 151, despite the fact that the IRA on its face does not require 
such consideration and Congress' intent in enacting the IRA focuses on 
the needs of Tribal Nations rather than the needs of other entities.
    Part 151 requires that local interests are notified of the possible 
trust acquisition and given the opportunity to comment. For trust 
acquisitions pursuant to the IRA, the Department must notify the state 
and local governments having regulatory jurisdiction over the land to 
be acquired.\39\ As part of its review of trust acquisition 
applications, the Department prepares a Notice of Application to inform 
state and local governments and any person or entity requesting notice 
about the application and the opportunity to provide comments. Each 
notified party is then given 30 days to provide written comments 
regarding potential impacts on regulatory jurisdiction, real property 
taxes, and special assessments, and then the applicant Tribal Nation is 
provided with the comments and given a reasonable time to reply.\40\ 
Further, if a significant amount of time lapses between the dates of 
the Notice of Application permitting submission of comments and the 
Notice of Decision regarding the ultimate decision, the procedures 
require that the Notice of Application be reissued to allow for updates 
to the comments and the applicant's response to those comments.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \39\ 25 C.F.R. Sec. Sec. 151.10, 151.11(d).
    \40\ Id.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Part 151 also calls for compliance with NEPA.\41\ As part of its 
Environmental Compliance Review under NEPA, the Department provides 
state and local governments with an extensive opportunity to comment 
and then considers comments received.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \41\ See id. at Sec. Sec. 151.10(h), 151.11(a).
    Part 151 then requires the Department to consider effects on local 
interests in making a determination of whether to acquire land into 
trust. For trust acquisitions under the IRA, included within the 
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
regulatory criteria considered by the Department are the following:
        If the land to be acquired is in unrestricted fee status, the 
        impact on the state and its political subdivisions resulting 
        from the removal of the land from the tax rolls; [and]
        Jurisdictional problems and potential conflicts of land use 
        which may arise.\42\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \42\ Id. at Sec. 151.10.
    If the land is located off-reservation, the criteria demand even 
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
more careful and weighty consideration of local interests, stating:
        The location of the land relative to state boundaries, and its 
        distance from the boundaries of the Tribe's reservation, shall 
        be considered as follows: as the distance between the Tribe's 
        reservation and the land to be acquired increases, the 
        Secretary shall give greater scrutiny to the Tribe's 
        justification of anticipated benefits from the acquisition. The 
        Secretary shall give greater weight to the concerns raised 
        pursuant to [the provision providing for comment by local 
        interests] of this section.\43\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \43\ Id. at Sec. 151.11(b).
    The Department's Fee-to-Trust Handbook states that the Notice of 
Decision ultimately issued should contain an analysis of comments and 
concerns by local interests.
The Administrative Requirements Properly Consider and Comply with the 
        Supreme Court's Ruling in Carcieri v. Salazar
    Some have claimed Part 151 does not properly consider and comply 
with the Supreme Court's holding in Carcieri v. Salazar. However, the 
Department's administrative process for acquiring land in trust under 
the IRA complies with the IRA, including the Supreme Court's decision 
in Carcieri interpreting the IRA.
    Included within the Department's analysis of the criteria under 
Part 151 is a determination of whether it has statutory authority for 
the trust acquisition. As part of this determination when the trust 
acquisition is to take place under the IRA, the Department conducts a 
legal analysis regarding whether the acquisition complies with the 
Supreme Court's interpretation of the IRA in Carcieri.\44\ The 
Department consults with the Office of the Solicitor regarding this 
analysis.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \44\ 555 U.S. 379 (2009).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The Court in Carcieri construed the temporal limitations of the 
Department's authority to acquire land in trust for Tribal Nations 
under the IRA. The Court determined that a Tribal Nation seeking to 
acquire land in trust under the IRA must meet an IRA definition of 
``Indian.'' \45\ The decision in Carcieri was limited to a statutory 
analysis of the meaning of ``now'' in the phrase ``now under Federal 
jurisdiction'' in the first IRA definition of ``Indian.'' \46\ The 
Court held that a Tribal Nation meeting that definition must have been 
``under Federal jurisdiction'' when the IRA was enacted in 1934.\47\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \45\ Id. at 393.
    \46\ Id. at 382.
    \47\ Id. at 395.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The Court in Carcieri did not address the meaning of ``under 
Federal jurisdiction,'' \48\ and it did not state Tribal Nations must 
have been federally recognized in 1934 in order to acquire land in 
trust under the IRA.\49\ Thus, although some have claimed the Supreme 
Court held in Carcieri that the Department may only acquire land in 
trust under the IRA for Tribal Nations that were federally recognized 
in 1934, the Supreme Court's holding was actually much narrower than 
this. It is important not to conflate the two terms--``under Federal 
jurisdiction'' and ``Federal recognition''--which are distinct legal 
concepts and of which the Supreme Court in Carcieri addressed only the 
former. Still, opponents of Tribal land acquisitions often self-
servingly conflate the two.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \48\ Instead, the Court noted the petition for certiorari had 
asserted that the Tribal Nation at issue there was not under Federal 
jurisdiction in 1934 and that ``[t]he respondents' brief in opposition 
declined to contest this assertion.'' Id. at 395-96 (majority opinion); 
see also id. at 399 (Breyer, J., concurring); Stand Up for California! 
v. U.S. Dep't of Interior, 919 F.Supp.2d 51, 66 (D.D.C. 2013) (``The 
first and most pressing question left open by Carcieri is what it means 
to have been `under Federal jurisdiction' in 1934.'').
    \49\ Nowhere in its decision did the Court hold a Tribal Nation 
must be federally recognized in 1934 to acquire land into trust under 
the IRA. Instead, Justice Breyer in his concurrence indicated a Tribal 
Nation may have been under Federal jurisdiction in 1934 regardless of 
whether the Federal Government understood it to be federally recognized 
at that time. Carcieri v. Salazar, 555 U.S. 379, 397 (2009) (Breyer, 
J., concurring). He also stated that the IRA ``imposes no time limit 
upon recognition. Id. at 398. Justice Breyer explained that sometimes 
``later recognition reflects earlier `Federal jurisdiction.' '' Id. at 
398-99. Justices Souter and Ginsberg concurred in Justice Breyer's 
explanation of the majority opinion in the concurring portion of their 
opinion.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The Department has created a rigorous framework for determining 
whether a trust acquisition under the IRA would comply with the Supreme 
Court's Carcieri decision. Courts have found the IRA ambiguous in its 
reference to ``recognized'' and ``under Federal jurisdiction'' and have 
thus concluded that--under the legal principles set forth in Chevron v. 
Natural Resources Defense Council, Inc., 467 U.S. 837 (1984)--the 
Department has the legal right to reasonably interpret their meanings 
and courts must defer to its reasonable interpretation.\50\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \50\ See, e.g., Confederated Tribes of the Grand Ronde Community v. 
Jewell, 830 F.3d 552, 560-61, 564 (D.C. Cir. 2016).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The Department first articulated its Carcieri framework in its 2013 
trust acquisition for the Cowlitz Indian Tribe, and it later 
memorialized its framework in an official 2014 M-Opinion issued by the 
Solicitor.\51\ Contrary to some claims, the Department has by no means 
read the restrictions of the Carcieri decision out of existence. In 
fact, courts have upheld the Department's rigorous framework as a 
reasonable interpretation of the meaning of ``under Federal 
jurisdiction'' warranting deference under Chevron.\52\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \51\ Memorandum from Solicitor to Secretary re The Meaning of 
``Under Federal Jurisdiction'' for Purposes of the Indian 
Reorganization Act (Mar. 12, 2014).
    \52\ See, e.g., Confederated Tribes of the Grand Ronde Community v. 
Jewell, 830 F.3d 552, 565 (D.C. Cir. 2016).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Based on an exhaustive review of the IRA's legislative history and 
its extensive experience examining the tribal status of and Federal 
relationship with Tribal Nations, the Department's framework properly 
does not require a Tribal Nation to have been federally recognized in 
1934. In 1934, the Federal Government lacked a formal mechanism for 
officially federally recognizing Tribal Nations. In fact, the 
Department has acknowledged that its understanding of Tribal status and 
Tribal-Federal relationships in the 1930s was limited and often 
inaccurate.\53\ In an effort to clarify Tribal status questions and 
facilitate a smoother Federal relationship, the IRA provided a 
mechanism for formal organization of Tribal Nation governments--thereby 
evidencing the IRA's contemplation of later Federal recognition.\54\ 
Even today, in an era where Tribal Nations can receive formal Federal 
recognition, the status of ``Federal recognition'' and the status of 
``under Federal jurisdiction'' are two different, although overlapping, 
relationships between the Federal Government and a Tribal Nation. Thus, 
as Justice Souter rightly noted, ``the two concepts, recognition and 
jurisdiction, may be given separate content'' and each should be given 
its ``own meaning.'' \55\ In upholding the Department's Caricieri 
framework as a reasonable interpretation of the IRA, courts have 
likewise upheld as reasonable the Department's position that a Tribal 
Nation need not have been recognized in 1934.\56\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \53\ See, e.g., Fed. Reg. 9280, 9281 (Feb. 25, 1994); 43 Fed. Reg. 
39361 (Sept. 5, 1978).
    \54\ Pub. L. No. 73-838, Sec. 16 (codified at 25 U.S.C. Sec. 5123). 
The Department, with the help of legal opinions from its Solicitor's 
Office, thereafter federally recognized Tribal Nations through 
organization pursuant to the IRA. See Carcieri v. Salazar, 555 U.S. 
379, 398-99 (2009) (Breyer, J., concurring).
    \55\ Carcieri v. Salazar, 555 U.S. 379, 400 (2009) (Souter, J., 
concurring in part and dissenting in part).
    \56\ See, e.g., Confederated Tribes of the Grand Ronde Community v. 
Jewell, 830 F.3d 552, 565 (D.C. Cir. 2016).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The Department's Carcieri framework requires a Tribal Nation to 
meet a two-part test to establish that it was under Federal 
jurisdiction in 1934. This two-part test preserves sufficient 
flexibility to allow the Department to make determinations on a case-
by-case basis that are measured against the backdrop of well-
established principles of Indian law and take into account the unique 
history and circumstances of each tribe and its relationship to the 
United States. It acknowledges that the United States has established a 
wide variety of relations with Tribal Nations arising out of historical 
and other circumstances and takes into account that in some cases these 
relationships are broad and all-encompassing and in others they are 
more limited. Under the two-part test, the Department first examines 
whether at some point prior to 1934 the Tribal Nation was under Federal 
jurisdiction, which is evidenced by the United States taking ``an 
action or series of actions--through a course of dealings or other 
relevant acts for or on behalf of the tribe or in some instance tribal 
members--that are sufficient to establish, or that generally reflect 
Federal obligations, duties, responsibility for or authority over the 
tribe by the Federal Government.'' \57\ The Department second examines 
``whether the tribe's jurisdictional status remained intake in 1934.'' 
\58\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \57\ Memorandum from Solicitor to Secretary re The Meaning of 
``Under Federal Jurisdiction'' for Purposes of the Indian 
Reorganization Act, at 19 (Mar. 12, 2014).
    \58\ Id.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
   Administrative Procedures Rather than Statutory Procedures Should 
   Implement the Enduring Purposes of the IRA and Address Legitimate 
         Considerations Without Unduly Burdening Tribal Nations
    The Department's regulatory procedures properly implement the trust 
land acquisition provisions of the IRA in a way that is likely more 
flexible and responsive to Tribal Nations' needs than procedures 
formally codified by Congress or case-by-case statutory trust 
acquisition legislation would be. This more flexible and responsive 
framework better implements the IRA's over-riding purposes of 
facilitating the self-determination and self-sufficiency of Tribal 
Nations.
    In additional to reversing allotment and restoring Tribal Nation 
lands taken from them under the GAA and previous Federal Indian 
policies, an over-riding purpose of the IRA was to reduce Federal 
paternalism and control over the internal affairs of Tribal Nations. In 
his memorandum to Congress, Commissioner Collier noted: 
``Fundamentally, under existing law, the Government's Indian Service is 
a system of absolutism.'' He stated that the IRA ``seeks to curb this 
administrative absolutism and it provides the machinery for a 
progressive establishment of home rule by [Tribal Nations] or groups of 
Indians.'' \59\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \59\ Readjustment of Indian Affairs: Hearings on H.R. 7902 Before 
the H. Comm. on Indian Affairs, 73d Cong. 2d Sess. 21-22 (1934) 
(Memorandum of John Collier, Commissioner of Indian Affairs).
    Commissioner Collier also spoke to the balance of congressional 
direction and administrative authority in the IRA, a balance that was 
carefully considered and intentionally struck. He noted the unrealistic 
situation Tribal Nations would face if they were required to obtain 
separate statutory authority from Congress for each trust land 
acquisition sought, a hardship that would be even more difficult today. 
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
He explained:
        By way of reaction to the excessive inflexibility of blanket 
        legislation in the past and the overcentralized administration 
        which such legislation has imposed on the Office of Indian 
        Affairs, there has arisen in recent years an increasing number 
        of requests for special legislation dealing with the particular 
        problems of one reservation or another. . . . For Congress to 
        assume the task of passing upon the claims of each particular 
        Indian group and dealing with the problems of 214 reservations 
        in 214 or more separate statutes would clearly involve an 
        assumption by Congress of onerous and complex administrative 
        functions.
        The present bill pursues a middle road between blanket 
        legislation everywhere equally applicable and specific statutes 
        dealing with the problems of particular [Tribal Nations]. It 
        sets up, in effect, an administrative machinery for dealing 
        with the problems of different Indian reservations, and lays 
        down certain definite directions of policy and restrictions 
        upon administrative discretion in dealing with these problems.
        It is recognized that the unlimited and largely unreviewable 
        exercise of administrative discretion by the Secretary of the 
        Interior and the Commissioner of Indian Affairs has been one of 
        the chief sources of complaint on the part of the Indians. It 
        is the chief object of the bill to terminate such bureaucratic 
        authority by transferring the administration of the Indian 
        Service to the Indian communities themselves.\60\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \60\ Id. at 21-22.
    Thus, the IRA was designed to preserve sufficient flexibility to 
address the wide-ranging needs of diverse Indian communities (and avoid 
the need for Congress to constantly enact exceptions for individual 
Tribal Nations), while avoiding administrative over-reach by putting 
more decision-making power in the hands of Tribal Nations. Consistent 
with our current policies, the IRA envisioned that Tribal Nations would 
exercise self-government, escape the heavy thumb of Federal 
paternalism, and manage their own affairs and resources as they saw 
fit. In many ways, this is the quintessential American ideal of ``home 
rule,'' which allows local jurisdictions to exercise decentralized 
governance powers.
    In seeking to improve the trust land acquisition process today, 
both Congress and the Administration must be mindful not to take any 
steps backward from the important gains that have been made under the 
IRA. As Tribal Nations build on the successes of self-governance and 
self-sufficiency made in the past few decades and work to address 
ongoing needs for improved housing, health care, social and educational 
programs, training and employment, and cultural and religious exercise, 
the goal should be to remove rather than add to the existing burdens on 
Tribal Nations and the Federal Government in doing so. The solution is 
not to return to an era of excessive Federal dependence and control by 
stifling the agility and flexibility of Tribal Nations' governments, 
but to further the IRA's vision of robust, self-determined Tribal 
Nations and communities that are able to rely less on the Federal 
Government.
    USET SPF does not dismiss the fact that trust land acquisition can 
have a range of impacts on local communities in the area in which the 
land is located--often the same local communities that benefited by 
gaining control of Tribal Nations' lands as a result of policies the 
IRA was intended to reverse. However, legitimate considerations can be 
addressed through reasonable and responsible administrative procedures 
that strike an appropriate balance between flexibility, stability, 
efficiency, and responsiveness. For example, existing procedures 
provide states and local communities with the right to be notified of, 
and comment on, pending fee-to-trust applications.
    On the other hand, the statutory imposition of limits on the 
purposes for which Tribal Nations' trust lands are used, or the vesting 
of virtual veto power in state or local governments over a matter 
arising in the inherently Federal context of Indian law and policy, as 
some have called for, would signal a return to the abusive practices of 
paternalism and ``absolutism'' that the IRA was intended to reject. 
Such rigid legislation would jeopardize the underlying policy goals 
first stated in the IRA, but which have carried through to the present 
day. USET SPF unequivocally opposes any attack on the continued 
vitality of the IRA's purpose to repatriate Tribal Nations' lands taken 
from them under the GAA and previous Federal Indian policies and to 
empower Tribal Nations to manage their own affairs and resources 
through the exercise of self-government and self-sufficiency on their 
own lands.
    USET SPF thanks the Subcommittee for taking the time to conduct 
this oversight hearing. The importance of the IRA and its trust 
acquisition provisions to Tribal Nations today cannot be overstated. 
They are absolutely fundamental to our ability to thrive as vibrant, 
healthy, self-sufficient communities within the United States, as much 
today as they were in 1934. USET SPF hopes this testimony has been 
helpful in illuminating that the IRA's underlying goals and the tools 
it gave us should be protected and strengthened as we continue to 
improve Federal Indian policy and, through it, the lives of our Indian 
people.
                                 ______
    Mr. LaMalfa. Thank you, Mr. Francis, I appreciate it.
    The Chair now recognizes Mr. Allyn to testify for 5 
minutes.
</option>
    <option>                      LEDYARD, CONNECTICUT
    Mr. Allyn. Chairman, Ranking Member, and members of the 
Subcommittee, I submit my testimony on behalf of the towns of 
Ledyard, North Stonington, and Preston, Connecticut. I am the 
Mayor of Ledyard, a town of 15,000 residents located in the 
southeastern corner of the state.
    My testimony covers the impact to local communities from 
the application of Federal Indian law specifically for trust 
land acquisition, and efforts to pre-empt legitimate state and 
local taxation on non-Indian entities on tribal land. Our 
experience comes from decades of serving as the host community 
for the Mashantucket Pequot Tribe and Foxwoods Resort Casino.
    My own family has been in Ledyard for 358 years, and we are 
proud of the relationship that we have with the tribe. But 
Federal Indian law does little to foster the kind of 
cooperative relationships that we have. The town's experiences 
date from 1993, when the tribe applied to have 247 acres of 
off-reservation land placed into trust. Our lawsuit filed in 
1995 lasted for almost 10 years. In the end, the tribe withdrew 
its request and began working with us to pursue its off-
reservation development plans under state and local laws, and 
to acquire land in trust only for on-reservation parcels, which 
the town has been able to support. The town has even revised 
zoning regulations to allow for the tribe's use.
    Our experience also comes from recent litigation with the 
tribe over its claims that non-tribal slot machine vendors are 
exempt from personal property tax. In 2013, after 8 years of 
litigation, the Second Circuit court ruled in our favor, 
finding that the economic effect of the tax on the tribe was 
minimal, but the tax revenues were essential to the town's 
ability to fund public services, including the education of 
tribal children and the maintenance of the roads that bring 
customers to the casino.
    I will address the defects in Federal Indian law in both of 
these areas. The impacts on local communities from trust land 
acquisition are several, as illustrated by our experiences.
    First, the demand for government services increases, 
especially when gaming or large-scale development occurs. Since 
Foxwoods opened in 1992, our police force has grown by 40 
percent, while the population of our town has only grown by 1 
percent. Traffic has tripled, and DUI arrests are twice the 
state average.
    Second, revenues declined from the loss of our tax base. 
The most recent trust land acquisition cost the town 
approximately $250,000 in annual property tax revenues out of a 
current annual budget of just $55 million.
    Third, once taken into trust, development is not subject to 
zoning, allowing incompatible development to transform the 
character of our community. The experiences of the town 
illustrate the very real impacts trust land acquisition can 
have on local communities. But our experience also shows that 
local communities can have positive relationships with 
neighboring tribes if trust decisions are made on a level 
playing field.
    We need Congress to set the standards that will govern land 
trust acquisition. The BIA rules have been in place for 
decades, and they are flawed, suffering from two over-riding 
flaws: the lack of objective standards and the lack of 
procedures that ensure real consideration of local community 
impact.
    As just one example, the regulations require BIA to 
consider the need of the tribe for additional land, yet they do 
not define the type of need to be considered, and how it should 
be evaluated. BIA accepts generic statements that trust land 
will further tribal self-governance and self-determination, and 
finds the need criteria unsatisfied for even the wealthiest of 
tribes.
    My written testimony details additional problems that also 
need to be addressed. To address these concerns, the towns 
recommend the land should only be taken into trust when clear 
objective standards have been met, and the concerns of local 
government have been satisfied. No acquisition should be 
approved unless impacts to the local community have been fully 
addressed.
    Finally, my town also faces the potential loss of very 
significant personal property taxes. The impact to our small 
town would be tremendous. Recently our fire marshal offered to 
buy his uniforms from Walmart to save the town $180 a year. 
These are very real, small-town decisions that are made every 
day.
    BIA is now considering a last-minute Obama administration 
initiative to revise regulations governing the so-called Indian 
traders under obsolete statutes originally enacted between 1790 
and 1903, to prevent Indians from being defrauded by traders 
doing business with them. No one seems to follow these 
regulations today, and they are irrelevant for trader purposes. 
This initiative seems to have the sole intent of pre-empting 
legitimate state and local taxes on non-Indian businesses, and 
is confirmed by the comments received by BIA and documents 
released under FOIA.
    The decision on whether the state and local governments 
should be pre-empted from exercising this power should be made 
by Congress, not by BIA. Of course, taxation powers must be 
left in place.
    Thank you for your time and consideration of my testimony, 
and I will take any questions you may have. Thank you.
</option>
    <option>     Prepared Statement of Fred Allyn III, Mayor, Town of Ledyard, 
                              Connecticut
    Chairman LaMalfa, Ranking Member Torres, and members of the 
Subcommittee, thank you for the opportunity to testify on issues 
related to trust land acquisition under the Indian Reorganization Act 
of 1934 (IRA). I am the Mayor of Ledyard, Connecticut, a municipal 
government for a town of 15,000 residents, located in the southeastern 
corner of the state. I also submit this testimony on behalf of our 
neighboring towns of Preston and North Stonington.
    Based on our experiences with the Mashantucket Pequot and Mohegan 
Tribes, we are uniquely situated to provide testimony on the issues 
associated with Indian gaming, including trust land, off-reservation 
casinos and gaming-related facilities, taxation of non-tribal personal 
property on-reservation lands, and tribal acknowledgment. Our 
experience comes from decades of serving as the host community for the 
reservation of the Mashantucket Pequot Tribe, the Foxwoods Resort 
Casino and, to a lesser degree, from our proximity to the Reservation 
of the Mohegan Tribe and the Mohegan Sun Casino.
    The purpose of this testimony is to discuss why the current 
standards and procedures of the Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA) 
regulations for trust land acquisition in 25 C.F.R. Part 151 are 
seriously flawed and need to be revised to ensure that decisions meet 
the intent of Congress in the IRA. My testimony will speak to the 
concerns of local government bodies with the BIA rules. I also will 
speak to an Advance Notice of Proposed Rulemaking (ANPRM), published by 
the Obama administration on December 9, 2016, to revise the current 
rules implementing the Indian Trader laws. 81 Fed. Reg. 89, 015-017. As 
my testimony will discuss, the ANPRM will be very harmful to state and 
local governments and is motivated not by a desire to address the 
regulation of ``Indian traders'' but instead to manufacture a basis for 
the pre-emption of state and local taxation of non-Indian economic 
activities on Indian lands. The potential loss of such tax revenues on 
Indian lands is one of the significant burdens imposed on local 
governments when land is taken into trust.
                      impacts to local communities
    Before making recommendations, I offer perspective on why acquiring 
off-reservation land in trust has such a profound negative impact on 
local communities. These impacts fall into four categories. While the 
nature and extent of the impacts will vary according to the intended 
use of the land, I believe that these types of impacts will be 
experienced by most communities that confront the expansion of tribal 
lands pursuant to trust land acquisition undertaken by the Secretary of 
the Interior through the BIA.
    First, local governments will experience an increase in the demand 
for government services, especially when gaming or large-scale economic 
development occurs, bringing large influxes of both patrons and 
employees. Local governments provide services used by all, including 
emergency and law enforcement services, public sanitation, and the 
expansion and maintenance of public roads, schools, and hospitals. 
These services directly benefit, and often are essential to, such 
tribal economic development. In fact, it is generally the case that 
states and local governments do not differentiate between tribal 
members and other citizens in providing governmental services.
    Second, while financial burdens increase, revenues decline from the 
loss of tax base. Land in trust is not subject to state and local 
property taxes, and economic substitution effects can affect the local 
economy, resulting in losses of other tax revenue streams as well. 
Increasingly, tribes are challenging state and local taxation of non-
Indian activities on trust lands, further threatening local government 
funding.
    Third, control is lost over the use of land, often resulting in 
fragmented development and negative environmental and quality-of-life 
impacts. Once taken into trust, land is not subject to local zoning 
laws, allowing incompatible development that the local government 
cannot regulate. State and local environmental laws also do not apply.
    Finally, changes occur in the nature of daily life in the area 
surrounding the trust land, and in the ability of residents or 
government officials to decide whether those changes are desirable or 
how they should be achieved. Large-scale tribal gaming or other 
economic development can completely transform the character of a small 
town or a rural community. To a large extent, local communities can 
feel as if they have lost control of their own future.
    Our experience illustrates these impacts. As noted above, the three 
towns extensive experience with trust land acquisition by the Secretary 
of the Interior. Our experience dates from 1993, when we learned that 
the Mashantucket Pequot Tribe had filed an application to have 247 
acres of off-reservation land acquired in trust on its behalf. 
Concerned about the loss of tax revenue in the face of growing burdens 
on our small-town government due to the success of the Foxwoods Casino 
and negative impacts of development inconsistent with local land use 
and environmental laws, Ledyard joined with the neighboring towns of 
North Stonington and Preston to oppose the Secretary's acquisition of 
this land in trust.
    Our lawsuit, filed in 1995, lasted for almost 10 years. In the end, 
the Tribe withdrew its request and instead worked with the town to 
pursue its off-reservation development plans in accordance with state 
and local laws, and to acquire land in trust only for on-reservation 
parcels, which the town of Ledyard has been able to support.
    Our experience also comes from recent litigation with the Tribe 
over its claim that non-tribal slot machine vendors who lease gaming 
equipment for use at Foxwoods are exempt from local personal property 
tax. Mashantucket Pequot Tribe v. Town of Ledyard, 722 F.3d 457 (2d 
Cir. 2013). In 2005, the Tribe challenged Ledyard's assessment of 
Connecticut's personal property tax on the lessors of slot machines 
used by the Tribe at its casino, arguing that the tax, which the Tribe 
contractually agreed to pay, infringed on tribal sovereignty. After 8 
years of litigation, the Second Circuit ultimately ruled that non-
Indian slot machine companies must indeed pay personal property tax 
like any other business that maintains such property. Id. The Court 
found that the state and local interests in the tax revenues at stake 
outweighed the Federal and tribal interests in economic development and 
tribal sovereignty. The Court found that the economic effect of the tax 
on the Tribe was minimal, but the tax revenues were essential to the 
town's ability to fund public services, including the education of 
tribal children, and the maintenance of the roads that bring customers 
to the Tribe's casino. In short, the town and state had more at stake 
than the Tribe.
    The result of this progression from divisive and expensive 
litigation and conflict to amicable and collaborative land use planning 
provides important lessons learned and a clear picture of the changes 
needed to improve trust land acquisition decision making, which I offer 
in this testimony.
                          the town of ledyard
    We commend the Tribe for its great success in developing Foxwoods 
and achieving governmental and economic self-sufficiency. The fact 
remains, however, that the town of Ledyard has been adversely impacted 
since the opening of the first casino in 1992. This is a result of the 
governmental burdens our town must bear to accommodate Foxwoods and the 
lack of an adequate source of revenue for that purpose due to the tax-
exempt status of trust land.
    To understand the basis for my testimony, the Subcommittee needs 
background information on my town. Ledyard has an annual budget of $55 
million, which is a mere fraction of the annual revenues of the Tribe, 
estimated to be in excess of $1.5 billion/year. Within such a small 
budget, we must be able to recover all of the costs of the governmental 
services we supply to the Tribe and provide for our own residents. This 
must occur with declining State Aid.
    The shortfall in the town's budget increases every time the Federal 
Government takes more land into trust. Currently, the Tribe has 
approximately 1,095 acres held in non-taxable trust within its existing 
reservation boundary, which encompasses about twice that amount of 
land. At present, we do not believe the Tribe seeks to add any trust 
land outside of its reservation boundaries. Since the enactment of the 
Connecticut Indian Land Claim Settlement Act of 1983, however, the 
Tribe has gradually and continually expanded the amount of land in 
trust status inside the reservation.
    Consistent with the town's cooperative working relationship with 
the Tribe, we have supported on-reservation trust land acquisition, 
provided all applicable laws are satisfied and the town is consulted 
with in advance. In supporting these requests, however, the town has 
had to absorb a significant loss in tax revenue every time another 
acquisition is completed. For example, the Federal Government's most 
recent trust land acquisition for the Tribe cost the town approximately 
$250,000 in annual property tax revenue. We believe the Tribe intends 
to continue to add more trust land within its reservation boundaries, 
so further losses in tax revenue to the town will occur.
             flaws in the current trust acquisition process
    The current trust acquisition process is so deficient that it 
cannot possibly meet the intent of Congress in enacting the IRA. The 
current process suffers from two over-riding flaws:(1) the lack of 
objective standards governing the trust acquisition decision; and (2) 
the lack of procedures that ensure real consideration of the impacts to 
local communities. This lack of any real constraints on the BIA's 
discretionary authority is what allowed the Obama administration to 
make the heavily publicized political commitment to take 500,000 acres 
of land into trust while in office, and in fact was able to exceeded 
that target.\1\ The trust acquisition process should not be so 
unconstrained as to allow administrations to make political promises to 
take such a significant and arbitrary amount of land into trust, even 
before any consideration of the actual merits of individual 
applications.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \1\ https://www.doi.gov/pressreleases/obama-administration-exceeds-
ambitious-goal-restore-500000-acres-tribal-homelands.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    In our 1995 lawsuit, joined by the state of Connecticut, we argued 
that Section 5 of the IRA was intended to serve a limited, but 
important, purpose of assisting tribes in achieving a sufficient land 
base, usually within reservation boundaries, to achieve economic 
development and provide for their members. We also argued, in the first 
case to raise the so-called ``Carcieri issue'' that such authority has 
to be used only for ``any recognized Indian tribe now under Federal 
jurisdiction.'' Unfortunately, while this intent of Congress was clear, 
apparently the words chosen in Section 5 were not, which has allowed 
BIA to proceed with trust land acquisition that has virtually no limits 
and no discernible standards, and to acquire land in trust for tribes 
that were not recognized in 1934.
    The courts have thus far not found Section 5 of the IRA to be so 
lacking in any intelligible principle governing its exercise as to be 
an unconstitutional delegation of legislative authority. Nonetheless, 
the statute itself provides little guidance as to the basis for trust 
decisions. Section 5 simply states that the Secretary of the Interior 
is ``hereby authorized, in his discretion, to acquire . . . lands . . . 
for the purpose of providing land for Indians.'' The statute thus 
provides no meaningful guidance to the decision maker, tribes, state or 
local governments, or the public.
    The trust acquisition regulations at 25 C.F.R. Part 151 set forth 
various criteria, but provide little meaningful guidance.\2\ For 
example, the regulations require the BIA to consider ``the need of the 
individual Indian or tribe for additional land,'' yet the regulations 
do not define or provide guidance on the type of need to be considered 
and how the level of need should be evaluated. The BIA regularly 
accepts generic statements that placing land in trust will further 
tribal self-governance and self-determination as showing sufficient 
need, and finds the need criterion satisfied for even the wealthiest of 
tribes.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \2\ See generally, Government Accountability Office, Indian Issues: 
BIA's Efforts to Impose Time Frames and Collect Better Data Should 
Improve the Processing of Land Trust Applications (GAO-06-781).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Similarly, the regulations require consideration of the purposes 
for which the land will be used, but according to the BIA, almost any 
purpose will suffice. Moreover, in many cases, the tribe claims one 
proposed land use, or even no change in land use, but then pursues 
completely different uses once the land is in trust. Changes in uses 
are not subject to further review by the BIA, so there is a strong 
incentive to claim that no change in land use is intended to avoid the 
need for review under the National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA). As 
a result, the impacts of development are not considered in the trust 
decision, local communities are blindsided, distrust replaces 
cooperation, and negative impacts that could easily have been avoided 
or mitigated nonetheless occur.
    If the land to be acquired is in unrestricted fee status, the 
regulations require the BIA to consider the impact on the state and its 
political subdivisions resulting from the removal of the land from the 
tax rolls. This is a fundamental concern for local governments, yet the 
regulations provide no guidance on what constitutes an acceptable level 
of tax loss. In addition, only the amount of current property taxes on 
what is often undeveloped land is considered, rather than the property 
taxes that would be generated after the land is developed, even when 
proposed development is the purpose of the trust request, and will 
generate greater demand for public services. In addition, the BIA 
refuses to consider the cumulative impact of trust acquisitions, and 
every new request is treated in isolation, even in cases where half the 
land in a county is already in trust.
    The BIA is also required to consider jurisdiction problems and 
potential conflicts of land use that may arise. The exercise of zoning 
authority is one of the primary tools by which communities can protect 
their integrity, and this important local government tool is lost once 
land is in trust. Again, there is no guidance in the regulations on 
what types of jurisdictional and land use concerns might warrant denial 
of the application. As a result, the BIA consistently fails to accord 
any real weight to the loss of local government zoning authority over 
lands taken into trust. Indeed, the BIA often cites the need to 
eliminate such state and local control as a reason to take land into 
trust.
    The BIA must also consider the extent to which the applicant has 
provided information that allows the Secretary to comply with 
environmental requirements, particularly under NEPA. Yet again, the 
regulations provide no guidance on the amount or type of information 
needed by the BIA to make the required environmental determinations. 
Under what is known as a categorical exclusion, the BIA frequently 
exempts proposed acquisitions from any environmental review at all. 
Rather than serving as a mechanism to explore and resolve negative 
impacts through agreements with local governments or other parties, or 
meeting tribal needs without taking land into trust, NEPA is often 
viewed as a roadblock to unbridled trust land acquisition, and an 
obstacle to be avoided.
    In addition to the flaws in these standards, the BIA routinely 
limits, or ignores, the role of local governments in making decisions, 
including for off-reservation lands. The BIA limits its inquiries with 
local governments to little more than getting information on tax value 
of land to be removed from the rolls; it seldom considers the other 
impacts on communities or does anything to encourage cooperative 
relationships between tribes and local governments. Local governments 
are typically ignored, or treated as a problem to be overcome. As a 
result, there is little incentive for tribes to work with local 
governments to explore alternatives to trust land acquisition, often 
leading to conflict, litigation, and negative impacts.
                     recommendations on trust land
    To address these concerns, the town recommends that trust 
acquisitions be limited as follows: First, to give effect to the intent 
of Congress in enacting the IRA, on-reservation acquisitions under 
Section 5 of the IRA should be limited to land located within the 
boundaries of Indian reservations that were in existence on June 18, 
1934--the date of enactment of the IRA. Second, all other lands should 
only be taken into trust when clear, objective standards have been met, 
and the concerns of local governments have been satisfied. In 
particular, tribes should be required to seek solutions to trust land 
requests before seeking BIA approval; local governments should be 
consulted early in the process; and no acquisition should be approved 
unless impacts to the local community have been addressed and 
mitigated, either through binding agreements with the tribe, or 
enforceable Federal decisions. Meaningful requirements should be 
established for tribes to prove the need for trust land, as envisioned 
by Congress in 1934. And no change in use or purpose should be allowed 
without a new decision.
    In addition, the Secretary's authority to take land out of trust 
should be confirmed. The BIA appears reluctant to remove land from 
trust after conveyances have been made, even if the decisions are made 
in error. The Secretary should also have clear authority to remove land 
from trust if the proposed land use changes after trust acquisition to 
a land use that was not considered in the original decision, or to stop 
the new land use from occurring until a new review is conducted.
  rulemaking to revise the indian trader regulations will make these 
                             problems worse
    In addition to the loss of tax revenues from trust land 
acquisition, the town is also facing the loss of potentially 
significant revenues from state tax laws that require the payment of 
personal property taxes to local governments. Those assessments amount 
to hundreds of thousands of dollars in personal property tax every 
year, and, as previously described, were upheld by the Second Circuit 
in 2013. To be clear, these are taxes paid by non-Indians for personal 
property, wherever it is held, including on Indian lands. The potential 
loss of these revenues would obviously be magnified as more land is 
taken into trust.
    The BIA, however, is considering whether to proceed with an Obama 
administration initiative to revive obsolete and unused regulations 
governing ``Indian traders.'' The comment letters submitted by tribes 
to the ANPRM, issued in December of 2016, as well as records obtained 
under the Freedom of Information Act documenting communication between 
the BIA and tribes prior to the ANPRM, reveal that the true objective 
of this rulemaking is to pre-empt state and local taxes--including 
taxes on sales to non-Indians, as well as non-Indian personal 
property--that are valid under existing law, rather than any sincere 
objective to modernize the role played by the archaic concept of 
``Indian traders.''
    Our town, in conjunction with the towns of North Stonington and 
Preston, Connecticut, submitted comments opposing revising the Indian 
Trader regulations, which are no longer used by the vast majority of 
tribes and non-Indian businesses. Congress enacted the original Indian 
Trader Statutes more than two centuries ago, during a time when most 
tribes were isolated and economically undeveloped, to protect them from 
exploitation.\3\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \3\ The first Indian Trade and Intercourse Act was enacted in 1790. 
Act of July 22, 1790, 1 Stat. 137 (``An Act to regulate trade and 
intercourse with the Indian tribes.'').
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The current versions of the Indian Trader Statutes (Statutes) were 
enacted between 1834 and 1903 to prevent Indians from being defrauded 
by traders doing business with Indian tribes. 25 U.S.C. Sec. Sec. 261-
264. The Statutes authorized the Federal Government to regulate those 
who trade with Indians. See id. Sec. Sec. 261, 262. The Statutes 
directed the Secretary to specify the kind and quantity of goods that 
traders could sell to Indians and at what prices. See id. In 1957, the 
BIA promulgated the current regulations to implement the Statutes, 
which, among other things, prohibited traders from selling alcohol, 
selling tobacco to minors, and conducting gambling of any type on 
Indian reservations. See 25 C.F.R. Part 140. The regulations required 
traders to seek a license, prohibited them from trading with Indians 
anywhere other than at trading posts, and required traders to charge 
prices that were fair and reasonable.
    No one follows these regulations today. Tribes now conduct all 
sorts of business activities where they or their management companies 
operate gaming and sell alcohol. They also have pharmaceutical 
operations; they operate outlet malls, gas stations, box stores, 
hotels, restaurants, golf courses, convention centers and arenas. In 
some cases, they do this directly. In other cases, they enter into 
business arrangements where non-Indians operate businesses. Tribes are 
no longer dependent on a single or a few Indian traders for goods and 
services as many were when the Statutes were enacted; instead they have 
ordinances pursuant to which they govern their own economic activities.
    There is no need, therefore, to resurrect regulations to effectuate 
what are paternalistic and effectively obsolete statutes. The only 
appropriate contemporary response is that the Statutes are obsolete and 
the regulations should be eliminated entirely. Both the BIA and tribes 
recognize the modern irrelevance of the Indian Trader Statutes and the 
implementing regulations.
    The BIA's current effort to ``update'' those regulations, 
therefore, appeared intended, even at the time, to serve an entirely 
different purpose--to undermine the ability of states and local 
governments to assess legitimate taxes on non-Indians engaged in 
commerce on Indian land. Even on its face, the key focus of the ANPRM 
appeared to be taxation--an issue not addressed in the Indian Trader 
Statutes.
    The ANPRM states that ``the Department recognizes that dual 
taxation on tribal lands can undermine the Federal policies supporting 
tribal economic development, self-determination, and strong tribal 
governments.'' In that context, the ANPRM explicitly sought comments on 
``how the Federal Government can bolster those tribes that currently 
comprehensively regulate trade;'' the ``services [tribes] currently 
provide to individuals or entities doing business in Indian Country and 
what role do tax revenues play in providing such services;'' and ``how 
revisions to the trade regulations could facilitate economic activity 
in Indian Country and tribal economic self-sufficiency.'' It therefore 
seems likely that the BIA intends to include a provision purporting to 
pre-empt state and local taxation on non-Indians.
    The Secretary does not have the power to determine the 
applicability of state and local laws to non-Indians and should not be 
attempting to do so by regulation. The Secretary's lack of authority, 
however, is little comfort to those local governments that will have to 
defend against the lawsuits that will inevitably follow. The BIA 
recently included similar provisions when it revised leasing and right-
of-way regulations in the last administration, and those provisions 
have indeed generated significant litigation across the Nation. And 
while the Department has stated in Federal courts that the tax 
provisions in those rules have no pre-emptive effect, those regulations 
have clearly been used to undermine state and local taxation. This is 
the sort of outcome Federal agencies ought to be avoiding, not 
exacerbating.
    The impression that this rulemaking effort is intended to displace 
valid, and very necessary, state and local taxation of non-Indian 
activities was fully confirmed by the comments received by the BIA in 
response to the ANPRM. Almost every comment letter, out more than 50 
received by the BIA, was from an Indian tribe or tribal organization, 
and those comment letters uniformly supported the rulemaking effort as 
a way to eliminate the so-called ``dual taxation'' by state and local 
governments under existing law. In our view, there is no ``dual 
taxation;'' there is only the legitimate exercise of state and local 
authority to tax non-Indians, and the Tribe's authority to apply its 
power to tax where it has the authority to do so.
    In addition, documents released under the Freedom of Information 
Act reveal that issuance of the ANPRM was heavily influenced by a 
coordinated effort by the National Congress of American Indians (NCAI) 
and numerous Indian tribes to persuade the BIA to undertake this 
rulemaking, specifically for the purpose of pre-empting state and local 
taxation of all non-Indian economic activity on Indian lands. The NCAI 
provided a detailed memorandum, dated July 7, 2016, that is 
particularly revealing. Addressed to Solicitor Hilary Tompkins, the 
memorandum presents a legal argument for the BIA's authority to 
completely delegate the Indian trader licensing function to tribal 
governments and to ``eliminate dual taxation'' by promulgating a clear 
and unambiguous statement of Federal pre-emption of state and local tax 
laws. Expressing the concern that most Secretaries of the Interior come 
from a state government background, and therefore are sympathetic to 
the interests of state governments, the memorandum states that, 
``[b]ecause our proposal is for updated regulations that would further 
define the Federal interest in limiting state taxing authority on 
Indian reservations, many past Secretaries of Interior wouldn't let it 
see the light of day.''
    The ``light of day'' is indeed the best medicine for the BIA's 
initiative. The ANPRM, however, failed to draw the public's attention 
to the purpose and implications of such a rulemaking. As a result, the 
public at large failed to understand the significance of this 
rulemaking. Our towns were one of the very few non-Indian commenters on 
the ANPRM, and our comments were the only comments in opposition to 
this effort.
    Our town, like most local governments, is dependent on state and 
local taxation to fund the crucial governmental services we provide to 
all of our residents, including tribal members. Like virtually all (if 
not all) non-Indian governmental entities, we do not operate for-profit 
businesses and cannot easily offset tax revenues lost by Federal 
regulation. As previously described, our town has made significant 
efforts to defend our taxing authority.
    The town therefore opposes any effort by the BIA to create legal 
uncertainty regarding taxes that we have successfully defended in 
Federal court, as well as any general effort to undermine state and 
local taxing authority under the guise of reviving now-defunct 
regulations. We simply cannot afford to leave personal property tax 
revenues on the table from all non-tribal companies doing business on 
the reservation. If state and local taxation authority over non-Indians 
is to be pre-empted, that's a decision for Congress to make, not the 
Assistant Secretary for Indian Affairs. We ask this Subcommittee to use 
its authority to ensure the ANPRM does not move forward.
                               conclusion
    In conclusion, the trust acquisition process must be reformed to 
include objective standards for off-reservation requests and the full 
consideration of impacts to local communities. The current rulemaking 
proceeding to revive the Indian Trader Regulations should be halted to 
protect valid state and local revenue streams from non-Indian 
activities on trust lands. In addition, Congress should clarify the 
authority of the Secretary to remove land from trust if the proposed 
land use changes from that which was evaluated in the original 
decision, or to correct decisions made in error.
    Thank you for considering this testimony.
                                 ______
Questions Submitted for the Record by Chairman Rob Bishop to Mayor Fred 
                  Allyn, Town of Ledyard, Connecticut
    Question 1. You indicated that the trust land process does not 
accommodate the concerns of local governments. Please describe what 
changes should be made to the regulations or the procedures used to 
consider trust land requests for that purpose.
    Answer. As the municipal CEO of a small community, I believe it is 
crucial for the host community, as well as adjacent, potentially 
impacted communities, to be provided advanced notice of an application 
for proposed trust acquisition. Further, these same municipalities 
should be consulted and permitted to participate in the discussion and 
ultimate approval of proposed and future uses of the requested trust 
lands. If a tribe is unwilling to permit such collaborative effort, the 
land trust request should not be granted in the absence of a very 
strong ``need'' to do so. Existing criteria must be revised to take 
into consideration the aforementioned as well as the economic success 
of the requesting tribe.
    Specifically, Congress should amend section 5 of the Indian 
Reorganization Act to require the consent of the affected local 
government before off-reservation land is acquired in trust. The 
purpose for which land is proposed for acquisition--and which is 
analyzed under NEPA--must be clear and binding. Significant changes in 
land use must be subject to a new Federal approval, so that additional 
impacts can be addressed.
    In addition, ``on-reservation'' must be strictly limited to land 
within officially proclaimed reservation boundaries, not simply 
touching trust lands located anywhere. An objective standard for 
``need'' should be defined, including consideration of the tribe's 
economic success and its relative need for the extraordinary benefit of 
trust land compared to the impacts to the economic and social well-
being of the surrounding community. The impact to local tax revenues 
must be based on the proposed use, not the undeveloped land, because 
development will increase the cost of public services, without a 
commensurate increase in tax revenues.
    An objective definition of need is a critical step, as the economic 
benefit to the tribe in acquiring existing taxable lands in trust and 
potentially constructing new, non-taxable development will have a 
profound impact on the financial and social well-being of the host and 
adjacent communities. Low-density housing with ancillary uses such as 
community centers, places of worship and the like may pose modest 
impact on the host community and surrounding communities in terms of 
infrastructure, schools, emergency services and general municipal 
support. Gaming and other high-impact uses which may include, but are 
not limited to, destination retail, specialty retail, arenas/convention 
centers, professional athletic complexes and for that matter, large 
corporate headquarters will have tremendous impacts on both host and 
adjacent communities from many perspectives, including public utilities 
(such as generating a need to expand water treatment facilities), 
roads, bridges, emergency services, schools and other municipal 
services. How will these burdensome impacts on host and adjacent 
communities be addressed? In the current format, communities are left 
to address the impacts on their own, after the fact, and with a 
substantial increase in cost to taxpayers. In an open, collaborative 
format under revisions to the trust acquisition process, each of these 
impacts can be quantified and addressed in a manner that seeks fairness 
to all parties involved.
    Depending on the location of a reservation and based on current 
trust acquisition laws, it may be possible for a tribe to acquire land 
in trust, citing the existing arbitrary ``need criterion,'' then 
relocate a corporate headquarters or large scale manufacturing facility 
to a reservation. Such proposals on trust lands are not required to 
seek planning or zoning approvals, or to address local traffic impacts 
or impacts to municipal services. Should such an event occur, it would 
essentially become a new form of tax inversion. If it is not the intent 
of the Federal Government to fully guaranty reimbursement funding 
through Payment In Lieu Of Taxes (PILOT) and other means to the host 
and adjacent communities for the potential and very real impacts to, 
and ongoing maintenance of, the aforementioned municipal services, then 
the need for advance notice and a place at the table for the impacted 
communities must be provided for a revised trust acquisition process.
    Procedurally, the tribe should be required to provide advance 
notice to the affected local governments before an application is 
submitted to BIA, and those local governments must be consulted 
throughout the process. Trust acquisitions should not be approved 
without local government consent in the absence of a compelling need to 
do so.
    Question 2. You said that pre-empting state/local personal property 
tax over non-Indians would have a negative impact on your town. Can you 
provide specific information about that impact?
    Answer. The state of Connecticut empowers municipalities to tax 
personal property (including vehicles), as a means to assist in funding 
municipal government needs. To that end, the town of Ledyard issues tax 
bills for personal property only to the non-Indian private enterprise 
vendors doing business on the tribe's reservation. In Ledyard's case, 
this includes private enterprises doing business within the Foxwoods 
Resort Casino campus, including California Pizza Kitchen, Dunkin Donuts 
and Panera Bread Company as well as Tanger Outlets (a $2.5 billion 
publicly traded company), and the outlet and factory stores associated 
with the Tanger Outlet center, which include Nike, Ann Taylor, Armani, 
Gap Stores as a few of the 80+ stores. These non-Indian businesses 
generate a variety of burdens on our local government, and make use of 
our public services, for which the personal property tax is the only 
way we have of collecting revenue to pay for these costs. For example, 
these businesses depend on our public roads for their customers, 
employees, and suppliers. Those customers and employees can require 
emergency services from the town while in transit, and many employees 
live in Ledyard, using the full range of public services provided by 
the town, as well.
    For Fiscal Year 2016-2017, the town of Ledyard collected 
$539,073.54 in personal property taxes from these private enterprise, 
profit-motivated, non-Indian owned businesses operating on the 
reservation. These personal property taxes, a routine cost of doing 
business in numerous states throughout the country, have minimal impact 
on corporate owners, yet to our town, represent more than .5 mils 
annually in taxes used to mitigate the tax burden on our residents. In 
our town of 15,100 residents and a tax base comprised of 92 percent 
residential and only 8 percent commercial, each tax dollar increase or 
decrease falls squarely on the backs of the homeowners.
    To be clear, the town does not collect real property taxes on any 
structure upon the reservation, it is strictly limited to personal 
property taxes collected only from non-Indian owned entities (The Hard 
Rock Cafe is excluded from all taxes as it operates within the 
Foxwood's Resort Casino and it is owned by the Seminole Indian Tribe of 
Florida). The collection of personal property taxes should have no 
impact on the Mashantucket Pequot Tribe as the non-Indian owned 
businesses operating within the casino and reservation boundaries are 
responsible for paying these personal property taxes, not the tribe. 
There is nothing unusual about this in terms of what is often labeled 
as ``double taxation''--private businesses are typically subject to 
various taxes by more than one jurisdiction (Federal, state, local, or 
tribal), which are used to pay for the costs of government and the 
public services provided by each jurisdiction.
    The town has prevailed in a Federal legal case brought by the tribe 
regarding the town's taxation rights on personal property of privately 
owned, leased slot machines located on the reservation. The town has 
expended more than $1 million in this case and much to my dismay, the 
town has yet to be compensated for this 10-year legal battle.
    The loss of personal property taxes levied on businesses operating 
within the reservation would be catastrophic for our town. We have a 
total of two departments with more than 10 employees within the town's 
general government--those being the Police Department and Public Works. 
The balance of the departments are 1 to 3 employees. We do not have 
fluff and we have no overstaffing. The town operates on a very lean 
annual budget and find ourselves combing through line item expenditures 
yearly to seek savings as little as $50-$75. At last year's budgeting 
sessions, our Fire Marshal offered to purchase his uniforms at Wal-Mart 
at an annual savings to the town of approximately $180. This is but one 
example of the very real financial challenges we face daily. As Chief 
Francis of the Penobscot Tribe of Maine pointed out in congressional 
testimony on July 13, 2017, Ledyard does receive money from the so-
called Mashantucket Pequot/Mohegan Fund, as do ALL 169 municipalities 
within the state of Connecticut. As administrator of these funds, the 
state distributes this ``grant funding'' from this revenue stream that 
currently produces $269 million for the state. These proceeds are never 
fully distributed. As a host community, we receive an additional amount 
of funding. In Fiscal Year 2016-2017 that additional payment was 
$128,678--roughly enough funding to pay for one fully burdened police 
officer. A town adjacent to Ledyard, but not adjacent to the tribe's 
reservation, receives more than double what Ledyard receives as a host 
community. As of this writing, the governor of Connecticut's budget 
calls for elimination of all payments from this fund.
    We also educate the tribe's children in our public schools. 
Currently, we have 76 enrolled in our schools. For that, we receive 
annual Federal Impact Aid in an amount equal to $4,044.40 per pupil. 
Additionally, 14 percent of those students are special needs students. 
The town receives an additional annual payment of $669.90 per pupil for 
this. The annual cost of education per pupil in Ledyard is currently 
$15,100. This education example is one of the many additional costs 
placed upon the host community with no consideration of impact.
                                 ______
    Mr. LaMalfa. Thank you, Mayor Allyn.
    I now recognize Mr. Mitchell to testify for 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>                             ALASKA
    Mr. Mitchell. Thank you, Mr. Chairman and Ranking Member 
Torres. This is my fourth time since the Carcieri decision that 
the Committee has invited me to discuss it and the Indian 
Reorganization Act. How I got this gig is an interesting war 
story, but here I am again, and I very much appreciate the 
opportunity.
    In addition to my analysis of the situation in my written 
testimony, I would just make three points that I think are all 
self-evident.
    First, the Indian commerce clause of the U.S. Constitution 
grants Congress, not the Secretary of the Interior, not 
employees of the BIA bureaucracy, but Congress, the exclusive 
plenary authority to decide the Nation's Indian policies. 
Congress expresses its policy preferences by enacting statutes. 
The executive branch has a constitutional obligation to 
implement those statutes in the manner that the Congress that 
enacted a particular statute intended.
    That is not the situation that has happened here, as the 
Ranking Member just said, what the Carcieri decision did was to 
unsettle a ``long-standing administrative interpretation.'' 
Well, that is not how our constitutional system works.
    The way our constitutional system works is that they should 
have been administering the intent of Congress as that intent 
was enacted and codified in 1934. The U.S. Supreme Court said 
that they had not been doing that. And it is quite amazing that 
in 2014, that Solicitor Hilary Tompkins, having learned 
absolutely nothing from the Carcieri experience, came up with a 
Solicitor's Opinion to try to explain away the Carcieri holding 
in her Solicitor's Opinion on what ``under Federal 
jurisdiction'' means. And I suspect that when some day that is 
litigated, we will find that once again the Department has done 
whatever it can to not implement the intent of Congress from 
1934.
    The second point I would like to make is that, since the 
days of Ada Deer as the Assistant Secretary in 1993, I have 
been around a long time, this Committee has continually been 
told that the Members of the 73rd Congress intended their 
enactment of the IRA to end the ``assimilation policy'' of 
assimilation being the objective of Congress' Indian policy. 
That is simply historically inaccurate.
    To the man and the single woman, the members of the Senate 
and House Committees on Indian Affairs that wrote the IRA were 
committed assimilationists in that they thought that the best 
thing Congress could do for Native Americans who lived on 
reservations in existence in 1934 was to have programs that 
would encourage them to integrate themselves into the economy 
and popular culture of the Nation in which those reservations 
are located.
    Now, you can agree with that or you can disagree with that, 
but that was what they intended by any fair reading of the 
historical record. And what they intended was that the IRA 
should benefit people that were residing on reservations that 
were in existence in 1934.
    If you could bring Senator Burton Wheeler, who was a 
progressive Democrat, or Chairman Edgar Howard, the Chairman of 
the House Indian Committee, back from the dead, and tell them 
that 80 years later Congress was creating Indian tribes like 
the Graton Rancheria in statutes, or that the BIA was creating 
Indian tribes like the Cowlitzes out in Washington, they would 
be, first, astounded, and then outraged. And I am not 
expressing my policy views, I am just trying to tell you what 
those people that enacted the statute that is on the table 
today intended.
    Then the last thing I would say, Mr. Chairman, is that 
every member of this Committee has introduced bills that they 
hope that the 115th Congress will enact into law. If one of 
those bills is enacted, with the possible exception of Mr. 
Young, nobody stays in the U.S. House of Representatives 
forever, and if one of your bills was enacted, and 20, 30 years 
later you came back and you found out that the Interior 
Department bureaucracy did not like what you had done in your 
statute, and therefore had come up with an administrative 
interpretation to nullify it, I would suspect that, regardless 
of party or political philosophy, that each of you would be 
outraged.
    And that is, in fact, historically what has happened with 
respect to the Department's implementation of the Indian 
Reorganization Act in the modern age. Thank you very much, Mr. 
Chairman.
</option>
</Hearing>
