<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing>
    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <info>                         [H.A.S.C. No. 115-85]</info>
    <info>                                HEARING</info>
    <info>                                   ON</info>
    <info>                   NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT</info>
    <info>                          FOR FISCAL YEAR 2019</info>
    <info>                                  AND</info>
    <info>              OVERSIGHT OF PREVIOUSLY AUTHORIZED PROGRAMS</info>
    <info>                               BEFORE THE</info>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES</committee_name>
    <option>                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             SECOND SESSION
                               __________
</option>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON EMERGING THREATS AND CAPABILITIES HEARING</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                                   ON
                     A REVIEW AND ASSESSMENT OF THE
                    FISCAL YEAR 2019 BUDGET REQUEST
       FOR DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY PROGRAMS
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                             MARCH 14, 2018
                            _________ 
                U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
29-489                  WASHINGTON : 2019      
</option>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON EMERGING THREATS AND CAPABILITIES</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                ELISE M. STEFANIK, New York, Chairwoman
BILL SHUSTER, Pennsylvania           JAMES R. LANGEVIN, Rhode Island
BRAD R. WENSTRUP, Ohio               RICK LARSEN, Washington
RALPH LEE ABRAHAM, Louisiana         JIM COOPER, Tennessee
LIZ CHENEY, Wyoming, Vice Chair      JACKIE SPEIER, California
JOE WILSON, South Carolina           MARC A. VEASEY, Texas
FRANK A. LoBIONDO, New Jersey        TULSI GABBARD, Hawaii
DOUG LAMBORN, Colorado               BETO O'ROURKE, Texas
AUSTIN SCOTT, Georgia                STEPHANIE N. MURPHY, Florida
JODY B. HICE, Georgia
                Peter Villano, Professional Staff Member
              Lindsay Kavanaugh, Professional Staff Member
                          Neve Schadler, Clerk
</option>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <Speakers>STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>Hon James R Langevin</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative from Rhode Island Ranking Member</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon Elise M Stefanik</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative from New York Chairwoman</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <Witness>RADM David J Hahn</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>USN Chief of Naval Research</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Mary J Miller</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Performing the Duties of Assistant Secretary of Defense for Research and Engineering Office of the Under Secretary of Defense for Research and Engineering</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Dr Thomas P Russell</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Dr Thomas P</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Jeffrey H Stanley</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Deputy Assistant Secretary of the Air Force for Science Technology and Engineering</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Dr Steven H Walker</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Director Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency</peopleinfo>
    <option>APPENDIX</option>
    <Speakers>Prepared Statements:</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>RADM David J Miller Hahn</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Mary J Russell Dr Thomas P Stanley</peopleinfo>
    <subcomittee_name>Subcommittee on Emerging Threats and Capabilities,</subcomittee_name>
    <Chairman>
        <Cname>                         Washington</Cname>
        <Clocation> 2018.</Clocation>
    </Chairman>
    <people>
        <Pname>The subcommittee met</Pname>
        <Plocation> in </Plocation>
    </people>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>room 2118</Cname>
        <Clocation> Hon. Elise M. </Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <people>
        <Pname>Stefanik (chairwoman of the subcommittee) presiding.</Pname>
        <Plocation>Stefanik (chairwoman of the subcommittee) presiding.</Plocation>
    </people>
    <option>FROM NEW YORK, CHAIRWOMAN, SUBCOMMITTEE ON EMERGING THREATS AND 
                          CAPABILITIES
    Ms. Stefanik. The subcommittee will come to order.
    Welcome to this important hearing entitled ``A Review and 
Assessment of the Fiscal Year 2019 Budget Request for the 
Department of Defense Science and Technology Programs.''
    Defense Secretary Jim Mattis recently testified that, 
quote: ``Our competitive edge has eroded in every domain of 
warfare: air, land, sea, space, and cyber.'' End quote. And I 
couldn't agree more. Our committee, and the Emerging Threats 
and Capabilities Subcommittee in particular, has spent a 
considerable amount of time reviewing and understanding 
adversarial threats, most notably from China and Russia, while 
also keeping an eye on emerging technology such as quantum 
science, artificial intelligence [AI], nanotechnology, 
synthetic biology, autonomy, and robotics.
    We have seen troubling adversarial advances in warfighting 
systems like hypersonics and directed energy, and adversarial 
advances in enabling technologies, to include high-performance 
computing and artificial intelligence. We have also learned 
that many of our adversaries continue to increase their 
research and development [R&amp;D] budgets, and implement national-
level strategic plans.
    Russia has increased their basic research budget by nearly 
25 percent, and the Chinese have national-level plans for 
science and technology, as well as an approach to lead the 
world in AI by 2030.
    All of these signs point to top-down government-driven 
agendas that provide resources and road maps for strategic 
collaboration between industry, academia, and civil society. 
These efforts could propel Russia and China to continue to leap 
ahead in many of the technology sectors we will talk about 
today.
    But adversarial dominance is not a foregone conclusion. 
What we learn today and in future hearings must be translated 
into action--to inform and reform the Department of Defense 
[DOD] in support of national-level efforts in order that the 
United States remains home to the world's leading experts, 
researchers, and technological breakthroughs.
    Artificial intelligence is one sweeping area that I am 
particularly interested in from a national security 
perspective. Next week, I plan to introduce standalone 
legislation that will start the discussion on how we should 
better organize our government to understand and leverage AI.
    I look forward to working with my colleagues on the 
committee, and also with the Department of Defense as we craft 
solutions for this year's NDAA [National Defense Authorization 
Act]. Given these challenges, I am very pleased to see a total 
of $13.7 billion for science and technology [S&amp;T] in the 
Department of Defense budget request, an approximate $500 
million increase, and 2.3 percent of the total defense budget.
    But despite this increase, I remain concerned that our S&amp;T 
investments represent a small percentage of our overall defense 
budget. To truly increase lethality and provide a superior 
technological edge for our warfighters, we should ask ourselves 
if 2.3 percent of the total defense budget is the correct 
balance. A properly resourced science and technology enterprise 
in the long run reduces risk, and when properly executed, can 
generate efficiencies within the Department, something we need 
to keep in mind amidst debates on sequestration and continuing 
resolutions.
    Now more than ever our S&amp;T enterprise and investments play 
a strategic role and are central to our national and economic 
security. This hearing also marks our first open S&amp;T event 
since the National Defense Authorization Act directed the 
reestablishment of the position of the Under Secretary of 
Defense for Research and Engineering [R&amp;E] within the 
Department.
    And as I have said in previous statements, I firmly believe 
that the Under Secretary for R&amp;E needs to be the prime mover to 
drive change and foster innovation within the Department. A 
primary mission of this office should be to provide distinct 
direction and leadership to energize the defense industrial 
base, the military services, combatant commanders, and the 
Department of Defense labs. It must also guide newer 
initiatives, such as the Strategic Capabilities Office, the 
Defense Innovation Unit Experimental or DIUx, and even the 
Algorithmic Warfare Working Group, and the Defense Digital 
Service.
    And while many of these new initiatives have created 
tremendous momentum and energized the conversation about 
changing ``the culture'' of the Department of Defense, much 
more needs to be done to make these more than one-off quick 
gains. If properly empowered and resourced, I also believe that 
the Under Secretary for R&amp;E will be in a unique position to 
drive a national-level dialogue for S&amp;T policy that will, in 
addition to helping maintain a battlefield advantage, energize 
our domestic industrial and innovation bases, and provide 
technology jobs and opportunities across many of the sectors we 
will talk about today.
    So we have significant expectations, clearly, of Dr. Mike 
Griffin and his office, but we do so while also offering our 
support and confidence because the threats we face from our 
adversaries demand that we energize and organize our government 
to ensure that policy indeed keeps pace with technology.
    So to help us with this important topic today, we welcome 
five distinguished witnesses, starting with my left: Ms. Mary 
Miller, Performing the Duties of the Assistant Secretary of 
Defense for Research and Engineering [USD (R&amp;E)]; Dr. Steven 
Walker, Director of the Defense Advanced Research Projects 
Agency, DARPA; Dr. Tom Russell, Deputy Assistant Secretary of 
the Army for Research and Technology; Rear Admiral David Hahn, 
Chief of Naval Research; and Mr. Jeff Stanley, Deputy Assistant 
Secretary of the Air Force for Science, Technology, and 
Engineering.
    Welcome to all of our witnesses and we look forward to your 
testimony. I want to welcome my friend and ranking member, Jim 
Langevin, whose timing is indeed perfect.
    And when he gets situated, I would like to recognize him 
for any opening comments he would like to make.
    Thank you, Jim, I know today has been a busy day for all of 
us.
</option>
    <option>Appendix on page 33.]
</option>
    <option>RHODE ISLAND, RANKING MEMBER, SUBCOMMITTEE ON EMERGING THREATS 
                        AND CAPABILITIES
    Mr. Langevin. Thank you, Madam Chair. It worked out well, I 
actually literally just flew in a little while ago because of 
the northeaster we received yesterday. I got snowed out and 
wasn't able to get in until this afternoon.
    So, anyway, welcome to our witnesses. Thank you all for 
being here. And, regrettably, I understand Secretary Griffin 
was unable to join us today, although I recognize that he was 
just recently confirmed, and I understand his vision for 
science and technology and innovation, as the first Under 
Secretary of Research and Engineering, is paramount for the 
subcommittee.
    And I certainly look forward to engaging him in the very 
near future. And I appreciate, though, that Ms. Miller is here, 
that you are here representing the Office of the Secretary of 
Defense, R&amp;E enterprise, and it is good to see you again.
    Today we begin consideration, fiscal year [FY] 2019 budget 
request for S&amp;T across the Department of Defense, the total is 
$13.7 billion up from $13.2 billion requested in FY 2018. The 
amount requested for advanced development and prototyping is 
$20.8 billion, $3 billion more than requested in FY 2018, for a 
total of $34.5 billion requested for R&amp;E activities.
    This budget request comes on the heels of the recently 
released National Defense Strategy [NDS] that highlights 
specific technological advancements that the U.S. needs to 
leverage to maintain its warfighting edge. Many of these are in 
areas this subcommittee supported over the years, including 
artificial intelligence, directed energy, hypersonics, 3-D 
printing, and autonomous systems.
    The NDS also highlights long-term strategic competition 
with China and Russia and the need for an unparalleled national 
security innovation base. It is no secret that China is 
employing measures that encroach upon, poach from, and steal 
from us to further their objectives to be an R&amp;E powerhouse and 
degrade our warfighting edge.
    This is utterly alarming and greatly affects our national 
security. Unfortunately, China is not the only nation 
conducting such activities. They are, however, one of the few 
state actors that has coupled such tactics with considerable 
money and other resources behind a national strategy that 
involves a whole-of-government effort and leverages society to 
promote indigenous innovation. If the U.S. is to remain a 
global leader in technology, then we just can't play defense, 
we must also play offense.
    Our efforts to deter and counter China and other actors 
that threaten our ability to maintain our technological edge 
are absolutely critical, as are investments in science and 
research, prototyping, and other development efforts to advance 
warfighting capabilities and to promote deterrence. No less 
important are investments in STEAM [science, technology, 
engineering, the arts, and mathematics] education and in 
programs that develop junior talent into future tech leaders. 
And the implementation of strategic policies that promote a 
sound economic and political environment on U.S. soil where 
global collaboration, discovery, innovation, public 
institutions, and industry can thrive.
    We must also balance participation in the global S&amp;T and 
innovation environment with protection of national security 
interests. Clearly, this cannot be done through DOD alone, 
however. DOD has a significant role to play as a customer and 
driver of S&amp;T innovation. DOD S&amp;T ecosystem includes science 
technology and reinvention laboratories that house some of our 
Nation's greatest assets and people. It also includes DARPA, 
which is invested in some of the pie-in-the-sky ideas that came 
to fruition and change how we fight and how we live.
    They have absolutely lived up to what our expectations are 
to invest in those high-risk, high-payoff initiatives, and 
avoid technological surprise wherever possible. Over the course 
of many years, Congress has worked tirelessly to provide 
authorities and legislation that enable these institutions to 
be utilized to the fullest potential by the Department. Tools 
such as the Rapid Innovation Fund and Small Business Innovation 
Research [SBIR] program have been provided to DOD to leverage 
commercial innovation and have proven beneficial to that end.
    DIUx and other entities have stood up to enable the 
Department to make use of commercial technology and tech 
advancements. However, I believe DOD can make better use of 
these tools as well. DOD also administers the research and 
education program for historically black colleges and 
universities and national defense education programs, which I 
am pleased to say, received funding increases this year, 
although I believe those increases should be bigger. These 
programs enhance DOD's S&amp;T efforts and produce top talent for 
the future workforce.
    The NDS framework and the recent reorganization by DOD by 
Congress to separate program acquisition and sustainment [A&amp;S] 
from research and engineering provide the Department an 
opportunity to rethink how it approaches delivering the most 
advanced capabilities to the warfighter in the near, mid, and 
long term, and to bridge the ``valley of death.''
    In the era of strategic state competition, it is time to 
get creative, and we must outsmart our competitors and our 
adversaries. Today I look forward to hearing about how the NDS 
is shaping DOD's R&amp;D landscape; how the budget request reflects 
an investment being made that serves DOD's interest as both the 
consumer and driver of technology advancements; and how DOD is 
leveraging its ecosystem to the fullest extent so that we may 
remain the global technology leader.
    With that, I want to thank you, Madam Chair, for putting 
this hearing together. And with that, I yield back.
    Ms. Stefanik. Thank you, Jim. We now turn to our witnesses. 
Thank you for being here today. Your written statements were 
submitted for the record, so please summarize your opening 
comments within 5 minutes or less. And I will start with 
Assistant Secretary Miller. You have 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option> SECRETARY OF DEFENSE FOR RESEARCH AND ENGINEERING, OFFICE OF 
  THE UNDER SECRETARY OF DEFENSE FOR RESEARCH AND ENGINEERING
    Ms. Miller. Chairwoman Stefanik, Ranking Member Langevin, 
and distinguished members of this subcommittee, thank you for 
this opportunity to discuss the state of the Department's 
science and technology program for fiscal year 2019.
    I am proud to be here today representing the newly 
confirmed Under Secretary of Defense for Research and 
Engineering, Dr. Mike Griffin, and the scientists and engineers 
within the DOD S&amp;T enterprise. We are in an era of constant 
competition. We see nations like China and Russia investing 
heavily in research, trying to close the technology gap with 
the U.S. We see high-end military technology that has diffused 
to many countries that would have been unable to develop it 
themselves, even reaching some nonstate actors.
    In a world with near equal access to technology, speed is 
becoming the discriminator. Not just speed of discovery, but 
speed of delivery. How fast we can develop, adopt, or leverage 
technology to meet the warfighters' needs, and get it into 
their hands will determine our ability to outpace our 
adversaries.
    Under Dr. Griffin's leadership, I look forward to 
instilling within the Department a culture that embraces a more 
agile approach to development and delivery. You have been 
briefed countless times that our adversaries have spent decades 
watching us, how we conduct our warfare, how we fight. They 
have seen our equipment, watched our tactics, techniques, and 
procedures, and determined our concepts of operations. They 
have assessed both our strengths and vulnerabilities and 
strategically invested in capabilities to mitigate our 
advantages and exploit areas of perceived weakness.
    China, for example, has sustained increased defense 
spending since the early 2000s, with the fundamental goal of 
dominating the next generation of military and civilian 
technologies by 2050, making them both a military and an 
economic superpower that prioritize the research and 
development in areas that they believe will help them achieve 
this goal. Areas such as advanced materials and manufacturing, 
hypersonics weapons, advanced computing, artificial 
intelligence, and robotics, to name a few.
    Similarly, Russia has reemerged on the world stage and is 
pursuing force modernization while actively seeking to 
manipulate and dominate the global information environment. 
Meanwhile, North Korea conducts cyber operations to achieve a 
range of offensive effects with little or no warning, and 
continues to flaunt their emerging ballistic missile 
capabilities on a frequent basis. These threats span the air, 
land, sea, space, and cyber domains, which have all experienced 
dramatic capability advancements throughout the world. These 
advancements, coupled with our adversaries' commitment to a 
pace of prototyping, experimentation, and fielding that far 
outstrips our own, present a formidable challenge to our U.S. 
forces operating around the globe.
    In this competitive environment, the Department must pay 
much more attention to future readiness, and ensure our 
conventional overmatch remains over time. We must be willing 
and able to tap into commercial research, recognize its 
military potential, and develop new capabilities and 
operational and organizational constructs to employ them faster 
than our competitors. This would not be possible without our 
DOD scientists and engineers who are doing groundbreaking and 
innovative work. They are embracing these hard challenges our 
military faces every day, seeking to better understand the 
warfighters' problems and working diligently on affordable and 
effective solutions.
    The Department is addressing critical technology and 
capability gaps through a combination of adaptation of existing 
systems, such as efforts conducted through the Strategic 
Capabilities Office, and the development and introduction of 
innovative new technologies through our DOD labs and centers, 
DARPA, and DIUx.
    We recognize that our adversaries present us with a 
challenge of a sophisticated, evolving threat. We are prepared 
to meet that challenge and restore the technical overmatch of 
the United States Armed Forces through focus and innovation.
    Thank you for your strong interest in, and support of, the 
Department's science and technology efforts as we work to 
discover, design, and deliver technology capabilities our 
warfighters will need now and in the future. I appreciate this 
opportunity to testify on this important issue, and I look 
forward to your questions. Thank you.
</option>
    <option>Appendix on page 36.]
    Ms. Stefanik. Thank you. Dr. Walker.
</option>
    <option>                    RESEARCH PROJECTS AGENCY
    Dr. Walker. Can you hear me? Is it on? Okay.
    Thank you, Chairwoman Stefanik and Ranking Member Langevin, 
for having me here today. For 60 years DARPA has held to the 
singular enduring mission to develop breakthrough technologies 
and capabilities for national security. The genesis of that 
mission and of DARPA itself dates back to a commitment that 
President Eisenhower made that the United States would always 
be the initiator of strategic surprise.
    Working with innovators inside and outside of government, 
DARPA has repeatedly delivered on that mission, transforming 
revolutionary concepts and even seeming impossibilities into 
practical capabilities for the U.S. and allied warfighter. In 
the six decades since DARPA was established the world has 
changed dramatically. These changes include some remarkable and 
even astonishing scientific and technological advances, that if 
wisely and purposefully used, have the potential not only to 
ensure ongoing U.S. military superiority and security, but also 
to catalyze societal and economic advances.
    At the same time, the world is experiencing deeply 
disturbing geopolitical shifts that pose real threats to U.S. 
preeminence and stability. These dueling trends of 
unprecedented opportunity and risk deeply informed DARPA's 
strategic investments decision moving forward.
    My priorities for investment are very much aligned with 
President Trump's National Security Strategy and with Secretary 
Mattis' National Defense Strategy. So my priorities for 
investment in the future are defending the homeland, number 
one, from varied threats, to include developing cyber-
deterrence capabilities, bio-surveillance and bio-protection 
technologies, and the ability to sense and defend against 
weapons of mass terror.
    Number two. Deterring and prevailing against peer 
competitors in Europe and Asia will require new thinking. The 
U.S. can no longer be dominant across all scenarios, but it 
needs to be highly lethal in select ones. Realizing new 
capabilities across all the physical domains will be important, 
and hypersonics will be a key technology there, but we also 
have to look at space and the electromagnetic spectrum domains. 
They are going to be very important for that fight.
    Number three. Effectively prosecuting stabilization efforts 
across the globe requires us to get better at fighting 
differently and in different environments. Capabilities to 
address gray zone conflict, and 3-D [three-dimensional] city-
scale warfare, along with the development of rigorous and 
reliable models to predict adversarial moves will be critical.
    Last, but definitely not least, is number four, 
foundational research in science and technology. This will 
underlie all of DARPA's grounded pursuits, and is what makes 
possible never-before-seen capabilities. We must continue to do 
what I think DARPA does better than anyone, and that is to 
follow where technology can lead us to solve the country's 
toughest challenges.
    One of the foundational technology paths we are on 
currently is to help re-create advanced electronics. DARPA has 
had a key role over the years in advancing the state of the art 
in advanced electronics, especially in semiconductors. Today 
the advanced electronics industry is at an inflection point; 
design and fabrication [of] semiconductors is becoming ever 
more difficult and costly.
    China, which is significantly behind the U.S. now, has 
decided to invest huge sums of government-directed private 
capital to acquire today's onshore semiconductor design and 
manufacturing capabilities. In 2018, DARPA launched the 
electronic resurgence initiative, or ERI, which aims to create 
leap-ahead technology that will develop new materials, new 
circuit design tools, and new system architectures and 
manufacturing capabilities for the U.S. semiconductor industry 
and for our defense sector, to keep us out in front.
    As DARPA looks to its next 60 years, it promises to 
continue to be a bold, risk-tolerant investor in high-impact 
technologies so the Nation can be the first to develop and 
adopt the novel capabilities made possible by such work. With 
the continued support of Congress, and especially this 
committee, as well as the backing of the Pentagon and my S&amp;T 
partners on this panel, we will succeed. Thanks.
</option>
    <option>Appendix on page 44.]
    Ms. Stefanik. Thank you, Dr. Walker.
    Dr. Russell.
</option>
    <option>            OF THE ARMY FOR RESEARCH AND TECHNOLOGY
    Dr. Russell. Chairman Stefanik, Ranking Member Langevin, 
and distinguished members of the subcommittee, I would like to 
thank you for the opportunity to discuss the United States 
Army's program for science and technology for fiscal year 2019. 
This committee plays a vital role in supporting Army S&amp;T, as 
the program seeks to ensure the Army can operate and dominate 
in complex environments.
    These environments pose a variety of challenges 
characterized by adaptive adversaries employing conventional, 
unconventional, and hybrid methods designed to challenge U.S. 
national security. The Army and the joint future operational 
environment will demand a land power dominance with increased 
flexibility, adaptability, and speed of responsiveness.
    As a means to address current capability shortfalls and 
outpace anticipated threats, the Army S&amp;T strategy pursues a 
foundational technology development for future, and leverages 
organic capacity and the capacity of our partners. Army S&amp;T is 
the only portfolio focused in the Army's future investments. It 
makes investments today in fundamental science and technology 
initiatives that will ensure breakthroughs that will yield 
affordable, decisive, and advantages for the future.
    The S&amp;T portfolio is now being rebalanced to meet the 
Army's needs to prepare for and deter possible near-peer 
threats in the mid and far term. Based on the Chief of Staff of 
the Army's guide, the S&amp;T community with our stakeholders, 
reviewed the entire S&amp;T portfolio and concluded that the 
existing portfolio was out of balance, with too great of a 
focus on the near term, and technology developments focused on 
the counterinsurgency fight versus the near-peer threats.
    The Secretary and the Chief of Staff's modernization 
initiatives have further focused the S&amp;T program on the Army's 
top priorities, while maintaining vital long-term research into 
the cutting edges of military relevant science. As a result, 
greater than a billion dollars in S&amp;T funding was redirected 
from near-term efforts and projects to mid-term projects, 
reducing investments in counterinsurgency programs, and 
increasing and accelerating investments in technologies to 
prepare for and deter possible near-peer threats.
    This portfolio rebalance is impacting budget years 2019 
through 2023, which will allow S&amp;T to maintain a balanced 
portfolio investment to guide breakthrough science and research 
and technology innovation. The Army's S&amp;T program fully 
supports the six key modernization priorities: long range 
precision fires, next generation combat vehicles, future 
vertical lift, network/C3I [command, control, communications, 
and intelligence], air and missile defense, and soldier 
lethality.
    S&amp;T also pursues the broader basic and applied research 
that will create new capabilities and prevent technological 
surprise, including, but not limited to eight key technology 
investments: directed energy, artificial intelligence, 
robotics, internet of things, virtual reality, energetic 
materials, and ultra-design materials.
    In addition, state-of-the-art technical facilities are 
essential to ensuring that the Army's S&amp;T enterprise is 
positioned for discovery and maturation of critical 
technologies. An enterprise-wide approach to modernize is 
centered on three primary thrusts: organic technical 
infrastructure, informing construction of our partner 
facilities, and infrastructure collaboration such as the ARL 
[U.S. Army Research Laboratory] open campus business model.
    Our S&amp;T strategy provides the unifying framework for Army 
labs and our industry and academic partners to collaboratively 
mature new technologies. In addition to the 12,000 scientists 
and engineers in our S&amp;T enterprise, the Army labs and the 
research development engineering centers are critical assets 
for the Army. They have delivered key capabilities and support 
of ongoing combat operations and will continue to do so in the 
future.
    I welcome your questions.
</option>
    <option>Appendix on page 52.]
    Ms. Stefanik. Thank you, Dr. Russell. Rear Admiral Hahn.
</option>
    <option>    Admiral Hahn. Well, good afternoon, and thank you for 
having me. Chairwoman, Ranking Member, and members of the 
subcommittee, thank you for your leadership. So the opening 
comments of the Chair I think provide a pretty good summary of 
the state of affairs. And I think the significant term there is 
the advantage has eroded.
    Those who have gone before you in the seats that you sit 
in, in what used to be called the Naval Affairs Committee, back 
in the year 1946 were going through a similar conversation 
about how do we sustain science and technology and all that we 
had learned throughout the conflict of World War II to ensure 
that we don't repeat those same lessons going forward.
    So that group, the Naval Affairs Committee, stood up the 
Office of Naval Research. And I find the words in the 
legislation that created the Office of Naval Research continues 
to provide us our mission statement today. So I think it is 
important that we think about that for a moment. And I am going 
to read those words to you because that is what gives us our 
charge.
    So in your legislation, it says that my charge is to plan, 
foster, and encourage scientific research, in recognition of 
its paramount importance, as related to the maintenance of 
future naval power, and the preservation of national security. 
So those words echo the theme that as a maritime nation without 
naval power in the present and in the future, we will find 
ourselves at a disadvantage.
    The National Defense Strategy lays out pretty clearly, I 
think, that naval power is going to be very important in this 
great power competition that we find ourselves in yet again. So 
it is my charge to figure out how naval power is going to get 
generated through the elements of science and technology.
    I think it is pretty clear to the members of the committee 
that naval power comes from a combination in balance of 
capacity, capability, and lethality, and science and technology 
are at the heart of every one of those elements of naval power. 
Your United States Navy and Marine Corps is going to play the 
away game every single time.
    So my charge is to make sure that we are the first to field 
to take advantage of the speed of technology that is being 
created each day and to figure out a way to get that into 
programs of record where that capability gets to scale, and do 
it in a more and more lethal and a more and more creative way 
every single day, leveraging all those pieces of the puzzle 
that got put together back again in our experience in World War 
II, and that we leverage going forward to today.
    And you mentioned the three legs of that stool: it is 
academia, it is our industry partners, and it is our government 
workforce that understands how naval warfighting looks, and 
what technologies will apply to the naval warfight in the 
future. And those are the ones we invest in and try to carry 
forward.
    So there is good news here, right? Your leadership and your 
investment in a continued and steady way across the years has 
created a workforce of over 4,000 in my part of the enterprise 
and an analogous number and the same kind of talent across this 
whole team here. And it is our job to keep that team moving in 
the same direction, to leverage each other's investments and 
make the best of it.
    So I am happy to take all the questions. I look forward to 
the dialogue. And I couldn't be more proud than to sit here 
with the members of my team. Thank you.
</option>
    <option>Appendix on page 62.]
    Ms. Stefanik. Thank you. Mr. Stanley.
</option>
    <option>     THE AIR FORCE FOR SCIENCE, TECHNOLOGY AND ENGINEERING
    Mr. Stanley. Chairwoman Stefanik, Ranking Member Langevin, 
members of the subcommittee and staff, I am pleased to have the 
opportunity to testify on the Air Force's FY 2019 science and 
technology program. Challenges and threats to our national 
security are evolving rapidly. In some cases our near-peer 
competitors are matching or exceeding our Nation in 
capabilities.
    The Air Force has taken action on multiple fronts to change 
the way we leverage science and technology. The Secretary of 
the Air Force recently commissioned a broad-reaching initiative 
to assess our science and technology investment strategy to 
ensure our dominance across air, space, and cyber. Because of a 
variety of factors, the Defense Department is no longer driving 
the industrial base like it did 10 or 20 years ago.
    The Secretary's initiative is looking across industry, 
academia, the national laboratories, and other agencies to see 
where we need to invest in technology, and how we might change 
our processes and business approach. Change is necessary. And 
the Air Force is committed to ensuring our warfighters have the 
best technological advantage we can give them.
    Additionally, we have pivoted in several game-changing 
technology areas to amplify the enduring attributes of air 
power: speed, range, flexibility, and precision. To do this, 
the Air Force is partner with our other services and agencies 
to accelerate the delivery of these technologies. We partner 
with DARPA on our hypersonics developments and initiated two 
follow-on developments. We recently completed a directed energy 
flight plan and are in lockstep with the Navy and the Army to 
demonstrate mature high-energy lasers, high-powered microwaves 
for base defense, aircraft self-protection, and other tactical 
situations.
    Attritable systems like the low-cost attritable aircraft 
technology effort will change future air battles. Teaming with 
commercial industry, the Air Force has leveraged several 
advances in additive and 3-D manufacturing technologies, 
research into limited-life design methodologies, and advanced 
composites to create a family of vehicles like LCAAT [Low Cost 
Attritable Aircraft Technology], which are not only lethal but 
impose costs on our adversaries.
    The space industry landscape continues to change and we are 
aggressively pursuing low-cost access to orbit for payloads and 
microsatellites with programs like EAGLE [ESPA Augmented GEO 
Laboratory Experiment], which will launch next month. It is not 
only the technologies in which the Air Force invests that is 
important, but the pace at which the Air Force innovates and 
responds.
    Global competition has changed the speed at which the world 
around us operates. The Air Force recognizes that it is not the 
country that innovates the best, but rather innovates and 
applies technology the fastest.
    I want to thank the Congress for the recent NDAA language 
regarding prototyping. Prototyping allows us to bridge the gap 
between science and technology and programs of record, and 
deliver capabilities at the speed the warfighter needs.
    Lastly, the global competition for technology and the pace 
of technology development directly translates to the workforce. 
The workforce for science, technology, and engineering 
continues to be our most important resource. This is a national 
issue. And the demand for technical talent is far outpacing 
degree production in the United States.
    We are appreciative of the continued support from Congress 
through flexible personnel authorities. The Air Force continues 
to utilize these authorities to ensure we attract and retain 
the world-class workforce capable of providing these 
revolutionary capabilities for our warfighters.
    In summary, as the Air Force budget request highlights, the 
Air Force senior leadership is committed to science and 
technology and driving innovation across our enterprise. I 
thank the committee for the opportunity to testify today, and 
look forward to your questions.
</option>
</Hearing>
