<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing>
    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <info>                         [H.A.S.C. No. 115-97]</info>
    <info>                                HEARING</info>
    <info>                                   ON</info>
    <info>                   NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT</info>
    <info>                          FOR FISCAL YEAR 2019</info>
    <info>                                  AND</info>
    <info>              OVERSIGHT OF PREVIOUSLY AUTHORIZED PROGRAMS</info>
    <info>                               BEFORE THE</info>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES</committee_name>
    <option>                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             SECOND SESSION
                               __________
</option>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON EMERGING THREATS AND CAPABILITIES HEARING</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                                   ON
                     A REVIEW AND ASSESSMENT OF THE
                     DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE BUDGET,
                     STRATEGY, POLICY, AND PROGRAMS
    FOR CYBER OPERATIONS AND U.S. CYBER COMMAND FOR FISCAL YEAR 2019
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                             APRIL 11, 2018
                            _________ 
                U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
30-571                  WASHINGTON : 2019      
</option>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON EMERGING THREATS AND CAPABILITIES</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                ELISE M. STEFANIK, New York, Chairwoman
BILL SHUSTER, Pennsylvania           JAMES R. LANGEVIN, Rhode Island
BRAD R. WENSTRUP, Ohio               RICK LARSEN, Washington
RALPH LEE ABRAHAM, Louisiana         JIM COOPER, Tennessee
LIZ CHENEY, Wyoming, Vice Chair      JACKIE SPEIER, California
JOE WILSON, South Carolina           MARC A. VEASEY, Texas
FRANK A. LoBIONDO, New Jersey        TULSI GABBARD, Hawaii
DOUG LAMBORN, Colorado               BETO O'ROURKE, Texas
AUSTIN SCOTT, Georgia                STEPHANIE N. MURPHY, Florida
JODY B. HICE, Georgia
                Pete Villano, Professional Staff Member
              Lindsay Kavanaugh, Professional Staff Member
                          Neve Schadler, Clerk
</option>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <Speakers>STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>Hon James R Langevin</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative from Rhode Island Ranking Member</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Hon Elise M Stefanik</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative from New York Chairwoman</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <Witness>Kenneth P Rapuano</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Assistant Secretary of Defense for Homeland Defense and Global Security US Department of Defense</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>ADM Michael S Rogers</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>USN Commander</peopleinfo>
    <option>APPENDIX</option>
    <Speakers>Prepared Statements:</Speakers>
    <peopleSpeaker>Kenneth P Rogers Rapuano</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>ADM Michael S Stefanik Hon Elise M</peopleinfo>
    <subcomittee_name>Subcommittee on Emerging Threats and Capabilities,</subcomittee_name>
    <Chairman>
        <Cname>                         Washington</Cname>
        <Clocation> 2018.</Clocation>
    </Chairman>
    <people>
        <Pname>The subcommittee met</Pname>
        <Plocation> in </Plocation>
    </people>
    <ViceChair>
        <Cname>room 2212</Cname>
        <Clocation> Hon. Elise M. </Clocation>
    </ViceChair>
    <people>
        <Pname>Stefanik (chairwoman of the subcommittee) presiding.</Pname>
        <Plocation>Stefanik (chairwoman of the subcommittee) presiding.</Plocation>
    </people>
    <option>FROM NEW YORK, CHAIRWOMAN, SUBCOMMITTEE ON EMERGING THREATS AND 
                          CAPABILITIES
    Ms. Stefanik. The subcommittee will come to order.
    Welcome, everyone, to today's hearing of the Emerging 
Threats and Capabilities Subcommittee on the posture of cyber 
operations and U.S. Cyber Command [CYBERCOM] for fiscal year 
[FY] 2019.
    This hearing is the second of three cyber events today. 
This morning, we heard from former Secretaries of Homeland 
Security Chertoff and Johnson, as well as former CYBERCOM 
Commander Keith Alexander.
    Adversaries such as China and Russia aggressively leverage 
and integrate cyber information and communications technologies 
for geopolitical and economic gain, and they do so in a 
seamless way. Dictatorships have those advantages, and their 
control over these technologies and information is as much 
about exerting control over their own populations as it is 
confronting free societies such as ours.
    As discussed in the Worldwide Threat Assessment for 2018 
from the Director of National Intelligence [DNI], Iran and 
North Korea also continue to increase their offensive cyber 
capabilities and techniques. Over the last few years, both of 
these nations are believed to be behind cyber attacks that 
demonstrate not only a capability to deploy a variety of 
techniques and tools, but also a willingness to use cyber 
attacks as a means to achieve their national objectives.
    Needless to say, cyber threats today from state and non-
state adversaries are real, pervasive, and growing. Cyberspace 
and the information domain writ large remains contested and 
under continual stress. We are no longer peerless, and cyber 
superiority is not assured.
    Yet, while these adversaries continue to use cyber as a 
means to achieve strategic objectives, I remain concerned that 
we, as a government, do not have a strategy in place to 
mitigate, deter, or oppose their advances. It is safe to say 
that we have improved our military cyberspace and cyber warfare 
capabilities and also improved our resilience in many areas, 
but I am sure not the same can be said of the rest of our 
government--most notably, the protection of our critical 
infrastructure that preserves our economic security and ensures 
our way of life.
    Further work is needed to build interagency partnerships to 
ensure a whole-of-government approach to countering the growing 
cyber threat. The Department of Defense [DOD] plays an 
important role in this area, certainly when considering a 
significant cyber incident that may require their expertise 
during a time-sensitive emergency.
    From where I sit, a great deal of work remains to be done 
to improve our ability to defend, fight, and win in this 
critical domain, and also to improve and align our decision-
making processes and operational authorities so that we are 
fast, agile, and relevant. Only then will our Nation be 
prepared for the 21st-century challenges we face.
    Our witnesses today are very well-qualified to help us 
navigate these multidimensional challenges. Appearing before 
our subcommittee, we have Admiral Mike Rogers, Commander of 
U.S. Cyber Command and Director of the NSA [National Security 
Agency], and the Honorable Kenneth Rapuano, Assistant Secretary 
of Defense for Homeland Defense and Global Security and 
Principal Cyber Advisor for the Secretary of Defense.
    Thank you both for being here today.
    Admiral Rogers, this will be your last appearance before 
this subcommittee, and I want to extend my sincerest thanks and 
appreciation for your decades of service to our country and for 
the relationship that you have built with so many of our 
members on the House Armed Services Committee [HASC]. We wish 
you great success in your next chapter and wish your family 
well. Thank you again for your service.
    I would now like to recognize my friend and the ranking 
member, Jim Langevin, for his opening remarks.
</option>
    <option>Appendix on page 25.]
</option>
    <option>RHODE ISLAND, RANKING MEMBER, SUBCOMMITTEE ON EMERGING THREATS 
                        AND CAPABILITIES
    Mr. Langevin. Thank you, Chairwoman Stefanik.
    And thank you to both of our witnesses for being here 
today. I look forward to your testimony. I have certainly been 
studying cybersecurity issues now for over a decade, and I have 
to say, I still learn something every day as the domain and the 
actors in it continue to evolve.
    Secretary Rapuano, it is good to see you once again. We 
certainly appreciated your testimony on countering weapons of 
mass destruction a few weeks ago, and I certainly look forward 
to today's testimony that you will provide on cyber.
    And, Admiral Rogers, it is a pleasure to have you back 
before us again today, and I want to thank you for your service 
to the Nation. It has been many years that you and I have had 
the opportunity to interact, whether it is here on the HASC or 
in my years on the HPSCI [House Permanent Select Committee on 
Intelligence], and it has been an honor to work with you. And I 
am just grateful for everything that you have done and all your 
contributions to better protecting our Nation's cyberspace. I 
certainly wish you and your family well as you start the next 
chapter as well.
    2018 is poised to be a notable year for U.S. Cyber Command. 
Following the legislative action out of this subcommittee over 
the past several years, CYBERCOM will be elevated to a new 
unified combatant command [COCOM] after confirmation of the 
next commander.
    Additionally, a cyber posture review is being conducted for 
the first time, and a legislative framework is in place for 
notification of sensitive cyber operations. Cyber evaluations 
of major defense systems continue to be conducted to mitigate 
known vulnerabilities posing operational or other risk.
    Furthermore, cyber activities supporting named and 
contingency operations overseas have also matured, allowing the 
Department to leverage lessons learned when it comes to 
tactics, techniques, and procedures, as well as command and 
control of our forces.
    All teams of the Cyber Mission Force [CMF] are expected to 
achieve full operational capability [FOC] by the end of the 
year.
    These are all excellent steps forward, toward maintaining 
our superiority in an ever-changing domain, but, though 
progress has been made, of course, these efforts and 
achievements do not mean we have reached the finish line. 
Instead, I would argue that we have just begun the race.
    In addition to reaching FOC, we must ensure that the CMF 
has the right people, continuous training and education, and 
the best capabilities in our toolbox to perform against any 
threats that may confront us. We must be able to measure the 
readiness of these teams, define the requirements against which 
they are being or may be employed, and the frameworks in place 
to rapidly employ them and enable them to respond, when 
appropriate, based on clear legal policy and operational 
authorities.
    Existing frameworks are too ambiguous to effectively, 
clearly, concisely, and consistently employ the CMF against all 
mission sets. Effective and comprehensive policies to deter and 
respond to adversarial actors, as well as efforts to shape 
international norms of state behavior, particularly regarding 
use of military cyber capabilities outside of a combat zone, 
are progressing more slowly than desired.
    As I said at the outset, this domain continues to evolve 
quickly, and it is simply not good enough to just keep up with 
our adversaries. Instead, we must set the pace. However, we 
must not compromise our morals and values when employing cyber 
forces, for those qualities are what set us apart from those 
who seek to do us harm.
    We must also avoid a cyber cold war of sustained activities 
carried out by proxies or below the level of armed conflict. 
Instead, the U.S. must continue leading in crafting of sound 
domestic and international policies and laws for cyberspace and 
cyber warfare, working with our allies to assert and enforce 
rules of the road, rather than letting malicious actors do it 
for us.
    With that, I would like to once again thank our witnesses 
for being here.
    Take care, Admiral Rogers. I thank you again for your 
service and wish you well.
    And, again, thank you for being here today to discuss such 
an important aspect of our military's capabilities. I strongly 
believe that each and every conflict we face in the future will 
contain some element of cyber, and, as such, we must be 
prepared for all activities in the cyber domain.
    With that, I want to thank you all again, and Madam Chair, 
I yield back.
    Ms. Stefanik. Thank you, Jim.
    I would also like to remind members that immediately 
following this open hearing the subcommittee will reconvene 
right next door--oh, upstairs for a closed, classified 
roundtable with our witnesses.
    Before we move to our opening statements, I ask unanimous 
consent that non-subcommittee members be allowed to participate 
in today's briefing after all subcommittee members have had the 
opportunity to ask questions. Is there objection?
    Without objection, non-subcommittee members will be 
recognized at the appropriate time for 5 minutes.
    Welcome again to our witnesses.
    Admiral Rogers, the floor is yours.
</option>
    <option>        COMMAND, AND DIRECTOR, NATIONAL SECURITY AGENCY
    Admiral Rogers. Thank you, Chairwoman Stefanik, Ranking 
Member Langevin, and distinguished members of the committee. 
Thank you for your enduring support and the opportunity to talk 
to you today about the hardworking men and women of United 
States Cyber Command.
    On behalf of those hardworking men and women, I am here to 
discuss the command's posture and describe how we prepare for 
and execute operations in the cyberspace domain to support the 
Nation's defense against increasingly sophisticated and capable 
adversaries.
    The cyberspace domain that existed when we first 
established Cyber Command 8 years ago has evolved dramatically. 
Today, we face threats that have increased in sophistication, 
magnitude, intensity, velocity, and volume, threatening our 
vital national security interests and economic well-being.
    Russia and China, which we see as peer or near-peer 
competitors respectively in cyberspace, remain our greatest 
concern. But rogue nations like Iran and North Korea have 
growing capabilities and are using aggressive methods to 
conduct malicious cyberspace activities. Further, several 
states have mounted sustained campaigns against our cleared 
defense contractors to identify and steal key enabling 
technologies, capabilities, platforms, and systems.
    Our adversaries have grown more emboldened, conducting 
increasingly aggressive activities to extend their influence, 
with limited fear of consequences. We must change our 
approaches and responses here if we are to change that dynamic.
    While the domain has evolved, Cyber Command's three mission 
areas endure. Our first priority is the defense of the 
Department of Defense Information Networks, or DODIN. Second, 
we support other joint force commanders through the application 
of offensive cyber capabilities. And, finally, when directed to 
do so by the President or the Secretary of Defense, we defend 
critical U.S. infrastructure against a range of significant 
cyber consequences in support of the Department of Homeland 
Security [DHS] and others.
    In concert with the National Defense Strategy, we are 
charting a path to achieve and sustain cyberspace superiority 
to deliver strategic and operational advantage and generate 
increased options for combatant commanders and policymakers. 
Without cyberspace superiority on today's battlefield, risk to 
mission increases across all domains and endangers our 
security.
    Since my last update, Cyber Command has achieved a number 
of significant milestones.
    First, Joint Force Headquarters DODIN, our subordinate 
headquarters responsible for securing, operating, and defending 
the Department's complex IT [information technology] 
infrastructure, has achieved full operational capability.
    Secondly, Joint Task Force-Ares [JTF], our warfighting 
construct focused on the fight against ISIS [Islamic State of 
Iraq and Syria], has successfully integrated cyberspace 
operations into the broader military campaign to defeat ISIS. 
And we will continue to pursue ISIS in support of the Nation's 
objectives.
    Third, we have enhanced our training in cyber operations to 
prepare the battle space against our key adversaries.
    This year will bring several additional accomplishments.
    Cyber Command will be elevated to a unified combatant 
command. As a combatant command, we will have the unique 
responsibilities of being a joint force provider and a joint 
force trainer, responsible for providing mission-ready 
cyberspace operations forces to other combatant commanders and 
ensuring that joint cyber forces are trained to a high standard 
and remain interoperable.
    In addition, this month, we will start moving in several 
hundred people into our new, state-of-the-art integrated cyber 
center and joint operations center at Fort Meade. This will be 
our first fully integrated operations center that enhances a 
whole-of-government coordination and improves planning and 
operations against a range of growing cyber threats.
    And within this dynamic domain, it is imperative to 
continually evolve our training and our tools for our 
operators. We have recently delivered the first of several 
foundational toolkits, enabling the Cyber Mission Force to work 
against adversary networks while reducing risk of exposure, as 
well as equipping JTF-Ares with capabilities to disrupt ISIS's 
use of the internet.
    Innovation and rapid development demand competition and the 
ability to leverage all partners, including that of small 
businesses in the private sector. We intend to create an 
unclassified collaboration venue where businesses and academia 
can help tackle tough problems with us without needing to jump 
through clearance hurdles, which are often very difficult for 
some of them.
    Of course, all of our tools require a talented and 
sophisticated workforce to operate them. The Cyber Excepted 
Service, which Congress has helped create, will help us 
recruit, manage, and retain cyber expertise in a highly 
competitive talent market.
    Our success also hinges and remains entwined with continued 
integration of the Reserve and National Guard. In our 
headquarters, for example, we currently employ more than 300 
full-time and part-time reservists. And, in addition, Reserve 
and National Guard members are mobilized every day to lead and 
execute cyberspace operations.
    Perhaps most significantly, in the coming year, we are 
nearing completion of the build-out of our Cyber Mission Force, 
with all of our teams on a glide path to reach full operational 
capability by the end of fiscal year 2018. And, in fact, we 
will achieve this goal ahead of time.
    And as the teams reach FOC, our focus is on shifting from 
beyond the build, i.e., creating this force, to ensuring that 
this force is ready to perform their mission and is optimized 
to sustain mission outcomes year after year after year.
    Now, I fully realize that cybersecurity is a national 
security issue that requires a whole-of-nation approach that 
brings together not only government departments like the DOD 
and other agencies, but also the private sector and our 
international partners. And over the last year, we have also 
increased our interaction with critical infrastructure elements 
within the private sector and the broader set of U.S. 
Government partners supporting them.
    And, as you know, I serve as both Commander of United 
States Cyber Command and the Director of the National Security 
Agency. This dual-hat appointment underpins the close 
partnership between these two organizations. The fiscal year 
2017 National Defense Authorization Act [NDAA] includes a 
provision that describes the conditions for any potential split 
of this dual-hat arrangement. And the Department is working its 
way through this question. And, ultimately, the Secretary, in 
conjunction with the Director of National Intelligence, will 
provide a recommendation as to the way ahead here to the 
President.
    All of us are proud of the roles we play in our Nation's 
cyber efforts and are motivated to accomplish our assigned 
missions, overseen by the Congress, particularly this 
committee.
    And, finally, as you have already mentioned, after serving 
for over 4 years as the Commander of United States Cyber 
Command, and after nearly 37 years of service in uniform, I am 
set to retire later this spring. And, as I do so, I am grateful 
for the committee and its past and continued support and its 
confidence in me and in the Cyber Command team.
    And I look forward to answering your questions. Thank you 
very much.
</option>
    <option>the Appendix on page 27.]
    Ms. Stefanik. Thank you.
    Assistant Secretary Rapuano.
</option>
    <option> FOR HOMELAND DEFENSE AND GLOBAL SECURITY, U.S. DEPARTMENT OF 
                            DEFENSE
    Secretary Rapuano. Thank you, Chairman Stefanik, Ranking 
Member Langevin, and members of the committee. It is an honor 
to appear before you alongside Admiral Rogers, Commander of 
U.S. Cyber Command, to discuss the Department of Defense's 
priorities in cyberspace.
    In these roles, I oversee the development and 
implementation of the Department's cyber strategy and policy 
with regard to cyberspace, leading the Department's interagency 
cyber coordination efforts, advising the Secretary and the 
Deputy Secretary on cyberspace activities, and ensuring that 
the Department's cyber forces and capabilities are integrated 
across the joint force to support the missions assigned by the 
President and the Secretary of Defense.
    The Department's primary mission is to defend the United 
States and its interests. My focus from the outset has been on 
ensuring we are organizing, resourcing, and posturing ourselves 
to be ready to fight in and through cyberspace in a conflict 
with great-power competitors.
    To that end, we have prioritized the three themes of the 
2018 National Defense Strategy: increasing lethality, 
strengthening alliances, and reforming the Department's 
practices.
    The Department is pushing hard to ensure that we can deter 
aggression and out-think, out-maneuver, out-partner, and out-
innovate our competitors and adversaries in cyberspace.
    2018 will be a landmark year when U.S. Cyber Command will 
elevate to a unified combatant command, welcome a new 
commander, and complete the force-generation phase of the Cyber 
Mission Force.
    DOD's cyber forces are uniquely responsible for executing 
both offensive and defensive cyber operations, but national 
cybersecurity is inherently a team sport. Individuals, 
corporations, and organizations that own and operate critical 
networks must take appropriate steps to implement best 
practices in configuring connected devices and systems to 
mitigate known vulnerabilities, to harden the most critical 
networks' systems and information, and to implement basic cyber 
hygiene and security measurers.
    Cybersecurity experts estimate that some 90 percent of 
cyber attacks could be defeated by better implementation of 
better cyber hygiene practices and best-practice sharing. 
Therefore, an essential element of cyber deterrence must be to 
minimize vulnerabilities that potential adversaries can exploit 
with significant effects.
    Through basic cyber hygiene and information sharing across 
the government and private sector, we can drastically decrease 
the opportunities for our adversaries to hold us at risk, and 
the amount of time and resources we must spend responding to 
malicious cyber activity directed against us.
    We can then devote more capacity to developing and 
maintaining capabilities to hold our adversaries at risk. The 
Department is focused on preparations to defend the United 
States by halting or degrading strategic cyber attacks using 
cyber effects operations. We also seek to leverage the 
Department's extensive information collection mechanisms to 
provide timely indicators and warnings to public and private 
owners and operators.
    If a cyber attack of significant consequence should occur, 
the Department of Homeland Security and the Department of 
Justice, with other departments and agencies in support, would 
take the lead in responding to, recovering from, and 
investigating the different elements of a significant cyber 
incident.
    The DOD stands ready to provide additional support to DHS 
and other Federal agencies upon request. The technical skills 
possessed by the Cyber Mission Force can augment our 
interagency partners when the magnitude of a cyber event calls 
for a collaborative government response. We are currently 
working with the Department of Homeland Security to determine 
the most effective and efficient ways for DOD to enhance our 
support to these efforts.
    We must always keep in mind that the capabilities of the 
Cyber Mission Force were developed and optimized for DOD's 
warfighting mission. Offensive operations are the means by 
which the military seizes and retains the initiative while 
maintaining freedom of action and achieving decisive results.
    If and when the Nation faces a large-scale cyber attack, 
DOD cyber resources will be focused on and most effectively 
employed in our adversaries' networks--detecting, preventing, 
preempting, degrading, or defeating malicious cyber activities 
at their source, as well as holding at risk other critical 
equities and capabilities of the adversary.
    DOD cyber forces must also protect our networks and weapons 
systems against malicious cyber activity. The Department 
conducts network defensive operations every day in order to 
enhance our cyber resiliency. Defending DOD systems also 
requires identifying and mitigating our own vulnerabilities. We 
are moving forward to assess and redress major weapons 
platforms and critical infrastructure vulnerabilities, as 
mandated by the NDAAs for fiscal years 2016 and 2017.
    As outlined in the National Defense Strategy, the 
Department's weight of effort must be directed toward 
preparedness for war. At all times we must be ready to respond 
with both cyber and non-cyber capabilities to malicious cyber 
activity that results in loss of life, major damage to 
property, serious adverse foreign policy consequences, or 
serious economic impact to the United States.
    DOD must be prepared to compete and win in conflict below 
the threshold of conventional war as well. This is commonly 
referred to as the gray zone.
    Our adversaries are adept at calibrating their actions in 
both the physical and cyber domains so that no single event 
rises to the level that would merit a significant United States 
response. However, the cumulative effect of these actions can 
be significant.
    The Department's cyber forces must be prepared to respond 
to malicious cyber activity in the gray zone by preempting 
imminent malicious cyber operations, disrupting ongoing 
malicious cyber activities, supporting other agencies with our 
technical skills and capacity, and working with and through our 
allies and partners to apply diplomatic and economic pressure 
on these actors.
    I am grateful for the support we have received from 
Congress. The hiring authorities you have provided us have been 
critical to creating the Cyber Excepted Service. And your 
generous resourcing of DOD cyber activities has allowed us to 
stand up the Cyber Mission Force and put U.S. Cyber Command on 
the path to elevation.
    The President's request for FY 2019 helps us sustain that 
momentum and continue to strengthen DOD's ability to operate in 
and through cyberspace. The request includes $8.6 billion for 
cyber-related activities and represents an increase of roughly 
$600 million over the FY 2018 budget request.
    In closing, I would like to thank the subcommittee members 
for your time and your assistance working alongside us to 
develop the cyber force the Nation needs. The people in our 
cyber community are the best in the world, and I am honored to 
serve with them.
    The Department is committed to approaching the development 
of our cyber capabilities with the sense of urgency warranted 
by the gravity of threats we face. Our strong relationship with 
Congress has been a critical component of our success and will 
remain vital as we continue our work to ensure that the 
Department's cyber forces are prepared to compete, deter, and 
win against any opponent.
    I look forward to your questions.
</option>
</Hearing>
