<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing>
    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <Doc-title>VARIOUS MEASURES</Doc-title>
    <option>=======================================================================
                                 MARKUP
                               BEFORE THE
</option>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON FOREIGN AFFAIRS</committee_name>
    <option>                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                                   ON
              H. Res. 422, H.R. 425, H.R. 1196, H.R. 1660,
               H.R. 2658, H.R. 3320, H.R. 3329, H.R. 3342
                             and H.R. 3445
                               __________
                           SEPTEMBER 28, 2017
                               __________
                           Serial No. 115-69
                               __________
        Printed for the use of the Committee on Foreign Affairs
Available via the World Wide Web: http://www.foreignaffairs.house.gov/ 
                                  or 
                       http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/
                                 ______
                 U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
 27-013 PDF                 WASHINGTON : 2017       
____________________________________________________________________
 For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing Office,
Internet:bookstore.gpo.gov. Phone:toll free (866)512-1800;DC area (202)512-1800
  Fax:(202) 512-2104 Mail:Stop IDCC,Washington,DC 20402-001                                     
</option>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON FOREIGN AFFAIRS</comitteeM_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>EDWARD R. ROYCE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CHRISTOPHER H. SMITH</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Jersey</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ELIOT L. ENGEL</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ILEANA ROS-LEHTINEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRAD SHERMAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DANA ROHRABACHER</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>GREGORY W. MEEKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEVE CHABOT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ALBIO SIRES</Pname>
        <Plocation> New Jersey</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOE WILSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> South Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>GERALD E. CONNOLLY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MICHAEL T. McCAUL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>THEODORE E. DEUTCH</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TED POE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>KAREN BASS</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DARRELL E. ISSA</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>WILLIAM R. KEATING</Pname>
        <Plocation> Massachusetts</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TOM MARINO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DAVID N. CICILLINE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Rhode Island</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JEFF DUNCAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> South Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>AMI BERA</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MO BROOKS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>LOIS FRANKEL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PAUL COOK</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TULSI GABBARD</Pname>
        <Plocation> Hawaii</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SCOTT PERRY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOAQUIN CASTRO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RON DeSANTIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROBIN L. KELLY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARK MEADOWS</Pname>
        <Plocation> North Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRENDAN F. BOYLE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TED S. YOHO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DINA TITUS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nevada</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ADAM KINZINGER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>NORMA J. TORRES</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>LEE M. ZELDIN</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRADLEY SCOTT SCHNEIDER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DANIEL M. DONOVAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>THOMAS R. SUOZZI</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>F. JAMES SENSENBRENNER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Jr.</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ADRIANO ESPAILLAT</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Wisconsin</Pname>
        <Plocation>Wisconsin</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TED LIEU</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ANN WAGNER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Missouri</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRIAN J. MAST</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>FRANCIS ROONEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BRIAN K. FITZPATRICK</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>THOMAS A. GARRETT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Amy Porter</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chief of Staff</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Thomas Sheehy</Pname>
        <Plocation> Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jason Steinbaum</Pname>
        <Plocation> Democratic Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <table-of-content>C O N T E N T S</table-of-content>
    <peopleSpeaker> H Res </peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>Urging the adherence to the ``one country two systems'' policy as prescribed in the Joint Declaration between the Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and the Government of the People's Republic of China on the Question of the Hong Kong Amendment in the nature of a substitute to H Res  offered</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> by the Honorable Eliot L Engel</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of New York</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> HR </peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>To authorize the revocation or denial of passports to individuals affiliated with foreign terrorist organizations and for other purposes Amendment in the nature of a substitute to HR  offered by</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> the Honorable Ted Poe</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Texas Amendment to the amendment in the nature of a substitute to HR  offered by the Honorable Joaquin Castro a Representative in Congress from the State of Texas</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> HR </peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>To require a plan to combat international travel by terrorists and foreign fighters accelerate the transfer of certain border security systems to foreign partner governments establish minimum international border security standards</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> the Honorable Lee M Zeldin</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of New York</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> HR </peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>To direct the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development to submit to Congress a report on the development and use of global health innovations in the programs projects and activities of the Agency</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> HR </peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>To provide humanitarian assistance for the Venezuelan people to defend democratic governance and combat widespread public corruption in Venezuela and for other purposes Amendment in the nature of a substitute to HR  offered by the Honorable Eliot L Engel</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> HR </peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>To direct the Secretary of State to develop a strategy to regain observer status for Taiwan in the World Health Organization and for other purposes</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> HR </peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>To amend the Hizballah International Financing Prevention Act of  to impose additional sanctions with respect to Hizballah and for other purposes Amendment in the nature of a substitute to HR  offered by</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> the Honorable Edward R Royce</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> from the State of California</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>and chairman Committee on Foreign Affairs Amendment to the amendment in the nature of a substitute to HR  offered by: The Honorable Brendan F Boyle a Representative in Congress from the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania The Honorable David Cicilline</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> HR </peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>To impose sanctions on foreign persons that are responsible for gross violations of internationally recognized human rights by reason of the use by Hizballah of civilians as human shields and for other purposes</peopleinfo>
    <peopleSpeaker> HR </peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>To enhance the transparency and accelerate the impact of programs under the African Growth and Opportunity Act and the Millennium Challenge Corporation and for other purposes</peopleinfo>
    <option>APPENDIX</option>
    <option>Markup notice....................................................   228
Markup minutes...................................................   229
Markup summary...................................................   231
The Honorable Edward R. Royce: Prepared statement................   232
The Honorable Gerald E. Connolly, a Representative in Congress 
  from the Commonwealth of Virginia: Prepared statement..........   234
The Honorable Joe Wilson, a Representative in Congress from the 
  State of South Carolina: Prepared statement....................   236
The Honorable Theodore E. Deutch, a Representative in Congress 
  from the State of Florida: Prepared statement..................   237
The Honorable Ted Poe: Prepared statement........................   239
The Honorable David Cicilline: Prepared statement................   241
The Honorable Jeff Duncan: Prepared statement....................   242
The Honorable Brendan F. Boyle: Prepared statement...............   243
The Honorable Bradley S. Schneider: Prepared statement...........   244
The Honorable Thomas R. Suozzi, a Representative in Congress from 
  the State of New York: Prepared statement......................   245
</option>
    <Doc-title>VARIOUS MEASURES</Doc-title>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="">    The committee met, pursuant to notice, at 10:00 a.m., in 
room 2172, Rayburn House Office Building, Hon. Ed Royce 
(chairman of the committee) presiding.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman Royce</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Chairman Royce">This committee will come to order. Pursuant
to notice we meet today to mark up nine bipartisan measures. 
Without objection all members may have 5 calendar days to 
submit statements or extraneous materials on today's business.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Chairman Royce">I am actually going to place my own prepared statement into 
the record to save time, as we have been notified that final 
floor votes for the week will start at 10:15. As members were 
notified yesterday, we intend to consider today's measures en 
bloc, and so without objection the following items previously 
provided to members and also in your packets will be considered 
en bloc and are considered as read.</paragraph>
    <opening>[The information referred to follows:]H. Res.</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="">    House Resolution 422, urging the adherence to the ``one 
country, two systems'' policy for Hong Kong. It should not be 
one country, one and-a-half systems. It should be one country, 
two systems. Engel amendment 58 in the nature of a substitute; 
H.R. 425, the Foreign Terrorist Organization Passport 
Revocation Act of 2017, Poe amendment 45 in the nature of a 
substitute, Castro amendment 54; H.R. 1196, the 
Counterterrorism Screening and Assistance Act of 2017, Zeldin 
amendment 25 in the nature of a substitute; H.R. 1660, the 
Global Health Innovation Act of 2017; H.R. 2658, the Venezuela 
Humanitarian Assistance and Defense of Democratic Governance 
Act, Engel amendment 57 in the nature of a substitute; H.R. 
3320, to Develop a Strategy to Regain Observer Status for 
Taiwan in the World Health Organization; H.R. 3329, the 
Hizballah International Financing Prevention Amendments Act, 
Royce amendment 56 in the nature of a substitute, Boyle 
amendment 9, Cicilline amendment 8, Duncan amendment 33, Ros-
Lehtinen amendment 36, Schneider amendment 47; H.R. 3342, 
Sanctioning Hizballah's Illicit Use of Civilians As Defenseless 
Shields; and H.R. 3445, the AGOA and MCA Modernization Act.
422 
H.R. 425 
Castro 
H.R. 1196 
H.R. 1660 
H.R. 2658 
H.R. 3320 
H.R. 3329 
Boyle 
Cicilline 
Duncan 
Ros-Lehtinen
Schneider 
H.R. 3342 
H.R. 3445 
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman Royce</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Chairman Royce">So before placing my prepared statement
into the record I want to briefly highlight one measure here. 
H.R. 3329, which amends and strengthens the Hizballah 
International Financing Prevention Act, which was signed into 
law last Congress. In recent weeks we have seen alarming 
reports that Hizballah and Iran are building illicit missile 
factories on Israel's doorstep. This, combined with a reported 
fourfold increase in Iranian support to Hizballah, is pushing 
the region to the brink. We have got to further tighten the 
screws on these terrorists.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Chairman Royce">In addition to the $800 million annual support funding that 
they receive from Tehran, Hizballah continues to make millions 
from its trafficking in cocaine and other narcotics and in 
illicit cigarettes. This bill pushes back against Hizballah's 
international financial network, against its Russian and Syrian 
enablers, and against its sponsor, Iran. And I want to thank 
Ranking Member Engel for working with me on this important 
measure.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Chairman Royce">    Without objection my full statement on all nine bills will 
be entered for the record, and I now recognize the ranking 
member, Mr. Engel.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Engel</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Engel"> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Thank you for calling
this markup. I support all of the measures before us this 
morning, and I know we are on a tight schedule, so I am going 
ask that my statement in its entirety be entered into today's 
record.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman Royce</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Chairman Royce"> Without objection.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Engel</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Engel">Before I yield back I want to recognize
Francisco Marquez, who is with us today, a former political 
prisoner of the Maduro Government in Venezuela. He is here to 
raise awareness about Congressman Wilmer Azuaje, another 
political prisoner. The Congressman has been tortured, 
isolated, and denied medical attention, as well as access to 
his lawyer and family. Mr. Marquez, we have heard your story 
and so many stories like it, and with the bill I introduce with 
Representative Ileana Ros-Lehtinen of Florida, the Venezuela 
Humanitarian Assistance and Defense of Democratic Governance 
Act, we are providing humanitarian assistance to the Venezuelan 
people and raising the alarm about political prisoners and the 
assault on the rule of law.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Engel">    I also thank Senator Cardin for first offering this 
legislation in the other body. So I will leave it there, but 
again, I am glad to support all nine measures today. Mr. 
Chairman, thank you as always for your leadership, and I yield 
back.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman Royce</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Chairman Royce">Thank you, Mr. Engel.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Chairman Royce">Now, do any other members seek recognition?</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Chairman Royce">    Judge Ted Poe.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Poe</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Poe"> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I support all the
legislation. I also support Mr. Castro's amendment to my bill, 
the Foreign Terrorist Organization Passport Revocation bill, 
and especially appreciate Mr. Zeldin's legislation as well. And 
I ask that all my statements for all bills will be made part of 
the record.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman Royce</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Chairman Royce"> Without objection.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Poe</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Poe"> I yield back.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman Royce</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Chairman Royce"> Mr. Schneider?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Schneider</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Schneider">Thank you. And likewise, I commend the
committee for bringing this legislation to markup. I support 
this legislation. I have an amendment to the Hizballah 
Amendments Act, and I appreciate the support for that, and I 
will submit my statement to the record.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. Schneider">    Thank you very much.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman Royce</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Chairman Royce"> Thank you. Mr. Schneider. Mr. Wilson?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Wilson</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. Wilson"> Mr. Chairman, I would like to thank you and
also the ranking member, Eliot Engel, for the legislation that 
we have today, and I have prepared a statement in support, 
which I have offered for the record.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman Royce</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Chairman Royce"> Thank you, Mr. Wilson. Mr. Sires?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Sires</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="21" speaker="Mr. Sires"> I would also like to say thank you to you and
the ranking member for all the hard work. I certainly support 
all the bills that are here today, and thank you very much. And 
for the sake of time--I appreciate it.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Chairman Royce</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="22" speaker="Chairman Royce">Thank you very much, Mr. Sires.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="23" speaker="Chairman Royce">Hearing no further request for recognition the question 
occurs on the items considered en bloc.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="24" speaker="Chairman Royce">All those in favor say aye.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="25" speaker="Chairman Royce">All those opposed, no.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="26" speaker="Chairman Royce">In the opinion of the Chair the ayes have it, and the 
measures considered en bloc are agreed to. And without 
objection the measures considered en bloc are ordered favorably 
reported as amended.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="27" speaker="Chairman Royce">Staff is directed to make any technical and any conforming 
changes, and the Chair is hereby authorized to seek House 
consideration under suspension of the rules.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="28" speaker="Chairman Royce">And that concludes our business for today. I want to thank 
Ranking Member Engel and all of our committee members for their 
contributions and their assistance with today's markup.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="29" speaker="Chairman Royce">The committee is adjourned.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="30" speaker="Chairman Royce">[Whereupon, at 10:10 a.m., the committee was adjourned.]</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="31" speaker="Chairman Royce">----------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="32" speaker="Chairman Royce">Material Submitted for the Record</paragraph>
</Hearing>
