<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing>
    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <Doc-title>THE WEAPONIZATION OF THE NATIONAL ENVIRONMENTAL POLICY ACT AND THE IMPLICATIONS OF ENVIRONMENTAL LAWFARE</Doc-title>
    <option>                 IMPLICATIONS OF ENVIRONMENTAL LAWFARE
=======================================================================
                           OVERSIGHT HEARING
                               before the
</option>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES</committee_name>
    <option>                     U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             SECOND SESSION
                               __________
                       Wednesday, April 25, 2018
                               __________
                           Serial No. 115-44
                               __________
       Printed for the use of the Committee on Natural Resources
        Available via the World Wide Web: http://www.govinfo.gov
                                   or
          Committee address: http://naturalresources.house.gov         
                             _________ 
                U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
 29-883 PDF              WASHINGTON : 2018       
</option>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES</comitteeM_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROB BISHOP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RAUL M. GRIJALVA</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ranking Democratic Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Don Young</Pname>
        <Plocation> AK</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Grace F. Napolitano</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Chairman Emeritus</Pname>
        <Plocation>Chairman Emeritus</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Madeleine Z. Bordallo</Pname>
        <Plocation> GU</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Louie Gohmert</Pname>
        <Plocation> TX</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jim Costa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Chairman</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Gregorio Kilili Camacho Sablan</Pname>
        <Plocation> </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug Lamborn</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CNMI</Pname>
        <Plocation>CNMI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Robert J. Wittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Niki Tsongas</Pname>
        <Plocation> MA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Tom McClintock</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jared Huffman</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Stevan Pearce</Pname>
        <Plocation> NM</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Ranking Member</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Ranking Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Glenn Thompson</Pname>
        <Plocation> PA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Alan S. Lowenthal</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul A. Gosar</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Donald S. Beyer</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Raul R. Labrador</Pname>
        <Plocation> ID</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Ruben Gallego</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Scott R. Tipton</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Colleen Hanabusa</Pname>
        <Plocation> HI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug LaMalfa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Nanette Diaz Barragan</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jeff Denham</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darren Soto</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul Cook</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>A. Donald McEachin</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Bruce Westerman</Pname>
        <Plocation> AR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Anthony G. Brown</Pname>
        <Plocation> MD</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Garret Graves</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Wm. Lacy Clay</Pname>
        <Plocation> MO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jody B. Hice</Pname>
        <Plocation> GA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jimmy Gomez</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Aumua Amata Coleman Radewagen</Pname>
        <Plocation> AS</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Nydia M. Velazquez</Pname>
        <Plocation> NY</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Daniel Webster</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jack Bergman</Pname>
        <Plocation> MI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Liz Cheney</Pname>
        <Plocation> WY</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Mike Johnson</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jenniffer Gonzalez-Colon</Pname>
        <Plocation> PR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Greg Gianforte</Pname>
        <Plocation> MT</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>John R. Curtis</Pname>
        <Plocation> UT</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Cody Stewart</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chief of Staff</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Lisa Pittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chief Counsel</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>David Watkins</Pname>
        <Plocation> Democratic Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <table-of-content>CONTENTS</table-of-content>
    <peopleSpeaker>   Hearing held on Wednesday</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>April</peopleinfo>
    <Members>Statement of Members:</Members>
    <Speaker>Hon Rob Bishop</Speaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Utah Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>Statement of Witnesses:</witnesses>
    <Witness>Hon Raul M Grijalva</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Arizona Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>James Coleman</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Professor Southern Methodist University</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Horst Greczmiel</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Former Associate Director of NEPA Oversight Council on Environmental Quality</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Melissa Hamsher</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Vice President Environmental</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Laura Alice Watt</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>PhD Professor</peopleinfo>
    <submittedMaterial>Additional Materials Submitted for the Record:</submittedMaterial>
    <SubmittedMaterial>List of documents submitted for the record retained in the Committee's official files Submissions for the Record by Representative Bishop American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Richard A ``A Critique of Current Practices Under NEPA</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Submissions for the Record by Representative Grijalva Backcountry Hunters &amp; Anglers</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Letter to Chairman Bishop and Ranking Member Grijalva GreenLatinos and The City Project</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Submissions for the Record by Representative Huffman Point Reyes National Seashore</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Letters from ranchers and leaseholders printed in the Point Reyes Light OVERSIGHT HEARING ON THE WEAPONIZATION OF THE NATIONAL ENVIRONMENTAL POLICY ACT AND THE IMPLICATIONS OF ENVIRONMENTAL LAWFARE  Wednesday April</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>The Committee met</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>at : pm in</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>room</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Hon Rob Bishop [Chairman of the Committee] presiding</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Present: Representatives Bishop</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Thompson</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Tipton</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Cook Westerman</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Cheney</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Sablan Huffman</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>Gallego</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>Soto and McEachin</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>The Chairman All right We will call this Committee meeting to order We are here today to hear testimony on the weaponization of the National Environmental Policy Act</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>and</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>implementations of environmental lawfare Great words Under Committee Rule (f)</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>any oral opening statements are</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>limited to the Chairman and the Ranking Member This will allow us to hear from witnesses sooner Therefore</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>I am going to ask</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>unanimous consent that any other Members' opening statement be part of the hearing record if it is submitted to the Subcommittee Clerk by : pm today If there are no objections</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>that will be so ordered</peopleinfo>
    <SubmittedMaterial>All right</SubmittedMaterial>
    <peopleinfo>as</peopleinfo>
    <option>                     FROM THE STATE OF UTAH
    The Chairman. Today, this Committee is meeting to discuss 
the National Environmental Policy Act, a law that has been 
interpreted and administered far differently than Congress 
intended when it was created in the 1970s. It shows you what 
happens when we write vague and ambiguous language that can be 
defined not by congressional intent, but by litigation and 
courts and ad hoc decision making of agencies operating out of 
a fear of the next lawsuit for projects that are going to be 
large and/or small.
    As a result, we have an ever-expanding coagulation--you 
guys actually wrote ``coagulation'' for me?----
    [Laughter.]
    The Chairman [continuing]. Coagulation of regulation, 
guidance, and caselaw. As it has grown, NEPA compliance has 
become more complex, expensive, and time-consuming for agencies 
and the public.
    For example, we now average 5 years to prepare the average 
environmental impact statement. That is 675 days longer than 
the average was in 2000. Even an environmental impact statement 
will still run tens of thousands of pages and take a decade to 
complete. Even something shorter than that can still be in the 
thousands of pages, which simply means it makes a total mockery 
of CEQ's suggestion that complex EISs should be no longer than 
300 pages. And it puts the United States at a total competitive 
disadvantage with other western countries.
    The NEPA process that we have today is not a product of 
design, it is not a product of careful planning, it just kind 
of happened through cycles of litigation, over and over again. 
NEPA was never intended to be a weapon for litigants to force 
delays and denials on all sorts of activities with a Federal 
nexus. But the NEPA, as it is being implemented, provides just 
that.
    In fact, environmental reviews should inform governments of 
the actions they need to take, not paralyze it. And that is 
what is happening today.
    My hope is, with this hearing, to pause, take a step back, 
and examine through the witnesses' testimonies how NEPA has 
been weaponized by vexing litigation and begin to identify ways 
to restore it to its original intent.
    With that, I will ask that the entire statement I have be 
submitted into the record under unanimous consent and yield 
back my time.
</option>
    <option>   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman, Committee on 
                           Natural Resources
    Today, the Committee meets to discuss the National Environmental 
Policy Act, a law that's been interpreted and administered far 
differently than what Congress intended by its creation in 1970.
    Due to NEPA's vague and ambiguous language, the law's purpose and 
administration has largely been defined not by congressional intent or 
agency rulemaking, but rather litigation, court rulings, and ad hoc 
decision making of agencies operating out of fear of the next lawsuit 
for projects large and small.
    As a result, the NEPA process is now an ever-expanding coagulation 
of regulation, guidance, and caselaw. As it's grown, NEPA compliance 
has become more complex, expensive, and time-consuming for agencies and 
the public. The average environmental impact statement now takes 5 
years to prepare, 675 days longer than the annual average recorded in 
2000. An Environmental Impact Statement for a large-scale 
infrastructure project can run into the tens of thousands of pages and 
take a decade to complete. Even, shorter environmental assessments now 
routinely number in the thousands of pages. This makes a mockery of 
CEQ's suggestion that complex EISs be no longer than 300 pages. It also 
places the United States at a competitive disadvantage in comparison to 
other western countries like Canada, Germany, and Australia, who can 
complete most large environmental reviews within 2 years.
    The NEPA process is not the product of deliberate design and 
careful planning. It is a result of legal accretion. The outcome of 
repeated cycles of litigation and increased regulation. It was intended 
by Congress to be a mechanism for inter-agency coordination. It created 
a framework for Federal agencies to take into consideration the 
significant environmental impacts of ``major Federal actions.'' NEPA's 
drafters never anticipated that it would become the basis for thousands 
of lawsuits and administrative challenges.
    Nowhere does NEPA's text provide private parties with a right to 
challenge agency determinations in court. It was not intended as a 
weapon for litigants to force delays and denials on all sorts of 
activities with a Federal nexus. In its current form, NEPA provides 
just that.
    Faced with the credible threat of expensive and time-consuming 
litigation, agencies attempt to ``bulletproof'' their environmental 
impact statements, adding to the volume of paperwork without improving 
the quality of the review. ``Analysis paralysis,'' the seemingly never-
ending search for complete information, is a common phenomenon as 
agencies attempt to evaluate every potential impact or hypothetical 
factual scenario no matter how minimal or unlikely.
    Countless provisions have become law to streamline at least some 
aspect of the environmental review process or carve out particular 
classes of projects. In the executive branch, successive 
administrations from both parties have sought to improve NEPA failures 
administratively, to no avail. However, we've failed to address the 
underlying problem: the law itself.
    We can both better protect the environment and allow for thorough 
review and processing of critical economic, energy and infrastructure 
activities in a timely manner. These concepts are not mutually 
exclusive. But it simply won't happen unless Congress acts to clarify 
NEPA's intent, scope, and limitations. Environmental reviews should 
inform government action, not paralyze it.
    My hope with this hearing is to pause, take a step back and examine 
through the witnesses' testimonies how NEPA has been weaponized by 
vexatious litigation and begin to identify ways to restore its original 
intent.
                                 ______
    The Chairman. With that, I recognize the Ranking Member for 
his opening statement of up to 5 minutes. I did mine in 3 
minutes; see if you can beat it.
    Mr. Grijalva. No, mine is pretty coagulated right now. I 
just have to go forward with it.
    [Laughter.]
    The Chairman. It is damn bloody.
    Mr. Grijalva. It is bloody.
</option>
    <option>               CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF ARIZONA
    Mr. Grijalva. I want to thank you, Mr. Chairman, and thank 
you and our witnesses for taking the time to be with us today.
    Here we go again: another Republican attempt to undermine 
the National Environmental Policy Act so that companies making 
big private profits on our public lands can do so more quickly.
    My Republican colleagues really cranked up the misleading 
hearing title machine this time for this one, with 
``weaponization of NEPA.'' To be clear, the silencers and 
armor-piercing bullets Republicans tried to sneak into the 
sportsmen's legislation earlier this week were indeed weapons. 
The firearms that extremists used to take over a refuge in 
Oregon, those were real weapons.
    The National Environmental Policy Act is not a weapon, it 
is a shield. NEPA requires our government to assess threats to 
our environment and public health through consideration of 
alternatives and public input. The law protects average 
citizens from an unthinking government, and it is NEPA that is 
under attack at this meeting.
    This hearing will feature overheated rhetoric and unproven, 
irrelevant anecdotes from the Majority side. Before we get to 
that, I would like to lay out a couple of facts.
    Every year, tens of thousands of projects and activities 
are subject to NEPA review. And every year, about 95 percent of 
these projects are handled in a matter of days through the 
categorical exclusion process. Less than 1 percent of these 
projects go through full environmental impact statements, or 
the EIS process. An EIS can take time, but those projects 
requiring an EIS are the most complex and have the most 
potential to affect things like our air or water quality.
    Allowing time for a careful review of these projects is 
warranted. And the mere fact that a project took a decade to 
complete is not evidence that NEPA was the cause of the delay.
    Of course, the review process should move and could move 
much faster if the Majority would stop starving Federal 
agencies of the money and people they need to do their work.
    Of the tens of thousands of projects and activities subject 
to NEPA review, only about 100 lawsuits are filed each year--
100 out of more than 50,000 NEPA reviews each year. That is a 
small fraction of 1 percent. And that fraction of 1 percent are 
simply examples of citizens seeking to hold their government 
accountable, something I would think that my Republican 
colleagues would respect.
    NEPA is not too burdensome and it doesn't lead to too much 
litigation. Our economy is thriving since NEPA was enacted, and 
our environment has gotten much better. NEPA is not a weapon. 
In the vast, dark bureaucracy of the Federal Government, NEPA 
pulls back the curtain and lets the sunlight stream in. If that 
sunlight is a weapon, as my Republican colleagues now claim, 
the only thing that it is killing is bacteria. We need more of 
that, not less of that.
    With that, Mr. Chairman, I yield back.
</option>
    <option>   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Raul M. Grijalva, Ranking Member, 
                     Committee on Natural Resources
    Thank you, Mr. Chairman. And thank you to our witnesses for taking 
the time to be with us here today.
    Here we go again: another Republican attempt to undermine the 
National Environmental Policy Act so that companies making big, private 
profits on our public lands can do so more quickly.
    My Republican colleagues really cranked up the misleading-hearing-
title-machine for this one with ``The weaponization of NEPA.'' To be 
clear, the silencers and armor-piercing bullets Republicans tried to 
sneak into the sportsmen legislation earlier this Congress--are 
weapons. The firearms that extremists used to take over a refuge in 
Oregon--an action most of my Republican colleagues have yet to 
condemn--were weapons. The National Environmental Policy Act is not a 
weapon--it is a shield.
    NEPA requires our government to assess threats to our environment 
and public health through consideration of alternatives and public 
input. The law protects average citizens from an unthinking 
government--and it is NEPA that is under attack.
    This hearing will feature overheated rhetoric and unproven, 
irrelevant anecdotes from the Majority side, so before we get to that, 
I'd like to lay out a couple facts. Every year, tens of thousands of 
projects and activities are subject to NEPA review. And every year, 
about 95 percent of those projects are handled in a matter of days 
though the Categorical Exclusion process. Less than 1 percent of these 
projects go through the full Environmental Impact Statement, or EIS 
process.
    An EIS can take time, but those projects requiring an EIS are the 
most complex and have the most potential to affect things like our air 
or water quality. Allowing time for a careful review of these projects 
is warranted. And the mere fact that this project or that took a decade 
to complete is not evidence that NEPA was the cause for that delay.
    Of course, the review process would move faster if Congressional 
Republicans would stop starving Federal agencies of the money and 
people they need to do their work. Of the tens of thousands of projects 
and activities subject to NEPA review, only about 100 lawsuits are 
filed each year--100 out of more than 50,000 NEPA reviews each year. 
That is a small fraction of 1 percent. And that fraction of 1 percent 
are simply examples of citizens seeking to hold their government 
accountable; something I would think my Republican colleagues would 
respect.
    NEPA is not too burdensome, and it doesn't lead to too much 
litigation. Our economy has thrived since NEPA was enacted, and our 
environment has gotten cleaner.
    NEPA is not a weapon. In the vast, dark bureaucracy of the Federal 
Government, NEPA pulls back the curtain and lets sunlight stream in. If 
that sunlight is a weapon--as my Republican colleagues now claim--the 
only thing it is killing is bacteria; we need more of that, not less.
    With that, I yield back.
                                 ______
    The Chairman. Thank you. You should have coagulated more.
    [Laughter.]
    The Chairman. Now we are going to turn to our Committee to 
talk about the vision of the 1970s versus the reality of today.
    Our first witnesses are from left to right: Dr. Laura Alice 
Watt, a professor at Sonoma State University's Department of 
Geography, Environment, and Planning, and a member of the 
Resilient Agriculture Group--thank you for being here; Ms. 
Melissa Hamsher, who is the Vice President of Environmental, 
Health, Safety, and Regulatory at the Eclipse Resources 
Corporation--I appreciate you being here; Mr. Horst Greczmiel--
am I close to that--who is a former Associate Director of NEPA 
Oversight at the Council on Environmental Policy--thank you for 
joining us; and then Mr. James Coleman, who is a law professor 
at Southern Methodist University, the Dedman School of Law.
    I appreciate all four of you taking the time and effort to 
travel here to do this. Let me remind you that under our 
Committee Rules, I think you have all been here before, 
anything that you have written is already part of the record. 
This is an oral statement and is limited to 5 minutes.
    The microphones in front of you have to be turned on--make 
sure you do that--and then turned off again.
    The green light is go, the yellow light means you are about 
to get screwed over. And the red light--look, I will apologize 
to all of you here. We have to be back on the Floor right now, 
so I will be leaving quickly. For those of you who are here and 
I am still the Chairman, as soon as it hits five, I am shutting 
you down, regardless. Whoever replaces me in the Chair may be a 
little bit wimpier.
    [Laughter.]
    The Chairman. But for whomever is doing that, I hope not. 
And the only reason we do that 5 minutes is so that we can get 
on and make sure that you have time to answer questions from 
the Committee members, as well. So, I appreciate that.
    We will go from left to right as I am looking at you, 
starting with Dr. Watt. You are recognized for 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option>GEOGRAPHY, ENVIRONMENT, AND PLANNING, SONOMA STATE UNIVERSITY, 
                    ROHNERT PARK, CALIFORNIA
    Dr. Watt. Good afternoon, Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member 
Grijalva, and members of the Committee. Thank you for inviting 
me to testify today about the importance of consistency and 
accuracy in conducting environmental review under the authority 
of NEPA.
    I am a professor of environmental history and policy at 
Sonoma State and also an award-winning environmental planner, 
so I speak today both as a researcher and as a practitioner.
    [Slide.]
    Dr. Watt. I have spent 20 years researching and analyzing 
the history of land management by the National Park Service of 
historic working landscapes at the Point Reyes National 
Seashore in Northern California.
    May I have the next slide?
    [Slide.]
    Dr. Watt. This work has recently been published as a book 
titled, ``The Paradox of Preservation: Wilderness and Working 
Landscapes at Point Reyes National Seashore.''
    When Congress created the seashore in 1962, it recognized 
the significance of this working landscape with specific 
provisions to maintain the agricultural land uses within its 
boundary. Yet, since then, actions by Park Service officials 
have gradually eroded the number of working ranches at Point 
Reyes from 25 at the time of establishment to only 11 today.
    Based on my historic research, both agency action and 
inaction have contributed to this decrease. Examples at both 
the programmatic level and the individual ranch level include 
the failure to update the seashore's 1980 general management 
plan--I think I am a little off on the slides--which would 
provide an over-arching vision for the seashore's management to 
give agency actions coherence and consistency.
    This is despite starting a planning process in 1997, and 
actually completing a draft GMP in 2010, but that was never 
released to the public.
    This also includes failure to manage and control an 
expanding population of the reintroduced tule elk, which can 
damage ranch fencing and infrastructure, and threaten the 
organic certification of many of the ranches.
    Another example is the direct cancellation of several 
ranching permits, resulting in serious degradation of historic 
buildings, and increases in fire hazard from unmanaged pastures 
being taken over by invasive brush and weeds.
    Next one.
    [Slide.]
    Dr. Watt. A substantial part of this erosion of the working 
landscape has occurred through the uneven application of NEPA 
by Point Reyes staff.
    And the next one, please.
    [Slide.]
    Dr. Watt. On this chart--oops, I think we are off. One 
more. There we go.
    [Slide.]
    Dr. Watt. On this chart, the shading should line up across 
each row as some proposed change in land use or management 
triggers one or another level of NEPA review.
    But as you can see, in instances involving changes in 
natural resource management like the wetlands restoration, NEPA 
review has been conducted as it should. Yet, in each case 
involving agricultural use, either its removal or its 
continuation, the agency response with NEPA is the opposite of 
what it should be. NEPA has been conducted in cases where no 
land use change would occur, merely a continuation of existing 
use, and has not been conducted in instances of removing 
agricultural or maricultural use, even though these removals do 
cause change, and often substantial change, to the environment.
    These are concrete examples of an agency applying NEPA 
inconsistently when it sees fit, apparently on the basis of 
whether it likes a particular program or project. These 
inconsistencies in NEPA are troubling. They have contributed to 
the uneven treatment of land uses that Congress intended should 
be treated equally.
    Specifically, the 1962 Enabling Act contained clear 
congressional intent to retain the working ranches within the 
seashore's boundary. However, when the Park Service was granted 
full condemnation authority in 1970, the specific attention to 
agricultural lands was removed in the process. While Congress 
passed additional legislation in 1978 to create a procedure for 
ranching families to shift from reservations of use and 
occupancy to leases or permits, it neglected to reaffirm its 
originally expressed intent that working ranches remain 
indefinitely.
    Restating this intention now by amending the seashore's 
enabling legislation would not only help avoid further lawsuits 
by groups interested in forcing ranching out, but would also 
provide important benchmarks for what is considered a 
reasonable range of alternatives for NEPA review in future 
planning processes.
    In closing, I want to strongly advocate for the importance 
of environmental review, as it is often the only moment where 
we stop and at least consider the impacts of our actions on the 
human and non-human worlds around us. Yet, I also want to be an 
advocate for consistency and application of that review.
    Agencies should not scrutinize at one level here, and an 
entirely different one there. The rigor of NEPA review and, 
indeed, whether it is done at all, cannot merely turn on an 
agency's preference, but must serve to implement congressional 
intent for management of all resources. Thank you.
</option>
    <option> Prepared Statement of Dr. Laura Alice Watt, Professor, Department of 
 Geography, Environment, and Planning, Graduate Coordinator, Cultural 
     Resources Management Masters Program, Sonoma State University
    Good afternoon Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and 
members of the Committee. Thank you for inviting me to testify before 
the Natural Resources Committee today about the importance of 
consistency and accuracy in conducting environmental review under the 
authority of the National Environmental Policy Act, or NEPA. For the 
past 12 years I have been a professor at Sonoma State, teaching 
environmental planning as well as environmental history and policy. 
Prior to taking this academic post, I spent 4 years working as an 
environmental planner for EDAW, Inc., in San Francisco, primarily 
contracted to write 20-year Resource Management Plans for several 
northern California BLM offices, one of which--our RMP for the King 
Range National Conservation Area--won an award for ``NEPA Excellence'' 
from the National Association of Environmental Professionals. Hence I 
am speaking today about NEPA from my experiences both as a researcher 
and a practitioner.
    And before agreeing to testify, I took several days to consider 
this invitation, as I am concerned that some Members of Congress might 
be looking for information that could be used to weaken environmental 
regulations and review--as a life-long Democrat and dedicated 
environmental studies scholar, I would not want to contribute to such 
an effort. But I have decided to have faith that good information and 
insight will benefit environmental planning processes, rather than 
cause additional problems. So I am here today in the spirit of 
collaboration, and not as a partisan, to discuss the importance of 
consistency, accuracy, and fairness in agencies' application of NEPA.
    Specifically, I would like to tell you about a subject to which I 
have devoted some two decades of academic research and analysis: the 
history of land management by the National Park Service of the 
historic, working landscapes at the Point Reyes National Seashore 
(PRNS) and the Golden Gate National Recreation Area (GGNRA)'s northern 
district. This work resulted in the 2017 publication by the University 
of California Press of my book The Paradox of Preservation: Wilderness 
and Working Landscapes at Point Reyes National Seashore. Earlier this 
month, I updated my findings, based on developments since my book was 
published, in a presentation to the annual conference of the 
Association of American Geographers.
    What is now Point Reyes National Seashore has always been a 
stunning natural environment: A dark evergreen forest covers the spine 
of Inverness Ridge running up the eastern side of the peninsula, 
contrasting with the pale greens, golds, and grays of the more open 
hillsides that tumble down its western side to the ocean's edge. A 
typical day may bring bright sunshine in the morning, turning to dense 
fog and howling ocean winds by afternoon. But it has also been a 
working landscape for centuries. The native Coast Miwok actively 
managed this landscape through burning and other methods, to maintain 
open grasslands and encourage the species that rely on them. Since its 
earliest settlement by non-native residents--first Mexican rancheros in 
the 1830s, followed by northeastern dairiers in the 1850s--West Marin 
has been a place of pastoral beauty, an unexpected meeting of the wild 
Pacific Ocean with wide expanses of green pastures and white victorian 
ranches. Many of the families working the land have roots that go back 
four, five, or six generations, stemming from several groups of 
European immigrants who together form the region's distinctive 
character.
    Congress recognized the significance of this working landscape when 
it created the Seashore in 1962, with specific provisions to maintain 
the agricultural land uses within its boundary. Yet since the 
Seashore's establishment, actions by PRNS officials have consistently 
eroded the number of working ranches at Point Reyes--from 25 on the 
Point Reyes Peninsula at the time of establishment, to 11 today. On the 
lands owned by the GGRNA but managed by PRNS, the number of working 
ranches has dropped from 19 in 1972 to 8 today, with 6 additional ranch 
parcels leased for grazing. Based on my field research, this is a 
result of both agency intention and neglect. Examples, both 
programmatic and at the individual ranch level, abound, and include:
    &lt;bullet&gt; Failure (continuing to today) to update the 1980 General 
            Management Plan (despite completing a Draft GMP in 2010 
            that was never released to the public) to provide on over-
            arching vision for the Seashore's management;
    &lt;bullet&gt; Failure to manage and control the (re-introduced) tule elk 
            population so that it does not damage ranch fencing and 
            infrastructure, and threaten the organic certification of 
            many of the ranches; and
    &lt;bullet&gt; Pushing several permittees to discontinue ranching and 
            accede to the cancellation of their permits, resulting in 
            serious degradation of historic buildings and increases in 
            fire hazard from unmanaged pastures being taken over by 
            invasive brush and weeds.
    A substantial part of this erosion of the working landscape has 
occurred through the inconsistent application of NEPA by PRNS staff. I 
will describe a few examples, and urge the Committee to refer to the 
chart below showing inconsistencies over time:
    &lt;bullet&gt; All ranches shifted from Reservations of Use and Occupancy 
            (RUOs) to agricultural leases or special use permits in the 
            early 1990s (except Kehoe, 10 years later) with no 
            environmental review; documents indicate these changes 
            either being categorically excluded or tiering off 1980 
            GMP. This makes sense, because there was no change in land 
            use or management, just a continuation of the status quo. 
            Yet when Drakes Bay Oyster Company (DBOC, formerly 
            Johnson's) anticipated shifting from a RUO to a special use 
            permit in 2012, this change was deemed to require an 
            Environmental Impact Statement (EIS), which was completed 
            without a true no-action alternative--in the sense that a 
            no-action alternative should analyze the continuation of 
            present management--and with what the National Academy of 
            Sciences found were serious and material scientific 
            deficiencies.
    &lt;bullet&gt; Two ranch permits were canceled in 2000/01 (Horick at D 
            Ranch and Tiscornia at Rancho Baulines), but no 
            environmental review was conducted, despite a major change 
            in land use by removing an operating ranch and allowing, 
            over time, proliferation of non-native vegetation--with 
            dangerously increased risk of wildfire.
    &lt;bullet&gt; Despite the 1998 Finding of No Significant Impact 
            associated with the Tule Elk Management Plan written that 
            year--which involved relocating nearly 50 animals by 
            helicopter from Tomales Point to the wilderness area near 
            the Limantour Road--in 2008, 2010, and 2013, when ranchers 
            complained about tule elk causing problems on leased 
            ranchlands, NPS claimed the elk could not be relocated 
            without additional environmental review, despite there 
            being functionally no difference between moving animals 
            from Drakes Beach/Home Ranch rather than Tomales Point. 
            (And it's worth noting that in the 2006 Non-Native Deer 
            Removal Plan and EIS, elimination of the non-native deer's 
            economic impacts on the leased ranches was described as a 
            long-term, major beneficial impact.)
    &lt;bullet&gt; Secretary of the Interior Ken Salazar prompted the NPS to 
            issue 20-year permits to the ranchers in November 2012, yet 
            a year later PRNS announced that a Ranch Comprehensive 
            Management Plan, with associated NEPA review, would be 
            required first, despite the fact that only the length of 
            the permits would change.
CHART OF MAJOR PLANNING EFFORTS AT POINT REYES NATIONAL SEASHORE, 1990-
                    PRESENT
    .EPSAs the chart shows, since 2000, NEPA review has consistently 
been applied to agricultural lands in cases where no land use change 
would occur, merely a continuation of existing use, and has not been 
conducted for instances of removing agricultural or maricultural use. 
These are concrete examples of an agency applying NEPA inconsistently 
when it sees fit, apparently on the basis of whether it likes a 
particular program or project.
    The most recent example to come to light, just a few weeks ago, is 
the fact that PRNS had completed a full Draft GMP/EIS in 2009, that it 
never released to the public. Park officials have been quoted as saying 
that the DBOC EIS meant that park staff did not have time to work on 
the Draft GMP, yet PRNS completed several large planning efforts--
including the 1998 Elk Management Plan, the 2006 Non-Native Deer 
Management Plan, the 2007 Giacomini Wetlands Restoration Plan, a fire 
management plan, and a trails inventory--during the same time they were 
working on the Draft GMP. Furthermore, the Draft GMP was already 
completed, or very nearly so, when PRNS began work on the DBOC EIS.
    And it was this lack of a completed GMP that was targeted in the 
most recent lawsuit: In 2016, the Arizona-based Center for Biological 
Diversity (CBD) and two other groups filed suit and even brought a 
motion for a preliminary injunction to stop PRNS from renewing any 
permits for ranching at Point Reyes. CBD has long made clear its 
commitment to eliminating the working ranches from Point Reyes so it 
can be re-cast as a wilderness and preserve for the reintroduced tule 
elk. And, earlier this month, the Executive Director for the Idaho-
based Western Watersheds Project, one of the other plaintiffs in the 
lawsuit, penned an op-ed in the San Francisco Chronicle calling for the 
elimination of ranching from Point Reyes, for the same reasons: https:/
/www.sfgate.com/opinion/article/Cattle-grazing-on-Point-Reyes-public-
lands-is-12815606.php. As I wrote on the last page of my 2017 book: 
``[W]hen absolutist environmental organizations sling lawsuits at the 
NPS that explicitly aim to end ranching at Point Reyes, they are 
bringing the legal equivalent of the rifles and threats of the Bundy 
militants to the local community.''
    This suit resulted in a Settlement Agreement, whereby the NPS 
committed to study at least three alternatives for ranching, all of 
which result in the further reduction or elimination of ranching. 
Moreover, the Settlement Agreement gives PRNS until July 2021 to 
complete the process for this required General Management Plan 
Amendment (GMPA) and associated Environmental Impact Statement (EIS). 
While the Settlement Agreement was inked in July 2017, and initial 
scoping meetings were held and public comment solicited in November 
2017, PRNS has yet to issue a Notice of Intent to formally begin 
preparation of the GMPA/EIS--which usually occurs before scoping 
begins, not after. As someone who has conducted Federal public land 
management planning and associated NEPA review myself, it's difficult 
to understand what purpose delaying the Notice of Intent serves, and 
more importantly, why it would take 4 years to complete a GMP Amendment 
and EIS process, covering only a limited portion of the Seashore; in 
contrast, writing the full Resource Management Plan for the King Range 
NCA--an area of roughly the same size with very similar management 
issues to Point Reyes--took just a little over 2 years from start to 
finish.
    These inconsistencies in NEPA and land management planning 
processes are troubling. Congress created the Point Reyes National 
Seashore, and so Congress ultimately bears responsibility for the 
decisions that are made there. If Congress cares about the future of 
this working landscape, it should provide clear direction regarding its 
intended purposes. When working to write the King Range NCA's 
management plan, both the BLM staff and my team as consultants took 
guidance from the law establishing the Area, which gave clear, 
unambiguous direction. In the case of Point Reyes, the 1962 Enabling 
Act also contained clear congressional intent to retain the working 
ranches within the Seashore's boundary. However, when NPS was granted 
full condemnation authority in the 1970 legislation, along with raising 
the land acquisition appropriation, the specific attention to 
agricultural lands was removed in the process. While Congress put in 
place a process for the ranching families to shift from RUOs to leases 
or permits with its 1978 legislation, it did not reaffirm its expressed 
intention that the working ranches remain indefinitely. Restating this 
intention now in the Seashore's enabling legislation would not only 
help avoid further lawsuits, but would provide useful benchmarks for 
what is a reasonable range of alternatives to consider for NEPA review 
in the current GMPA/EIS process. Prompt passage of a narrowly tailored 
purposes amendment that preserves the historical and cultural uses of 
ranches and dairies at Point Reyes would finally provide the certainty 
and security of tenure necessary for these wonderful examples of 
sustainable agriculture to continue.
    In closing, I want to strongly advocate for the importance of 
environmental review, as it is often the only moment where we stop and, 
at very least, consider the impacts of our actions on the human and 
non-human worlds around us--and yet I also want to advocate for the 
need for consistency in application of that review. It cannot 
scrutinize at one level here, and an entirely different one there. Its 
rigor--indeed, whether it is done at all--cannot merely turn on whether 
the lead agency ``likes'' a project.
    Furthermore, in my book, I suggest that an environmental thinker 
who deserves more attention in park management is Aldo Leopold, who in 
his pioneering advocacy for wilderness protection also wrote of the 
importance of re-establishing a personal and cooperative relationship 
with the natural world through working the land. For Leopold, visiting 
and admiring is not enough; we need to recognize our reliance on and 
co-existence with the wild through living and working with it. I do not 
want to romanticize ``the local,'' but I also believe that communities 
who are directly affected by a Federal action, be it a project or a 
plan, should have some specific input into how that project or plan 
takes shape--not better than, or above, or before other public comment, 
but simply as a different category of input. NEPA aims to consider 
impacts on the human environment, but too often the near-scale of human 
involvement is sacrificed to the broader scales of national 
implications--whether in regard to maximizing GDP or industrial profit 
on the one hand, or an idealization of environmental purity on the 
other.
    Point Reyes has long been ideally suited to be managed as a 
Leopoldian park, a place where the wild and the pastoral are not in 
competition but are complementary, thriving side by side. The NPS 
itself is beginning to understand this relationship, with some of its 
leaders calling for a greater focus on integrated stewardship, as well 
as ``deepening public engagement and establishing ever-more-meaningful 
connections'' between parks and the communities they serve. Geographer 
David Lowenthal has advised the agency that parks and wilderness areas 
``must begin to exemplify, rather than be set apart from, the everyday 
terrain of our ordinary places of work and play, travel and repose.'' 
Numerous examples of successful management of working landscapes within 
national parks can be found elsewhere around the globe. By building on 
the insight of Aldo Leopold, recognizing that the wild and the pastoral 
can not only co-exist but also strengthen each other, Point Reyes could 
be a powerful model of this evolving stewardship approach.
                                 ______
      Supplemental Testimony Submitted for the Record by Dr. Watt
                           Sonoma State University,
                                   Rohnert Park, California
                                                        May 5, 2018
    Dear Representatives:
    It has come to my attention that the National Parks and 
Conservation Association (NPCA) has submitted a letter to your 
Committee that, among other statements, takes issue with testimony I 
provided in writing on April 23, 2018, and in person at your 
Committee's hearing on April 25, 2018. Specifically, the NPCA's letter 
alleges that the Resilient Agriculture Group, of which I am a member, 
is ``secretive'' and that my testimony ``lacks credibility on this 
topic and contains factual inaccuracies.'' I am writing to rebut these 
claims.
    To me, it is telling that the NPCA asserts that my testimony 
contains factual inaccuracies, yet the organization provides no 
evidence of such. The same is actually true of Representative Jared 
Huffman's comments during the hearing, in that he stated that he 
``disagreed'' with some of my testimony, but offered no facts or 
information to counter my detailed analysis. While he correctly stated 
that NEPA requirements vary widely with different kinds of projects and 
circumstances, my testimony contains instances of inconsistent review 
at Point Reyes applied to agency actions that are very, very similar, 
if not identical in their scope--such as extending an existing lease. I 
am confident that all information I have provided to the Committee is 
factually accurate and represents a genuine history of uneven 
application of NEPA.
    The suggestion that I lack credibility on the topic of the 
application of environmental review under the authority of the National 
Environmental Policy Act (NEPA) is laughable; as I stated in my 
testimony, I not only teach NEPA and environmental planning regularly, 
I also have four years of experience as an environmental consultant, 
primarily contracted to produce twenty-year Resource Management Plans 
for several northern California BLM offices, one of which--our Plan and 
Environmental Impact Statement for the King Range National Conservation 
Area--won an award for ``NEPA Excellence'' from the National 
Association of Environmental Professionals. This background 
unquestionably gives me credibility on the subject of NEPA.
    Furthermore, I have spent twenty years researching the history of 
land management at the Point Reyes National Seashore (PRNS) and the 
Golden Gate National Recreation Area (GGNRA)'s northern district. This 
work resulted in the 2017 publication by the University of California 
Press of my book The Paradox of Preservation: Wilderness and Working 
Landscapes at Point Reyes National Seashore, as well as several peer-
reviewed articles. Given that my recent testimony focused on NPS 
practices of NEPA review at Point Reyes in the last few decades, I 
believe my archival research and analysis also gives me credibility to 
write and speak about Point Reyes and the uneven application of NEPA 
review for a variety of projects and plans.
    Based on this research, I would also like to correct Representative 
Huffman's statement, made during the hearing, that ``there are more 
acres grazed today than during the 1980 General Management Plan,'' as 
that is not the case. While the 1980 GMP did not include detailed 
tallies of all acres grazed, adding together the acreage in grazing for 
both the Point Reyes peninsula and the GGNRA lands managed by PRNS, the 
total was approximately 30,000 acres in 1980, and has decreased to 
28,000 today. While this reduction is a relatively small portion of the 
total, the number of ranches that have ceased operation in this time is 
much larger: The Point Reyes peninsula supported twenty-five active 
ranches when the Seashore was established in 1962, but has only eleven 
active operations today, or fewer than half. In the GGNRA's northern 
district, the number of operating ranches has dwindled from twenty in 
1972 to eight today, a decrease of roughly sixty percent. A working 
landscape cannot only be measured in terms of acres in grazing, but 
also in terms of the human families and broader community that those 
lands represent, so these reductions are truly troubling.
    The NPCA's claim that the Resilient Agriculture Group is 
``secretive'' is also inaccurate; members of our group have been quite 
open about our membership in the local press, and have been in regular 
correspondence with both the Point Reyes Seashore Ranchers Association 
(PRSRA), representatives of other organizations that support 
environmental quality and sustainable agriculture, and local elected 
officials on the subject of Point Reyes management for months. Anyone 
interested in the membership or the goals of our group only needs to 
ask. We are not currently incorporated formally, but neither are many 
other groups active in commenting on these issues--examples include the 
People for the Golden Gate National Recreation Area, which participated 
extensively in NPS management of both PRNS and GGNRA for decades; the 
Committee to Preserve the Tule Elk, which similarly provides comment 
letters on activities at Point Reyes; and indeed the PRSRA itself.
    Lastly, the NPCA's letter also asserts that ``Dr. Watt is not a 
rancher at the Seashore and does not speak for or represent the 
ranchers''; this statement is puzzling to me, as I have never claimed--
neither in my testimony nor on any other occasion--to be a rancher or 
to represent the Seashore ranchers. In my Congressional testimony, I 
only represented myself as an expert on the subject at hand. I 
similarly have written comment letters to the Point Reyes National 
Seashore in the past, regarding their various planning and NEPA 
efforts, representing only myself and my professional expertise. I 
count many members of the PRSRA as personal friends, and in 2013 their 
organization honored me with a Certificate of Appreciation, which still 
hangs in my office. I am copying the PRSRA on this letter, to ensure 
that they understand that I would never presume to speak on their 
behalf; they are perfectly capable of representing themselves.
    My testimony made clear my strong support for NEPA and the 
environmental review process; in no way have I questioned the need for 
environmental review, nor current planning efforts at Point Reyes. My 
comments called for better consistency in NEPA review going forward, 
based on evidence from the past, and I do not appreciate a national 
environmental advocacy group trying to imply otherwise.
            Sincerely,
                                      Dr. Laura Alice Watt,
                                                         Professor.
                                 ______
    The Chairman. Thank you. You did that with 6 seconds to 
spare, thank you.
    I am going to apologize that I have to leave. I think, Mr. 
Thompson, you are going to take my place. Now I recognize Ms. 
Hamsher for your 5-minute testimony.
    Thank you again, and I apologize for walking out on you. 
Nothing personal. You are recognized.
</option>
    <option>HEALTH, SAFETY, AND REGULATORY, ECLIPSE RESOURCES CORPORATION, 
                  STATE COLLEGE, PENNSYLVANIA
    Ms. Hamsher. Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and 
members of the Committee, thank you for inviting me today to 
speak about my company's experience with permitting natural gas 
projects in Appalachia and dealing with NEPA.
    My name is Melissa Hamsher, and I serve as the Vice 
President of Environmental, Health, Safety, and Regulatory at 
Eclipse Resources Corporation. I hope that my technical 
experience, coupled with my history working for a state 
regulator, and my current work in private industry will be 
beneficial to the Committee.
    My company, Eclipse Resources Corporation, is an 
independent oil and gas exploration and production company 
focusing on cutting-edge technology and innovation as we 
develop oil and natural gas resources in the Appalachian Basin. 
We also pioneered the ``Super-Lateral'' drilling program.
    As this Committee has heard before, the growth in oil and 
natural gas production in the Appalachian region has largely 
occurred on private and state lands, with development on 
Federal Government lands lagging far behind. These delays, 
largely the result of long Federal environmental reviews and 
litigation at most steps of the process are costing the United 
States Treasury significant dollars in royalty payments.
    Let's start by focusing on the process of accessing 
Federal-owned sub-surface resources in Ohio. Eclipse has leased 
substantial sub-surface acreage within the boundaries of the 
Wayne National Forest for oil and natural gas development. 
After permitting and approval by the state of Ohio, the Federal 
Government inserted itself on environmental grounds, citing 
NEPA, even though BLM's only interest is in the proportionately 
small sub-surface minerals.
    Piecemeal parcels of public and private land combined with 
a mixture of Federal and private mineral rights make up the 
Wayne National Forest.
    You can change that.
    [Slide.]
    Ms. Hamsher. This combination results in much of the land 
within the Federal boundaries being owned wholly by private 
parties.
    Eclipse Resources initially submitted expressions of 
interest on parcels in the Wayne National Forest in 2012. In 
October 2016, BLM issued a finding of no significant impact, 
FONSI, and shortly thereafter announced their competitive 
online auction sale for leases on December 13, 2016. Eclipse 
Resources successfully won parcels in the December auction, but 
did not receive title until May 23, 2017, after 5 months of 
delay.
    Proceeding with our development plans in July, we filed an 
APD for the well named Rolland A, Well Number 1H, with the 
intent of starting work in August. This well would be drilled 
horizontally, more than a mile beneath the surface from a 2016 
well pad previously constructed on private land, in accordance 
with all state regulations.
    Since we are utilizing horizontal drilling methods, the 
wells would have no significant impact to the Wayne National 
Forest. Therefore, we believe our submitted permits should be 
subject to BLM's categorical exclusion for no Federal surface 
impact. However, BLM determined that the agency must use the 
guidance in an outdated instructional memorandum which subjects 
APDs on private lands to environmental analysis that have nexus 
to Federal minerals. This decision came shortly after a lawsuit 
by environmental NGOs. We believe these two events are directly 
related.
    Following this decision, 1 month later, in August, BLM 
conducted site visits on our landowners' private properties in 
an effort to undertake their NEPA analysis. States have primacy 
over development of minerals on private property. In accordance 
with Ohio regulations, Eclipse Resources had already conducted 
the necessary administrative and environmental reviews, meeting 
Ohio's requirements, and received all the relevant permits. 
Still, BLM deemed it necessary to conduct a full environmental 
assessment on private land, a requirement that Eclipse and its 
landowners have fully met.
    Eclipse Resources will have no surface impacts to Federal 
surface parcels from oil or natural gas development occurring 
within the boundaries of the Wayne National Forest. The 
horizontal position of the well bore penetrates only sub-
surface minerals. Private landowners hold title to all the 
surface parcels where the work will occur.
    Despite our full cooperation with the process, I sit here 
today with no sense of when the Federal reviews will be 
completed, or when we can begin producing on private land, 
where Eclipse already has its state-issued permits in hand. I 
hope the Committee will look at issues like these to find ways 
to allow robust environmental reviews on state lands, coupled 
with responsible mineral development to control projects like 
Eclipse and others going forward.
    In short, we would like the states to have primacy over 
environmental reviews for sub-surface Federal parcels with no 
Federal surface impact. Extensive and intrusive environmental 
and archeological studies are being conducted on private-
surface lands where no Federal surface or Federal sub-surface 
are located within thousands of feet. This simply does not need 
to happen to ensure good stewardship.
</option>
    <option>       Prepared Statement of Melissa L. Hamsher, Vice President, 
   Environmental, Health, Safety, and Regulatory, Eclipse Resources 
                              Corporation
    Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and members of the 
Committee, thank you for inviting me today to speak about my company's 
experience with permitting natural gas projects in Appalachia and 
dealing with the National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA).
    My name is Melissa Hamsher and I serve as the Vice President of 
Environmental, Health, Safety, and Regulatory at Eclipse Resources 
Corporation. I have held this job since 2011 and held a similar title 
at Rex Energy Corporation for 5 years prior to that. Before my work in 
the private sector, I worked at the Pennsylvania Department of 
Environmental Protection for 6 years as an engineer in the Bureau of 
Oil and Gas Management.
    I may very well be the only environmental specialist with advanced 
technical knowledge of oilfield processes to come before this 
Committee, and I really do appreciate the opportunity to share the 
Eclipse story with you. I hope that my technical experience, coupled 
with my history working for a state regulator and my current work in 
private industry, will be beneficial to the Committee.
    My company, Eclipse Resources Corporation, is an independent oil 
and gas exploration and production company focused on cutting edge 
technology and innovation as we develop oil and natural gas resources 
in the Appalachian region. This testimony includes significant detail 
on Eclipse later.
    As this Committee has heard before, the growth in oil and gas 
production in the Appalachian region has largely occurred on private 
and state lands, with development on Federal Government lands lagging 
far behind. These delays, largely the result of long Federal 
environmental reviews and litigation at most steps of the process, are 
costing the United States Treasury significant dollars in royalty 
payments. They also cost local governments funds they rely on for 
schools and other crucial programs. I understand that the Committee is 
currently working on both the ONSHORE Act and the POWER Counties Act. 
Both bills make valuable progress in fixing the issues related to oil 
and natural gas development involving Federal minerals. However, these 
two bills alone are insufficient to remedy extensive permit delays on 
projects that are carefully designed and environmentally responsible.
    Let's start by focusing on the process of accessing Federal-owned, 
sub-surface resources in Ohio. Eclipse has leased substantial sub-
surface acreage within the boundaries of the Wayne National Forest for 
oil and natural gas development. This hearing to better understand how 
bureaucratic delays caused by duplicative environmental reviews and 
extensive analysis by the Bureau of Land Management (BLM) for sub-
surface mineral penetration effectively halts development of our 
Nation's natural resources is important and timely. Using our project 
within the bounds of the Wayne National Forest as an example, after 
permitting and approval by the state of Ohio, the Federal Government 
inserted itself on environmental grounds, citing NEPA, even though 
BLM's only interest is in the proportionately small sub-surface 
minerals.
    Piecemeal parcels of public and private land, combined with a 
mixture of Federal and private mineral rights, make up the Wayne 
National Forest. This combination results in much of the land within 
the Federal boundaries being owned wholly by private parties. More 
background on the unique makeup of the forest follows, but these 
realities make Federal environmental review even less logical.
    Since submitting our Application for Permits to Drill (APD) in 
July, Eclipse has faced numerous procedural roadblocks from BLM and 
unreasonable agency requests that have significantly delayed 
development and negatively affected our planned drilling programs. 
Multiple layers of Federal regulation, the direct result of BLM 
inserting itself into this process, have delayed this project for many 
months and we do not have a timeline for the process' conclusion.
    Eclipse Resources initially submitted Expressions of Interest 
(EOIs) on parcels in the Wayne National Forest in 2012. In October 
2016, BLM issued a Finding of No Significant Impact (FONSI) and shortly 
thereafter announced their first competitive online auction sale for 
leases on December 13, 2016. Eclipse Resources successfully won parcels 
in the December auction sale but did not receive title until May 23, 
2017, after more than 5 months of delay.
    Proceeding with our development plans, in July, we filed an APD for 
the well named Rolland A, Well Number 1H, with the intent to start work 
in August. This well would be drilled horizontally, more than a mile 
beneath the surface from the 2016 well pad previously constructed on 
private land--in accordance with all state regulations.
    Since we are utilizing horizontal drilling methods, the wells would 
have no surface impact to the Wayne National Forest. Therefore, we 
believe our submitted permits should be subject to BLM Categorical 
Exclusion (CX) Document 43 CFR part 1600 2016 Amendment, as there would 
be no surface occupancy or disturbance of the unit.
    However, BLM determined that the agency must use the guidance in an 
outdated Instruction Memorandum 2009-078, which subjects APDs on 
private lands to environmental analyses that have nexus to Federal 
minerals. This decision, coincidentally, came shortly after a lawsuit 
by environmental non-governmental organizations.
    Following the decision, 1 month later in August, BLM conducted site 
visits on our landowners' private properties in an effort to undertake 
their NEPA analysis. States have primacy over development of minerals 
on private property. In accordance with Ohio regulations, Eclipse 
Resources had already conducted the necessary administrative and 
environmental reviews, meeting Ohio's requirements, and received all 
relevant permits. Still, BLM deemed it necessary to conduct a full 
environmental assessment on private land--a requirement that Eclipse, 
and its landowners, have fully met.
    Eclipse Resources will have no surface impacts to Federal surface 
parcels from oil and natural gas development occurring within the 
boundaries of the Wayne National Forest on Federal surface parcels. The 
horizontal portion of the well bore penetrates only sub-surface 
minerals. Private landowners hold titles to all of the surface parcels 
where the work will occur.
    To summarize, Eclipse has followed all applicable state guidance, 
laws, and regulations, cooperated with the Federal Government, and 
implemented aggressive environmental mitigation techniques for 
exploration on private land within the boundaries of a national forest. 
Despite the foregoing, BLM has repeatedly slowed the review of this 
project and has undertaken an unwarranted full environmental review. 
Despite our full cooperation with the process, I sit here today with no 
sense of when the Federal reviews will be completed or when we can 
begin producing on private land where Eclipse already has its state-
issued permits in hand.
    At the same time, no other producer has received an APD from that 
December 2016 sale. Almost 18 months after leases were purchased, the 
Federal Government has obstructed development.
    While I have spent a lot of time discussing our natural gas 
exploration experience, I want to note that NEPA applies to a broad 
range of projects--airports, highways, resource exploration, renewable 
projects, and so many other types of development. I bring this up, 
because while discussing NEPA is important to Eclipse and its projects, 
it is crucial to so much economic growth all over our country.
    I hope the Committee will look at issues like these to find ways to 
allow robust environmental reviews in the states, coupled with 
responsible mineral development, to control projects like Eclipse's and 
others going forward. In short, we would like the states to have 
primacy over environmental reviews for sub-surface Federal parcels with 
no Federal surface impact. Extensive and intrusive environmental and 
archeological studies are being conducted on private surface lands 
where no Federal surface or Federal sub-surface are located for 
thousands of feet. This simply does not need to happen to ensure good 
stewardship.
    In addition, I would like to provide some significant background 
for the Committee's consideration on Eclipse Resources, the company's 
advanced environmental controls and protections, oil and gas 
exploration in Appalachia, and the particulars of the Wayne National 
Forest.
                           eclipse resources
    Eclipse pioneered the ``Super-Lateral'' drilling concept, leading 
the industry with the development of horizontal wells in excess of 3 
miles in length. Our innovations have led to less expensive well 
development, more efficient resource development, and, most 
importantly, safety and environmental excellence.
    As you know, Appalachia is at the center of the Utica and Marcellus 
Shale plays, and Eclipse has focused on the responsible development of 
resources in the ``core'' of the natural gas fields in southeastern 
Ohio. While our corporate headquarters are located in Pennsylvania, we 
have our primary production volumes in the state of Ohio.
                         environmental controls
    I want to underscore Eclipse's commitment to environmental 
stewardship. While Eclipse outlines many of the environmental 
safeguards we undertake in the work we do in Appalachia on its 
corporate website, I would like to draw your attention to some efforts 
that I think are particularly important. During development, we conduct 
reviews and studies that far exceed state or Federal requirements.
    Eclipse uses a closed-loop drilling system, which recycles drilling 
fluids and eliminates the need for earthen pits. This practice, 
although not required by law, ensures that there are no environmental 
impacts to local groundwater sources, or to flora and fauna from 
cuttings and fluids storage. Eclipse ensures minimization of its 
environmental footprint through the installation of multi-well pads, 
which diminish the effects on local infrastructure and limit forest 
fragmentation. ``Green Fracs,'' while not required, are employed by 
Eclipse to reduce diesel emissions through the utilization of natural 
gas as a power source during hydraulic fracturing operations. Where 
state regulations may be lagging, we take it upon ourselves to ensure 
the sustainability of surface water aquatic biology through extensive 
stream studies and self-imposed water withdrawal restrictions.
    Prior to it being required by regulation, Eclipse was a pioneer in 
voluntarily submitting chemical usage to the public. Eclipse employs a 
robust air protection program, studying, monitoring, and testing to 
ensure fugitive emissions do not exist at our well sites. While the 
company's environmental stewardship is not necessarily the topic of 
this hearing, it is crucial to Eclipse's business and something I want 
to ensure is on the record, as I discuss the effect of NEPA on our 
operations.
                       oil and gas in appalachia
    Given Eclipse Resource's position in southeastern Ohio, at the 
center of Appalachian shale development, I also wanted to share some 
key facts and figures from the region with you. The oil and natural gas 
industry supports more than 650,000 jobs, paying more than $41 billion 
in wages, and had a $90 billion economic impact in Pennsylvania, Ohio 
and West Virginia in 2015, according to a PricewaterhouseCoopers LLP 
study released last year by the American Petroleum Institute. In 
addition, hundreds of millions of dollars have been spent on taxes that 
support local schools, municipal governments, and vital infrastructure.
    What's more is that these investments have occurred in some of the 
most economically depressed areas of these three states, along the Ohio 
River. In Ohio, for example, the oil and natural gas industry paid more 
than $45 million in taxes and $300 million in improvements to roads and 
bridges.
    Counties along the Ohio River have reported that they would have 
gone bankrupt, had it not been for the oil and natural gas industry 
activities over these past few years. There is simply no greater 
example of the economic turnaround in Appalachia than Monroe County, 
Ohio. In 2013, Monroe County lost its largest employer, the Ormet 
aluminum smelting plant, leaving 1,000 people out of work in Ohio and 
West Virginia. The county of 14,500 people faced a bleak future with 
skyrocketing unemployment and a loss of $4.5 million in tax revenues 
from the plant closure.
    However, thanks to some of the best natural gas producing wells in 
the Appalachian Basin, sales tax revenues have skyrocketed, jumping 
over 340 percent. Unemployment in the region has declined to 10.4 
percent after spiking above 14 percent in 2014 according to data from 
the Ohio Department of Job and Family Services. This prolific natural 
gas production has led to other major investments in the region, such 
as a natural gas power plant and a natural gas liquids storage hub.
    What concerns us, however, is that the county is only just 
beginning the road to recovery and these economic gains are at risk as 
Federal red tape is causing unnecessary roadblocks to continued 
investments in these communities.
                       the wayne national forest
    To highlight this point, Monroe County is home to the Wayne 
National Forest and some of the most prolific natural gas wells in the 
Utica Shale. There are several dozen oil and natural gas producers that 
operate in Monroe County, both large operators and small operators. In 
fact, there are over 1,200 decades-old wells producing oil and natural 
gas on the surface of the Wayne National Forest today, independent of 
the newer shale wells. Unlike many other Federal forests, the Wayne 
National Forest is a patchwork of private and Federal lands and 
minerals. In fact, the Federal Government only holds ownership of 25 
percent of the land within the Forest Proclamation Boundary. In 
addition, 59 percent of the minerals in the boundaries of the Wayne 
National Forest are privately owned.
    Federal lands are exempt from property taxes, which can create 
financial hardships for entities that receive public funds and in Ohio. 
With property taxes as the primary base of school district and township 
funds, local governments in Ohio are awaiting new development in the 
region. Leasing of Federal minerals and, more importantly, royalty 
monies received from oil and natural gas production is sorely needed to 
help fund local schools and municipalities in these Appalachian 
communities. Just last week, the superintendent of the Switzerland 
Local School testified before the Energy and Mineral Resources 
Subcommittee in support of the POWER Counties Act about this growing 
issue, and I would encourage you to review his testimony, if you have 
not already done so.
    To date, the oil and natural gas industry has spent over $8 million 
to secure Federal leases in the Wayne National Forest. A portion of 
those bonus payments has already gone back to local communities. It is 
my understanding that the intent of allowing leases on Federal land is 
to realize development of minerals and collect royalty payments, lease 
payments, and tax revenue. With the Federal Government's fiduciary 
responsibility to the taxpayers to see our minerals developed, I very 
much hope we can work together to eliminate the unnecessary delays and 
snags in the permitting process.
    I want to re-emphasize that since the Bureau of Land Management's 
first lease sale, which was held December 13, 2016, not one Application 
for Permit to Drill (APD) has been issued.
                               conclusion
    Again, I want to say thank you to the Committee for holding this 
important meeting today. I look forward to working with all of you to 
find a way to ensure responsible mineral development on both public and 
private land, under the direction of states and as intended by 
Congress. I look forward to answering your questions and continuing the 
conversation.
    Mr. Thompson [presiding]. Thank you, Ms. Hamsher.
    I am now pleased to recognize Mr. Greczmiel for 5 minutes.
</option>
    <option> NEPA OVERSIGHT AT COUNCIL ON ENVIRONMENTAL QUALITY, FAIRFAX, 
                            VIRGINIA
    Mr. Greczmiel. Thank you. Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member 
Grijalva, and members of the Committee, thank you for inviting 
me here today to speak to you about the National Environmental 
Policy Act, its implementation, and NEPA litigation.
    For over a decade, I worked at agencies writing, reviewing, 
and providing guidance on NEPA reviews. I then moved over to 
the Council on Environmental Quality, where I served as 
Associate Director for NEPA for over 16 years. My work focused 
on NEPA and other environmental reviews and permits for all 
manner of Federal agencies' approvals and activities, including 
putting new or revised regulations into place, establishing 
land management policies and plans, and the development of 
pipelines, transmission lines, bridges, highways, and other 
infrastructure.
    NEPA is often referred to as this country's environmental 
Magna Carta, as it says, ``to create and maintain conditions 
under which man and nature can exist in productive harmony and 
fulfill the social, economic, and other requirements of present 
and future generations.''
    NEPA does not put the environment above other requirements, 
or above the social, economic, or other issues. It simply 
requires Federal agencies to inform decision makers and the 
public of the environmental consequences of a proposed action 
before a decision is made.
    One of the most rewarding aspects of being Associate 
Director for NEPA was the opportunity to work with Federal, 
tribal, state, and local officials and local citizens who 
sought a greater voice, either as formal partners in the NEPA 
process or in providing comments on NEPA reviews that impacted 
their lives.
    The NEPA process, the analytical framework for NEPA 
reviews, is fleshed out in the CEQ regulations and the agency 
NEPA implementing procedures. As you heard, there are three 
levels of environmental review.
    The categorical exclusion, which agencies establish because 
they believe that that type of activity is not one that has 
significant environmental impacts or the potential for those 
impacts, is used over 95 percent of the time. Tens, if not 
hundreds, of thousands of actions a year that are taken by the 
Federal Government are covered by categorical exclusions.
    The next level of environmental review is a bit more 
rigorous, and that is the environmental assessment when a CE 
isn't appropriate and the agency hasn't determined that there 
could be potential significant impacts. Approximately 4 percent 
of NEPA reviews, tens of thousands a year, are environmental 
assessments.
    Finally, the most intensive level of review is the 
environmental impact statement. An EIS is used when the 
proposed action is considered to have the possibility for those 
significant impacts. Approximately 1 percent of NEPA reviews, 
about 200 a year, go through the EIS process.
    Does the process or litigation slow down Federal permits or 
approvals? As to timeliness, let me be clear. Considering the 
consequences before taking action, considering alternatives 
that might have less of an impact, looking at the impacts of 
the proposed activities, and engaging the public does take 
time. But that is time that, in my opinion, should be taken 
when there is a potential for significant environmental impacts 
that an affected community may have to live with for years or 
decades.
    Experience has taught me that NEPA is not usually the cause 
of delays, and delays do occur in a large number of NEPA 
reviews. A multitude of factors, including a lack of funding 
for the projects, change in project design after planning has 
started, change in priorities, local opposition, or delays in 
other non-NEPA permitting or approval processes at the state, 
local, or tribal level have all added to those.
    I might add that, sadly, not providing the capacity, the 
people, and the training to prepare and oversee NEPA reviews 
and how to use the efficiencies, the lessons learned, and the 
latest developments in improving the timeliness of NEPA also 
leads to delay.
    The CEQ regulations provide many mechanisms. You have 
already heard of the three levels that make the amount of 
review commensurate with the expected impacts. But they also 
provide for tailored time limits, using an open process for 
identifying the issues that merit review, and integrating 
NEPA's requirements with others to avoid duplication. Just as 
the number of required EISs is proportionately low in 
comparison to the number of reviews, in my experience the 
number of cases filed is proportionately very small, with 
concerned parties currently typically filing approximately 100 
NEPA lawsuits per year. Considering the amount of Federal 
actions that are taken, that context, I think, is important.
    The criticism that NEPA produces wasteful litigation 
overlooks the essential role that it plays. For many, it is the 
only mechanism for enforcing NEPA. The main reason plaintiffs 
file suit was, and continues to be, that NEPA is inadequate 
because the information was incomplete, or the analysis was not 
sufficient. Litigation is often their only recourse.
    Most litigation is won by the agencies, by the way. 
However, despite courts' deference to agency work, a good 
number of cases find that the plaintiff's challenges do have 
merit. In 2016, 30 percent of the appellate cases found for the 
plaintiffs.
    Injunctions and remands, they don't stop NEPA, they require 
the agency to go back, correct their work, and allow the 
project to proceed.
    Finally, from my perspective working with local 
communities, bringing suit and litigation is expensive and 
time-consuming. It is usually the last resort that they want to 
employ after they have been shut out of the NEPA process, or 
have been unable to work effectively in that process, so that 
their concerns could be met.
    Thank you, and I look forward to answering your questions.
</option>
    <option> Prepared Statement of Horst Greczmiel, Former Associate Director for 
           NEPA Oversight at Council on Environmental Quality
                          introductory remarks
    Chairman Bishop, Ranking Member Grijalva, and members of the 
Committee, thank you for inviting me to speak to the House Natural 
Resources Committee on the National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA), 
its implementation, and NEPA litigation.
    I first became familiar with NEPA near the end of my 14-plus year 
military career when, after receiving my LL.M. in Environmental Law 
from George Washington University, I was assigned to the U.S. Army 
Environmental Law Division. There, I worked on NEPA and other 
environmental reviews and permits on activities including desert 
training operations, military installation development and expansion, 
and base closure and realignment. After leaving active military service 
in 1992, I entered the civilian Federal workforce as an attorney 
advisor at the Coast Guard Environmental Law Division. At the Coast 
Guard, my work focused on NEPA and other environmental reviews and 
permits for activities including the disposition of Governor's Island 
and Coast Guard vessel operations along the Atlantic coast. While at 
USCG Headquarters, I served a detail to the Council on Environmental 
Quality (CEQ) during the President George H.W. Bush administration. 
Several years later, in November 1999, I became the Associate Director 
for National Environmental Policy Act Oversight at CEQ, overseeing the 
Federal Government's implementation of NEPA. I served in that capacity 
for over 16 years and retired on December 31, 2015.
                 the national environmental policy act
    The National Environmental Policy Act, NEPA, is often referred to 
as this country's environmental Magna Carta and is viewed as an 
essential tool to help agencies plan Federal actions responsibly. The 
Act requires Federal agency leaders, the decision makers, to consider 
the environmental consequences of their actions before making a 
decision. NEPA sets forth this Nation's policies regarding the 
environment in Section 101, the Congressional Declaration of National 
Environmental Policy, where Congress declares:
        it is the continuing policy of the Federal Government, in 
        cooperation with State and local governments, and other 
        concerned public and private organizations, to use all 
        practicable means and measures, including financial and 
        technical assistance, in a manner calculated to foster and 
        promote the general welfare, to create and maintain conditions 
        under which man and nature can exist in productive harmony, and 
        fulfill the social, economic, and other requirements of present 
        and future generations of Americans.
    The Act goes on to provide important policy goals:
        it is the continuing responsibility of the Federal Government 
        to use all practicable means, consist with other essential 
        considerations of national policy, to improve and coordinate 
        Federal plans, functions, programs, and resources to the end 
        that the Nation may--
        1. fulfill the responsibilities of each generation as trustee 
        of the environment for succeeding generations;
        2. assure for all Americans safe, healthful, productive, and 
        aesthetically and culturally pleasing surroundings;
        3. attain the widest range of beneficial uses of the 
        environment without degradation, risk to health or safety, or 
        other undesirable and unintended consequences;
        4. preserve important historic, cultural, and natural aspects 
        of our national heritage, and maintain, wherever possible, an 
        environment which supports diversity, and variety of individual 
        choice;
        5. achieve a balance between population and resource use which 
        will permit high standards of living and a wide sharing of 
        life's amenities; and
        6. enhance the quality of renewable resources and approach the 
        maximum attainable recycling of depletable resources. \1\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \1\ 42 U.S.C. Sec. 4331.
    Congress passed NEPA by overwhelming bipartisan majorities.\2\ 
Signed into law by President Richard M. Nixon, the Act mandated that 
Federal agencies employ the NEPA process to achieve those policy goals. 
It also established CEQ to, among other responsibilities, oversee the 
implementation of NEPA. In 1983, the U.S. Supreme Court made it clear 
that NEPA has two main goals:
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \2\ The House of Representatives adopted NEPA by a vote of 372 to 
15. 115 CONG. REC. 19,013 (1969). The Senate passed NEPA by voice vote 
without recorded dissent. 115 CONG. REC. 26,590 (1969).
        First, it places upon an agency the obligation to consider 
        every significant aspect of the environmental impact of a 
        proposed action. Second, it ensures that the agency will inform 
        the public that it has indeed considered environmental concerns 
        in its decision-making process. Congress in enacting NEPA, 
        however, did not require agencies to elevate environmental 
        concerns over other appropriate considerations. Rather, it 
        required only that the agency take a ``hard look'' at the 
        environmental consequences before taking a major action . . . 
        Congress did not enact NEPA, of course, so that an agency would 
        contemplate the environmental impact of an action as an 
        abstract exercise. Rather, Congress intended that the ``hard 
        look'' be incorporated as part of the agency's process of 
        deciding whether to pursue a particular Federal action. \3\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \3\ Baltimore Gas &amp; Electric Co. v. Natural Resources Defense 
Council, Inc., 462 U.S. 87, 97, 100 (1983).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
                            the nepa process
    The NEPA process provides an analytical framework fleshed out in 
the CEQ Regulations Implementing the Procedural Provisions of NEPA 
Regulations issued in 1978 (CEQ NEPA Regulations) \4\ NEPA affords the 
public the opportunity the public and local governmental officials 
notice and the opportunity to be informed during Federal Government 
decision making; giving them a voice in those decisions and allows them 
to suggest alternatives and further refined and adapted to agency 
missions and needs in Federal agency NEPA Implementing Procedures.\5\ 
During the course of the NEPA process, a Federal agency identifies a 
need for a taking action, develops a proposed action, identifies 
reasonable alternatives, and analyzes the potential effects of the 
alternatives.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \4\ 40 CFR parts 1500-1508 available at https://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-
bin/text-idx?SID=30655823cf5f0 dcb1c5ee59d01883b89&amp;mc=true&amp;tpl=/
ecfrbrowse/Title40/40chapterV.tpl.
    \5\ 40 CFR 1507.3. Agency implementing procedures are available at 
https://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-
idx?SID=30655823cf5f0dcb1c5ee59d01883b89&amp;mc=true&amp;tpl=/ecfrbrowse/
Title40/40 chapterV.tpl.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    There are essentially three levels of NEPA review:
    &lt;bullet&gt; Categorical Exclusion (CE): A CE is a category of actions 
            established, after CEQ and public review, in agency 
            procedures implementing NEPA that is expected not to have 
            individually or cumulatively significant environmental 
            impacts. An action within such a category is excluded from 
            analysis and documentation in an Environmental Assessment 
            or an Environmental Impact Statement provided there are no 
            unusual circumstances associated with the proposed action 
            that warrant further environmental consideration, or, in 
            NEPA terms, that there no extraordinary circumstances. A CE 
            can be concluded with a determination that a proposed 
            action falls within one of the established categories of 
            actions and there are no extraordinary circumstances.\6\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \6\ 40 C.F.R. Sec. 1508.4.
    &lt;bullet&gt; Environmental Assessment (EA): When a CE is not 
            appropriate, or if the agency has not determined whether a 
            proposed action could cause significant environmental 
            effects, then an EA is prepared. If, as a result of the EA, 
            a finding of no significant impact (FONSI) is appropriate, 
            then the NEPA review process is completed with the FONSI 
            or, when mitigation is included to reduce the intensity of 
            the impacts to a level that is not significant, a mitigated 
            FONSI; otherwise an EIS is prepared.\7\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \7\ 40 C.F.R. Sec. 1508.9.
    &lt;bullet&gt; Environmental Impact Statement (EIS): When a proposed 
            action is expected to result in significant impacts to the 
            human environment, the agency prepares an EIS, the most 
            intensive level of analysis. The NEPA review process is 
            concluded when a record of decision (ROD) is issued.\8\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \8\ 40 C.F.R. part 1502.
    The conclusion of the NEPA process provides decision makers and the 
public with a ``hard look'' at the environmental consequences of 
proposed actions. Recognizing there are many factors in addition to the 
environment that are considered when making a decision, it is left to 
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
agency leaders to decide whether and how to best proceed.
    One of the groundbreaking and most valued aspects of the NEPA 
process is that NEPA gives a voice to the people. NEPA affords the 
public and local officials notice of what their government is doing 
before it happens. NEPA affords them the opportunity to offer 
reasonable alternatives and to be involved in the analyses that informs 
Federal decisions that impact their communities and livelihoods. One of 
the most rewarding aspects of being Associate Director for NEPA was the 
opportunity to work with Federal, tribal, state, and local officials, 
including mayors, county commissioners, governors, tribal councils, and 
with local citizens who sought a greater voice in how the Federal 
environmental reviews and permits impacted their activities and lives, 
either as formal partners in the NEPA process or in providing comments 
on a NEPA review. Many of them told me how important it was that they 
could participate in this way.
    There is a considerable amount of flexibility under the CEQ NEPA 
Regulations as to how agencies can implement the NEPA process. Under 
the CEQ NEPA Regulations each department and agency identifies, based 
on experience and expertise, the anticipated level of environmental 
review that is typically necessary for undertaking the type of actions 
it normally undertakes. Those anticipated levels are identified in the 
agency NEPA procedures that are called for by the CEQ NEPA Regulations 
and are reviewed and approved by CEQ.\9\ In addition, CEQ issues 
guidance and provides direction on implementing NEPA and the CEQ NEPA 
Regulations. CEQ also works with agencies to address the challenges 
they face when implementing those procedures for all manner of Federal 
decisions (e.g., placement and development of pipelines, transmission 
lines, bridges, water treatment facilities, military relocations, 
nuclear material storage, and land management policies and plans).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \9\ 40 CFR 1507.3(a).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    There is ongoing debate regarding the need for measures to address 
assertions that NEPA delays Federal projects. A good portion of that 
debate stems from disagreement among stakeholders regarding the degree 
to which, if any, the NEPA process itself is to blame for Federal 
project delays. Complaints about delays attributed to the NEPA process 
generally fall into two broad categories: those related to the time 
needed to complete required NEPA reviews (primarily EISs) and those 
resulting from NEPA-related litigation.
                               timeliness
    I'll first address the issue of delay that people attribute to the 
time needed for NEPA reviews and will note the efficiencies available 
to address key challenges Federal agencies face in ensuring the 
timeliness of NEPA reviews. The perception that compliance with NEPA 
causes significant delays in approvals of large numbers of proposed 
actions is simply wrong. Experience taught me that NEPA is not usually 
the cause, and that delays do not occur in a large number of NEPA 
reviews.
    A multitude of factors, other than NEPA, can affect the timing of 
Federal project delivery. In my experience factors that can cause delay 
include lack of funding, changes in the design or planning processes, 
inadequate staff capacity to implement or even oversee the NEPA 
process, changes in priorities that keep a proposed project from 
proceeding in the near term, local controversy or local opposition to a 
project, or delays in other (non-NEPA) permitting or approval processes 
at the Federal, state, tribal, or local level. With regard to the 
latter, certain Federal actions such as highway construction projects 
and permitting for mining operations, cattle grazing, forest thinning, 
and energy development may require compliance with other statutory and 
regulatory requirements which can add time, especially if they are 
raised late in the environmental review process. This is particularly 
the case when such review or permitting requires the participation or 
input of increasing numbers of local, state, tribal, or Federal 
agencies. In addition, agencies responsible for protecting resources 
are often confronted by problems with the project's alternatives 
analysis, incorrect or incomplete information, disagreements or 
differences of opinion among agencies, poor communication with project 
proponents and other agencies, or the environmental or biological 
analyses associated with the project.\10\ More often than not, factors 
other than complying with NEPA or the NEPA Regulations are the reasons 
for delaying Federal projects.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \10\ See, for example, The Role of the Environmental Review Process 
in Federally Funded Highway Projects: Background and Issues for 
Congress, CRS 7-5700, R42479, April 11, 2012, p. 36.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    NEPA does take time, and that should be time well spent. For 
example, NEPA should take time when a proposed action has the potential 
for significant environmental impacts that an affected community likely 
may live with for decades if not centuries, depending on the nature of 
the action. Time taken for the purposes of preparing a sound analysis 
and adequate public involvement is time well spent. It is also 
important to understand that citizens need some real time to review 
documents and write comments.
    It is also true the NEPA process is delayed at times for reasons 
that have nothing to do with the protection of the environment, our 
communities, or public lands. In my experience, and the experience of 
many that I have worked with, there are two key reasons for such 
delays, both are issues of capacity: lack of agency staff with 
responsibility for NEPA implementation and lack of adequate training. 
Agency capacity has been severely diminished over the last 20 years. In 
some agencies, offices have been disbanded; in others, additional 
responsibilities have been assigned to staff to the point that their 
capacity for NEPA work is severely diluted. In one of the worst 
situations I encountered, an agency decided not to fill regional NEPA 
positions on the theory that ``everyone'' would do the NEPA work. Just 
as detrimental is the loss of capacity for NEPA training within the 
agencies, either through lack of funding for training or through the 
loss of expertise to provide internal training. For far too many 
employees, NEPA is an ``other duty as assigned.''
    Additionally, far too many employees with NEPA responsibility are 
provided only ``OJT'', on the job training. Regrettably, that training 
too often relies on how the work has been done in the past rather than 
focusing on lessons learned and integrating improvements into the 
agency NEPA process. Staff members who are not fully trained in 
implementing NEPA often end up doing extra work in an attempt to make 
sure they are doing the right thing and agency lawyers require more 
time to ensure there is an adequate record to support the agency 
decision. An effective NEPA process would ensure sufficient people with 
knowledge and capacity are in appropriate agency offices.
    Compounding the lack of capacity problem is the paucity of 
information about the implementation of NEPA noted by the Government 
Accountability Office (GAO) and the Congressional Research Service 
(CRS) in their 2014 and 2015 reports.\11\ However, GAO and CRS have 
prepared a series of reports, remarkably consistent in their findings, 
regarding the construction of highway projects and the relationship of 
environmental laws generally and NEPA specifically to decision-making 
timeliness. More of this type of analysis is needed if agencies and/or 
legislators are going to be able to identify the causes of delays and 
formulate successful approaches to reducing such delays. In short, a 
number of Federal projects have indeed been delayed or stopped but for 
reasons that have nothing to do with NEPA; unfortunately and unfairly 
NEPA usually gets the blame.\12\ Misplaced blame makes correcting any 
problem more difficult.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \11\ Little Information Exists on NEPA Analysis, GAO-14-369, April 
2014, p. 7-8; The National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA): Background 
and Implementation, CRS RL33152, January 10, 2011, p. 26.
    \12\ See, The National Environmental Policy Act: Streamlining NEPA, 
CRS 7-5700, December 6, 2007 and The Role of the Environmental Review 
Process in Federally Funded Highway Projects: Background and Issues for 
Congress, CRS 7-5700, R42479, April 11, 2012.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    In the years prior to my retirement, the Federal agencies 
intensified their efforts to identify and address the challenges 
agencies face in preparing timely and effective NEPA reviews. Among the 
challenges identified were the need for early communication and 
coordination among all the agencies involved in the environmental 
review of a proposed action and developing and meeting coordinated 
timelines. Another key challenge is in identifying and engaging all 
agencies--Federal, tribal, state, and local--as well as the public, 
particularly the communities likely to be impacted, in order to focus 
on the issues that need to be addressed during the review and 
permitting process and the analyses and methods to address those 
issues.
                              efficiencies
    Before I turn to recent initiatives, the CEQ NEPA Regulations merit 
attention. Although they are frequently criticized for their age, such 
criticism overlooks the value they add to NEPA reviews by focusing on 
efficiencies and timeliness.
    As noted above, the CEQ NEPA Regulations require agencies to 
establish agency-specific NEPA implementing procedures that allow for 
the efficient identification of the appropriate level of NEPA review 
for a proposed action (categorical exclusion [CE], environmental 
assessment [EA], and environmental impact statement [EIS]). These three 
levels of NEPA review exemplify the flexibility provided by NEPA is 
shaping the extent of the environmental analysis to be commensurate 
with the expected environmental effects. This flexibility has proven 
itself over time as evidenced by the fact that most Federal actions 
receive only the least rigorous form of environmental review--the CE--
and a relatively small number of Federal actions receive the most 
rigorous--the EIS. This is demonstrated by the fact that fewer than 300 
final EISs have been published by the agencies each year since 
2000.\13\ This is also borne out by the results of the congressionally 
mandated reporting on the status of NEPA reviews for the hundreds of 
thousands of Federal activities funded under the American Reinvestment 
and Recovery Act (ARRA).\14\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \13\ In 2012, the last year for which data is posted on the CEQ 
website, there were less than 200 draft and less than 200 final EIS 
prepared and filed (available at https://ceq.doe.gov/docs/get-involved/
combined-filed-eiss-1970-2012.pdf). The EPA EIS database shows an 
average of less than 400 draft and final EISs were filed in 2013-2017 
(available at https://cdxnodengn.epa.gov/cdx-enepa-public/action/eis/
search).
    \14\ Public Law 111-5, Section 1609(c): ``The President shall 
report to the Senate Environment and Public Works Committee and the 
House Natural Resources Committee every 90 days following the date of 
enactment until September 30, 2011 on the status and progress of 
projects and activities funded by this Act with respect to compliance 
with National Environmental Policy Act requirements and 
documentation.''
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    The ARRA reports from May 2009 through November 2011 covered over 
275,000 funded activities for which agencies fulfilled their NEPA 
responsibilities with over 184,000 CEs, over 7,000 EAs, and less than 
900 EISs.\15\ This Federal Government wide data is consistent with 
information provided by one agency that tracks all of its NEPA reviews. 
In 2007, the Federal Highway Administration reported that approximately 
92 percent of all highway projects met their NEPA responsibilities with 
CEs, and approximately 4 percent were met with EAs and 4 percent with 
EISs.\16\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \15\ Available at https://ceq.doe.gov/ceq-reports/
recovery_act_reports.html.
    \16\ The National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA): Background and 
Implementation, CRS RL33152, January 10, 2011, p. 15-16.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    In addition to calling for agency-specific procedures that allow 
for the efficient identification of the appropriate level of NEPA 
review, the CEQ NEPA Regulations encourage agencies to reduce paperwork 
and delay (40 C.F.R. sections 1500.4 and 1500.5). They also provide for 
tailored time limits (40 C.F.R. section 1501.8); scoping by using an 
early and open process for identifying those issues that merit detailed 
analysis (40 C.F.R. section 1501.7); integrating NEPA requirements with 
other review and consultation requirements to avoid duplication of 
effort (40 C.F.R. section 1502.25); and eliminating duplication with 
state and local procedures (40 C.F.R. section 1506.2).
    Throughout my time as Associate Director for NEPA at CEQ, I found 
that the over-arching and common objective to improve the efficiency 
and timeliness of the NEPA process aligned with the goals of many major 
Administration initiatives. Efforts to improve the timeliness and 
efficiency of NEPA reviews are now beginning to yield government wide 
improvements. For example, the Corps of Engineers led the interagency 
effort that developed an up-to-date ``how-to'' guide for synchronizing 
environmental reviews as early as possible.\17\ Another interagency 
effort focused on reducing delay through early engagement and 
coordination with all agencies that may be involved in the 
environmental review and permitting of a proposed action as well as the 
communities that may be impacted is the Unified Federal Review (UFR) 
initiative. The UFR initiative, led by the UFR Steering Committee,\18\ 
establishing an expedited and unified interagency review process to 
ensure compliance with environmental and historic requirements under 
Federal law relating to disaster recovery projects.\19\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \17\ The Red Book on Synchronizing Environmental Reviews for 
Transportation and Other Infrastructure Projects available at https://
www.environment.fhwa.dot.gov/strmlng/Redbook_ 2015.asp.
    \18\ Federal Emergency Management Agency, the Department of 
Homeland Security, the Advisory Council on Historic Preservation, and 
CEQ.
    \19\ Unified Federal Environmental and Historic Preservation Review 
at https://www.fema.gov/unified-federal-environmental-and-historic-
preservation-review-presidentially-declared-disasters.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Finally, the continued and increased use of a public, transparent, 
Permitting Dashboard \20\ that tracks agencies' progress in 
coordinating and meeting major review and permitting milestones 
incentivizes expeditious preparation and completion of NEPA reviews as 
well as any other necessary reviews and permitting processes. The 
Permitting Dashboard also has the potential to identify other factors 
that impact the efficiency, transparency, and accountability of Federal 
decisions. By providing a fact-base set of data on multiple projects, a 
public dashboard can identify factors that contribute to delays and 
allow for more fully informed discussions of whether further changes 
should be considered and how those changes would interact with the 
other factors at play in reaching a final decision. The overly 
simplistic and, I would argue, misleading reliance on simply cost and 
time, and examples of long or short process times that support a 
presenter's subjective view of the value of the process are not 
helpful. The data on a transparent dashboard and other information can 
then be used identify and develop additional practices to improve the 
process without undermining the value of the reviews, informed decision 
making, and public participation.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \20\ www.permits.performance.gov.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
                            nepa litigation
    Opponents of NEPA often incorrectly blame NEPA litigation for 
project delays. Just as the number of required EISs is proportionately 
low, so too are the number of lawsuits brought and the even lower 
number of cases that succeed against the Federal Government. The number 
of NEPA cases began to decline in the mid-1970s and has remained 
relatively constant since the late 1980s.\21\ Out of the tens of 
thousands of Federal actions that require environmental reviews under 
NEPA, only a small fraction is challenged in lawsuits. Although 
litigation may have had a larger impact in the past, the total number 
of NEPA-related cases in the past two decades has been proportionately 
very small when compared with the total number of Federal actions 
requiring some level of environmental review under NEPA. Furthermore, 
the main reason that plaintiffs filed suit was, and continues to be, 
their claims that an EIS or EA is inadequate (e.g., information was 
incomplete or the document did not sufficiently analyze the direct, 
indirect, and cumulative effects of an action).\22\ Plaintiffs are 
typically required to show that the agency was made aware of their 
concerns during the NEPA process itself rather than ``ambushing'' the 
agency for the first time in court.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \21\ See Council on Environmental Quality, Environmental Quality: 
25th Anniversary Report, 1996, p. 51, available at https://ceq.doe.gov/
publications/effectiveness_study.html.
    \22\ Litigation Surveys for 2001 through 2013, available at https:/
/ceq.doe.gov/ceq-reports/litigation.html.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Critics of NEPA often contend that the Act produces too much 
wasteful litigation. Such criticism overlooks the essential role the 
courts play by ensuring NEPA is enforced. When Federal agencies' NEPA 
compliance falls short, litigation brought by aggrieved parties is 
often the only recourse to ensure an adequate NEPA review and 
sufficient public engagement for a particular project or activity. 
Agency personnel and industry representatives sometimes complain about 
the pressure that the Act places on agencies to do thorough and 
defensible environmental reviews, lamenting the creation of 
``bulletproof'' EISs. In my experience there are indeed excessive 
documents, but it is not required by courts. Rather it comes from 
agencies ``throwing in the kitchen sink'' instead of focusing their 
attention on the issues that matter.
    Removing or limiting the opportunity for judicial review will not 
guarantee more focused or concise analyses. It is more likely that 
without the enforcement mechanism provided by the courts, Federal 
agency EISs would devolve into rote documents or checklists making NEPA 
a hollow and worthless exercise. Such an outcome further reduces the 
opportunity for public involvement in agency decisions that affect them 
and leads to less informed and effective agency decision making.
    The courts' rulings in NEPA cases have clarified many of the basic 
principles for conducting environmental impact analyses under the Act. 
The application of those principles to the circumstances of a 
particular Federal project, however, is inevitably case-specific and 
fact driven. It is thus not surprising that the courts confront certain 
difficult recurring issues--such as the appropriate level of NEPA 
review, adequate analysis of cumulative impacts, or whether a Federal 
agency has properly determined its action will not have significant 
effects on the human environment--whenever they are confronted with a 
new proposed project or activity.
    The criticism that NEPA generates huge volumes of litigation is 
also not accurate. In my experience, and according to several surveys 
of NEPA litigation, the number of cases filed is proportionately very 
small in comparison to the thousands of Federal actions decided upon in 
a given year. As shown in the table below, according to CEQ litigation 
reports for 2001-2013, there are few cases filed and few cases where a 
proposed project or activity is stopped from proceeding pending further 
action by either the court or the agency.\23\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \23\ See https://ceq.doe.gov/ceq-reports/litigation.html. See also 
P.E. Hudson &amp; Lucinda Low Swartz, 2016 NEPA Cases, NAEP Annual National 
Environmental Policy Act (NEPA) Report, National Association of 
Environmental Professionals, June 2017, p. 31-32 (This paper reflects a 
consistently low number of annual appellate NEPA case decisions ranging 
from 14 to 28 a year, and an 11 year total of fewer than 250).
------------------------------------------------------------------------
                         Number of NEPA Cases    Number of Injunctions/
         Year                   Filed                   Remands
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2001                     136                       30
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2002                     148                       40
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2003                     140                       32
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2004                     167                       32
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2005                     118                       43
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2006                     108                       72
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2007                      86                       49
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2008                     132                       35
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2009                      97                       23
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2010                      87                       16
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2011                      94                       21
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2012                      88                       10
------------------------------------------------------------------------
          2013                      96                       14
------------------------------------------------------------------------
    NEPA actually generates a relatively small volume of litigation 
with concerned parties typically filing about 100-150 NEPA lawsuits per 
year. The proportionately low percentage of cases filed was further 
confirmed when the Forest Service, in support of its Environmental 
Analysis and Decision-Making Initiative, compiled data between Fiscal 
Years 2009 and the first quarter of 2017 and found that it was sued on 
less than 3 percent of all projects.\24\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \24\ Forest Service Environmental Analysis and Decision-Making 
Initiative, USFS, 2017, available at https://vimeo.com/237902205 at 
52:24.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Given the broad range of members of the public with interests 
affected by Federal actions, the types of plaintiffs bringing NEPA 
suits include states and state agencies, local governments, business 
groups, individual property owners, and Indian tribes, and public 
interest groups. This last category, public interest groups, comprise 
the largest number of plaintiffs and range in size from small local 
citizen groups organized around a particular issue or project to large 
environmental organizations.
    Even the tiny fraction of NEPA actions that give rise to court 
suits overstates the significance of litigation because only a few of 
these suits result in court orders blocking government action. 
According to data compiled by CEQ, injunctive relief was not given in 
the majority of NEPA cases. The term ``permanent injunction'' is 
misleading in this context because such a final court order imposes 
only a temporary delay until the agency revises its environmental 
review to comply with NEPA and takes that information into account in 
reviewing the proposed action. Further, the courts have ordered a 
remand of certain issues to the Federal agency in only a relatively 
small number of cases and remands also provide the agency the 
opportunity to revise the NEPA review.
    Some argue that the high percentage of cases won by the Federal 
agencies indicates that litigation is abused. While it is true that in 
a substantial percentage of cases the courts have ruled in favor of the 
defendant agencies and uphold the agency NEPA work, it is equally true 
that there are a good number of cases where the courts have found--
despite courts' deference to the Federal agencies' NEPA work--that 
plaintiffs' challenges had merit.
    NEPA's critics also routinely disparage the motivations of 
plaintiffs who challenge agency environmental reviews. The rules of 
civil procedure require counsel in any litigation to certify, based on 
reasonable inquiry, that the action is not brought for any improper 
purpose, such as to harass or to cause unnecessary delay or needless 
cost, and that the claims presented have a sound basis in fact and law. 
I am not aware of any court sanctioning a NEPA plaintiff for bringing a 
frivolous complaint, or for filing suit for improper purpose, such as 
mere delay.\25\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \25\ See also Robert G. Dreher, Testimony Before the Task Force on 
Updating the National Environmental Policy Act, Committee on Resources, 
Hearing on NEPA: Lessons Learned and Next Steps, November 17, 2005, 
available at https: / / scholarship.law.georgetown.edu/cgi/view 
content.cgi?referer=https://www.google.com/
&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;article=1100&amp;context=cong.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Litigation is expensive and time-consuming. In my experience it is 
generally the last resort that citizens, local governments (such as 
county commissioners) and conservation groups invoke after they have 
been unsuccessful in getting the agency to address their serious 
concerns during the NEPA review. Moreover, environmental plaintiffs 
understand that they face an uphill battle as NEPA requires only 
reasonable, good-faith consideration and disclosure of environmental 
consequences and that a Federal court will not substitute its judgment 
for that of the agency on the wisdom of a proposed project. They also 
appreciate that courts will almost always give the Federal agency the 
opportunity to revisit and revise its NEPA review. Consequently, for 
plaintiffs, a successful outcome occurs when the agency is required to 
correct the NEPA review by fully evaluating and disclosing the 
environmental impacts of a proposed action which may lead to a 
different, more environmentally-sensitive approach--for example, 
adoption of an alternative with less environmental impact, or 
commitment of additional mitigation. Litigation seeking a better 
outcome is based on the belief that identification and disclosure of 
environmental consequences will have an environmentally-beneficial 
effect on government decision making, just as Congress envisioned when 
it enacted NEPA.
                    litigation examples adding value
    The following are summaries of some cases where NEPA litigation led 
to a better outcome. As I stated earlier, cases can be found when NEPA 
takes too long or litigation delays a project; however, outliers do not 
tell the whole story. Actions taken to change the NEPA process or 
access to the courts that do not address the real causes of delay are 
both premature and ill-advised. I strongly believe key factors causing 
delays include the lack of capacity and resources. The cases below 
provide examples of the value provided by a legal remedy when a Federal 
agency's NEPA process is insufficient or inadequate.\26\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \26\ Examples of NEPA success stories and benefits not including 
litigation are available at https://ceq.doe.gov/get-involved/
success_stories.html.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
Colorado: Canyons of the Ancients National Monument
    The Canyons of the Ancients National Monument in southwestern 
Colorado contains over 6,000 archaeological sites representing 
Ancestral Pueblan and other Native American cultures. As a result of 
the designation, the existing oil and gas leases on the land were 
permitted to run their course but would not be renewed. On the eve of 
the lease's expiration, the lessees proposed a new seismic exploration 
project for the land. However, the Bureau of Land Management's (BLM) 
Environmental Assessment was allegedly based on inadequate cultural 
resource surveys, and, as a result, allowed exploration on the edges of 
several sensitive sites and artifacts. In an effort to protect these 
irreplaceable areas, a coalition of groups led by San Juan Citizens 
Alliance filed suit in Federal district court and were granted an 
emergency injunction. Negotiations between all stakeholders ensued, 
with conservation groups, BLM, and the lessees coming to the table to 
work out a compromise. The result of the negotiations structured an 
exploration project that enabled lessees to obtain the seismic 
information they needed while avoiding the National Monument's most 
significant cultural features and fragile habitats. All in all, it was 
a win-win that balanced energy exploration with cultural resource 
protection, and exemplifies effective multiple-use management of the 
public lands.\27\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \27\ New Energy Project at Monument, Los Angeles Times, August 13, 
2002, available at: http://articles.latimes.com/2002/aug/13/nation/na-
drill13; Energy Exploration Approved in Colorado Monument, Institute 
for Agriculture and Trade Policy, September 25, 2002, available at: 
https://www.iatp.org/news/energy-exploration-approved-in-colorado-
monument.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
Florida: Scripps Research Institute Florida
    In October 2003, Palm Beach County and Scripps Research Institute 
jointly developed plans for a Biotechnology Research Park to be built 
on the Mecca Farms site--a 1,919-acre parcel in rural western Palm 
Beach County bordered by wetlands and conservation areas. In addition, 
Mecca's wetlands drain into the Loxahatchee River, a nationally 
designated Wild and Scenic River and an essential component of the 
Everglades Ecosystem. In order to develop the area, Palm Beach County 
and Scripps sought approval of a Clean Water Act Section 404 permit 
from the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers to fill wetlands at the Mecca 
Farms. The Corps issued the permit in 2005 based upon an EA concluding 
there were no significant environmental impacts associated with filling 
the wetlands. However, the Corps' EA--designed to identify any 
significant impacts a project may have on both the environment and 
public health--had been limited to only 25 percent of the 1,919 acre 
Mecca Farms site. Environmental groups--who had brought the matter to 
the Corps' attention during the agency process--challenged the adequacy 
of the EA under NEPA. In 2005, a District Court held that the Corps' 
issuance of the permit had violated both the National Environmental 
Policy Act and Clean Water Act and ordered preparation of a new 
environmental review before the project could proceed. During the 
ensuing evaluation process, Palm Beach County and Scripps decided to 
relocate the research park to a new location that minimized 
environmental impacts and saved money by utilizing existing access 
roads. The grand opening of the new facility took place on February 26, 
2009, and today the Scripps Florida Research Institute operates a 
state-of-the-art biomedical research facility focusing on neuroscience, 
cancer biology, medicinal chemistry, drug discovery, biotechnology, and 
alternative energy development employing more than 500 research 
staff.\28\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \28\ Florida Wildlife Federation v. U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, 
404 F.Supp.2d 1352 (2005). Available at: https://www.courtlistener.com/
opinion/2315811/florida-wildlife-federation-v-us-army-corps-of-
engineers.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
Minnesota: Central Corridor Light Rail
    The Central Corridor Light Rail is a 10.9-mile light rail transit 
line connecting downtown Minneapolis and St. Paul. Running along 
University Avenue for most of the route, the project included 
construction of 18 new stations. In January 2011, the NAACP filed suit 
against the U.S. Department of Transportation (DOT) and the 
Metropolitan Council (the regional transit authority) claiming that the 
final environmental impact statement for the project was inadequate, in 
part because it failed to analyze the short-term impact of project 
construction on surrounding businesses. Specifically, the businesses 
were concerned with the project's removal of street parking, which 
would prevent customers from patronizing their stores. In response, the 
DOT used the NEPA process to hold town meetings, hearings, and 
otherwise engage the community, resulting in a supplemental EIS that 
suggested a range of mitigation measures to help small businesses 
resulting in providing help to small, affected local businesses in the 
corridor cope with the impacts of construction and loss of street 
parking.\29\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \29\ St. Paul Branch of NAACP v. U.S. DOT, 764 F. Supp. 2d 1092 
(2011); see also https: / / metrocouncil.org/ Transportation/ Projects/ 
Light-Rail-Projects/ Central-Corridor/ Environmental. aspx.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
Washington State: Huckleberry Land Exchange
    Under the proposed Huckleberry Land Exchange, the U.S. Forest 
Service would trade nearly 7,000 acres of mature and old-growth forest 
in Washington's Mt. Baker-Snoqualmie National Forest, including a 
portion of the Muckleshoot Tribe's historic Huckleberry Divide Trail, 
for about 30,000 acres of high-elevation land held by Weyerhaeuser 
Timber Company. Citizen groups and the Muckleshoot Indian Tribe 
challenged this proposal. The court found that the Forest Service 
violated NEPA by failing to consider an adequate range of alternatives 
and by neglecting to analyze the cumulative impacts of the proposed 
exchange. As a result, the Forest Service improved their analysis and 
altered their plans for carrying out the exchange. Ultimately, the 
Huckleberry Land Exchange went forward with a better design that 
protected old-growth forest and culturally and recreationally important 
public lands.\30\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \30\ Muckleshoot Indian Tribe v. Forest Service, 177 F. 3d 800 (9th 
Cir. 1999); see also http://elawreview.org/case-summaries/muckleshoot-
indian-tribe-v-united-states-forest-service.
                                 ______
Questions Submitted for the Record by Rep. Grijalva to Horst Greczmiel, 
            Former CEQ Associate Director of NEPA Oversight
    Question 1. Can you please provide specific examples of how the 
NEPA process has saved Federal tax dollars by bringing to light 
information that led to cheaper, more efficient projects?
    Answer. Case studies and compilations of success stories provide 
examples that show the value of using the NEPA process to engage the 
public, organizations, and other government entities. The five examples 
below show that alternatives to the initial proposed action shaped by 
collaboratively engaging the public can address the purpose and need 
for the proposed project in a way that is less impactful on the human 
environment and lead to more efficient projects that can include 
reduced and avoided costs.
Highway 26 Bypass
    Highway 26 is a regional road that runs through south-central 
Wisconsin, connecting Illinois to Wisconsin's Fox River Valley. To 
address increasing traffic from trucks and regional drivers on the 
road, Wisconsin's Department of Transportation (WisDOT) proposed the 
construction of a bypass. NEPA provided the opportunity for 
stakeholders to engage in discussions about the project development. 
``NEPA forces us into providing alternatives that are representative of 
the interests of all agencies involved,'' said James Oeth, WisDOT 
project manager. As stipulated by NEPA, several alternatives were 
selected, studied in detail, and made available for public comment. 
``Without NEPA, we would have just asked what the shortest distance was 
and built the road through there,'' said Oeth.
    The final decision created a route with the least impact and 
disruption to the community. For example, while the original route 
would have plowed through Ed McFarland's dairy farm, which sits west of 
Watertown, the final plan navigated around it. ``Public involvement 
helped us . . . the less land we lose, the better,'' said McFarland. 
Additionally, under the final plan, the bypass skirted the community's 
urban service area, instead of destroying pristine land. While not all 
of the community's major requests were accommodated, residents 
appreciated the opportunity to be involved in the process. ``I believe 
NEPA allowed for these alterations to take place,'' said Andy Didion, a 
Jefferson resident. ``The DOT is getting much better and realizing this 
affects people's lives.'' ``We talked out problems and came up with 
solutions that were agreeable to most participants,'' stated Greg 
David, a Jefferson County Supervisor. ``The NEPA process has saved us a 
lot of money and mitigated many of the externalized consequences of a 
freeway expansion project.'' \1\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \1\ The Road to Better Transportation Projects, Wisconsin Highway 
26 Bypass, NEPA Brings Communities to the Table, Sierra Club website, 
retrieved May 2, 2018, from http://vault.sierraclub.org/sprawl/nepa/
wisconsin.asp.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
Lakeview-Reeder Roads Project
    In Idaho, the Forest Service proposed the Lakeview-Reeder Roads 
project to improve fish passage in Priest Lake and reduce sedimentation 
as part of a Healthy Forest Restoration Project. Public participation 
in the plan's NEPA review brought to light a discrepancy between the 
planned and the required buffer zone for the protection of the 
endangered boreal toad. In response, the Forest Service redesigned the 
proposed road maintenance and construction to adequately protect the 
species.\2\ By informing the public of its plan, listening to citizen 
comments, and modifying the proposed project, the Forest Service 
avoided irretrievably committing taxpayer dollars to a project that 
violated Federal laws, thereby preventing possible litigation and a 
waste of taxpayer money.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \2\ Idaho Panhandle National Forest NEPA Projects: Lakeview-Reeder 
HFRA Project, U.S. Forest Service website, retrieved May 2, 2018 from 
https://data.ecosystem-management.org/nepaweb/
nepa_project_exp.php?project=6258; Lakeview-Reeder Roads Record of 
Decision, U.S. Forest Service, December, 2009, available at: https://
www.fs.usda.gov/nfs/11558/www/nepa/6430_FSPLT1_017770.pdf.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
Paris Pike
    Kentucky's Paris Pike is a scenic road between Lexington and Paris 
that runs for 13.5 miles through rolling hills dotted with historic 
thoroughbred horse farms. However, its beauty was overshadowed by 
congestion and safety hazards, such as a lack of passing and turning 
lanes. The initial proposed project called for a standard four-lane 
highway but faced opposition from local communities concerned about 
irreparable harm to the historic corridor's natural landscape. A judge 
agreed with the communities and called for revisiting the planning 
process and developing a workable alternative. As a result, a design 
was developed that fit the aesthetics and contours of the land while 
minimizing environmental impacts.
    The new design, which has won national awards, added a shoulder; 
preserved existing trees, fences, and stone walls; and installed 
additional walls and guardrails to increase safety and enhance the 
highway's aesthetics. The new design also converted a historic 
farmhouse into a visitors' center, generating tourism dollars for a 
community that would have lost money if the original project had been 
implemented. ``It has been an immensely successful project,'' said 
Cumberland Sierra Club chapter chair Lane Boldman. ``It preserved 
aesthetic integrity while doing what it was supposed to do: increase 
safety and capacity. It has significantly improved the corridor.'' 
Local resident Hank Graddy said the NEPA process was essential, noting 
that it ``brought people and ideas to the table that otherwise would 
not have been there.'' Paris Pike represents a true compromise 
facilitated by the NEPA process: road expansion without accompanying 
aesthetic and natural destruction.\3\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \3\ Raymond Werkmeister and Donn Hancher, The Paris to Lexington 
Road Reconstruction Project, University of Kentucky College of 
Engineering Kentucky Transportation Center, Sept. 2001, available at 
http://www.e-archives.ky.gov/pubs/transportation/tc_rpt/ktc_02_02_fr79_ 
96_1f.pdf; See also Transportation Research Board presentation 
retrieved May 2, 2018, from https://trid.trb.org/view/650514.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
Scripps Research Institute
    Palm Beach County Florida and Scripps Research Institute jointly 
developed plans for a Biotechnology Research Park to be built on the 
Mecca Farms site--a 1,919-acre parcel in rural western Palm Beach 
County bordered by wetlands and conservation areas. Mecca's wetlands 
drain into the Loxahatchee River, a nationally designated Wild and 
Scenic River and an essential component of the Everglades Ecosystem. In 
order to develop the area, Palm Beach County and Scripps sought 
approval of a Clean Water Act Section 404 permit from the U.S. Army 
Corps of Engineers to fill wetlands at the Mecca Farms. The Corps 
issued the permit in 2005 based upon an EA concluding there were no 
significant environmental impacts associated with filling the wetlands. 
However, the Corps' EA--designed to identify any significant impacts a 
project may have on both the environment and public health--had been 
limited to only 25 percent of the 1,919 acre Mecca Farms site. 
Environmental groups--who had brought the matter to the Corps' 
attention during the agency process--challenged the adequacy of the EA 
under NEPA.
    The District Court held that the Corps' issuance of the permit had 
violated both the National Environmental Policy Act and Clean Water Act 
and called for the preparation of a new environmental review before the 
project could proceed.\4\ During the ensuing evaluation process, Palm 
Beach County and Scripps decided to relocate the research park to a new 
location that minimized environmental impacts and saved money by 
utilizing existing access roads. The grand opening of the new facility 
took place on February 26, 2009,\5\ and today the Scripps Florida 
Research Institute operates a state-of-the-art biomedical research 
facility focusing on neuroscience, cancer biology, medicinal chemistry, 
drug discovery, biotechnology, and alternative energy development 
employing more than 500 research staff.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \4\ Florida Wildlife Federation v. U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, 
404 F.Supp.2d 1352 (2005), available at: https://www.courtlistener.com/
opinion/2315811/florida-wildlife-federation-v-us-army-corps-of-
engineers.
    \5\ Opening Ceremonies Celebrate New Scripps Florida Biomedical 
Research Facilities, The Scripps Research Institute, February, 2009, 
available at: https://www.scripps.edu/news/press/2009/022609.html.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
Crenshaw/LAX Transit Corridor Project
    When construction is completed in 2019, the Crenshaw/LAX line in 
Los Angeles CA will run from the Jefferson Park neighborhood in the 
north to Inglewood and El Segundo in the south and add a long-sought 
rail connection from downtown to one of the busiest airports in the 
world. Without the approval of ``Measure R,'' a half-cent sales tax 
approved by Los Angeles County voters in 2009 that provided a dedicated 
funding for 12 metro area transit projects, the city wouldn't have had 
the money to proceed. Early project planning and work on the 
Environmental Impact Statement (EIS) to construct the 8.5-mile line 
connecting two existing subway lines began in 2009. During this review 
process, the Federal Transit Administration (FTA) and Los Angeles Metro 
officials considered public concerns and identified a rarely used 5-
mile long freight rail line instead of building new tracks that would 
have disrupted several neighborhoods and proven far costlier. That 
decision decreased project costs, saved time, and reduced disturbances 
for the nearby community by using an existing right-of-way.
    Throughout the environmental review and planning process, local 
residents were engaged to ensure the project would completed in an 
equitable, beneficial, and resourceful way that met the needs of local 
communities. For example, a station was added to service Leimert Park 
Village, an important cultural center for black residents of Los 
Angeles, and the Crenshaw/LAX Community Leadership Council ensured that 
community issues are considered throughout the planning process.\6\ As 
one of the Federal Transit Administration's first projects piloting a 
new process to help identify and mitigate project risks more 
efficiently, the project's EIS was finalized in less than 2 years in 
2011 and the Crenshaw/LAX light-rail alternative moved forward.\7\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \6\ Community Organizations Shed Light On New Crenshaw District, 
Los Angeles Sentinel, December 2, 2015, available at: https://
lasentinel.net/community-organizations-shed-light-on-new-crenshaw-
district.html; see also About the Crenshaw/LAX Community Leadership 
Council (CLC), Los Angeles County Metropolitan Transportation Authority 
website retrieved May 4, 2018, from https://www.metro.net/projects/
crenshaw_corridor/clc-about/.
    \7\ Final Environmental Impact Statement/Final Environmental Impact 
Report: Crenshaw/LAX Transit Corridor, Federal Transit Administration, 
August 31, 2011, available at: http://media.metro.net/projects_studies/
crenshaw/images/FEIS_FEIR/00_Cover_Table_of_Contents.pdf; Record of 
Decision: Crenshaw/LAX Transit Corridor, Federal Transit 
Administration, December 30, 2011, available at: http://
media.metro.net/projects_studies/crenshaw/images/20111230_ 
CrenshawLAX_Record_of_Decision.pdf.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
Northwest Corridor Project
    In 2007, the Federal Highway Administration and Georgia Department 
of Transportation (GDOT), in cooperation with other state and Federal 
agencies, proposed to expand I-75 and I-575 in the Atlanta metropolitan 
area's Northwest Corridor to alleviate traffic congestion in one of the 
region's most congested thoroughfares. When completed later this year, 
the Northwest Corridor Project (NWCP) is expected to be the most 
expensive highway project in Georgia's history at nearly $1 billion, 
adding nearly 30 miles of reversible lanes along I-75 and I-575 through 
Cobb and Cherokee counties. The initial design plan proposed an even 
larger project, expanding sections of I-75 and I-575 from 6 to 10 lanes 
by adding 4 general-purpose lanes. Community members using the NEPA 
review process to express their environmental, public health, and 
economic concerns about the project led the Georgia Department of 
Transportation (GDOT) to make improvements to the plan.\8\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \8\ Final Environmental Impact Statement Reevaluation: Northwest 
Corridor Project, Federal Highway Administration and Georgia Department 
of Transportation. October 2011. Available at: http://nwcproject.com/
media/pdfs/REEVAL/FEISReeval13.pdf; Record of Decision: Northwest 
Corridor Project,'' Federal Highway Administration and Georgia 
Department of Transportation, May 2013, available at http://
www.nwcproject.com/media/pdfs/NWCP_ROD_2013.pdf.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Instead of adding new lanes, GDOT's final designed plan called for 
the conversion of the existing medians and road space on I-75 into 
reversible HOV traffic lanes--modifications that will save a 
significant amount of money. In addition, the NWCP modifications 
minimized adverse effects on low-income and minority communities by 
reducing the number of residences and businesses displaced from over 
300 to 18, and reduced the project's impact on the nearby wetlands that 
are home to an endangered species from 4.2 to 0.3 acres. Thanks to the 
NEPA public review process, the NWCP has fewer impacts on local homes, 
businesses, and the environment, and is more cost-effective than the 
original plan. Construction broke ground in October 2014 and the 
project is anticipated to fully open to traffic later this year.
    Question 2. Can you explain the purpose and value of the CEQ's 2016 
Greenhouse Gases and Climate Change Guidance, and what impacts we can 
expect to see with its recent withdrawal?
    Answer. The guidance came about, at least in part, as a result of 
three converging factors. First, the public, the scientific community, 
and the courts are increasingly recognizing the importance of 
greenhouse gas emissions and climate change as an environmental issue 
and characterizing the effects as significant.\9\ The growing number of 
court cases reflect the view that the NEPA process is an appropriate 
venue to address the issue.\10\ Cases, however, are fact specific and 
result in varied approaches to address when and how analysis of those 
issues is appropriate.\11\ Second, CEQ was asked to provide guidance by 
Federal agencies and the public.\12\ CEQ was also formally petitioned 
to consider regulations and guidance on analyzing GHG emissions and the 
impacts of climate change under NEPA.\13\ And third, a major CEQ role 
is the oversight of Federal agencies' implementation of NEPA.\14\ 
Without enforcement authority, CEQ maintains that role through its 
leadership and the support of the agencies and the public by addressing 
and helping to overcome challenges that impede Federal agencies' 
ability to prepare useful and timely environmental reviews.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \9\ For example, see the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change 
website, retrieved May 2, 2018, from http://www.ipcc.ch/.
    \10\ For example, see Border Power Plant Working Group v. DOE, 260 
F. Supp. 2d 997 (S.D. Cal. 2003).
    \11\ Michael B. Gerrard, Survey of Climate Change Litigation, New 
York Law Journal, Sept. 28, 2007, available at https://
files.arnoldporter.com/arnold%20&amp;%20porter%20llp.survey%20of%20 
climate%20change%20litigation.new%20york%20law%20journal.september%2028%
202007.pdf.
    \12\ Recommendations of the State, Local, and Tribal Leaders Task 
Force on Climate Preparedness and Resilience, November 2014, at page 20 
(recommendation 2.7) available at http://
www.adaptationclearinghouse.org / organizations / state-local-and-
tribal-leaders-task-force-on-climate-preparedness-and-resilience.htm; 
see also Future Federal Adaptation Efforts Could Better Support Local 
Infrastructure Decision Makers, Government Accountability Office, Apr. 
12, 2012, available at https://www.gao.gov/products/GAO-13-242.
    \13\ International Center for Technology Assessment, Natural 
Resources Defense Council, and Sierra Club, Petition Requesting That 
the Council on Environmental Quality Amend its Regulations to Clarify 
That Climate Change Analyses be Included in Environmental Review 
Documents, Feb. 28, 2008 (the petition requested CEQ issue guidance and 
the petition to amend the regulations was denied on August 7, 2014).
    \14\ 42 U.S.C. 4344.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Throughout its history, CEQ has been shown deference by the courts 
when speaking to how agencies can meet their responsibilities under 
NEPA and the CEQ NEPA Regulations.\15\ Consequently, in the face of the 
continued challenges to when and how agencies were to address 
greenhouse gas emissions and climate change, CEQ had the opportunity--
and the responsibility--to issue guidance that would clarify the 
matter.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \15\ Associations Working for Aurora's Residential Env't v. 
Colorado Dep't of Transp., 153 F.3d 1122, 1127 n .4, 28 ELR 21459 (10th 
Cir. 1998); see also Andrus v. Sierra Club, 442 U.S. 347 (1979) 
(``CEQ's interpretation of NEPA is entitled to substantial 
deference.'').
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    CEQ issued the guidance to provide for greater clarity and more 
consistency in how agencies address climate change in the environmental 
impact assessment process. Climate change was acknowledged as a 
fundamental environmental issue with effects that should be analyzed 
under NEPA.\16\ Although climate change is a particularly complex 
challenge given its global nature and the inherent inter-relationships 
among its sources, causation, mechanisms of action, and impacts, the 
guidance recognized that analyzing a proposed action's GHG emissions 
and the effects of climate change relevant to a proposed action--
particularly how climate change may change an action's environmental 
effects--could provide useful information to decision makers and the 
public. The guidance used long-standing NEPA principles because such an 
analysis should be similar to the analysis of other environmental 
impacts under NEPA.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \16\ NEPA recognizes ``the profound impact of man's activity on the 
inter-relations of all components of the natural environment.'' (42 
U.S.C. 4331(a)). It was enacted to, inter alia, ``promote efforts which 
will prevent or eliminate damage to the environment biosphere and 
stimulate the health and welfare of man.'' (42 U.S.C. 4321).
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Furthermore, the guidance used a reasoned practical approach to 
ease the burden of developing complex analyses by recommending agencies 
use available tools to project GHG emissions, and where applicable 
carbon sequestration, as a proxy for assessing potential climate change 
effects. The guidance also advised agencies to use existing available 
information when assessing the potential future state of the 
environment rather than undertaking new research and thereby extending 
the review process. In short, the guidance provides a pathway for 
agencies to comply with NEPA through more focused, shorter, and less 
resource intensive means than were becoming the norm in order to 
address the many different stakeholder views and court rulings.
    Withdrawing the guidance leaves the agencies without clear 
direction on what should be analyzed and how intensive that analysis 
should be. The result is longer documents containing differing analyses 
that are subject to challenge along with less clarity for decision 
makers, project sponsors, and the public. The hope is that the current 
Administration's notice that the guidance was withdrawn for further 
consideration \17\ will result in new or revised guidance that furthers 
the ability of agencies to address GHG emissions and climate change in 
a practical and reasoned manner. In the absence of such guidance, I 
fear we will continue to see the development of different requirements 
and interpretations by different agencies and courts that will make 
consistent approaches more difficult and lead to longer, less focused, 
and less timely NEPA reviews.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \17\ 82 FR 16576, Apr. 5, 2017, available at https: / / 
www.federalregister.gov / documents / 2017 / 04 / 05 / 2017-06770 / 
withdrawal-of-final-guidance-for-federal-departments-and-agencies-on-
consideration-of-CFR1501.8greenhouse-gas; note that the withdrawn 
guidance is still available on https://ceq.doe.gov/guidance/
ceq_guidance_nepa-ghg-climate_final_guidance.html as is the webpage on 
GHG emissions accounting tools: https://ceq.doe.gov/guidance/ghg-
accounting-tools.html.
    Question 3. During the 2018 State of the Union, President Trump 
called for legislation that would reduce the Federal permitting process 
for infrastructure projects ``to no more than 2 years, and perhaps even 
1.'' Do you believe that a lack of mandated timelines is actually a 
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
hurdle to efficient environmental review?
    Answer. When agencies have adequate resources and training, I 
believe that project specific non-mandatory timelines, or schedules, 
can facilitate the timely development of efficient NEPA environmental 
reviews. Mandated timelines with monetary penalties or ``automatic 
approvals'' for not meeting deadlines do not do so.
    The CEQ NEPA Regulations provide for time limits \18\ and the 
timing of the NEPA review.\19\ What was true when the CEQ NEPA 
Regulations were established in 1978 remains true today--specific time 
limits for the entire NEPA process are too inflexible and individual 
proposed projects vary due to numerous factors (e.g., location, design, 
environmental impact). Consequently, imposing a one-size-fits-all 
approach is impractical. The recent One Federal Decision Memorandum of 
Understanding, builds on the efficiencies provided for in CEQ NEPA 
Regulations \20\ and uses existing rules and best practices such as 
pre-scoping, milestones (non-mandatory schedules) and early dispute 
resolution, to provide for more coordinated and timely environmental 
reviews and authorization processes.\21\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \18\ 40 CFR 1501.8.
    \19\ 40 CFR 1502.8.
    \20\ Memorandum for Heads of Federal Departments and Agencies: 
Improving the Process for Preparing Efficient and Timely Environmental 
Reviews under the National Environmental Policy Act, CEQ, Mar. 6, 2012, 
available at: https: / / ceq.doe.gov/docs/ceq-regulations-and-guidance/
Improving_NEPA_Efficiencies_06Mar2012.pdf.
    \21\ Memorandum of Understanding Implementing One Federal Decision 
Under Executive Order 13807, April 2018, available at https: / / 
www.ferc.gov/ legal/ mou/2018/MOU-One-Federal-Decision.pdf.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    While there is value in setting time goals based on similar 
projects, non-mandatory goals are preferable. There is a real risk that 
mandating a time for a decision can lead to either rushed decisions 
that do not fully consider nor seek to avoid negative environmental 
consequences, or denials to avoid making uninformed decisions 
vulnerable to challenges for incomplete information or analyses.
    A timeline should, at a minimum, provide opportunities to stop-the-
clock when appropriate: for example, when applicants need time to 
provide additional information relevant to the NEPA review of a 
requested approval or permit; when a state takes time to identify 
matching funds; or when a pending state, local, or tribal approval or 
permit is necessary for a proposed project to proceed. Most 
importantly, until agencies are provided adequate resources and 
training to conduct efficient and timely NEPA reviews, agencies will 
continue to struggle to prepare timely NEPA reviews.
    Question 4. Do you believe that mandated timelines would lead to 
speedier project completion for most projects?
    Answer. I do not believe that mandated timelines would lead to 
speedier project completion. In addition to my response above, it is 
important to remember that a multitude of factors other than 
undertaking NEPA compliance affect the timing of Federal project 
delivery and that once the NEPA review is completed, and the project 
decided upon, the project must still be implemented.
    In my experience factors that can cause delay include lack of 
funding; changes in the design or planning processes; inadequate staff 
capacity to implement or oversee the NEPA process; changes in 
priorities that keep a proposed project from proceeding; local 
controversy or local opposition to a project; or delays in other (non-
NEPA) permitting or approval processes at the Federal, state, tribal, 
or local level. With regard to the latter, certain Federal actions such 
as highway construction projects and permitting for mining operations, 
cattle grazing, forest thinning, and energy development may require 
compliance with other statutory and regulatory requirements that can 
add time, especially if they are raised late in the environmental 
review process. This is particularly the case when such review or 
permitting requires the participation or input of increasing numbers of 
local, state, tribal, or Federal agencies. In addition, agencies 
responsible for protecting resources are often confronted by problems 
with the project's alternatives analysis, incorrect or incomplete 
information, disagreements or differences of opinion among agencies, 
poor communication with project proponents and other agencies, or the 
environmental or biological analyses associated with the project.\22\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \22\ See, for example, The Role of the Environmental Review Process 
in Federally Funded Highway Projects: Background and Issues for 
Congress, CRS 7-5700, R42479, April 11, 2012, p. 36, available at 
https://environment.transportation.org/pdf/proj_delivery_stream/
crs_report_ envrev.pdf.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    More often than not, factors other than complying with NEPA or the 
NEPA Regulations are the reasons for delaying projects. Those factors 
remain regardless of any mandated timelines for Federal permitting and 
environmental reviews. Coordinated schedules and timelines tailored to 
specific projects with the ability to stop-the-clock for appropriate 
time periods, coupled with ensuring agencies have the capacity to 
prepare effective and timely reviews and permits, offers a better 
approach to improve timeliness.
    Question 5. Do you think there would be negative environmental 
impacts caused by this kind of mandated time limit?
    Answer. In addition to my responses above, mandated time limits 
would cause agencies to decrease the amount of time for two specific 
aspects of NEPA. Public engagement and the consideration of 
alternatives are often pointed to as two of the most time-consuming 
aspects of a NEPA review and would, in my opinion, most likely be 
curtailed by either reducing time for public engagement and comment 
periods or reducing the number of alternatives considered. The value of 
engaging the public and considering reasonable--technically and 
economically feasible--alternatives is significant. This has been 
demonstrated by case studies--success stories--that show the benefits, 
and the avoidance or reduction of adverse impacts, to communities and 
the human environment.\23\ Furthermore, engaging the public in 
reviewing and developing alternatives results in a better understanding 
of the Federal agency and its actions, leading to greater community 
support for the final decision.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \23\ See for example: NEPA Success Stories: Celebrating 40 Years of 
Transparency and Open Government, Environmental Law Institute, 2010, 
available at https: / / ceq.doe.gov/docs/get-involved/
NEPA_Success_Stories.pdf.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    At the September 15, 2010, celebration of the 40th Anniversary of 
NEPA sponsored by the Environmental Law Institute and the Partnership 
Project, both Russell Train and Congressman John Dingell reflected on 
the value of NEPA.\24\ Russell Train, former Administrator of the 
Environmental Protection Agency and the first Chairman of the Council 
on Environmental Quality, found that National Environmental Policy Act 
(NEPA) successes demonstrate ``how public involvement and careful 
consideration of alternatives has produced better outcomes--for the 
agencies themselves, for the nation, and for the human environment.'' 
``NEPA covers every situation that we confront,'' Representative 
Dingell said. ``Despite attacks over the years, people realized the 
tremendous success of the statute.''
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \24\ https://obamawhitehouse.archives.gov/administration/eop/ceq/
initiatives/nepa/symposium.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    It is encouraging to note that a recent study of oil and gas 
development showed that NEPA adds value by reducing certain media 
specific impacts more than would be the case by relying solely on 
existing substantive laws such as the Clean Air Act and Clean Water 
Act. That study also showed that having more alternatives to evaluate 
leads to greater benefits such as protecting more wetlands, disturbing 
less lands, and improving air quality.\25\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \25\ John Ruple and Mark Capone, NEPA--Substantive Effectiveness 
Under a Procedural Mandate: Assessment of Oil and Gas EISs in the 
Mountain West, George Washington Journal of Energy &amp; Environmental Law, 
Winter 2016.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    In closing, I believe there is a real risk that mandating a time 
for a decision will lead to rushed decisions that do not fully consider 
nor seek to avoid negative environmental consequences.
                                 ______
    Mr. Thompson. Mr. Greczmiel, thank you very much.
    The Chair now recognizes Mr. Coleman to testify.
</option>
    <option>        UNIVERSITY, DEDMAN SCHOOL OF LAW, DALLAS, TEXAS
    Mr. Coleman. My thanks to the Committee. There are a lot of 
studies and statistics about the National Environmental Policy 
Act process, but I don't think any of us in this room disagree 
about those statistics. We are all using the same stats. There 
are about 200 major infrastructure projects every year that 
require an environmental impact statement. If you look at the 
reviews that ended in the year 2016, the average review takes a 
little bit over 5 years.
    So, the two questions for the Committee to consider today 
are, first, should each of these projects have to wait so long 
for their environmental approval; and second, if not, is there 
anything that Congress can do about it?
    On the first question, there has been some bipartisan 
agreement. Both parties have said these reviews take too long. 
For the last 20 years, Democratic and Republican Congresses, 
President Bush and President Obama passed laws and issued 
orders to try to streamline these reviews. Congress and the 
President have asked agencies to track projects, to streamline 
reviews, and to set deadlines, but so far the environmental 
reviews are just getting longer.
    Under President Bush, the average review took 3\1/2\ years. 
By the end of President Obama's term, the average review took 
more than 5 years. And that is the average review for projects 
completed in 2016. We know that these reviews are getting 
longer each year. So, if you were to enter a review process 
today, how long would it take to complete? It is probably going 
to be 6 years, maybe potentially longer.
    So, why do these reviews keep getting longer? On that, I 
think we really need to listen to what the NEPA practitioners 
say, practitioners like Mr. Greczmiel. These reviews take time, 
so every time there is a proposal for streamlining reviews, 
NEPA practitioners say the same thing, ``Well, that might just 
backfire, because if you try to do the reviews faster, the 
courts are going to strike down the reviews, and it is just 
going to take you more time.''
    And I think they might be right. Given how courts review 
NEPA claims, agencies may feel that unless they gold-plate 
their review, unless they really do far more than the statute 
was intended to require, the review will get struck down in 
court.
    When outside groups challenge a permit under NEPA, more 
than half of those lawsuits are filed in the Ninth Circuit. And 
plaintiffs win a lot of those cases. Even if they don't win in 
district court, they might win in the court of appeals. It is a 
minority of cases, but it is a significant percentage.
    In theory, if the government loses one of those challenges 
to a permit, it could appeal that loss to the Supreme Court. 
But the Supreme Court takes very few cases. NEPA has been 
around for about 50 years, and the Supreme Court has taken 17 
NEPA cases.
    What does the Supreme Court say when it takes those cases? 
It always says basically the same thing. In each of those 
cases, the Supreme Court has said first the government did 
enough review, the government has won each of those cases. In 
fact, almost all of those cases have been unanimous decisions 
of the U.S. Supreme Court. And second, the Supreme Court has 
said often, ``Lower courts, cut it out. Stop asking agencies to 
meet an impossible standard in these NEPA reviews.''
    If you are an agency, however, you cannot count on getting 
that Supreme Court review, since they take so few cases. So, 
you might think, if I don't want my analysis overturned, this 
over 5 years, soon-to-be 6 years of review overturned, I had 
better gild the lily. And if I am an investor looking at 
investing in one of these major infrastructure projects in the 
United States, I think if I want to build a major project in 
the United States it is probably going to take me 6 years for 
my environmental review. And even if I get it, there is a 
significant chance that I will be caught up in years of 
litigation.
    Can Congress do anything about that? Well, let me offer two 
proposals.
    First, for some natural gas projects, we have asked that if 
you file a NEPA challenge, you do it within a specified time 
period, and do it in the D.C. Circuit. I don't know any reason 
why all projects aren't as important as natural gas projects. 
What about a solar farm on Federal land, or what about a 
transmission project to support that solar farm? I think it is 
possible that all of those projects should be given expedited 
review in the D.C. Circuit.
    The second proposal that I would offer is that at some 
point the NEPA challenges should end. So, if the government has 
issued a final environmental impact statement and it has been 
over 7 years, 8 years, 9 years, some point, that NEPA 
obligation should no longer be enforceable. Because, again, 
NEPA was intended to be a procedural requirement. It is not 
supposed to be a standard for whether projects are approved. 
So, I think that if you have done more than 6, 7, 8 years of 
review, that should be considered adequate.
    Thank you, and I also look forward to your questions.
</option>
</Hearing>
