<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing>
    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <Doc-title>OVERSIGHT HEARING ON LIQUEFIED NATURAL GAS AND U.S. GEOPOLITICS</Doc-title>
    <option>=======================================================================
</option>
    <Doc-title>OVERSIGHT HEARING ON LIQUEFIED NATURAL GAS AND U.S. GEOPOLITICS</Doc-title>
    <option>                               before the
</option>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON ENERGY AND</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                           MINERAL RESOURCES
                                 of the
</option>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES</committee_name>
    <option>                     U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             SECOND SESSION
                               __________
                       Tuesday, February 27, 2018
                               __________
                           Serial No. 115-38
                               __________
       Printed for the use of the Committee on Natural Resources
        Available via the World Wide Web: http://www.govinfo.gov
                                   or
          Committee address: http://naturalresources.house.gov
                                   ______
                         U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE 
28-794 PDF                     WASHINGTON : 2018 
</option>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES</comitteeM_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROB BISHOP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RAUL M. GRIJALVA</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ranking Democratic Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Don Young</Pname>
        <Plocation> AK</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Grace F. Napolitano</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Chairman Emeritus</Pname>
        <Plocation>Chairman Emeritus</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Madeleine Z. Bordallo</Pname>
        <Plocation> GU</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Louie Gohmert</Pname>
        <Plocation> TX</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jim Costa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Chairman</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Gregorio Kilili Camacho Sablan</Pname>
        <Plocation> </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug Lamborn</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CNMI</Pname>
        <Plocation>CNMI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Robert J. Wittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Niki Tsongas</Pname>
        <Plocation> MA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Tom McClintock</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jared Huffman</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Stevan Pearce</Pname>
        <Plocation> NM</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Ranking Member</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Ranking Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Glenn Thompson</Pname>
        <Plocation> PA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Alan S. Lowenthal</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul A. Gosar</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Donald S. Beyer</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Raul R. Labrador</Pname>
        <Plocation> ID</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Norma J. Torres</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Scott R. Tipton</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Ruben Gallego</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug LaMalfa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Colleen Hanabusa</Pname>
        <Plocation> HI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jeff Denham</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Nanette Diaz Barragan</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul Cook</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darren Soto</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Bruce Westerman</Pname>
        <Plocation> AR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>A. Donald McEachin</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Garret Graves</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Anthony G. Brown</Pname>
        <Plocation> MD</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jody B. Hice</Pname>
        <Plocation> GA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Wm. Lacy Clay</Pname>
        <Plocation> MO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Aumua Amata Coleman Radewagen</Pname>
        <Plocation> AS</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jimmy Gomez</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Daniel Webster</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jack Bergman</Pname>
        <Plocation> MI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Liz Cheney</Pname>
        <Plocation> WY</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Mike Johnson</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jenniffer Gonzalez-Colon</Pname>
        <Plocation> PR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Greg Gianforte</Pname>
        <Plocation> MT</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>John R. Curtis</Pname>
        <Plocation> UT</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Cody Stewart</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chief of Staff</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Lisa Pittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chief Counsel</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>David Watkins</Pname>
        <Plocation> Democratic Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON ENERGY AND MINERAL RESOURCES</subcomittee_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>PAUL A. GOSAR</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ALAN S. LOWENTHAL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ranking Democratic Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Louie Gohmert</Pname>
        <Plocation> TX</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Anthony G. Brown</Pname>
        <Plocation> MD</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug Lamborn</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jim Costa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Robert J. Wittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Niki Tsongas</Pname>
        <Plocation> MA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Stevan Pearce</Pname>
        <Plocation> NM</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jared Huffman</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Glenn Thompson</Pname>
        <Plocation> PA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Donald S. Beyer</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Scott R. Tipton</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darren Soto</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul Cook</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Nanette Diaz Barragan</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Chairman</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vacancy</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vacancy</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Garret Graves</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vacancy</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vacancy</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jody B. Hice</Pname>
        <Plocation> GA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Raul M. Grijalva</Pname>
        <Plocation> ex officio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jack Bergman</Pname>
        <Plocation> MI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Liz Cheney</Pname>
        <Plocation> WY</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>John R. Curtis</Pname>
        <Plocation> UT</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Rob Bishop</Pname>
        <Plocation> ex officio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <table-of-content>CONTENTS</table-of-content>
    <peopleSpeaker>   Hearing held on Tuesday</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>February</peopleinfo>
    <Members>Statement of Members:</Members>
    <Speaker>Hon Paul A Gosar</Speaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Arizona Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>Statement of Witnesses:</witnesses>
    <Witness>Hon Alan S Lowenthal</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of California Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Peter B Doran</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>President and CEO Center for European Policy Analysis</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Meg Gentle</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>President and CEO Tellurian</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>David Livingston</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Deputy Director for Climate and Advanced Energy Atlantic Council</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Christopher Smith</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Senior Vice President Policy</peopleinfo>
    <submittedMaterial>Additional Materials Submitted for the Record:</submittedMaterial>
    <Doc-title>OVERSIGHT HEARING ON LIQUEFIED NATURAL GAS AND U.S. GEOPOLITICS</Doc-title>
    <option>                              ----------                              
                       Tuesday, February 27, 2018
                     U.S. House of Representatives
</option>
    <subcomittee_name>Subcommittee on Energy and Mineral Resources</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                     Committee on Natural Resources
                             Washington, DC
                              ----------                              
    The Subcommittee met, pursuant to call, at 2:14 p.m., in 
room 1324, Longworth House Office Building, Hon. Paul A. Gosar 
[Chairman of the Subcommittee] presiding.
    Present: Representatives Gosar, Lamborn, Tipton, Graves, 
Hice, Cheney, Bishop (ex officio), Lowenthal, Costa, Beyer, and 
Soto.
    Dr. Gosar. The Subcommittee on Energy and Mineral Resources 
will come to order.
    The Subcommittee is meeting today to hear testimony on 
liquefied natural gas and U.S. geopolitics.
    Under Committee Rule 4(f), any oral opening statements at 
the hearing are limited to the Chairman, the Ranking Minority 
Member, and the Vice Chair. This will allow us to hear from our 
witnesses sooner and help Members keep to their schedules. 
Therefore, I ask unanimous consent that all other Members' 
opening statements be made part of the hearing record if they 
are submitted to the Subcommittee Clerk by 5:00 p.m. today.
    Without objection, so ordered.
</option>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR, A REPRESENTATIVE INCONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF ARIZONA</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR">Dr. Gosar. The advent of the Shale Revolution in America 
has revolutionized the way we extract valuable hydrocarbons, 
leading to lower energy prices and an infusion into the 
American economy with billions in revenues. The combination of 
horizontal drilling and hydraulic fracking technologies has 
also allowed the United States to transition from a position of 
energy insecurity to energy dominance.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR">In recent years, the production of natural gas has allowed 
the United States to become an undeniable force within the 
global energy market. Indeed, the United States has become the 
world's largest producer of natural gas since 2009. And this 
production must continue if we are to provide our allies with 
reliable energy, while maintaining jobs and increasing revenues 
from production here at home.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR">Further driving our Nation's energy security is the 
production of liquefied natural gas, or LNG. LNG is produced by 
shipping natural gas to a liquefication facility, where the gas 
is cooled until it is compressed 600 times, becoming liquid. 
The LNG is then ready to be shipped anywhere in the world.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR">Global demand for natural gas has tripled in the last two 
decades, and the advent of new market opportunities indicates 
that this trend will no doubt continue and increase America's 
role in energy security for our allies.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR">Just last year, the United States became a net exporter of 
natural gas for the first time since the 1950s. The production, 
liquefication, and shipping of LNG has risen to meet the 
incredible global demand for the product, implicating 
geopolitics across the globe.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR">For instance, Russia has long monopolized the gas supply to 
Europe. According to Deputy Secretary of State John McCarrick, 
11 European countries relied on Russian gas to meet 75 percent 
of their heating and electrical generation needs. The continent 
is therefore quite exposed to supply disruptions, either 
intentionally imposed or not.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR">Russia's Nord Stream pipeline, which supplies westbound gas 
from Russia to Germany across the Baltic Sea, is approaching 
its full transmission capacity of 55 billion cubic meters. 
Germany supports the construction of an identical pipeline, 
Nord Stream 2, which effectively doubles capacity. If 
constructed, the highly controversial pipeline will allow 
Russia to supply 75 percent of Europe's natural gas demand.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR">In 2017, Cheniere delivered the first shipment of American-
produced LNG from its Sabine Pass export terminal in Louisiana 
to the Baltic nation of Lithuania. Lithuania, like many of its 
Eastern European neighbors, relied exclusively on Russia to 
meet its energy demand for decades. This monumental shipment of 
LNG indicates that the European nations are looking to 
diversify and to break the stranglehold of Russian energy 
control.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR">Outside of Europe, demand for natural gas is skyrocketing 
in Asia. Last year alone, demand grew 20 percent in China, 
South Korea, and Japan as these nations continue to grow their 
economies while limiting greenhouse gas emissions. China is on 
track to more than double its natural gas from 38.1 million 
metric tons today to 82 million metric tons by 2030.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR">Meanwhile, India, which currently operates four LNG import 
and regasification facilities, is planning to expand its import 
capacity by 11 terminals.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR">American companies, such as Cheniere Energy, Incorporated, 
represented by Mr. Christopher Smith today, have signed some of 
the largest long-term supply agreements. Just this month, 
Cheniere signed the first ever long-term LNG supply contract 
with the Chinese National Petroleum Corporation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="THE HON. PAUL A. GOSAR">With the rise in demand, Australia has stepped up in the 
Asian markets, supplying over 80 percent of China's demand for 
LNG. As such, the United States is now competing for market 
share with strong local suppliers, and, therefore, it is 
essential that we support production, LNG export facility 
permitting, and pipeline capacity here on the American shores.</paragraph>
    <opening>[The prepared statement of Dr. Gosar follows:]</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="Dr. Gosar ">Today, we will discuss the implications of being a major 
player in the expanding global energy market.
Prepared Statement of the Hon. Paul A. Gosar, Chairman, Subcommittee on</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Dr. Gosar ">Energy and Mineral Resources</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Dr. Gosar ">The advent of the ``Shale Revolution'' in America has 
revolutionized the way we extract valuable hydrocarbons--leading to 
lower energy prices and an infusion in the American economy with 
billions in revenues. The combination of horizontal drilling and 
hydraulic fracturing technologies has also allowed the United States to 
transition from a position of energy insecurity to energy dominance.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Dr. Gosar ">In recent years, the production of natural gas has allowed the 
United States to become an undeniable force within the global energy 
market. Indeed, the United States has been the world's largest producer 
of natural gas since 2009, and this production must continue if we are 
to provide our allies with reliable energy, while maintaining jobs and 
increasing revenues from production here at home.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Dr. Gosar ">Further driving our Nation's energy security is the production of 
Liquefied Natural Gas (LNG). LNG is produced by shipping natural gas to 
a liquefaction facility, where the gas is cooled until it is compressed 
600 times becoming liquid. The LNG is then ready to be shipped anywhere 
in the world. Global demand for natural gas has tripled in the last two 
decades, and the advent of new market opportunities indicates that this 
trend will no doubt continue--and increase America's role in energy 
security for our allies.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Dr. Gosar ">Just last year, the United States became a net exporter of natural 
gas for the first time since the 1950s. The production, liquefaction, 
and shipping of LNG has risen to meet the incredible global demand for 
the product, implicating geopolitics across the globe.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Dr. Gosar ">For instance, Russia has long monopolized gas supply to Europe. 
According to Deputy Secretary of State John McCarrick, 11 European 
countries relied on Russian gas to meet 75 percent of their heating and 
electrical generation needs. The continent is therefore quite exposed 
to supply disruptions, be they intentionally imposed or not. Russia's 
Nord Stream pipeline, which supplies westbound gas from Russia to 
Germany across the Baltic Sea, is approaching its full transmission 
capacity of 55 billion cubic meters. Germany supports the construction 
of an identical pipeline, Nord Stream 2, which effectively doubles 
capacity. If constructed, the highly controversial pipeline would allow 
Russia to supply 75 percent of Europe's natural gas demand. In 2017, 
Cheniere delivered the first shipment of American produced LNG from its 
Sabine Pass export terminal in Louisiana to the Baltic nation of 
Lithuania. Lithuania, like many of its Eastern European neighbors, 
relied exclusively on Russia to meet its energy demands for decades. 
This monumental shipment of LNG indicates that European nations are 
looking to diversify and break the stranglehold of Russian energy 
control.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Dr. Gosar ">Outside of Europe, demand for natural gas is skyrocketing in Asia. 
Last year alone, demand grew 20 percent in China, South Korea, and 
Japan, as these nations continue to grow their economies while limiting 
greenhouse gas emissions. China is on track to more than double its 
natural gas from 38.1 million metric tons today to 82 million metric 
tons by 2030. Meanwhile, India, which currently operates four LNG 
import and regasification facilities, is planning to expand its import 
capacity by 11 terminals. American companies, such as Cheniere Energy, 
Inc., represented by Mr. Christopher Smith today, have signed some of 
the largest long-term supply agreements. Just this month, Cheniere 
signed the first ever long-term LNG supply contract with the Chinese 
National Petroleum Corporation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Dr. Gosar ">With the rise in demand, Australia has stepped up in the Asian 
markets, supplying over 80 percent of China's demand for LNG. As such, 
the United States is now competing for market share with strong local 
suppliers, and therefore, it is essential that we support production, 
LNG export facility permitting, and pipeline capacity here on American 
shores. Today, we will discuss the implications of being a major player 
in an expanding global energy market.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Dr. Gosar ">______</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Dr. Gosar ">Dr. Gosar. I now recognize the Ranking Member.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Dr. Gosar ">    Do you have a statement?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Beyer</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Beyer">Mr. Chair, I would yield to the actual Ranking
Member when he comes later, if that is possible. If not, we 
will put it in the record.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Beyer">Dr. Gosar. That sounds good. We are going to go right to 
our witnesses then.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Beyer">First, we have Mr. Christopher Smith, Senior Vice President 
of Policy, Government, and Public Affairs, Cheniere Energy, 
Incorporated; Mr. Peter Doran, President and CEO of the Center 
for European Policy Analysis; Mr. David Livingston, Deputy 
Director for Climate and Advanced Energy at the Atlantic 
Council; and Ms. Meg Gentle, President and CEO of Tellurian, 
Incorporated.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Beyer">Let me remind the witnesses that, under our Committee 
Rules, they must limit their oral statements to 5 minutes, but 
their entire statement will appear in the record as detailed.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. Beyer">Our microphones are not automatic. For the first 4 minutes, 
you will see the green. Then it will turn to yellow for 1 
minute. When you see it red, summarize and get done.</paragraph>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF CHRISTOPHER SMITH, SENIOR VICE PRESIDENT, POLICY,</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="CHRISTOPHER SMITH">    I will now recognize Mr. Smith for your 5 minutes.
GOVERNMENT, AND PUBLIC AFFAIRS, CHENIERE ENERGY, INC., HOUSTON, 
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Smith</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Smith">Thank you very much. Chairman Gosar, Ranking
Member Lowenthal, and members of the Subcommittee, it is an 
honor to appear before you on behalf of Cheniere Energy, 
Incorporated. I would also like to recognize Representative 
Graves and Gohmert from Louisiana and Texas, where Cheniere 
lives and works.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Smith">Cheniere Energy is a Houston-based energy company that 
provides clean, secure, and affordable U.S. natural gas to the 
world. Over 280 cargos of U.S. LNG from Sabine Pass have been 
delivered to 25 countries and regions since start-up in 
February of 2016.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Smith">Cheniere is a full-service liquefied natural gas company, 
which makes us unique in the U.S. LNG industry. We procure 
North American natural gas, transport that gas through our own 
pipelines or existing pipeline networks, build and operate 
large-scale liquefaction facilities, and offer U.S. LNG to our 
customers either at our facility or delivered to import 
facilities around the world.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Smith">Cheniere's operations create jobs at home and project 
American influence abroad. Cheniere is the first company to 
export LNG from the contiguous United States and is the largest 
U.S. LNG exporting company. Cheniere is investing approximately 
$30 billion in American energy infrastructure and has created 
thousands of direct jobs and tens of thousands of indirect jobs 
across America.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Smith">When all our production capacity that is currently under 
construction is on line in 2020, we will be a top-five global 
LNG supplier.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Smith">Cheniere's investment is having a positive impact on global 
energy markets, providing affordable and reliable natural gas 
to countries around the world to meet their energy needs. U.S. 
natural gas is an attractive alternative for many customers, 
particularly those who are captive to a handful of suppliers, 
making them vulnerable to supply disruptions and, at times, 
geopolitical dynamics.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Smith">Due to the commercial nature of our domestic energy 
industry, U.S. natural gas did not come with a political 
requirement or pressures, helping to depoliticize the 
commodity. As a result, it is making natural gas a more 
economic and more secure fuel for buyers around the world.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Smith">Many countries--developed and developing, traditional LNG 
importers and emerging markets--are also choosing natural gas 
as part of a global shift toward a lower-carbon energy mix that 
favors natural gas over coal and liquid fuels, reducing air 
pollution and carbon emissions. Just as the Shale Revolution 
has allowed the United States to reduce carbon emissions, the 
export of liquefied natural gas makes similar advances possible 
worldwide.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Smith">Cheniere is the largest physical consumer of natural gas in 
the United States, sourcing gas from Texas, Louisiana, 
Arkansas, Pennsylvania, Ohio, West Virginia, Oklahoma, 
Illinois, and Kentucky.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Smith">We have a role in promoting environmental standards that 
will maintain the sustainability of the LNG that we sell. We 
are committed to working with our suppliers to maintain high 
and consistent environmental standards, including working to 
reduce methane leakage.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Smith">Cheniere and the U.S. LNG industry are well-positioned to 
compete in the increasingly competitive global natural gas 
market. Indeed, earlier this month, we executed two long-term 
agreements with the China National Petroleum Corporation. Our 
success in China to date is due to our ability to execute, and 
a value proposition that will be difficult for others to match.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Smith">These are the first direct, long-term LNG supply contracts 
between a Chinese company and a U.S. LNG exporter, a historic 
milestone in energy cooperation between the United States and 
China and a constructive way to address trade imbalances. We 
expect these agreements to support our growth plans and are 
focused on the remaining steps necessary to achieve a final 
investment decision at Train 3 at Corpus Christi in the next 
several months. This will be the first new large-scale LNG 
capacity to progress to construction in the United States since 
2015.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Smith">And we are just getting started. Cheniere plans to lead the 
next wave of American LNG by continuing to make investments in 
American jobs and infrastructure. It is important to note that 
Cheniere's existing LNG platform, over $30 billion, has 
followed a transparent public regulatory process both by the 
Department of Energy and the FERC, where it has considered both 
environmental and economic issues.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Smith">And while we always like to see these processes move along 
faster, our business model does not benefit from cutting 
corners. It is important that these processes are robust enough 
to withstand public scrutiny. If we want to continue to project 
American influence abroad through U.S. LNG exports, we need to 
ensure regulatory certainty for domestic infrastructure and 
that domestic production is safe and environmentally 
sustainable.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Smith">The future growth of U.S. LNG exports will be determined by 
whether projects are able to provide the most attractive 
commercial terms in a fiercely competitive global LNG market. 
In that, Cheniere plans to continue leading the U.S. LNG export 
industry.</paragraph>
    <opening>[The prepared statement of Mr. Smith follows:]</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Thank you, and I look forward to answering your questions 
during the question session.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Prepared Statement of Christopher Smith, Senior Vice President,</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Cheniere Energy, Inc.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Chairman Gosar, Ranking Member Lowenthal, and members of the 
Subcommittee, it is an honor to appear before you on behalf of Cheniere 
Energy, Inc. We appreciate the opportunity to discuss the global 
economic, energy security, and environmental benefits of exporting U.S. 
natural gas. I'd also like to recognize Representatives Graves and 
Gohmert from Louisiana and Texas, where we live and work.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Cheniere Energy is a Houston-based energy company that provides 
clean, secure, and affordable U.S. natural gas to the world. Cheniere 
is a full-service liquefied natural gas (``LNG'') company, which makes 
us unique in the U.S. LNG industry: we procure natural gas from the 
robust North American natural gas market, construct and operate 
pipelines and contract capacity on multiple existing pipelines to 
transport that gas to our facilities, build and operate large-scale 
liquefaction facilities, and offer U.S. LNG to our customers either at 
our facility or delivered to import facilities around the world. 
Cheniere owns and operates the Sabine Pass LNG Terminal in Cameron 
Parish, Louisiana and is constructing additional liquefaction and 
export facilities at the Sabine Pass LNG Terminal and near Corpus 
Christi, Texas. Cheniere has a global presence with offices in Houston, 
Washington, London, Santiago, Singapore, Tokyo, and Beijing.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Cheniere's operations create jobs at home, and project American 
influence abroad. Cheniere is the first company to commercially export 
LNG from the contiguous United States. Cheniere is constructing or 
operating around half of the approximately 10 Bcf per day of LNG export 
capacity under construction in the United States, making Cheniere the 
largest U.S. LNG exporting company.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Cheniere expects to make an approximately $30 billion investment in 
American energy infrastructure. Cheniere has directly created thousands 
of jobs and, from local services to increased domestic energy 
production, tens of thousands of indirect jobs across America. 
Cheniere, with our engineering, procurement and construction (``EPC'') 
contractor Bechtel, sources materials for our facilities from nearly 
1,600 different manufacturers across 46 states. Supporting U.S. energy 
exports and free trade supports U.S. jobs and American manufacturing.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Cheniere's investment is having an impact on global energy markets. 
When all of our production capacity currently under construction is on 
line, which is expected to be by 2020, we are projected to be a top-5 
global LNG supplier alongside longtime industry participants such as 
Shell and Qatar Petroleum.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Cheniere Energy is uniquely committed to U.S. success on both 
energy production and environmental stewardship, as it is that 
combination that supports the long-term growth of U.S. natural gas 
exports. An important part of our business model is the fact that we're 
selling an affordable, reliable, cleaner fuel that customers around the 
world want. Cheniere sells into a global market, and every Cheniere 
customer resides in a country that has committed to reducing emissions 
under the Paris Agreement. LNG is contributing to a global shift toward 
a lower-carbon energy mix that favors natural gas over coal and liquid 
fuels--reducing air pollution and carbon emissions. Many countries--
developed and developing, traditional LNG importers and emerging 
markets--are choosing natural gas as a lower-carbon, affordable and 
reliable option for their energy portfolio.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Cheniere is already the largest physical consumer of natural gas in 
the United States. We are currently consuming approximately 3.2 Bcf/d 
of gas per day, and once our seven trains that are either operating or 
are under construction are in operation, we will be consuming 
approximately 5-6 percent of total U.S. gas production at a level just 
under 6 Bcf/d. This gas consumption, which supplies our export 
facilities, is responsible for many jobs associated with the upstream 
domestic production and transportation of natural gas across the 
country. Cheniere sources gas produced across the country, including 
Texas, Louisiana, Arkansas, Pennsylvania, Ohio, West Virginia, 
Oklahoma, Illinois, and Kentucky. We have also purchased gas produced 
in the Montney basin in Canada.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Our market position domestically and internationally provides us 
with a unique responsibility to promote standards that support the 
value of the LNG that we sell. Methane leakage rates are a critical 
variable in the Greenhouse Gas lifecycle of LNG. We are committed to 
working with our suppliers to maintain high and consistent 
environmental standards, including working to reduce methane leakage as 
well as promoting water conservation and recycling.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Since the start-up of operations in February 2016, over 280 cargoes 
of U.S. LNG from Sabine Pass have been delivered to 25 countries and 
regions. In 2017, cargoes from Sabine Pass were landed all over the 
world, with Mexico, South Korea and China as the top three 
destinations. This is in line with recent trends in the global market, 
reflecting Asia as the most dominant source of LNG demand growth. About 
45 percent of the cargoes from Sabine Pass were delivered to Asian 
markets, 30 percent to Latin America, 15 percent to Europe, and about 
10 percent to Middle East and North Africa. The worldwide distribution 
of destinations from the Sabine Pass LNG Terminal is a result of 
Cheniere's business model and destination free contracts.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Cheniere's liquefaction facilities currently under construction or 
in operation across our two facilities are underpinned by long-term 
contracts with 13 third party customers which represent approximately 
80 percent of their expected aggregate LNG production capacity. Our 
long-term foundation customers--a mix of International Oil Companies 
(``IOC''), National Oil Companies (``NOC''), Trading Houses and end-
users (such as utilities)--purchase LNG at our facilities at a price 
linked to Henry Hub, and can pick it up to deliver to their end market 
or almost anywhere in the world. To date, Cheniere has initiated our 
long-term contracts with Shell/BG of the UK and Holland, Gas Natural 
Fenosa of Spain, and Korea Gas Corporation (``KOGAS'') according to 
their date of first commercial delivery (``DFCD'') under their 
contracts, and will shortly begin long-term supply to GAIL Limited of 
India in March. Cheniere's long-term foundation customers determine the 
final destination of U.S. LNG in accordance with U.S. law and 
regulation, and the multitude of destinations for U.S. LNG highlights 
its importance to the development of an open, transparent and free 
market for global LNG. Cheniere also manages a portfolio of our 
liquefaction capacity, chartering a fleet--currently over 20--of LNG 
carriers to deliver LNG directly to our customers at import facilities 
around the world, directing cargoes based on market prices.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Smith ">The same exports that grow our economy strengthen the global energy 
market, providing affordable and reliable natural gas to countries 
around the world to meet their energy needs. U.S. natural gas is an 
attractive alternative for many consumers, particularly those who are 
captive to a handful of suppliers, making them vulnerable to supply 
disruptions and, at times, geopolitical dynamics. Due to the commercial 
nature of the domestic energy industry, U.S. natural gas does not come 
with political requirements or pressures, helping to depoliticize the 
commodity. U.S. natural gas priced at a linkage to Henry Hub in the 
Gulf Coast--the most transparent and liquid gas price index in the 
world--provides price and supply source diversity to customers, who 
have traditionally purchased LNG based on a price linked to oil, 
helping strengthen competition in natural gas markets and the global 
energy market. U.S. LNG is making the global natural gas trade more 
competitive, more responsive to customer needs and more resilient. As a 
result it is making natural gas a more economic and more secure fuel 
for buyers around the world.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Cheniere and the U.S. LNG industry are well-positioned to compete 
in the increasingly competitive global natural gas market. Destination 
flexible contracts, affordable prices linked to Henry Hub, and 
diversified supply from the robust U.S. natural gas market are key 
factors that will drive the expansion of U.S. export capacity. 
Cheniere's on time and on budget engineering and construction record, 
growing reputation as a reliable operator and ability to leverage first 
mover advantages leading to the most attractive commercial terms are 
key differentiators that will help us continue to lead the U.S. LNG 
industry.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Indeed, Cheniere recently announced three new long-term Sales and 
Purchase Agreements (``SPA''). In January we executed a long-term SPA 
with Trafigura, and earlier this month we executed two long-term SPAs 
with a subsidiary of China National Petroleum Corporation. These CNPC 
transactions in particular demonstrate Cheniere's strategic 
positioning, our ability to execute, and a value proposition that is 
difficult for many to match. We are honored to be involved in this 
historic deal--the first direct, long-term LNG supply contract between 
a Chinese company and a U.S. LNG exporter--a significant milestone in 
energy cooperation between the United States and China. We expect these 
long-term SPAs to support our growth plans and we are focused on the 
remaining steps necessary to make a final investment decision Train 3 
at Corpus Christi in the next several months, which would be the first 
new large-scale LNG capacity to progress to construction in the United 
States since 2015.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. Smith ">The United States is still adjusting from an age of scarcity to an 
age of abundance with respect to energy, and U.S. LNG is showing the 
benefits of that abundance. The export of natural gas from the United 
States as LNG is driving beneficial changes in the global natural gas 
trade--changes that help make the fuel mix of many existing trade 
partners more sustainable, more economic and more secure. It also has 
and is expected to open new trade routes and relationships--extending 
the sphere of U.S. trade influence. To support U.S. LNG exports and 
domestic energy production, it is important for the United States to 
continue to advocate free and open markets, the rule of law and 
contract sanctity, and the importance of low-carbon energy sources. 
This will help ensure the continued growth of U.S. natural gas exports, 
creating jobs and economic benefits to the United States.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Mr. Smith ">______
 Questions Submitted for the Record by Rep. Hice to Christopher Smith,</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. Smith ">SVP, Cheniere Energy</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Question 1. As our export capacity grows, we will increasingly be 
able to compete with Russian companies--such as Gazprom--to supply 
Europe with energy sources. Do you feel that our ability to export LNG 
to the continent reduces Russian leverage in Europe and could improve 
the national security of our European allies?</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="21" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Answer. U.S. natural gas is an attractive alternative for many 
consumers, particularly those who are captive to a handful of 
suppliers, making them vulnerable to supply disruptions and, at times, 
geopolitical dynamics. Due to the commercial nature of the domestic 
energy industry, U.S. natural gas does not come with political 
requirements or pressures, helping to depoliticize the commodity.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="22" speaker="Mr. Smith ">In addition, Europe, like many places around the world, is looking 
for supply diversity, with the understanding that it is a competitive 
price environment. Diversifying energy supplies is one of the primary 
means for ensuring energy security. The flexibility conferred by the 
nature of Cheniere's contracts, global presence, and charted fleet of 
LNG carriers ensure that we have the capacity to supply U.S. natural 
gas to markets looking to diversify their supplies.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="23" speaker="Mr. Smith ">______</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="24" speaker="Mr. Smith ">Dr. Gosar. Thank you, Mr. Smith.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="25" speaker="Mr. Smith ">We are going to go a little out of sequence, go down the 
row and then back to the Ranking Member.</paragraph>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF PETER B. DORAN, PRESIDENT AND CEO, CENTER FOR</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="PETER B. DORAN">So, Mr. Doran, you are now recognized for 5 minutes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="PETER B. DORAN">            EUROPEAN POLICY ANALYSIS, WASHINGTON, DC
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Doran</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Doran">Good afternoon, Mr. Chairman, Ranking Member,
and members of the Committee. I am Peter B. Doran, President 
and CEO of CEPA, the Center for European Policy Analysis. I 
want to thank you for the opportunity to speak with you today. 
It is an honor to give this testimony.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Doran">I would like to submit my written testimony for the record 
and offer a few brief thoughts on my summary of liquid natural 
gas and U.S. geopolitics.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Doran">Mr. Chairman, my organization is a U.S.-based non-profit 
policy institute dedicated to the study of Central Europe. At 
CEPA, we have developed an ongoing effort to inject new 
insight, analysis, and ideas into the current considerations 
over the role of LNG exports and to support America's allies 
and partners overseas.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Doran">Our goal is to make sure that the world has a chance for 
safe, secure, rules-based energy relationships. This is 
especially important in countries like central Europe. The 
timing and scope of this hearing could not be more relevant.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Doran">When we look at the question of LNG and geopolitics, we 
invariably uncover the persistent question of competition from 
Russia. Russia's advocates like to say that Kremlin gas is 
cheaper than American LNG. Based on our research and reporting 
at CEPA, my main message to the Committee is this--there is no 
such thing as cheap Russian gas. More than the cost of a BTU, 
energy relations with Russia impose high political and 
geopolitical costs on countries, customers, and the idea of 
fair play in a marketplace.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Doran">When we survey the horizon, we can be sure that increased 
demand for American LNG is good for domestic production, good 
for our economy, and great for customers who need it. The 
problem is that LNG exporters like the United States face stiff 
competition in Europe from monopolistic suppliers like Russia. 
The Russian government derives immense benefits from placing 
its hidden costs on its consumers, most especially when these 
hidden costs allow the Kremlin to use energy as a weapon or, 
most recently, as a wedge issue between America and Europe.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Doran">More than any other commodity, energy relations bind 
countries together. Russian leaders understand this dynamic. 
They want America's allies to be dependent on Russia's state-
owned companies to fuel their economies and keep their citizens 
warm in winter.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Doran">If ever there was a time for robust American leadership in 
Europe and to increase our own ties that bind us closer to 
allies in partner countries, this is it.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Doran">The problem is that, right now, Russia is ahead of us. I am 
speaking, of course, of Russia's Nord Stream pipeline to 
Germany. A sizable addition to this pipeline, Nord Stream 2, is 
proposed, and if it is ever completed, the unwanted costs that 
Russia imposes on its European customers, our allies, will be 
substantial.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Doran">This Committee should have no doubt, Russia's Nord Stream 2 
pipeline is not a straightforward commercial venture to link 
Germany to Russian gas fields. Instead, Nord Stream 2 has 
larger strategic purposes: to undercut the EU's energy supply 
security, to close large parts of Europe to gas-on-gas 
competition, and to isolate and damage America's strategic 
partner Ukraine. We should take this challenge very seriously.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Doran">Mr. Chairman, I would suggest to the Committee that the 
solution to this geopolitical challenge has three parts, and 
America plays an essential role in each. First, American and 
other LNG exporters are helping to protect vulnerable consumers 
against monopolistic business practices by the Kremlin. Second, 
energy connectivity is happening, linking our upstream in 
America with downstream consumers. This is a process, and the 
job is not yet done.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Doran">A third part of this solution is in the policy realm. Give 
Congress a round of applause for the work it has done in 
actually providing the Administration the tools that it needs 
to help support the allies we have in Europe. I would 
especially note the provisions in existing legislation to 
encourage the State Department to work closely with Ukraine. 
Ukraine could suffer tremendously if Nord Stream 2 is 
constructed.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Doran">Looking ahead, my final message to the Committee is this: 
the contest over the future of Nord Stream 2 is likely to 
intensify in 2018, and its consequences could reverberate for 
years to come. I have included a menu of recommendations for 
the Committee to consider in my written testimony, and I am 
happy to take questions from Members.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Doran">But I would highlight this message to you: U.S. leadership 
is crucial in helping to protect our allies and partner 
countries from monopolistic business practices by the Kremlin. 
Its geopolitical interests are at odds with ours. Let's not let 
Vladimir Putin win. Let's disappoint him.</paragraph>
    <opening>[The prepared statement of Mr. Doran follows:]</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
  Prepared Statement of Peter B. Doran, President and CEO, Center for</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Doran ">European Policy Analysis</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Good afternoon, Mr. Chairman, Ranking Member, and members of the 
Committee. I am Peter B. Doran, President and CEO at the Center for 
European Policy Analysis (CEPA). I want to thank you for inviting me 
here today. It is an honor and a privilege to give this testimony. I 
would like to submit my written testimony for the record and offer a 
summary of my thoughts on ``Liquefied Natural Gas and U.S. 
Geopolitics.''</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Mr. Chairman, my organization is a U.S.-based non-profit policy 
institute dedicated to the study of Central Europe. At CEPA, we have 
developed an ongoing effort to inject new insight, analysis, and ideas 
into current considerations over the role U.S. energy exports (such as 
LNG), and to support the efforts of America's allies and partner 
countries to establish an energy future that is safe, secure and based 
on the rules of the market. The timing and scope of this hearing could 
not be more relevant.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Based on our research and reporting at CEPA, my main message to the 
Committee is this:</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Doran ">There is no such thing as ``cheap'' Russian gas. More than the cost 
of a Btu (British thermal unit), energy relations with Russia impose 
high political and geopolitical costs on countries, customers, and the 
idea of fair play in a marketplace. The Russian government derives 
immense benefit from placing these hidden costs on its customers, most 
especially when they allow the Kremlin to use energy as a weapon--or 
most recently--as a wedge issue between America and Europe.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Doran ">More than practically any other commodity, energy relations bind 
countries together. Russian leaders understand this dynamic. They want 
America's allies to be dependent on Russia's state-owned energy 
companies to fuel their economies and keep their citizens warm in 
winter. In order to do so, Russia seeks to limit--where possible--
outside energy competition in Europe. This is Russia's aim--and we 
should not let the Kremlin win.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Doran ">If ever there was a time for robust American leadership in Europe--
and to increase our own ties that bind us closer to allies and partner 
countries--this is it. The problem is that, for now, Russia is ahead of 
us.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Doran ">For the first time since the 2008 Russia-Ukraine Gas Crisis, 
America's allies in Europe face a return to the dangers of widespread, 
long-term energy dependence on Russia. During the previous crisis in 
2008, the Russian government demonstrated its `winner-take-all' 
approach to energy deals when it abruptly halted winter natural gas 
shipments to tens of millions of consumers extending from the Ukrainian 
border all the way to the Eastern Balkans. The Kremlin had turned 
energy into a political weapon.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Doran ">What followed in the wake of this crisis was a groundbreaking 
response from the EU to construct a new network of regulatory and legal 
fortifications against monopolistic energy suppliers. This effort was 
historic in nature and broad in scope, and in many ways important. 
Only, these steps were just a set-back for monopolistic energy 
suppliers--not a knock-out. In Russia's case, the Kremlin's state-owned 
energy sector has now offered a response: the Nord Stream 2 (NS2) 
pipeline.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Doran ">This Committee should have no doubt: Russia's NS2 project is not a 
straight-forward commercial venture to link Germany with Russian gas 
fields.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Instead, NS2 has a larger strategic purpose: to undercut the EU's 
energy supply security, to close large parts of Europe to gas-on-gas 
competition, and to isolate and damage America's strategic partner: 
Ukraine. These outcomes present a mid- to long-term danger to American 
interests, yes. But they are a far more existential challenge to the 
immediate national interests of our allies and partner countries in 
Europe. We should take this challenge very seriously.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Mr. Chairman, I would suggest to the Committee that the solution to 
this geopolitical challenge has three parts--and America plays an 
essential role in each.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Doran ">First, we should view America's capacity to export LNG to the world 
as more than just an economic boon at home. This capacity offers 
profound strategic benefits to America. As members of the Committee are 
aware, over the last two decades the North American shale revolution 
has positioned the United States to bring ever-increasing levels of LNG 
(and crude oil) onto the global energy market. It is exceptionally 
beneficial to our allies and partner countries in Asia, Europe and 
elsewhere. In some cases, our energy shipments are helping to diversify 
allies away from sole-source dependence on Russia. This has been a 
long-standing aim of U.S. foreign policy. And we are only now beginning 
to achieve it. Together with supplies from the Middle East and other 
regions, Americans can take pride in the fact that we are helping to 
protect vulnerable consumers beyond our shores; and to increase their 
leverage in energy negotiations with Moscow. These are great outcomes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Second, energy interconnectivity is happening. There was a time 
when individual markets in Europe were cut off from America, isolated 
from their neighbors, and largely dependent on a single pipe(s) from 
Russia. That's changing. Today we are seeing how new infrastructure is 
beginning to redraw the energy map of Europe. This change is beginning 
to give consumers options. On the U.S. side, facilities like the Sabine 
Pass LNG terminal (and others) give our companies the ability to reach 
new export markets abroad. Meanwhile in the Central-East European (CEE) 
region--a region that previously enjoyed few alternatives to Russia--we 
have seen the construction of coastal LNG terminals in Swinousjscie 
(Poland) and Klaipeda (Lithuania); as well as well as the realization 
of necessary interconnectors across borders. The overall result is 
positive. These interconnectors represent a major step toward achieving 
the goal of encouraging market forces to match supply with demand in 
the CEE natural gas sector, but the job is far from done. 
Interconnectivity is a crucial precondition. The main question of 
getting non-Russian gas to vulnerable consumers is still unresolved for 
some land-locked countries. Major infrastructure development is still 
an unfinished business.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Doran ">A third part of the solution exists in the policy realm. Congress 
should be commended for doing its part. I would highlight for the 
Committee the importance of the ``Countering Russian Influence in 
Europe and Eurasia Act of 2017,'' and applaud the provisions directing 
the Department of State to work with the government of Ukraine to 
increase that country's energy security. The Administration deserves 
equal recognition. When Sec. Rex Tillerson declared America's 
opposition to NS2 in Warsaw last month, his statement was welcomed by 
many allies from the Baltic to the Black Seas. For years, Europeans 
asked America to lead from the front. Now we are--and we are not alone. 
We have allies in Europe who support us. Sec. Tillerson was correct 
when he stressed in Warsaw how America's opposition to NS2 was based on 
our mutual strategic interests with Europe. NS2 is a threat to 
everyone. And thanks to Congress, the executive branch has an arsenal 
of new tools to counter the spread of the Kremlin's malign influence in 
the energy space. If deployed carefully, judiciously, and in the right 
sequence then the Administration's expanded armory of policy tools--
including sanctions--may have a beneficial effect in halting the spread 
of Russia's malign influence across Europe. It is a robust toolkit 
that, as a citizen, I would like to see fully employed in support of 
our allies and partner countries.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Now, if this assessment seems positive--and indeed there is a lot 
of good news here--I would add a note of caution for the Committee: be 
wary of the next phase in the fight over NS2.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Mr. Doran ">This is my second message to the Committee: The contest over the 
future of NS2 is likely to intensify in 2018; and its consequences 
could reverberate for many years to come.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. Doran ">As stated earlier, the NS2 pipeline is not a purely commercial 
venture. This project serves the Kremlin's geopolitical aims. These are 
in direct conflict with our own.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Ultimately, NS2 is intended to shut down gas-on-gas competition in 
Europe--and to isolate America's strategic partner: Ukraine. NS2 is a 
direct challenge to America's win-win approach to our relations with 
European allies. By contrast, Russia sees its interests in NS2 in terms 
of win-lose--and the Kremlin wants us to lose. Let's disappoint 
Vladimir Putin.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="21" speaker="Mr. Doran ">In the commercial realm, we want Europe to enjoy the benefits of 
gas-on-gas competition, where supply and demand determine prices--not 
international politics. As a threat to gas-on-gas competition, Russia's 
NS2 will be bad for European consumers. Moreover, the pipeline will 
make entire countries and regions inside the EU more vulnerable to the 
use of energy as a weapon. In the past, Russia has repeatedly used 
energy as a weapon against its neighbors. There is good reason to 
believe that it could do so in the future. It is why the establishment 
of enduring, market-based alternatives to Russia are firmly in line 
with U.S. national interests; and the interests of everyday Europeans.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="22" speaker="Mr. Doran ">A second area where our energy interests conflict with Russia is 
over the future of Ukraine. Here too, Russia's NS2 pipeline serves a 
geopolitical purpose--one that runs counter to our own. By completing 
NS2, Russia will be able to deny Ukraine between $2-3 billion a year in 
gas transit revenue. Moscow seeks to isolate Ukraine in the energy 
space and pressure it financially. The Russian government does not want 
Ukraine's Western-orientated policies and reforms to succeed. Once 
again, we want the opposite.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="23" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Ukrainians have already showed the world that they seek a Western 
future for their country. The United States wants Ukraine's success to 
be a resounding refutation of Vladimir Putin's authoritarian model. And 
unlike Putin, America has a very clear and compelling interest to see 
that Ukraine succeeds.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="24" speaker="Mr. Doran ">If Russia's NS2 gambit is ever going to be completed, then its 
owners will need to pull off a series of financial, regulatory, and 
legal victories. In terms of finance, it appears that the pipeline's 
backers will not be able to bear the full cost of NS2 out of Russia's 
coffers. The pipeline will therefore need outside lenders to assist 
with financing. On the regulatory front, NS2 must receive a series of 
approvals at the national and European levels in order to proceed. A 
final `green light' from Germany--for example--would almost certainly 
pit Berlin against other European capitals who feel they would be 
negatively impacted by NS2. Diplomatic cooperation and multilateral 
communication between the United States and European allies will be 
essential on this front, particularly if disagreement over the pipeline 
between EU Member States sets up a third battle in the EU court system. 
Even if Russia loses its NS2 gambit in the political or legal realm, it 
will gain by creating ruptures between its presumed competitors in the 
West. This makes energy deliberations in Europe a national security 
priority for the United States.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="25" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Mr. Chairman, these questions are front and center for my 
organization, CEPA, and like you, we will be watching such developments 
closely.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="26" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Looking ahead into 2018, the potential challenges may seem great--
but so are the opportunities. We should never doubt that America's new 
energy abundance grants us a tremendous economic benefit at home and a 
strategic advantage abroad. When we consider risks on the horizon, 
Europe should be at the forefront of our attention. If members of this 
Committee, leaders in the Administration, the private sector, and the 
expert community are going to defeat Russia's attack on long-term 
energy security in Europe (via NS2), then allies on both sides of the 
Atlantic will need to apply the right combination of commercial, 
diplomatic, and legal mechanisms to stop NS2. The stakes for Europe are 
tremendously high--and the clock is ticking.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="27" speaker="Mr. Doran ">For the recommendations that follow, CEPA has developed a package 
of ideas to address different dimensions of the energy and geopolitical 
problem--set in Europe--and how America might play a beneficial role.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="28" speaker="Mr. Doran ">I present them to the Committee for consideration.
Recommendations</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="29" speaker="Mr. Doran ">When it comes to NS2, European law is on our side--let's encourage 
Member States to use it. Congress and the Administration should 
encourage EU Member States to mobilize their clear and vocal support in 
Brussels for the full and uniform implementation of the EU's 2009 Gas 
Directive. They should make it abundantly clear: EU law applies to 
everyone uniformly--Russia does not get its own special exemptions. 
Full and uniform implementation of the 2009 Gas Directive could halt 
NS2 in its tracks.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="30" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Leverage our soft power to the hilt. The Administration can ramp up 
its diplomatic engagement in countries like Croatia, where Russia wants 
to prevent a new LNG facility from being constructed on Krk Island. 
Croatia needs to know: it does not stand alone, but with the United 
States. Its LNG project serves a strategic purpose in Europe. When 
completed, Krk Island would open up non-Russian gas alternatives to 
consumers across Southeast and Central Europe.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="31" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Make energy security part of Ukraine's success story. Fair 
competition and market liberalization are just as important for 
Ukraine's energy sector as they are for the EU. Ukraine stands to gain 
as much--and more--from a diversification of its energy imports. 
Finding ways to prioritize U.S. exports of energy to Ukraine will 
benefit our own economy and strengthen our foreign policy position east 
of NATO.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="32" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Energy is a front in Russia's information war against the West--
let's defend that front. CEPA research has shown how outlets of Russian 
propaganda are conducting a comprehensive disinformation campaign to 
manipulate the energy vulnerabilities of allies like the Baltic states. 
Its narratives are calibrated to divide U.S. allies against each other, 
while spreading the false impression that the EU does not support 
energy independence from Russia in the Baltics. When crafting America's 
all-of-government approach to counter-propaganda, addressing energy 
disinfo should be a priority.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="33" speaker="Mr. Doran ">______</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="34" speaker="Mr. Doran ">Dr. Gosar. Thank you, Mr. Doran.</paragraph>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF DAVID LIVINGSTON, DEPUTY DIRECTOR FOR CLIMATE AND</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="DAVID LIVINGSTON">Mr. Livingston, you are now up for 5 minutes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="DAVID LIVINGSTON">       ADVANCED ENERGY, ATLANTIC COUNCIL, WASHINGTON, DC
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Livingston</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Livingston">Chairman Gosar, Ranking Member Lowenthal,
and distinguished members of the Subcommittee, thank you for 
the opportunity to appear before you and to present additional 
perspectives on the matters being discussed today.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Livingston">My name is David Livingston, and I serve as Deputy Director 
for Climate and Advanced Energy in the Global Energy Center of 
the Atlantic Council. The Atlantic Council is a non-partisan, 
non-profit organization headquartered in Washington, DC.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Livingston">My remarks and written testimony were prepared in 
accordance with the Atlantic Council policy on intellectual 
independence. These remarks are my own, and the Atlantic 
Council and its donors do not determine, nor do they 
necessarily endorse or advocate for, any of my views.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Livingston">Given that the topic of LNG's role in U.S. geopolitics has 
been well-covered and will continue to be well-covered by the 
other witnesses, I plan to address the role of climate 
leadership and advanced energy technologies in further 
advancing global gas markets and U.S. national security.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Livingston">To begin with, the United States should embrace rather than 
retreat from the broader trend shaping the global energy market 
in an increasingly climate-conscious world. A number of 
countries, including China, specifically identify natural gas 
as a greenhouse gas emissions reduction strategy to meet their 
Paris climate commitments. And many others, from Latin America 
to Southeast Asia, clearly have a compelling need for LNG to 
meet their decarbonization goals.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Livingston">When the unambiguous clean air benefits of natural gas over 
coal are taken into account, its appeal for countries grappling 
with harmful smog and air pollution is all the more clear.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Livingston">How might the United States, then, best capitalize on these 
opportunities? I would suggest that the United States should 
embrace an international climate change framework that is 
flexible, fair, and that grows markets for gas, renewables, and 
other advanced energy technologies in which the United States 
has natural advantages.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Livingston">This framework exists. It is the Paris Agreement, 
formalized in 2015 but many years in the making by American 
diplomats.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Livingston">Indeed, I would note the recent words of George David 
Banks, a climate and energy adviser who served in both the 
George W. Bush and, more recently, the Trump administration, 
``The Paris agreement is a good Republican agreement. It's 
everything the Bush administration wanted. . . . It's a climate 
policy based on U.S. national interest that the Bush team 
started and the Obama team kept.. . . The climate agenda is not 
going to go away anytime soon, and if you're not engaged 
aggressively, actively, there are going to be policies that are 
detrimental to the United States.''</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Livingston">I agree with this assessment and will briefly outline a few 
ways in which the lack of U.S. climate leadership might be 
detrimental to U.S. economic and national security interests.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Livingston">Given that if it were to leave the Paris Agreement the 
United States would be the only country in the world outside of 
it, this would leave significant scope for future evolutions of 
the international climate governance architecture, over which 
the United States would have no say but by which it would 
inevitably be impacted.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Livingston">In the 1960s, the United States accounted for 40 percent of 
global GDP. Today, it accounts for just over 20 percent. In 
other words, the United States, as an isolated climate policy 
island, is not insulated from the rising tide of agreements and 
economic architectures forged by the rest of the world.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Livingston">For example, some foreign officials and politicians have 
floated the idea of tariffs or even sanctions being applied to 
the United States should it unilaterally withdraw from the 
Paris Agreement.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Livingston">With the opening of China's national carbon market this 
year, a growing share of the global economy is under a formal 
carbon price, increasing the dangers of tariffs or other 
measures being levied against jurisdictions without formal 
carbon pricing.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. Livingston">The most punitive of these prospects would likely never 
occur. Others are distant but plausible. But some are already 
evident. The European Union is now refusing to complete a new 
trade agreement with any partner that has not only joined but 
also officially ratified the Paris Agreement. To take another 
angle, imagine if countries were to halt LNG imports from 
countries that have not ratified the Paris Agreement, just as 
today the United States provides preferential LNG export 
approval to countries which have a free trade agreement with 
the United States.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Mr. Livingston">Equally, if not more, critical to the long-term 
geopolitical interests of the United States is that this 
country does not abandon its superlative strengths in 
innovation and advanced energy technologies. Global renewables 
deployment has gone from less than $20 billion per year a 
decade ago to now enjoying the eighth consecutive year in which 
investment has been between $250 billion and $350 billion.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. Livingston">But, today, as the United States mulls dramatic budget cuts 
to its leading energy innovation programs, other actors such as 
China are stepping in to fill the gap. China recognizes not 
only the domestic benefits of advanced energy, from clean air 
to reduced energy imports, but also the geopolitical 
opportunities. In emerging sectors, such as batteries and 
electric vehicles, it seeks to shape markets early on, setting 
key standards, locking in certain technology pathways, and 
locking out innovations from smaller countries with its 
economies of scale.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. Livingston">In conclusion, the opportunities afforded by growing LNG 
exports, while plentiful, should not distract from other 
critical priorities, including shaping global climate action 
and ensuring that innovation drives America's energy edge well 
into the future.</paragraph>
    <opening>[The prepared statement of Mr. Livingston follows:]</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Thank you for the opportunity to provide my thoughts on 
U.S. energy and geopolitics, and I look forward to taking your 
questions.
 Prepared Statement of David Livingston, Deputy Director for Climate &amp;</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Advanced Energy, Atlantic Council</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Chairman Gosar, Ranking Member Lowenthal, and distinguished members 
of the Subcommittee, thank you for the opportunity to appear before you 
and to present additional perspectives on the matters being discussed 
today.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">My name is David Livingston and I serve as deputy director for 
climate and advanced energy in the Global Energy Center of the Atlantic 
Council. The Atlantic Council is a non-partisan, non-profit 
organization headquartered in Washington, DC. My remarks and written 
testimony represent my views, and do not necessarily represent the 
views of my colleagues or institution.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">liquefied natural gas and u.s. geopolitics</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">U.S. natural gas production has been booming for nearly a decade, 
while recently U.S. liquefied natural gas (LNG) exports have been 
increasing, as well. There are a number of benefits that accrue to the 
United States from exports of liquefied natural gas and the expansion 
of domestic natural gas production needed to support them. Increased 
LNG exports can help to narrow the U.S. current account deficit, expand 
economic activity and employment in the natural gas extraction, 
processing, and related industries, and aid broader American foreign 
policy goals insofar as they contribute to a diverse, sustainable, and 
affordable energy mix in recipient markets. As such, increased LNG 
exports would indeed appear to strengthen the U.S. position in global 
geopolitics.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Three commonly raised caveats to the aforementioned view are that 
(1) U.S. economic and energy security interests may be better-served by 
keeping most, or all, of this gas at home as inputs into domestic 
activities, (2) local environmental risks could rise alongside 
increasing U.S. production needed to feed exports, particularly U.S. 
shale production, and (3) natural gas may not offer climate benefits, 
either due to high rates of methane leakage associated with its 
production and processing, or due to it ``crowding out'' opportunities 
for lower-carbon sources of energy such as renewables.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">I will briefly address each of these caveats.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">On the first, that the U.S. economy would be better-served by 
curbing exports, there is significant ex-ante analysis, before U.S. LNG 
export growth, and additional empirical evidence, now that LNG export 
growth is underway, that the economic benefits from exporting LNG 
outweigh the gains to energy-intensive manufacturing that might accrue 
if exports were to be curbed.\1\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">\1\ Michael Levi, A Strategy for U.S. Natural Gas Exports, The 
Hamilton Project, Brookings, June 2012.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">On the second concern, environmental risks, it looks increasingly 
likely that local environmental risks are real and possible, but are 
not inevitable and can be avoided through responsible gas production, 
transport, processing, and utilization. However, this is unlikely to 
happen on its own in a uniform manner, and thus responsible regulation 
is both necessary and also serves to reward the most responsible, 
efficient U.S. operators with a competitive advantage.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">On the third concern, interactions with decarbonization, the story 
is more complicated. Switching from coal to natural gas has been a 
major driver of recent greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions reductions in the 
United States. While the pace of coal-to-gas switching can be expected 
to slow in coming years, it will likely continue to be a positive story 
for the United States in providing energy not only with lower GHG 
emissions, but also delivering cleaner air, as well.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">However, more can be done to ensure that gas maintains a clear edge 
over more carbon-intensive resources. The GHG emissions of natural gas, 
as a general rule of thumb, have traditionally been considered to be 40 
percent lower than those of coal and 20 percent lower than those of oil 
on a per-unit of energy basis. However, as a recent report from the 
International Energy Agency has pointed out, the climate profile of gas 
depends upon responsible extraction, transportation, and utilization of 
the gas so as to avoid methane leakage. Methane is a potent greenhouse 
gas (GHG), with a short term radiative forcing (global warming) 
potential that is between 28-36 times more powerful than that of carbon 
dioxide over a 100-year time frame, and around 85 times more powerful 
over a 20-year time frame.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">At current estimated average rates of methane leakage of gas 
production globally (a leakage rate of 1.7 percent of gas produced), 
the total climate impact of natural gas is still less than that of 
coal. However, the variance in methane leakage among different 
individual wells and operators is likely significant, again 
underscoring the importance of responsible regulations in order to 
ensure that American gas is some of the cleanest and most competitive 
in the world.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">According to analysis by the International Energy Agency, producers 
can reduce greenhouse gas emissions by 75 percent simply by improving 
supply chain practices. About half of that can be cut at no net cost--
i.e., they pay for themselves over the long term by monetizing the 
methane that is captured.\2\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">\2\ International Energy Agency, World Energy Outlook 2017, 14 
November 2017.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Moreover, implementing only net negative cost measures could result 
in an equivalent long-term climate benefit as would be achieved by 
immediately shutting all existing coal-fired power plants in China.\3\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">\3\ Energy Institute, Golden age of gas dependent on changing DNA 
of industry, new EI survey reveals, press release, 19 February 2018, 
https://www.energyinst.org/media-relations/media-centre/1735.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">The other decarbonization concern associated with natural gas is 
that it may ``crowd-out'' lower-carbon forms of energy. So far, this 
appears not to be the case in most regions. Under proper market design, 
natural gas can serve as a ``force multiplier'' for renewables that 
enhances the value of renewable energy to the grid by balancing out the 
intermittency of wind and solar.\4\ Eventually, natural gas may also 
find new sources of demand that are consistent with long-term 
decarbonization trajectories, such as in the transport sector or vis-a-
vis a hydrogen-based energy system that draws on existing natural gas 
infrastructure. Natural gas, then, can be a valuable tool in the 
transition to a more advanced energy economy in the United States and 
around the world.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">\4\ NREL, Opportunities for Synergy Between Natural Gas and 
Renewable Energy in the Electric Power and Transportation Sectors, 
Technical Report, NREL/TP-6A50-56324, December 2012.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="21" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Over time, it is possible that new technological advances and cost 
reductions will bring to bear lower-carbon options, such as renewables 
paired with energy storage or demand flexibility services, that compete 
directly with natural gas in some markets. Lithium ion battery costs 
were down to $230 per kilowatt-hour in 2016, compared with almost 
$1,000 per kilowatt-hour in 2010, and McKinsey &amp; Co. projects that 
prices could reach $200 per kilowatt-hour by 2020 and $160 per 
kilowatt-hour or less by 2025.\5\ Storage is already economical for 
many commercial customers, and is increasingly being deployed by 
companies on-site to reduce peak-demand and avoid demand charges.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="22" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">\5\ Paolo D'Aprile, John Newman, and Dickon Pinner, The New 
Economics of Battery Storage, McKinsey &amp; Company, August 2016, https://
www.mckinsey.com/business-functions/sustainability-and-resource-
productivity/our-insights/the-new-economics-of-energy-storage.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="23" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Already, there are signs of faster-than-expected cost decline 
trajectories for utility-scale renewables plus storage, with a recent 
solicitation from Xcel Energy in Colorado resulting in median bids of 
$36 per megawatt-hour for solar-plus-storage, and $21 per megawatt-hour 
for wind-plus-storage. These bids are for projects that would be 
delivered in 2023, and thus represent anticipated, rather than 
realized, cost reductions.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="24" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Nevertheless, over the next 10 years energy storage coupled with 
renewables and demand response may increasingly undercut the economics 
of coal as well as natural gas peaker plants.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="25" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">This dynamic, however, would only seem to underscore the importance 
of focusing on the role of exports. LNG exports can be an important 
outlet for increasing domestic natural gas production as domestic U.S. 
gas demand growth begins to flatten. Over the next 5 years, the United 
States is poised to see a dramatic increase in LNG exports. With most 
outlooks foreseeing less than 6 billion cubic feet per day (Bcf/d) of 
demand growth, but nearly 18 Bcf/d of net supply growth, around 12 Bcf/
d of new gas exports may be realized over the period. Of this, 
somewhere around 3 Bcf/d of the export increase is likely to be sent to 
Mexico via pipeline, while the remainder (8-10 Bcf/d) will be exported 
as LNG.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="26" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">However, the United States is neither the least-cost LNG exporter, 
nor the closest to many key demand markets. In order to sustain and 
grow the global demand necessary to support continued U.S. LNG exports, 
it should support systemic drivers of global gas demand growth, 
including an accelerated transition from coal to gas in emerging 
markets. A number of studies have indicated that the lifecycle 
greenhouse gas emissions of U.S. LNG are lower than that of Russia, and 
as highlighted earlier there are ample opportunities to further reduce 
these lifecycle emissions over time. The United States is better-suited 
to deliver lower-carbon gas than many of its competitors, given both 
numerous homegrown technologies and innovations that help reduce 
emissions, as well as the comparatively more sophisticated 
environmental policy-making apparatus of the United States. The United 
States should not neglect these significant advantages.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="27" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Notably, the Paris Agreement on climate change may represent one of 
the most compelling opportunities to create future gas demand growth. A 
number of countries, including China, specifically identify natural gas 
as a GHG emissions reduction strategy to meet their Paris commitments, 
while others, such as India, do not mention natural gas but clearly 
have a compelling need for additional LNG imports if they are to enjoy 
an affordable, sustained supply of gas needed to wean the country off 
of coal. When the unambiguous clean air benefits of natural gas over 
coal are taken into account, its appeal for countries grappling with 
harmful smog and air pollution is all the more clear.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="28" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Latin America also represents a significant opportunity, and a 
logical nearby market, for U.S. LNG to contribute to decarbonization 
goals. LNG aided Brazil to maintain steady energy supplies during its 
historic drought periods of the mid-2010s, and many countries in the 
region are planning to expand LNG import capacity as part of their 
decarbonization strategies.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="29" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">The United States should embrace, rather than retreat from, the 
broader trends shaping the global energy market in an increasingly 
climate-conscious world. Two additional points are worth making here: 
(1) advanced energy will represent the fastest growing segment of the 
energy market over coming decades and it is imperative that the United 
States play a leadership role; and (2) climate change not only shapes 
the energy market, but is a critical determinant of U.S. national 
security and likewise demands a leading role by the United States.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="30" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">advanced energy, innovation, and u.s. leadership</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="31" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">American hydrocarbon abundance should not obscure the importance of 
focusing strategy on the largest growth opportunities in the global 
energy sphere.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="32" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Global renewables deployment has gone from less than $20 billion 
per year a decade ago to now enjoying the eighth consecutive year in 
which investment has been between $250 billion to $350 billion. The 
global head of the Blackrock Infrastructure Investment Group recently 
stated that renewables represent ``almost 30 percent of the globally 
addressable market in infrastructure. This is no longer niche, it's 
fundamental to any infrastructure allocation.'' \6\ Wood Mackenzie, the 
energy consultancy, forecasts an annualized growth rate of 6 percent 
for wind and 11 percent for solar, compared with half a percent for oil 
and around 2 percent for gas, over the next 20 years.\7\ Last year, 
solar power grew by around 50 percent, with China accounting for 
approximately half of this growth.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="33" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">\6\ CNBC, Cost, not climate, is driving transition to renewables: 
BlackRock's Jim Barry, 23 February 2018, https://www.cnbc.com/2018/02/
23/cost-not-climate-is-driving-transition-to-renewables-blackrocks-jim-
barry.html.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="34" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">\7\ Wood MacKenzie, Could Renewables be the Majors' Next Big 
Thing?, 4 May 2017.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="35" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Whereas Europe and the United States were once dominant players in 
renewable and advanced energy markets--and indeed, U.S. national labs 
played a critical role in the birth of modern photovoltaic solar 
technologies--other actors such as China are now playing a larger and 
larger role as they recognize not only the energy system and commercial 
opportunities of advanced energy, but also the geopolitical 
opportunities to shape markets early on, setting key standards and 
favoring certain technologies that accrue outsized domestic benefits. 
This is further magnified by concerns over energy security in countries 
less-rich in hydrocarbons than the United States.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="36" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Indeed, there may be limits to the heretofore exponential rise in 
China's liquefied natural gas imports. In 2017, China became the 
world's second largest importer of natural gas, after Japan, with an 
average of 5 billion cubic feet per day. China also finds itself 
increasingly dependent on imported oil, which now accounts for around 
two-thirds of its total oil demand. As Chinese concerns over gas and 
oil imports continue to grow, this in turn will drive further support 
for renewables and other advanced energy technologies that can reduce 
energy import reliance. It was widely reported at the beginning of this 
year that the city of Shenzen in China has procured more electric 
busses--17,000--than the number of busses both conventional and 
electric in the five largest North American metropolitan fleets 
combined.\8\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="37" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">\8\ Steve Hanley, Shenzhen Completes Switch To Fully Electric Bus 
Fleet. Electric Taxis Are Next, Clean Technica, 1 January 2018, https:/
/cleantechnica.com/2018/01/01/shenzhen-completes-switch-fully electric-
bus-fleet-electric-taxis-next/.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="38" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">The United States is not yet losing the advanced energy race, and 
still represents a significant market for the deployment of advanced 
energy. Renewables now generate almost as much electricity as the U.S. 
nuclear fleet, and if Texas were a country, it would be the fourth 
largest global producer of wind power. The largest wind farm in the 
free world is being built in Oklahoma.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="39" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">A key question, though, is whether the United States will invest 
in, and support, the historical source of its advanced energy edge--
innovation. Deployment of today's technologies is not enough. From the 
Department of Energy's SunShot Initiative to the ARPA-E innovation 
agency and beyond, investment in advanced energy innovation today will 
continue to underwrite American energy security and competitiveness 
tomorrow. Energy innovation has been, and can continue to be, a 
defining strategic advantage of this country.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="40" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">climate change and u.s. leadership</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="41" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Finally, I would like to highlight the importance of climate change 
to these discussions, not only as an exacerbating factor of the risk 
landscape but also as an area where the abdication of U.S. leadership 
could have deleterious effects on broader U.S. economic and energy 
interests.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="42" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">A historical lens reveals that the recognition of climate change as 
a U.S. national security risk driver is not a new, nor a partisan, 
phenomenon. In 1969, Daniel Patrick Moynihan--then an adviser to 
President Richard Nixon--wrote a memo to the president raising concern 
over the possible ``apocalyptic change'' represented by anthropogenic 
climate disruption, and called it an issue that the ``[Nixon] 
administration ought to get involved with'' and a ``natural for NATO.'' 
\9\ Climate change first appeared in the National Security Strategy in 
1991 as an identified environmental challenge that does not respect 
international boundaries, and has been included in the Worldwide Threat 
Assessment since 2009 and the Quadrennial Defense Review since 2010.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="43" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">\9\ Nixon Library, Memorandum from Daniel Patrick Moynihan, 17 
September 1969, https://www.nixonlibrary.gov/virtuallibrary/releases/
jul10/56.pdf.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="44" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">This is not limited to threats that will draw on the utilization of 
our military assets abroad, but also poses challenges for our 
military's own capabilities and readiness. A Department of Defense 
(DoD) report published in January surveyed 3,500 military sites in the 
United States and found that over half have already experienced 
climate-related challenges. This builds upon a 2009 DoD report which 
found that 128 coastal installations, including 56 naval installations 
valued at over $100 billion, would be at risk if sea level rise of more 
than 1 meter were to occur. Recent projections of end-of-century sea 
level rise under current assumptions range from two-tenths of a meter 
to 2 meters.\10\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="45" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">\10\ NASA, Understanding Sea Level: Empirical Projections, https://
sealevel.nasa.gov/understanding-sea-level/projections/empirical-
projections.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="46" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">How might the United States best deal with these risks? The purpose 
of this hearing is not to contest the most appropriate instrument or 
approach for dealing with the climate challenge, but I would note the 
recent words of George David Banks, a climate and energy advisor who 
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
has served in both the George W. Bush and the Trump administrations:</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="47" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">``The Paris agreement is a good Republican agreement. It's</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="48" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">everything the Bush administration wanted . . . It's a climate</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="49" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">policy based on U.S. national interest that the Bush team</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="50" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">started and the Obama team kept . . . The climate agenda is not</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="51" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">going to go away any time soon, and if you're not engaged</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="52" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">aggressively, actively, there are going to be policies that are</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="53" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">detrimental to the United States.'' \11\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="54" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">\11\ Lisa Friedman, Former Trump Aide Calls Paris Climate Accord `a 
Good Republican Agreement', 22 February 2018, https://www.nytimes.com/
2018/02/22/climate/george-david-banks.html.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="55" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">I tend to agree with this assessment, and will briefly mention a 
number of ways in which lack of U.S. climate leadership may be 
detrimental to U.S. economic and national security interests.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="56" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Given that, if it were to leave the Paris Agreement, the United 
States would be the only country in the world not party to the 
Agreement, this would leave significant scope for future evolutions of 
the international climate governance regime over which the United 
States would have no say but would inevitably be impacted by. In the 
1960s, when awareness of climate change was emerging, the United States 
accounted for 40 percent of global GDP. Today, it accounts for just 
over 20 percent. An isolated United States is not large enough to avoid 
the economic repercussions of agreements forged by the rest of the 
world.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="57" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">For example, a number of foreign officials and politicians have 
floated the idea of tariffs, or even sanctions, being applied to the 
United States should it unilaterally withdraw from the Paris Agreement. 
With the opening of China's national carbon market this year, a growing 
share of the global economy is under a formal carbon price, increasing 
the dangers of tariffs or other measures to be levied against 
jurisdictions without formal carbon pricing. The most punitive of these 
prospects would likely never occur. Some are distant but plausible. 
Others are already evident: the European Union is now refusing to 
complete a new trade agreement with any partner that has not only 
joined, but also officially ratified, the Paris Agreement. To take 
another angle, imagine if countries were to begin prioritizing LNG 
imports from countries that have ratified the Paris Agreement, just as 
the United States today provides preferential LNG export approval to 
countries which have a free trade agreement with the United States.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="58" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">It is also worth noting that even in the absence of a Federal 
carbon price, there exists a complex mosaic of de-facto carbon prices 
across the United States. A wide range of regulations, from methane 
rules to fuel efficiency standards, create compliance costs that equate 
to an implicit price on carbon. For example, the 25 cent increase in 
the Federal gas tax that has recently been debated is the equivalent of 
a transport sector carbon price of around $30 per ton.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="59" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">A growing number of U.S. companies are pricing carbon voluntarily, 
as well. In 2017, almost 1,400 firms were integrating an internal 
carbon price into business decisions, a more than eightfold increase 
from 2013. Most large integrated oil companies now use internal carbon 
prices between $40-$80 per ton.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="60" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">While this patchwork of de-facto carbon prices is better than no 
climate action, it nonetheless suffers from opacity, asymmetry, and--
undoubtedly--inefficiency. A far more efficient and effective approach 
would be an economy-wide carbon price. This would level the playing 
field, encourage the lowest-cost carbon reductions to be harvested 
first, and would give the United States many more policy options for 
defending the competitiveness of its industry vis-a-vis competitors in 
countries both with and without carbon prices. A pragmatic, stable, 
predictable carbon price remains a prudent policy option for the United 
States.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="61" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">conclusion</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="62" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">In conclusion, the United States finds itself at a unique point in 
history in which its endowment of hydrocarbon resources, including 
natural gas, are re-shaping both domestic markets as well as, 
increasingly, the global energy landscape. While the growth of U.S. 
natural gas exports is poised to be a positive development for energy, 
economic, and climate security, this should be complemented by the 
strategies, investments, and policies necessary to ensure that gas 
maintains its relevance and value in the shift to more advanced and 
decarbonized energy systems in the United States and elsewhere. 
Moreover, excitement over the opportunities afforded by growing LNG 
exports should not distract from other critical priorities, including 
ensuring that innovation drives America's energy edge well into the 
future. Thank you for the opportunity to provide my thoughts on U.S. 
energy and geopolitics. I look forward to taking your questions.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="63" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">______</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="64" speaker="Mr. Livingston ">Dr. Gosar. Thank you, Mr. Livingston.</paragraph>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF MEG GENTLE, PRESIDENT AND CEO, TELLURIAN, INC.,</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="MEG GENTLE">Ms. Gentle, you are up next for 5 minutes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="MEG GENTLE">                         HOUSTON, TEXAS
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Ms. Gentle</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Ms. Gentle">Thank you, Mr. Chairman, Ranking Member
Lowenthal, and members of the Subcommittee. It is an honor to 
speak with you today about the role that U.S. liquefied natural 
gas production, exports, and investment plays in powering the 
global leadership of the United States and supporting the 
safety and security of our allies.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Ms. Gentle">I serve as President and CEO of Tellurian, Inc., a 2-year-
old company created to build a global natural gas business with 
the intention of spending nearly $30 billion of investment in 
infrastructure in this country, including manufacturing dollars 
in 18 states, and creation of almost 50,000 direct and indirect 
jobs.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Ms. Gentle">As I speak, we are witnessing change in the global energy 
system unprecedented in its scale and speed. Access to flexibly 
produced LNG allows countries from Eastern Europe, to East and 
South Asia, to our neighbors in our own hemisphere to diversify 
their energy supply, diminish the power of sole-source 
suppliers, and access gas more quickly and at a lower cost. It 
helps countries meet their decarbonization goals, access more 
affordable electricity, and improve their air quality and, 
overall, improve their energy security.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Ms. Gentle">We need your support to build out the infrastructure needed 
to meet domestic and global demand for gas. We can empower our 
friends and deny leverage to hostile powers while growing the 
U.S. economy and employing tens of thousands of Americans 
across our country.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Ms. Gentle">The world is turning inexorably toward LNG. The 
International Energy Agency estimates that LNG will constitute 
60 percent of the total inter-regional trade of gas by 2040, up 
from just 39 percent today. The world has seen a rapid increase 
in LNG importers in recent years, with 10 new importers added 
between 2011 and 2016 alone and a total of 38 countries now 
importing LNG.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Ms. Gentle">Many of these are smaller, emerging importers which seek to 
grow their domestic gas markets for a range of security, public 
health, and climate-related reasons. Our southern neighbors 
Brazil, Chile, and Argentina rely on the spot markets to buy 
gas for base-load power and to back up their renewable energy.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Ms. Gentle">Shorter, more flexible contracts, the steady decline of 
destination clauses, and the rise of floating storage and 
regasification technology has propelled LNG and innovative U.S. 
suppliers like Tellurian forward. The United States has played 
a key role in driving this transition of an LNG market from one 
dominated by a few powerful, inflexible suppliers to a 
commoditized, integrated global gas market.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Ms. Gentle">The management team at Tellurian includes in its ranks the 
first innovators of destination-flexible contracts. This 
feature of U.S. LNG exports has helped bolster the energy 
security of our allies on every continent and disempower 
unfriendly and hostile regimes who would seek to use vital 
energy resources as bargaining chips or outright pressure. In 
Europe, Poland's ability to import LNG forced Russia to cuts 
its export prices before a single molecule had actually been 
imported. Russia had little choice, as Gazprom depends on the 
European market for the bulk of its revenues.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Ms. Gentle">Yet, despite these developments, Russian gas still supplies 
40 percent of all of Europe's supply and exported 8 percent 
more gas to Europe last year. Even now, Russia seeks to expand 
its influence to growing markets in Asia through the $55 
billion Power of Siberia pipeline to China. In 2014, China and 
Russia executed $400 billion in gas supply agreements.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Ms. Gentle">In the Middle East, our allies Kuwait, the United Arab 
Emirates, Israel, Egypt, and Jordan have started importing LNG 
to produce electricity and potable water. The IEA noted in its 
2017 World Energy Outlook that, next to Asia-Pacific, the 
Middle East region will experience the greatest total gas 
demand growth in the coming decades, at approximately 2.2 
percent per annum.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Ms. Gentle">The power sector drives the bulk of this growth. UN data 
shows that our allies in the Middle East power generation from 
burning oil was equivalent to the amount of electricity 
generated by the great state of Ohio.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Ms. Gentle">LNG imports can enhance the electric grids of these nations 
and provide security of supply. Natural gas demand to fuel 
desalinization facilities is also key, as the water-scarce 
region requires more water to support its growing population.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Ms. Gentle">In Asia, hundreds of millions of people remain without 
access to reliably and cleanly produced electricity. An 
analysis produced from a joint CSIS and IEA workshop in May 
2017 noted, ``Asian countries, including India, will continue 
to be the dominant forces globally in terms of demand for 
growth for LNG.'' Among these are Japan and Korea, critical 
U.S. allies, as well as China, which has relied on LNG to 
address grave air quality concerns.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Ms. Gentle">We at Tellurian are up for the challenge of continuing to 
support our allies and worldwide energy security. Tellurian 
stands firm behind supporting expanded access to clean American 
energy, enhancing diversity of supply, ending price 
discrimination and undermining those who practice it, and 
enabling energy transitions to lower carbon fuels throughout 
the world.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Ms. Gentle">Simultaneously, LNG exports will continue to help the 
American people by creating thousands of jobs and fueling 
expansion of the economy while having limited effect on 
domestic natural gas prices given continued increases in shale 
productivity.</paragraph>
    <opening>[The prepared statement of Ms. Gentle follows:]</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">Tellurian plans to invest $29 billion in natural gas and 
LNG infrastructure, but we need additional infrastructure 
across the value chain to ensure American energy remains 
competitive. We ask policy makers to encourage the 
infrastructure investments which will support our industry and 
ultimately our geopolitical goals.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">Prepared Statement of Meg Gentle, President and Chief Executive</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">Officer, Tellurian Inc.
 the geopolitical imperatives of expanded u.s. natural gas production</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">and infrastructure investment</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">Mr. Chairman, Ranking Member Lowenthal and members of the 
Subcommittee, it is an honor to speak with you today about the role 
that U.S. liquefied natural gas (LNG) production, exports and 
investment plays in bolstering the global leadership of the United 
States and the safety and security of our allies.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">Recent years have brought tremendous change across global energy 
markets, including the dramatic expansion of the LNG trade. The U.S. 
shale gas revolution has been a boon for the American people as the 
application of new technologies has opened trillions of cubic feet of 
cleaner-burning natural gas for U.S. consumption.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">Exporting natural gas as LNG continues to benefit the American 
people by creating thousands of jobs and stimulating economic 
expansion. We expect our Driftwood LNG project alone to create at least 
13,000 jobs while supporting manufacturing jobs in 18 U.S. states. U.S. 
LNG exports advance American geopolitical interests and leadership by 
strengthening the energy security of our allies and improving air 
quality through cleaner-burning natural gas. The United States is 
positioned to lead a global energy transformation as countries around 
the globe grapple with an array of energy modernization and climate 
challenges.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">These benefits can only be achieved through a continued partnership 
of all public and private constituents that support American LNG's 
cost-competitiveness. Other nations such as Russia and Qatar continue 
to grow their LNG export capacity, expanding their financial, 
geopolitical, and industrial influence. Timely infrastructure 
investment for pipelines and export facilities will be essential to 
support continued U.S. leadership in the global LNG market. Our team at 
Tellurian can support U.S. geopolitical goals by offering low-cost gas 
supply and flexible terms, but even our plans to invest $29 billion in 
American infrastructure are insufficient to meet this growing 
challenge. With more investment in American energy infrastructure, the 
United States is uniquely positioned to support global energy security 
and air quality through a leadership position in LNG markets for 
decades.
A Changing Market</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">The LNG market is rapidly commoditizing. Traditionally, LNG has 
been traded through rigid, long-term contracts with large volumes at a 
price indexed to oil. Today, LNG is increasingly traded in short-term 
and spot markets, with prices reflecting global supply and demand 
balances. This price transparency has supported natural gas demand 
growth in financially challenged regions and countries, providing 
nations with an environmental and cost-competitive alternative to coal.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">These changes support a new wave of LNG buyers worldwide and create 
an advantage for suppliers who can compete with low-cost supply. The 
development of a spot market enables countries with varying degrees of 
credit worthiness to access LNG supplies without signing long-term 
contracts. The world has seen a rapid increase in LNG importers in 
recent years, with 10 new importers entering the market between 2011 
and 2016 and a total of 38 countries importing LNG at the end of 2017.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">LNG exports from the U.S. lower-48 began from Sabine Pass in 2016, 
with cargoes destined for emerging importers in our own hemisphere, 
such as Brazil, Chile, and Argentina, which rely almost exclusively on 
the spot markets. Some buyers purchase on a seasonal basis based on 
hydroelectric variability, others as a backup for renewables, and still 
others to deal with disruptions in supply. The rise of floating storage 
and regasification units (FSRUs) has made it easier for other countries 
to quickly access low-cost LNG supplies. FSRUs enable gas buyers to 
access LNG supplies within months rather than years while minimizing 
the cost to build infrastructure. By year-end 2017, 40 percent of LNG 
importers used FSRUs, and IHS forecasts that over 50 percent of import 
markets will use FSRU terminals by 2025.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">The United States is uniquely positioned to supply this 
heterogeneous market. With a stable and reliable regulatory 
environment, low-cost gas, skilled labor, and flexible contract terms, 
we can be the preferred supplier to the world. Indeed, Tellurian is 
pioneering a low-cost, flexible and reliable LNG supply model ideal for 
a maturing commoditized market. Customers have the opportunity to 
invest in Driftwood LNG to access gas at cost for approximately $3/
mmBtu on the beach. Tellurian stands at the forefront of the LNG 
revolution, positioned to compete in a rapidly evolving market.
Geopolitical Impacts of the New Market</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">The United States has played a key role in driving this transition 
of an LNG market dominated by a few powerful, inflexible suppliers to a 
commoditized, integrated global gas market. The management team at 
Tellurian includes in its ranks the first innovators of destination-
flexible contracts. This feature of U.S. LNG exports has helped bolster 
the energy security of our allies on every continent and disempower 
unfriendly and hostile regimes which seek to use vital energy resources 
as bargaining chips or outright pressure.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">In Europe, the transformative effect of LNG imports has been 
enormous. The flexible nature of LNG has allowed European buyers 
dependent on a single supplier of pipeline gas to access the same fuel, 
but with a greater diversity of suppliers and sources. By offering a 
wider range of suppliers, LNG introduces price competition. Lithuania, 
hitherto an energy island in Europe, successfully negotiated lower gas 
prices from its traditional gas supplier just by publicly engaging in 
talks with potential LNG suppliers. Lithuanian President Dalia 
Grybauskaite has said the ability to import LNG would put an end to the 
``existential threat'' of relying on one supply source.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">Russia seeks to expand its market share to growing markets in Asia, 
notably through the $55 billion Power of Siberia pipeline to China, a 
$13 billion pipeline to Turkey, and the new Yamal LNG export terminal 
in its far east. In 2014, China and Russia concluded $400 billion in 
gas supply agreements and Russia intends to build additional pipelines 
to serve growing Chinese demand. Low-cost LNG supplies from the United 
States offer gas buyers in Europe, Asia and around the world an 
opportunity to diversify their energy mix.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">U.S. LNG exports can also fuel economic development and help meet 
basic human needs for many of our allies and friends around the world. 
Hundreds of millions of people remain without access to reliable and 
cleanly produced electricity, including nations in the Middle East, 
Asia, Latin America, and Sub Saharan Africa. Even those with access to 
electricity often face severe air pollution, harmful to human health 
and the global environment. Low-cost, clean, and reliable LNG can help 
tackle these issues and improve diplomatic relationships with our 
allies.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">The Middle East, including our allies in the region--Kuwait, the 
UAE, Israel, Egypt, and Jordan--has started importing LNG in the last 8 
years to produce electricity and potable water. The IEA noted in its 
2017 World Energy Outlook that next to Asia-Pacific, the Middle East 
region will experience the greatest total gas demand growth in coming 
decades, consuming an additional 318 bcm in the period to 2040, 
equivalent to a fifth of global growth in that time frame. The power 
sector drives the bulk of this growth; UN data shows that our allies in 
the Middle East burned around 168 TWh of oil to generate electricity, 
equivalent to all the electricity consumed in the great state of Ohio 
in 2016. Natural gas demand to fuel desalination facilities is also a 
key demand driver, as the water-scarce region requires more water to 
support its growing population. Supplying LNG to this dynamic region 
directly supports our allies' energy security and, by extension, our 
military and diplomatic presence.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">The same is true in Asia, where hundreds of millions of people 
remain without access to reliable and cleanly produced electricity. A 
CSIS analysis ``U.S. Natural Gas in the Global Economy,'' produced from 
a joint CSIS-IEA workshop in May 2017, noted ``Asian countries 
including India will continue to be the dominant forces globally in 
terms of demand growth for LNG.'' Among these are Japan and Korea, 
critical U.S. allies in the region that consumed a combined 42 percent 
of global LNG in 2017.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">China has relied on LNG to address grave air quality concerns; in 
this winter alone, China installed gas heaters in 5.54 million 
households in northern China to reduce particulate emissions. The 
environmental impacts were immediate, as residents reported cleaner air 
and blue skies atypical of Chinese winters. However, 426,000 of these 
households reported gas shortages despite record purchases of LNG to 
satisfy this increased demand for cleaner burning fuels. Not 
surprisingly, the IEA estimates that China will account for 40 percent 
of total global natural gas demand growth between now and 2022--but 
China must have ample supply to meet its ambitious coal-to-gas 
switching targets.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">India, similarly, will be the other major driver of global economic 
growth; despite similar air pollution and public health problems as 
those facing China, Bloomberg New Energy Finance notes that in 2016 
India added 16 GW of new coal-fired generation--nearly double the total 
amount of renewable capacity added that year. Natural gas is well-
suited to meet India's energy modernization challenges and bridge the 
gap between its stated climate and pollution goals and its tremendous 
need for more power. Its government has invested accordingly: this 
month, the Indian government announced that its current 4 LNG terminals 
will be augmented by 11 new terminals over the next 7 years as part of 
plans to have natural gas contribute 15 percent of its energy mix by 
2020. Spot LNG supplies will be vital for these new terminals, many of 
which will support India's enormous and growing coastal cities.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="21" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">U.S. exports to Asia can fill the gap and help meet future energy 
demand growth--but natural gas must be cost competitive and widely 
available to compete with coal in this region. If this massive 
continent continues to rely on coal to generate its accelerating power 
demand, these nations will not meet their targets under the Paris 
climate agreement and the global climate consequences could be grave. 
Indeed, the United States is in a historic position to be a world 
leader in reducing pollution and improving air quality around the 
world, saving millions from dying from preventable environmental 
diseases. For many governments facing these public health threats, air 
quality is the driver for a coal-to-gas transition, more than climate 
change alone. One study last year suggested that Sub Saharan Africa 
alone saw over 175,000 preventable deaths in the region due to air 
pollution. Positioning the United States as a leading supplier of a 
fuel resources which could dramatically improve these problems is more 
than just good business--it's good policy. It is the essence of 
``smart'' power, leveraging America's energy abundance help meet basic 
humanitarian needs throughout the world.
Investment in Infrastructure</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="22" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">The prolific U.S. natural gas resource base can support American 
geopolitical, environmental and economic goals, but only through 
sustained investment, initially totaling $170 billion over 5 years in 
U.S. natural gas infrastructure to support expected production growth. 
Earlier this month, the Energy Information Agency (EIA) forecasted that 
natural gas production will reach 80.3 Bcf/d in 2018, establishing a 
new record. We expect natural gas production to grow 20 Bcf/d by 2025 
from five shale basins alone.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="23" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">However, this natural gas is at risk of being stranded or flared 
without additional investment in pipeline and LNG infrastructure. There 
are six U.S. LNG export terminals approved by the Federal Energy 
Regulatory Commission (FERC), under construction, and existing, 
providing over 9 Bcf/d of LNG export capacity. Based on the pace of 
natural gas production, the United States requires 13 Bcf/d of new 
natural gas transportation and export infrastructure to support 
incremental gas output. Indeed, a recent BTU Analytics report noted 
that U.S. gas production growth may be limited to the total capacity 
and utilization of LNG export facilities, suggesting that the United 
States can produce as much LNG as the global gas market can absorb.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="24" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">Typically, LNG infrastructure operates under a long multi-year 
development cycle, where the speed at which decisions are made today 
will impact the ability of the United States to supply low cost gas 5 
years from now. We are far from the only ones with an eye to the 
future. Qatar recently announced that it will increase LNG output by 30 
percent, Australia is moving ahead with new LNG export infrastructure, 
and Russia is planning new liquefaction plants while laying miles of 
pipelines across Eurasia. Perhaps most importantly, our allies want to 
buy our gas. The same CSIS analysis mentioned earlier also notes, 
``Many already well-established LNG import markets in Asia have looked 
toward U.S. LNG for diversification of both supplies and contractual 
terms . . . Asian importers seem to recognize that the value of U.S. 
LNG goes beyond price; it alleviates the region's heavy reliance on the 
Middle East and the Asia-Pacific for LNG and attendant maritime 
chokepoints, such as the Straits of Hormuz and Malacca.'' The United 
States clearly enjoys many advantages, but our valuable supply stands 
at risk of being left behind if we don't build infrastructure now.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="25" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">Tellurian plans to invest $29 billion in natural gas and LNG 
infrastructure, but we need additional infrastructure across the value 
chain to ensure American energy remains competitive on a global basis. 
In addition to laying the literal groundwork for U.S. gas exports, the 
importance of a supportive, efficient policy and regulatory environment 
for natural gas cannot be overstated. The potential is undeniably 
there, but the United States must make deliberate decisions today to 
realize the opportunity before it as we pursue ``energy dominance'' in 
the years to come.
Conclusion</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="26" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">The United States is well positioned to help make the global LNG 
market more competitive by providing low-cost supply on flexible terms 
to buyers everywhere while empowering our friends and allies to have 
greater control over their energy security. Tellurian stands firmly 
behind supporting expanded access to American energy, enhancing 
diversity and security of supply, ending price discrimination and 
undermining those who would practice it, and enabling energy 
transitions to lower carbon fuels throughout the world. To reach this 
goal we must make investments today that will enable our leadership in 
global markets in the years ahead. We encourage policy makers to 
advance the supportive dialogue regarding infrastructure development 
and investments which will help the energy industry play a leading role 
in supporting America's international and geopolitical goals.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="27" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">______
Questions Submitted for the Record by Rep. Lowenthal to Ms. Meg Gentle,</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="28" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">President and CEO of Tellurian, Inc.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="29" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">Question 1. During the hearing, you appeared to indicate that you 
did not believe that anthropogenic emissions are the main driver of 
climate change. Could you please clarify your position on this issue?</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="30" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">Answer. Yes. Humans definitely contribute to climate change. In 
fact, it is our responsibility to reduce and mitigate human emissions, 
and we take that responsibility very seriously in our operations.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="31" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">______</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="32" speaker="Ms. Gentle ">Dr. Gosar. Thank you, Ms. Gentle.</paragraph>
    <opening>STATEMENT OF THE HON. ALAN S. LOWENTHAL, A REPRESENTATIVE INCONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA</opening>
    <paragraph paraId="1" speaker="THE HON. ALAN S. LOWENTHAL">    I now recognize the Ranking Member, who showed up, my 
friend Mr. Lowenthal.
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Lowenthal</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="2" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">Thank you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="3" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">I thank the Chairman for allowing me to give my opening 
statement after the witnesses, and I thank the witnesses for 
putting up with me.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="4" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">    Dr. Gosar. Do I get to question you?
</paragraph>
    <speaker>Mr. Lowenthal</speaker>
    <paragraph paraId="5" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">Yes, you do. You always get the chance to
question. But this should not be counting on my time.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="6" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">The topic of today's hearing is something that would have 
been unthinkable 10 years ago. Back then, U.S. oil and gas 
production was going down, imports were going up, and members 
of this Committee were being urged to immediately open the 
Atlantic Ocean to new drilling because we were in desperate 
need of more natural gas.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="7" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">Today, U.S. natural gas production is at record levels, 
U.S. oil production is near record levels and climbing, and we 
are seeing soaring volumes of exports, not imports.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="8" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">Nearly all of this turnaround happened during President 
Obama's time in office. While the Republicans rarely accept 
this, oil production on Federal lands went up nearly 80 percent 
under President Obama. He signed the law ending the crude oil 
export ban, and his administration approved 24 natural gas 
export licenses.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="9" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">But President Obama had a real all-of-the-above strategy, 
not just fossil fuels. He made the deployment of renewable 
energy a top priority while also acknowledging that all forms 
of energy development have impacts that must be addressed.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="10" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">Summary--natural gas is seen as a very important but as an 
intermediate solution. It is not the long-term solution for our 
energy needs.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="11" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">What is that long-term solution? Well, we have already 
begun to measure it. Wind power in the United States quadrupled 
under President Obama, while solar power grew almost 40-fold. 
When he took office, there were no solar plants on public 
lands. When he left office, 34 had been approved, with a 
potential capacity of nearly 10,000 megawatts.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="12" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">All told, solar and wind generation in the United States 
has nearly quadrupled since 2008, generating almost 20 percent 
of U.S. electricity last year.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="13" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">But we are not doing enough. Global carbon emissions 
continue to rise, and the impacts of climate change have become 
evident. In 2017, it is the third year in a row that every 
single state in the Lower 48 had above-average temperatures.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">President Obama took this very seriously by signing us onto 
the Paris Accord and making meaningful commitments to cut 
emissions. President Trump only has a single agenda--more 
fossil fuels--all in the service of an ill-defined agenda of 
geopolitical bullying which he calls ``energy dominance.'' But 
this is like saying that we are going to achieve 
telecommunications dominance by making ourselves the world 
leader on landline telephones.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">Focusing on the energy of the past and ignoring the impacts 
of climate change is not a formula for being dominant. It will 
simply marginalize us internationally and handicap us 
economically.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">Other countries are already bypassing us in advanced energy 
investments. Last year, a major energy consulting firm dropped 
the United States to third place in the rankings of the most 
attractive countries for renewable energy investment, behind 
China and India. These two countries are now leading the world 
in deploying renewable energy, and both governments are setting 
ambitious renewable energy targets and attracting tremendous 
private-sector investments.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">In January of 2017, China announced that it would invest 
$360 billion in renewable energy by 2020, a move that is 
forecast to create over 13 million jobs and to help reduce 
hazardous air pollution. India has pledged to install 100 
gigawatts of solar and 60 gigawatts of wind by 2022.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">It goes without saying that both nations are party to the 
Paris Accord, because every single nation on Earth is party to 
the Paris Accord--at least, they all will be until President 
Trump makes us the odd country out.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">Developing more renewable energy and increasing investments 
in innovative technology is a win-win for our climate, our 
security, and our economic competitiveness.</paragraph>
    <paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. Lowenthal">I am pleased with this hearing, because we are looking 
today at some of the bigger-picture issues around energy and 
where we are moving toward. But I hope that this means we will 
soon have hearings on climate change and renewable energy in 
this Subcommittee. If we care about geopolitical strength as 
much as we say, we will give climate change the attention it 
rightfully deserves.</paragraph>
    <opening>[The prepared statement of Mr. Lowenthal follows:]</opening>
    <option>Subcommittee on Energy and Mineral Resources</option>
</Hearing>
