<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing>
    <info>&lt;body&gt;&lt;pre&gt;</info>
    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <info>.                    </info>
    <Doc-title>INTERIOR, ENVIRONMENT, AND RELATED   AGENCIES APPROPRIATIONS FOR 2018</Doc-title>
    <option>                     AGENCIES APPROPRIATIONS FOR 2018
_______________________________________________________________________
                                 HEARINGS
                                 BEFORE A
                           SUBCOMMITTEE OF THE
</option>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON APPROPRIATIONS</committee_name>
    <option>                         HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                      ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                              FIRST SESSION
                   ___________________________________
</option>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON INTERIOR, ENVIRONMENT, AND RELATED AGENCIES</subcomittee_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>KEN CALVERT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MICHAEL K. SIMPSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Idaho</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BETTY McCOLLUM</Pname>
        <Plocation> Minnesota</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TOM COLE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oklahoma</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CHELLIE PINGREE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Maine</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DAVID P. JOYCE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DEREK KILMER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Washington</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CHRIS STEWART</Pname>
        <Plocation> Utah</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARCY KAPTUR</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARK E. AMODEI</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nevada</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>EVAN H. JENKINS</Pname>
        <Plocation> West Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>NOTE: Under committee rules</Pname>
        <Plocation> as</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname> ranking minority member of the full committee</Pname>
        <Plocation> are authorized to sit as members of all subcommittees.</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Dave LesStrang</Pname>
        <Plocation> Jason Gray</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Betsy Bina</Pname>
        <Plocation> and Kristin Richmond</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Subcommittee Staff</Pname>
        <Plocation>Subcommittee Staff</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PART 6</Pname>
        <Plocation>PART 6</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Page</Pname>
        <Plocation>Page</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Indian Health Service Budget Oversight </Pname>
        <Plocation>Indian Health Service Budget Oversight </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Hearing...........................................................</Pname>
        <Plocation>Hearing...........................................................</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>High Risk American Indian &amp; Alaska </Pname>
        <Plocation>High Risk American Indian &amp; Alaska </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Native Programs--U.S. Government </Pname>
        <Plocation>Native Programs--U.S. Government </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Accountability Office Oversight Hearing...........................</Pname>
        <Plocation>Accountability Office Oversight Hearing...........................</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>U.S. Forest Service Budget Oversight </Pname>
        <Plocation>U.S. Forest Service Budget Oversight </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Hearing...........................................................</Pname>
        <Plocation>Hearing...........................................................</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Department of the Interior Budget </Pname>
        <Plocation>Department of the Interior Budget </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Oversight Hearing.................................................</Pname>
        <Plocation>Oversight Hearing.................................................</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Environmental Protection Agency Budget </Pname>
        <Plocation>Environmental Protection Agency Budget </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Oversight Hearing.................................................. 385 </Pname>
        <Plocation>Oversight Hearing.................................................. 385 </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Printed for the use of the Committee on Appropriations</Pname>
        <Plocation>Printed for the use of the Committee on Appropriations</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE</Pname>
        <Plocation>U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>WASHINGTON : 2017</Pname>
        <Plocation>WASHINGTON : 2017</Plocation>
    </people>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON APPROPRIATIONS</comitteeM_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>RODNEY P. FRELINGHUYSEN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>HAROLD ROGERS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Kentucky \1\</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>NITA M. LOWEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROBERT B. ADERHOLT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARCY KAPTUR</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>KAY GRANGER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PETER J. VISCLOSKY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Indiana</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MICHAEL K. SIMPSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Idaho</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOSE E. SERRANO</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOHN ABNEY CULBERSON</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROSA L. DeLAURO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Connecticut</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOHN R. CARTER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DAVID E. PRICE</Pname>
        <Plocation> North Carolina</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>KEN CALVERT</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>LUCILLE ROYBAL-ALLARD</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TOM COLE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Oklahoma</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SANFORD D. BISHOP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Georgia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARIO DIAZ-BALART</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BARBARA LEE</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CHARLES W. DENT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>BETTY McCOLLUM</Pname>
        <Plocation> Minnesota</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TOM GRAVES</Pname>
        <Plocation> Georgia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>TIM RYAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>KEVIN YODER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Kansas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>C. A. DUTCH RUPPERSBERGER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Maryland</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEVE WOMACK</Pname>
        <Plocation> Arkansas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DEBBIE WASSERMAN SCHULTZ</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JEFF FORTENBERRY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nebraska</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>HENRY CUELLAR</Pname>
        <Plocation> Texas</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>THOMAS J. ROONEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Florida</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CHELLIE PINGREE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Maine</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CHARLES J. FLEISCHMANN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Tennessee</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MIKE QUIGLEY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Illinois</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JAIME HERRERA BEUTLER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Washington</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DEREK KILMER</Pname>
        <Plocation> Washington</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DAVID P. JOYCE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ohio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MATT CARTWRIGHT</Pname>
        <Plocation> Pennsylvania</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DAVID G. VALADAO</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>GRACE MENG</Pname>
        <Plocation> New York</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ANDY HARRIS</Pname>
        <Plocation> Maryland</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARK POCAN</Pname>
        <Plocation> Wisconsin</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARTHA ROBY</Pname>
        <Plocation> Alabama</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>KATHERINE M. CLARK</Pname>
        <Plocation> Massachusetts</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>MARK E. AMODEI</Pname>
        <Plocation> Nevada</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>PETE AGUILAR</Pname>
        <Plocation> California</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CHRIS STEWART</Pname>
        <Plocation> Utah</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DAVID YOUNG</Pname>
        <Plocation> Iowa</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>EVAN H. JENKINS</Pname>
        <Plocation> West Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>STEVEN M. PALAZZO</Pname>
        <Plocation> Mississippi</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DAN NEWHOUSE</Pname>
        <Plocation> Washington</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>JOHN R. MOOLENAAR</Pname>
        <Plocation> Michigan</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>SCOTT TAYLOR</Pname>
        <Plocation> Virginia</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Nancy Fox</Pname>
        <Plocation> Clerk and Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR</Pname>
        <Plocation> AND RELATED AGENCIES </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>APPROPRIATIONS FOR 2018</Pname>
        <Plocation>APPROPRIATIONS FOR 2018</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Wednesday</Pname>
        <Plocation> 2017.</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>INDIAN HEALTH SERVICE</Pname>
        <Plocation>INDIAN HEALTH SERVICE</Plocation>
    </people>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <option>REAR ADMIRAL CHRIS BUCHANAN, ACTING DIRECTOR, INDIAN HEALTH SERVICE, 
    U.S. DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH AND HUMAN SERVICES
ANN CHURCH, ACTING DIRECTOR, OFFICE OF FINANCE AND ACCOUNTING
CAPTAIN MICHAEL TOEDT, M.D., ACTING CHIEF MEDICAL OFFICER
GARY HARTZ, P.E., DIRECTOR, OFFICE OF ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH AND 
    ENGINEERING
                  Opening Remarks of Chairman Calvert
    Mr. Calvert [presiding]. The committee will come to order.
    Good afternoon, and welcome to th``is oversight hearing of 
the Fiscal Year 2018 budget for the Indian Health Service.
    Funding for Indian Country has been a nonpartisan priority 
of this subcommittee for many years now. Working together, we 
have begun to address the most urgent needs, and we are making 
a difference. Contract support costs are now fully funded 
freeing up funds for operations, affording tribes the capacity 
to run additional programs rather than relying on the Federal 
government to do it for them.
    Funds to meet extraordinary medical costs for victims of 
disasters or catastrophic illness, which used to run out in the 
middle of the year and led to the common refrain in Indian 
Country do not get sick after June, and now finally estimated 
to last the entire year.
    More children are receiving proper dental care. More teens 
are receiving the help and support they need to battle 
substance abuse and suicide. More providers are being recruited 
because we are helping to pay back their student loans. More 
new care facilities are opening their doors each year. The list 
of accomplishments goes on and on, and we are deeply proud of 
our work.
    But we also recognize that we still have a long way to go 
before the health disparities in the American Indian and Alaska 
Native population, compared to the Nation as a whole, become a 
thing of the past. That is why I am disappointed by the fiscal 
year 2018 budget proposal for the Indian Health Service, which 
would cut the Agency's budget by $301 million, or 6 percent 
below the amount we just appropriated for fiscal year 2017.
    The proposal contains none of the increases enacted for 
fiscal year 2017. It contains no additional funds to keep pace 
with tribal and Federal pay costs, medical inflation, and 
population growth in order to maintain current level of 
service. It contains no funds to replace the dilapidated 
staffing quarters, or repay additional student loans, or make 
any extra effort for that matter to save the Agency from low 
recruitment and retention rates.
    For the first time since 2011, when the subcommittee began 
to annually appropriate enough funding to reduce the 
maintenance backlog, the budget request proposes to drive the 
backlog upwards again.
    The average age of Indian Health Service facilities is four 
times the nationwide average. At current spending rates, any 
facility constructed in 2015 will not be replaced for 400 
years. And yet, the budget request proposes to cut the 
construction budget by $18 million.
    Earlier this year, the Government Accountability Office 
added the Indian Health Service to the list of the highest risk 
programs across the Federal government. Whether that addition 
will rally support for IHS or, conversely, sink Agency morale 
and recruitment even further and exacerbate the Agency's 
problems, remains to be seen. But what is clear is this. The 
United States has a moral and legal responsibility to provide 
the highest possible standard of healthcare to American Indians 
and Alaska Natives.
    This responsibility is grounded in the earliest treaties 
between the sovereign and equal nations, and it must not be 
compromised at the expense of lower priorities in the Federal 
budget. Let me be clear. Congress must not balance the budget 
on the backs of American Indians and Alaska Natives.
    With us today from the Indian Health Service to explain the 
budget request and answer questions are Rear Admiral Chris 
Buchanan, Acting Director of the Indian Health Service, Dr. 
Michael Toedt, acting chief medical officer, and Ann Church, 
acting director, Office of Finance and Accounting. Thank you 
for being here today and for your public service to Indian 
Country.
    Before we turn to your opening statement, I will ask our 
distinguished ranking member, Ms. McCollum, for any opening 
remarks.
                    Opening Remarks of Ms. McCollum
    Ms. McCollum. Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman, and 
welcome to those of you who are going to be testifying later. 
As the chairman clearly stated, last week we heard testimony 
from Native American witnesses about the need for adequate 
resources for healthcare services. They gave us their firsthand 
accounts describing their experiences and their challenges 
faced by their communities.
    Native Americans and Alaska Natives suffer some of the 
worst health disparities of all Americans, and live on average 
4.4 years less than anyone else in the U.S., all race 
populations in the United States. Additionally, suicide rates 
are four times higher than the national average, and suicide is 
the second leading cause of death for Native American youth.
    We know that much needs to be done to address these 
problems to improve the lives our Nation's indigenous people. 
Our goal today is to outline and understand the Indian Health 
Service's challenges and to look for ways we can work with you 
to address that. That said, I agree with the chairman, and I am 
personally deeply disappointed in the fiscal year 2018 
President's budget that cuts the Indian Health Service by $300 
million below the 2017 enacted level. Moreover, this reduction 
will significantly compound if the Patient Protection and 
Affordable Care Act is eliminated.
    Multiple tribal leaders expressed concern about this last 
week, knowing that a large portion of the American Indians and 
Alaska Natives could lose coverage, decreasing revenue streams 
upon which the services for the Indian Health Service rely.
    Funding for the Indian Health Service has been an area of 
broad bipartisan cooperation, as you can tell by the chairman's 
comments. And although we have provided increases in the Indian 
Health Service appropriation over the last several years, 
current events in the Great Plains region signal that more 
needs to be done. The continuing problem in the Great Plains 
region are a clear indication that IHS should be focusing its 
efforts on strengthening the organization and recruiting and 
retaining permanent staff.
    The 2017 statement of managers, ``We are very clear about 
our dedication providing access to healthcare for IHS patients 
all across the system. We stated our expectation that the IHS 
should aggressively work down the current health construction 
priority system and examine ways to effectively close the 
service gap.''
    This budget clearly, clearly does the opposite. It is 
reprehensible that the Administration's budget request includes 
$98 million, or 18 percent, reduction for Indian health 
facilities, especially when the average age of federally 
operated IHS facilities is 31 years, with some facilities older 
than 40 years without any repair or renovation. Furthermore, 
this budget does not include an increase provided by this 
Congress in the 2017 budget for things such urban Indian 
healthcare programs, dental, mental health, alcohol, and 
substance abuse.
    This budget also eliminates the Tribal Management Grant 
Program to assist tribes in assuming all or part of the IHS 
program services, functions, or activities, and only includes 
$2 million for accredited emergencies, when $29 million was 
added in 2017. Tragically, these cuts to IHS are just one part 
of President Trump's cruel and reckless budget. His proposal 
rips apart the social safety net with cruel cuts that fall on 
vulnerable children, families, and seniors, including Native 
Americans.
    In a Nation as prosperous as the United States, 
purposefully inflicting harm on vulnerable people is just plain 
immoral. Instead, we should be working together to build a 
stronger America for tribal nations and our Nation as a whole 
by making smart, sustainable investments in infrastructure, 
public schools, healthy environment, and safe streets.
    This should also be our guide in approaching comprehensive 
solutions and holistic approaches to address health, education, 
and the quality of life needs of Native Americans. 
Unfortunately, this proposed Indian Health Service budget falls 
short on the mark. I look forward to working with all of my 
subcommittee colleagues to craft a bill that will appropriately 
fund the IHS.
    We have a moral and legal responsibility to Native 
Americans, and when we fall short, it is just not a violation 
of treaty agreements that we hold with Native Americans, but it 
is a violation of the trust we share.
    Mr. Chairman, I thank you for holding this hearing. I thank 
you for your comments in your opening statement, and I look 
forward to working with you on these important issues, and 
doing our best to build back healthy tribal communities.
    I yield back.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. Thank you, Ms. McCollum, and I 
appreciate your remarks.
    We are going to have a series of votes, so we are going to 
have Admiral Buchanan's testimony, and then we are going to 
recess for a vote. Admiral, you are recognized.
            Opening Remarks of Acting Director RADM Buchanan
    Rear Admiral Buchanan. Thank you. Good afternoon, Mr. 
Chairman, members of the subcommittee. I am Chris Buchanan, the 
acting director for Indian Health Service. Here with me today 
are three of my colleagues, Captain Michael Toedt, chief 
medical officer, Ann Church, the acting director of the Office 
of Finance and Accounting, and Mr. Gary Hartz, director of the 
Office of Environmental Health and Engineering.
    Today I am providing testimony on the President's fiscal 
year 2018 budget request for IHS, which will allow us to 
maintain and address our Agency's mission to raise the 
physical, mental, social, and spiritual health of American 
Indians and Alaska Natives to the highest level.
    IHS is responsible for providing Federal health services to 
approximately 2.2 million Americans and Alaska Natives from 567 
federally-recognized tribes in 36 States through a network of 
662 hospitals, clinics, and health stations. These health 
services are provided directly by IHS, by the tribes, and 
tribal organizations under the authorities of the Indian Self-
Determination Education and Assistance Act. Our budget plays a 
critical role in providing a path to fulfill our commitment to 
ensure a healthier future for American Indian and Alaska Native 
people.
    The fiscal year 2018 President's budget proposes a total 
discretionary budget authority for IHS of $4.7 billion, which 
is $59 million below the fiscal year 2017 annualized continuing 
resolution. The budget reflects the Administration's high 
priority commitment to Indian Country, protecting the direct 
healthcare investments, and reducing IHS' overall program level 
by only .9 percent in the context of an 18 percent reduction 
within the overall HHS discretionary budget.
    In order to prioritize funding for the direct healthcare 
services to our population and newly-constructed joint venture 
healthcare facility scheduled to open in fiscal year 2017, the 
budget includes a reduction to funding levels for facilities, 
infrastructure projects, and management activities of $75 
million below the fiscal year 2017 annualized continuing 
resolution.
    IHS, like all of you, remains committed to addressing the 
behavioral health challenges, including high rates of alcohol, 
substance abuse, mental health disorders, and suicides, in 
American Indians and Native American communities. The budget 
for these services is maintained at the fiscal year 2016 level 
for a total of $288 million.
    The IHS, in partnership with tribes, uses evidence-based 
practices at the local levels to reduce the incidences of 
preventable diseases and improve the health of individuals, 
families, and communities across Indian Country. Programs such 
as public health nursing, health education, and community 
health representatives play an integral role in delivering 
culturally appropriate services.
    The fiscal year 2018 budget assumes $1.2 billion in 
estimated health insurance reimbursements from third-party 
collections. These third-party collections allow IHS and 
tribally managed programs to meet accreditation and compliance 
standards, and expand the provisions of healthcare services by 
funding staff positions, purchasing new equipment, and 
maintaining and improving buildings.
    The budget request includes $20 million to support staffing 
and operating costs for two joint venture construction program 
projects that include the Choctaw Nation Regional Medical 
Clinic in Oklahoma and the Flandreau Health Center in South 
Dakota. In addition, the budget includes funding to support 
three facility projects that include the Alamo Health Center in 
New Mexico, the Rapid City Health Center in South Dakota, and 
the Dilkon Alternative Rural Health Center in Arizona.
    The budget supports self-determination by continuing the 
separate indefinite appropriations account for contract support 
costs, or CSC, through fiscal year 2018, and includes an 
estimated $718 million to fully fund CSC. Maintaining the 
flexible funding authority of an indefinite appropriation 
allows IHS to guarantee full funding of CSC as required by law 
while protecting the Service's funding for the direct service 
tribes.
    Finally, we are working aggressively to address the quality 
care issues at three of our facilities in the Great Plains 
area: Winnebago, Rosebud, and Pine Ridge. The challenges are 
longstanding, especially around recruitment and retention of 
providers. The deficiencies cited in the reports by CMS are 
unacceptable. Providing high quality of care to our IHS 
patients is my priority, and we have intense efforts under way 
right now to correct the problem cited by CMS at these 
hospitals. In November 2016, we launched the Quality Framework, 
an implementation plan to strengthen the quality of care that 
IHS delivers to patients we serve.
    Despite all these challenges, we are firmly committed to 
improving quality safety and access to healthcare for American 
Indians and Alaska Natives in collaboration with the HHS, our 
partners across Indian Country, and the Congress. I appreciate 
all the efforts in helping us provide the best possible 
healthcare services to our people we serve to ensure a 
healthier future for American Indians and Alaska Natives.
    Thank you, and we are happy to answer any questions you may 
have.
    [The statement of Admiral Buchanan follows:]
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you for your testimony, Admiral. We are 
going to recess for probably about a half an hour. We have five 
votes, and we will come back immediately after the last vote.
    We are recessed.
    [Recess.]
    Mr. Calvert. The committee will come to order.
    We have a hard stop at 3:30 today and two hearings to get 
through, so I will try to keep things moving. I ask that 
members consider deferring at least some of their questions for 
the record so we can keep to our schedule today.
    I will start off. Let me see. Which question do I want to 
ask first? [Laughter.]
                          gao high risk report
    Admiral, do you have any concerns about any of the GAO 
recommendations on this high-risk report?
    Admiral Buchanan. I would like to explain some of the 
activities that are related to the GAO risk report. We accept 
those findings from GAO wholeheartedly. There were some that we 
did not agree with, but the majority of those we did, and we 
can provide detailed information related to each specific 
finding going forward.
    The way the GAO identified their reports were basically in 
five different areas related to oversight, Federal activities, 
workforce planning. Some of the things that IHS has been doing 
can be lumped into two big areas as far as quality and PRC 
activities. Quality, we have been implementing the Quality 
Framework as the GAO has recommended. We have identified those 
high-risk areas that we want to focus on, so making----
    Mr. Calvert. Well, since you made that offer to provide the 
subcommittee with information, we would love to have a written 
status update on every IHS related recommendation in the GAO 
High Risk Report. It is important we stay on top of this.
    Admiral Buchanan. Yes, sir.
    [The information follows:]
                          GAO High Risk Report
    IHS takes GAO's recommendations very seriously. IHS plans to focus 
on making audit resolution a key priority in improving the management 
controls of the IHS, and to sustain those improvements. IHS will 
continue to work directly with your staff to provide status updates on 
this topic on an ongoing basis.
    Mr. Calvert. Your 2018 budget proposes no increases for pay 
costs, medical inflation, population growth in an effort just 
to maintain current levels of service. Previous budgets have 
estimated current services costs to be upwards of $200 million. 
What is the estimated increase necessary to maintain current 
services in fiscal year 2018?
    Admiral Buchanan. Great question. I do not have that 
information right in front of me, but I would be happy to 
provide that information to the record.
    [The information follows:]
                      Maintaining Current Services
    Approximately $200 million would cover the costs of medical and 
non-medical inflation, pay, and population growth.
                          MAINTENANCE BACKLOG
    Mr. Calvert. Yeah. Well, you got a tough job, do you not?
    Maintenance backlog. The 2018 budget proposes a $15 million 
decrease in the maintenance budget. For the past 2 years, we 
have provided sufficient maintenance funding to start driving 
the backlog downward again, even if by a little bit. What is 
your estimated size of the maintenance backlog?
    Admiral Buchanan. Thank you for the question. The 
maintenance backlog, as you were referring to, is the 
maintenance and improvement area. And we definitely use the 
maintenance and improvement activities to drive our costs. 
Those usually are offset by third party collections going 
forward. Specific information I would defer to, with your 
permission, Gary Hartz to provide that answer for us.
    Mr. Calvert. Gary.
    Mr. Hartz. Thank you, Mr. Calvert.
    Mr. Calvert. Speak into----
    Mr. Hartz. Thank you, Mr. Calvert. The----
    Mr. Calvert. Please say your name for the record, sir. 
Thank you.
    Mr. Hartz. My name is Gary Hartz. I am the director of 
environmental health and engineering for the Indian Health 
Service, and have served in that position now for a number of 
years.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you.
    Mr. Hartz. Thank you for the question. The backlog of 
essential maintenance alteration and repair currently is right 
at about $515 million.
    Mr. Calvert. Since you are here, will the maintenance 
backlog go up or down at the requested funding level for 2018?
    Mr. Hartz. The industry standards pretty much outline that, 
you know, as you have aging facilities or even new facilities, 
you are looking at about a 3 to 4 percent increase in that 
backlog if not adequately addressed.
    Mr. Calvert. So, if it is not adequately addressed, so the 
backlog will go up.
    Mr. Hartz. That is what the standards pretty much outline, 
and we compare our facilities and our health centers to that of 
the industry of the healthcare industry. The answer is 
affirmative.
    Mr. Calvert. What is the estimated funding level necessary 
to keep driving the backlog downward? You mentioned 3 to 5 
percent. How much money does that equate to?
    Mr. Hartz. That would be the annual amount that I 
mentioned. When you look at what is needed by the National 
Research Council, they say that you should be taking a look at 
your asset inventory value, and that typically should run 
somewhere between 2 to 4 percent of your asset inventory value.
    Mr. Calvert. What number would that be?
    Mr. Hartz. It is a quite large number, sir.
    Mr. Calvert. What is that?
     Voice. Provide it----
    Mr. Calvert. Yeah, if you could provide that for the 
record?
    Mr. Hartz. We will absolutely, 10-4.
    [The information follows:]
                      Estimated Maintenance Costs
    The estimated annual maintenance cost to address the necessary 
repair, preventive maintenance, materials, direct labor and contract 
costs for the IHS/Tribal plant inventory value of $4.81 billion would 
be $100-$200 million.
           2016 FACILITY NEEDS ASSESSMENT REPORT TO CONGRESS
    Mr. Calvert. The 2016 Facility Needs Assessment Report to 
Congress states that at the existing replacement rate, a new 
2016 facility would not be replaced for 400 years. Please 
explain that.
    Mr. Hartz. Sure. Based on an appropriation level, and that 
was submitted in 2016. Based on an appropriation level of $85 
million a year, which is what we received in 2016, we were 
receiving at that point. We actually a got a bump in 2016, but 
when we did the report it was $85 million.
    And if you look at the square footage that the Indian 
Health Service operates within to deliver healthcare for 
American Indians and Alaska Natives, both Federal and tribal 
programs, and you take a look at the cost to build and you run 
the calculations, sir, it comes out to just a little under 400 
years.
    Mr. Calvert. Well, I have a series of questions relating 
the construction backlog. And I do not want to embarrass 
anybody, but we need to get these answers. I am going to submit 
those to you for written response.
    But obviously, with the facilities as old as they are, this 
is a significant problem, along with others. With that, I will 
recognize Ms. McCollum.
                                STAFFING
    Ms. McCollum. Thank you, Mr. Chair. We are tracking the 
same way. You are talking about facilities, and I am going to 
talk about the people who go in the facilities, and let us talk 
about staffing.
    The Trump Administration has directed all agencies to 
submit a long-term workforce reduction plan by June 30th, 2017. 
If you look at the March GAO report of 2016, the report states 
that IHS informed them that the insufficient workforce was the 
biggest impediment to ensuring patients' access to timely 
primary care.
    So, are you finding other agencies that are better able to 
offer salary and benefit packages? Are those agencies 
recruiting your staff? You know, kind of fill us in. What are 
the current number of vacancies in the Indian Health Service, 
and are you having problems with turnover rate?
    I have some other follow-up questions, but just on 
staffing.
    Admiral Buchanan. Thank you for the question. We have a 
staff of around 15,000 people. We have approximately 3,000 
vacancies. We have a vacancy rate of 20 percent. Some of our 
high vacancies include, of course, our healthcare providers for 
sure. Our physicians are at 30 percent.
    Ms. McCollum. We have a physician shortage of 30 percent.
    Admiral Buchanan. Yes, ma'am.
                       RECRUITMENT AND RETENTION
    Ms. McCollum. Compared to the VA and other Federal agencies 
and Federal groups--the DOD offers healthcare, for example--
where are you on the pay scale? Are they competition for you? 
Are you the same?
    Admiral Buchanan. That is a great question. Some of the 
activities we have been doing regarding recruitment and 
retention, as I mentioned in the Quality Framework, is trying 
to get more providers into the system, and we have got some 
creative initiatives going. Some of those that you are 
referencing would relate to the VA. Under Title 38 we have some 
of those same authorities that the VA has.
    Ms. McCollum. Given the fact that you have a 20 percent 
shortage of employees, you have a 30 percent shortage in 
physicians alone, what has been your response as you are 
preparing this June 30th report to the Trump Administration? 
Are you telling the Administration that you do not have 
problems as far as you have too much workforce, but you have 
too little workforce? I do not see how you could be submitting 
a reduction plan to the White House when you have a 20 percent 
shortage, a 30 percent shortage in physicians. What is the 
dialogue between you and the White House on this?
    Admiral Buchanan. That is a great question. You know, this 
budget is a tough budget for sure, truly tough budget going 
forward. We had to make tough decisions on this budget. So, you 
know, we are committed to meeting the mission of the Indian 
Health Service.
    Ms. McCollum. Okay. I do not mean to put you on the spot to 
answer that, but one would hope that the White House is open to 
hearing that not all agencies are the same to do across-the-
board workforce reductions.
                          GAO HIGH RISK REPORT
    The GAO report of 2017 highlighted the adverse effects of 
the inconsistency area office and facility leadership on the 
oversight of facility operations and supervision of personnel. 
That goes to the fact that you have a workforce shortage.
    For example, the Great Plains area, which is an area where 
we are really focused on seeing some radical improvement, you 
were the acting director in 2016. There were four area 
directors between 2011 and 2016 before you came there. Four 
different area directors. Seven chief executive officers at the 
Rosebud Service Agency. Ten executive officers at the Omaha 
Winnebago Hospital. Three executive officers at Pine Ridge 
Service Unit.
    Can you please tell us what you are trying to do, because 
you went in there at a time of crisis, to stabilize the 
leadership, to create an environment where the correct 
decisions can be made in a timely fashion to turn this around? 
And, again, how is the workforce shortage affecting your 
ability to recruit and retain.
    I show this as an example to back up why I was making the 
points before that the Administration has to pay careful 
attention when they are asking for long-term workforce 
reductions, especially as to how it will affect the IHS.
    Admiral Buchanan. Great question, and thank you for that. 
One of the things that we found in the Great Plains, and 
specifically in my time, there was leadership, as you 
mentioned, there was a high turnover going forward. Some of the 
things that we addressed and put into place is the Quality 
Framework, as I mentioned, knowing that we needed 
organizational capacity and accountability going forward.
    And specifically with that priority in the Quality 
Framework is to recruit and retain qualified staff, provide 
accountability, identify quality measures to make sure that we 
are providing it consistently. Some of the items that were 
identified in GAO and some of the CMS findings include strong 
governance. And that is one of the things we put in place for 
accountability and spread that throughout not only the Great 
Plains area, but throughout IHS.
    Ms. McCollum. Well, Mr. Chair, I have lots of other 
questions on third party payments and what happens if the 
Special Diabetes Program does not get authorized, but I will 
submit them for the record.
    Thank you.
                           PATIENT WAIT TIMES
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. Thank you, Ms. McCollum. Real 
quickly before I pass it over to Mr. Cole, does IHS track 
patient wait times like the Veterans Administration does?
    Admiral Buchanan. We do track patient wait times at the 
local level, but we actually have an initiative as related to 
the Quality Framework. That is one of our patient experience 
priorities is wait time measurements.
    Mr. Calvert. How do they compare?
    Admiral Buchanan. I would love to defer that question with 
your permission to Dr. Toedt.
    Mr. Calvert. How do they compare to the VA, Doctor?
    Dr. Toedt. Thank you for the question. So, the Indian 
Health Service, respectfully, we do not consider as one broad 
brush. You know, we have Federal, tribal, and urban clinics. We 
have hospitals. We have health centers. Urban programs 
sometimes do not directly see patients, but rather provide care 
coordination and different levels of access. So, we are not 
identical to the VA and cannot have a direct comparison.
    However, we have been looking at examples from the public 
and private sector, including DOD and the VA, and we are 
approaching this to deliver metrics that make sense for our 
system. One of the ways we are doing that is through a patient 
experience survey. And we are asking our patients if they are 
able to get an appointment when they wanted it. We are also 
asking patients if they have, when they arrive their visit, do 
they have to wait long for their providers.
    Mr. Calvert. In the interest of time, will you get us a 
copy of that survey when it is completed, please?
    Dr. Toedt. Yes, sir.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you.
    [The information follows:]
    Mr. Calvert. Mr. Cole.
                         FY 2018 BUDGET REQUEST
    Mr. Cole. Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman, and I want to 
thank witnesses for being here. I certainly do not have any 
doubt, Admiral, Captain, Ms. Church, about your commitments in 
this area at all, so any remarks I make are certainly not 
addressed to any of you. And, frankly, I do not have any doubt 
about our friend, Secretary Price, either. My friend, the 
chairman, and I actually visited with him.
    I will submit this for the record. I think you already have 
it, though.
    [The information follows:]
    Mr. Cole. We showed him, you know, what our Federal 
expenditures per capita for Native Americans, Medicaid 
recipients, Medicare recipients, and veterans. And as you can 
imagine, I mean, spending on Native American health is at the 
absolute bottom, and not by a little bit, but by a lot. So, 
this is clearly a place, no matter how hard this committee has 
worked, and it has on a bipartisan basis over recent years. We 
have not been able to get anywhere near where we would like to 
be.
    So, a $300 million cut really is not defensible or 
acceptable. And, you know, whether the Administration knows it 
or not, this budget reflects that it does not care very much 
about Indian healthcare.
    So, I think part of the root of our problem here is 
twofold, and the chairman and I have had this discussion. One, 
because this is an old healthcare system, long pre-dating 
Medicare and Medicaid. I mean, most of our medical things are 
taken out of mandatory funding, and this committee, hard as it 
tries, has limited amounts of dollars. And so, you know, one of 
the things we need to look at long term is, frankly, getting 
out of the discretionary business and funding Native American 
healthcare the way everybody else's healthcare is funded.
    And the second thing, if we cannot do that, and, again, the 
chairman and I have visited about this, this is not a very big 
pot of money for this committee. It is about $31 billion, if I 
recall, $30, $31 billion, and with a range of responsibilities.
    At least over at Labor-H, we have got $160 plus billion, at 
least right now. And, you know, it would be a lot easier in 
something that large to honestly make the kind of significant 
strides that I think we need to make here.
    So, I appreciate, and I really do because, again, you guys 
have devoted your life to this. And I admire the service, I 
really do, because I do not think we have given you anywhere 
near the resources to do the job at hand. If we are going to 
redo Indian facilities once every 400 years, that expresses a 
great deal of optimism about the future of the United States 
when we can see that far ahead. [Laughter.]
    But, so I guess that is the silver lining in that 
statement.
    We do have, too, as you know, tremendous variation. This 
committee through the CODEL a number of years ago. I know Mr. 
Simpson was on it, and my good friend, Ms. McCollum was on it, 
and we saw what was really a first world healthcare system that 
the Chickasaws have because they put a lot of their own money 
in it. And then we went to some of these facilities that later 
were listed in the Great Plains. We were at Rosebud, and we 
were at Pine Ridge.
    And so, I mean, the care difference, you know, was just 
dramatic, and the difference was nothing wrong with the people 
in those two places. They just did not have anywhere near the 
resources they needed. And obviously, in the remote locations, 
it is very difficult to get personnel to come and stay there.
    How you administer a system that diverse with that 
different a capability, frankly, at the tribal level is an 
interesting question. But the bottom line is the Chickasaws are 
doing a lot more because they can, but they should not have to. 
This is a treaty obligation.
    I am not a lawyer, but when I look at numbers like this, if 
you could not take the United States government to court, which 
the Indians have done before on contract services, and win, I 
would not be surprised because we certainly have not kept up 
our end of the obligations here.
    So, I do not really have any questions for you because I do 
not think they are fair to put you in that position. And I do 
admire, you know, all of you and your fellows, who I think, 
again, we have let you down. You have not let us down.
    But the Administration needs to take sight of this, and 
they are now in the responsible quarter. And beginning this 
challenge by cutting the available resources, absolutely 
unacceptable. I mean, it will be over my dead body. I am not 
look for efficiencies here.
    But we are going to do everything we can to try and reverse 
these numbers, or I will, and then I think beyond that, we are 
going to just have to find a better way. And I would invite the 
Administration in all seriousness to sit down and let us 
explore that better way, because I do not think this committee, 
no matter how hard it works with the amount of money it has, 
can ever get us to where we need to be.
    So, we need to think of some sort of structural change that 
will put the appropriate amount of resources here. And, you 
know, forcing you guys to come here and either beg for nickels 
and dimes or defend what I think what are indefensible cuts I 
think is not the right way to go. There has got to be a better 
policy solution than we have stumbled onto here.
    And fortunately, this committee has the leadership and the 
will on a bipartisan basis to try and think through those 
issues, and, you know, my commitment is to continue to work on 
this. But, again, the message I would deliver back to the folks 
at OMB, because I suppose who dreamed this up, is I would like 
some of you guys to come to Pine Ridge and to come to Rosebud, 
and go look at some of the conditions that American Indians are 
living in in places like that, and then tell me how you could 
defend this, and I do not think they can.
    This is one of those cases where have got a bunch of number 
crunchers, and that is great. We all need number crunchers. No 
offense, Ms. Church. I did not mean that directed at you 
obviously. [Laughter.]
    But, you know, they just do not have any connection with 
the real world, they really do not, or they would not present a 
budget like this. You do. You are our number cruncher, you 
know. [Laughter.]
    But just, again, I apologize honestly that you were put in 
this situation that you had to come here and defend this 
because I know you would all want a more robust budget, and a 
budget that was adequate to the challenges that you 
legitimately have.
    And this is a population that now lives 4 and a half years 
less than the average American, some places over 20 years less, 
Indian men, white men. I think, in Montana that is the number. 
Higher rates of disease than any other part of our population, 
you know, more challenged in every other way. And to think we 
are going to sit here and cut this is just, I mean, honestly, I 
very much hope Congress does not ever do anything like that.
    I mean, we have got a bad enough record over the course of 
240 years. This committee has done what it can under bipartisan 
leadership in the last few years to try and reverse that, which 
I am very proud of this committee and the members on both sides 
of the aisle, the chairmen we have had on both sides of the 
aisle, two of which are sitting right next to me now. And we 
can do better than this.
    So, I admire your bravery for being here and your 
professionalism. I hold you all in very high esteem. But I can 
tell you, whoever came up with this budget I do not hold in 
high esteem, and will do everything I can to make sure it does 
not stand.
    With that, I will yield back.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you, Mr. Cole. I appreciate it.
    Next, Ms. Pingree.
                            OPIOID EPIDEMIC
    Ms. Pingree. Thank you, Mr. Chair, and I know the chair has 
asked us to limit our questions, and I can submit most of mine 
for the record.
    Frankly, I do not think I can improve on my colleagues here 
today on both sides of the aisle and their huge concerns about 
this budget, and the difficulties under which you have to 
operate. The idea that we would be making cuts to an already 
underserved population is really unthinkable.
    The only thing I will highlight in the mix of things that 
just do not look good in here is no more resources to deal with 
the opioid epidemic. We already know how challenging that is in 
States throughout the country, and it is even more challenging 
in Indian Country. I know that the tribes in my State have told 
us of very long wait times. In the State of Maine, you have to 
go to North Carolina to get inpatient treatment. I mean, that 
is just impossible, and it is very hard to come back if you do 
get to inpatient and then reintegrate into your community and 
try to make sure that you can stay off of opioids.
    I noticed in the budget justification here, which is just 
an unthinkable number, it says that there has been a 454 
percent increase in drug-related deaths since they started 
counting in 1979. That is just an unfathomable number, and 
obviously we should be doing much more here.
    I will submit my questions for the record and add that in 
as, you know, another important consideration, and echo 
everyone's appreciation for the work you do, and hope that we 
can change the numbers in this budget.
    Thank you.
    Mr. Calvert. I thank the gentlelady. Mr. Simpson.
                         FY 2018 BUDGET REQUEST
    Mr. Simpson. Thanks, Mr. Chairman. Since we just got the 
budget yesterday, I have not had a lot of time to go through 
the budget and the justification. I do not know whose book that 
is, but I want one because I want to sit down and be able to 
look at what the justifications for some of these things are.
    And let me tell you, frankly, I could not have said it 
better than my good friend Mr. Cole, so I will not try. But the 
Administration's budget is just in general terms disappointing, 
especially after all the work we have done on this committee 
over the last several years to try to make sure we address 
Indian health services, that we get them the care that they 
need.
    And we have done it, frankly, at great expense for a lot of 
other programs within this budget. You know, the backlog 
maintenance that is growing in a lot of areas, we have said 
that is not as important as Indian healthcare, and a lot of the 
other programs. To see this Administration kind of retreat on 
that is obviously disappointing to us.
    I am not one who believes that just throwing more money at 
something solves the problem. If you have got better ways of 
delivering services to our Native American brothers and 
sisters, I am all for that. But even if you could deliver the 
resources that we currently appropriate in the most efficient 
manner that could possibly be used, we are still way behind. 
Regardless of how we do it, we do need more resources.
    And ultimately the President makes recommendations. That is 
his job. And it is our Constitutional responsibility to do the 
appropriations. And I am sure this committee will look at the 
overall budget and look through the justifications of what has 
been proposed, and will come up with a budget that continues to 
move us forward.
    I feel confident in Chairman Calvert--it is all on his 
back----
    [Laughter.]
    Mr. Simpson [continuing]. That we will move forward in 
advancing, that which we have tried to do for some time. The 
other thing we have discovered over the years as we have looked 
at this, Indian Health Service was our highest priority because 
if you do not have your health, you do not have anything.
    But there are so many other problems in Indian Country, 
whether it is Indian education, whether it is law enforcement 
in Indian Country, we have to address these issues. So, we were 
kind of hoping that we were moving ahead on Indian Health 
Service so that we could also concentrate on Indian education, 
which we did in the last budget.
    We look forward to working with you. And, again, it is not 
a criticism of any of you, not even of the bean counters. I 
mean, I love you, and you do a great job. [Laughter.]
    But we look forward to working with you to try to improve 
healthcare in Indian Country across this country. Thank you.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you, Mr. Simpson. Mr. Kilmer.
                    BACKLOG IN SANITATION FACILITIES
    Mr. Kilmer. Thanks, Mr. Chair, and thanks for being with 
us. We sat through a couple of days of testimony with tribal 
leaders from around the Nation. One of the issues that came up 
a number of times was the significant backlog in sanitation 
facilities. I guess that is part of the reason I was surprised 
to see a proposed cut of 25 percent for construction of 
sanitation facilities. I think the Department has identified a 
backlog of 2,800 projects that would cost a total of $2.8 
billion, primarily dealing with sewer systems and safe drinking 
water.
    I have got one specific question, and I will submit it for 
the record. There is a sewer system in our district, located on 
the Ho Tribe's reservation, that was approved in 2013, and the 
Department only just now issued an RFP. I would like to get 
some understanding of what caused the delay and whether these 
proposed cuts would further delay something that is already 
very long overdue.
                         FY 2018 BUDGET REQUEST
    Mr. Kilmer. In general, do you feel like this budget 
actually makes progress on meeting those needs of a lot of 
tribes who have a lot of very significant needs when it comes 
to safe drinking water and sewage treatment?
    Admiral Buchanan. The budget, again, really a tough, tough 
budget. We have consulted with the tribes. We understand their 
concerns for sure going forward. None of the cuts that were 
identified were easy to make, but you have my commitment to 
continue to move forward on the mission with the Indian Health 
Service.
    Mr. Kilmer. Thanks. In the interest of time, I will yield 
back, but I will submit additional questions about the Ho 
Tribe's project for the record. Thanks.
    Admiral Buchanan. Thank you.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. Mr. Joyce.
    Mr. Joyce. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I understand my 
question was already addressed by Ms. McCollum. But I will echo 
the sentiments of the chairman, Chairman Simpson, and Mr. Cole 
about the need for us to do better for you.
    Thank you.
    Mr. Calvert. I thank the gentleman. I just want to make one 
final comment. This is the beginning of a process. We all 
respect all three of you. You are doing the best you can under 
these circumstances. We will do our best to make some changes 
in this budget proposal obviously and to improve the situation 
in Indian Country. That is our mandate, and that is our intent.
    Ms. McCollum. Mr. Chair?
    Mr. Calvert. Yes, Ms. McCollum.
    Ms. McCollum. Before you close this off, I want to say, the 
chairman and I asked some pretty tough questions, and as you 
said, it is a pretty tough budget. But we have to put them out 
publicly to send a signal to the White House of our 
displeasure. But I think Mr. Cole was right in saying our 
displeasure is not directed at the fine work that you do as 
Federal employees working for the Indian Health Services.
    Thank you, Mr. Chair.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. This concludes our hearing on the 
fiscal year 2018 budget for Indian Health Service. Again, I 
want to thank you all for your testimony today and your efforts 
to lead the Indian Health Service during a time of great change 
and obviously even greater challenges.
    This hearing is now adjourned. We will move right into our 
next hearing with the Government Accountability Office and a 
closer look at tribal programs under our jurisdiction that GAO 
has recently added to the biannual high-risk report.
                                           Wednesday, May 24, 2017.
OVERSIGHT HEARING--HIGH RISK AMERICAN INDIAN AND ALASKA NATIVE PROGRAMS 
                    (EDUCATION, HEALTHCARE, ENERGY)
</option>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <option>MELISSA EMREY-ARRAS, DIRECTOR, EDUCATION, WORKFORCE, AND INCOME 
    SECURITY TEAM, U.S. GOVERNMENT ACCOUNTABILITY OFFICE
KATHLEEN KING, DIRECTOR, HEALTH CARE TEAM, U.S. GOVERNMENT 
    ACCOUNTABILITY OFFICE
FRANK RUSCO, DIRECTOR, NATURAL RESOURCES AND ENVIRONMENT TEAM, U.S. 
    GOVERNMENT ACCOUNTABILITY OFFICE
                  Opening Remarks of Chairman Calvert
    Mr. Calvert [presiding]. Good afternoon, and welcome to 
this oversight hearing on programs within the subcommittee's 
jurisdiction that the Government Accountability Office recently 
added to its list of highest risk programs across the Federal 
government.
    Since 1990, the GAO High Risk List has highlighted those 
government programs most in need of attention from Congress and 
the executive branch. The High Risk List differs from most GAO 
reports because once a program is put on that list, it has to 
earn its way off. Some programs have been on the list since its 
inception, leading some to draw the comparison to the 1977 
Eagles hit Hotel California, where you can check out anytime 
you like, but you can never leave. [Laughter.]
    However, since 1990, 23 other programs have earned their 
way off the list, and so doing that have turned into models of 
how government should work, and saving billions of dollars 
along the way. Today we will talk about three more programs I 
expect to soon follow in those footsteps.
    Since 2011, the GAO has published 14 reports pertaining to 
education, energy, and healthcare programs that serve federally 
recognized Indian tribes and their members. Those reports 
contain 41 recommendations for improvements. Thirty-nine 
recommendations are still open. Failure to implement these 
recommendations has literally put people's health and safety at 
risk, which is precisely why these programs have been added.
    For example, the GAO discovered that the Department of 
Interior has failed to conduct annual health and safety 
inspections and make repairs at many of the 185 elementary and 
secondary schools under its purview. Also, for example, the GAO 
found that the Indian Health Service provides inadequate 
oversight of its hospitals, and is unable to ensure that 
patients receive quality care. At a few locations, the 
situation has gotten so bad that the Centers of Medicare and 
Medicaid Services has cited the hospitals for putting patient 
health and safety in imminent jeopardy.
    This subcommittee has stepped up its efforts in recent 
years to improve the situation in Indian Country, particularly 
in the very areas we hear about today. To some, the addition of 
these programs on the High Risk List may seem like a setback. 
But I see this is an opportunity not only to raise awareness 
and support throughout Congress, but also to challenge this 
subcommittee and the new Administration to provide the 
resources and the oversight to get these programs back on 
track, and the GAO has provided the roadmap to get there.
    Now, some of our colleagues in Congress have argued against 
funding programs with significant management problems. I 
certainly can sympathize, and in some cases even agree. But in 
other cases, management problems are a function of limiting 
funding. We all know that it takes money to hire and retain 
good people. The programs we will hear about today are 
challenged by both poor management and limited funding. Teasing 
these apart so that we can chart a responsible path forward is 
the challenge before us today.
    We are joined today by three members of the GAO leadership 
team who will testify about their important work.
    First up will be Melissa Emrey-Arras, director of Education 
Workforce and Income Security, who will discuss education. 
Next, we will hear from Frank Russo--Rusco I should say--
director of National Resources and Environment, who will 
discuss the BIA energy program. And last, but not least, 
welcome Kathleen King, director of Health Care, to talk about 
the Indian Health Service.
    We will hear opening statements from each of you before 
turning to questions and discussion with members of this 
committee. Before we begin, though, I would like to first ask 
our distinguished ranking minority member, Ms. McCollum for any 
opening remarks she may wish to make.
                    Opening Remarks of Ms. McCollum
    Ms. McCollum. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, and I would like to 
join you in welcoming the panel to the subcommittee this 
afternoon, and fully would like to acknowledge your remarks and 
agree with them.
    It is essential that the Federal government meet its trust 
responsibilities to Native American Indians, and oversight of 
Indian programs is a very important piece to ensuring that 
these commitments are appropriately met. I am very pleased that 
the GAO has been closely investigating the numerous challenges, 
as the chair put it, facing the delivery of healthcare and 
education, especially by the Bureau of Indian Education and the 
Indian Health Services, who we just heard from.
    The management issues and lack of accountability are 
reoccurring themes, and GAO has really helped to document the 
need for reform. This critical need was amplified in February 
when GAO added the Federal management of Indian programs to its 
High Risk List, something that was appropriate and long 
overdue, in my opinion.
    Just last week, this committee held two days of tribal 
public witness hearings. We listened and learned about the 
unthinkable hardships in Indian Country, and we also heard the 
message loud and clear. More work is needed to be done to 
improve healthcare and education services.
    But it is very unfortunate that this Administration has put 
forward a budget that cuts Indian programs. Indian Health 
Service is cut by $300 million, and the Bureau of Indian 
Affairs by $372 million. These cuts, in my opinion, are cruel 
and they are unnecessary, and, if enacted, would jeopardize the 
health and wellness of our Indian brothers and sisters.
    So, today's hearing, Mr. Chair, is very timely, and I think 
the GAO will continue to be an important resource and partner 
as we carry out our oversight role. The findings from your 
investigations that we are going to hear from help both 
agencies that this committee works with, and it will help the 
committee to start fixing broken programs, or should I say 
broken promises. I look forward to discussing the findings 
today.
    Thank you, Mr. Chair, for the courtesy of an opening 
statement.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. We are going to recognize Ms. 
Emrey-Arras. Welcome back to the subcommittee, and thanks again 
for being here today. You are recognized for 5 minutes to give 
your testimony.
                   Opening Remarks of Ms. Emrey-Arras
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. Thank you, Chairman Calvert, Ranking 
Member McCollum, and members of the subcommittee. Thank you for 
inviting me here today to discuss a new area we added to our 
High Risk List this year, improving Federal management programs 
that serve tribes and their members. We added this area to our 
High Risk List this past February in response to serious 
problems in Federal management and oversight of Indian 
education, energy, and healthcare programs, which were 
highlighted in several of our prior reports.
    There are nearly 40 recommendations from these prior 
reports that have not been implemented. Overall, our High Risk 
Program has served to identify and help resolve serious 
weaknesses in areas that involve substantial resources and 
provide critical services to the public.
    In order for this area to be removed from our High Risk 
List, which is our ultimate goal here, Interior and HHS need to 
show improvement on five key elements, and we have a star here 
that demonstrates the five separate areas. Those are leadership 
commitment, having capacity to resolve risk, having an action 
plan, doing monitoring, and demonstrating progress.
    Since this is a new area, it does not have a star created 
yet for it. However, in our next High Risk Report in 2019, we 
will have a star specific to this new area, which will show the 
actual status at that point in time and whether or not any 
progress has been made.
    I will now highlight some of the concerns we have with 
Indian education.
    In our High Risk Report, we identified serious weaknesses 
in BIE's oversight of school spending. For example, in 2014 we 
found that BIE did not have written procedures and risk 
criteria to ensure that schools use Federal funds to educate 
students. Further, we found that BIE staff lacked expertise and 
training to effectively oversee school spending. As a result, 
we found several instances of misused funds, including over $1 
million for one school that was improperly transferred to 
offshore accounts.
    We also identified unsafe school conditions in our High 
Risk Report. Specifically, in 2016, we found that deteriorating 
facilities and equipment contributed to unsafe conditions at 
BIE schools. At one school, we found seven boilers that failed 
inspection because of safety hazards, such as elevated levels 
of carbon monoxide and a natural gas leak. And you can see the 
failed inspection tag there. Though they endangered student 
safety, most of the boilers were not repaired until 8 months 
after the inspection.
    In addition to our prior work, we also have two new reports 
for this subcommittee that are being released today that raise 
new concerns about safety inspections and school construction. 
In terms of safety inspections, we found that no office 
routinely monitors the quality of inspection reports, and we 
found that 28 of 50 inspection reports we looked at were 
incomplete, inaccurate, or unclear.
    For example, we found reports in which inspectors did not 
inspect all of the buildings. In one of the reports we 
reviewed, an inspector noted that he did not inspect a dorm 
because he did not have the key. The head of the safety office 
told us that this is not a valid reason for not inspecting a 
building. We also found cases of inspectors incorrectly giving 
school officials a year to fix broken fire alarms instead of 
the required 24 hours. Additionally, inspectors submitted 
nearly a third of all inspection reports to schools late after 
Indian Affairs' required 30-day timeframe. Some reports were 
more than 4 months late.
    In response to our new findings, we are recommending today 
that Interior monitor the quality and timeliness of school 
inspection reports.
    In a separate report also being released today for this 
subcommittee, we found significant problems with the school 
construction process. Specifically, we found that Interior has 
not consistently used accountability measures to ensure that 
construction projects are completed on time, within budget, and 
meet school needs.
    We found that of 49 recent projects, 16 were 3 or more 
years late, one was almost 10 years late, 10 were 20 percent or 
more over budget. Interior does not always use accountability 
measures, such as warranties, to have builders replace 
defective parts because project managers do not always 
understand how to use these measures. So, the warranty 
provisions may be in the contracts, but they are not being 
employed.
    As a result, we are recommending today that Interior 
develop guidance to help staff learn how to use accountability 
measures in school construction projects. We plan to monitor 
Interior's efforts to address both our prior recommendations 
and the 12 new recommendations in today's reports.
    Thank you.
    [The statement of the U.S. Government Accountability Office 
follows:]
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you.
    Next, Mr. Rusco.
                   Opening Remarks of Mr. Frank Rusco
    Mr. Rusco. Thank you, Chairman Calvert, Ranking Member 
McCollum, and members of the subcommittee. I am also grateful 
to be here today to discuss BIA's management of its 
responsibilities regarding energy development on tribal and 
Indian lands.
    As you know, the United States has recognized the sovereign 
status of tribes, and currently recognizes 567 tribes as 
distinct independent political communities that possess certain 
powers of sovereignty and self-government. In 2016, Congress 
founded an Indian Trust Asset Reform Act that through treaties, 
statutes, and historical relations with Indian tribes, the 
United States has undertaken a unique trust responsibility to 
protect and support Indian tribes and Indians.
    These fiduciary responsibilities reflect commitments made 
in treaties and agreements under which Indians surrendered 
claims to vast tracts of land to the benefit of the people of 
the United States. This history has established enduring and 
enforceable Federal obligations to which our national honor has 
been committed.
    So, I raise that just because I think context is important 
here. And I am going to say a lot of things about the 
performance of the BIA in meeting its fiduciary 
responsibilities, and it is not meeting its fiduciary 
responsibilities very well. But I believe this context is 
essential in our work to keep an eye on that, that the high-
risk area is about what the agencies are doing. And our efforts 
are to improve what the agencies do with the money they have. 
And having listened to the statements of the committee members 
in the last hearing, I understand that that is not the whole 
story. But I want that context to be reflected in the work we 
do.
    I have two handouts that I want to talk about just briefly, 
and one of them is in the hearing statement--this one is--and 
the other one is not.
    So, you know, there are a lot of energy resources on Indian 
and tribal lands, and so the first handout, that is a map of 
the United States of the lower 48. And it shows shale oil and 
gas resources and then where they intersect with tribal lands. 
And there are more than 20 tribes that have oil and gas 
resources, just shale oil and gas resources, on their lands, 
and several of them have coal.
    And in addition, something that is not on the map is that 
more than 200 tribes have the capacity needed to create utility 
scale renewable power generation. And, you know, this is 
important because, you know, Federal funding is scarce, and it 
always has been and always will be. And tribes that have made 
improvements often have done that by developing some kind of 
economic base, and these opportunities represent that.
    And so, when I talk about how the agencies are not doing 
their jobs effectively enough to help tribes that choose to 
develop these resources, that is what is at stake, the tribes' 
ability to develop their own resources, their own economic base 
in order to actually take over some of the responsibilities. 
And when they do, they can do a better job perhaps.
    So, tribes and their members can determine how to use their 
energy resources, but many of those resources are held in trust 
or a restricted status. And because of that, BIA must review 
and approve leases, permits, and other documents required for 
development.
    We found many deficiencies in BIA's management of Indian 
resources in several areas. And before I get into a couple of 
examples, I will say that we put the Interior's management of 
oil and gas development on Federal lands on the High Risk List 
in 2011 because there were many of the same deficiencies we 
found.
    And we have seen since then a lot of progress. Interior has 
made a great deal of progress in resolving a lot of those 
recommendations that got them on the High Risk List, and I 
would like to talk about some of those in this hearing because 
those are things that if the Agency does these things, they can 
solve some of the problems, and they are not all related to the 
budget. Well, they are related to budget.
    Let me be specific. One of the biggest problems is a lack 
of the staff with the right skills in the right place at the 
right time to review permits and environmental assessments, or 
do environmental assessments, and to do the kinds of 
permitting, evaluation, and realty to figure out who owns what 
resources. And we find that all over on Federal lands.
    So, BLM has struggled with having the right staff with the 
right training. And the problem is they are competing for some 
of these positions with industry, so they are out there trying 
to hire petroleum engineers, and industry is going to pay 
$100,000 more a year. So, what do you do, and how do you fix 
that?
    Well, you know, government employment is not private 
employment. There are some benefits, so you have to do the best 
you can with those. And Interior, since we put them on the High 
Risk List, has gone to OPM, and they have gotten special 
authority to pay more for key areas, like petroleum engineers 
or natural resource experts, who otherwise would not go and 
live at some small regional town with a small regional office 
because, you know, where would their kids go to school? Where 
would their spouse find employment?
    But they have gone and they have gotten extra pay 
authority. They have used the tools. They did that through OPM. 
They also went to Congress and they asked for money to pay for 
more staff, and they got that for offshore staff, and they got 
some extra appropriations. They use that effectively. They 
hired more people, and they closed some of those gaps.
    And when they did that, we said, all right, you are showing 
leadership commitment. You are doing the things you can do. You 
are asking Congress for help when you need it, and so they are 
making progress on their star. And so, I have every reason to 
believe that BIA, with the right leadership commitment, could 
do some of the same things.
    So, I will not take up a huge amount of time with examples 
that we found, but I want to talk about one thing in 
particular, and that is in response to tribal requests for 
increased coordination across agencies. And if you look at the 
second handout, you can see there are 14 agencies and 22 
activities that are related to energy. And that does not even 
include all the State agencies and bodies you have to deal with 
when you want to develop energy. And then, there is the tribal 
government.
    So, it is immensely more complex than even doing this on 
Federal lands, which is more complex than doing it on private 
or State lands. And from a regulatory basis, it is a mess. And 
Interior has taken some steps, initial steps, to form a new 
office, the Indian Energy Service Center. This is a great idea. 
It is a great idea because where there is a complex regulatory 
framework, you really need experts in a centralized area who 
can resolve problems and give good advice to people who are 
trying to get things done. And I will give you an example.
    The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission is the final 
permitting authority for interstate pipelines. And sometimes, 
depending on where you are going and what things you are 
crossing, whether you are crossing parks or water, navigable 
waters or whatever, you might be dealing with 13 other 
agencies. And FERC is a one-stop clearinghouse for information 
on how to get through that regulatory process.
    So, if you are going to build a pipeline, you go to FERC 
first. You do a pre-application. They tell you you need to go 
here, you need to do environmental assessments here, you need 
to go over here, you need to check with the Fish and Wildlife 
Service. And not only that, but FERC coordinates with those 
agencies to make sure that that those things are getting done. 
And in Indian Country, an application can come to one of those 
resource agencies, and people, they just sit on it, and it 
takes forever to get things going.
    So, this Indian Energy Service Center, if it is done 
correctly, could provide some of the solution. But the problem 
is when they set it up, they did not set it up to try to 
include all the agencies that are involved. So, we recommended 
that they do coordinate with those, and they have taken steps 
to start to build some relationships and agreements.
    The last thing I will say about that, and then I will 
conclude my statement, is that to fully staff that body will, 
as they envision it with 48 FTEs, would take about twice what 
their appropriation has been in the last couple years, and they 
have asked for twice what they got. And so, it does not mean 
that they cannot do good with what they have, but I think to 
get the most out of it, they are going to keep asking to fill 
these spots. And, you know, what happens after that is none of 
my business. [Laughter.]
    And I am happy to answer any questions. Thank you.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. Thank you for your testimony.
    Ms. King.
                  Opening Remarks of Ms. Kathleen King
    Ms. King. Chairman Calvert, Representative McCollum, thank 
you so much for inviting me to be here today to talk about our 
work on the Indian Health Care Service. And much of what I was 
going to say has already been said by you and members of the 
committee. [Laughter.]
    So, I am going to abbreviate my remarks and just focus on a 
few key things.
    Since 2011, we have issued 7 reports on IHS. We made a 
number of recommendations. Some of them have been implemented, 
but most have not. And we have 14 outstanding recommendations.
    Our reports have found serious shortcomings in the quality 
of care rendered at IHS facilities and a lack of oversight. 
What IHS does is devolve a lot of responsibilities down to the 
area offices without national standards, and there is not a 
feedback loop coming back to headquarters for them to know what 
is going on.
    So, they do not know what is going on with quality of care, 
and they also do not have any standards or way of knowing what 
is going on with regard to patient wait times for primary care. 
We think that is a serious shortcoming, and that they should 
have national standards, and they should have a way of knowing 
what is going on out in the field.
    We have also done some work on the PRC program and found 
some shortcomings there as well. There is a formula, a base 
formula for the PRC program that dates back to the 1930s. No 
one can tell us the origin of this formula, but it results in a 
lot of disparities across the areas ranging from when we did 
our work to a low of $299 per capita to $801 per capita. This 
is inequitable because IHS could not say to us that there were 
differences among the areas in terms of health needs.
    We made a matter to Congress some years ago saying that 
Congress should direct the IHS to develop a more equitable 
formula for the PRC program, and legislation was introduced on 
that, but not enacted.
    IHS did adopt another one of our recommendations which we 
thought was very significant. Under the PRC program, it used to 
be that they paid physicians and other non-hospital providers 
what they charged. In some cases, they negotiated contracts or 
had discounted rates, but in most places they were paying what 
physicians charge, and that is not typical in the health 
insurance industry. We made a recommendation that they reduce 
the payments to the same as Medicare paid, and they did adopt 
that, and as part of that, we estimated that they would save 
$32 million. So, that was a positive step.
    We have also made a number of recommendations to improve 
the management of the PRC program and to encourage IHS to 
expand their outreach efforts to get people enrolled in other 
third party insurance, such as Medicaid, because when people 
enroll in that insurance, two good things can happen for IHS. 
One, if they seek care at an IHS facility, IHS can bill for 
that revenue and keep it, and that enhances their PRC revenue. 
Or if someone takes their Medicaid or other insurance and goes 
elsewhere and gets care, that reduces the demand on IHS. So, 
that is another important step.
    With that, I think I will stop because I know you will have 
questions for us.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you for all your testimony. It is 
obviously extremely concerning what is going on out in Indian 
Country. We will have a number of questions for the record, but 
I will lead off with a couple of questions that seem to be 
appropriate.
                 GAO HIGH RISK REPORT: TRIBAL PROGRAMS
    I think I will start with you, Melissa. What changed from 
2015 to 2017 that prompted GAO to add tribal programs the list?
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. I think the number of reports that we had 
during that timeframe and the significance of those findings 
really caused concerns for us, and made us realize that this 
was really a high-risk issue. And it did not help that there 
were so many open recommendations that had not been resolved.
    Mr. Calvert. How frequently does GAO meet with the agencies 
to monitor progress?
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. We talk with the agencies regularly about 
their recommendations and the like. I would say at a minimum, 
at least every 6 months, but it is frequently quite often more 
than that. We often talk with them in the course of our ongoing 
studies as well.
    Mr. Calvert. Okay.
    Mr. Rusco. And in addition to that, being on the High Risk 
List means that that there will be a meeting with OMB, the 
Secretary of the Interior, the deputy secretaries, and all the 
assistant secretaries of the relevant bureaus. And in that 
meeting, we will talk about where they are in high risk, and 
they will talk about what they are doing to get off it, and OMB 
will be there to try to add some accountability. So, that also 
happens.
                         ASSISTANCE TO AGENCIES
    Mr. Calvert. When asked, does GAO provide any help? Do you 
provide any help if some of these agencies ask for help?
    Mr. Rusco. Well, so we provide our recommendations, and we 
will clarify what we mean if asked. But we cannot really tell 
them in detail how to resolve problems, and then still come 
back later and audit them and say whether they are doing a good 
job. [Laughter.]
    So, we are careful about that. [Laughter.]
    Mr. Calvert. You know, you have got a couple of these 
charts up. There is one that looked like----
    Ms. McCollum. It is a nightmare.
    Mr. Calvert. It looks like Obamacare, does it not? 
[Laughter.]
    No, I am just kidding.
    Ms. McCollum. Well, the ACA works. [Laughter.]
    Mr. Calvert. But anyway, this extremely complicated chart. 
How do you explain that? There has to be some efficiencies that 
can be found. So, you do not give any advice, but where do they 
go? I mean, this has got to be cleaned up. So, who do they work 
with to do that?
    Mr. Rusco. You know, this is a case where I think there are 
two things. We need to look further into that, you know, and 
see where there might be efficiencies, and specifically where 
coordination could resolve a problem, or where there is maybe 
multiple agencies doing something.
    But I will give you one example. There are two Indian 
energy loan guarantee programs, and one is in Interior, and one 
is in DOE. DOE's has never been funded, but Interior's is 
funded. DOE has loan programs. They have all the expertise to 
run loan programs. And we have not looked at the Interior's 
loan programs, but I have looked at DOE's loan program since 
their inception in 2005, and it took them forever to get up to 
speed. And when they finally did, they have a solid group of 
professionals who can evaluate loans and make them, but that 
took years to do.
    And so, one of the things that we would look at is do you 
really need two Indian energy loan guarantee programs, or could 
you use the resources from one and save some money that then 
that money could go to increasing the amount of loans, because, 
you know, honestly, the annual amount in the Indian Energy Loan 
Guarantee Program, that would fund one large energy project. 
And so, you know, you could use all the money you can get.
    And so, we have not looked at that, so that is not a 
recommendation, but that is the kind of place we would look. We 
would look for that sort of efficiency.
                           OFFSHORE ACCOUNTS
    Mr. Calvert. This goes to management, and that goes to 
leadership and finding somebody maybe outside to look at this 
entire process and improve upon it. One last question. $1 
million dollars to an offshore account? Explain that.
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. Sure. It actually happened in 11 separate 
transactions, and it went to three Asian countries, but 
primarily Indonesia. And they were not able to recover the 
money.
    Mr. Calvert. And who did this?
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. The thought was that it might have been 
some kind of hacking or cyber, you know, crime. However, the 
bank accused the school of not having properly secure computers 
to do these transactions, and so the account was compromised.
    Mr. Calvert. So, nobody----
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. Nobody was held, yeah. So, nobody was 
arrested. In the end, the money was not returned. And we have a 
concern because there is limited funding, as we have been 
talking about, and you want to make sure that the funding that 
is provided goes to schools and it is not diverted. And because 
of that, we made recommendations to better oversee school 
spending to guard against those kinds of problems.
    Actually, in 2014 we made recommendations to have basic 
written procedures to oversee school funding to make sure it is 
being spent appropriately, and that has yet to happen.
    Mr. Calvert. Wow.
    Mr. Joyce. Mr. Chairman?
    Mr. Calvert. Yes?
    Mr. Joyce. Could you yield for a second?
    Mr. Calvert. Sure.
                           RECOVERY OF FUNDS
    Mr. Joyce. Does not the FBI or other law enforcement 
agencies assist you in the recovery of such funds? I mean, if 
it was taken from a bank account, obviously it had to be 
transferred to some other account.
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. The FBI was brought in by the Interior's 
IG office to look into this, but they were not able to identify 
the individuals or obtain the money in the end.
     Voice. So, it could have been an outside job.
    Mr. Calvert. Amazing. Ms. McCollum.
                         STAFFING AND TRAINING
    Ms. McCollum. Thank you very much for your testimony, and 
thank you for working with the agencies because I think the 
Indian programs within the Department of Interior, these are 
people who get up every morning and want to do the best job 
that they can. One of the challenges that is becoming very 
apparent, besides facility maintenance and backlog, is 
staffing. I am just going to roll a couple things out, and then 
have you all respond.
    So, one of the things that became very clear in one of the 
reports that we received on the inspection for schools is the 
BIA might have one person who works on this in the Agency. They 
have hundreds and hundreds and hundreds of miles to cover, and 
they have multiple hats to wear. And they really have not gone 
to school to become a really good inspector of buildings, but 
then that becomes their job. Or we have things that are 
contracted out, but we do not have the personnel in place to do 
a double check of what is happening with the contractor.
    To your point about warranties, I worked in the private 
sector for years. I worked for a major retailer, and I dealt 
with carpet warranties and furniture warranties. And I will 
tell you, it is a full-time job, and you have to be on it 24/7. 
Here again, if you do not have the school maintenance person in 
Indian Country really knowing how to deal with some of these 
warranty issues, they can be very difficult to resolve. Some of 
this is staffing and some is training, so that I would point 
out in education a little bit.
    Staffing and training and what you were saying about 
energy, Mr. Rusco, which is trying to get people to stay and be 
retained in the Agency, as well as understanding all the 
quagmire from who to report to who. It would seem to me that 
there are State models out there. You mentioned FERC. There are 
models out there that Indian Country can look at, or work with, 
or sit down and have a roundtable with the agencies on how to 
streamline and move forward. Having timely inspections, and 
permits, and everything are very, very important.
    But there are some things that are going to be going on in 
the EPA budget regarding permits and timely inspections. I am 
going to follow up to see if there is something I should be 
watching in that budget. They are in Indian Country as well, 
and I am kind of concerned about their permitting.
    Ms. King, I am going to end with this. This Administration 
has given a directive to Indian Health Services, and Indian 
Affairs and Education, and all the rest of the Agencies to 
reduce staffing. They have huge gaps, holes, not enough 
positions filled in Indian Health Service, and problems 
retaining and recruiting people. Is part of your 
recommendations to beef up and get the right people doing the 
right kind of staffing and figure out how to retain them? 
Because I, quite frankly, think I need to write a letter to the 
White House saying, in this particular area, to ask people to 
be doing a workforce reduction is pound foolish.
    Ms. King. During the course of our work, IHS has told us 
that not having the right staff is one of the key impediments 
to quality of care and access to timely primary care. Some of 
our work really documented the change in leadership in the area 
offices and in key positions. We also have some ongoing work 
now where we are looking at staffing issues. And we hope to 
have some constructive advice that comes out of that, creative 
solutions or things that they can do. But certainly having the 
staff, especially the medical staff, in these facilities is 
important.
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. I would add on the education front, we 
have similar concerns in terms of workforce planning. We have 
two outstanding recommendations regarding workforce planning to 
make sure that they have the right staff in the right locations 
to do the work. We had people telling us that they were not 
accountants, they did not know how to review single audits, and 
yet that was their job. So, that was a concern of ours.
    In terms of the training issue that you brought up and 
inspections, in the report that is released today we found that 
33 out of 39 staff with safety responsibilities did not 
complete required training. So, they are not even doing the 
training that is provided by the Agency and required by the 
Agency.
    Ms. McCollum. But for how many of those individuals was 
that not their only job? That is part of my point here. If 
there are Federal employees not doing their job, they need to 
be held accountable to it. But sometimes we are asking the same 
Federal employee, whether it is in Indian Health or Indian 
Education, to do multiple jobs. We are asking these people to 
perform superhumanly. Is that part of your report, too?
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. That does cover individuals who may have 
responsibilities in addition to safety issues.
    Mr. Rusco. With respect to the energy side, there are other 
examples of agencies doing more with less by being creative. 
So, BLM has repeatedly, because of the boom and bust nature of 
oil and gas, they have repeatedly been sort of mis-staffed in 
regional offices. So, when the shale boom came, all of sudden 
they do not have anybody in North Dakota. They have tons of 
people in Wyoming. Shale gas just drove coal-bed methane gas 
out of business, and so all of a sudden Wyoming has people in 
BLM offices with nothing to do. North Dakota does not have 
people, and they have all these permits and all these 
inspections to do.
    And so, they implemented a pilot program to try to move 
people into hotspots and take care of business, and we have not 
looked at that closely enough. When we looked at it, and it was 
a very successful pilot. They should continue that, and I think 
BIA can learn from that. But we have not looked specifically at 
BIA to see how well, that centralized model works where you 
have people that can go for a specific time and take care of a 
workload problem. But I think that is a very promising 
potential.
    Ms. McCollum. Thank you, Mr. Chair.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. Mr. Simpson.
              BUREAU OF INDIAN EDUCATION: SAFETY CONCERNS
    Mr. Simpson. Thank you. Could you put the star back up? I 
know it is there somewhere.
    Ms. McCollum. You do not want the yellow tag?
    Mr. Simpson. No, I think I have seen the yellow tag. Did 
they use that school for the 8 months that they had the yellow 
tags up?
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. Yes, and there were students involved.
    Ms. McCollum. They probably should have been red tagged.
                               LEADERSHIP
    Mr. Simpson. That is amazing. As I read your report last 
night, and I did read all of it. That was an amazing 
accomplishment I think. [Laughter.]
    The one thing that came to my mind as I read in all three 
of these areas, and it seemed like there was one common theme 
of this star and this leadership commitment. And if you look at 
the incredible turnover within these agencies, whether it is at 
the local level, mid-local level, even in Washington, D.C., has 
anybody looked at why is there such a huge turnover in these 
programs of leadership, and how do you keep a leadership 
commitment that is continually turning over?
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. In terms of BIE issues, we have reported 
on the significant turnover and cited that as a management 
challenge. As many of you know, the prior director of BIE was 
removed from his position last year due to ethics concerns.
    Mr. Rusco. So, Interior faced this when they were put on 
the High Risk List for oil and gas management and Federal 
lands. We think that they have largely solved that leadership 
issue with one Bureau's exception, but they did it by 
institutionalizing the ownership, so, of the issues. So, they 
said, all right, this is your position. You own these issues. 
You own the recommendations. And once that is institutionalized 
and that is part of your job description, if you have turnover, 
that is still part of your job description.
    And it will not solve everything. It will not solve bad 
acting. But if you get somebody who has got a job and here is a 
description, and it is written into it that this is what you 
do, then I think that is how they have dealt with it. And they 
have a lot of turnover, too, but they have been making great 
progress.
    Mr. Simpson. Go ahead.
    Ms. King. With respect to IHS, I think they have been 
without permanent leadership for about 2 years. They had an 
acting director, I believe, for about the last year of the 
Obama Administration, and there are no, as we saw today, no 
permanent people in place yet in this Administration. So, that 
is a long time with temporary leadership.
    And the other thing that we saw in the area offices, when 
there was a problem when one area, they moved people around to 
go to that area to fix the problem there, to fix the crisis. 
But it results in a big churn among the area offices.
                           STAFFING: TURNOVER
    Mr. Simpson. Have we have gone out and asked people that 
left why they left, what is driving them to leave that field 
and go into something else? What is the cause of the turnover? 
I mean, we have talked on this committee with people who worked 
in or ran IHS, just to give background information, and the 
stories we have heard from people that used to work there years 
ago. Has anybody gone out and done that?
    Ms. King. I have not.
    Mr. Rusco. No.
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. No.
    Mr. Simpson. Well, it would be interesting to find out what 
it is. But, you know, my wife often makes recommendations of 
things that I should do that I do not think are in my best 
interest. [Laughter.]
    Sometimes agencies might look at you and say that you are 
the data geeks and all that kind of stuff, and so you make all 
these recommendations. Do they ever look at you and say, that 
is neat on paper, but it is not the real world that we live in 
and try to deal with every day, consequently we are not going 
to implement that, and that is why 39 out of the 41, or 
whatever it is, recommendations have not been implemented. How 
do you work that out between agencies to try to implement your 
recommendations?
    Mr. Rusco. Well so, we try very hard not to make 
recommendations that we have not got really good ideas are 
implementable. And we do that by getting past the leadership 
and onto the ground and find out. Like, you know, a lot of our 
recommendations come from the Agency. We talk to them. They 
tell us what is wrong. It is amazing how much they admit when 
you go out in the field and talk to people.
    They know where their problems are, and they are trying to 
solve them, too, but it gets back to the leadership issue, and 
so, it goes all the way to the Secretary of Interior. If the 
Secretary of Interior does not put in the budget I need more 
resources for Indian programs, well then, where do you go? I 
mean, obviously it is up to OMB, too, right? You know how it 
works a lot better than I do.
    Mr. Simpson. Unfortunately, yeah.
    Mr. Rusco. And so, but that leadership has to come from the 
top. It has to go down to the bureaus, and then the bureaus 
have to institutionalize the ownership of the problem, and then 
you have got a commitment. And that is when you can see 
progress, at least in my experience.
                          CONGRESSIONAL ACTION
    Mr. Simpson. Well, if that leadership is not coming from 
the top or has not come from the top, and I am not trying to 
point fingers at anybody. But if it does not come from the top, 
what can this committee do? Can we write into legislation, into 
our bill some of these recommendations and require the agencies 
to do some of those things that need to be done?
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. Yes.
    Mr. Simpson. Would you recommend that we do some of those 
things that maybe are the harder ones to get done or that get 
more resistance?
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. Yes. I think simple things, like having 
written procedures to oversee school spending, should be done 
immediately, not languish for years.
    Ms. King. I think things like hearings, too, are helpful 
because what I find is that in our areas, occasionally IHS has 
disagreed with us and said, nope, we are not going to implement 
that recommendation. But more frequently they agree, but they 
do not do it.
                     INDIAN LOAN GUARANTEE PROGRAM
    Mr. Simpson. One more thing. Since I chair the Energy and 
Water Appropriations committee, we will look at the possibility 
of including the Indian Loan Guarantee Program under the 
direction of the DOE Loan Guarantee Program. I know that 
Secretary Moniz recommended some of that in the last budget, 
and we just did not feel we had the money to do it or did not 
feel confident of what they were trying to do. So, but I think 
that is a valid recommendation.
                             MEDICARE RATES
    Here is one thing I will say, though. And, Kathleen, you 
mentioned that one of the recommendations that had just been 
implemented by one of the programs was that they pay the 
Medicare rate to doctors instead of the rate that doctors were 
charging. Has anybody followed that up to see what the 
accessibility to doctors has been? Has that decreased 
accessibility?
    And the reason I ask that, I was a dentist in the real 
world, and while I am not talking about Medicare, I will tell 
you that if somebody said we are only going to pay the Medicaid 
rate, which is what dentists usually deal with, if I only 
operated on Medicaid patients, I would be out of business to 
cover the costs.
    Ms. King. We actually----
    Mr. Simpson. So, I mean, you have to look at accessibility, 
too.
    Ms. King. We actually did some sounding out on that before 
we made that recommendation, and we asked a number of providers 
what do you think about this. And, some people said, IHS should 
have done this a long time ago. The rates that are being paid 
are too high.
    But we did make a recommendation to IHS to follow up and 
make sure that access is maintained because that is an 
important aspect.
    Mr. Simpson. Thank you.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. Ms. Pingree.
                BUREAU OF INDIAN EDUCATION: CONSTRUCTION
    Ms. Pingree. Thank you, Mr. Chair. Thank you very much for 
the work you have been doing and for your testimony. It has 
been very educational and much appreciated to hear the work 
that you are doing. And I am sure where we can yield some 
improvements, it will be good.
    I do not have a lot of questions or comments to make. 
Certainly some of the concerns about Indian Health and Indian 
Education have been problems in our State. We do not have a 
drop of energy besides wind in our State. That is not on your 
list.
    I will just add that in terms of education we have been 
concerned about the role that the BIA plays in the Bureau of 
Indian Education. We have one facility in the pipeline in our 
State, and the Committee has been very helpful with that, the 
Beatrice Rafferty school, which is a Passamaquoddy school. It 
has taken us 3 years to get from the design stage to the 
construction stage, and it still does not look like there will 
be a groundbreaking until 2019.
    In any other circumstance in school construction, it would 
not look like that. Every time there has been a hitch, we have 
followed up and tried to figure it out. It has been 
bureaucratic, intractable. It just does not make any sense. 
Even when there are, differences in the rules or everything 
else, you are just thinking, does everybody put a roadblock 
everywhere they can to keep this from happening? This is a 
school that was funded, but, funding delays cost money. Little 
glitches all of a sudden result in more money because somebody 
interprets one thing one way.
    You look like you might have a comment.
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. I would just say that the report that we 
are releasing today does get to that issue of construction 
delays. And one of the things that we heard repeatedly was that 
Interior was not providing enough technical assistance and 
oversight to tribes on construction projects, and that they 
were not responding in a timely way to requests, which was 
resulting in extensive delays.
    Ms. Pingree. So, we will look forward to reading the 
report, but that was what we have experienced from observing 
this process.
    As with most schools, and everyone on this Committee knows 
it better than me, these are already schools generally that are 
condemned, that have, unhealthy conditions, uninspected 
boilers, mold, all kinds of other problems already. When it 
takes long delays, you have got students locked in places that 
they should not be, and teachers trying to teach under 
inadequate situations. Communities feeling really bad about the 
situation, which leads to all the kinds of health 
complications, and, suicide rates and all kinds of other things 
when you are compounding problems, especially starting with 
kids.
    So, thank you for your work. Thank you, Mr. Chair.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. Mr. Joyce.
            BUREAU OF INDIAN EDUCATION: CONSTRUCTION DELAYS
    Mr. Joyce. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. And then following 
along those lines, it seems like there was an 8-month interval 
between the initial finding of the problem and anything being 
done. Can you explain why there was such a delay?
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. I do not know why there was a delay, but 
this is not unusual. There are frequently issues where hazards 
are identified and they are not remediated. And in our prior 
work, we found that it was so extensive that it was not 
uncommon to have the next year's inspection find the same 
problems as in the previous year's inspection.
    We did make a recommendation for Interior to provide 
assistance to schools to be able to actually fix the problems 
and help them build capacity so that they know how to do that. 
But that recommendation remains unimplemented.
    Mr. Joyce. The funding exists for it. There is just a 
failure to do so at the local or at that one individual level. 
Is this occurring in other schools?
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. It is occurring at multiple schools in 
terms of identified problems that have not been fixed and 
remain for years. And in terms of the issues there, I think one 
of the issues is having staff at the school level who know how 
to read an inspection report, who know what to do to correct 
the problem. You may have janitorial staff, for example, 
responsible, and they may not know exactly what to do in terms 
of certain repairs. And we think it is critical that Interior 
provide that technical assistance to schools so that they can 
address safety concerns versus having concerns repeat from year 
to year, or last 8 months in this situation.
    Mr. Calvert. If the gentleman would yield.
    Mr. Joyce. Absolutely.
              BUREAU OF INDIAN EDUCATION: SAFETY CONCERNS
    Mr. Calvert. When something like that occurs where you have 
a boiler which obviously if it has a malfunction could blow up 
and kill a number of people, why was that school not 
immediately closed until that problem was fixed? Do they not 
have the authority to close that school, or does anybody not 
have the common sense to understand that?
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. We had the same concern. It was 
unfathomable to us that that boiler remained in that condition 
with those gas leaks while students and staff were in the area.
    Ms. McCollum. Mr. Chair?
    Mr. Calvert. Yes?
    Ms. McCollum. Was that the yellow tag school? Because 
usually there is a big difference between a yellow tag and a 
red tag. I am not trying to pretend to be a plumber or a 
pipefitter here, but I have dealt with this a little bit in 
real life. We can see that is a yellow tag.
    Usually with the yellow tag you get told, okay, we are not 
going to shut you down. It is not immediate, but you have to 
get it repaired within X number of hours. They have a 
responsibility, the plumbing company. Maybe all States are not 
created equal--maybe it gets into State jurisdiction to be back 
in 48 or 24 hours to make sure that it is correct. But in other 
words, a yellow tag means we can fix this. It can be fixed 
properly. It will be fixed expeditiously.
    If this is the school we were just discussing, it seems to 
me whoever put the yellow tag on it put the wrong color on it, 
and the school should have been closed.
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. That is possible. You can see that the 
sign says, I think, that the carbon monoxide is too high on the 
tag. I mean, that is another issue in terms of the inspections 
is that they are not always done in in an accurate way as 
evidenced by some of our findings in terms of broken fire 
alarms and the like. People were told that they had a year to 
fix things when they should have been fixed within 24 hours. 
So, there is often an issue in terms of the directions that are 
provided by the inspector.
    Ms. McCollum. But it is not the school that puts that tag 
on it or the janitor. Usually that is somebody whose license is 
on the line.
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. That is an outside inspector. That is 
correct.
    Mr. Calvert. Mr. Joyce.
    Mr. Joyce. I am sorry, but I do not find it humorous. On 
top of the explosion factor, on top of the carbon monoxide 
factor, people are going to die. And so, I do not get the 
disconnect between you write a report that says these things 
need to be fixed and nothing happens. There has to be some 
other agency or somebody who is going to step in, because you 
are putting all these kids' lives at risk.
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. We have a similar concern. We think that 
things need to change. We have made recommendations, and that 
is partly why we have put this issue on the High Risk List.
    Mr. Joyce. Again, it is a list. There has to be some type 
of, I do not care who the local authorities are. If you have a 
theft of a million dollars, it is a theft of a million dollars. 
25 years as a prosecutor, that galls me, and the fact that you 
put in things like this. I used to represent school districts. 
You put in something like this, and nobody does anything about 
it? This cannot go on.
    Mr. Calvert. Well, they did not have anything to do with 
the crime.
    Mr. Joyce. Well, I appreciate that, but they find people 
who are doing this. Where is this disconnect? We have to find 
out where it is and fix it. I am sorry.
    Ms. Emrey-Arras. We share your concern.
    Mr. Calvert. We have a hard stop here at 3:30, and it is 
3:35. I certainly appreciate this panel. I have some additional 
questions I will be submitting to you.
    Ms. King. We will be happy to answer them.
    Mr. Calvert. We certainly appreciate your coming today.
    Ms. King. Thank you for having us.
    Mr. Calvert. We appreciate your testimony and your truthful 
answers. We are adjourned.
    Mr. Rusco. Thank you all.
                                            Thursday, May 25, 2017.
                          U.S. FOREST SERVICE
</option>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
    <option>HON. SONNY PERDUE, SECRETARY OF AGRICULTURE
TOM TIDWELL, CHIEF, U.S. FOREST SERVICE
                  Opening Remarks of Chairman Calvert
    Mr. Calvert. The subcommittee will come to order.
    Good morning. I would like to extend a warm welcome to our 
distinguished full committee, my colleagues; our witnesses; and 
to the audience. Today is a special occasion for the Interior 
Subcommittee.
    We have the Secretary of Agriculture, the Honorable Sonny 
Perdue, as well as the chief of the Forest Service, Mr. Tom 
Tidwell, testifying before us.
    My staff reviewed the committee hearing records as far back 
as the 1960s, found no mention of the Secretary of Agriculture 
appearing before the subcommittee on Forest issues. I 
understand your staff jogged the memories of long-time USDA 
employees, and no one could remember it happening either, so we 
are breaking new ground today.
    Secretary, Chief Tidwell, we are pleased and honored to 
have you both with us. We look forward to hearing from you on 
the fiscal 2018 budget request for the Forest Service.
    The President's fiscal year 2018 budget request is a 
significant departure from the last several fiscal years with 
his proposed overall reduction of $900 million, or 16 percent 
below fiscal year 2017 enacted level for the Forest Service 
programs.
    And again, we have a budget request in which more than 50 
percent of the Service's budget is dedicated to fighting fires. 
We will have many questions about these cuts and their effects 
on operations, staffing, and other programs. In particular, 
this subcommittee continues to be concerned about the cost of 
fighting wildfires and the effect it has on other Forest 
Service budgets, programs, and management.
    And I would like to thank you, Chief Tidwell, for the 
administration's efforts over the past several years to change 
the way we budget for fires.
    I would also like to thank Congressman Simpson for keeping 
the pressure on Congress to address the issue.
    While firefighting costs seem to dominate most discussions 
about the Forest Service, there are numerous other issues, 
including aviation management, law enforcement, land 
acquisition, basic budgeting, program management, among others, 
that need to be attended to.
    As I said before, the Service must demonstrate that it is 
accountable, transparent, and able to improve the condition of 
our national forests, all while managing unpredictable fire 
seasons. This is not an easy task.
    Secretary Perdue, we invited you to participate in this 
hearing, in part, to help you understand the importance of the 
Forest Service to this subcommittee, the Department of 
Agriculture as a whole, and the Nation. Healthy, productive 
national forests provide quality timber and other forest 
products. They clean our air and water, provide recreational 
opportunities, and enhance the natural beauty of our country.
    We understand the challenges facing our national forests 
and statutes under which they are managed. However, I believe 
our national forests need a renewed focus on their health and 
productivity. As Secretary, you can help with that, and I ask 
you to consider making forest management one of your 
priorities.
    For the past 1\1/2\ years, the subcommittee, along with our 
Senate counterparts, has been investigating the Forest Service 
accounting, budget, and management practices. We found some 
areas where improvements were needed.
    Some of these needed to be addressed by Congress; others 
could be addressed by the Service. In fiscal year 2017 
Consolidated Appropriations Act, we, one, imposed fiscal year 
limits on most Forest Service accounts. The Service has not had 
limits for 20 years or more. We directed the Service to 
standardize its budgeting across the agency. We understand each 
region does it differently. We directed the Service to reduce 
printing expenditures. The Service has significantly higher 
printing costs than any other USDA agency. Increased oversight 
of the Service by the Department's budget office to improve 
coordination and standardization of budgets, and we required 
more detailed budget requests in the future. We need more 
numbers and less narrative.
    Chief, we appreciate the dedication, creativity, and 
responsiveness of your budget staff. They are working long 
hours without complaint to address our concerns and make the 
Forest Service more accountable, effective, and transparent.
    The subcommittee is serious about the need for improvements 
in your accounting, budgeting, and managing practices. They 
need to be especially important if we see large reductions to 
the Service's budget. We must ensure that we are getting the 
absolute most out of every taxpayer dollar invested in our 
national forest. We pledge to work with you. I hope you also 
will pledge to work with us.
    Secretary Perdue, Chief Tidwell, I thank you and the entire 
Forest Service staff for your work to care for the Nation's 
forests. We know that all of you care deeply for our forests 
and the communities that depend on them.
    Now I am happy to yield to the gentlelady from Minnesota, 
who has a few forests of her own, Ms. McCollum, for any opening 
remarks she would like to make.
    Ms. McCollum. Thank you, Mr. Chair. I do have a few 
forests.
                    Opening Remarks of Ms. McCollum
    Secretary Purdue, it is great to have you here.
    Chief Tidwell, good to see you again this morning.
    I would like to first echo the chairman's comments about 
the subcommittee's commitment to help the Forest Service 
improve its accounting and its budgeting and its management 
practice. But at the same time, Chief, I would like to 
acknowledge the hard work and cooperation of your budget staff 
as we move forward on this shared goal.
    The American people rely on the U.S. Forest Service to 
responsibly manage the national forest system in a way that 
sustains the health, diversity, and productivity of our 
Nation's forests and grasslands.
    Now, we can all agree on that a strong America is one where 
we protect our natural resources for future generations. Being 
good stewards of those resources requires robust investments in 
both resource management and the staffing to carry that 
management out.
    Unfortunately, President Trump's fiscal year 2018 budget 
request is a cruel and, I believe, a reckless plan that pays 
for lavish tax breaks for billionaires with cuts to the very 
investments our future families need, our small businesses, and 
our communities count on.
    When it comes to the U.S. Forest Service, this budget 
request is far worse than I could have imagined. It slashes 
many of the important programs that are critical to ensuring 
the health of our Nation's forests. Nine programs are 
completely eliminated, and States and local units of government 
must find the resources in their already strained budgets to 
replace these Federal funding streams.
    The programs within the State and private forestry accounts 
are particularly important to State and local governments. This 
account provides resources so that our State partners can 
manage their forests to protect water quality, provide habitat, 
forest products, and opportunities for recreation and other 
public benefits.
    So sadly, the Trump administration cuts this account by 46 
percent, or $99 million. Again, States--and I will speak for my 
State, which is going through a budget process right now--can 
simply not afford to fill this void that this budget will 
create.
    And I am disappointed that the administration has failed to 
pursue any proposals to reform the way we fund wildfire costs. 
As the chairman had pointed out, Mr. Simpson has been working 
tirelessly on this, and has the totally nonpartisan support 
from this committee on this, because the costs associated with 
fighting wildland fires continue to rise, and this budget 
illustrates how other important programs suffer when funding is 
diverted into fighting wildfires.
    So, Chief, in the past years, you have supported wildfire 
disaster proposals.
    Mr. Secretary, I would ask you to work with the Chief, with 
the Administration, with Mr. Simpson, with all of us, to 
develop a plan to tackle this issue so that we can fund 
wildfire fighting in a sustainable fashion.
    And as I pointed out, every member of this subcommittee, 
especially in the last Congress, was a cosponsor of Mr. 
Simpson's Wildfire Disaster Funding bill, and I hope he will 
reintroduce it again.
    If we continue on the path of underfunding programs to 
manage firefighting, we jeopardize the health and longevity of 
America's national forests.
    As you can tell, I believe this budget is grossly 
inefficient. It disregards the jobs, recreational 
opportunities, and the environmental benefits our national 
forests provide for our health and our economy to be prosperous 
for all the American people.
    So I hope that we will reject the proposed cuts and instead 
work with you to ensure that the Service has the resources 
necessary to remain a leader in natural resources; 
conservation; recreation; management; and, of course, with 
timber. Thank you.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you.
              Opening Statement of Secretary Sonny Perdue
    And, Secretary Perdue, you may begin your statement.
    Secretary Perdue. Good morning. I really appreciate, Mr. 
Chairman, the informal environment here. It is a little 
different than many other committees we go through, and it is a 
welcome change. For that reason, I am going to forego reading 
my opening statement, you have that for the record, but I hope 
we can just have a genuine and transparent conversation this 
morning over the issues that I have seen already in visiting 
with 75 of your colleagues during my confirmation process. We 
understand that the U.S. Forest Service has had some 
challenges.
                            FIRE FUNDING FIX
    I want to thank this committee--particularly for being 
solution oriented in some of those, and we will talk about the 
fire funding, as Congresswoman McCollum mentioned this morning. 
It is a serious issue. As you and I visited in your office, and 
we have got to right size that and get ahead of that because 
you know the challenges there.
                         BUDGET ACCOUNTABILITY
    I also appreciated the fact that you want to hold us 
accountable. My goal, frankly, as Secretary and in the Forest 
Service is to earn your trust in management where you will not 
have to be as prescriptive as you were in the 2017 budget.
    I liked what you said, I have sort of said the same thing 
in my budget briefings: I want more numbers and less narrative. 
We are trying to do budget briefings with slides. I want to see 
the numbers over the historical trends of what we are doing.
    I view myself as a manager, my goal, as Governor of 
Georgia, which I think we made a lot of progress too, is be the 
best managed, most effective, efficient State in the Nation, 
and by and large, that is my same goal for this Department.
    When we leave our tenure here, I want people to say: ``That 
is the best managed agency in the U.S. Government.'' That is a 
focus on facts based, data driven, science based, transparent, 
ethical, integrity, and with a customer focus, and that means 
everything.
    What I heard as I visited, while the U.S. Forest Service 
has had a wonderful history and a wonderful contribution to the 
beauty of our Nation, I am not sure we are being as good a 
neighbor in our U.S. Forest Service as we had been in the past, 
and that is another one of my goals.
    Good neighbors treat one another with respect, with 
dignity. Private landowner neighbors, if they see something 
going on and they help one another or give counsel and advice, 
and we know that our private forests benefit from a combination 
of good neighborhood, and we want to be a good neighbor within 
the culture of the communities the U.S. Forest Service finds 
itself in that regard. So I look forward to that.
    Our new motto does not deal specifically with the Forest 
Service, but I think you can imply that as well when we say, 
``Do right and feed everyone.'' We want to create jobs. We want 
to make our rural communities prosper where there was once 
millions and billions of board feet of timber cut. We know 
those jobs have disappeared there. Much of it has to do with 
litigation.
                              FIRE FUNDING
    Fire funding is a huge issue. I look forward to working 
with this committee, who has been a huge sponsor, and Mr. 
Simpson kind of the spiritual leader of that effort, to see if 
we can get that across the goal line.
    I will advocate very strongly, as Ms. McCollum advised, to 
the administration over--and I think the President gets that. 
From a management standpoint, you cannot--as you and I talked, 
you cannot manage a budget where you do not know where your 
emergency or your disaster funds come out.
    Fifty three percent of the Forest Service budget is in 
suppression. It should be down, like it used to be, in the 15 
to 20 percent area, and let us use the rest of the funds wisely 
in the management of those.
    So that is a big issue, and I really appreciate you all and 
your efforts in that regard, and I look forward to working with 
you to make that a reality in our budgetary system.
                               LITIGATION
    Certainly, you also know that litigation is a challenge for 
our U.S. Forest Service. Some of that has maybe been a problem 
because we have not been doing as well as we could do in some 
of those areas. The Cottonwood case is a particular one in 
mind. That ruling obviously creates a lot of problems over the 
continued consultation regarding habitat, if there is any 
change. I hope we can really look at some legislation to make 
sure and clear to the courts that that only delays all these 
projects more months and years sometimes, and we have got at 
least 80 forest management projects at risk of being enjoined 
through that ruling right now. That is affecting 72,000 acres 
and over 100 million board feet.
    Simply, that is jobs. We want to be good environmental 
stewards. I believe our farms and ranchers and forests are some 
of the best natural stewards of the land we can have, and we 
want to let them do it in a way that makes sense, while we 
regard the habitat and the wildlife and all those things in a 
reasonable commonsense kind of way.
    I will address some of the budget issues that I think are 
most important here we believe that we would like to ask for 
your help in.
                                 ROADS
    When you think about jobs that our U.S. forests can create, 
there was one, I think, that was probably ill-advised and maybe 
not in keeping with the President's wishes as well, and that 
had to do with our lack of improvements, particularly in roads. 
You can not harvest lumber on these if you do not have roads to 
do that.
    So I know you all will look at that in your consideration 
and think about the capital improvement and maintenance 
program. We do not need a lot more equipment, but you can not 
get to trees and you can not create jobs without roads to get 
to them, so we would like to talk to you about that.
                           PROGRAM MANAGEMENT
    Ms. McCollum mentioned a relationship that we have had. The 
U.S. Forest Service has had great relationships with our State 
and local forest programs, and I think we need to review that 
and see how we can restore some relationships there. This is a 
signal to them that we do not really appreciate that 
relationship, and I hope that we will do that.
    So you mentioned several times the management. That is what 
I think I am supposed to do. I am a manager, and that is, 
frankly, not in your area, but that is one of the reasons I 
elevated the Rural Development program up to my level, because 
I am not a micromanager, but I am a hands-on manager. And I 
plan to be a hands-on manager with the Forest Service utilizing 
the good services of a good chief forester, but I will be 
directly involved and accountable for those, the results of 
that.
    I know that you all have relied on the chief in years past, 
but the buck stops here, and we are going to change the Forest 
Service for the better to make it more responsive to our 
neighborhoods, our communities, and to our mills out there. 
Once again, we have got a great resource. It is renewable.
    It is a wonderful blessing, frankly, in this Nation to have 
the kind of forests that we have, and we want to be as equally 
good managers of our U.S. Forest Service as our private 
landowners. I come from a State that has amazing private 
landownership management, and we want to take those best 
practices and spread them across our whole U.S. Forest Service.
    So I will stop there and look forward to your questions.
    [The statement of Secretary Perdue and Chief Tidwell 
follows:]
            2017 CONSOLIDATED APPROPRIATIONS ACT DIRECTIVES
    Mr. Calvert. Well, thank you, Mr. Secretary.
    As I mentioned in my opening statement, the fiscal year 
2017 Consolidated Appropriations Act included several changes 
for our fiscal year limits to our forest accounts. The House 
and Senate Appropriations Committee also included directives in 
the statement of managers on the expectations regarding 
improvements to the Service's accounting, budgeting, management 
systems, and practices.
    Have you been able to review the changes in the Act and 
read the statement, Mr. Secretary?
    Secretary Perdue. Well, I am beginning my fifth week on the 
job, so only at a high level. The, obviously, omnibus came out 
within that period of time, and just recently, so I am not as 
specifically detailed. I have the numbers, certainly, in that 
area.
    Once again, my goal is to earn your trust, and as you see 
changes in management of doing things well in those areas, my 
goal is to earn more flexibility in that by proving that we can 
get the job done.
    Mr. Calvert. Well, as you go through that and you get more 
time to look at those changes and directives, we certainly want 
to work with you and help you and the Forest Service improve 
its processes. We are not here to obstruct or make your life 
more complicated.
    We all want the same thing and we think those directives 
are good directives. I hope that you will feel the same way 
after you look at them that they should be followed.
    We believe the Forest Service needs to impose certainly 
more discipline in the accounting, budgeting, and management 
processes, and I know you will be taking that seriously as we 
do, and we will look forward to working with you.
                           CALIFORNIA FORESTS
    I am going to get somewhat parochial now and talk about the 
California forests, the ones that are still standing. We have 
had significant fires in California. The Rim Fire is one that 
comes to mind. But national forests cover about one-fifth, 
which is 20 percent, 20 million acres of the land in California 
that people--you always think of California as an urbanized 
State, but a significant part of California is not.
    Fortunately, California's drought of record is now over. It 
is amazing what 1 year can do. We had a tremendous drought over 
the last number of years, and we had a tremendous amount of 
rain this last year. However, it caused lasting effects for the 
forests and expected to permanently alter forest cover in some 
areas. And we now have more than 100 million dead and dying 
trees in the State. The State and Forest Service have worked to 
remove the trees that pose the most risk to communities, 
however, the work seems to be a little too little and too late.
    So as the drought continued, why didn't the Forest Service 
take more decisive action? I think I already know the answer to 
this question, Chief, but why didn't the Forest Service take 
more decisive action to remove dead and dying trees?
    Mr. Tidwell. Well, Mr. Chairman, we have worked closely 
with the State, and with the Governor's task force to address 
the issue once we started to see the die-off occur. We have 
continued to divert additional funding for the last 2 years and 
again this year.
    Last year, we spent $41 million addressing the concern to 
be able to take out the trees that pose the threat to the 
public and provide access and ingress into the communities and 
also to keep the infrastructure there as far as power lines, 
and also water facilities. Then this year, we are planning to 
use another $37 million to be able to continue to do that work.
    We struggle with finding any market for this material, and 
we are able to remove a little of it, but that is another 
challenge that we are dealing with. We are working closely with 
the State and the local communities to be able to continue to 
address that.
    And even though, as you mentioned, we have had a very, very 
favorable moisture year, we do expect to continue to see more 
die-off to occur. So we are actually moving up into the areas, 
more to the north and be able to get out there, and instead of 
just taking out the dead and dying, to also be thinning out the 
parts of the forest that we have not seen the mortality yet to 
be able to get out ahead of this as we expect to have the 
lingering effects of the drought.
                           CALIFORNIA FORESTS
    Mr. Calvert. Well, I know you have authority to do this, 
and if you need additional authority, please let us know, 
because this is a huge problem in California. We expect--the 
rain is great, but I suspect there is going to be more forest 
fires because we are going to have a lot more brush that can 
burn, and that goes into the forest and that is going to 
potentially cause a big problem this summer. So hopefully we 
are ready to deal with it.
    Ms. McCollum.
    Ms. McCollum. Thank you. Would you put that up?
    Chief Tidwell, I am putting something up here, and we are 
handing out the copies and some photos to the committee 
members.
    Mr. Calvert. Is your mike on?
                               WATERSHEDS
    Ms. McCollum. I need to talk into it. Thank you. Thank you, 
Mr. Chair.
    This is Voyageurs National Park and the Rainey River Basin 
watershed. We come from all different parts of the country. So 
one of the things I wanted to show you, as I am speaking and as 
you are looking at this, is this water knows no boundaries. It 
is going to move. It flows north, not south, because of where 
we are on the Laurentian Divide, and it affects not only the 
Boundary Waters wilderness and Superior National Forest; it 
also affects Voyageurs Park and our neighbors to the north in 
Canada.
    So, Chief Tidwell, as you know, the Superior National 
Forest in Minnesota is the home of the Boundary Waters Canoe 
Area Wilderness. It is vast. It is an interconnected waterway 
of pristine lakes and streams, and this is an untarnished 
wilderness. It is a national treasure. The Forest Service is 
responsible for protecting it.
    Hundreds of thousands of Americans who visit this 
wilderness every year rely on your agency, as well as the 
17,000 Minnesotans who work on the outdoor recreation industry 
in the northeastern region of our State.
    I know that the Forest Service takes this responsibility 
seriously, because last year, the Service denied the renewal of 
mining leases by a foreign-owned company that, as you said, 
posed an unacceptable risk.
    The rejection of these lease renewals noted that, ``copper-
nickel sulfide mining might cause serious and irreplaceable 
harm to this unique, iconic, and irreplaceable wilderness.'' 
Multiple scientific assessments have shown that these sulfide 
ore mines are sources of toxic contamination. Acid drainage 
would cause significant harm to the waterways, aquatic life, 
and the forests that make the Boundary Waters Conoe Area (BWCA) 
such a special place. And in fact, 92 percent, 92 percent of 
the sulfide ore copper mines operating in the United States 
have experienced failures that impact water quality.
    The pictures that are on the other handout that the members 
have show what recently happened in 2014 in Canada. Canada has 
some of the same stringent safeguards that we try to put in 
place, but 92 percent of these mines fail.
    So I want to really give a shout out to the Forest Service 
for the work that you are currently doing with the Department 
of Interior to conduct a 2-year science-based study to 
determine if approximately 230,000 acres of national forest 
lands within the watershed of the Boundary Waters should be off 
limits to sulfide ore copper mining for the next 20 years.
                           MINING WITHDRAWAL
    Last week, the Forest Service staff confirmed with my 
office that you are going to have an additional public meeting 
in the Twin Cities regarding this mining withdrawal, and people 
from southern Minnesota as well as the Twin Cities are very 
appreciative of the Forest Service doing this. You have had 
hearings in northern Minnesota, but we really appreciate the 
ability for the folks in the Twin Cities to go forward.
    I am assuming this meeting is moving forward. I am asking 
you in public, could you please talk about the potential 
consequences for the wildlife, the waters, and the forests in 
the BWCA and the adjacent lands if there is a discharge, a 
leak, or a spill from the sulfide mine, all of which are common 
events for this industry.
    I know that you are receiving phone calls. I know you are 
receiving pressure from the mining industry, and we have a rich 
tradition of mining in Minnesota. This is the only mining in 
Minnesota that I have come out forcefully against, in part, 
because of its location in the watershed.
    So could you please enlighten us on what--and I am going to 
include you, Mr. Secretary--what you two gentlemen can do to 
ensure that this proposed study goes forward as planned so that 
we have robust public participation, grounded in science, and 
figure on how to best preserve this pristine wilderness when 92 
percent, even here in the United States, of these mines fail.
    Mr. Perdue, I think you saw what happened in Canada when it 
leaked up there.
    Mr. Tidwell.
    Secretary Perdue. Well, you have addressed your questions 
to him, if I may precede him in that.
    Ms. McCollum. Oh, yeah. Go ahead.
    Secretary Perdue. As I stated earlier, the buck stops here. 
I am the U.S. Secretary of Agriculture, and the U.S. Forest 
Service is under the Secretary of Agriculture. While we have a 
chief forester who knows the history of this and can address 
those specific questions, I want you to know this is on my 
radar screen as well.
    Secretary Zinke and I have already met about this. And I 
think your statement regarding the two-year study over the 
sound science, none of us know what to do without the facts 
based and the sound science, and we are absolutely allowing 
that to proceed.
    You also know that your State has a shot at that after that 
recommendation as well. So we are determined to proceed in that 
effort and let it run its course. No decision will be made 
prior to the conclusion of that.
    Ms. McCollum. Well, thank you. Governor Dayton will be 
excited to hear that. Thank you.
    Secretary Perdue. Well, he is already well aware of his 
roles and responsibilities in this effort.
    Ms. McCollum. Well, he has taken the State lands off. Thank 
you.
    Mr. Tidwell.
    Mr. Tidwell. Well, the only thing I would add is that the 
study allows us to really pull together the information and the 
data and look at the overall balance.
    Mining is an essential part of multiple-use. It is 
especially very important in your State, but it is also 
essential for this country. We can have mining operations that 
are environmentally safe. There are many that have proven to be 
able to do that.
    You did raise the question about the sulfide ore. That is 
more challenging, especially in areas where we have as much 
water as we do up in that part of the State. So this gives us 
an opportunity to be able to pause, collect the information, to 
be able to visit, and really meet with the public.
    We just want to be able to sit down with them and really 
hear from their concerns. Then as we move forward, to find that 
balance, the balance where mining needs to occur and it can be 
done in a safe, environmental way. Then if decisions are to be 
made for other areas, that it is just potentially maybe too 
hazardous, those are the type of decisions that can come out of 
this study.
    Ms. McCollum. Well, I thank you, gentlemen, for your 
comments, and I thank you for your reassurance to let the 2-
year study go forward. Thank you.
    Secretary Perdue. Let me give you maybe a principle that 
may help your feelings that way. While I might always do right 
and feed everyone, as a veterinarian, I also ascribe to the 
Hippocratic oath. First of all, do no harm, and that we hear 
you loud and clear.
    Ms. McCollum. Thank you, sir.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. And as I look at this map of these 
beautiful pristine lakes, it reminds me of Minnesota's greatest 
exports to California: the Los Angeles Lakers. So I always 
appreciate that.
    Ms. McCollum. Yes. Jerry West was a hero of mine. I do 
remember when Mr. West left.
    Mr. Calvert. Mr. Simpson.
                            LAND MANAGEMENT
    Mr. Simpson. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. And thank you for 
being here, Secretary. As the chairman mentioned, this is the 
first time I can ever remember, maybe the first time ever that 
the Secretary has appeared before this committee, along with 
the chief of the Forest Service. When I look back at it, it was 
almost like there was the Department of Agriculture and the 
Forest Service.
    The Forest Service is going to stay under the Department of 
Agriculture. We have had hearings about trying to move them 
over into a land management agency with Interior. I don't see 
that happening. They do a good job where they are at.
    In fact, I will tell you, I have had a lot of dealings with 
the Forest Service over the years, and while we sometimes 
complain about them. I count 62 people in this room. That means 
there are 62 different people, there are 62 different ideas 
about what should be done with the national forests and how any 
particular decision should be made.
                               LITIGATION
    So these are public lands, and the public has a right to 
say how they are managed. The question is, and you brought it 
up with the Cottonwood case, how do you maintain the public's 
right to have a say in how their public lands are managed and 
get on with managing instead of spending all the resources we 
use in lawsuits?
    I once asked a former chief of the Forest Service, when you 
decide to make a decision on a timber cut, or any decision that 
you make, how much of the money is spent making what you 
believe to be a good, sound, scientific decision, and how much 
is trying to make it bulletproof from a lawsuit?
    And he said given the decision, it is probably between 25 
and 50 percent on making a good, sound, scientific decision, 
and between 50 and 75 percent trying to make it bulletproof. 
Wouldn't it be nice if we could use some of that money to 
actually manage the public lands?
    And this Cottonwood case, and I am glad you brought it up, 
is a perplexing problem that we need to address legislatively. 
I don't have the answer about how we change some of these laws, 
and you could go through the litany of them. It is important to 
maintain the public's right to have a say but we should 
streamline it. We have created situations where you can get 
sued at every step of the way, and there are multiple steps all 
along the way, and it is just unmanageable, frankly.
                              FIRE FUNDING
    Thank you also for mentioning the fire borrowing issue. We 
need your help. We need Secretary Zinke's help, along with this 
committee's, to make everyone understand the importance of 
addressing this issue. Fire borrowing has gotten out of hand. 
When 53 percent of your budget goes to fighting wildfires, that 
means there is no money left for anything else.
    That is one of the reasons my constituents complain about 
the Forest Service. They are not doing any trail maintenance. 
They are not doing fuels reduction. And I noticed in your 
budget that hazardous fuels reduction numbers are down, trail 
maintenance numbers are down, land and water conservation 
numbers are down. Well, we are spending all the money on 
fighting wildfires.
    And when they come up to me and say, I was out hiking and 
they hadn't done any maintenance on this trail, why haven't 
they. I say we have appropriated money for them, but guess 
what, it has gone to fight wildfires.
    Unfortunately, I don't know if this is a good idea or not, 
but what happens is because the Forest Service--and they are 
pretty good firefighters. They do a darn good job when you look 
at the number of fires that they actually put out on initial 
attack. It is the 2 percent that blow up that cause the 
problems. But we allow the Forest Service to borrow from every 
other fund to fight wildfires. It is an emergency, unlike any 
other agency or account.
    I thought of working with Chairman Calvert and see if we 
can strike that language that is in our appropriation bills 
that says you can't borrow from other accounts. The reason 
being, when the rest of the Members of Congress look at the end 
result they say, they must have had the money to put out fires 
because they fought the wildfires and didn't run out of money. 
What they don't see is what is not done because they are 
borrowing the money to fight wildfires.
    And if we stopped the borrowing legislatively--I would 
rather do it with our wildfire fire bill, but if we could stop 
the borrowing legislatively, it would force the Forest Service 
to come to Congress for a supplemental, and then people would 
understand what the true cost of fighting these wildfires are.
    And when you look at it, it has gone from 14 percent of the 
Forest Service budget 30 years ago to 53 percent now, and it is 
projected to be over 70 percent in the next 10 years if nothing 
is done about it. But we need your help, as well as the Members 
of the Congress and outside groups to make our leadership and 
others understand the importance of addressing this issue.
                         FY 2018 BUDGET REQUEST
    While I don't have a question in there, I will tell you 
that within the budget--and I know that you have just come on 
and your job is to support the President's budget. I understand 
all that. I do have some concerns about the reduction in the 
hazardous fuels management, the trail maintenance, LWCF, and 
some other areas within this budget.
    If you really what to see what LWCF has done, when you are 
out to Idaho, I will take you down to South Fork, and it has 
been incredible what LWCF funds have done there.
    Chief, I noticed that you said, when you were talking with 
the chairman about what you are going to do in northern 
California, that you are going to go out and you need to thin 
these forests.
    I suspect the reason you haven't done that is because you 
don't have the money. Last year, when we were hiking at the end 
of August and the fires were going on, you said we should be 
out doing some hazardous fuels reductions, fire mitigation, and 
those types of activities. The problem is we have spent all our 
money on wildfires, and the money is not available.
    That is a real challenge for how we get ahold of this. I 
don't know how you manage a budget where 53 percent of it is 
unknown. But let me also tell you, and since I don't really 
have any questions in there, I do want to tell you I have, 
there are a lot of people who complain about land management in 
the West. That is where most of the public lands are, whether 
it is BLM, Forest Service, Park Service, whatever. And there is 
movement to try to have the States take over all the Federal 
lands. I don't see that happening either.
    It would not happen, and I don't want it to happen in Idaho 
because, frankly, we live in Idaho because we love our public 
lands. We are oftentimes upset with our land managers because, 
as I said, in this room, every one of us could do a better job 
of managing the forest sometimes, or the BLM or whatever, or we 
think we could. We are all good Monday morning quarterbacks.
    They have a tough job. And I tell you, you have got some 
great employees out in Idaho that I have had the opportunity to 
work with that do a fantastic job, and I found that true 
throughout the Forest Service. For as much criticism as they 
get, they really try to manage an almost untenable position 
between the public that wants and believes something should be 
done one way. What I have seen them do is try to work with the 
public, and as you mentioned, try to become advocates for 
trying to solve a problem.
    And maybe they can't do it the way the individual wants it 
done, but what I have seen is they will sit down and try to 
solve problems. And I am proud to call these people my friends 
that have worked out in Idaho and have done a great job of 
maintaining our public lands out there and the reason people 
want to come to Idaho.
    So when you are out there Friday visiting NIFC, I would 
like to try to make it back with you. It is an incredible 
place. Welcome to Idaho early.
    Secretary Perdue. May I respond to your nonquestion?
    Mr. Simpson. Okay.
                               LITIGATION
    Secretary Perdue. I think certainly the litigation issue is 
something we all need to be looking at, whether it is a 
retooling of the NEPA process or those kind of things that are 
in your job and in our jobs, we are never going to please 
everybody. That is what represented democracy is all about, but 
we have got to make the principles of good facts based, data 
driven, sound science decisions, and then move forward.
    I do believe we in the Forest Service have probably been a 
little intimidated and practiced defensive forestry over 
bulletproofing decisions that way and may have rolled over. I 
am willing to go to court on some of these things. If we are 
doing right and if we have got a good scientific base for our 
decisions, I think we need to be in court, if that is what the 
other side chooses to do. I think we need to win some of those 
decisions but first of all, we have got to get our house in 
order of doing the right thing.
                              FIRE FUNDING
    I hope that we will be able to prevail on your best choice, 
which is the fire budget rather than the nuclear option of 
preclusion, because that would put the Chief and us in a pretty 
untenable position having a fire. You can not predict a 
hurricane, you can not predict a tornado, you can not predict a 
flood; and neither can you predict a major forest fire.
    The challenge is, as you indicated, typically one to two 
percent is all we need. If we can get that in the disaster 
budget like these other natural disasters, the Forest Service 
is perfectly capable of managing all these others, and then 
managing the forest.
    So again, from a flexibility standpoint, if we are not too 
handcuffed over those kind of things, we are going to take that 
increase in forest management and do the things that make for 
healthy forests.
    Mr. Simpson. Thank you.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you, Mr. Secretary.
    Mr. Kilmer.
    Mr. Kilmer. Mr. Chair, I will yield to Ms. Pingree, because 
I know she has got to get to another subcommittee.
    Mr. Calvert. Okay.
    Ms. Pingree. Thank you. I appreciate my colleague yielding 
to me, because I know he has to go to another subcommittee too, 
but I appreciate that. I apologize in advance having to go to 
my other committee after this. So I will just be here briefly.
    But it is nice to see you again, Mr. Secretary. It was a 
pleasure to have you in the Agriculture Committee yesterday, 
and thank you for giving us so much time there, and also for 
being here today.
    And, Chief Tidwell, it is nice to see you again.
    My colleagues on the committee have mentioned some of their 
concerns with the budget, and I will submit a variety of things 
for the record. I am concerned that there is nine programs that 
are zeroed out. In particular, the Forest Legacy Program, which 
has been very important to us in Maine. I am concerned about 
the cuts at the Land and Water Conservation Fund. But I just 
want to focus my brief time on two other programs that actually 
are quite important to us and have your comments.
    First one is on the family forestry and forest stewardship. 
Coming from Maine, I know everyone has a lot of forests, but of 
course, we think we have bigger challenges and more of 
everything. Eighty-six percent of our State is forested, and I 
think that might be the highest percentage of any State. We 
don't always think about Maine or New England as having so many 
forests, but we are particularly proud of them, but we also 
have a lot of challenges, and we want to make sure they are 
preserved and well taken care of.
    We have about 264 million acres of land which are basically 
in private ownerships. Unlike many of the Western States, we 
have virtually no Federal land and have a lot of private 
landowners.
    The Forest Stewardship Program leverages millions from our 
State budget and from landowners themselves. It has helped 
landowners learn how to better manage their land, navigate 
numerous challenges to help them determine how to change their 
land management in changing situations, and adapting to new 
market conditions to stay financially viable. So that has been 
very important to us in very changing times.
                            FOREST PRODUCTS
    The forest products industry in our State has a big 
footprint. In 2016, the total economic impact of forest 
products was estimated at $8.5 billion, accounts for more than 
33,000 jobs. That may not seem a lot if you come from 
California, but in a State of 1.3 million people, it is very 
important to our State.
    But we have had a lot of changes in the forest products 
industry. In the last few years, we have seen five paper mills 
close their doors. That has been devastating to communities 
throughout our State and a huge change for us.
    My colleagues and I in the Maine delegation worked with our 
local industry and community leaders to request that the 
Economic Development Administration coordinate and mobilize its 
Federal partners to participate in an economic development 
assessment team. The goal of the EDAT was to help the industry, 
along with the State, local, and Federal leaders, not only to 
coordinate their work, but work together, combine their efforts 
and resources to support our forest industry.
    They spent about 3 days, and the groups did site visits 
around the State of Maine and learned a lot about our industry 
and our forests. And there were a lot of long-term strategic 
goals as well some immediate next steps in what they were 
doing.
    The most direct request was for the Forest Service to work 
with industry to define specific technical assistance data and 
other strategic resources that could support the forest 
industry aspect of the strategic plan. These efforts are 
already under way within our State, and we know that there will 
be additional modeling and support through the Forest Service.
    So between the EDAT and the forestry industry and forestry 
stewardship program, they are just very important to us. Mr. 
Secretary, if you would like to comment, thank you, and Mr. 
Chief, if you want to. Those are just things that we just hope 
will be there in the future and need your support and help.
                       FOREST STEWARDSHIP PROGRAM
    Secretary Perdue. I would comment on the fact that, Ms. 
Pingree, I think the way to accomplish more in tight budgetary 
times really is with public-private partnerships, and that is 
one of the ways we hope to do more with less. The Forest 
Stewardship Program with private landowners is one of those.
    I also come from a State where over 95 percent of them are 
privately managed, and our citizens have utilized those, I 
think, in a very wise way and developed some best practices 
along with our State foresters and our Federal partners to do 
that. So I concur with you.
    Obviously, rural prosperity is a big part of what we do 
overall. I think Mr. Simpson earlier talked about timber and 
agriculture. In Georgia and your State, timber is agriculture.
    Ms. Pingree. Right.
    Secretary Perdue. And that is the way we view it. So we are 
going to do everything we can from a rural prosperity. In 
Maine, it means helping your small organic farmers, as we 
talked about yesterday, it helps your private landowners in 
that renewable resource that grow so well in your beautiful 
State.
    Ms. Pingree. Thank you. I do appreciate that there are a 
lot of similarities between Georgia and Maine. Except the 
temperature, we have a lot in common.
    Secretary Perdue. Our lobsters don't grow as well in 
Georgia.
    Ms. Pingree. Yeah 'And don't start trying.
    Mr. Calvert. Mr. Jenkins.
              MONONGAHELA NATIONAL FOREST--FLOOD RECOVERY
    Mr. Jenkins. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    Mr. Secretary, congratulations. Welcome. Chief, great to 
see you. I would like to maybe ask about two things in 
particular. The Monongahela National Forest has a big chunk in 
my district. We call it The Mon. And last year, in June, we had 
a once in 1,000-year flood in West Virginia. Devastating. 
Almost two dozen lost their lives. The Mon took a real hit.
    In working with the Forest Service, working with the local 
superintendent, I know you have also been working with Federal 
Highways, what can you share with me as an update? The estimate 
was tens of millions of dollars in damage to roads and trails 
and infrastructure. Where are we in that work, if you are able 
to update me? And secondly, what is the road ahead, vis-a-vis, 
this funding cycle in the budget that has been proposed?
    Mr. Tidwell. We are continuing to collect information about 
all the damage that has occurred, because we have also, just in 
the last few weeks, have had additional flooding in West 
Virginia. We are working closely with Federal Highways to be 
able to use their emergency road funding, and we are applying 
to Federal Highways for funding, and going through a process to 
really prioritize what is the absolutely most important 
projects to get completed and the most urgent, to realize that 
it is going to take awhile and it is, as the Secretary 
mentioned, it is going to take a need for all of us to work 
together, the State, the counties, the Federal agencies to come 
together to be able to address this.
    Our first focus, of course, is going to be on public 
safety, especially on some bridges, to be able to maintain the 
highest priority roads. Some of those are actually used for 
school routes, for school bus routes.
    So that is what we are doing. And as we are completing the 
analysis, we are out there doing the urgent stuff to be able to 
get as many of these roads open, but it is going to be a little 
while, and I will be glad to provide you a more extensive 
update.
    [The information follows:]
    Mr. Jenkins. I would welcome that. We are, obviously, very 
engaged with it. We have got incredible need. This is the time, 
as we have seen, since last June to, collect the information, 
make the down payment, but also we understand this is a 
journey, not a point in time conclusion.
    So we really truly want to work with the Forest Service, 
your local superintendent. We want to help make sure you do get 
that data collection. I want to make sure I am doing what I can 
from a funding standpoint to address those needs. I am trying 
to avoid any surprises 6 months from now or a year from now 
that, well, the money just wasn't there. So please make sure we 
are fully aware of the needs as identified.
     MONONGAHELA NATIONAL FOREST--TIMBER SALES AND SPECIFIC HABITAT
    The second, and also for you, Chief, it certainly plays on 
what the Secretary referenced, is still relating to The Mon. 
With regard to the forest management, and in particular, the 
timber sales, this is an ongoing frustration and challenge that 
we have seen, and I just need to figure out how to break this 
logjam. Pardon the pun. The Mon is 919,000 acres, 12 percent 
set aside as wilderness. But under the allowable sales 
quantities under the forest plan, each year, for the last 4, 5, 
6 years, we have only been selling about 12 percent of what is 
allowed. So for example, in 2016, only 12 percent was sold; 
2015, 10 percent was sold; 2014, 13 percent was sold.
    What are the impediments to a forest plan objective that 
has an allowable sale quantity, but each year we are in the 10, 
11, 12 percent actually sold? What is going on? What can we do 
about it? This is basic good forest management practice.
    Mr. Tidwell. First of all, I share your frustration. There 
is a combination of things that several members and the 
Secretary have already mentioned that we are working on. Your 
forest has history when it comes to environmental issues that 
go way back in time. We have been able to move forward on many 
of those concerns.
    So today, where we are at, is to be able to find more 
capacity. One of the things where we are making, I think, some 
great progress is using the Good Neighbor Authority that you 
provided with the 2014 Farm Bill so that we can work with the 
State forester and their staff to be able to actually get more 
work done out on the ground and use their capacity, and also to 
be able to learn from them.
    Many of our States have, I believe, some better practices 
than some of the things that we have in place that I could 
argue were put in place years ago because of certain lawsuits. 
We are finding, by being able to use the Good Neighbor 
Authority and working with the States, we are able to actually 
get more work done, get more timber harvested, and then to be 
able to do it in a way that we can cover the State's costs.
    So this is one of the things that we are really making some 
good progress on. I think your forest, especially, is one that 
is placed for us to move out using that authority.
    Mr. Jenkins. Well, if progress is being defined as 
percentage of allowable sold, we are not making progress.
    Secretary Perdue. I hear you loud and clear, Mr. Jenkins. 
Those numbers that you just described are pretty frustrating to 
me, and we will have a better answer and a better reason by the 
next time I come before you.
    Mr. Jenkins. Thank you.
    Secretary Perdue. I put this chart, Mr. Chairman, in your 
package there. Our forests are renewable resources. Forests are 
just like us and animals. If you do not do something with them 
while they are healthy, they die, and then they create more 
problems with fire and other things.
    So these are not good statistics here, and our goal is to 
make sure that we harvest the renewable part of our forest. We 
would love to have that balance. We talked about some of the 
root causes regarding the budget and the management aspect, but 
that is absolutely my goal is to use the resources from our 
jobs, from our revenue standpoint.
    These are crops. Those are crops there that ought to be 
harvested for the benefit of the American public.
    Mr. Jenkins. A breath of fresh air, Mr. Secretary. We look 
forward to working with you. We look forward to that better 
answer, and we look forward to getting her done. Thank you.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you.
    Mr. Kilmer.
           COLLABORATIVE FOREST LANDSCAPE RESTORATION PROGRAM
    Mr. Kilmer. Thanks, Mr. Chairman. And thanks for being with 
us.
    I have got one question for the Secretary and one for Chief 
Tidwell. Mr. Secretary, as everyone is extending invitations to 
you, I will do the same. We had the honor of having your 
predecessor come out to visit the Olympic Peninsula to see how 
important the Forest Service lands are to the rural timber-
dependent communities that I represent and to visit with the 
Olympic Penninsula Forest Collaborative that is really making 
progress towards increasing harvest levels in a responsible 
way.
    We have got the conservation community and the industry at 
the same table working through some of these tough issues, and 
I think it addresses a couple of the issues that you raised. 
One, the value of public-private partnership, and two, trying 
to reduce litigation when it comes to timber sales.
    Having said that, I am somewhat surprised to see the 
elimination of funding for the Collaborative Forest Landscape 
Restoration Program in the budget, because I just think it is 
fundamentally important to sound stewardship and was hoping 
that you could just speak to what the rationale was for that 
program elimination.
    Secretary Perdue. Well, certainly beginning my job here, I 
support the budget and its conclusions, but I think probably it 
would have been a little different had we been there long 
enough to have an impact in that area. The reason we were given 
was some duplicative programs, but I already expressed my 
desire to see more public-private partnerships. And we hope to 
persuade others in the administration that we think we can get 
more bang for the buck that way.
    Mr. Kilmer. Well, we would certainly love to have you see 
the success that our collaborative has had, but we need more 
help.
    Secretary Perdue. As for the visit, I hope to get your way 
soon. We are heading that way. We were in the Black Hills over 
the past weekend. We are going to be in Idaho next weekend, so 
we are moving your way.
    Mr. Kilmer. If you get any further west than me, you are in 
the ocean.
    Secretary Perdue. Yes. We are not going to Victoria Island.
                        LEGACY ROADS AND TRAILS
    Mr. Kilmer. Chief Tidwell, I think the last time I saw you 
was at an event celebrating the Legacy Roads and Trails Program 
and the removal of the 1,000th culvert. It was a pretty 
spectacular event in that you had recreationalists, sports 
fishermen, and a bunch of different stakeholders celebrating 
both the economic and ecological benefits of what is a pretty 
modest program.
    So this is another program that I was pretty shocked to see 
eliminated. According to your own budget justification, since 
2008, Legacy Roads and Trails has restored fish passage at 
1,000 sites, providing access to over 1,000 miles of habitat, 
improved almost 18,000 miles of road for safety and flood 
resiliency, constructed or reconstructed 141 bridges for 
safety, upgraded or fixed 4,390 miles of trails so people can 
actually enjoy the areas that they love, and created or 
maintained 800 to 1,200 jobs annually.
    It is really hard to argue with the success of this 
program, so I am hoping you can help me understand the 
rationale for eliminating it.
    Mr. Tidwell. Well, I would just like to basically repeat 
what the Secretary has said, but one of the reasons, the 
funding that is provided with Legacy Roads and Trails, we can 
do that same work with our trails budget and with our roads 
budget. Where it has been an effective program to really focus 
on the legacy work to be able to improve and deal with stream 
crossings and culverts, it is something we can do within our 
other budget line items. We are going to continue to do that 
work and be able to build on the partnership, but we will be 
able to continue that with our other budget line items.
    Secretary Perdue. I think prior to you coming in, there 
were two budget items that we would love to have your help on, 
and obviously, trails is one of those. We know, from an 
economic perspective as well as a recreation perspective, if 
you can not maintain, you can not get to it, you can not cut 
trees, and you can not have--enjoy the beautiful landscape. So 
we appreciate your help there.
    Mr. Kilmer. Thank you.
    Thanks, Mr. Chairman. I yield back.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you.
    Mr. Stewart.
                                GRAZING
    Mr. Stewart. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    And, Mr. Perdue, congratulations on your new 
responsibilities.
    Chief, thank you for the time and extraordinary effort you 
have made in some cases to help people in the rural west.
    I know of one example where you flew out to my district and 
met with some of our county commissioners and flew back the 
same day. That is an example of you trying to make yourself 
available and trying to hear them, and I think that is so 
important.
    I love the fact that you are here together. And I would 
like to mimic something you said, Mr. Secretary, if I could, 
and that is, these are--our forests are national jewels. There 
is a reason I live in Utah. It is because I love Utah, and part 
of that is loving the forests.
    But they are also a resource. And as you said, Mr. 
Secretary, they are like a crop. They are a renewable resource, 
and properly managed, they can be a very effective economic 
resource that we could take such advantage of.
    I would like to make one point very quickly and then come 
to you, Chief, if I could, for an issue that I have been 
concerned about. We often talk about their value to us in 
timber, and that has been brought up several times here. But 
when I hike, as I often do in Utah, or at least I used to when 
I had a life before I came to Congress, but it wouldn't be 
unusual to see cattle grazing in our forest. And my father-in-
law has a permit where he would graze his cattle in the forest.
    Do we agree--and again, this is a simple question. Do we 
agree that that is a part of management as well in taking 
proper advantage of this resource?
    Secretary Perdue. Absolutely. I would like to expand on 
that a little bit. By the way, I was in Rapid City, South 
Dakota this last weekend and Ellsworth Air Force base. There 
was a little airplane over there I think you may be familiar 
with.
    Mr. Stewart. Just a little airplane, yes.
    Secretary Perdue. Got up in the cockpit of the B-1 and I 
kind of chided them from stealing that from Robins Air Force 
Base, but we had a National Guard group down there, wing, that 
flew that airplane, I had been in it before.
    Mr. Stewart. Well, we can agree it is the sexiest aircraft 
ever built, right?
    Secretary Perdue. And pretty effective, as well. But on 
your specific question, certainly in your area, as well, I 
think grazing is a realistic management. I was in Northern 
Nebraska over our grasslands there, our cattle ranchers are 
doing things on their own lands that thrive and make good 
management practices. We want to adopt more of those.
    Frankly, I hope Secretary Zinke, and I, and you can go out 
to your area and hear from your people, not just the elected 
officials, but hear from those cattle ranches, hear from those 
people who have to deal with our Forest Service and our Bureau 
of Land Management (BLM) lands and let us really develop a 
level of trust and a good neighbor policy there that is more 
than just a name. We have a good neighbor policy officially, 
but being a good neighbor is more than just saying I am one, so 
I hope we can do that in your area.
    Mr. Stewart. Yes.
    Secretary Perdue. So I hope we can do that in your area.
             DEPARTMENT OF LABOR--OVERTIME AND MINIMUM WAGE
    Mr. Stewart. And, Mr. Secretary, I am so grateful to hear 
you say that. I can tell you I grew up ranching and farming, 
and no one cares more about that land than those individuals 
who their livelihood depends on that resource being healthy, 
and they are as intrinsically interested in protecting it as 
anyone I can imagine.
    Chief, if I could come to you with a problem, as I said, I 
am a little bit frustrated, and I think we have talked about it 
before. 2014 the Department of Labor instituted a rule 
regarding overtime and minimum wage for Federal employees, 
which they had the right to do, and I don't object to that, but 
where we have a problem is it caught up, I think, individuals 
that it was never intended to be, that is outfitters and guides 
who work in the rural west.
    You know, people who take people on horseback rides, river 
rafting, et cetera, who help tourists and people who otherwise 
wouldn't be able to experience the west because they just 
wouldn't do it on their own.
    But they were defined as a Federal employee because they 
happened to traverse Federal lands or in some cases operate on 
Federal lands. And, you know, we worked with the Department, 
again in this case the Department of Labor, for a year, more 
than a year, trying to get them to relook at us and saying this 
isn't the intent. They actually agreed with us, at least they 
told us they did, though nothing came from that. We included 
legislation in the appropriations or language in the fiscal 
year 2016 appropriations bill, which would have exempted them 
from this.
    And I have to say before I make my final point, these 
aren't big corporate outfits and guides these are mom-and-pop 
shops, you know, people who are making a lot less money than 
most of us here in this room. And they just simply can't afford 
it. I mean, an outfitter out there hits 40 hours in the first 
two days, and after that he has got to be paid overtime on a 
minimum wage, a Federal defined minimum wage.
    It frustrates me that it seems like the Forest Service has 
ignored the intent of Congress because their permit requires 
still that they comply with this. I wonder if you could give us 
some relief on that and some hope that we can work together to 
come to what I think most of us agree is a reasonable 
conclusion.
    Mr. Tidwell. I appreciate you bringing it back up again. 
Well, we will go back to see what we can do to address that and 
continue to work with the Department of Labor.
    I agree with your point that most of the outfitter and 
guide operations I know are usually family operations, and its 
relatives, or you could even say they are all part owners in 
that operation, and I don't even think they work by the hour, 
they just work by the day to provide that service. It is one of 
the things that we work with the Department of Labor and will 
continue to do that to be able to address a solution there so 
that it doesn't have unintended consequences of impacting their 
operations.
    Mr. Stewart. I appreciate that, Chief, and we will pursue 
that with you, and if I could just conclude, and, Mr. 
Secretary, it seems like you want to respond----
    Secretary Perdue. Yeah. I think there are a lot of 
unintended consequences regarding that labor rule that we want 
to look at as it pertains to the USDA, and obviously outfitting 
is a seasonal job. They do not work year-round. Seasons do not 
last that long, and that caught up a lot of seasonal workers 
that is very intense for a period of time, that is when they 
have to work and make their money, and so we will be very 
attentive to that.
    Mr. Stewart. Well, please do, and I will conclude with 
this. I met with many of these owners, dozens of times, I 
suppose, but I have also met with generally college kids who 
come to me and say, Look, I don't get to do what I used to love 
to do. I was more than happy to do this for the wage they were 
paying me. I was doing it because I love it, and now my job has 
gone away, and now I am working at Walmart or McDonald's when I 
would much rather be out showing people the land.
    So thank you, and we look forward to working with you on 
that. Chairman, I yield back.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. Ms. Kaptur.
    Ms. Kaptur. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, and welcome, Mr. 
Secretary.
    Secretary Perdue. Thank you.
                         FOREST SERVICE BUDGETS
    Ms. Kaptur. Chief Tidwell, thank you for your service to 
our country.
    According to the numbers that I have, and I hope they are 
correct, in the fiscal year 2016 the Forest Service had a 
budget of $7.03 billion. For this fiscal year what was finally 
signed into law was 6.17 billion. And for the proposal we are 
reviewing now it has gone down to $5.20 billion. That is a cut 
of 26 percent over the last 3 years. That is in my judgment 
enormous.
                      URBAN AND COMMUNITY FORESTRY
    I don't come from the west. I come from up where the U.S. 
border meets the Canadian border over Lake Erie. Congressman 
Joyce and I share this very important region with the 
shallowest of the Great Lakes in deep trouble.
    And when I look at this budget, I see that though Ohio is 
not like Utah and California and big western States with big 
Federal forest lands, trees are terribly important to us. Lake 
Erie has the least number of trees surrounding it of any of the 
Great Lakes. We have the most threatened of the Great Lakes. My 
home community of Toledo, Ohio, which has water systems that 
serve a region of half a million to 750 million people plus 
businesses was shut off two and-a-half years ago for 3 days 
because a very wicked little toxin called microcystin that 
forms an algae got into the water system.
    It is not the only water system on Lake Erie that has been 
shut off. Many of our rural water systems have been shut off 
over the last couple years. They didn't get a lot of publicity 
because we are not New York City, we are not Chicago. You know, 
we are out there on Lake Erie, and I will tell you what, it was 
completely frightening. And we live with this hanging over our 
heads every day, and the situation is not getting better.
    I won't go into all the details of what we are trying to do 
to address it, but because we don't have the full engagement of 
the Forest Service along Lake Erie because we are using the 
Urban and Community Forestry Program, which this budget 
proposes to eliminate along with the Community Forest and Open 
Space Program, and the Landscape Scale Restoration Program. We 
are trying to find ways to deal with planting 20 million trees 
we have to replace just because of the emerald ash borer just 
to keep pace with an inadequate number of trees to begin with 
to operate as buffer strips to help to filter the nutrients 
going into Lake Erie from the Maumee River. The largest river--
God gave me the largest river in the Great Lakes, and with no 
resources to try to fix what is wrong.
    The NRCS has been great, Mr. Secretary, in trying to help 
us figure out what do we do with a tri-state bi-national 
watershed in order to prevent these nutrients from going into 
the rivers and streams and falling toward the lake, and your 
NRCS people in Ohio have been phenomenal. They are 
underresourced. There is no political jurisdiction that can put 
their arms around this region. And it is frightening to see 
what is happening.
    Cleveland, at the eastern end of my district, and the 
western end of David's district, used to be called Forest City. 
And with the levels of asthma there and other issues and many 
urban areas.
    I frankly take it as a personal offense that the Government 
of the United States, not you, but that the government of this 
country doesn't consider the Great Lakes and our urban areas 
important enough to focus on trees. We are always off, you 
know, in other areas that I feel sorry for because there is not 
enough money to keep trails. Deferred maintenance in this 
budget is eliminated. Legacy and Trails Program eliminated. 
Facilities accounts, 84 percent cut. I mean, I feel sorry for 
you, trying to take over this. I keep saying, where are we 
going to get some private sector people to donate money to fill 
the gap here.
    But I would love to invite you to our region because it is 
the canary in the coal mine. Your dad, I like his quote, ``We 
are all stewards of the land, owned or rented, and our 
responsibility is to leave it better than we found it.'' I 
couldn't agree more. NRCS sponsored a book one time called 
``Land, Food, and People.'' I loved it, but there was a word 
missing, and that was ``water.''
                               WATERSHEDS
    And what we face in our region is that in the two 
watersheds I represent, but the one that is causing the most 
problems that extends over three States and Canada, there are 
two million people that live in that watershed. There are 
between 10 and 11 million animals, the largest egg-producing 
region in the whole country, generating 43,500 train carloads 
of manure every year, much of it put on the land. And we've got 
no answer.
    When I was born there were 146 million people in this 
country. Today there are 320 million. By 2050 we will have 390 
million according to the latest projections, and somehow the 
formula for land, food, water, and people, to say nothing of 
temperature changes, it is not a winning formula.
    So we would invite you to our region. We would fly in your 
helicopter if you want to.
    Secretary Perdue. I would like that.
                           USDA MISSION AREAS
    Ms. Kaptur. NRCS has to play a role in this. I have a bill 
to recreate the Civilian Conservation Corp to help the whole 
country, including our area, and I got some ideas about it 
would require more than USDA, it would require Department of 
Labor, National Guard. We got to fix this, and I want to do it 
in my lifetime.
    So that we do what your dad said in our time and 
generation. It is our responsibility. And, unfortunately, we 
don't have structure to do it.
    I think NRCS is one of the few structures we really have, 
but it is not used to working across jurisdictions, and States. 
And we need its help. So we got the problem. We don't have the 
mechanism to fix it. And the problem is getting ahead of us 
just like in the west.
    I will tell you, I don't live in the west. The forest fires 
scare me to death because I studied a little bit about forest 
succession. I worry about the eastern forests, as well as the 
western forests. We are not taking care of this problem for the 
country. We simply aren't. And it is not true to our heritage.
    I just thank all the people that work for the Forest 
Service. I feel sorry for the firefighters, all those people 
that risk their lives up there all the time. We are not doing 
our job, and we have got to figure out a way to do it. If we 
have to beg the private sector and go to Goldman Sachs and all 
these people that ripped off the people of the United States 
and beg the money, I am willing to do it. But we gotta fix 
this.
    So my extension of an invitation is very serious. We need 
your help, and we need it fast. Ohio and Michigan, if we could 
figure out how to plant 20 million trees in the next 5 years 
that wouldn't be enough, but it would be a heck of a lot better 
than our limping along with what we are doing now.
    So that is just my statement and my concern about your 
budget, and we will work with you and our great chairman and 
ranking member to try to produce something better.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you, Marcy.
    Secretary Perdue. I appreciate your concern and your 
passion. I have heard great things about the Great Lakes 
Restoration Project. I think we were making progress in that, 
as well as the Chesapeake. And we hope we will have the 
opportunity to continue that.
    As a former governor, you know I know how this government 
works. We have an executive branch that proposes. We have an 
legislative branch that legislates and appropriates. We have 
got a judicial branch. So I hope all together we can come 
together and address some of those concerns certainly so we can 
leave it better than we found it.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. Mr. Joyce. The Great Lakes are well 
represented here today.
                           EMERALD ASH BORER
    Mr. Joyce. Secretary Purdue, Chief Tidwell, thank you very 
much for being here today.
    I was happy to hear you call trees an agricultural product, 
having owned a small Christmas tree farm. I thought this would 
be a wonderful way for our family to all work together, and I 
found the kids only liked it when they were selling the trees 
and giving out candy canes and not doing much else during the 
course of the year.
    But I would like to follow up on my colleague from Ohio Ms. 
Kaptur's comments about the emerald ash borer. You brought up 
the Great Lakes Restoration Initiative (GLRI), and you happened 
to be able to get some of that money to help prevent what is a 
100 percent mortality rate with the emerald ash borer, but I 
understand only the Wayne National Forest is in Ohio.
    I know it is not necessarily part of your purview, but are 
you doing anything to help people or nongovernmental entities 
surrounding the forest systems to try to combat this emerald 
ash borer because having lost this in my own yard, once they 
are in there, boom, all your trees are dead within years. It 
really has become a problem.
    It is restricted. You can't even use it for firewood, 
transferring county to county, and we really need some help.
    Secretary Perdue. The Chief can address this specifically, 
but my goal, my principles are in cooperation with the Forest 
Service is just almost like the Ag Extension Service. We have 
got an education, a research education communication network 
out here, and that is where many of these private partnerships 
working with State and private landowners have been so 
effective in communicating what they can do.
    I have got a picture here in the west that talks about good 
forest management and how it impacts that. So the Chief may 
know more specifically about the emerald borer, but the 
principle is we want Forest Service to be an educational tool 
to get best practices both for private lands and for public 
lands.
    Mr. Joyce. I have got to tell you, Mr. Secretary, that is 
music to our ears. Because part and parcel of the GLRI is also 
educating the farmers to reduce the amount of fertilizer, and 
they get higher yields with less fertilizer but when the State 
comes in and says they are going to cut down on the amount they 
can use, well, the first thing a guy does is overloads the 
field to make sure he is in before the edict is actually 
implemented. So you really want to try to educate them.
    There are so many ways they can do that now. I am amazed. I 
was at one combine with a guy who uses his iPad, not even 
touching the steering wheel. We are going down the field, and 
he is measuring the soils and less fertilizer, higher yields, 
it all works but it is going to take education, just what you 
are saying.
    Secretary Perdue. It would. And technology and rural 
broadband connectivity. They depend on being able to connect 
into the data systems that do that. So there are a lot of 
opportunities, a lot of challenges, but that is why we are 
here.
    And I look forward to visiting your area. I am not as 
familiar with the border of Lake Erie as I could be. I lived in 
Ohio, down at Columbus, in the middle seventies in the Air 
Force but didn't make it up to your beautiful area.
    Ms. Kaptur. You are welcome.
    Mr. Joyce. Love to have you. If you like to fish we have 
some pretty good fishing, too. Chairman Calvert wants to come 
too and catch some walleye. Excuse me, Chief.
    Mr. Tidwell. Just quickly, we still haven't found a 
solution to the emerald ash borer, and our scientists are 
working with the other agriculture agencies and also with 
universities to find some type of--ideally a biological control 
on this pest that came into this country through one of our 
ports and now has spread all the way up to Canada.
    One of the things we are working with is the places to get 
out in front of it and actually have to clear out the ash to 
just be able to stop the spread. That is one of the tools that 
has been helpful, but when you are out in the country that is 
something you can do, but as it is going through communities, 
it is not what people want to see their ash trees cut down.
    So it is just still challenging, but it does make the point 
about our research and development branch of the forest service 
that we work very closely with the other agencies and 
universities for us to be able to maintain that, and this 
budget request does allow us to be able to maintain our 
research with the emerald ash borer to be able to find that 
solution. At the same time to be able to do what we can to 
prevent the next pest from coming in to this country, through 
our ports.
    Ms. Kaptur. Would the gentleman yield?
    Mr. Joyce. Absolutely.
    Ms. Kaptur. Could I ask, on the emerald ash borer and the 
loss of ash trees, do you know, sir, how many we have lost 
already and what the projected loss is and what percentage that 
comprises of our ash tree population?
    I just know Ohio and Michigan. I don't know the whole 
country number.
    Mr. Tidwell. I can provide that information to you, but it 
is devastating to the ash in the east, and if we can't find a 
solution to this, there is a high likelihood we will lose the 
ash tree from the Eastern United States.
    [The information follows:]
    It is estimated that the emerald ash borer has killed more 
than 100 million trees in the cities and rural forests of the 
30 States in which it is currently found. According to FIA 
estimates, the total number of ash trees on forested lands is 
9.4 billion (this does not include urban areas). The most 
recent National Insect and Disease Risk Map estimates that more 
than 700,000 acres of ash forests are at risk to EAB-caused 
mortality in the next 15 years. The Forest Service does not 
track the total numbers of ash trees in forested rural and 
urban areas.
    Mr. Joyce. Wow.
    Mr. Tidwell. I wish I had a more positive response, but 
that is the challenge we are up against.
    Mr. Joyce. Isn't that what is used to make baseball bats?
    Mr. Tidwell. Yes.
    Voice. Baseball is gone, then we are into basketball.
    Mr. Tidwell. Aluminum.
    Ms. Kaptur. If you go through one of the communities I 
represent it is like you take a razor and you just zzzzzz, you 
go right, and they are gone. It is astounding.
    Mr. Joyce. Thank you both. I yield back, Mr. Chairman.
                            AVIATION ASSETS
    Mr. Calvert. I have a number of questions I am going to 
submit to you for the record, but one thing I would like to 
talk about quickly is some of our Forest Service aviation 
assets. As you know, we had $65 million in fiscal year 2015 
account that was to acquire an additional aircraft. So I was 
wondering what the status of that acquisition is and when do 
you expect to award the contract, and do you anticipate the 
award will be contested?
    Mr. Tidwell. We are currently reviewing the bids we 
received to acquire an aircraft, and I expect I can report back 
to the committee in the next few weeks on the progress of that.
    As to the second question, that is always just part of the 
process.
    Secretary Perdue. My question would be, how many people 
make the 130J?
    Mr. Calvert. I think you know what State it is from, too. 
You might like that aircraft.
    Also, the Defense Authorization Act in 2014, as you 
remember, transferred seven HC-130Hs from the Coast Guard and 
15 C-23 Sherpas from the Army just to the Forest Service, and 
we provided $130 million for the planes to be retrofitted.
    So I would like to get the status of where those aircraft 
are right now, what is the status of those transfers, if they 
have happened, and where we are on the retrofit.
    Mr. Tidwell. We will be flying one HC-130H again this 
summer, and then fiscal year 2019 we will have two C-130Hs with 
the tank installed. Then in fiscal year 2020 we will have four 
more. Then by fiscal year 2021 we will have all seven of those 
with the tanks installed.
    There was an issue with the contract Air Force was using to 
install the tanks. It slowed down the progress there, but as 
they have put on the new wing boxes on those planes, we take 
one each year and we fly that with a MAFS unit and then rotate 
that back in to be able to get the internal tank installed.
    Mr. Calvert. Okay. Good. Ms. McCollum.
    Ms. McCollum. Thank you. Back to the aircraft, when I was 
up in Northern Minnesota talking to the pilots, they said it is 
really hard to get pilots right now because of what is going on 
in the industry. So I hope as we get the planes we can retain 
the pilots, and if you need any flexibility with how you go 
about retaining and recruiting pilots, please keep us apprised.
    Mr. Chair, I am also going to submit some questions for the 
record. As Secretary Purdue and Mr. Tidwell know, we want to be 
helpful on the backlog of maintenance. There is an inspector 
general's report on that, so I know that you are capable of 
getting us the ash tree number.
                            INVASIVE SPECIES
    Let me just put a couple statistics out there. I don't 
represent Minneapolis, but it is part of the Twin Cities. Five 
thousand trees a year are being lost until the city's public 
ash trees are gone. That is how much they are cutting down a 
year.
    And in Saint Paul where I live 8,500 boulevard ashes have 
been removed so far. The pace is increasing. We take them down 
in the winter when the little pests aren't active.
    By the end, we think that over 60,000 trees will be gone. 
It is important we remove them in the urban areas because how 
they got here to the Twin Cities was hitchhiking on railroad 
cars. So if we don't get them down as the railroad cars and the 
shortlines go through, these little pests will figure out a way 
to get on them and go into more rural areas.
    This is really an all hands on deck to reduce the spread of 
this from going any further east than the Mississippi River. So 
I appreciate the work that the Forest Service Station in the 
Twin Cities and the St. Paul Campus for the University of 
Minnesota are doing together.
    This is all hands on deck, and we are going to see more and 
more of this as the climate puts more stress with the climate 
change on our forests and hardwood.
    So I want to thank the Forest Service, and thank you Mr. 
Perdue. It was a delight meeting you today.
    I thank you for your support of keeping our pristine waters 
clean in the northern part of our United States.
                              BARK BEETLE
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you. We will be closing down here in a 
minute, unless there is any further comment.
    But one comment about these invasive species. I am from 
California, and we have not just the bark beetle, which is 
obviously devastating the forest, but since we have you here in 
the citrus industry, which is kind of important in my State 
still. It has literally wiped out the citrus industry in 
Florida, as you know. It is in Texas now. So it is in 
California, except it is not as affected at this point. They 
found some in the Hacienda Heights area.
    Mr. Simpson. Mr. Chairman, I just want you to know that in 
parts of Idaho, we consider Californians an invasive species.
    Ms. Kaptur. Mr. Chairman----
    Mr. Calvert. With that I think we may adjourn here pretty 
soon.
    Ms. Kaptur. Mr. Chairman.
    Mr. Calvert. Yes.
                          USDA REORGANIZATION
    Ms. Kaptur. I would just, since the Secretary is here and 
he has been very gracious with his time, I wanted to just ask 
you when you realigned USDA and you put farm production and 
conservation together, could you expound a little bit on how 
that relates to the Forest Service and what is your thinking?
    Secretary Perdue. Sure. As you know, NRCS was under the 
missionary of the Forest Service. The Forest Service has about 
a third of the employees of USDA and in many areas. We have got 
a lot of challenges. As I went around and I heard it looked 
like to me we had a lot of challenges for forest management and 
the Forest Service. I wanted someone, first of all, who was 
dedicated to resolving many of those issues of the questions 
you raised this morning.
    The second point was NRCS is a customer-facing 
responsibility. There are more aligned with the Farm Service 
Agency and the risk manager from a producer standpoint. So 
those missionaries are going to be under one Undersecretary and 
have three directors there that collaborate.
    Our data systems weren't talking to one another, and 
sometimes we were colocated, but it was all separating. We act 
like we were separate agencies. So this is a customer-facing 
responsibility trying to fulfill our customer service 
responsibility.
    The other thing on the realignment had to do with rural 
development. As I said, I am not a micromanager, but I am a 
hands-on manager. I wanted that person with access to be on a 
walk-in basis where we got projects we can move quickly, rather 
than having to float up through a chain and sometimes lose the 
opportunity, so that was the purpose.
    Ms. Kaptur. Thank you sir.
    I just wanted to say that I would very much appreciate your 
review of my bill on a Civilian Conservation Corps. You can 
redline it. You can amend it. You can do anything you want, but 
I would be very interested to hear what you think about it, and 
how we might achieve it. Thank you.
    Mr. Calvert. Thank you.
    Secretary Perdue. If I can close, I probably should have 
started this, but I wanted to see in this packet.
    This is healthy forest versus unhealthy forest. This was 
from the Black Hills. I was there last weekend. And it just 
shows you what good thinning management can do.
    This is the mountain pine beetle, one of those species that 
can be--those brown where trees have died there. The green 
areas where they had been thinned ahead of time. That is why it 
is so important we get the forest budget straightened out so we 
can do more of this all over our forests there.
    So we have used over a thousand words, but that picture is 
worth a thousand words there.
    Mr. Calvert. Well, thank you, Secretary Perdue. We 
appreciate you getting on top of this and working with our 
chief, Chief Tidwell. We appreciate all your years of service, 
and with that we are adjourned.
                                            Thursday, June 8, 2017.
                       DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR
</option>
    <witnesses>WITNESSES</witnesses>
</Hearing>
