<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing>
    <info>[House Hearing, 115 Congress]</info>
    <info>[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]</info>
    <Doc-title>DISCUSSION DRAFT OF H.R. ______, " COMMUNITY RECLAMATION PARTNER-SHIPS  ACT "</Doc-title>
    <option>                                 ACT''
=======================================================================
                          LEGISLATIVE HEARING
                               before the
</option>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON ENERGY AND</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                           MINERAL RESOURCES
                                 of the
</option>
    <committee_name>COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES</committee_name>
    <option>                     U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                        Wednesday, May 24, 2017
                               __________
                            Serial No. 115-8
                               __________
       Printed for the use of the Committee on Natural Resources
         Available via the World Wide Web: http://www.fdsys.gov
                                   or
          Committee address: http://naturalresources.house.gov
                                  ______
                         U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE 
25-554 PDF                     WASHINGTON : 2017 
-----------------------------------------------------------------------
  For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing 
  Office Internet: bookstore.gpo.gov Phone: toll free (866) 512-1800; 
         DC area (202) 512-1800 Fax: (202) 512-2104 Mail: Stop IDCC, 
                          Washington, DC 20402-0001
</option>
    <comitteeM_name>COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES</comitteeM_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>ROB BISHOP</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>RAUL M. GRIJALVA</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ranking Democratic Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Don Young</Pname>
        <Plocation> AK</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Grace F. Napolitano</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Chairman Emeritus</Pname>
        <Plocation>Chairman Emeritus</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Madeleine Z. Bordallo</Pname>
        <Plocation> GU</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Louie Gohmert</Pname>
        <Plocation> TX</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jim Costa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Chairman</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Gregorio Kilili Camacho Sablan</Pname>
        <Plocation> </Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug Lamborn</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>CNMI</Pname>
        <Plocation>CNMI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Robert J. Wittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Niki Tsongas</Pname>
        <Plocation> MA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Tom McClintock</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jared Huffman</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Stevan Pearce</Pname>
        <Plocation> NM</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Ranking Member</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Ranking Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Glenn Thompson</Pname>
        <Plocation> PA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Alan S. Lowenthal</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul A. Gosar</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Donald S. Beyer</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Raul R. Labrador</Pname>
        <Plocation> ID</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Norma J. Torres</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Scott R. Tipton</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Ruben Gallego</Pname>
        <Plocation> AZ</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug LaMalfa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Colleen Hanabusa</Pname>
        <Plocation> HI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jeff Denham</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Nanette Diaz Barragan</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul Cook</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darren Soto</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Bruce Westerman</Pname>
        <Plocation> AR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jimmy Panetta</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Garret Graves</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>A. Donald McEachin</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jody B. Hice</Pname>
        <Plocation> GA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Anthony G. Brown</Pname>
        <Plocation> MD</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Aumua Amata Coleman Radewagen</Pname>
        <Plocation> AS</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Wm. Lacy Clay</Pname>
        <Plocation> MO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darin LaHood</Pname>
        <Plocation> IL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Daniel Webster</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>David Rouzer</Pname>
        <Plocation> NC</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jack Bergman</Pname>
        <Plocation> MI</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Liz Cheney</Pname>
        <Plocation> WY</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Mike Johnson</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jenniffer Gonzalez-Colon</Pname>
        <Plocation> PR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jason Knox</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chief of Staff</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Lisa Pittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chief Counsel</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>David Watkins</Pname>
        <Plocation> Democratic Staff Director</Plocation>
    </people>
    <subcomittee_name>SUBCOMMITTEE ON ENERGY AND MINERAL RESOURCES</subcomittee_name>
    <people>
        <Pname>PAUL A. GOSAR</Pname>
        <Plocation> Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>ALAN S. LOWENTHAL</Pname>
        <Plocation> Ranking Democratic Member</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Louie Gohmert</Pname>
        <Plocation> TX</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Anthony G. Brown</Pname>
        <Plocation> MD</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Doug Lamborn</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jim Costa</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Robert J. Wittman</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Niki Tsongas</Pname>
        <Plocation> MA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Stevan Pearce</Pname>
        <Plocation> NM</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jared Huffman</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Glenn Thompson</Pname>
        <Plocation> PA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Donald S. Beyer</Pname>
        <Plocation> VA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Scott R. Tipton</Pname>
        <Plocation> CO</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darren Soto</Pname>
        <Plocation> FL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Paul Cook</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Nanette Diaz Barragan</Pname>
        <Plocation> CA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vice Chairman</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vice Chairman</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vacancy</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vacancy</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Bruce Westerman</Pname>
        <Plocation> AR</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Vacancy</Pname>
        <Plocation>Vacancy</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Garret Graves</Pname>
        <Plocation> LA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Raul M. Grijalva</Pname>
        <Plocation> ex officio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Jody B. Hice</Pname>
        <Plocation> GA</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Darin LaHood</Pname>
        <Plocation> IL</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Liz Cheney</Pname>
        <Plocation> WY</Plocation>
    </people>
    <people>
        <Pname>Rob Bishop</Pname>
        <Plocation> ex officio</Plocation>
    </people>
    <table-of-content>CONTENTS</table-of-content>
    <peopleSpeaker>   Hearing held on Wednesday</peopleSpeaker>
    <peopleinfo>May</peopleinfo>
    <Members>Statement of Members:</Members>
    <Speaker>Hon Paul A Gosar</Speaker>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of Arizona Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <witnesses>Statement of Witnesses:</witnesses>
    <Witness>Hon Alan S Lowenthal</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>a Representative in Congress from the State of California Prepared statement of</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Thom Kay</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Senior Legislative Representative Appalachian Voices</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>John Stefanko</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>Deputy Secretary for the Office of Active and Abandoned Mine Operations Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>Chris Wood</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>President/Chief Executive Officer Trout Unlimited</peopleinfo>
    <Witness>SURFACE MINING CONTROL AND RECLAMATION ACT OF  TO AUTHORIZE PARTNERSHIPS BETWEEN STATES AND NONGOVERNMENTAL ENTITIES FOR THE PURPOSE OF RECLAIMING AND RESTORING LAND AND WATER RESOURCES ADVERSELY AFFECTED BY COAL MINING ACTIVITIES BEFORE AUGUST</Witness>
    <peopleinfo>AND OTHER PURPOSES ``COMMUNITY RECLAMATION PARTNERSHIPS ACT''  Wednesday</peopleinfo>
    <subcomittee_name>Subcommittee on Energy and Mineral Resources</subcomittee_name>
    <option>                     Committee on Natural Resources
                             Washington, DC
                              ----------                              
    The Subcommittee met, pursuant to notice, at 2:12 p.m., in 
room 1324, Longworth House Office Building, Hon. Paul Gosar 
[Chairman of the Subcommittee] presiding.
    Present: Representatives Gosar, Pearce, Thompson, Tipton, 
Westerman, Hice, LaHood; Lowenthal, Beyer, and Barragan.
    Dr. Gosar. The Subcommittee on Energy and Mineral Resources 
will come to order. The Subcommittee is meeting today to hear 
testimony on the discussion draft of the Community Reclamation 
Partnerships Act.
    Under Committee Rule 4(f), any oral opening statements at 
the hearing are limited to the Chairman, the Ranking Minority 
Member, and the Vice Chair. This will allow us to hear from our 
witnesses sooner, and help Members keep to their schedules. 
Therefore, I ask unanimous consent that all other Members' 
opening statements be made part of the hearing record, if they 
are submitted to the Subcommittee Clerk by 5:00 p.m. today.
    Without objection, so ordered.
</option>
    <option>               CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF ARIZONA
    Dr. Gosar. Today the Subcommittee will consider our 
discussion draft of the Community Reclamation Partnerships Act. 
This bill would amend the Surface Mining Control and 
Reclamation Act of 1977, or SMCRA, to enable states to partner 
with non-governmental entities to reclaim abandoned mine sites 
and facilitate acid mine drainage cleanup across the country.
    Currently, state reclamation activities are funded solely 
by fees levied on the coal industry. These fees have resulted 
in the reclamation of approximately $4 billion of abandoned 
mine land, or AML, liabilities.
    However, according to the Department of the Interior, over 
6,650 AML sites remain, with an estimated remediation cost 
exceeding $10.5 billion. These abandoned mines pose threats to 
the surrounding communities, and prohibit opportunities for 
further development.
    Because these sites were abandoned before the era of modern 
regulation and there are no current liable parties, the states 
are responsible for reclaiming these sites and restoring the 
environmental quality of the surrounding areas. The cost of 
reclaiming these sites will continue to strain state resources 
in the coming decades, and the condition of these sites will 
only worsen over time.
    Non-government entities have recognized the need for 
reclamation in coal communities and are willing to contribute 
their resources and expertise to address the problem. 
Unfortunately, liability and regulatory concerns have 
discouraged them from partnering with states on reclamation 
projects. This legislation will enable NGO participation in 
state reclamation programs by minimizing undeserved liability 
and codifying proven practices established by the state 
reclamation agencies.
    This legislation would recognize non-governmental entities 
who wish to conduct reclamation projects, including watershed 
groups, conservation organizations, and industry partners, as 
``Community Reclaimers.'' It will allow the state to extend 
liability protection to these entities, much like they already 
do for their approved reclamation contractors.
    This legislation also addresses common problems that states 
experience in addressing water pollution at AML sites. One of 
the most challenging aspects of mine reclamation is the 
treatment of acid mine drainage discharges. Currently, states 
are required to fully comply with the Clean Water Act when 
treating water at AML sites. While the water quality at AML 
sites can be improved, it will never reach Clean Water Act 
standards, even with the best water treatment systems in place. 
As a result, states must choose between risking non-compliance 
under the Clean Water Act, or foregoing acid mine drainage 
abatement projects all together.
    Some states have addressed this problem by establishing 
their own guidelines for the treatment of water pollution at 
AML sites. These state-specific strategies have resulted in 
successful water treatment projects and a significant reduction 
in acid mine drainage in several states.
    However, these states risk subjecting their programs to 
suit, due to the lack of any statutory authorization for their 
water treatment programs. This legislation would statutorily 
recognize the practice of crafting acid mine drainage treatment 
strategies in each state.
    These strategies must be laid out in the form of a 
Memorandum of Understanding between the relevant state and 
Federal agencies and approved by the EPA and Department of the 
Interior. Community Reclaimers will be able to execute acid 
mine drainage projects consistent with the approved MOUs in 
each state.
    I would like to note that this legislation does not allow 
for re-mining in conjunction with Community Reclaimer projects. 
SMCRA already allows for the regulation of re-mining 
activities, and this legislation does not in any way amend the 
existing requirements. Should mining companies choose to serve 
as Community Reclaimers, they will not be able to conduct 
mining activity in the course of completing a reclamation 
project, and they must not have any outstanding SMCRA 
violations.
    Today, we will hear from Mr. Stefanko, Deputy Secretary for 
the Office of Active and Abandoned Mine Operations at 
Pennsylvania's Department of Environmental Protection. In his 
role, Mr. Stefanko is responsible for overseeing the state's 
Abandoned Mine Reclamation Program. He will discuss his 
program's experience with allowing non-governmental entities to 
reclaim AML sites, current challenges in cleaning up acid mine 
drainage, and the need for Community Reclaimers in states like 
Pennsylvania.
    We will also hear from Mr. Chris Wood, President and CEO of 
Trout Unlimited. Trout Unlimited is a national organization 
dedicated to conservation and fisheries restoration that has 
partnered with several states on abandoned mine land projects. 
Mr. Wood will discuss the ability of non-governmental entities 
like Trout Unlimited to serve as Community Reclaimers, and the 
environmental benefits that these partnerships will yield for 
communities nationwide.
</option>
    <option>Prepared Statement of the Hon. Paul A. Gosar, Chairman, Subcommittee on 
                      Energy and Mineral Resources
    Today, the Subcommittee will consider a discussion draft of the 
Community Reclamation Partnerships Act. This bill would amend the 
Surface Mining Control and Reclamation Act of 1977 (SMCRA) to enable 
states to partner with non-governmental entities to reclaim abandoned 
mine sites and facilitate acid mine drainage cleanup across the 
country.
    Currently, state reclamation activities are funded solely by fees 
levied on the coal industry. These fees have resulted in the 
reclamation of approximately $4 billion of abandoned mine land, or AML, 
liabilities. However, according to the Department of the Interior, over 
6,650 AML sites remain with estimated remediation costs exceeding $10.5 
billion. These abandoned mines pose threats to the surrounding 
communities and prohibit opportunities for further development. Because 
these sites were abandoned before the era of modern regulation and 
there are no current liable parties, the states are responsible for 
reclaiming these sites and restoring the environmental quality of the 
surrounding areas. The cost of reclaiming these sites will continue to 
strain state resources in the coming decades and the conditions of 
these sites will only worsen over time.
    Non-governmental entities have recognized the need for reclamation 
in coal communities and are willing to contribute their resources and 
expertise to address the problem. Unfortunately, liability and 
regulatory concerns have discouraged them from partnering with the 
states on reclamation projects. This legislation will enable NGO 
participation in state reclamation programs by minimizing undeserved 
liability and codifying proven practices established by the state 
reclamation agencies.
    This legislation would recognize non-governmental entities who wish 
to conduct reclamation projects, including watershed groups, 
conservation organizations and industry partners, as ``Community 
Reclaimers.'' It will allow the state to extend liability protection to 
these entities, much like they already do for their approved 
reclamation contractors.
    This legislation also addresses common problems that states 
experience in addressing water pollution at AML sites. One of the most 
challenging aspects of mine reclamation is the treatment of acid mine 
drainage discharges. Currently, states are required to fully comply 
with the Clean Water Act when treating water at AML sites. While the 
water quality at AML sites can be improved, it will never reach Clean 
Water Act standards, even with the best water treatment systems in 
place. As a result, states must choose between risking noncompliance 
under the Clean Water Act or foregoing acid mine drainage abatement 
projects altogether.
    Some states have addressed this problem by establishing their own 
guidelines for the treatment of water pollution at AML sites. These 
state-specific strategies have resulted in successful water treatment 
projects and a significant reduction in acid mine drainage in several 
states. However, these states risk subjecting their programs to suit 
due to the lack of any statutory authorization for their water 
treatment programs. This legislation would statutorily recognize the 
practice of crafting acid mine drainage treatment strategies in each 
state. These strategies must be laid out in the form of a Memorandum of 
Understanding between the relevant state and Federal agencies and 
approved by the EPA and Department of the Interior. Community 
Reclaimers will be able to execute acid mine drainage projects 
consistent with the approved MOUs in each state.
    I would like to note that this legislation does not allow for re-
mining in conjunction with Community Reclaimer projects. SMCRA already 
allows for the regulation of re-mining activities and this legislation 
does not in any way amend the existing requirements. Should mining 
companies choose to serve as Community Reclaimers, they will not be 
able to conduct mining activity in the course of completing a 
reclamation project, and they must not have any outstanding SMCRA 
violations.
    Today, we will hear from Mr. John Stefanko, Deputy Secretary for 
the Office of Active and Abandoned Mine Operations at the Pennsylvania 
Department of Environmental Protection. In his role, Mr. Stefanko is 
responsible for overseeing the States' Abandoned Mine Reclamation 
Program. He will discuss his program's experience with allowing non-
governmental entities to reclaim AML sites, current challenges in 
cleaning up acid mine drainage, and the need for Community Reclaimers 
in states like Pennsylvania.
    We will also hear from Mr. Chris Wood, President and CEO of Trout 
Unlimited. Trout Unlimited is a national organization dedicated to 
conservation and fisheries restoration that has partnered with several 
states on abandoned mine land projects. Mr. Wood will discuss the 
ability of non-governmental entities like Trout Unlimited to serve as 
Community Reclaimers and the environmental benefits that these 
partnerships will yield for communities nationwide.
                                 ______
    Dr. Gosar. The Chairman now recognizes the Ranking Member 
for any statement. The gentleman from California is recognized.
</option>
    <option>             CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA
    Dr. Lowenthal. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. The draft of the 
bill before us today is an interesting and potentially 
promising tool to help address one of the big questions that 
confronts the issue of cleaning up abandoned mines. Namely, how 
can we allow Good Samaritans--people who had nothing to do with 
causing the pollution--how can we allow them to help with 
cleaning up these sites?
    There is no question that help is needed. Reclaiming all of 
the remaining abandoned coal mines in this country would cost 
an estimated $10 billion.
    Reclaiming our abandoned hardrock mines would be even more 
expensive, with an estimated cost of anywhere from $20 to $54 
billion. The Gold King Mine incident was just the most visible 
example of why this immense responsibility needs to be taken on 
in a serious way, and it needs to be done soon.
    Volunteers, whether we call them Good Samaritans, Community 
Reclaimers, or anything else, will simply not be enough to 
tackle this problem.
    Coal companies, at least, chip in to the Abandoned Mine 
Land Fund to help address the legacy of centuries of 
unreclaimed coal mines. Unfortunately, hardrock mining 
companies do not contribute to help cover the enormous cost of 
cleaning up their own legacy of pollution, which are the over 
half-million abandoned gold, silver, copper, and other mines 
that each day poison rivers and streams throughout the country 
with millions of gallons of toxic water containing lead, 
arsenic, cadmium, and other metals.
    The hardrock mining industry has also continually fought 
efforts to hold them accountable for these sites. That needs to 
change.
    Last Congress, Ranking Member Grijalva and I introduced the 
Hardrock Mining Reform and Reclamation Act, which, among other 
things, would require the hardrock mining industry to pony up 
and pitch in like the coal industry has done. Frankly, that is 
the only way we are going to make a significant dent in this 
problem.
    Particularly, I raise this, since the Administration has 
now decided that cleaning up abandoned hardrock mines is not a 
priority. The President has proposed a cut of nearly $11 
million for the Bureau of Land Management's Abandoned Mine 
Lands Program, more than half--and I repeat that, more than 
half--of the budget of that already underfunded program.
    Mr. Chairman, I hope that this is an issue that we can look 
at in more depth this Congress. As for the bill we are 
discussing today, this is a novel approach to addressing the 
Good Samaritan issue, and I thank Mr. LaHood for proposing it, 
and you, the Chairman, for holding a hearing on it. Having 
Community Reclaimers partner with states under their abandoned 
mine land programs could potentially provide the liability 
protections that these Good Samaritans need to undertake in a 
number of helpful projects.
    However, I don't believe it is entirely clear how this bill 
would work. It appears that the bill would provide a broad 
waiver for projects that do not meet Clean Water Act standards 
if there is a Memorandum of Understanding between the state and 
the Federal Government. Unfortunately, there is very little 
detail in the bill about what these memoranda would contain. 
The only requirement seems to be that the Secretary of the 
Interior and the Administrator of the Environmental Protection 
Agency find that a memorandum would help facilitate additional 
work under the state's Abandoned Coal Mine Reclamation Plan.
    But there are a lot of ways that we could do that. And it 
is not clear if there are protections to keep coal companies 
from using this as a way to re-mine old sites without having to 
comply with the Clean Water Act.
    I understand that is not the intent of this bill, so I hope 
we can work together, guided by some of the comments of the 
testimony provided by our witnesses today, to craft something 
that is bipartisan and that can have a real and lasting 
positive impact.
    Thank you to the witnesses for being here, and I yield back 
the balance of my time.
</option>
    <option>   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Alan S. Lowenthal, Ranking Member, 
</option>
    <option>Subcommittee on Energy and Mineral Resources</option>
    <option>    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    The draft of the bill before us today is an interesting and 
potentially promising tool to help address one of the big questions 
that confronts the issue of cleaning up abandoned mines. Namely, how 
can we allow Good Samaritans--people who had nothing to do with causing 
the pollution--how can we allow them to help with cleaning up these 
sites?
    There is no question that help is needed. Reclaiming all of the 
remaining abandoned coal mines in this country would cost an estimated 
$10 billion.
    Reclaiming our abandoned hardrock mines would be even more 
expensive, with an estimated cost of anywhere from $20 to $54 billion. 
The Gold King Mine incident was just the most visible example of why 
this immense responsibility needs to be taken on in a serious way, and 
it needs to be done soon.
    Volunteers, whether we call them Good Samaritans, Community 
Reclaimers, or anything else, will simply not be enough to tackle this 
problem.
    Coal companies, at least, chip in to the Abandoned Mine Land fund 
to help address the legacy of centuries of unreclaimed coal mines. 
Unfortunately, hardrock mining companies do not contribute to help 
cover the enormous cost of cleaning up their own legacy of pollution, 
which are the over half-million abandoned gold, silver, copper, and 
other mines that each day poison rivers and streams throughout the 
country with millions of gallons of toxic water containing lead, 
arsenic, cadmium, and other metals.
    The hardrock mining industry has also continually fought efforts to 
hold them accountable for these sites. That needs to change.
    Last Congress, Ranking Member Grijalva and I introduced the 
Hardrock Mining Reform and Reclamation Act, which among other things 
would require the hardrock mining industry to pony up and pitch in like 
the coal industry has done. Frankly, that is the only way that we will 
make a significant dent in this problem.
    Particularly since the Administration has decided that cleaning up 
abandoned hardrock mines isn't a priority. The President has proposed a 
cut of nearly $11 million for the Bureau of Land Management's Abandoned 
Mine Lands program, more than half of the budget of that already 
underfunded program.
    Mr. Chairman, I hope that this is an issue that we can look at in 
more depth this Congress. As for the bill we are discussing today, this 
is a novel approach to addressing the Good Samaritan issue, and I thank 
Mr. LaHood for proposing it and the Chairman for holding a hearing on 
it. Having Community Reclaimers partner with states under their 
Abandoned Mine Land programs could potentially provide the liability 
protections that these Good Samaritans need to undertake a number of 
helpful projects.
    However, I don't believe it is entirely clear how this bill would 
work. It appears that the bill would provide a broad waiver for 
projects that don't meet Clean Water Act standards if there is a 
Memorandum of Understanding between the state and the Federal 
Government. Unfortunately, there is very little detail in the bill 
about what these memoranda would contain. The only requirement seems to 
be that the Secretary of the Interior and the Administrator of the 
Environmental Protection Agency find that a memorandum would help 
facilitate additional work under the State's Abandoned Coal Mine 
Reclamation Plan.
    But there are a lot of ways that you could do that. And it's not 
clear if there are protections to keep coal companies from using this 
as a way to re-mine old sites without having to comply with the Clean 
Water Act.
    I understand that isn't the intent of this bill, so I hope we can 
work together, guided by some of the comments in the testimony provided 
by our witnesses today, to craft something that is bipartisan and can 
have a real and lasting positive impact.
    Thank you to the witnesses for being here, and I yield back the 
balance of my time.
                                 ______
    Dr. Gosar. I thank the gentleman. Now I will introduce our 
witnesses.
    First, Mr. Chris Wood, President and Chief Executive 
Officer for Trout Unlimited.
    Mr. Thom Kay, Senior Legislative Representative for 
Appalachian Voices.
    And third, Mr. John Stefanko, Deputy Secretary for the 
Office of Active and Abandoned Mine Operations, Pennsylvania 
Department of Environmental Protection.
    Let me remind the witnesses that, under our Committee 
Rules, they must limit their oral statements to 5 minutes. But 
their entire statement will appear in the hearing record.
    Our microphones are not automatic. You will need to press 
the talk button when you begin your testimony. When you begin, 
the light on the witness microphone will turn green, and after 
4 minutes will turn yellow, subsequently followed by the red 
light. Summarize your statements from there on, and hopefully 
keep it to that aspect.
    I would like to now recognize Mr. Wood for his testimony.
    Good seeing you again, Chris.
</option>
    <option>              TROUT UNLIMITED, ARLINGTON, VIRGINIA
    Mr. Wood. Thank you, Chairman Gosar, Ranking Member 
Lowenthal, and Subcommittee members. My testimony is on behalf 
of Trout Unlimited and our 300,000 members and supporters 
around the country. I want to thank you for inviting us to be 
here today.
    TU's mission is to conserve, protect, and restore trout and 
salmon fisheries and the watersheds that they depend on. I have 
often referred to TU as the patron saint of forgotten 
environmental causes. And our work to clean up abandoned mines, 
whether they are in the coal fields of Appalachia or hardrock 
mining lands in the Rocky Mountains, is a testament of that.
    [Slide]
    Mr. Wood. As you can see from this map that is on the 
screen here, abandoned coal mines are a pervasive problem all 
across the country, not just in Appalachia.
    Next slide, please.
    [Slide]
    Mr. Wood. The Gold King spill in Colorado several years ago 
made national news. But the stream on the left is a typical 
representation, and it is all too familiar from any landowners 
across Appalachia and the rest of the country. These yellow 
streams and red streams occur outside of the media's view, but 
all around the country.
    Cleaning up these mines is pretty straightforward. As the 
picture on the upper right shows, you can run them through 
these passive treatment systems and constructed wetlands, and 
the result is that you can recover native species such as the 
brook trout, down in the lower-right corner. We are quite proud 
of the fact that in Pennsylvania, because of our work on a 
watershed called Kettle Creek, we were able to recover over 6 
miles of spawning and rearing habitat for brook trout that had 
been lost for over a century to abandoned mine waste.
    Next slide, please.
    [Slide]
    Mr. Wood. This map shows what is possible. Kettle Creek, 
that I just mentioned, is a small part of the West Branch of 
the Susquehanna watershed, which drains about 20 percent of the 
Commonwealth of Pennsylvania. The line in red represents the 
river from the 1980s. If you can't read the chart, essentially 
the entire river was acidic to one degree or another.
    Today, that is not the case. You can see the progress that 
has been made over the past decades as a result of the 
partnership between the state, dozens of watershed groups, and 
organizations like Trout Unlimited.
    Much, much more work remains to be done, in spite of the 
success that we have had on the West Branch. In the West Branch 
alone, we have over 1,000 miles of acidic streams that need to 
be treated. These are particularly important for brook trout. 
And we have over 5,000 miles in the rest of the Commonwealth 
that are also in need of treatment.
    Next slide, please.
    [Slide]
    Mr. Wood. This work not only cleans our water, it provides 
thousands of high-paying, family wage jobs in rural areas. And, 
of course, it makes the fishing better, which, in turn, drives 
a significant recreation economy, which everyone benefits from.
    We are very grateful, Representative LaHood and Chairman 
Gosar, for your continued leadership on this issue, and we 
appreciate the willingness of the authors to allow for some 
discussion of this bill. These deliberations, we think, will 
lead to strong bipartisan support for a very, very good draft.
    This draft is a significant step in the right direction. It 
must work well on the ground, of course, and we are looking 
forward to having a little bit of time to give you more 
detailed comments from our practitioners in the field. We will 
offer some additional feedback in the coming days, but we are 
quite confident that the finished, introduced bill will be 
worthy of the Subcommittee's strong consideration and eventual 
approval.
    Just three points that we would like to highlight here for 
the balance of my time.
    Number one, we think the bill should consider some process 
for grandfathering some of the 250 projects that are already 
ongoing in the state of Pennsylvania through the MOU process.
    Number two, we would like to ensure that there is strong 
public involvement in the development of these MOUs. We think 
that consent of the people in these areas is really important 
to getting good, solid projects.
    And then, finally, we would like to see qualifying private 
landowners eligible to become Community Reclaimers in their own 
right. It was unclear from the draft if that is intended.
    Improving the Nation's water quality is a goal that every 
American shares. We are pleased that the Subcommittee is 
looking at one of the more vexing water quality problems in the 
country right now, and we stand ready to work with you to 
promote clean and fishable waters across the country.
    Thank you for considering our views, and thank you for 
working on these most important matters.
</option>
    <option>  Prepared Statement of Chris Wood, President/CEO of Trout Unlimited, 
                          Arlington, Virginia
    Chairman Gosar, Ranking Member Lowenthal, and Subcommittee Members: 
my name is Chris Wood. I am the President and CEO of Trout Unlimited. 
Thank you for the opportunity to testify today on abandoned coal mine 
cleanup legislation.
    I offer the following testimony on behalf of Trout Unlimited and 
its nearly 300,000 members and supporters nationwide. My testimony will 
focus on the Discussion Draft (Draft Bill), cleanup of abandoned coal 
mine lands and water, and specifically the need to facilitate abandoned 
coal mine cleanups by Community Reclaimers (also often known as ``Good 
Samaritans'')--those individuals or entities who have no legal 
obligation to take on an abandoned mine cleanup, but who wish to do so 
in order to improve water quality and watershed health.
    We deeply appreciate the Subcommittee's focus on this issue, and we 
urge the Subcommittee to continue to work with us, the states, the 
Interior Department, the EPA, and other stakeholders on such a bill to 
help provide an important tool to facilitate cleanups.
    TU's mission is to conserve, protect and restore North America's 
trout and salmon fisheries and the watersheds they depend on. In 
pursuit of this mission, TU has worked to restore streams and rivers 
damaged by pollution from abandoned mines from the Appalachian 
coalfields in Pennsylvania to the hardrock mining areas of the Rocky 
Mountain states, and my testimony is based upon these experiences. TU 
stands ready to expand our work to clean up abandoned mine pollution, 
and we need such legislation to make it happen.
    We are grateful for the Draft Bill, and the leadership of its 
authors, Representative LaHood and Chairman Gosar. It is a thoughtful 
approach and a workable, new model. We appreciate the willingness of 
the authors to allow for ample discussion of the draft. We hope that 
the deliberations will lead to strong, bipartisan support for the bill.
    There is room for improvement in some areas, but we regard the 
draft as a significant step that is headed in the right direction. It 
must work well on the ground, of course, and as our field practitioners 
are studying the Draft Bill, we will offer additional feedback in the 
coming days. We are confident that the finished, introduced bill will 
be worthy of the Subcommittee's strong consideration and eventual 
approval.
  abandoned mine pollution is a widespread problem but much of it is 
                                fixable
    Americans want clean water. Trout Unlimited members give 
substantial amounts of their time and treasures to protecting and 
restoring trout watersheds. But even a cursory look at the damages to 
our streams, rivers and groundwater caused by pollution from abandoned 
coal and hardrock mines show that we have a long way to go to achieve 
clean water for all. There is no better time than right now, as the new 
Trump administration and the 115th Congress discuss including water 
cleanup work as part of an infrastructure package, to address clean up 
of pollution from abandoned coal mine.
    Sadly, much of abandoned mine pollution is ``out of sight, out of 
mind.'' But in August 2015, we received a vivid view of the mess. The 
3-million gallons spill of polluted water from the Gold King mine near 
Silverton, Colorado showed the world what TU members and staff who live 
in mining country see every day: Orange, polluted water leaking out 
from abandoned mines.
    Cleaning up abandoned mines is challenging and expensive. That does 
not make it any less imperative. The legacy of historical mining 
practices--thousands of abandoned coal and hardrock mines with an 
estimated cleanup cost in the billions of dollars--has persisted for 
the better part of a century with insufficient progress toward a 
solution.
    Abandoned coal mines dot the Appalachian landscape. Pollution from 
abandoned coal mines continues to damage thousands of miles of streams 
and rivers--over 10,000 miles just within Pennsylvania and West 
Virginia--and while much has been accomplished through the Surface 
Mining Control and Reclamation Act's (SMCRA) extremely valuable 
Abandoned Mine Lands Fund (AML Fund), a great deal more remains to be 
done. The cost of cleanup in Pennsylvania alone has been estimated as 
high as $15 billion.\1\
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    \1\ http://pa.water.usgs.gov/projects/energy/amd/.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
    A reclamation fee, paid by the mining companies, is collected for 
each ton of coal produced to support the AML Fund. Since 1977, more 
than $10.5 billion has been put to good use making safe and cleaning up 
abandoned coal mines.
    We have developed a number of model projects that can be easily 
replicated. In Pennsylvania, aided by state-based Good Samaritan 
policy, watershed groups, including Trout Unlimited, are working with 
state agencies, communities, and other partners to conduct more than 
250 abandoned coal mine pollution projects throughout the state. We can 
do lot more if the problem is fixed.
 our best environmental law, the clean water act, can be a barrier to 
                      abandoned coal mine cleanup
    There are many projects where water quality could be improved by 
collecting run-off, or taking an existing discrete discharge, and 
running the polluted water through a treatment system. However, for 
would-be Community Reclaimers, Clean Water Act (CWA) compliance and 
liability issues remain a barrier to such projects. Several courts have 
held that discharges from systems that treat wastewater from abandoned 
mines are point source discharges that require a National Pollutant 
Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) permit under section 402 of the 
CWA. Although EPA and some eastern states have not considered such 
projects to be point sources requiring NPDES permits, the Fourth 
Circuit's 2010 decision in West Virginia Highlands Conservancy, Inc. v. 
Huffman creates some uncertainty around that approach.
    Stakeholders in projects involving treatment of mine drainage have 
been held back because of CWA liability for two reasons. First, NGOs, 
including TU, are not well suited to apply for and hold permits for 
such projects. TU does not have an adequate funding mechanism to 
legally bind itself to pay for the perpetual costs associated with 
operating a water-treatment facility and permit compliance.
    Second, for many projects it may be impossible to obtain a permit, 
because the treatment systems, even if they will improve conditions, 
may not be able to treat abandoned mine wastewater to a level that 
meets all applicable water quality standards or other applicable 
criteria. It should be noted that while these treatment systems are 
certainly capable of producing water that will support a healthy 
fishery, the resulting water quality might not meet CWA standards for 
some pollutants that are particularly difficult to remove from mine 
waste (for example, passive wetland systems that effectively treat 
highly polluted water often leave levels of manganese that do not 
comply with CWA standards).
    This is not to say that CWA standards should be weakened; just the 
opposite, in fact. But there should be incentives for would-be 
Community Reclaimers to make water cleaner even if still short of full 
CWA standards. Put another way, Federal law should provide incentives 
for would be Good Samaritans to make our water cleaner and communities 
safer.
  good projects could be expanded and replicated with effective good 
                       samaritan policy for coal
    In Pennsylvania, as we explain below, polluted water is being 
successfully treated and streams and rivers are being brought back to 
life because the Commonwealth has provided Good Samaritans with 
dedicated funding. We believe that we can export the Pennsylvania model 
across the rest of the country if liability concerns are eased.
    Kettle Creek, Pennsylvania. Our experiences in Pennsylvania are 
illustrative of the positive effect of Good Samaritan cleanups Over the 
past 20 years, Pennsylvania has seen an increase in abandoned mine 
reclamation projects by watershed groups, including TU. This boom has 
been fueled by funding from the state's Growing Greener grant program 
and the Federal Abandoned Mine Land (AML) reclamation fund. Most of 
these projects involve treatment of acid mine drainage using passive 
treatment systems, which run the polluted mine drainage through a 
series of limestone basins and wetlands that increase the water's pH 
and cause heavy metals to precipitate out. These projects have 
significantly improved water quality and restored fish populations in 
numerous Pennsylvania streams.
    The Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection estimates 
that public funding sources have paid for the construction of nearly 
250 passive treatment systems in the state, the majority of which have 
been constructed by private watershed groups, conservation districts or 
other local groups.
    Beginning in 1998, the work of TU and its partners in the lower 
Kettle Creek watershed has resulted in the reclamation of approximately 
160 acres of scarred abandoned mine lands and installation of nine 
treatment systems that successfully improved mine water polluted with 
high levels of acidity and metals. The results to date have been 
tremendous, with water quality restored to 3 miles of previously dead 
streams and 6 miles of a fully reconnected and thriving native brook 
trout population.
    This story of recovery plays out again and again in individual 
streams and watersheds. Several years ago, the Babb Creek Watershed 
Association accomplished delisting 14 miles of Babb Creek, now a wild 
trout fishery, from EPA's impaired streams list. Another 14 miles in 
the Tangascootack Creek watershed is pending removal from the impaired 
streams list as a result of passive treatment systems constructed by 
the Clinton County Conservation District.
    On a much larger scale, the West Branch Susquehanna River watershed 
has made tremendous strides over the past few decades. A comparison of 
conditions in the West Branch Susquehanna in 1972 with those in 2009 
indicated that fish species increased 3,000 percent, and pH increased 
from 3.8 to 6.6.
    These improvements result in economic benefits. In Pennsylvania, 
almost $4 billion was spent on fishing, hunting, and wildlife viewing 
in 2006. A 2008 study found that full remediation of the West Branch 
Susquehanna River watershed would result in ``an additional $22.3 
million in sport fishing revenues could be expected to be generated 
each year. Additional recreation spending--over and above that for 
fishing--would be expected after remediation is completed.''
    Regardless of the overall scope of the abandoned mine problem, each 
of these projects restored a significant water body and represents a 
big win for the local community.
                      assessment of the draft bill
1. Positive Features of the Draft Bill
    &lt;bullet&gt; Houses the program within SMCRA and the existing AML 
            cleanup program. This will ensure that many of the positive 
            features of current AML programs will be retained.
    &lt;bullet&gt; The Clean Water Act liability protection mechanism for 
            Community Reclaimers is narrowly tailored, is located 
            within SMCRA, and relies on our state partners.
    &lt;bullet&gt; Allows eligible states to enter into abandoned mine 
            pollution clean up MOUs with Interior through the current 
            AML program, to be approved by Interior and EPA, to ensure 
            that water pollution cleanup results in a significant 
            improvement to the environment.
2. Sections of the Draft where clarifications or improvements should be 
        considered
    &lt;bullet&gt; The bill should ensure that ongoing, well functioning 
            projects should not have to go through the bill's approval 
            process if the states, through the MOU mechanism, certify 
            that the existing projects are being implemented 
            effectively and are improving water quality as planned. As 
            we mentioned, some 250 projects are currently functioning 
            well in Pennsylvania, and thus they should be smoothly 
            embedded in the new program with minimal additional review.
    &lt;bullet&gt; The bill language should clarify that adequate public 
            notice and comment is available for the draft MOUs from 
            each state, and for each project.
    &lt;bullet&gt; The bill should clarify that private landowners who are 
            not responsible for abandoned mine cleanup on their lands, 
            but who are willing to work cooperatively with the 
            Community Reclaimer and the state to clean up pollution 
            from abandoned mines on their land, should also receive 
            liability protection from the bill over the life of the 
            project.
    Cleanup of abandoned coal mine pollution is a long-term job, and 
long-term funding is needed to get the job done. Thus, Congress needs 
to start work on reauthorizing Title IV AML for coal. The AML fund is 
the lifeblood of funding for abandoned coal mine work in the coalfield 
areas of America, especially the East. Congress passed a very useful 
15-year reauthorization for the AML fund in 2006. Trout Unlimited and 
other stakeholders urge Congress to get started on the task of 
reauthorization now to ensure a smooth reauthorization is achieved by 
2021. Such a valuable, complex law is worth the effort needed to make 
sure the critical funding is maintained.
    Last, the Subcommittee knows well the need to have a hardrock Good 
Samaritan policy enacted to provide a critical tool for western 
abandoned mine cleanup. We appreciate the Subcommittee's work in the 
last Congress to find the solution. Under Chairman Lamborn's 
leadership, good progress was made. After the Committee passes this 
bill, we would like to see this Subcommittee take up the hardrock 
abandoned mine bookend.
                               conclusion
    Improving water quality around the Nation is a fundamental goal of 
the work of this Subcommittee, and thus we are pleased that the 
Subcommittee is looking at one of the most vexing water problems 
remaining in coal country. We stand ready to work with you so that 
affected communities around the Nation will again have clean, fishable 
waters. Thank you for considering our views, and thank you for working 
with us on these important matters.
                                 ______
    Dr. Gosar. Thank you very much.
    The Chair now recognizes Mr. Kay for his 5 minutes of 
testimony. Thank you.
</option>
    <option>           APPALACHIAN VOICES, BOONE, NORTH CAROLINA
    Mr. Kay. Thank you, Chairman Gosar, Ranking Member 
Lowenthal, and members of the Committee, for the opportunity to 
testify on the discussion draft of the Community Reclamation 
Partnerships Act. I am the Senior Legislative Representative 
for Appalachian Voices, an organization working to protect the 
land, air, and water of central and southern Appalachia for 
future generations, and to one day see the region upheld as a 
national model of a vibrant, just, and sustainable economy.
    Throughout Appalachia, there is an enormous need to restore 
former coal mine lands. Abandoned mine lands from before the 
passage of SMCRA and mines that have been bond-forfeited more 
recently put large burdens on state agencies and the public. 
State agencies work hard to treat existing problems, but they 
simply do not have the resources necessary to complete the 
reclamation of millions of acres of land and thousands of miles 
of streams anytime in the near future.
    Virginia, for example, has over $400 million in remaining 
AML costs, but only receives in the ballpark of $5 million per 
year in AML grants. In order to build wealth and prosperity in 
rural communities, clean water is absolutely essential. 
Additional resources are clearly needed for states to address 
decades worth of mining pollution.
    Cleaning up mine sites has both environmental and economic 
benefits, along with creating immediate reclamation jobs and 
drawing tourism to improving the land and protecting fish and 
wildlife. Cleaning up mining pollution can help improve the 
health of local communities.
    Appalachian communities have demonstrated growing 
excitement about the lasting benefits associated with mine 
reclamation. Between the AML pilot program and the progress of 
the RECLAIM Act, communities are envisioning new, long-term 
economic opportunities that can be combined with reclamation. 
Pairing such efforts with passage of the Community Reclamation 
Partnerships Act could result not only in more cleanup, but 
also spur innovative projects in coal communities.
    It is my understanding that the bill is intended to 
encourage organizations to take on some of the heavy burden of 
treating water pollution, while also preventing mining 
companies from escaping any of the responsibilities they have 
under current law. Most importantly to Appalachian Voices is 
that this bill does not allow companies to conduct any mining 
with any reduction in standard permitting requirements under 
the Clean Water Act or SMCRA.
    In certain cases, incidental coal removal can reduce the 
overall cost of site reclamation. This should be allowed if 
reclamation leaves previously polluted streams cleaner than 
they were before, but we see no reason for any company to 
receive extra liability protection for re-mining.
    We do not believe there is an intention to allow companies 
to carry out re-mining projects under this bill; but, as 
changes are made through the legislative process, I urge the 
Committee to ensure no loopholes are created that would allow 
any company to abuse the liability waivers granted under this 
Act in order to obtain new surface mining permits at an AML 
site.
    Included in the bill's definition of a Community Reclaimer 
are sensible restrictions that would prohibit companies with 
unfulfilled reclamation obligations or outstanding violations 
from qualifying. We agree with that decision, but defining such 
persons or companies can be quite difficult. In many instances, 
a parent company may own as many as several dozen subsidiary 
mining companies.
    For example, Alpha Natural Resources owns at least 22 coal 
companies currently registered with the West Virginia Secretary 
of State. These companies all list the same manager, organizer, 
and office address, yet the state of West Virginia routinely 
treats them as individual companies. We suggest updating the 
definition to ensure that no one can get around the sensible 
restrictions in the bill by acting through a subsidiary.
    Last, there is a provision that requires a notice be 
provided to the public before the project is initiated. That is 
important, but should go further in providing an opportunity 
for people to express concerns and have them addressed by the 
state or a Community Reclaimer. After all, a notice in the mail 
can raise a lot more questions than it answers.
    Regardless of how beneficial a project might be, neighbors 
may raise legitimate issues. They deserve the chance to share 
their thoughts with the Community Reclaimer and the state, and 
to have their concerns addressed in a timely manner.
    As the Community Reclamation Partnerships Act moves 
forward, we hope you will consider our thoughts and ensure that 
re-mining is not considered eligible for liability waivers, and 
that there is proper engagement with local communities. If the 
Committee is able to sufficiently address those issues while 
providing non-governmental entities the liability coverage they 
need to help clean up Appalachian streams, then we would urge 
Congress to pass this bill quickly.
    Thank you for your time, and I look forward to your 
questions.
</option>
    <option>Prepared Statement of Mr. Thom Kay, Senior Legislative Representative, 
                           Appalachian Voices
    Thank you Chairman Gosar, Ranking Member Lowenthal, and members of 
the Committee for the opportunity to testify on the discussion draft of 
the ``Community Reclaimers Partnership Act.''
    I am the Senior Legislative Representative for Appalachian Voices, 
an organization working to protect the land, air, and water of central 
and southern Appalachia for future generations and to one day see the 
region upheld as a national model of a vibrant, just, and sustainable 
economy.
  there is an enormous burden on state agencies to deal with existing 
                               pollution
    Throughout Appalachia, there is an enormous need to restore former 
coal mine lands. Mined land that existed prior to the passage of the 
Surface Mining Control and Reclamation Act of 1977 (SMCRA), known as 
Abandoned Mine Land (AML), and mines that have been bond-forfeited more 
recently put large burdens on state agencies and the public. State 
agencies work hard to treat existing problems, but they simply do not 
have the resources necessary to complete the reclamation of millions of 
acres of land and thousands of miles of streams anytime in the near 
future. Virginia, for example, has over $400 million in remaining AML 
costs, but only receives in the ballpark of $5 million per year in AML 
grants. While distribution totals may change once the AML program is 
reauthorized, there is no reason to believe sufficient funds will all 
of a sudden become available.
    The decline of the coal industry over the last 5 years has led to a 
staggering number of bankruptcies and associated bond forfeitures. 
SMCRA was supposed to address this issue through bonding; however, 
bonding programs in central Appalachian states remain insufficient to 
deal with the industry downturn. In many cases, bonds at individual 
mines are insufficient to cover reclamation costs, especially when 
long-term water treatment becomes necessary. Many companies have been 
allowed to self-bond, in which states rely on a ``too big to fail'' 
approach, even as many of the largest companies have gone bankrupt. In 
other cases, pool bond programs have not accounted for multiple 
forfeitures at once. While these situations would not be directly 
impacted by this bill, they are important to consider because they 
place an additional burden upon state agencies. Once a mine is bond-
forfeited, its reclamation becomes the responsibility of the state.
         clean up provides economic and environmental benefits
    In order to build wealth and prosperity in rural communities, clean 
water is absolutely essential. Additional resources are clearly needed 
for states to address decades' worth of mining pollution.
    Cleaning up mine sites can improve both surface water and 
groundwater, which has clear environmental and economic benefits. Along 
with creating immediate reclamation jobs and drawing tourism through 
improving the land and protecting fish and wildlife, cleaning up mining 
pollution can help improve the health of communities. Stream and well 
water contamination are both widespread throughout central Appalachia. 
Many rural communities do not have easy access to municipal water when 
their well water becomes contaminated. Some common contaminants, such 
as iron, are a nuisance--staining clothes and appliances orange. Other 
common contaminants, like manganese, have potential effects on 
childhood development that are only beginning to be understood. Though 
thankfully more rare, some contaminants, such as arsenic, are known 
carcinogens. Appalachian Voices has found all three of these 
contaminants, as well as many others, in private well water throughout 
the region.
    Appalachian communities have demonstrated growing excitement about 
the lasting benefits associated with mine reclamation. Between the AML 
Pilot Program and the progress of the RECLAIM Act (H.R. 1731), 
communities are envisioning new, long-term economic opportunities that 
can be paired with the reclamation of our country's Abandoned Mine 
Lands. Pairing such efforts with passage of the Community Reclaimer 
Protections Act could result not only in more cleanup, but also spur 
innovative projects in coal communities, many of which continue to 
struggle with the decline of coal mining jobs.
 the bill should not allow any company to abuse the liability waivers 
                             for re-mining
    It is my understanding that the bill is intended to allow for and 
encourage non-governmental organizations to take on some of the heavy 
burden of treating water pollution caused by coal mining before 1977, 
while also preventing mining companies from escaping any of the 
responsibilities they have under current law. Most importantly to 
Appalachian Voices is that this bill does not allow companies to 
conduct any mining with any reduction in standard permitting 
requirements under the Clean Water Act, SMCRA, or other applicable law.
    We understand that, in certain cases, incidental coal removal can 
reduce the overall cost of site reclamation and does not further 
threaten water resources. This type of activity should be allowed if 
reclamation leaves previously polluted streams cleaner than they were 
before. But we see no reason for any company to receive extra liability 
protection for re-mining.
    We do not believe there is an intention to allow companies to carry 
out re-mining projects under this bill, but it is possible, perhaps 
even likely, that changes to the existing language of this discussion 
draft will occur. I urge the Committee to ensure no loopholes are 
created that would allow any company to abuse the liability waivers 
granted under this act in order to obtain new surface mining permits at 
an AML site.
                   defining a ``community reclaimer''
    While one solution to the issue of coal companies abusing the bill 
is to simply prohibit any such company from qualifying as a ``Community 
Reclaimer,'' I understand that the authors would like to give companies 
that opportunity. Given the experience and resources mining companies 
bring to the table, that decision is not unreasonable. Included in the 
bill's definition of a ``Community Reclaimer,'' however, are sensible 
restrictions that would prohibit companies with unfulfilled reclamation 
obligations or outstanding violations from qualifying. We agree with 
that decision, but defining such persons or companies can be quite 
difficult.
    In many instances, a parent company may own as many as a several 
dozen subsidiary mining companies. These corporate structures often 
shield each individual company, as well as the parent company, from 
protective measures within SMCRA intended to prevent widespread 
pollution issues. According to the Office of Surface Mining Reclamation 
and Enforcement, ``section 510(c) of SMCRA prohibits issuance of a new 
permit to any applicant who owns or controls mining operations having 
unabated or uncorrected violations anywhere in the United States until 
those violations are abated or corrected or are in the process of being 
abated or corrected to the satisfaction of the agency with jurisdiction 
over the violation.'' State agencies routinely issue permits to 
subsidiary companies even when other subsidiaries have outstanding 
violations.
    For example, citizens living around Coal River Mountain in West 
Virginia recently objected to the issuance of several new mountaintop 
removal permits in their area. Republic Energy, Inc., a subsidiary of 
Alpha Natural Resources, applied for the permits. Republic's newest 
permit for the Long Ridge Mine was issued over citizens' objection, 
even when Alex Energy, another Alpha subsidiary, had outstanding 
reclamation schedule violations at the time. Alpha Natural Resources 
owns at least 22 coal companies currently registered with the West 
Virginia Secretary of State. These companies all list the same manager, 
organizer, and office address. Alpha Natural Resources and its 
subsidiary have had numerous recent issues in West Virginia, including 
ongoing violations, coal slurry spills, and allegations of fraud, yet 
the subsidiaries are routinely treated as individual companies and 
granted leniency when it comes to permitting decisions and enforcement 
actions.
    Due to the prevalence of permitting and enforcement issues among 
subsidiary companies, the language defining ``Community Reclaimer'' 
should be strengthened. Currently, the definition includes, ``Is not a 
past or current owner or operator of any site with ongoing reclamation 
obligations or subject to violations listed pursuant to section 510(c) 
of this Act (30 U.S.C. 1260(c)).'' We suggest updating the definition 
to read ``Is not a past or current owner or operator, and does not 
share a common owner or parent company with a past or current owner or 
operator, of any site with ongoing reclamation obligations or subject 
to violations listed pursuant to section 510(c) of this Act (30 U.S.C. 
1260(c)).''
                     communications with the public
    Last, there is a provision in this act that requires a notice be 
provided to ``adjacent and downstream landowners and the public before 
the project is initiated.'' That is important, but should go further in 
providing each of the listed entities the opportunity to express 
concerns and have those concerns addressed by either the state or the 
Community Reclaimer. After all, a notice in the mail can raise a lot 
more questions than it answers.
    Regardless of how beneficial a project might be, neighbors may 
raise legitimate issues. They deserve an accessible and clear method of 
sharing their thoughts with the Community Reclaimer and the state and 
to have their concerns addressed in a timely manner.
    To be perfectly clear, we are not advocating for the creation of a 
bureaucratic barrier that could serve to prevent good projects from 
moving forward, nor do we want to allow any person from stopping 
projects without cause. Instead, we think the bill could be improved by 
making a clear requirement that the public should be given a reasonable 
opportunity to express concerns and have those concerns addressed.
    In doing so, it should also be clarified in the bill which entity 
is responsible for communication with the public from a project's 
inception to completion: the state or the Community Reclaimer. It 
appears that the responsibility falls to the Community Reclaimer, but 
clarification would be helpful.
                               conclusion
    As the Community Reclaimer Protection Act moves forward, we hope 
you'll consider our thoughts and ensure that re-mining is not 
considered eligible for liability waivers and that local communities 
are given an opportunity to voice concerns and have them addressed. If 
the Committee is able to sufficiently address those issues while 
providing non-governmental entities the liability coverage they need to 
help clean up Appalachian streams, then we would urge Congress to pass 
this bill quickly.
                                 ______
    Dr. Gosar. I thank the gentleman.
    The Chair now recognizes Mr. Stefanko for his testimony. 
Thank you.
</option>
    <option> ACTIVE AND ABANDONED MINE OPERATIONS, PENNSYLVANIA DEPARTMENT 
   OF ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION, HARRISBURG, PENNSYLVANIA, ON 
BEHALF OF THE INTERSTATE MINING COMPACT COMMISSION AND NATIONAL 
          ASSOCIATION OF ABANDONED MINE LAND PROGRAMS
    Mr. Stefanko. Thank you, Mr. Chairman and members of the 
Committee. I am appearing here today on behalf of the 
Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, the Interstate Mining Compact 
Commission, and the National Association of Abandoned Mine Land 
Programs. We appreciate the opportunity to share our 
perspective on the status of the abandoned mine drainage 
treatment efforts, and to express our support for this much-
needed amendment to SMCRA.
    Acid mine drainage, casually known as AMD, is a massive and 
pervasive problem. In Pennsylvania alone, over 5,600 miles of 
streams are impacted by AMD pollution from abandoned coal 
mines. The impacts to the health, environment, and economic 
livelihoods of our state's communities are felt every day, and 
the story is similar for historic coal communities throughout 
the country.
    The AML program, under SMCRA, gives states the resources 
they need to counteract coal AML problems within their borders, 
including impacts to water resources. In an era of increasing 
economic hardship for coal field communities, this work has 
become more important than ever. But due to the problematic 
overlap in Federal law applicable to treatment of these sites, 
the AML programs are not being allowed to fully realize their 
mission.
    Coal AML sites are generally handled exclusively through 
SMCRA, but in cases where the Clean Water Act potentially 
applies, the state's responsibilities are generally unclear. 
And where they are clear, they are typically not practical, and 
this is having a chilling effect on the state's efforts to 
address AMD.
    The Clean Water Act, as a cornerstone of Federal 
environmental law, is intentionally very strict in regulating 
impacts to our Nation's water resources. But as an unintended 
consequence of the strict design, its requirements simply do 
not comport well with the realities of treating AMD from 
abandoned mines. These sites are, by definition, already 
polluted and, therefore, do not meet the Clean Water Act 
standards at the time treatment begins.
    Furthermore, the nature of AMD pollution is such that, in 
many cases, no amount of remediation work could achieve these 
standards fully in any case. Even so, joint and several 
liability under the Clean Water Act means any party who affects 
such a site becomes permanently responsible for treating the 
discharge to meet full standards.
    As a result, the states and their partners are exposed to 
significant, undeserved potential liability in the due course 
of their work, even where the project is authorized under 
SMCRA, conducted properly, and improving water quality.
    The key to resolving these issues is bringing clarity and 
practicality to the responsibilities borne by the AML programs 
as they conduct AMD projects. The bill before the Committee 
today--or discussion bill--would accomplish that goal by 
setting an established process for states to work with the 
relevant government authorities to outline a clear, achievable 
strategy for AMD water treatment under SMCRA. This will result 
in more prevalent and effective AMD water treatment work by the 
state AML programs, and more effective overall implementation 
of Federal law with respect to these sites.
    As much as these obstacles to the AMD treatment work can 
strain and complicate state efforts, circumstances are even 
worse for the state's potential partners. These groups tend to 
have limited sources of funding, often in the form of discreet 
grants, and are, therefore, all the more vulnerable to the 
risks of undeserved liability.
    Pennsylvania recognized long ago that with the availability 
of these voluntary efforts, many of the state's abandoned mine 
discharges would be eliminated or improved at little or no cost 
to the Pennsylvania taxpayer, if only the potential for 
undeserved liability could be addressed.
    To that end, Pennsylvania enacted its Environmental Good 
Samaritan Act of 1999, under which 79 AMD treatment projects 
have been undertaken in various partnerships among the 
Commonwealth. While these projects often do not strictly adhere 
to Clean Water standards, they nevertheless significantly 
improve water quality in receiving streams, the aggregate 
effect of which produces drastic improvements in overall health 
of the greater watershed at a comparatively low cost.
    Pennsylvania's program has enabled these projects to occur 
without risk of undue liability under state law, but great 
risks still remain for the Commonwealth and their partners 
under Federal law, and still more projects could be pursued if 
not for that fact.
    The bill will allow the state-level program in Pennsylvania 
to achieve its full potential, and will provide the mechanism 
for other states to follow the successful model, and to enhance 
our own AMD treatment. The specter of undeserved liability 
under current circumstances constrains the state's efforts 
under SMCRA, and deters motivated, well-intentioned volunteers 
from assisting in that work, which serves only to prolong the 
environmental, social, and economic harm these sites represent.
    With this bill, Congress has the opportunity to restore 
SMCRA's role in AMD water treatment, enable the state AML 
programs and their partners to make meaningful progress in 
restoring our watersheds, and, in doing so, put an important 
piece of coal country's future into place. Thank you.
</option>
</Hearing>
