<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H11A9483B3A3C4AC089D0A9A2F08594AE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5269 IH: State and Territorial Approval for Restriction of Fishing Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5269</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180314">March 14, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000600">Mrs. Radewagen</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require State or territorial approval of restriction by the Secretary of the Interior and the Secretary of Commerce of recreational or commercial fishing access to certain State or territorial waters, respectively.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB55C72538AF248A2B4A00A90B658F34B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H65071D9708164104A59CF3095922FF8A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>State and Territorial Approval for Restriction of Fishing Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>STAR Fishing Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE46F02460D714DC48C97B01426D47EE6"><enum>2.</enum><header>State or territorial approval of restriction of recreational or commercial fishing access to certain State or territorial waters</header> <subsection id="H1BE47B50B46441AB8D2B10431B852FA2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Approval required</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior and the Secretary of Commerce shall not restrict recreational or commercial fishing access to any State or territorial marine waters or Great Lakes waters within the jurisdiction of the National Park Service or the Office of National Marine Sanctuaries, respectively, unless those restrictions are developed in coordination with, and approved by, the fish and wildlife management agency of the State or territory that has fisheries management authority over those waters.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HFD891177869E4EF0B1E663B46B98344F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>marine waters</term> includes coastal waters and estuaries.</text> </subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

