<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDF4402C78D8B4E10B155A134B5F253EE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5866 IH: To amend title 38, United States Code, to authorize individuals who are pursuing programs of rehabilitation, education, or training under laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to receive work-study allowances for certain outreach services provided through congressional offices, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5866</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180517">May 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000191">Mr. DeFazio</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to authorize individuals who are pursuing programs of rehabilitation, education, or training under laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to receive work-study allowances for certain outreach services provided through congressional offices, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H174A92A54CEA4B2C8AF55E2E704FCFFA" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF0BA1B51645A40F39F8A24A1E394E1FA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Expansion of work-study allowance to include certain outreach services conducted through congressional offices</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3485(a)(4) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA90514EAA9E74245A3019EF8AF51AEB6" style="USC"> <subparagraph id="HAFA071CE71D44ADB980F97FF845A5638" indent="up1"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The following activities carried out at the offices of Members of Congress for such Members:</text> 
<clause id="HA6FD7D11C243496BBD407503BED0A0AE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The distribution of information to members of the Armed Forces, veterans, and their dependents about the benefits and services under laws administered by the Secretary and other appropriate governmental and non-governmental programs.</text></clause> <clause id="H185C86FD67524E4BB60D1BB80A8BE37F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The preparation and processing of papers and other documents, including documents to assist in the preparation and presentation of claims for benefits under laws administered by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

