<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H33E32E487A544865A52444EF15B3C64E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5562 IH: Protecting Neonatal Abstinence Syndrome Babies Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5562</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180418">April 18, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000297">Mr. Jenkins of West Virginia</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Health and Human Services to develop a strategy implementing certain recommendations relating to the Protecting Our Infants Act of 2015, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HAF0A42C461DD4C398CA07E452581D6F2" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H10C540C967434272A25855A519311C33" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Neonatal Abstinence Syndrome Babies Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Protecting NAS Babies Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H3B6CA493907C47C09B5118AF6EA88F9E" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H55111A13C3AF469D8A2E25A6D33DF1D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Neonatal abstinence syndrome (referred to in this section as “NAS”) is a group of conditions that can afflict a newborn who had in utero exposure to drugs, including opioids.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB5083ECE1170440D98F05A5792B10517"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to a report by the Government Accountability Office, symptoms of NAS include irritability, loud crying, stiffness, sweating, vomiting, diarrhea, poor feeding, seizures, and respiratory distress.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H403CE2ED00204CECB23F18839D147942"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to a 2016 study by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, which was based on data from 28 States, the incidence of NAS increased 300 percent between 1999 and 2013.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H22D1A8284DD44702AEF32CBEB5CCB2AC"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to another study entitled, <quote>Neonatal abstinence syndrome and associated health care expenditures: United States, 2000–2009</quote>, the incidence rate of NAS in rural America rose from 1.2 per 1,000 hospital births in 2004 to 7.5 per 1,000 hospital births in 2013.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H72E880D01838445C889B503CFC499C04"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Innovative, specialized, and collaborative efforts are needed to address the treatment of infants diagnosed with NAS.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6E5244495D554511BA7CC8E3871C650D"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comprehensive Addiction and Recovery Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/198">Public Law 114–198</external-xref>), which was enacted in July 2016, required the Government Accountability Office to examine treatment options for infants with NAS (including options available under State Medicaid plans under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396</external-xref> et seq.)), assesses different medical care models and settings for the treatment of NAS, and prioritizes finding best practices for the treatment of infants with NAS.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H932DEBDACDF4472BB6B7CEDC3ADBBD9E"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An October 2017 report by the Government Accountability Office entitled, “Federal Action Needed to Address Neonatal Abstinence Syndrome”, recommended that the Department of Health and Human Services should take action on its report entitled, <quote>Protecting Our Infants Act: Final Strategy</quote>.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HF68BC27CA6644771A853CA732A5DFE14"><enum>3.</enum><header>Strategy implementing certain recommendations relating to Protecting Our Infants Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than six months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit to Congress a strategy for implementing recommendations under the <quote>child</quote> categories in the Department of Health and Human Services Behavioral Health Coordinating Council report entitled, <quote>Protecting Our Infants Act: Final Strategy</quote>. Such strategy shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9417ACD27CA848DFAF6764A442B7EE4F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>include a timeline for the implementation of each such recommendation;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H99CE3E3A92C14689965B0E8D9FBE032C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide for the dissemination of information to State health agencies on best practices and available resources and data with respect to implementing each such recommendation; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFD16614F9C0F4E6A91D0EAA4392F9C5C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>include recommendations for any statutory change, including providing for additional authorities, that would help the Department of Health and Human Services implement the strategy.</text> </paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

