<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H82E24417DE37489195190EBF7F46DC26" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5511 IH: Healthy Communities Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5511</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180413">April 13, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to require that the recommendations of the United States
			 Preventive Services Task Force on the effectiveness, appropriateness, and
			 cost-effectiveness of clinical preventive services be based on data for
			 the respective populations, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H96EC06B326A84BE3A29BB824EC846C53" style="OLC">
 <section id="H49727913B2FD47B0A508A9B034C74379" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Healthy Communities Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H60F268EAB05443CA8D9D8FFBA0B721C6" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H90EC24F5A7914C4F86C86FF15761F6EF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Despite marked reductions in health disparities following the enactment of the Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/148">Public Law 111–148</external-xref>), racial and ethnic disparities in medical status and access to health care persist in the United States.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFB0B1FB4D65D4542BE7A5E245EDDCDEB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>According to the Centers for Disease Control, from 2010 to 2014, breast cancer mortality was 41 percent higher among African-American women than White women.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD3C58FBF3BF246A68EA0074C57D76B39"><enum>(3)</enum><text>According to the Alzheimer’s Association, among individuals in the United States who are over 65 years of age, African-American individuals are about twice as likely to have Alzheimer’s disease, and Hispanic individuals are about 1<fraction>1/2</fraction> times as likely as White individuals.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4EECCCFFCB3D4582B8C810638E1D1EA4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The National Institutes of Health finds that African Americans, despite making up 13 percent of the population of the United States, account for about 35 percent of individuals with kidney failure in the United States.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5EAEB3124AC8444BABF1370DFDD29313"><enum>(5)</enum><text>According to research published in the Journal Frontiers in Bioscience, in the United States, African American men are 1.6 times as likely to develop, and 2 times as likely to die from, prostate cancer when compared to White men.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC8A30BEAB6134C02B316EA9E43AE26B5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Underutilization of preventive health services remains a barrier to reducing the chronic disease burden in the United States, particularly among racial and ethnic minorities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB82A9FD7E4764C4A9507E31B45AE6B77"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The Surgeon General of the Public Health Service has stated that <quote>Reducing disparities in health will give everyone a chance to live a healthy life and improve the quality of life for all Americans.</quote>.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H329DA14B03AB483C909A2A1658E4B7C5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Basing recommendations of United States Preventive Services Task Force on data for the respective
 populations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 915(a) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/299b-4">42 U.S.C. 299b–4(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H707A3544ED344560823F9EB9B45107CD" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H5417CC2ED31F44BBBB8B39244EE20ABB"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Basing recommendations on data for respective populations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making and updating recommendations on the effectiveness, appropriateness, and cost-effectiveness of clinical preventive services, as described in paragraph (1), the Task Force shall base such recommendations on data for the respective populations, including health disparity populations (as defined in section 464z–3(d)).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body>
</bill>


