<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HAF06F3847C004852B6894F9C76557A39" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5247 IH: Trickett Wendler, Frank Mongiello, Jordan McLinn, and Matthew Bellina Right to Try Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5247</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180313">March 13, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000568">Mr. Griffith</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000213">Mr. Barton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001243">Mrs. Blackburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001260">Mr. Buchanan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001105">Mrs. Comstock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001096">Mr. Cramer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001048">Mr. Culberson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001273">Mrs. Black</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000464">Mr. Faso</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001078">Mrs. Handel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001053">Mrs. Hartzler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000587">Mr. Lewis of Minnesota</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001198">Mr. Marshall</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001187">Mr. Meadows</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001189">Mr. Messer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001274">Mr. Brooks of Alabama</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000598">Mr. Rothfus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001191">Ms. Sinema</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000362">Mr. King of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Y000065">Mr. Yoho</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001092">Mr. Collins of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Y000063">Mr. Yoder</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001045">Mr. Harper</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000567">Mr. Lance</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000372">Mr. Allen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan of South Carolina</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001056">Ms. Herrera Beutler</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the use of eligible investigational drugs by eligible patients who have been diagnosed
			 with a stage of a disease or condition in which there is reasonable
			 likelihood that death will occur within a matter of months, or with
			 another eligible illness, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HBED720B7614C4D96A6EA0E87D728FECD" style="OLC">
 <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF0AA1AC83F374809A5739593222600DE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Trickett Wendler, Frank Mongiello, Jordan McLinn, and Matthew Bellina Right to Try Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HC552E0D14A9A4F7B86A11688EAEA32AF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Use of unapproved investigational drugs by patients diagnosed with a terminal illness</header> <subsection id="HB402719BB3F34B2786F65B0291E9745A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subchapter E of chapter V of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360bbb">21 U.S.C. 360bbb</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by inserting after section 561A (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360bbb-0">21 U.S.C. 360bbb–0</external-xref>) the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1A6EAF68764440C7A2B8979C33E29429" style="OLC">
					<section id="HEB4CAF1E7D464DF590D3FE4E33EAE659"><enum>561B.</enum><header>Investigational drugs for use by eligible patients</header>
 <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2E48EBB5A0A04899B93E1F5AF103B404"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section:</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC831BA647B084668A9800722759AEBFE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible patient</term> means a patient—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD4091DF4EC04483F809D5E7D564A7C4C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who has been diagnosed with an eligible illness;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3051865815E44B4FA020E4D759F618AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who has exhausted approved treatment options and is not eligible to participate in (for a reason such as the patient not meeting inclusion criteria) a clinical trial designed to evaluate an investigational drug for the treatment of such eligible illness with which the patient has been diagnosed, including one involving the eligible investigational drug, or for whom participation in such a clinical trial is not feasible (for a reason such as a lack of geographic proximity to the clinical trial), as certified by a physician, who—</text>
 <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8CFA2D31B0A7446ABA8A9818F62CEE9E"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is in good standing with the physician’s licensing organization or board; and</text> </clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H54FACE156B1B4FF184C7359AFF39580E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">will not be compensated for so certifying; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF58F5011C79D4E2891138DC65AA5B542"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who has provided to the treating physician written informed consent, as described in part 50 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations), regarding the eligible investigational drug, or, as applicable, on whose behalf a legally authorized representative of the patient has provided such consent.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEEB728EF89A84E2E8F15AD00FF843608"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible investigational drug</term> means an investigational drug (as such term is used in section 561)—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F424863394D4440A2EEFEB93445D752"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for which a phase 1 clinical trial has been completed;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2A8577D74AF247B19AF8D63017BB5E5D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that has not been approved or licensed for any use under section 505 of this Act or section 351 of the Public Health Service Act;</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD3C59E2527754126B46DB537123E469E"><enum>(C)</enum>
 <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H26CE132D090D41ADBB1648AFF98DEF47"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for which an application has been filed under section 505(b) of this Act or section 351(a) of the Public Health Service Act, as applicable, that is active; or</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H75445B839B654B3BA821E99F5149C0C5" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that is under investigation in a clinical trial that—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2A3EC5437EFC4C5EB09735CD507A7727"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is intended to form the primary basis of a claim of effectiveness in support of approval or licensure under section 505 of this Act or section 351 of the Public Health Service Act; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE867DA1B1C114942A3A1EA72B7410DBA"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is the subject of an active investigational new drug application under section 505(i) of this Act or section 351(a)(3) of the Public Health Service Act, as applicable; and</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H84F26E97034E45CFAC913B7E865CF337"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the active development or production of which—</text> <clause id="HFD6E0C36D1D7458494B42178A68A8DF9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is ongoing;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA9E9CB9BB08F4232ADCA96A79B5DFE66"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has not been discontinued by the manufacturer; and</text> </clause><clause id="HF270335A9B0E4527AE9F941EFA55FBB7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is not the subject of a clinical hold under the regulations implementing section 505(i) or section 351(a)(3) of the Public Health Service Act, as applicable.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4E88DB497D8E43DAB6B49F2896879671"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>phase 1 trial</term> means a phase 1 clinical investigation of a drug as described in section 312.21 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H35465AE9B42748729874A17898EE1D7F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible illness</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H9FA0D9318DB34F4FB2BB25B1CDD0936C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a stage of a disease or condition in which there is reasonable likelihood that death will occur within a matter of months; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9AE36DFBFC0740989F9DF3EB75C2D6F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a disease or condition that would result in significant irreversible morbidity that is likely to lead to severely premature death.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCD94DE6C8DF743D5A411855528ADA176"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Alternative pathway for eligible patients with a terminal illness</header>
 <paragraph id="H5851009A0C2E457D9E4DDACD3576DF08"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Eligible investigational drugs provided to eligible patients in compliance with this section are exempt from sections 502(f), 503(b)(4), and subsections (a) and (i) of section 505 of this Act, and section 351(a) of the Public Health Service Act so long as the conditions specified in paragraphs (2), (3), and (4) are met with respect to the provision of such investigational drugs.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBFE59EDE56CB4B27885AE5C03524CDFC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compliance with certain regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The conditions specified in this paragraph, with respect to an eligible investigational drug referred to in paragraph (1), are that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H0CCE831C1A28452DB8C465AE3800FA53"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the eligible investigational drug is labeled in accordance with section 312.6 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE87761EBE3904AF0BA6135B197A149FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the provision of such eligible investigational drug occurs in compliance with the applicable requirements set forth in sections 312.7 and 312.8(d)(1) of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations) that apply to investigational drugs, subject to paragraph (5).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HECA7C16D79234DA9A0E7DCE50109A89C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The condition specified in this paragraph, with respect to an eligible investigational drug referred to in paragraph (1), is that the sponsor of such eligible investigational drug notifies the Secretary of the provision of such eligible investigational drug for use by an eligible patient pursuant to this section. Such notification shall be submitted within 7 business days of the provision of such eligible investigational drug as correspondence to the investigational new drug application described in subsection (a)(2).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5F1749C47E0648AF818C4AD2A687D1F8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Adverse event reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The condition specified in this paragraph, with respect to an eligible investigational drug referred to in paragraph (1), is that the sponsor or manufacturer of such eligible investigational drug has required, as a condition of providing the drug to a physician for use by an eligible patient pursuant to this section, that such physician will immediately report to such sponsor or manufacturer any serious adverse events, as such term is defined in section 312.32 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations), associated with the use of the eligible investigational drug by the eligible patient.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC58E0921704C4F8C9AC755250714042B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Application</header><text>For purposes of this section, the requirements set forth in sections 312.7 and 312.8(d)(1) of title 21 of the Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations) are deemed to apply to any person who manufactures, distributes, prescribes, dispenses, introduces or delivers for introduction into interstate commerce, or provides to an eligible patient an eligible investigational drug pursuant to this section.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDC47AF00BB89439BA491DB3FF7D61F20"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Use of clinical outcomes</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H86BEFF60C9A84F069004DBBEB776D4A0"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, the Public Health Service Act, or any other provision of Federal law, the Secretary may not use a clinical outcome associated with the use of an eligible investigational drug pursuant to this section to delay or adversely affect the review or approval of such drug under section 505 of this Act or section 351 of the Public Health Service Act unless—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE39EEBD472244F9F8EEF6DB1DE0AC343"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary makes a determination, in accordance with paragraph (2), that use of such clinical outcome is critical to determining the safety of the eligible investigational drug; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE5B9B858CC1B4CBF86A82896017AC232"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the sponsor requests use of such outcomes.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEB1849C0A39B49799CED45B9B29DFBB7"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary makes a determination under paragraph (1)(A), the Secretary shall provide written notice of such determination to the sponsor, including a public health justification for such determination, and such notice shall be made part of the administrative record. Such determination shall not be delegated below the director of the agency center that is charged with the premarket review of the eligible investigational drug.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H96BA2ABCE78848BF9DA80549E256C55A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The manufacturer or sponsor of an eligible investigational drug that provides an eligible investigational drug pursuant to this section shall post on the same publicly available internet website used by the manufacturer for purposes of section 561A(b) an annual summary of any provision by the manufacturer or sponsor of an eligible investigational drug under this section. The summary shall include the number of requests received, the number of requests granted, the number of patients treated, the therapeutic area of the drug made available, and any known or suspected serious adverse events, as such term is defined in section 312.32 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations), associated with the use of the eligible investigational drug.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H05BD1DF099514850B863B5309950F3C5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed as limiting the authority of the Secretary to require manufacturers or sponsors of investigational drugs to review and report information relevant to the safety of such investigational drug obtained or otherwise received by the sponsor pursuant to part 312 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF245963D892F439295CE7FA5105E86F8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No liability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 561B of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, as added by subsection (a), is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7B917C63D8494540A03EE30DDF26C0D8" style="OLC">
					<subsection commented="no" id="H1ACED02ED0DC4348811D9C773254DD7F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Liability</header>
						<paragraph commented="no" id="H7B94D7F7B2FD453F8FC66DDA4BBEC25F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Alleged acts or omissions</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H83C0D432986B4D38847531DBE1DCBEA9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Manufacturer or sponsor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No manufacturer or sponsor (or their agent or representative) of an investigational drug shall be liable for any alleged act or omission related to the provision of such drug to a single patient or small group of patients for treatment use in accordance with subsection (b) or (c) of section 561 or the provision of an eligible investigational drug to an eligible patient in accordance with this section, including, with respect to the provision of an investigational drug under section 561 or an eligible investigational drug under this section, the reporting of safety information, from clinical trials or any other source, as required by section 312.32 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations).</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA76FB3744C2F4051996AA72D1B841E0A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Physician, clinical investigator, or hospital</header>
 <clause commented="no" id="H1C515A78E8554F1DBD37BC76F314493E"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No licensed physician, clinical investigator, or hospital shall be liable for any alleged act or omission related to the provision of an investigational drug to a single patient or small group of patients for treatment use in accordance with subsection (b) or (c) of section 561, as described in clause (ii), or the provision of an eligible investigational drug to an eligible patient in accordance with this section, unless such act or omission constitutes on the part of such physician, clinical investigator, or hospital with respect to such investigational drug or eligible investigational drug—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="H5CF918209CED4514B04CCE39877BFBC4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>willful or criminal misconduct;</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H2246E041491245C8A9935221379FCE0D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>reckless misconduct;</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HBE199825405540339B954DDF10ECDA22"><enum>(III)</enum><text>gross negligence relative to the applicable standard of care and practice with respect to the administration or dispensing of such investigational drug; or</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HA55D926A593145FA8080ED0FF7537EBA"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>an intentional tort under applicable State law.</text> </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HB97439D50E84442C88469609CEB28D2C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements described in this clause are the requirements under subsection (b) or (c) of section 561, including—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="H98CC725B2DFF41C080FB80953441AB3E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the reporting of safety information, from clinical trials or any other source, as required by section 312.32 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations);</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H97624489A7BA43209CDF3FC0A5B31DB1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>ensuring that the informed consent requirements of part 50 of title 21, Code of the Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations) are met; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H0979649D048A491E9D1EA6669FDF04D3"><enum>(III)</enum><text>ensuring that review by an institutional review board is obtained in a manner consistent with the requirements of part 56 of title 21, Code of the Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations).</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H482B4218F28F431A9806F306AEA3CBC0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination not to provide drug</header><text>No manufacturer, sponsor, licensed physician, clinical investigator, or hospital shall be liable for determining not to provide access to an investigational drug under this section or for discontinuing any such access that it initially determined to provide.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H1FD45C7BBE6E4BD3BF6BB5381C3A0EA5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HE1DF3C68F8C64D0495796F7673F113B3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as set forth in paragraphs (1) and (2), nothing in this section shall be construed to modify or otherwise affect the right of any person to bring a private action against a manufacturer or sponsor (or their agent or representative), physician, clinical investigator, hospital, prescriber, dispenser, or other entity under any State or Federal product liability, tort, consumer protection, or warranty law.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1B27A8CCA13348BD92FB903CDE0FCE70"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Federal Government</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to modify or otherwise affect the authority of the Federal Government to bring suit under any Federal law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


