<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HCC21972E1F2A4C0EBADCBA82A9132D06" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5889 IH: Recognizing Early Childhood Trauma Related to Substance Abuse Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5889</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180521">May 21, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001290">Mr. Brat</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="O000171">Mr. O'Halleran</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Health and Human Services to disseminate information, resources, and if
			 requested, technical assistance to early childhood care and education
			 providers and professionals working with young children on ways to
			 properly recognize and respond to children who may be impacted by trauma
			 related to substance abuse.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H0DC67CA8AFBA4DE186C7A45D6CF0EBB4" style="OLC">
 <section id="H8A43385F1BA94928B8859CDEB963F8A3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Recognizing Early Childhood Trauma Related to Substance Abuse Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H0302EE56DD0E4BC29FDAB6AE4C294681"><enum>2.</enum><header>Recognizing Early Childhood Trauma Related to Substance Abuse</header> <subsection id="H916754BCB5BA4C89B24E95E24894EA4B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Dissemination of information</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall disseminate information, resources, and, if requested, technical assistance to early childhood care and education providers and professionals working with young children on—</text>
 <paragraph id="H564CF311270B4C9CADA3BF6C3D28C199"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ways to properly recognize children who may be impacted by trauma related to substance abuse by a family member or other adult, and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDB7A8BCA6F8E432395E734BC7F37FB1A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>how to respond appropriately in order to provide for the safety and well-being of young children and their families.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD50871BA00D54B64B2B65117D324AF8B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Goals</header><text>The information, resources, and technical assistance provided under subsection (a) shall—</text> <paragraph id="H466779C610F94B579EE547983D0406C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">educate early childhood care and education providers and professionals working with young children on understanding and identifying the early signs and risk factors of children who might be impacted by trauma due to exposure to substance abuse,</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H493BA5B4FAF64E3BA3605ACF76814988"><enum>(2)</enum><text>suggest age-appropriate communication tools, procedures, and practices for trauma-informed care, including ways to prevent or mitigate the effects of trauma,</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCCAC5ED5E15049A9A18B025EEFDC6ED4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide options for responding to children impacted by trauma due to exposure to substance abuse that consider the needs of the child and family, including recommending resources and referrals for evidence-based services to support such family, and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H78A5BBD424D64DE79B09D541467025FC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>promote whole-family and multi-generational approaches to prevent separation and support re-unification of families whenever possible and in the best interest of the child.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8F9A04ED0F4742A29846BC3B81C32A8D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Such information, resources, and if applicable, technical assistance, shall not be construed to amend the requirements under—</text>
 <paragraph id="HABD0407CE0BD4A6B8AC4E138885A0448"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Child Care and Development Block Grant Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9858">42 U.S.C. 9858</external-xref> et seq.),</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HC4D7751ECF664C56BA0C18A8E72897C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Head Start Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9831">42 U.S.C. 9831</external-xref> et seq.), or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCE12224772244DB0B976E0D655DD4274"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1400">20 U.S.C. 1400</external-xref> et seq.).</text> </paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

