<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9BB0C8BFAF6741D5B2F2EB1C6927C15E" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4989 IH: Protecting Diplomats from Surveillance Through Consumer Devices Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4989</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180208">February 8, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Department of State to establish a policy regarding the use of location-tracking
			 consumer devices by employees at diplomatic and consular facilities, and
			 for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H25356570DADD4FBFAA111A8FDCD9E959" style="OLC">
 <section id="H474A4E2860BC4AA3AAF1BB0E90AE1150" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Diplomats from Surveillance Through Consumer Devices Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H296F7C9AC881477E9D34E5C3E9FBAFAC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Secure United States diplomatic and consular facilities against cy足ber足sur足veil足lance</header> <subsection id="HD9C54ED75A564F2A92D64B8BA7BAB0AA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Policy on location-Tracking consumer devices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall establish a policy on the use of location-tracking consumer devices, including GPS-enabled devices, at United States diplomatic and consular facilities by United States Government employees, contractors, locally employed staff and members of other agencies deployed to or stationed at such facilities.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H630B61687B444844811D4C333C7606BA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Security briefing</header><text>Existing and new employees at United States diplomatic and consular facilities, including contractors, locally employed staff, and members of other agencies deployed to or stationed at such facilities, shall, as a part of the security briefings provided to such employees, be informed of the policy described in subsection (a) and given instructions on the use of location-tracking consumer devices both on and off the premises of such facilities.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H4B0B9A079238426F94AC90256AECE9FD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Secretary of State may coordinate with the heads of any other agencies whose employees are deployed to or stationed at United States diplomatic and consular facilities in the formulation of the policy described in subsection (a) and the dissemination of such policy pursuant to subsection (b).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HBBE1C9637C9D4F48991F1FC858618DA2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the formulation of the policy described in subsection (a), the Secretary of State shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on the details of such policy.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


