<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA833EF5B78D14968AA92A41FD249B110" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5604 IH: Healthy Environment for Children Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5604</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180424">April 24, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001200">Mr. McEachin</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To prohibit any reduction, consolidation, or termination of offices and activities related to science research within the Environmental Protection Agency.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HEA84949AD37046ED8D65996157792EC1" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HCD9326B27E7742DB853C99A623338C2B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Healthy Environment for Children Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> <section id="H243F4B0DCDCF44B39100D157D72394BA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition of reduction, consolidation, or termination of the National Center for Environmental Research of the Environmental Protection Agency</header> <subsection id="H0264FC10BF10404FB5B0D969F841B3AC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6AD378B814E14B75A6768C55F6719BAC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may not reduce, consolidate, or terminate the National Center for Environmental Research; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE54E3AEBC3D4490FB867893338BF0EE9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall take such actions as are necessary to ensure that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA0BEE203C459451C99915F3A0011E343"><enum>(A)</enum><text>no reduction, consolidation, or termination occurs with respect to the activities described in subsection (b) that is not otherwise required by law; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDF0281281FA6494190BDBD019F81EDDA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each activity described in such subsection is carried out to the full extent provided by law. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1EB67A4ADAB7486FBE7BDA097A675A8A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Programs and research areas</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The activities under this subsection include all intramural grants, extramural grants, and research carried out by the National Center for Environmental Research, including—</text> <paragraph id="H017D748197494ACEAED96B4610808D5B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>research and grants to protect the health of children and adults from chemical exposure;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCD1D8493CE6A4F6B8580A235E35DD4C4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>funding for the Science To Achieve Results program that provides grants given to Children’s Environmental Health and Disease Prevention Research Centers;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFE0E7AD82B4F4496900E260857EEFC9B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>research intended to reduce children’s health risks from environmental factors;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEB2629B0D3334D939A2011DDF548D420"><enum>(4)</enum><text>research on air pollution, climate change, and air quality and their impacts on children and adults, including expecting mothers and newborns;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCA0419019816426A89D7B032217381BC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>research on water quality, availability, and potential contaminants that could affect the health of children;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB3BC2BD92CDB426BA0C3E6C5E24E012E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>safer chemical research grants supporting the development of innovative science to support safer, more sustainable use of chemicals in consumer products;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H12CCD6E60F9E45EDB6E771090DA279D9"><enum>(7)</enum><text>research grants to protect ecosystems and the air and water resources that provide numerous benefits for humans; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE301AFD9010C4EA49BF85C73C2D36822"><enum>(8)</enum><text>sustainability research to understand the conditions under which humans and nature can exist in productive harmony to support present and future generations; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H14DDEA38C01A4AC3BAC2D7061832F3D8"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">grants, fellowships, or competitions related to any of the 6 research programs supported by the Office of Research and Development, including the Small Business Innovation Research program, the Science To Achieve Results program, and the People, Prosperity and the Planet program.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


