<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H4B3FAC58D3BC43F588E9FCDA0CEC366D" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5798 IH: Opioid Screening and Chronic Pain Management Alternatives for Seniors Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5798</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180515">May 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000594">Mr. Paulsen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to require a review of current opioid prescriptions
			 for chronic pain and screening for opioid use disorder to be included in
			 the Welcome to Medicare initial preventive physical examination.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H5A927A93FC72427A8B274A013DEFD64F" style="OLC">
 <section id="H4156A9B9A0D3407AB122ECBC20FC855F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Opioid Screening and Chronic Pain Management Alternatives for Seniors Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HFBDB0D5B8E28457F91BFF159AAAA5F58"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requiring a review of current opioid prescriptions for chronic pain and screening for opioid use disorder to be included in the Welcome to Medicare initial preventive physical examination</header> <subsection id="H2FD76CFA4BD34BAAB179A61F3A27610F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1861(ww) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(ww)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H32EBEA8BC88C4EDFA9072204AFFBC30B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>and a review of current opioid prescriptions and screening for opioid use disorder (as defined in paragraph (4)),</quote> before <quote>but does not include</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H91AB73A00B4847D590AC872B372CAA1B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDE15B50D119A445BAD0FF93AD36B5523" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HA9C84C62ACA94AB0BB13240BB466D1BA" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA18864F2CC4049868F81DE74A23710F7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the term <quote>a review of current opioid prescriptions and screening for opioid use disorder</quote> means, with respect to an individual—</text>
 <clause id="H20881672552C4D48909E859E37A171F1" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a review by a physician or qualified non-physician practitioner of all current prescriptions of the individual; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H35686762CEB647FCB2E6E058012C3866" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an individual determined by the review of a physician or qualified non-physician practitioner under subparagraph (A) to have a current prescription for opioids for chronic pain that has been prescribed for a minimum period of time (as specified by the Secretary)—</text>
 <subclause id="H7920D409073E4D648E7A8DDA781230DA"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a review by the physician or practitioner of the potential risk factors to the individual for opioid use disorder;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H59A67BA6828A4498BB10684A966C5101"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an evaluation by the physician or practitioner of pain of the individual;</text> </subclause><subclause id="H36BA9DB753804B8D92E74B1934446435"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the provision of information regarding non-opioid treatment options for the treatment and management of any chronic pain of the individual; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HEAF9AC1A394645529DD001543F3A9D6F"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if determined necessary by the physician or practitioner based on the results of the review and evaluation conducted as described in this paragraph, an appropriate referral by the physician or practitioner for additional treatment.</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D8E932320754E12BEFB2290DD618A45" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <quote>qualified non-physician practitioner</quote> means a physician assistant, nurse practitioner, or certified clinical nurse specialist.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H91D35827F90F464C852B91AE61948DA3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall apply with respect to initial preventive physical examinations furnished on or after January 1, 2020.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


