<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9DCC32BDF62F4BC59FF2FA832D50553A" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5485 IH: Hemp Farming Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5485</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180412">April 12, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001108">Mr. Comer</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000598">Mr. Polis</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 to provide for State and Tribal regulation of hemp
			 production, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H61FED0734A6B43598D93361BB8CC5F1A" style="OLC">
 <section id="H61E37C8711384FB99BB9309606D66EA9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hemp Farming Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section commented="no" id="H5FC880796D1B47D6BBC124A2326D9C30"><enum>2.</enum><header>Hemp production</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1621">7 U.S.C. 1621</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEEC876745375479C9FC7282C8430A96F" style="OLC">
				<subtitle id="H8299E9D9C83140BCA46544D66F7A8EF9" style="OLC"><enum>G</enum><header>Hemp Production</header>
 <section id="H7E7D0ED1C47B420D8E072CDBC025C02F"><enum>297A.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this subtitle:</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H17140628DFA7420D9E368AA94E7BC77A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Hemp</header><text>The term <term>hemp</term> means the plant Cannabis sativa L. and any part of that plant, including the seeds thereof and all derivatives, extracts, cannabinoids, isomers, acids, salts, and salts of isomers, whether growing or not, with a delta-9 tetrahydrocannabinol concentration of not more than 0.3 percent on a dry weight basis.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD7C352326C794DE993FB6E95E8CBC0B6"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Indian tribe</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Indian tribe</term> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the <act-name parsable-cite="ISDA">Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H8C291F326EAC48EFB290EEF1D8B40612"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Agriculture.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H99A66A59DEBB426FB675D770384D0421"><enum>(4)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H71EC7713C9204F16930B8E3F363D45DD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF28348CDDC534F9B8179F0D7CAA876EC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the District of Columbia;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B22D49BCFEF404A9110D627D88BF649"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2CB8D00F3AA440F983EBC76B2D84D083"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other territory or possession of the United States.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HC9437BAF547B4D05B7FA2249733300DE"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State department of agriculture</header><text>The term <term>State department of agriculture</term> means the agency, commission, or department of a State government responsible for agriculture in the State.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCCBD31F9ABC54B6283BA237743F22495"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Tribal government</header><text>The term <term>Tribal government</term> means the governing body of an Indian tribe.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="H3AD85F12C4224E1C87C83FA3083BB594"><enum>297B.</enum><header>State and Tribal plans</header> <subsection id="HDC06D47B7BC045C58064979A920F3143"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Submission</header> <paragraph id="HC1A00764F2B24699817FB658C5F68ECB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State or Indian tribe desiring to have primary regulatory authority over the production of hemp in the State or territory of the Indian tribe shall submit to the Secretary, through the State department of agriculture (in consultation with the Governor and chief law enforcement officer of the State) or the Tribal government, as applicable, a plan under which the State or Indian tribe monitors and regulates that production as described in paragraph (2).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCDF19D58ECEB450CA77747840F361BD4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>A State or Tribal plan referred to in paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H46A435EA6F404725855EE27856DF720E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall only be required to include—</text>
 <clause id="H7DE031501DD24BB5BE6E5810599E474D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a practice to maintain relevant information regarding land on which hemp is produced in the State or territory of the Indian tribe, including a legal description of the land, for a period of not less than 3 calendar years;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H0D5FAF8152FF4989933BF6B918E4A2F3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a procedure for testing, using post-decarboxylation or other similarly reliable methods, delta-9 tetrahydrocannabinol concentration levels of hemp produced in the State or territory of the Indian tribe;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H665885385D5644C287096EE0684BA61C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a procedure for the effective disposal of products that are produced in violation of this subtitle; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HEA5151BA487E40A79241F491C737C842"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a procedure to comply with the enforcement procedures under subsection (d); and</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9B2C3AC499A49CD9112F8B0807734AD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include any other practice or procedure established by a State or Indian tribe, as applicable, to the extent that the practice or procedure is consistent with this subtitle.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H370BE05E97B44A2AB74762956BC67DE7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Relation to State and Tribal law</header>
 <subparagraph id="HADBDE477AC32482895137DCD3EE37D00"><enum>(A)</enum><header>No preemption</header><text>Nothing in this subsection preempts or limits any law of a State or Indian tribe regulating the production of hemp, to the extent that law is consistent with this subtitle.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B8D166F244E4A559650115ED4A637D8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>References in plans</header><text>A State or Tribal plan referred to in paragraph (1) may include a reference to a law of the State or Indian tribe regulating the production of hemp, to the extent that law is consistent with this subtitle.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3C75827061F54F11AB44AA150E75DFC9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Approval</header>
 <paragraph id="H9E8FEBEA803F4C93ABE3BAE09EA849D8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after receipt of a State or Tribal plan under subsection (a), the Secretary shall—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H56CF49C6F8A9471AA14B07B0F16E94C8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>approve the State or Tribal plan if the State or Tribal plan complies with subsection (a); or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD06DEE991238487A8D248AA207E5A316"><enum>(B)</enum><text>disapprove the State or Tribal plan only if the State or Tribal plan does not comply with subsection (a).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC60E281FFAD64B07A097EF853A2447BC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amended plans</header><text>If the Secretary disapproves a State or Tribal plan under paragraph (1)(B), the State, through the State department of agriculture (in consultation with the Governor and chief law enforcement officer of the State) or the Tribal government, as applicable, may submit to the Secretary an amended State or Tribal plan that complies with subsection (a).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HA585401707004DB9A4D6A20D0929978D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary may provide technical assistance to a State or Indian tribe in the development of a State or Tribal plan under subsection (a).</text>
						</subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H1C5E8845583C4B709AFA25F8BBC24DB6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Violations</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="H9C8F397F7FFE41B3855C2EB45CAFDAE4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A violation of a State or Tribal plan approved under subsection (b) shall be subject to enforcement solely in accordance with this subsection.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H5D38A194859744E9BB54AFFDB868293F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Negligent violations</header>
 <subparagraph id="HB9F727C8D6DF4062A6FCEF4DDE886BA9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A hemp producer in a State or the territory of an Indian tribe for which a State or Tribal plan is approved under subsection (b) shall be subject to subparagraph (B) of this paragraph if the State department of agriculture or Tribal government, as applicable, determines that the hemp producer has negligently violated the State or Tribal plan, including by negligently—</text>
 <clause id="H2671EBA2CBF64C5AA69FB6831EB27247"><enum>(i)</enum><text>failing to provide a legal description of land on which the producer produces hemp;</text> </clause><clause id="H51CE9C3121454208BD27D74FE0B04B1D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>failing to obtain a license or other required authorization from the State department of agriculture or Tribal government, as applicable; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H4B606A94777A44C881C3736362343C9C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>producing Cannabis sativa L. with a delta-9 tetrahydrocannabinol concentration of more than 0.3 percent on a dry weight basis.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86AEA6E13B20483CA632B19A36A54A76"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Corrective action plan</header><text>A hemp producer described in subparagraph (A) shall comply with a plan established by the State department of agriculture or Tribal government, as applicable, to correct the negligent violation, including—</text>
 <clause id="H56FEEFF1F5324EE38F232BD6C32AC826"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a reasonable date by which the hemp producer shall correct the negligent violation; and</text> </clause><clause id="HA80BF05E58254A5D9892A8B83BF72CE8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a requirement that the hemp producer shall periodically report to the State department of agriculture or Tribal government, as applicable, on the compliance of the hemp producer with the State or Tribal plan for a period of not less than the next 2 calendar years.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA63E03D6A5664AC4809309C9E130426B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Result of negligent violation</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (D), a hemp producer that negligently violates a State or Tribal plan under subparagraph (A) shall not be subject to any criminal or civil enforcement action by the Federal Government or any State government, Tribal government, or local government other than the enforcement action authorized under subparagraph (B).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9EC15E80CCB428583C3E4BDE2FE2FFF"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Repeat violations</header><text>A hemp producer that negligently violates a State or Tribal plan under subparagraph (A) 3 times in a 5-year period shall be ineligible to produce hemp for a period of 5 years beginning on the date of the third violation.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6542E535A0504EF790EA24D0DB531111"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Other violations</header><text>If the State department of agriculture or Tribal government in a State or the territory of an Indian tribe for which a State or Tribal plan is approved under subsection (b), as applicable, determines that a hemp producer in the State or territory has violated the State or Tribal plan with a culpable mental state greater than negligence—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H3B5C16D138184221960CFB1224B3ACE0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the State department of agriculture or Tribal government, as applicable, shall immediately report the hemp producer to—</text>
 <clause id="H3410F8F7657A4141AEC39201936E4969"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Attorney General; and</text> </clause><clause id="HACEEC84239BF41738ED303C79B2D6E5F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a State department of agriculture, the chief law enforcement officer of the State; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE489F174FEF24AAA8B3F9204A13DD45B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>paragraph (1) of this subsection shall not apply to the violation.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HA48F1781B3FA44B8A522C5D6B43EC231"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as are necessary to carry out this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H920C80B4E5DE4037933BCAFFBEFB159F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Effect</header><text>Nothing in this section prohibits the production of hemp in a State or the territory of an Indian tribe for which a State or Tribal plan is not approved under this section in accordance with other Federal laws (including regulations).</text>
 </subsection></section><section commented="no" id="HF2193C5586064547B2BEE8AF78933967"><enum>297C.</enum><header>Authority to issue regulations and guidelines</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall have sole authority to issue Federal regulations and guidelines that relate to the production of hemp, including Federal regulations and guidelines that relate to the implementation of section 297B.</text></section></subtitle><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="H6DFEC967A4664C0DA0C13C8EE8202F06"><enum>3.</enum><header>Funding for hemp research</header>
 <subsection id="H189F27DA04EB4D31A1F6D039CC866D25"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Supplemental and alternative crops</header><text>Section 1473D(c)(3)(E) of the <short-title>National Agricultural Research, Extension, and Teaching Policy Act of 1977 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/3319d">7 U.S.C. 3319d(c)(3)(E)</external-xref>)</short-title> is amended by inserting <quote>(including hemp (as defined in section 297A of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946))</quote> after <quote>material</quote>.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA733B7EDF2A24371A7EFF818FA9F8DCF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Critical agricultural materials</header><text>Section 5(b)(9) of the Critical Agricultural Materials Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/178c">7 U.S.C. 178c(b)(9)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>, and including hemp (as defined in section 297A of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946)</quote> after <quote>hydrocarbon-containing plants</quote>.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HC2D529A154CD432BA92EB9CD68B5C3F7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Legitimacy of industrial hemp research</header>
 <subsection id="HF0A448B6856049848934A735EF3D34FA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 7606 of the Agricultural Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/5940">7 U.S.C. 5940</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H4CE43A914C1642E2A7F05F439B5E2BA4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating subsections (a) and (b) as subsections (b) and (a), respectively, and moving the subsections so as to appear in alphabetical order;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA07707C36CA741FF9D6F010C0C2E3E99"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b) (as so redesignated), in the subsection heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">In general</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Industrial hemp research</header-in-text></quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H3582E66323154C67B219F15F40F7F2D9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H49C19396C8E543C4A7F8F37D27A41A64" style="OLC">
						<subsection id="HB0B9BFB129ED4C4B9DA6AD36043801DE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Study and report</header>
 <paragraph id="H156EE791C8354CE7AE1A6DE9F62CEFFD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct a study of agricultural pilot programs—</text> <subparagraph id="HF103C9E2073343DE889697D6393F8280"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to determine the economic viability of the domestic production and sale of industrial hemp; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA820F7F24E2D4FF88973B3E81EDD05BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that shall include a review of—</text> <clause id="H9A73F8D0E79D4F068C6AB1954F79ED8F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each agricultural pilot program; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H60139486E89A4289804F156EBDB064D6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other agricultural or academic research relating to industrial hemp.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA416DD676D73402BAB26DF820CF6F84C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report describing the results of the study conducted under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFB5622B080FD47CBAED2EA89E4186EF7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Repeal</header><text>Effective on the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, section 7606 of the Agricultural Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/5940">7 U.S.C. 5940</external-xref>) is repealed.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H3492EE98E649465C9A9474D0E903BB13"><enum>5.</enum><header>Federal crop insurance</header>
 <subsection id="H87991BA4155D49FFB012CC4BCE065A5F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of hemp</header><text>Section 502(b) of the Federal Crop Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1502">7 U.S.C. 1502(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H63CFE536926F4FC48C712084B339C7F3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (8) through (11) as paragraphs (9) through (12), respectively; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD9FCA00279894B40A3DB26E716DDBA70"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (7) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFAA8FC68F6D044BA974F3B1C7686D368" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H82F198A873594EEBA0D41E87957A5BBD"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Hemp</header><text>The term <term>hemp</term> has the meaning given the term in section 297A of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H30F256F7D78B4A9C9A20334B4C254CC6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Insurance period</header><text>Section 508(a)(2) of the Federal Crop Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1508">7 U.S.C. 1508(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and sweet potatoes</quote> and inserting <quote>sweet potatoes, and hemp</quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H103DD8C51A4D465A9F8C34084BCC45A9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Submission of policies and materials to board</header><text>Section 508(h) of the Federal Crop Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1508">7 U.S.C. 1508(h)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H37372BA7AAEA4C3ABCB8AFD63A2D9AB9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(B)—</text> <subparagraph id="HE5B81D6D5F0642CA887734FD59324BD3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating clauses (i) through (iii) as subclauses (I) through (III), respectively, and indenting appropriately;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC199E52AB2A9484B9C9740DA1BB85538"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subclause (I) (as so redesignated), by striking <quote>The Corporation shall</quote> and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H899137BA4FCF4EECA1571B2299F786F9" style="OLC"> <clause id="H6F3C8353E1EC4F77BF4AC7E2E4AD99F1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Corporation shall</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9F52294AF2A400ABBCA10CF84B5647A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in clause (i)(I) (as so redesignated), by inserting <quote>subject to clause (ii),</quote> before <quote>will likely</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF9204856DC3847D6B5C59AC5677C4428"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA82ABBE4742F4FB2881F305070B836E4" style="OLC">
 <clause id="H7214AC87D7FD4483B46B36CE02C9426A"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Waiver for hemp</header><text>The Corporation may waive the viability and marketability requirement under clause (i)(I) in the case of a policy or pilot program relating to the production of hemp.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H07F649B63F7F4F1AB07A145125FC68CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)(C)—</text> <subparagraph id="HF9EA8512FA2B412582AB1478E5F30959"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFF1CCA2D63B48478A4956EB562E70E6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A9FAF5E7E964C838D39CD54629E9054"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE779A172985F416BBF0A23B22CD38D3E" style="OLC">
 <clause id="H81A2908368134294BEE0B56361CBCEE4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in the case of reviewing policies and other materials relating to the production of hemp, may waive the viability and marketability requirement under subparagraph (A)(ii)(I).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCAB26CC24C894B1D8DD5DE0386F9C229"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Agricultural commodity</header><text>Section 518 of the Federal Crop Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1518">7 U.S.C. 1518</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>hemp,</quote> before <quote>aquacultural species</quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="HE9D38AA8F98E463CA76054AA6E6892F4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Research and development authority</header><text>Section 522(b) of the Federal Crop Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1522">7 U.S.C. 1522(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HA80874D4A35B4BC588897F8C23EBBBA0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6104C3B0D2F248809AF1BB7B21CDD3A2" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H8C9AC0DC8EA2414EAF07224981B598B8"><enum>(K)</enum><header>Waiver for hemp</header><text>The Board may waive the viability and marketability requirements under this paragraph in the case of research and development relating to a policy to insure the production of hemp.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H65D4EE62496E4F54B1F7ED2561BDFAEF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text> <subparagraph id="H92208DC1DA084A5CAE861840C1475EE5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The Corporation</quote> and inserting the following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF76A710FB9354823BFBA886C643D4A5A" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="HD77D2E3EA39846CB8509C0ECDC5FECB6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the Corporation</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF39D3B6EE5E4964831B736E8D24B10A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H28ED09AB162A4E9C947DFD544663D2F2" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="HEBD3B206AEBD403F811437E253DB4D41"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Waiver for hemp</header><text>The Corporation may waive the marketability requirement under subparagraph (A) in the case of research and development relating to a policy to insure the production of hemp.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H8FED37E4E8D148019F27928763E32265"><enum>6.</enum><header>Conforming changes to Controlled Substances Act</header>
 <subsection id="H4E27B971F21B4F30A4ED31B941E34B38"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 102(16) of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802(16)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H7FDF1B04F5BB4443B606FA334E5F4475"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(16) The</quote> and inserting <quote>(16)(A) Subject to subparagraph (B), the</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0D48F43ED89B4A698E7EB35301F636F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Such term does not include the</quote> and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H420D212EA15D4E5B9435C747050CD593" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H913911C460E34309B9C93ED33A5A2C95" indent="up2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <term>marihuana</term> does not include—</text>
 <clause id="H6C79539ADBF74F9EAD78DBCEAF2CDBC4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>hemp, as defined in section 297A of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946; or</text> </clause><clause id="HAC64113A102F4B2A91FAEADEBB1B30EA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5C50356A81F54A65802F7A70F34FBE41"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Tetrahydrocannabinol</header><text>Schedule I, as set forth in section 202(c) of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/812">21 U.S.C. 812(c)</external-xref>), is amended in subsection (c)(17) by inserting after <quote>Tetrahydrocannabinols</quote> the following: <quote>, except for tetrahydrocannabinols in hemp (as defined under section 297A of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946)</quote>.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H8092AC3C2F8748649D877D443933A3B7"><enum>7.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act authorizes interference with the interstate commerce of hemp (as defined in section 297A of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946, as added by section 2).</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


