<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8C6296389D484E1D8FD82BACD8CD3C0C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5378 IH: Reducing Antiquated Permitting for Infrastructure Deployments Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5378</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180321">March 21, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001176">Mr. Scalise</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Federal Communications Commission to conduct a proceeding to determine whether certain activities by licensees of the Commission are undertakings under division A of subtitle III of title 54, United States Code, or major Federal actions under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAAB7396E2E384195ACCE44827E5C65D5" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H9B20AB1840CD4B3288133F4D427759FF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Reducing Antiquated Permitting for Infrastructure Deployments Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>RAPID Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H02E4049BD02C436391DCDEE155663ABA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Determination of Federal Communications Commission regarding undertakings and major Federal actions</header> <subsection id="HA3CEEA6026024A77B30B553CB631FCE1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Proceeding required</header><text>Notwithstanding section 300320 of title 54, United States Code, or section 102 of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4332">42 U.S.C. 4332</external-xref>), not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall complete a proceeding to determine—</text>
<paragraph id="HC5D118841D934A508E7040965FA20E77"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the classes of activities of the entities to which the Commission issues radio station licenses that do not constitute an undertaking under such section 300320; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB52D7B77E6424774A87C6F45577EEEB4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the classes of activities of the entities to which the Commission issues radio station licenses that do not constitute a major Federal action under paragraph (2)(C) of such section 102.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HFADCCD318FA94B448EAD775718B4F1AB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text> <paragraph id="H456228D5ED3B49CD9E16CFAC8027E0B6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Communications Commission; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB5683645FE1F493FB7E5E08349B8C8BD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>radio station license</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/153">47 U.S.C. 153</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

