<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H673602E0BED5480EB5AD62581400F601" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5521 IH: VA Hiring Enhancement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5521</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180416">April 16, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001053">Mrs. Hartzler</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to provide for the non-applicability of non-Department of Veterans Affairs covenants not to compete to the appointment of certain Veterans Health Administration personnel, to permit the Veterans Health Administration to make contingent appointments, and to require certain Veterans Health Administration physicians to complete residency training.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8CAA12574EE04E959FABB1249E1CE9AB" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6C779B91DCCD4505B38EB578C176CDE0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>VA Hiring Enhancement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H60E2F64FDD924EC9A4F10B07E99636C9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Non-applicability of non-Department of Veterans Affairs covenants not to compete to appointment of Veterans Health Administration personnel</header> <subsection id="HA3681EC5A39D449988AB45B2394874C5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/74">chapter 74</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H74BA620CA6904A3D984EA811172A9D0B" style="USC"> 
<section id="HE06F1EDDB4D448E78E3ABE130AF3C1B4"><enum>7413.</enum><header>Effect of non-Department covenants not to compete</header> 
<subsection id="H813884D9223E4571B4FFC79310DE106C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Non-Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (b), in the case of an individual who is an applicant for appointment to a position in the Veterans Health Administration described in section 7401 of this title, any covenant not to compete into which the individual has entered with a non-Department facility or party shall have no force or effect with respect to the appointment of the individual to such a position.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA3CC528EBEA34259BA66F3BF7A80D5DE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Service obligation</header> <paragraph id="H61D233887FA34F4E8DD6E6CAFC9F0321" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Any individual who is appointed to such a position in the Veterans Health Administration shall, as a condition of such appointment, agree to provide clinical services at a Department medical facility for the duration of the period described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0E451F374160437C994F8BD3462A8628" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The period described in this paragraph is the period that begins on the date on which an individual is appointed to such a position and ends on the latter of the following dates:</text> <subparagraph id="H17A8AD0FC2FF4B079CCB6265D93B3653"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The date that is one year after such date of appointment.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H98FB73BA0DB14BFAB4E4B69F1088CD95"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The date of the termination of any covenant not to compete entered into between the individual and a non-Department facility or party.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAD2E05CFE28048A682C03C6079EF21ED" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Secretary may waive the requirement under paragraph (1) with respect to an individual at the discretion of the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8BF6EFD672ED46F4BA883C71AB73F865"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Termination of Department employment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an individual who is appointed to such a position in the Veterans Health Administration who has entered into a covenant not to compete that is rendered non-applicable pursuant to subsection (a), if the individual’s employment at the Veterans Health Administration is terminated for any reason before the specified termination date of such covenant, subsection (a) shall not apply with respect to such covenant after the date of the termination of the individual’s employment at the Veterans Health Administration. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H1878839A562A4FA585FEF3F1FFDEC754"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Covenant not To compete</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>covenant not to compete</quote> means an agreement—</text> 
<paragraph id="H02C1E85F974C4A2695A10FDF016EA90F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>between an employee and employer or a contractor and principal that restricts such employee or contractor from performing—</text> <subparagraph id="H96D53E0ADDAA46A1926C036FEBFB2C78"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any work for another employer for a specified period of time;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA4D891D913AB4B7BABD233067334EE5B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any work in a specified geographical area; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE452D60032A243E0BF7DB66032DFF213" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>work for another employer performing work that is similar to the work such employee or contractor performed for the employer or principal, included as a party to the agreement; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H723EE0FCD6A54B1C8D53B9473A526158"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that is entered into after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HD98C6695F28B4B079412EED0817E19E5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 7412 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H048886EBEE8D48EA99C7FE866F5C8273" style="USC"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">7413. Effect of non-Department covenants not to compete.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H9E825D591BA54A8284E1A39E4208074D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Recruitment of physicians on a contingent basis prior to completion of training requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 7402 of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H44D3402BAD334DB68036635A9CCF32E2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H281E62E4F25A4AF2A94F5E49A57A3DA7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A) by inserting <quote>or to be offered an appointment to such position on a contingent basis under subsection (h)</quote> after <quote>position</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H151E44134D8D4B5DBACF01B015274448"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (B) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H83381210941544CB807163BC83C4F4F9" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H9D41132291B34AF692ACF16B51164DEC" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum> 
<clause id="HDBC107B995B543BD8035B43A058B2DF4" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>have completed a residency leading to board eligibility in a specialty, satisfactory to the Secretary; or</text></clause> <clause id="H0EFDE98D50DD4D309BCD73D8EBCF21A2" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with respect to an offer for an appointment on a contingent basis under subsection (h), complete such a residency by not later than two years after the date of such offer; and</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H310EDCE01FE446E793E56F63B2FC6B56"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="HE182F30B9DBA4D17B4807F1654DA056F" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H7B09BD184F3449D3828FCFB4A8C918F9"><enum>(h)</enum> <paragraph id="HE6EDC74F5BD844C888B969E4877AB267" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary may appoint an individual under subsection (b)(1) on a contingent basis in accordance with this subsection if the Secretary reasonably anticipated that the individual will have completed the requirements for appointment under such subsection (b)(1) by not later than two years after the date on which the individual is so appointed.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2E4F871D8E944289903422DB59850B6C" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An individual who is appointed to a position on a contingent basis under paragraph (1) shall be appointed to such position on a permanent basis if, by not later than two years after the date of the contingent appointment, the individual completes all the requirements for appointment under subsection (b)(1).</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H9EB5446869394345AC95A072B3315871" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An individual who is appointed on a contingent basis under paragraph (1) who fails to complete the requirements for appointment under subsection (b)(1) by not later than two years after the date on which the individual is so appointed may not be appointed to such position on a permanent basis.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

