<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H6799119FDD84468D8FEC478917ED3598" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5859 IH: Education and Energy Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5859</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180517">May 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000470">Mr. Tipton</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Mineral Leasing Act to require that a portion of revenues from new Federal mineral and
			 geothermal leases be paid to States for use to supplement the education of
			 students in kindergarten through grade 12 and public support of
			 institutions of higher education, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HF07D71A1E15848F580E5A9C8ABAA7EFE" style="OLC">
 <section id="H48263D5E03D14F93A7D8A1A79CF5EEC9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Education and Energy Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HC783301A8CB14E04B5B82ABBCDFB4063"><enum>2.</enum><header>Use of revenues from new Federal mineral and geothermal leases for payments to State for education</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 35(a) of the Mineral Leasing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/191">30 U.S.C. 191</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>(1)</quote> before the first sentence, and by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
			<quoted-block id="H44FE6A13F1C442B0B7BC61C08E95EB5A" style="OLC">
				<paragraph id="H68070980E5F244C38864CF98CCDC12AE"><enum>(2)</enum>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7E204CB5818B405097DFFF63CD1EF7A3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Of amounts otherwise required under paragraph (1) to be deposited into the general fund of the Treasury each fiscal year that are derived from leases for tracts located in a State, the Secretary shall pay to the State 33 percent for use to supplement the education of students in kindergarten through grade 12 and to supplement public support of institutions of higher education.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD621481123543C49F3BE7F529685DDD" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Of the amounts otherwise required under paragraph (1) to be deposited into the general fund of the Treasury each fiscal year that are not required to be used for payments under subparagraph (A) of this paragraph, the Secretary shall pay to States, in equal amounts, 17 percent for use to supplement the education of students in kindergarten through grade 12 and to supplement public support of institutions of higher education.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46B0D617C1804CA587D9D4330E7C57DD" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Subparagraphs (A) and (B) shall apply only with respect to amounts that—</text> <clause id="H09882BD15A3343D0B7B4C1990D8734E8" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are received by the United States under leases entered into under this Act or the Geothermal Steam Act of 1970 after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Education and Energy Act of 2018</short-title>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H87C952698EA64E849CEA06BAB22DC487" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>exceed the amount of revenues that the Congressional Budget Office previously estimated would be received under such leases in the fiscal year.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H560DF414F473452AAED375C086CE6E21" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Subparagraphs (A) and (B) shall not apply with respect to amounts required by paragraph (1) to be paid into, reserved, appropriated, as part of the reclamation fund.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


