<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H3EC5A300EABA4535B2F80CBB20DBEF0F" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5664 IH: Stop Terrorist Use of Virtual Currencies Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5664</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180427">April 27, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000602">Miss Rice of New York</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="K000210">Mr. King of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Permanent Select Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence (Permanent Select)</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a report on the possible exploitation of virtual currencies by terrorist actors, to
			 authorize a competition program to identify regulatory solutions and
			 develop technology with respect to counter terror threat financing, and
			 for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H08C1B31E5B6448E296F7272AC6E6987F" style="OLC">
 <section id="HC86759ADAA3D469F94F4796D912972CF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop Terrorist Use of Virtual Currencies Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H79707C00351D469BBD9CE38615AE9A5C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H4751E27B8F6747DD846D0A2BCCC46BAA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Virtual currencies (VC) provide low-cost, high-speed means for verified transactions.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H82BF431C07A0400685AFCF29B8148AE2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>When used positively, VCs unite disparate financial markets and provide a convenient means for a number of constituencies, including the economically marginalized, to conduct transactions cheaply across large geographic expanses.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3D83BED5803D49D8BC68EC54449A8215"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Simultaneously, to the extent regulatory frameworks are premised on institution-based transactions, VCs could be exploited by terrorists and cybercriminals to fund untraceable operations.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H844A36F2C3474AF2B72A70CF2BFB1DDF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>According to the Center for New American Security (CNAS), if VCs become sufficiently liquid and easily convertible, and terrorist groups acquire technical infrastructure needed to support VC activity at a significant scale, VCs could pose a highly dangerous threat to the United States and its partners.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H16362AF686DB436AA2C0D82A85CD4ACC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Committee on Financial Services issued a report entitled, <quote>Stopping Terror Finance: Securing the U.S. Financial Sector</quote> in December, 2016, which includes numerous recommendations to enhance a whole-of-government approach towards counter terrorist financing.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H7031DD896DC6457B94EB71F1B11E2B49"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the Sense of Congress that—</text> <paragraph id="HBD5A3C4374814660985E6BD2917B416C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent current statutes require financial institutions to serve as the first line of defense against illicit activity in the global financial system, and that VCs specifically bypass such institutions, the United States needs to adapt its financial regulatory framework to ensure adequate supervision of financial activity;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3739A8C884B645699A5ED0C41695FF7C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the President should develop principles to prioritize counter terrorist financing among other forms of illicit financial activity and provide recommendations to Congress to address this threat;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD433D8B797E541F9B287264DD8F908DE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>such principles should include a focus on innovation and public-private partnership; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H12D1060A27AF4FA5A9E57A74B8CCB489"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network (FinCEN) should consider issuing more guidance and facilitating the establishment of institutions pursuant to sections 314(a) and 314(b) of the USA PATRIOT Act to facilitate greater information flow within and among global banks.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H48D1065C6C204D5EB5DE3DCA5559855A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The President, acting through the Secretary of the Treasury and the Director of National Intelligence, shall report on the possible exploitation of virtual currencies by terrorist actors. Such report shall include the following elements:</text>
 <paragraph id="H77CBD5DFF10446A588C3689D09118BD4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Recommendations to update the regulatory oversight structure regarding virtual currencies to address transactions that bypass financial institutions, including banks, Money Services Businesses (MSB), and other financial institutions subject to regulation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6CCB037485F04BDCB94D584C511755B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Assessment of current efforts by Federal departments and agencies to study and collect intelligence against the terror finance threat and money laundering methodologies.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA9641C29E93B4ED09B16440E50CC5581"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Identification of gaps between Federal and State regulations which could be exploited for illicit funding.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H8165324280264B15A50CC4D034BF949E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Innovation competition</header>
 <subsection id="HA3302D163A2F4AB29F13EB37C8A20F43"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to facilitate public-private partnership to develop and enhance illicit finance prevention systems, the Secretary of the Treasury may establish a program (referred to in this section as <quote>the competition</quote>) to be known as the <quote>Competition for Innovation in Combating Illicit Terrorist Financing</quote>.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H28AD8FB4E05F4825BA00701BCF152A2D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Activities supported</header><text>The Competition may carry out, through the provision of grants or an annual reward, the following activities:</text>
 <paragraph id="H52CD98C696194A5FA39F0F43522687A7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Collaborative research</header><text>Provide grants, for not more than two years, to engage students, entrepreneurs, and financial experts to identify regulatory solutions with respect to the exploitation of VCs by terrorists and other criminals.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H57A9E2BF55AD4AD4827A4F80C953FC42"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Competition</header><text>Establish an annual competition for a reward of not more than $500,000 to any individual, team, or nongovernmental entity that develops technologies to facilitate counter terror threat financing, particularly that addresses the use of VCs or emerging financial technology.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H88C13E70040743CFB2C3A988DD7EACEB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Management</header>
 <paragraph id="HBF42FCF4874D4FE78D1DAAA1B3697648"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Treasury, in consultation with the Director of National Intelligence, shall promulgate guidelines for review of grant applications to the Competition.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7D7AA0DCB8BD4733A6371B1BCF6AD348"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The guidelines required under this subsection shall address, at a minimum, the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H643D68256B6D432994CADF26E38370EA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Criteria by which grants shall be selected.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B54B4EA22EC480FA61E7354D17A937E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Policies to ensure that grants are in furtherance of United States security objectives.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE56329ABA8664BB6B379DEA29B423081"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Acceptance of funds from outside sources</header><text>The Competition may accept funds from outside sources, including foreign governments, nongovernmental organizations, and private business entities and, without further appropriation, use such funds to carry out the purpose of the Competition.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HFD4DCA6E7C3A41BA9C7AE48C2341EC84"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this Act may be construed to make any grant recipient an agent or establishment of the United States Government.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


