<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HC46EE0620F5F47DD86E5F46E3B2AB487" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5333 IH: Over-the-Counter Monograph Safety, Innovation, and Reform Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5333</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180319">March 19, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000566">Mr. Latta</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000410">Mr. Gene Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000197">Ms. DeGette</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act to clarify the regulatory framework with respect
			 to certain nonprescription drugs that are marketed without an approved new
			 drug application, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H403052877A454EF4A1A1A4C504C238D3" style="OLC">
 <section id="HE54CDDD1DA204BDF99AFF40250E6FF2B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Over-the-Counter Monograph Safety, Innovation, and Reform Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><title id="H8EC2F1497B1E4CE28414A4944FB2E5EA"><enum>I</enum><header>OTC Drug Review</header> <section id="HBEF519EAACF142718B80599DC446A70D"><enum>101.</enum><header>Regulation of certain nonprescription drugs that are marketed without an approved new drug application</header> <subsection id="H08554C1F35484F8E81AF771DC8075015"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Chapter V of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act is amended by inserting after section 505F of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355g">21 U.S.C. 355g</external-xref>) the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H9C4A4A3CB11747C0B82FC844EF0B8E25" style="OLC">
						<section id="HC9BE4BF8FC4E4CEB952D6B45779FBD40"><enum>505G.</enum><header>Regulation of certain nonprescription drugs that are marketed without an approved new drug
			 application</header>
 <subsection id="HDCF53A0C2B044775BF790BC594068A8B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Nonprescription drugs marketed without an approved application</header><text>Nonprescription drugs marketed without an approved new drug application under section 505, as of the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Over-the-Counter Monograph Safety, Innovation, and Reform Act of 2018</short-title>, shall be treated in accordance with this subsection.</text>
 <paragraph id="H15983AF8F35148298507757CA4D9335A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Drugs subject to a final monograph; category I drugs subject to a tentative final monograph</header><text>A drug is deemed to be generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1), not a new drug under section 201(p), and not subject to section 503(b)(1), if—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H7BD1A2F00E9449A48DAFFDB6CA7547F4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the drug is—</text> <clause id="HBE385B1950DF4F689289113441070B04"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in conformity with the requirements for nonprescription use of a final monograph issued under part 330 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (except as provided in paragraph (6)), the general requirements for nonprescription drugs, and requirements under subsections (b), (c), and (k); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H05DDECC8F739406A92E4CF68DADF41BC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">except as permitted by an order issued under subsection (b) or, in the case of a minor change in the drug, in conformity with an order issued under subsection (c), in a dosage form that, immediately prior to the date of the enactment of this section, has been used to a material extent and for a material time within the meaning of section 201(p)(2); or</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA61B764D3A2D4BBDA8AE37DCE2DE0729"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the drug is—</text> <clause id="H554D662F5C6E446EBA9502BD9C022EB4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">classified in category I for safety and effectiveness under a tentative final monograph that is the most recently applicable proposal or determination issued under part 330 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8AEC7B2EF2174D43A0F67C4687DF66DA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in conformity with the proposed requirements for nonprescription use of such tentative final monograph, any applicable subsequent determination by the Secretary, the general requirements for nonprescription drugs, and requirements under subsections (b), (c), and (k); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8C543A1379C84D34BED2DD6553A1AF84"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">except as permitted an order issued under subsection (b) or, in the case of a minor change in the drug, in conformity with an order issued under subsection (c), in a dosage form that, immediately prior to the date of the enactment of this section, has been used to a material extent and for a material time within the meaning of section 201(p)(2).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F68ED1500714F4F97EA6100F0AE72B2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Treatment of sunscreen drugs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to sunscreen drugs subject to this section, the applicable requirements shall be those set out at part 352 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations, as published at volume 64 page 27687 of the Federal Register, except that the applicable requirements governing effectiveness and labeling shall be those specified in section 201.327 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations, subject to the requirements of subsections (b), (c), and (k)(2).</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H73652230BC0449B59B4502FCC42C8A67"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Category III drugs subject to a tentative final monograph; category I drugs subject to proposed
 monograph or advance notice of proposed rulemaking</header><text>A drug that is not described in paragraphs (1), (2), or (4) is not required to be the subject of an application approved under section 505, and is not subject to section 503(b)(1), if—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H221F8B0CE4934406AE3BC768223FC074"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the drug is—</text> <clause id="H682F89FCCFC2498D9F7A205EBF3C3C07"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">classified in category III for safety or effectiveness in the preamble of a proposed rule establishing a tentative final monograph that is the most recently applicable proposal or determination for such drug issued under part 330 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H0FDD4BFC66434BB8A24E1DD92D6B7D2C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in conformity with—</text> <subclause id="H61DCF856DE46415E914781B3A886B83F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the conditions of use, including indication and dosage strength, if any, described for such category III drug in such preamble or in an applicable subsequent proposed rule;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H36FF7F6BC992488FB017E74612E14284"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the proposed requirements for drugs classified in such tentative final monograph in category I in the most recently proposed rule establishing requirements related to such tentative final monograph and in any final rule establishing requirements that are applicable to the drug; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HA0C046A902B74F4EA4761956EB828D6C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the general requirements for nonprescription drugs and requirements under subsections (b) or (k); and</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H0323B61CAA09420FB96532EF3E5EE563"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in a dosage form that, immediately prior to the date of the enactment of this section, was not required to have satisfied the requirements of section 330.14 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect at that time), in order for such drug to be lawfully marketed without an application approved under section 505; or</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDCE5E465AD7D4BFF94A8F434DCF4950B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the drug is—</text> <clause id="H0513F8AEE94F458F9C68CC127432EB2D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">classified in category I for safety and effectiveness under a proposed monograph or advance notice of proposed rulemaking that is the most recently applicable proposal or determination for such drug issued under part 330 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H42D6050217024BD49FA73DC2CFE926D8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in conformity with the requirements for nonprescription use of such proposed monograph or advance notice of proposed rulemaking, any applicable subsequent determination by the Secretary, the general requirements for nonprescription drugs, and requirements under subsections (b) or (k); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H288485307AA74C9499B6F2CCF97130A7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in a dosage form that, immediately prior to the date of the enactment of this section, has been used to a material extent and for a material time within the meaning of section 201(p)(2).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E3C2170F5ED495793ECA0B76EAF13A0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Category II drugs deemed new drugs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A drug that is classified in category II for safety or effectiveness under a tentative final monograph or that is subject to a determination to be not safe or effective in a proposed rule that is the most recently applicable proposal issued under part 330 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations, shall be deemed to be a new drug within the meaning of section 201(p), misbranded under section 502(ee), and subject to the requirement for an approved new drug application under section 505 beginning on the day that is 180 calendar days after the date of the enactment of this section, unless, before such day, the Secretary determines that it is in the interest of public health to extend the period during which the drug may be marketed without such an approved new drug application.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE3CE6C46A6D14418977E3AE0C42AE0A8"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Drugs not GRASE deemed new drugs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A drug that the Secretary has determined not to be generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1) under a final determination issued under part 330 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations, shall be deemed to be a new drug within the meaning of section 201(p), misbranded under section 502(ee), and subject to the requirement for an approved new drug application under section 505.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2BB9CE03AD4045BAB55E0B58F5E94892"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Other drugs deemed new drugs</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (m), a drug is deemed to be a new drug within the meaning of section 201(p) and misbranded under section 502(ee) if the drug—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HB98B8E029FDA4B06AA8249CE7EE47DFA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is not subject to section 503(b)(1); and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD638937DE4E248A08717D8404FD0BF33"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is not described in paragraphs (1), (2), (3), (4), or (5), or subsection (b)(1)(B).</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8C526BF1AD0F448E85952B8C1922A2D8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Administrative orders</header>
								<paragraph id="H695C3271ED5F45E385DA03CAC8AC3C79"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header>
 <subparagraph id="H420662CEE5564162A258CB51210C91E8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>The Secretary may, on the initiative of the Secretary or at the request of one or more requestors, issue administrative orders determining whether there are conditions under which specific drugs, classes of such drugs, or combinations of such drugs are determined to be—</text>
 <clause id="H4E142B18822D4A92B21F1F60F607CA69"><enum>(i)</enum><text>not subject to section 503(b)(1); and</text> </clause><clause id="HD4FA4424DABE4A66A139515D19010449"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H213153A316EE42479DB2D8B32DDF285D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Effect</header><text>A drug or combination of drugs shall be deemed to not require approval under section 505 if such drug or combination of drugs—</text>
 <clause id="HCEB6299E3EA147FF9B6D6434FFA99F75"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is determined by the Secretary to meet the conditions specified in clauses (i) and (ii) of subparagraph (A);</text>
 </clause><clause id="HED51276790314218A27ACC7529F8958F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is marketed in conformity with an administrative order under this subsection;</text> </clause><clause id="H6DE2510953804D468D90833849B2341E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>meets the general requirements for nonprescription drugs; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF04ED62D3B9C449995430FEDA8AB9D8F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>meets the requirements specified in subsections (c) and (k).</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0055DE13F1CB4140AF42ADCC32583053"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Standard</header><text>The Secretary shall find that a drug is not generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1) if—</text>
 <clause id="HB75F1B97A99946DE9E10D8089E7F95BC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the evidence shows that the drug is not generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1); or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H0D796FC94AC54E72864D4FFDAD3F6D4A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the evidence is inadequate to show that the drug is generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1).</text>
										</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H428C5AF35CA14812AAC5243FD36405C9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative orders initiated by the secretary</header>
 <subparagraph id="HF0239AABB29C40FCBBA7E347CF44DC0A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In issuing an administrative order under paragraph (1) upon the Secretary’s initiative, the Secretary shall—</text>
 <clause id="H293FFD51DC844487B3415DBCF7DE3D2F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>make reasonable efforts to notify informally, not later than 2 business days before the issuance of the proposed order, sponsors of drugs that will be subject to the administrative order;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB10296816D2748DE96645350668CCA26"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>after any such reasonable efforts of notification—</text> <subclause id="H53C0A78CC7D24976A80445C107A6B638"><enum>(I)</enum><text>issue a proposed administrative order by publishing it on the website of the Food and Drug Administration and include in such order the reasons for the issuance of such order; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HEF8E4A8BD8114BBAB0AB6D00073F8878"><enum>(II)</enum><text>publish a notice of availability of such proposed order in the Federal Register;</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="HBBE1603B147A454EBCBC2947EB33D0E0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>except as provided in subparagraph (B), provide for a public comment period with respect to such proposed order of not less than 45 calendar days; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H7CCB1F5D93BA42779B3EF2E800BC47D5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>if, after completion of the proceedings specified in clauses (i) through (iii), the Secretary determines that it is appropriate to issue a final administrative order—</text>
 <subclause id="H380FF903C2BA46A1A9CC811A66056004"><enum>(I)</enum><text>issue the final administrative order, together with a detailed statement of reasons, which order shall not take effect until the time for requesting judicial review under paragraph (3)(D)(ii) has expired;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HECAA3979660E46BA8FBE47F5DD04395E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>publish a notice of such final administrative order in the Federal Register;</text> </subclause><subclause id="H6F80D058CECB407E96B59B3036DF9000"><enum>(III)</enum><text>afford requestors of drugs that will be subject to such order the opportunity for formal dispute resolution up to the level of the Director of the Center for Drug Evaluation and Research, which initially must be requested within 45 calendar days of the issuance of the order, and, for subsequent levels of appeal, within 30 calendar days of the prior decision; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HFE3F4E9592C24495967CB5CF51F77FFC"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>except with respect to drugs described in paragraph (3)(B), upon completion of the formal dispute resolution procedure, inform the persons which sought such dispute resolution of their right to request a hearing.</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40F36D9B1C554AEF93550157C62E2547"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>When issuing an administrative order under paragraph (1) on the Secretary’s initiative proposing to determine that a drug described in subsection (a)(3) is not generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1), the Secretary shall follow the procedures in subparagraph (A), except that—</text>
 <clause id="H9B7C2C3CAAEB4A3AA7AD6155AE0F2698"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the proposed order shall include notice of—</text> <subclause id="HA89F31A60EB1411AB9A997C4D7C5048C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the general categories of data the Secretary has determined necessary to establish that the drug is generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1); and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HA0DB25D437E740DB80753F70FE19CD65"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the format for submissions by interested persons;</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="H1468BDFCE8B044B493165646AE184606"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Secretary shall provide for a public comment period of no less than 180 calendar days with respect to such proposed order, except when the Secretary determines, for good cause, that a shorter period is in the interests of public health; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H2C055B08F4A643E9BBBDF1C200A78DA2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any person who submits data in such comment period shall include a certification that the person has submitted all evidence created, obtained, or received by that person that is both within the categories of data identified in the proposed order and relevant to a determination as to whether the drug is generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1).</text>
										</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4DB15DA9C718419EBA2378D79399A931"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Hearings; judicial review</header>
 <subparagraph id="HA661982C27C24A429BB652712CA4612D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Only a person who participated in each stage of formal dispute resolution under subclause (III) of paragraph (2)(A)(iv) of an administrative order with respect to a drug may request a hearing concerning a final administrative order issued under such paragraph with respect to such drug. Such person must submit a request for a hearing, which shall be based solely on information in the administrative record, to the Secretary not later than 30 calendar days after receiving notice of the final decision of the formal dispute resolution procedure.</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H757E9D59787D423E940DC12FD94D382E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No hearing required with respect to orders relating to certain drugs</header>
 <clause id="HEDF892A9885A47FDA948DEC830895764"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall not be required to provide notice and an opportunity for a hearing pursuant to paragraph (2)(A)(iv) if the final administrative order involved relates to a drug—</text>
 <subclause id="H060679B2B193438F8A858939115ED752"><enum>(I)</enum><text>that is described in subsection (a)(3)(A); and</text> </subclause><subclause id="HC765518A8CBE4E8D8C048EE76613D403"><enum>(II)</enum><text>with respect to which no human or non-human data studies relevant to the safety or effectiveness of such drug have been submitted to the administrative record since the issuance of the most recent tentative final monograph relating to such drug.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H284B49AB02264EDABFDD8D2DB627F435"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Human data studies and non-human data defined</header><text>In this subparagraph:</text> <subclause id="H0E24C78C4D3142369F69D29C80B93088"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The term <term>human data studies</term> means clinical trials of safety or effectiveness (including actual use studies), pharmacokinetics studies, or bioavailability studies.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HE656F20AF52347DF813D040DAC5D3E07"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The term <term>non-human data</term> means data from testing other than with human subjects which provides information concerning safety or effectiveness.</text>
											</subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9EA22D167A3A41EC990D2D80FD7E0016"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Hearing procedures</header>
 <clause id="H10107A974E824A4890D0DB8C758A8DBC"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Denial of request for hearing</header><text>If the Secretary determines that information submitted in a request for a hearing under subparagraph (A) with respect to a final administrative order issued under paragraph (2)(A)(iv), does not identify the existence of a genuine and substantial question of material fact, the Secretary may deny such request. In making such a determination, the Secretary may consider only information and data that are based on relevant and reliable scientific principles and methodologies.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H303354E524DC478ABB083B21A06E0106"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Single hearing for multiple related requests</header><text>If more than one request for a hearing is submitted with respect to the same administrative order under subparagraph (A), the Secretary may direct that a single hearing be conducted in which all persons whose hearing requests were granted may participate.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H2B4F4839BA374B76B78C3635F9BAAC31"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Presiding officer</header><text>The presiding officer of a hearing requested under subparagraph (A) shall—</text> <subclause id="H4A79158522B64BF99E59AFF31894649C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>be designated by the Secretary;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HA1A6295436B0498E82935BC36FE666B1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>not be an employee of the Center for Drug Evaluation and Research; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H9327EADB7E9C42A684F389594BDC4F40"><enum>(III)</enum><text>not have been previously involved in the development of the administrative order involved or proceedings relating to that administrative order.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H4C0F0E28B7C8430DBFD2D08BE66AFFE4"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Rights of parties to hearing</header><text>The parties to a hearing requested under subparagraph (A) shall have the right to present testimony, including testimony of expert witnesses, and to cross-examine witnesses presented by other parties. Where appropriate, the presiding officer may require that cross-examination by parties representing substantially the same interests be consolidated to promote efficiency and avoid duplication.</text>
										</clause><clause id="HF77F96BF33DD404DA61C7A2491845393"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Final decision</header>
 <subclause id="HE6A716397C224546A2624698530A2656"><enum>(I)</enum><text>At the conclusion of a hearing requested under subparagraph (A), the presiding officer of the hearing shall issue a decision containing findings of fact and conclusions of law. The decision of the presiding officer shall be final.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HBCD13548B8724F849777EDB6E6D0635E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The final decision may not take effect until the period under subparagraph (D)(ii) for submitting a request for judicial review of such decision expires.</text>
											</subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36CC4288D517452B9D115831F513D32B"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Judicial review of final administrative order</header>
 <clause id="HA868DC13A41A4B16A288070297CEF8AC"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The procedures described in section 505(h) shall apply with respect to judicial review of final administrative orders issued under this subsection in the same manner and to the same extent as such section applies to an order described in such section except that the judicial review shall be taken by filing in an appropriate district court of the United States in lieu of the appellate courts specified in such section.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HDDC0837528BF4451A0838E65EE728935"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Period to submit a request for judicial review</header><text>A person eligible to request a hearing under this paragraph and seeking judicial review of a final administrative order issued under this subsection shall file such request for judicial review not later than 60 calendar days after the latest of—</text>
 <subclause id="H1E5F2108FF04416BAB6BD70B1AB34425"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the date on which notice of such order is published;</text> </subclause><subclause id="H4A77103424C44A94AE9998542F92F0CD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the date on which a hearing with respect to such order is denied under subparagraph (B) or (C)(i);</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HF3AD447CE522473392E4F72F5DBBC88E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the date on which a final decision is made following a hearing under subparagraph (C)(v); or</text> </subclause><subclause id="HC5D767C1CDAA4EEB855F4E0EC618DB59"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>if no hearing is requested, the date on which the time for requesting a hearing expires.</text>
											</subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B0D7AC70F034084ABC67AE2009B61C4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Expedited procedure with respect to administrative orders initiated by the Secretary</header>
									<subparagraph id="HFFC229BB9D8D4C27A996B86FCA62054D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Imminent hazard to the public health</header>
 <clause id="H5872A8824C5A4468BB15CFB2A5758513"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a determination by the Secretary that a drug, class of drugs, or combination of drugs subject to this section poses an imminent hazard to the public health, the Secretary, after first making reasonable efforts to notify, not later than 48 hours before issuance of such order under this subparagraph, sponsors who have a listing in effect under section 510(j) for such drug or combination of drugs—</text>
 <subclause id="H8D16D2FCDF9147E697AC419720343C25"><enum>(I)</enum><text>may issue an interim final administrative order for such drug, class of drugs, or combination of drugs under paragraph (1), together with a detailed statement of the reasons for such order;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H7153BBA18ED64482BCF8D7573A39A186"><enum>(II)</enum><text>shall publish in the Federal Register a notice of availability of any such order; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H3C0FD1EA4C7940368F5D9541FC16C5AE"><enum>(III)</enum><text>shall provide for a public comment period of at least 45 calendar days with respect to such interim final order.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="HAA0E7C04E76348139646A63262263EF3"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Nondelegation</header><text>The Secretary may not delegate the authority to issue an interim final administrative order under this subparagraph.</text>
										</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD1E7187B08946B5A70BF05B8F2414CE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Safety labeling changes</header>
 <clause id="H56C70D01BDB545F58DCC265DC2DA0A5A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a determination by the Secretary that a change in the labeling of a drug, class of drugs, or combination of drugs subject to this section is reasonably expected to mitigate a significant or unreasonable risk of a serious adverse event associated with use of the drug, the Secretary may—</text>
 <subclause id="HBB17FBB07C55449B97C358319354C585"><enum>(I)</enum><text>make reasonable efforts to notify informally, not later than 48 hours before the issuance of the interim final order, the sponsors of drugs who have a listing in effect under section 510(j) for such drug or combination of drugs;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HF34A4EDE594D42E09C8C819A72FB3CDF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>after reasonable efforts of notification, issue an interim final administrative order in accordance with paragraph (1) to require such change, together with a detailed statement of the reasons for such order;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HEBA02E8BAB2E4322A585A913056CA804"><enum>(III)</enum><text>publish in the Federal Register a notice of availability of such order; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="HD710BEB65FDD4A20819DD9B4FED11AF0"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>provide for a public comment period of at least 45 calendar days with respect to such interim final order.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H49B19FE35EF649328D8975EC7B11A2EB"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Content of order</header><text>An interim final order issued under this subparagraph with respect to the labeling of a drug may provide for new warnings and other information required for safe use of the drug.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC23069967DF44EC9ACBD27D988308C1E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>An order under subparagraph (A) or (B) shall take effect on a date specified by the Secretary.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7F6A5E7D473442E96E8B2D6B61F949C"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Final order</header><text>After the completion of the proceedings in subparagraph (A) or (B), the Secretary shall—</text>
 <clause id="HE1B208A751FF4E859E911E856EFF5010"><enum>(i)</enum><text>issue a final order in accordance with paragraph (1);</text> </clause><clause id="HBC87D60DA16243058ADD5758B720CA76"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>publish a notice of availability of such final administrative order in the Federal Register; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H958A87CD469B4B17B9705220FC71FAC4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>afford sponsors of such drugs that will be subject to such an order the opportunity for formal dispute resolution up to the level of the Director of the Center for Drug Evaluation and Research, which must initially be within 45 calendar days of the issuance of the order, and for subsequent levels of appeal, within 30 calendar days of the prior decision.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF97C22C1299E45B79C14F4750BD05659"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Hearings</header><text>A sponsor of a drug subject to a final order issued under subparagraph (D) and that participated in each stage of formal dispute resolution under clause (iii) of such subparagraph may request a hearing on such order. The provisions of subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C) of paragraph (3), other than paragraph (3)(C)(v)(II), shall apply with respect to a hearing on such order in the same manner and to the same extent as such provisions apply with respect to a hearing on an administrative order issued under paragraph (2)(A)(iv).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H195F7C1C001E4CCFA9A6D3561EBF74D0"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>Not later than 12 months after the date on which an interim final order is issued under subparagraph (A) or (B), the Secretary shall issue a final order in accordance with paragraph (1) and complete any required hearing.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC08E9B94AF8D4A2AA10E93A3E4EC846F"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Judicial review</header><text>A final order issued pursuant to subparagraph (F) shall be subject to judicial review in accordance with paragraph (3)(D).</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9073535AB14A48DEA23B591EB705EC5A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Administrative order initiated at the request of a requestor</header>
 <subparagraph id="H2008EECD36704DDDA10B58E4830BD0C5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In issuing an administrative order under paragraph (1) at the request of a requestor with respect to certain drugs, classes of drugs, or combinations of drugs—</text>
 <clause id="HBA8C8E3353B94547805A15C7EA975FDC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Secretary shall, after receiving a request under this subparagraph, determine whether the request is sufficiently complete and formatted to permit a substantive review;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8D5404641E6E482BBD6512065558CDD2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the Secretary determines that the request is sufficiently complete and formatted to permit a substantive review, the Secretary shall—</text>
 <subclause id="H0D03656D54F8426DAAF53A6479DAB696"><enum>(I)</enum><text>file the request; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="HA21C3368403845E3A8C66DA8612FB528"><enum>(II)</enum><text>initiate proceedings with respect to issuing an administrative order in accordance with paragraphs (2) and (3); and</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H750A1435A971490BBF73AE998D711A9C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>except as provided in paragraph (6), if the Secretary determines that a request does not meet the requirements for filing or is not sufficiently complete and formatted to permit a substantive review, the requestor may demand that the request be filed over protest, and the Secretary shall initiate proceedings to review the request in accordance with paragraph (2)(A).</text>
										</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA40587374A2144B2BE7851BF9C7CA5D4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Request to initiate proceedings</header>
 <clause id="H23D792AC02F14895B779F33930F84EEA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A requestor seeking an administrative order under paragraph (1) with respect to certain drugs, classes of drugs, or combinations of drugs, shall submit to the Secretary a request to initiate proceedings for such order in the form and manner as specified by the Secretary. Such requestor may submit a request under this subparagraph for the issuance of an administrative order—</text>
 <subclause id="HAF28D6153CEA45498AB7523B3FA6904F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>determining whether a drug is generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1), exempt from section 503(b)(1), and not required to be the subject of an approved application under section 505; or</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H64229069BED44BDBBB4E532959AFFC7F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>determining whether a change to a condition of use of a drug is generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1), exempt from section 503(b)(1), and not required to be the subject of an approved application under section 505, if such drug is—</text>
 <item id="H5822E5FC7911428AA209B7F241D1CF7B"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">absent such a changed condition of use, generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1) in accordance with subsection (a)(1), (a)(2), or an order under this subsection; or</text>
 </item><item id="H80042D6AD3174E3E9613604336FA6655"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>subject to subsection (a)(3), but only if such requestor initiates such request in conjunction with a request for the Secretary to determine whether such drug is generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1), which is filed by the Secretary under subparagraph (A)(ii).</text>
 </item></subclause></clause><clause id="HC791407E4F534FE38058203E2225F35C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The Secretary is not required to complete review of a request for a change described in clause (i)(II) if the Secretary determines that there is an inadequate basis to find the drug is generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1) under paragraph (1) and issues a final order announcing that determination.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HCF617BB5D23D4F63A2A4890344A3B8B7"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Withdrawal</header><text>The requestor may withdraw a request under this paragraph, according to the procedures set forth pursuant to subsection (d)(2)(B). Notwithstanding any other provision of this section, if such request is withdrawn, the Secretary may cease proceedings under this subparagraph.</text>
										</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8AE751201D3449E4BC0379F704348E88"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exclusivity</header>
 <clause id="H018BBE52474A4521A42053B5BC09CB66"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A final administrative order issued in response to a request under this section shall have the effect of authorizing solely the order requestor (or the licensees, assignees, or successors in interest of such requestor with respect to the subject of such order), for a period of 18 months following the effective date of such final order, to market drugs—</text>
 <subclause id="H2D787405439248B9A60909640C22119F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>incorporating changes described in clause (ii);</text> </subclause><subclause id="HB7D0EC97315B4146949C284AF8DA7DB7"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">beginning on the date the requestor (or any such licensees, assignees, or successors in interest) may lawfully market such drugs pursuant to the order; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HA5D93523E28043D39C9B5DF73CE68AC0"><enum>(III)</enum><text>subject to the limitations under clause (iv).</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="HE66EF3BF58D949CB98536D63950781C8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Changes described</header><text>A change described in this clause is a change subject to an order specified in clause (i), which—</text>
 <subclause id="HC195E4BF29B641BDB3670C9357580DE4"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides for a drug to contain an active ingredient (including any ester or salt of the active ingredient) not previously incorporated in a drug described in clause (iii); or</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H309A0054AA9C4E888D886AD980E92BAF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>provides for a change in the conditions of use of a drug, for which new human data studies conducted or sponsored by the requestor (or for which the requestor has an exclusive right of reference) were essential to the issuance of such order.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H839864B3074442ADBB501A5BEC5ED55B"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Drugs described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The drugs described in this clause are drugs—</text> <subclause id="HBEE9F00AB9A249A2A9F4625ACEB16715"><enum>(I)</enum><text>specified in subsection (a)(1), (a)(2), or (a)(3);</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H50B8F169AED24E70A3C0D40510ABCF10"><enum>(II)</enum><text>subject to a final order issued under this section;</text> </subclause><subclause id="H79D7940F86B041BCBCA52ED0A7A40E72"><enum>(III)</enum><text>subject to a final sunscreen order (as defined in section 586(2)(A)); or</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H10BBCC7F32834EC7840ADB3EF24E37CD"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">described in subsection (m)(1), other than drugs subject to an active enforcement action under chapter III of this Act.</text>
											</subclause></clause><clause id="H03E934B48FE149D093C0A77DB72D8983"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Limitations on exclusivity</header>
 <subclause id="H08A29637D63B47BAAA871324DC42107B"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Only one period of exclusivity shall be granted, under each order described in clause (i), with respect to changes (to the drug subject to such order) which are either—</text>
 <item id="HE87F7DD597B04E2AAF36B5CE990152AA"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>changes described in clause (ii)(I), relating to active ingredients; or</text> </item><item id="H7CAF40F0002E4232BB9927F851E700B7"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>changes described in clause (ii)(II), relating to conditions of use.</text>
 </item></subclause><subclause id="HFAB96473E09544E88E289EB732ED8683"><enum>(II)</enum><header>No exclusivity allowed</header><text>No exclusivity shall apply to changes to a drug which are—</text> <item id="H1C9BEEF0D2B94EA08B04DBD2421BE4FC"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the subject of a Tier 2 OTC monograph order request (as defined in section 744N);</text>
 </item><item id="HD2260DBF8AC34399827E46B7BCFD6F2A"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>safety-related changes, as defined by the Secretary, or any other changes the Secretary considers necessary to assure safe use; or</text>
 </item><item id="H890B95D24244461DBBC016F70E305C0D"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>changes related to methods of testing safety or efficacy.</text> </item></subclause></clause><clause id="H2E28EB4F9C2D4A61A4D68170AE9002AB"><enum>(v)</enum><header>New human data studies defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subparagraph, the term <term>new human data studies</term> means clinical trials of safety or effectiveness (including actual use studies), pharmacokinetics studies, or bioavailability studies, the results of which—</text>
 <subclause id="HC572387C7B0F441FB56C3E9638778670"><enum>(I)</enum><text>have not been relied on by the Secretary to support—</text> <item id="H8CC09F5EC431432DBB96684A451FDF93"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a proposed or final determination that a drug described in subclauses (I), (II), or (III) of clause (iii) is generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1); or</text>
 </item><item id="HD08AECAC802942F7B6A2519637895A53"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">approval of a drug that was approved under section 505 (except for an approval changing a drug from prescription to nonprescription status); and</text>
 </item></subclause><subclause id="HA61D9AC26AA24D659E55AD9F39E701E0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>do not duplicate the results of another study that was relied on by the Secretary to support—</text> <item id="H280E02EDA1AC4CC29A82C1C07F9BF87A"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a proposed or final determination that a drug described in subclauses (I), (II), or (III) of clause (iii) is generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1); or</text>
 </item><item id="H669E794D627D4149BA70228EF506ED51"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">approval of a drug that was approved under section 505 (except for an approval changing a drug from prescription to nonprescription status).</text>
 </item></subclause></clause><clause id="H0AC488318D7B4683982C7B02B7C5D532"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A final order subject to clause (i) shall take effect on the date when the order requestor (or the licensees, assignees, or successors in interest of such requestor with respect to such order) submits updated drug listing information under subsection (e) with respect to the change which is permitted under such order.</text>
										</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H48AE11AC816E4CD6B75363417D89DC89"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Information regarding safe nonprescription marketing and use as condition for filing a generally
			 recognized as safe and effective request</header>
 <subparagraph id="H04C1351F24344B4799A459AEED013D3A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In response to a request under this section that a drug described in subparagraph (B) be generally recognized as safe and effective, the Secretary—</text>
 <clause id="H330DBC82CD6B4583B1DF115E9C712A00"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may file such request, if the request includes information specified under subparagraph (C) with respect to safe nonprescription marketing and use of such drug; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="HBA253A91A44C456092A50113E37D967F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the request fails to include information specified under subparagraph (C), shall refuse to file such request and require that nonprescription marketing of the drug be pursuant to a new drug application as described in subparagraph (D).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF870D090C15941119D3C636496C0DBEC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Drug described</header><text>A drug described in this subparagraph is a nonprescription drug which contains an active ingredient not previously incorporated in a drug—</text>
 <clause id="H810027474A0D4524A3566B08238B9D82"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">specified in subsection (a)(1), (a)(2), or (a)(3);</text> </clause><clause id="H24EE7E681FF74BA88EF8073CE9453DAB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subject to a final order under this section; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H5A9C24113CD64D7CBA52F2D1258983C6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subject to a final sunscreen order (as defined in section 586(2)(A)).</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H539C717565D64F41B9B431A44BCF5209"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Information demonstrating prima facie safe nonprescription marketing and use</header><text>Information specified in this subparagraph, with respect to a request described in subparagraph (A)(i), is—</text>
 <clause id="HC344914DAD98436BA9A9788C449B64F9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>information sufficient for a prima facie demonstration that the drug subject to such request has a verifiable history of being marketed and safely used by consumers in the United States as a nonprescription drug under comparable conditions of use;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H56AB41A682BC4CD2BF0CABBE4766E57D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the drug has not been previously marketed in the United States as a nonprescription drug, information sufficient for a prima facie demonstration that the drug was marketed and safely used under comparable conditions of marketing and use in a country listed in section 802(b)(1)(A) or designated by the Secretary in accordance with section 802(b)(1)(B)—</text>
 <subclause id="HF9F9B07400D34EFFA8336C0FDCE6A5FA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>for such period of time as needed to provide reasonable assurances concerning the safe nonprescription use of the drug; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H4309A8EFCF894683A4AE2DD8E81FF8FF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>during such time was subject to sufficient monitoring by a regulatory body considered acceptable by the Secretary for such monitoring purposes, including for adverse events associated with nonprescription use of the drug; or</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H7F96F9DC53B340D78E38851FDD4CB504"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>if the Secretary determines that information described in clauses (i) or (ii) is not needed to provide a prima facie demonstration that the drug can be safely marketed and used as a nonprescription drug, such other information the Secretary determines is sufficient for such purposes.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CF0915DDE7340A7858BE979C6E0FDF0"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Marketing pursuant to new drug application</header><text>In the case of a request described in subparagraph (A)(ii), the drug subject to such request may be re-submitted for filing only if—</text>
 <clause id="HEBB839CA1E7B4110941BF5DC6232FEF1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the drug is marketed as a nonprescription drug, under conditions of use comparable to the conditions specified in the request, for such period of time as the Secretary determines appropriate (not to exceed five consecutive years) pursuant to an application approved under section 505; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HACB890ED5FB7489D977399E948044675"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>during such time period, one million retail packages of the drug, or an equivalent quantity as determined by the Secretary, were distributed for retail sale, as determined in such manner as the Secretary finds appropriate.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5FDF42A50D144B0FBAD3BD691BCEB131"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Rule of application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except in the case of a request involving a drug described in section 586(9), as in effect on January 1, 2017, if the Secretary refuses to file a request under this paragraph, the requestor may not file such request over protest under paragraph (5)(A)(iii).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H38747D7860AE4EABA1FC4D2CE65211AB"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Packaging</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An administrative order issued under paragraph (2), (4)(A), or (5) may include requirements for the packaging of a drug to encourage use in accordance with labeling. Such requirements may include unit dose packaging, requirements for products intended for use by children, requirements to reduce risk of harm from unsupervised ingestion, and other appropriate requirements. This paragraph does not authorize the Food and Drug Administration to require standards or testing procedures as described in part 1700 of title 16, Code of Federal Regulations.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H95DFD24012B941638B0E0FD6A5E5A36E"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Final and tentative final monographs for category I drugs deemed final administrative orders</header>
 <subparagraph id="H870587E743B240DD86BEC1E0B3546D47"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subparagraph (B), a final monograph or tentative final monograph establishing conditions of use for a drug described in subsection (a)(1), shall be deemed to be a final administrative order under this subsection and may be amended, revoked, or otherwise modified in accordance with the procedures of this subsection.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6107466762B04E6498E08ACA99A648E0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Deemed orders include harmonizing technical amendments</header><text>The deemed establishment of a final administrative order under subparagraph (A) shall be construed to include any technical amendments to such order as the Secretary determines necessary to ensure that such order is appropriately harmonized, in terms of terminology or cross-references, with the applicable provisions of this Act (and regulations thereunder) and any other orders issued under this section.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3DDED26B6B7E455C9967BFD9912D73EE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Procedure for minor changes</header>
 <paragraph id="H2A4FF1CFB8034A50A5629E8EF3CDE0DC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Minor changes in the dosage form of a drug that is described in paragraph (1) or (2) of subsection (a) or the subject of an order issued under subsection (b) may be made by a requestor without the issuance of an order under subsection (b) if—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD2D6C8C6D68A4653B7AC946D634D0BF8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the requestor maintains such information as is necessary to demonstrate that the change—</text> <clause id="HE333908E9EF74754A1A347A6F418CC66"><enum>(i)</enum><text>will not affect the safety or effectiveness of the drug; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB6F35D29F4DB4FD7AAB640D14C86D63E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>will not materially affect the extent of absorption or other exposure to the active ingredient in comparison to a suitable reference product; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2FB1286A220145AAA951F8115F0175F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the change is in conformity with the requirements of an applicable administrative order issued by the Secretary under paragraph (3).</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4768FFE2D62A457EBB4731608F132FA5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional information</header>
 <subparagraph id="H94046B35445B49D4BEE9F1DD6035B32C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Access to records</header><text>A sponsor shall submit records requested by the Secretary relating to such a minor change under section 704(a)(4), within 15 business days of receiving such a request, or such longer period as the Secretary may provide.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1B4B157765C4016BB8F8CFDB79CABB6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Insufficient information</header><text>If the Secretary determines that the information contained in such records is not sufficient to demonstrate that the change does not affect the safety or effectiveness of the drug or materially affect the extent of absorption or other exposure to the active ingredient, the Secretary—</text>
 <clause id="H64449848DD99425084E98CF36E9FB356"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may so inform the sponsor of the drug in writing; and</text> </clause><clause id="H71BCB05A584A4BB187A1C889A8E90E73"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide the sponsor of the drug with a reasonable opportunity to provide additional information.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47031960D76043FAA7A778F841F3A11D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Failure to submit sufficient information</header><text>If the sponsor fails to provide such additional information within the prescribed time, or if the Secretary determines that such additional information does not demonstrate that the change does not affect the safety or effectiveness of the drug or materially affect the extent of absorption or other exposure to the active ingredient, the drug as modified is a new drug within the meaning of section 201(p) and shall be deemed to be misbranded under section 502(ee).</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E5A2E2A0F924B2E8BEDE2292411AF9A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Determining whether a change will affect safety or effectiveness</header>
 <subparagraph id="H0987FF2C479D47938467A215CD918E4F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall issue one or more administrative orders specifying requirements for determining whether a minor change made by a sponsor pursuant to this subsection will affect the safety or effectiveness of a drug or materially affect the extent of absorption or other exposure to an active ingredient in the drug in comparison to a suitable reference product, together with guidance for applying those orders to specific dosage forms.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE402A2B40C94C30A00EBD0FC1626808"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Standard practices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The orders and guidance issued by the Secretary under subparagraph (A) shall take into account relevant public standards and standard practices for evaluating the quality of drugs, and may take into account the special needs of populations, including children.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC973B60F9324434CA723A0E66A2BDC58"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Confidentiality of information submitted by requestors</header>
 <paragraph id="H7E5A2AF50916425D93B00B5A9241A1D3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), any information, including reports of testing conducted on the drug or drugs involved, that is submitted by a requestor in connection with proceedings on an order under this section (including any minor change under subsection (c)) and is a trade secret or confidential information subject to section 552(b)(4) of title 5, United States Code, or section 1905 of title 18, United States Code, shall not be disclosed to the public unless the requestor consents to that disclosure.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8DC01B1C26D34128966867F3C444F554"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (1), the Secretary shall make available to the public any information (other than raw data sets) submitted by a requestor in support of a request under subsection (b)(5)(A) as of the date on which the proposed order is made public unless—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H3EE62250E5054A20A095CC8244869C0B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the information pertains to pharmaceutical quality information except to the extent that specific information is necessary to establish standards under which a drug is generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H409F761973F14B05BB7E993F4A2E5002"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the information is submitted in a requestor-initiated request, but the requestor withdraws such request, in accordance with withdrawal procedures established by the Secretary, before the Secretary issues the proposed order; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE136FAD289E441AC9551D95F63EDF016"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Secretary obtains the information under subsection (c).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDAF03BA315664673A1778AF294FA26FA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Updates to drug listing information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A sponsor who makes a change to a drug subject to this section shall submit updated drug listing information for the drug in accordance with section 510(j) within 30 calendar days of the date when the drug is first commercially marketed, except that a sponsor who was the order requestor with respect to an order subject to subsection (b)(5)(C) (or a licensee, assignee, or successor in interest of such requestor) shall submit updated drug listing information on or before the date when the drug is first commercially marketed.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H2229F8A4485A46BBBC0C261EF3CA7032"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Approvals under section 505</header><text>The provisions of this section shall not be construed to preclude a person from seeking or maintaining the approval of a drug under sections 505(b)(1), 505(b)(2), and 505(j). A determination under this section that a drug is not subject to section 503(b)(1), is generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1), and is not a new drug under section 201(p) shall constitute a finding that the drug is safe and effective that may be relied upon for purposes of an application under section 505(b)(2), so that the applicant shall be required to submit for purposes of such application only information needed to support any modification of the drug that is not covered by such determination under this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H61BCE64ABBD94D25A1D75065F5554334"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Public availability of administrative orders</header><text>The Secretary shall establish, maintain, update (as determined necessary by the Secretary but no less frequently than annually), and make publicly available, with respect to orders issued under this section—</text>
 <paragraph id="H7DEDFFC8880C4AF691C22ADDC77F4022"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a repository of each final order and interim final order in effect, including the complete text of the order; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF896B5C7D4424491853C126D1571F782"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a listing of all orders proposed and under development under subsection (b)(2), including—</text> <subparagraph id="H0351D50DF45542548FBA8B8054D3C70A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a brief description of each such order; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE177D9D79F364285AC587AD5696E7C16"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary’s expectations, if resources permit, for issuance of proposed orders over a three-year period.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H52233059EE2C49A6BEBBCB7573F00936"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Development advice to sponsors or requestors</header><text>The Secretary shall establish procedures under which sponsors or requestors may meet with appropriate officials of the Food and Drug Administration to obtain advice on the studies and other information necessary to support submissions under this section and other matters relevant to the regulation of nonprescription drugs and the development of new nonprescription drugs under this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H3010252A985E49E59B15DB2722666E15"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Participation of multiple sponsors or requestors</header><text>The Secretary shall establish procedures to facilitate efficient participation by multiple sponsors or requestors in proceedings under this section, including provision for joint meetings with multiple sponsors or requestors or with organizations nominated by sponsors or requestors to represent their interests in a proceeding.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H1714FE10E2894F44A20DF83561A84E89"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Electronic format</header><text>All submissions under this section shall be in electronic format.</text> </subsection><subsection id="HFE2C2F5BC1C147FBBFE44F764E9E9FF1"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Effect on existing regulations governing nonprescription drugs</header> <paragraph id="H32A71C7038134654A96F39CDD2225E32"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Regulations of general applicability to nonprescription drugs</header><text>Except as provided in this subsection, nothing in this section supersedes regulations establishing general requirements for nonprescription drugs, including regulations of general applicability contained in parts 201, 250, and 330 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations, or any successor regulations. The Secretary shall establish or modify such regulations by means of rulemaking in accordance with section 553 of title 5, United States Code.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="HE4767033844C4ABE9FDFDCEDC30E7142"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regulations establishing requirements for specific nonprescription drugs</header>
 <subparagraph id="H9B634480493C459D971ECC6708EA8716"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provisions of section 310.545 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the day before the date of the enactment of this section, shall be deemed to be a final order under subsection (b).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H958B2034A7CC4C19A557464C15E10BB9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Regulations in effect on the day before the date of the enactment of this section, establishing requirements for specific nonprescription drugs marketed pursuant to this section (including such requirements in parts 201 and 250 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations), shall be deemed to be final orders under subsection (b), only as they apply to drugs subject to paragraphs (1), (2), (3), and (6) of subsection (a).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8BD02E2D5C9433C8D09A352031A112A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Withdrawal of regulations</header><text>The Secretary shall withdraw regulations establishing final monographs and the procedures governing the over-the-counter drug review under part 330 and other relevant parts of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the day before the date of the enactment of this section), or make technical changes to such regulations to ensure conformity with appropriate terminology and cross references. Notwithstanding subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, any such withdrawal or technical changes shall be made without public notice and comment and shall be effective upon publication through notice in the Federal Register (or upon such date as specified in such notice).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H804BF4DA6C174B92BBDF628CFCCBA766"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>The Secretary shall issue guidance that specifies—</text> <paragraph id="HB01EBA8F1C89453C9396DF64B8848994"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the procedures and principles for formal meetings between the Secretary and sponsors or requestors for drugs subject to this section;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDD889D2107EE4693B74A8740D33C2F9F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the format and content of data submissions to the Secretary under this section;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HA79BDF439AE94A2F86BE9A8775990D00"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the format of electronic submissions to the Secretary under this section;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H236F06F596644F229E3FDDCDCBD94DFE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>consolidated proceedings and the procedures for such proceedings where appropriate; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H42CD69E02FD2490E9560849BCE2CE676"><enum>(5)</enum><text>for minor changes in drugs, recommendations on how to comply with the requirements in orders issued under subsection (c)(3).</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD6BB5EAE2CCE4F66ABC73F6B832325C1"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header>
 <paragraph id="H84EC3FB41AFF4F52B2CA83BAF0C97A03"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>This section shall not affect the treatment or status of a nonprescription drug—</text> <subparagraph id="H361F46D3FF4A4912A36015884E7F2123"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that is marketed without an application approved under section 505 as of the date of the enactment of this section;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8FA45478EBEE4239A17968877589970D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that is not subject to an order issued under this section; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB145B691B4D4A1F89E6E21D62117301"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to which paragraphs (1), (2), (3), (4), (5), or (6) of subsection (a) do not apply.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D9473CEDD444507952141E5BFAA0122"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Treatment of products previously found to be subject to time and extent requirements</header>
 <subparagraph id="HE92AEA1BAE9D46158428ED9DEF25F29D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Notwithstanding subsection (a), a drug described in subparagraph (B) may only be lawfully marketed, without an application approved under section 505, pursuant to an order issued under this section.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCCF64D78985847078D1F4F2A877CFD3B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A drug described in this subparagraph is a drug which, prior to the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary had determined in a proposed or final rule to be ineligible for review under the OTC drug review (as such phrase <quote>OTC drug review</quote> was used in section 330.14 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the day before the date of the enactment of this section).</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H88CE787729EE4C29BD786E2444513809"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Preservation of authority</header>
 <subparagraph id="HC4AAFD0ACCBF4CA7BE7D3C6F1C8DF704"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Nothing in paragraph (1) shall be construed to preclude or limit the applicability of any other provision of this Act.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H105479C36DB74C2584E8A26C900117A4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in subsection (a) shall be construed to prohibit the Secretary from issuing an order under this section finding a drug to be not generally recognized as safe and effective within the meaning of section 201(p)(1), as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H58E75F9E36AB473E8626B81DAFD838FB"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Inapplicability of paperwork reduction act</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/35">Chapter 35</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code, shall not apply to collections of information made under this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H59BAF15644B84A61B71D3801049BB903"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Inapplicability of notice and comment rulemaking and other requirements</header><text>The requirements of subsection (b) shall apply with respect to orders issued under this section instead of the requirements of subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H753283304DD34B5CA7D679CD0E7E559F"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HF4F867731CC84999984534B0E4F0713D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>nonprescription drug</term> refers to a drug not subject to the requirements of section 503(b)(1).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H20D050371CE8453389FA2EB28AC254CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>sponsor</term> refers to any person marketing, manufacturing, or processing a drug that—</text> <subparagraph id="H0B8368E1FE404D25BBADEBE8546ED194"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is listed pursuant to section 510(j); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC3377920F0B40B3BFA0B851D6C7E7E3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is or will be subject to an administrative order of the Food and Drug Administration.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA41413E2BD94735BF202CE4F2DEAB07"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>requestor</term> refers to any person or group of persons marketing, manufacturing, processing, or developing a drug.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection></section><section id="H8C07FF99368A41A5AE05234B80BDFD92"><enum>102.</enum><header>Misbranding</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 502 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/352">21 U.S.C. 352</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after paragraph (dd) the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H3FFB30F9E27F4588B5A3B0BC8AEE9A3D" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="HE1C78D2AEFA2423788C0D3AF3B78B6C2"><enum>(ee)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If it is a nonprescription drug that is subject to section 505G, not the subject of an application approved under section 505 or an exemption under section 505(i), and does not comply with the requirements under section 505G.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H3ED430DAC21C4503BB62CC39B5A13B77"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>If it is a drug and it was manufactured, prepared, propagated, compounded, or processed in a facility for which fees have not been paid as required by section 744O.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</section><section id="HD19F2FF038BD4519B4A4A9E5087D9702"><enum>103.</enum><header>Drugs excluded from the over-the-counter drug review</header>
 <subsection id="H4001EF22068B4FA28457A8A2C8A0C167"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Nothing in this Act (or the amendments made by this Act) shall apply to any nonprescription drug which was excluded by the Food and Drug Administration from the Over-the-Counter Drug Review in accordance with the statement set out at page 9466 of volume 37 of the Federal Register, published on May 11, 1972.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE10AA23BAA5F4571B2B5573247AAB06C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to preclude or limit the applicability of any other provision of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/301">21 U.S.C. 301</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
				</subsection></section><section id="H06A5ED4B2646442AB77886BA6A4A9905"><enum>104.</enum><header>Treatment of Sunscreen Innovation Act</header>
				<subsection id="HA6C76A846A90487EA171233AE985371E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review of nonprescription sunscreen active ingredients</header>
					<paragraph id="H4A0249BA24BF44F0AA2AC1EA470BF863"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicability of section 505G for pending submissions</header>
 <subparagraph id="HBAF81A767CA0401AA608EB9719CFA88C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A sponsor of a nonprescription sunscreen active ingredient or combination of nonprescription sunscreen active ingredients that, as of the date of enactment of this Act, is subject to a proposed sunscreen order under section 586C of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360fff-3">21 U.S.C. 360fff–3</external-xref>) may elect, by means of giving written notification to the Secretary of Health and Human Services within 90 calendar days of the enactment of this Act, to transition into the review of such ingredient or combination of ingredients pursuant to the process set out in section 505G of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, as added by section 101 of this Act.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52C7F6D53192434A8CDCCBC62B4A1F93"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Election exercised</header><text>Upon receipt by the Secretary of Health and Human Services of a timely notification under subparagraph (A)—</text>
 <clause id="HCB71B636406D4784AC7A17FFDAEB8EE8"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the proposed sunscreen order involved is deemed to be a request for an order under subsection (b) of section 505G of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, as added by section 101 of this Act; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA2F241D94EF841788F9DB3410BFE7DB4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such order is deemed to have been accepted for filing under subsection (b)(6)(A)(i) of such section 505G.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE9952BE2F5A646819C17746823BDEAD3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Election not exercised</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A sponsor of a nonprescription sunscreen active ingredient or combination of nonprescription sunscreen active ingredients described in subparagraph (A) that does not elect for such ingredient or combination of ingredients to be reviewed under section 505G of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, as added by section 101 of this Act, shall continue to have such ingredient or combination of ingredients reviewed in accordance with section 586C of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360fff-3">21 U.S.C. 360fff–3</external-xref>) and may not subsequently elect to transition into the review of such ingredient or combination of ingredients pursuant to the process set out in section 505G of such Act, as added by section 101 of this Act.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H041B8FB031D744A694C045B4834E8BA4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the terms <term>sponsor</term>, <term>nonprescription</term>, <term>sunscreen active ingredient</term>, and <term>proposed sunscreen order</term> have the meanings given to those terms in section 586 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360fff">21 U.S.C. 360fff</external-xref>).</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H00938382B8C24E78B02449377B3A3036"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amendments to sunscreen provisions</header>
 <paragraph id="H019C16EED8C44BE88A7F5BD876A20B07"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Final sunscreen orders</header><text>Paragraph (3) of section 586C(e) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360fff-3">21 U.S.C. 360fff–3(e)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF4AF71F8A7084D5FA781BA9A9AFDB0E7" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H245C13FDE5024B1091515DA252B41CDB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Relationship to orders under section 505G</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A final sunscreen order shall be deemed to be a final order under section 505G.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H551C853B24974F42AC28D872B6A8CB26"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (7) of section 586C(b) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360fff-3">21 U.S.C. 360fff–3(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H93DAA4E4B09F48328518E08536E6E833"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>A sponsor may request</quote> and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HADC29BFD3EF145C79CB5EAF3D2A7C993" style="OLC"> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H2B4590E709CF4B318A69C282D3CE36CD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A sponsor may request</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB5EE68E3DC7F4F2E9BA15E52F8709D49"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H524C8C25F4174369AB71BD1AC781A799" style="OLC"> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HEBBF8C2F95AB4F8CBB69C33BD7781F9B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Confidential meetings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A sponsor may request one or more confidential meetings with respect to a proposed sunscreen order, including a letter deemed to be a proposed sunscreen order under paragraph (3), to discuss matters involving confidential commercial information or trade secrets. The Secretary shall convene a confidential meeting with such sponsor in a reasonable time period. If a sponsor requests more than one confidential meeting for the same proposed sunscreen order, the Secretary may refuse to grant an additional confidential meeting request if the Secretary determines that such additional confidential meeting is not reasonably necessary for the sponsor to advance its proposed sunscreen order, or if the request for a confidential meeting fails to include sufficient information upon which to base a substantive discussion. The Secretary shall publish a post-meeting summary of each confidential meeting under this subparagraph that does not disclose confidential commercial information or trade secrets.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H9117550079134AB5BD65E5BD7A80D1DB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Sunset provision</header><text>Subchapter I of chapter V of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360fff">21 U.S.C. 360fff</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC7F83F417AC54311A9183C6C42FD7C95" style="OLC">
 <section commented="no" id="H5BB8D5F409734EBDA5C43446A86AB311"><enum>586H.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This subchapter shall cease to be effective at the end of fiscal year 2022.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE873B01274C04D8CAC493AD3E792B64F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Treatment of non-Sunscreen time and extent applications</header> <paragraph id="H40BF3092B2A74447A3A0BDEA9CA81336"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any application described in section 586F of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360fff-6">21 U.S.C. 360fff–6</external-xref>) that was submitted to the Secretary of Health and Human Services pursuant to section 330.14 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations, as such provisions were in effect immediately prior to the date of enactment date of this Act, shall be extinguished as of such date of enactment, subject to paragraph (2).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9B9EB471A5E14359A1F6983C9B41D62F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Order request</header><text>Nothing in paragraph (1) precludes the submission of an order request under section 505G(b) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, as added by section 101 of this Act, with respect to a drug that was the subject of an application extinguished under paragraph (1).</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H49208EE2F9134470A66E947CACFD6BFF"><enum>105.</enum><header>Annual update to Congress on appropriate pediatric indication for certain OTC cough and cold drugs</header>
 <subsection id="H7CBB0037721C4667B3C9965568CFEFC9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subsection (c), the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall, beginning not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, annually submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate a letter describing the progress of the Food and Drug Administration—</text>
 <paragraph id="H5622E42FEB2A43AF8A7DEEA7C82FE4B8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in evaluating the cough and cold monograph described in subsection (b) with respect to children under age 6; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE98A273EFF114DCC9A7B80EEB11A57E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as appropriate, revising such cough and cold monograph to address such children through the order process under section 505G(b) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, as added by section 101 of this Act.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H573D60A40A0546019BC4EAF3A5CA67FE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Cough and cold monograph described</header><text>The cough and cold monograph described in this subsection consists of the conditions under which nonprescription drugs containing antitussive, expectorant, nasal decongestant, or antihistamine active ingredients (or combinations thereof) are generally recognized as safe and effective, as specified in part 341 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect immediately prior to the date of enactment of this Act), and included in an order deemed to be established under section 505G(b) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, as added by section 101 of this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H3549A6C80B6641D5A3AB1502ADE83315"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duration of authority</header><text>The requirement under subsection (a) shall terminate as of the date of a letter submitted by the Secretary of Health and Human Services pursuant to such subsection in which the Secretary indicates that the Food and Drug Administration has completed its evaluation and revised, in a final order, as applicable, the cough and cold monograph as described in subsection (a)(2).</text>
				</subsection></section></title><title id="H522DB967697B4AEDA831AED460295634"><enum>II</enum><header>User Fees</header>
			<section id="H5726817DBD5741E893EB45D301405391"><enum>201.</enum><header>Short title; finding</header>
 <subsection id="H9E5E50F536FC43C29AC0CF99BDCE2DF0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This title may be cited as the <quote>Over-the-Counter Monograph User Fee Act of 2018</quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="HD5C61084D8424A438B809966FEC7AB04"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Finding</header><text>The Congress finds that the fees authorized by the amendments made in this title will be dedicated to OTC monograph drug activities, as set forth in the goals identified for purposes of part 10 of subchapter C of chapter VII of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, in the letters from the Secretary of Health and Human Services to the Chairman of the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Chairman of the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives, as set forth in the Congressional Record.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H056BC6F8BFC14937A5E5A989FBA5CE8C"><enum>202.</enum><header>Fees relating to over-the-counter drugs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subchapter C of chapter VII of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/379f">21 U.S.C. 379f</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by inserting after part 9 the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="HA688A533904845199816E510A095BCAD" style="OLC">
					<part id="H6A6B498A9E3842DBAE452E3E6DA06914"><enum>10</enum><header>Fees Relating to Over-the-Counter Drugs</header>
 <section id="H47E2F09E5E2B4F80A3F3A9703EAC782F"><enum>744N.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this part:</text> <paragraph id="HDB5499731C2647A6A8A0441B63366FAD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>affiliate</term> means a business entity that has a relationship with a second business entity if, directly or indirectly—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H01D9513FBC984C1498BD292340282CBF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>one business entity controls, or has the power to control, the other business entity; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B98B4A821034C22AA8874F1FB6C785D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a third party controls, or has power to control, both of the business entities.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H37ECCE41DB9B469F896B21EC7978F42E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>contract manufacturing organization facility</term> means an OTC monograph drug facility where neither the owner of such manufacturing facility nor any affiliate of such owner or facility sells the OTC monograph drug produced at such facility directly to wholesalers, retailers, or consumers in the United States.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H060B778EF2DF48BEBE6EF324E6799CE4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>costs of resources allocated for OTC monograph drug activities</term> means the expenses in connection with OTC monograph drug activities for—</text> <subparagraph id="H4A049843466E441480487C933771FB14"><enum>(A)</enum><text>officers and employees of the Food and Drug Administration, contractors of the Food and Drug Administration, advisory committees, and costs related to such officers, employees, and committees and costs related to contracts with such contractors;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC137495E9DBB455D81911ACEBF2A8CD6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>management of information, and the acquisition, maintenance, and repair of computer resources;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86C70F1561C746298FCE4C70A2B63194"><enum>(C)</enum><text>leasing, maintenance, renovation, and repair of facilities and acquisition, maintenance, and repair of fixtures, furniture, scientific equipment, and other necessary materials and supplies; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA5303F3F80941B9A8A29B0BB34A805B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>collecting fees under section 744O and accounting for resources allocated for OTC monograph drug activities.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDCC219C9BA254D58BA3A121E0B277F07"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>FDA establishment identifier</term> is the unique number automatically generated by Food and Drug Administration’s Field Accomplishments and Compliance Tracking System (FACTS) (or any successor system).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H11B13743C80446A1AC9AC1A14528FF17"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>OTC monograph drug</term> means a nonprescription drug without an approved new drug application which is governed by the provisions of section 505G.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9537B1DC1E1E47FC9835039D1471100A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The term <term>OTC monograph drug activities</term> means activities of the Secretary associated with OTC monograph drugs and inspection of facilities associated with such products, including the following activities:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H9DBAB4FAA2FA4050A017D89D152A31F1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The activities necessary for review and evaluation of OTC monographs and OTC monograph order requests, including—</text>
 <clause id="H7545B388A9BB42FE873D9F35CE95C785"><enum>(i)</enum><text>orders proposing or finalizing applicable conditions of use for OTC monograph drugs;</text> </clause><clause id="HFF6984565D5C4A0F9C8F1D976DBB8336"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>orders affecting status regarding general recognition of safety and effectiveness of an OTC monograph ingredient or combination of ingredients under specified conditions of use;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD073BC266AD24B20A4B53C9284390BE3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>all OTC monograph drug development and review activities, including intraagency collaboration;</text> </clause><clause id="H5027ED5F2959457BA0444D0CB92BA57D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>regulation and policy development activities related to OTC monograph drugs;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HDA65E3D4A8234C41A9A5D99C8E3F4BF1"><enum>(v)</enum><text>development of product standards for products subject to review and evaluation;</text> </clause><clause id="H985FA49719584BEBB979E5BA98963C2A"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>meetings referred to in section 505G(i);</text>
 </clause><clause id="H6F4D2F94EB254966A864D67405A94573"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>review of labeling prior to issuance of orders related to OTC monograph drugs or conditions of use; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H654285E508C74CF09D775B958A9AB273"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>regulatory science activities related to OTC monograph drugs.</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB24E7882346D459E9299DC13EA840C05"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Inspections related to OTC monograph drugs.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDE8F10A7D8A42DAA9604A39542BCCDA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Monitoring of clinical and other research conducted in connection with OTC monograph drugs.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E905AF3703F4201BE85351DDEBC9A13"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Safety activities with respect to OTC monograph drugs, including—</text>
 <clause id="H69F4CA0DCD7D4C6A9A72744D7D92B585"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collecting, developing, and reviewing safety information on OTC monograph drugs, including adverse event reports;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB3B7860EE5FA494CA91902B63F5E0724"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>developing and using improved adverse event data-collection systems, including information technology systems; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H74A3C706AC424B0AA501122C5EDAEDEE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>developing and using improved analytical tools to assess potential safety risks, including access to external databases.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5877EBE6A78346AEA28D5325AE1ED410"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Other activities necessary for implementation of section 505G.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7F7B242588C4E4EBC404AA604392F23"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The term <term>OTC monograph order request</term> means a request for an order submitted under section 505G(b)(6).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCE71C0D50E794A0ABF755693172BCD76"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The term <term>Tier 1 OTC monograph order request</term> means any OTC monograph order request not determined to be a Tier 2 OTC monograph order request.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9D60FD0C50C84D87932FED6E1241127D"><enum>(9)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0ED72FB1EAFA469F92D387375DC13FA2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <term>Tier 2 OTC monograph order request</term> means, subject to subparagraph (B), an OTC monograph order request for—</text>
 <clause id="H2D20E7066F954F2D9014790C7D6EDA10" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the reordering of existing information in the drug facts label of an OTC monograph drug;</text> </clause><clause id="H08F0316083114919828D1FE2FE19705F" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the addition of information to the other information section of the drug facts label of an OTC monograph drug, as limited by section 201.66(c)(7) of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations);</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA5D829CBC4E846A9B1B8AF347A2DB01F" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>modification to the directions for use section of the drug facts label of an OTC monograph drug, if such changes conform to changes made pursuant to section 505G(c)(3)(A);</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB63504F7335F4BB08808CEBFF7AE5343" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the standardization of the concentration or dose of a specific finalized ingredient within a particular finalized monograph;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA105BE66799A45B6A29D6C5B39314715" indent="up1"><enum>(v)</enum><text>a change to ingredient nomenclature to align with nomenclature of a standards-setting organization; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="HCC4465A0442844EDAACC0CDAA78E6812" indent="up1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">addition of an interchangeable term in accordance with section 330.1 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E81F294775B49F082364830FF7A551D" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may, based on program implementation experience or other factors found appropriate by the Secretary, characterize any OTC monograph order request as a Tier 2 OTC monograph order request (including recharacterizing a request from Tier 1 to Tier 2) and publish such determination in a proposed order issued pursuant to section 505G.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AECE7EACB67417E9312BD910F14AB86"><enum>(10)</enum>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HFA2A8A7FBC54485ABFD333C7604943AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <term>OTC monograph drug facility</term> means a foreign or domestic business or other entity that—</text> <clause id="HF349E0AA511D4D838AA75472432FBA54" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is—</text>
 <subclause id="H39BD92F4E7B74D77BEECF8612734C07F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>under one management, either direct or indirect; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H9E86994869FB49B08C94C3B91C2B9407"><enum>(II)</enum><text>at one geographic location or address engaged in manufacturing or processing the finished dosage form of an OTC monograph drug<italic></italic>;</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H5BB4BDB4A13842BCB5E07EF23CA17C7F" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes a finished dosage form manufacturer facility in a contractual relationship with the sponsor of one or more OTC monograph drugs to manufacture or process such drugs; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF484BC3FFCED4DB8AEA7C460087BBA4F" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>does not include a business or other entity whose only manufacturing or processing activities are one or more of the following: production of clinical research supplies, or testing.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB0FFBC03B434074B7BFCB94F772259D" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A)(i)(II), separate buildings or locations within close proximity are considered to be at one geographic location or address if the activities conducted in such buildings or locations are—</text>
 <clause id="HD32171B569914C2789BFCA4564E2545D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>closely related to the same business enterprise;</text> </clause><clause id="HE8D7562144884FD9A0845705072F4DCC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>under the supervision of the same local management; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HAC2476D0095849439CE3D32848791CB9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>under a single FDA establishment identifier and capable of being inspected by the Food and Drug Administration during a single inspection.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9D267638FB7441F8816C2FF17A9CA27" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a business or other entity would meet criteria specified in subparagraph (A), but for being under multiple management, the business or other entity is deemed to constitute multiple facilities, one per management entity, for purposes of this paragraph.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6AFA338442E41009EAB8E6690819310"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The term <term>OTC monograph drug meeting</term> means any meeting regarding the content of a proposed OTC monograph order request.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H781B0F3CB69742998A8BD0A3F6D97A1F"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The term <term>person</term> includes an affiliate of a person.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H97B46EC6B92349B9AB0E7DF6EE7E1746"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The terms <term>requestor</term> and <term>sponsor</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 505G.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="H93D010B825BE4886949FCD8FAFF46530"><enum>744O.</enum><header>Authority to assess and use OTC monograph fees</header> <subsection id="H82486C2CEF4748E8895FADFC6F55F41B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Types of fees</header><text>Beginning with fiscal year 2019, the Secretary shall assess and collect fees in accordance with this section as follows:</text>
								<paragraph id="H1D26643745A74FC39F906651F6E88FB7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Facility fee</header>
 <subparagraph id="H3CFCD693C52D4CE3A90C5DDF86C010EF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each person that owns a facility identified as an OTC monograph drug facility on December 31 of the fiscal year or at any time during the preceding 12-month period shall be assessed an annual fee for each such facility as determined under subsection (c).</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE466EB396455430DBC00DCDA77BD2B34"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exceptions</header>
 <clause id="H4283526839C0493C8532CB5FC8FD0461"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A fee shall not be assessed under subparagraph (A) if the identified OTC monograph drug facility has ceased all activities related to OTC monograph drugs prior to the date specified in subparagraph (D)(ii) and has updated its registration to reflect such change under the requirements for drug establishment registration set forth in section 510.</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HF50275ADE22B4C2C8060E61786894F66"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of the fee for a contract manufacturing organization facility shall be equal to <fraction>2/3</fraction> the amount of the fee for an OTC monograph drug facility that is not a contract manufacturing organization facility.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B231AA3B28841B0A079BD3A43AE1862"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>The amount of fees established under subparagraph (A) shall be established under subsection (c).</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54291529D0C443D29E4517211CD82E8B"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Due date</header> <clause id="HF998823B62CC425BB0C881DE1CEEBBF9"><enum>(i)</enum><header>For first program year</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For fiscal year 2019, the facility fees required under subparagraph (A) shall be due 45 calendar days after publication of the Federal Register notice provided for under subsection (c)(4)(A).</text>
 </clause><clause id="H4051CD8EAF2F40B68E7D7B1C4AFB98A8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Subsequent fiscal years</header><text>For each fiscal year after fiscal year 2019, the facility fees required under subparagraph (A) shall be due on the later of—</text>
 <subclause id="HF9AA440DCF2D4D7593C9E0F5AC7BEE25"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the first business day of June of such year; or</text> </subclause><subclause id="HB91716761B644C9A943F4683E038805C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the first business day after the enactment of an appropriations Act providing for the collection and obligation of fees under this section for such year.</text>
											</subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA5966DADB4F4AA1B20AEEE2DE5BE96C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>OTC monograph order request fee</header>
 <subparagraph id="HD7BA261FD4A34593835F1C33E4364CB5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each person that submits an OTC monograph order request shall be subject to a fee for an OTC monograph order request. The amount of such fee shall be—</text>
 <clause id="H41FCC75242D443318043D1DECA31A26D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for a Tier 1 OTC monograph order request, $500,000, adjusted for inflation for the fiscal year (as determined under subsection (c)(1)(B)); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H672862E876D34935AB5527D5D713CDC7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for a Tier 2 OTC monograph order request, $100,000 adjusted for inflation for the fiscal year (as determined under subsection (c)(1)(B)).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30C842B9327040E8B1FF2DF39312BC5D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Due date</header><text>The OTC monograph order request fees required under subparagraph (A) shall be due on the date of submission of the OTC monograph order request.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H074FA9EE58704CA8BBCFF791B2B62875"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exception for certain safety changes</header><text>A person who is named as the requestor in an OTC monograph order shall not be subject to a fee under subparagraph (A) if the Secretary finds that the OTC monograph order request seeks to change the drug facts labeling of an OTC monograph drug in a way that would add to or strengthen—</text>
 <clause id="H0EDE28236621418085C1C798A7A53B93"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a contraindication, warning, or precaution;</text> </clause><clause id="HABB80F63DBD14CC5BBFE484DB226782C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a statement about risk associated with misuse or abuse; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H35D5A0EE7E4845A2AC0B64CA57607ADF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an instruction about dosage and administration that is intended to increase the safe use of the OTC monograph drug.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4408F56FE1454CEF98D582F94D845EBE"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Refund of fee if order request is recategorized as a Tier 2 OTC monograph order request</header><text>If the Secretary determines that an OTC monograph request initially characterized as Tier 1 shall be re-characterized as a Tier 2 OTC monograph order request, and the requestor has paid a Tier 1 fee in accordance with subparagraph (A)(i), the Secretary shall refund the requestor the difference between the Tier 1 and Tier 2 fees determined under subparagraphs (A)(i) and (A)(ii), respectively.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D5B40CD5BE84AC6A427F7DDF702712E"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Refund of fee if order request refused for filing or withdrawn before filing</header><text>The Secretary shall refund 75 percent of the fee paid under subparagraph (B) for any order request which is refused for filing.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H44E177F9959E4EB69806B1C0EFA445E4"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Fees for order requests previously refused for filing or withdrawn before filing</header><text>An OTC monograph order request that was submitted but was refused for filing, or was withdrawn before being accepted or refused for filing, shall be subject to the full fee under subparagraph (A) upon being resubmitted or filed over protest.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA935AA4CCC9544CDA7EC0CEF13435BBA"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Refund of fee if order request withdrawn</header><text>If an order request is withdrawn after the order request was filed, the Secretary may refund the fee or a portion of the fee if no substantial work was performed on the order request after the application was filed. The Secretary shall have the sole discretion to refund a fee or a portion of the fee under this subparagraph. A determination by the Secretary concerning a refund under this subparagraph shall not be reviewable.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF0F3962C09746AE99BB9CF2C4AC3E94"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Refunds</header>
 <subparagraph id="H1F136D67039940889F5C14066EE7C267"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Other than refunds provided in subparagraphs (D) through (G) of paragraph (2), the Secretary shall not refund any fee paid under paragraph (1) except as provided in subparagraph (B).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE400ADB6139C4372B7D08E11A3917717"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Disputes concerning fees</header><text>To qualify for the return of a fee claimed to have been paid in error under paragraph (1) or (2), a person shall submit to the Secretary a written request justifying such return within 180 calendar days after such fee was paid.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1198D23689954FE782CF0E03A04D2AB8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>Within the timeframe specified in subsection (c), the Secretary shall publish in the Federal Register the amount of the fees under paragraph (1) for such fiscal year.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA9CF984CB4164141AB4BCFA54C4BDF98"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Fee revenue amounts</header>
 <paragraph id="H60EFC25C44744E40A9B66A47500C3E08"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Fiscal year 2019</header><text>For fiscal year 2019, fees under subsection (a)(1) shall be established to generate a total facility fee revenue amount equal to the sum of—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HDD0627699B5242E2811842FBFC0AE742"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the annual base revenue for fiscal year 2019 (as determined under paragraph (3);</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H65BC62B7256D4F45BE2F7661CA385160"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the dollar amount equal to the operating reserve adjustment for the fiscal year, if applicable (as determined under subsection (c)(2)); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5455EB6B61834CCCB10CF9D3775F82AD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>additional direct cost adjustments (as determined under subsection (c)(3)).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H723C5C0E5C4C4E03ADC9E26744F0A44C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subsequent fiscal years</header><text>For each of the fiscal years 2020 through 2023, fees under subsection (a)(1) shall be established to generate a total facility fee revenue amount equal to the sum of—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD28EC9B80685488698206774C396FA4D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the annual base revenue for the fiscal year (as determined under paragraph (3));</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9885784ED91A4ECBB4B6D1840B9B5E5A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the dollar amount equal to the inflation adjustment for the fiscal year (as determined under subsection (c)(1));</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1459A4096B74863BF7A1EBFE19299A2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the dollar amount equal to the operating reserve adjustment for the fiscal year, if applicable (as determined under subsection (c)(2));</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC8D306D45CB4AD3995B8DFECB351950"><enum>(D)</enum><text>additional direct cost adjustments (as determined under subsection (c)(3)); and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE419A9B0C75B4B87B73AA8B21E53D67E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>additional dollar amounts for each fiscal year as follows:</text>
 <clause id="HA0D6849963004F2F86B82B76180B6150"><enum>(i)</enum><text>$7,000,000 for fiscal year 2020.</text> </clause><clause id="HE63A6B702A90412EB35FFC0756ABF6AB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>$6,000,000 for fiscal year 2021.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD2A84B17AFC44554A629B124768D0B55"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>$7,000,000 for fiscal year 2022.</text> </clause><clause id="H98014C5F904B497DBDE13BA695265A86"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>$3,000,000 for fiscal year 2023.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3DFBEF85B97456698AFD7B9A742824D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Annual base revenue</header><text>For purposes of paragraphs (1)(A) and (2)(A), the dollar amount of the annual base revenue for a fiscal year shall be—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD62C2E3647A2480E94B80319E431101B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for fiscal year 2019, $8,000,000; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1949F550887E4405AF1196E1871B9A35"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for fiscal years 2020 through 2023, the dollar amount of the total revenue amount established under this subsection for the previous fiscal year, not including any adjustments made under subsection (c)(2) or (c)(3).</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0CC67F4FF26A42D59B9F4EF7EBD744B3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Adjustments; annual fee setting</header>
								<paragraph id="H89B69410564F44B58BE13123A076D6DA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Inflation adjustment</header>
 <subparagraph id="HF7AB9F8CB6AE43409D1F0176F059FBDA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of subsection (b)(2)(B), the dollar amount of the inflation adjustment to the annual base revenue for fiscal year 2020 and each subsequent fiscal year shall be equal to the product of—</text>
 <clause id="HE711BA6DEF364D2AB95C6205C0D61142"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such annual base revenue for the fiscal year under subsection (b)(2); and</text> </clause><clause id="H5807E7921CE442ECB525C51E5D170446"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the inflation adjustment percentage under subparagraph (C).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H2D6CF370FFB0463A8B4027A6347A80F6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>OTC monograph order request fees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a)(2), the dollar amount of the inflation adjustment to the fee for OTC monograph order requests for fiscal year 2020 and each subsequent fiscal year shall be equal to the product of—</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="H45053473B31C4DAF8104A89EC17CCF6B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the applicable fee under subsection (a)(2) for the preceding fiscal year; and</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="HDCF10A4B98F64DAC801212A2715A75CA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the inflation adjustment percentage under subparagraph (C).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B9C3609462F4CE18AE5C0C0A36E3947"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Inflation adjustment percentage</header><text>The inflation adjustment percentage under this subparagraph for a fiscal year is equal to—</text> <clause id="H0CBD24D0412A4F4AAAB631786654A656"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for each of fiscal years 2020 and 2021, the average annual percent change that occurred in the Consumer Price Index for urban consumers (Washington-Baltimore, DC–MD–VA–WV; Not Seasonally Adjusted; All items; Annual Index) for the first 3 years of the preceding 4 years of available data; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD0C8305E98A64D808F17C73F034761DB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for each of fiscal years 2022 and 2023, the sum of—</text> <subclause id="H7F9627993F1743C4A7AE6CEA25C40D9F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the average annual percent change in the cost, per full-time equivalent position of the Food and Drug Administration, of all personnel compensation and benefits paid with respect to such positions for the first 3 years of the preceding 4 fiscal years, multiplied by the proportion of personnel compensation and benefits costs to total costs of OTC monograph drug activities for the first 3 years of the preceding 4 fiscal years; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HD4B22059AD6B406E9632901219170716"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the average annual percent change that occurred in the Consumer Price Index for urban consumers (Washington-Baltimore, DC–MD–VA–WV; Not Seasonally Adjusted; All items; Annual Index) for the first 3 years of the preceding 4 years of available data multiplied by the proportion of all costs other than personnel compensation and benefits costs to total costs of OTC monograph drug activities for the first 3 years of the preceding 4 fiscal years.</text>
											</subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4E2831699AD486F8DBD339311E904B2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Operating reserve adjustment</header>
 <subparagraph id="H1DFBABD8807E477588291720555AB53C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For fiscal year 2019 and subsequent fiscal years, for purposes of subsections (b)(1)(B) and (b)(2)(C), the Secretary may, in addition to adjustments under paragraph (1), further increase the fee revenue and fees if such an adjustment is necessary to provide operating reserves of carryover user fees for OTC monograph drug activities for not more than the number of weeks specified in subparagraph (B).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13EFAD4DAE5545DBB3E27BEDC92294F0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Number of weeks</header><text>The number of weeks specified in this subparagraph is—</text> <clause id="HFBD040DC3A3B417DBF73204F0270FAE9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>3 weeks for fiscal year 2019;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF3E81111D5CF4A97A755F160617068C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>7 weeks for fiscal year 2020;</text> </clause><clause id="HE00C0395CBBF413183D3D5F5EBB8E165"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>10 weeks for fiscal year 2021;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H4112B605C2B64563B04CB1DFAF84212D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>10 weeks for fiscal year 2022; and</text> </clause><clause id="H08C911C701974A1F907E05650B93AFBD"><enum>(v)</enum><text>10 weeks for fiscal year 2023.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H794790ECC20A4C6BB987838176B76D4C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Decrease</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary has carryover balances for such process in excess of 10 weeks of the operating reserves referred to in subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall decrease the fee revenue and fees referred to in such subparagraph to provide for not more than 10 weeks of such operating reserves.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78ABB0046E674AEDA967F2B2D727D554"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Rationale for adjustment</header><text>If an adjustment under this paragraph is made, the rationale for the amount of the increase or decrease (as applicable) in fee revenue and fees shall be contained in the annual Federal Register notice under paragraph (4) establishing fee revenue and fees for the fiscal year involved.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE19A0B268FA4A5C92FECC9DED66072A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional direct cost adjustment</header><text>The Secretary shall, in addition to adjustments under paragraphs (1) and (2), further increase the fee revenue and fees for purposes of subsection (b)(2)(D) by an amount equal to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD9242506AE3B42D5B6BFBC9BE11DDC6D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$14,000,000 for fiscal year 2019;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47B6DBD490B94969AACCBE5D58754230"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$7,000,000 for fiscal year 2020;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H254BFA7F39C04F54ABE922D79EA26460"><enum>(C)</enum><text>$4,000,000 for fiscal year 2021;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78E1E6B80CF74061991DFD67197A368A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>$3,000,000 for fiscal year 2022; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21D2EE3589FD4E0CA14961EEA5284ED0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>$3,000,000 for fiscal year 2023.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EBD85AF56DB4227AF4976D23BFE01E0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Annual fee setting</header> <subparagraph id="H5A4181EDD64A4B35AE0A3E768121F4CE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Fiscal year 2019</header><text>The Secretary shall, not later than January 31, 2019—</text>
 <clause id="H3F5D35DB33464245BB3A0AB72748A630"><enum>(i)</enum><text>establish OTC monograph drug facility fees for fiscal year 2019 under subsection (a), based on the revenue amount for such year under subsection (b) and the adjustments provided under this subsection; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB6B1D7F42A2549939FBB23CAFB7D6C1D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">publish fee revenue, facility fees, and OTC monograph order requests in the Federal Register.</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F9D5AD3918743C8BB3ADDE7AC6270F6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Subsequent fiscal years</header><text>The Secretary shall, not later than January 31 of each fiscal year that begins after September 30, 2019, establish for each such fiscal year, based on the revenue amounts under subsection (b) and the adjustments provided under this subsection—</text>
 <clause id="HCF1856E012A7496081CD3F98FFAACBB3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>OTC monograph drug facility fees under subsection (a)(1);</text> </clause><clause id="HB0BD8D9B2D7D48AC8065737FBE386049"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>OTC monograph order request fees under subsection (a)(2); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H75836FE8BFA3494C8E376E14BDF9E312"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>publish such fee revenue amounts, facility fees, and OTC monograph order request fees in the Federal Register.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H06226683F52E45A68D2CC3582C5B7D6E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Identification of facilities</header><text>Each person that owns an OTC monograph drug facility shall submit to the Secretary the information required under this subsection each year. Such information shall, for each fiscal year—</text>
 <paragraph id="H66C53F89BAC94D4D9356142806F9609E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be submitted as part of the requirements for drug establishment registration set forth in section 510; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H32CA266CB3E1470BA098511853FBC1FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include for each such facility, at a minimum, identification of the facility’s business operation as that of an OTC monograph drug facility.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H55B11190A678468B9A547F123A2D5D92"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Effect of failure To pay fees</header>
								<paragraph commented="no" id="H908796D834A0465CA4517A329780781D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>OTC Monograph Drug Facility Fee</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H2F27FAB0B125413AA9DAA6C348E9D3CB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Failure to pay the fee under subsection (a)(1) within 20 calendar days of the due date as specified in subparagraph (D) of such subsection shall result in the following:</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="HBDED9FD671E4453793C0FE4E84E521F2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Secretary shall place the facility on a publicly available arrears list.</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="H1220EC6355E34E83BFE3DC662E37976F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>All OTC monograph drugs manufactured in such a facility or containing an ingredient manufactured in such a facility shall be deemed misbranded under section 502(a).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H2E3A9030AE8C4CF5AEEBB60E30D8DDC0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Application of penalties</header><text>The penalties under this paragraph shall apply until the fee established by subsection (a)(1) is paid.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H502EE045F8D84E0AA2A058049DF562B7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Order requests</header><text>An OTC monograph order request submitted by a person subject to fees under subsection (a) shall be considered incomplete and shall not be accepted for filing by the Secretary until all fees owed by such person under this section have been paid.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9C28A089ED5A47CA9E8961CA4F930B1F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person subject to fees under this section shall be considered ineligible for OTC monograph drug meetings until all such fees owed by such person have been paid.</text>
								</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7A0CDD9FA64944059930CA1898E6EB30"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Crediting and availability of fees</header>
 <paragraph id="H9599144E161D45C2BEB3172DF27FA5E0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2)(D), fees authorized under subsection (a) shall be collected and available for obligation only to the extent and in the amount provided in advance in appropriations Acts. Such fees are authorized to remain available until expended. Such sums as may be necessary may be transferred from the Food and Drug Administration salaries and expenses appropriation account without fiscal year limitation to such appropriation account for salaries and expenses with such fiscal year limitation. The sums transferred shall be available solely for OTC monograph drug activities.</text>
								</paragraph><paragraph id="H0D99B0E8916B4B67AAFCC38B9677C783"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Collections and appropriation Acts</header>
 <subparagraph id="H24707EDC64D141AFBAD037173231BB40"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraphs (C) and (D), the fees authorized by this section shall be collected and available in each fiscal year in an amount not to exceed the amount specified in appropriation Acts, or otherwise made available for obligation, for such fiscal year.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F44AD33801C4E79B1F659DD550B0DC5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Use of fees and limitation</header><text>The fees authorized by this section shall be available to defray increases in the costs of the resources allocated for OTC monograph drug activities (including increases in such costs for an additional number of full-time equivalent positions in the Department of Health and Human Services to be engaged in such activities), only if the Secretary allocates for such purpose an amount for such fiscal year (excluding amounts from fees collected under this section) no less than $12,000,000, multiplied by the adjustment factor applicable to the fiscal year involved under subsection (c)(1).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2723865E02124243BFCAE02ECEDCC171"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Compliance</header><text>The Secretary shall be considered to have met the requirements of subparagraph (B) in any fiscal year if the costs funded by appropriations and allocated for OTC monograph drug activities are not more than 15 percent below the level specified in such subparagraph.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82F3FF016E364F75AE2B789F19BCC875"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Fee collection during first program year</header><text>Until the date of the enactment of an Act making appropriations and providing for the collection and obligation of fees under this section through September 30, 2019, for the salaries and expenses account of the Food and Drug Administration, fees authorized by this section for fiscal year 2019 may be collected and shall be credited to such account and remain available until expended.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFFEC9B0F4B6481BB6DD587A3D9546E7"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Provision for early payments in subsequent years</header><text>Payment of fees authorized under this section for a fiscal year (after fiscal year 2019), prior to the due date for such fees, may be accepted by the Secretary in accordance with authority provided in advance in a prior year appropriations Act.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E474A4D4EB942C1B168C42776E5717A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>For each of the fiscal years 2019 through 2023, there is authorized to be appropriated for fees under this section an amount equal to the total amount of fees assessed for such fiscal year under this section.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2264E2E1987E4C37A8BC253670D3B9F9"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Collection of unpaid fees</header><text>In any case where the Secretary does not receive payment of a fee assessed under subsection (a) within 30 calendar days after it is due, such fee shall be treated as a claim of the United States Government subject to subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/37">chapter 37</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5D9E72A7B777463C8EDAC325E9E746D4"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>This section may not be construed to require that the number of full-time equivalent positions in the Department of Health and Human Services, for officers, employers, and advisory committees not engaged in OTC monograph drug activities, be reduced to offset the number of officers, employees, and advisory committees so engaged.</text>
							</subsection></section><section id="HC614E53FADB34DA6B3A81A363E82B2D4"><enum>744P.</enum><header>Reauthorization; reporting requirements</header>
 <subsection id="HD9ABE5D5CD4140D494EDFB94E2990CBF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Performance report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning with fiscal year 2019, and not later than 120 calendar days after the end of each fiscal year thereafter for which fees are collected under this part, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate a report concerning the progress of the Food and Drug Administration in achieving the goals identified in the letters described in section 201(b) of the <short-title>Over-the-Counter Monograph Safety, Innovation, and Reform Act of 2018</short-title> during such fiscal year and the future plans of the Food and Drug Administration for meeting such goals.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H2E71A2F6A4854E4CB7F5C45379B548B4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Fiscal report</header><text>Not later than 120 calendar days after the end of fiscal year 2019 and each subsequent fiscal year for which fees are collected under this part, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate a report on the implementation of the authority for such fees during such fiscal year and the use, by the Food and Drug Administration, of the fees collected for such fiscal year.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HB19CE1C252F54969960FD7276E4F5C83"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The Secretary shall make the reports required under subsections (a) and (b) available to the public on the Internet website of the Food and Drug Administration.</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="H6D34D3C0FD7E48979B54D5C498EF2F1A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reauthorization</header>
 <paragraph id="HA026BFF6E9E0420596CE2A5B3DBF3432"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In developing recommendations to present to the Congress with respect to the goals described in subsection (a), and plans for meeting the goals, for OTC monograph drug activities for the first 5 fiscal years after fiscal year 2023, and for the reauthorization of this part for such fiscal years, the Secretary shall consult with—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H9B58A61CC89348E086F257B269FB6648"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E37F6DACB1C4D6D8B641E5CEE5FE604"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEEE3D05F5C634035BBEA189ECF711506"><enum>(C)</enum><text>scientific and academic experts;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H099DA62396CF4A1ABFF092AE8C2FF0E9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>health care professionals;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6BE425BB37E24E8A870EC364D24163FD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>representatives of patient and consumer advocacy groups; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5AFD1A2A68384B539617A71AE5ABEB03"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the regulated industry.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A9E2CA212714319924B8EAD5DBCCC1A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public review of recommendations</header><text>After negotiations with the regulated industry, the Secretary shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HA1996168310F4F878C578FD1E19DB4C9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>present the recommendations developed under paragraph (1) to the congressional committees specified in such paragraph;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C9AB45859AC4382B76879AD9700530E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>publish such recommendations in the Federal Register;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74D03C748A2C4D1294A0EB413B149174"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide for a period of 30 calendar days for the public to provide written comments on such recommendations;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D18D466A5CC484FBCBA4497F32D71AD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>hold a meeting at which the public may present its views on such recommendations; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H071182F9723144FB9337EC63F4827386"><enum>(E)</enum><text>after consideration of such public views and comments, revise such recommendations as necessary.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H721AEBB912D94AE8AA1F1A8829F1CEDA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Transmittal of recommendations</header><text>Not later than January 15, 2023, the Secretary shall transmit to the Congress the revised recommendations under paragraph (2), a summary of the views and comments received under such paragraph, and any changes made to the recommendations in response to such views and comments.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</section></title></legis-body></bill>


