<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HAFCC246F3A3D4947A928E06854F73B2B" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5761 IH: Ending Maternal Mortality Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5761</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180510">May 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="H001056">Ms. Herrera Beutler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000577">Mr. Ryan of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000580">Ms. Michelle Lujan Grisham of New Mexico</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000324">Mr. Hastings</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001050">Ms. Hanabusa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services to submit to the Congress on a biennial basis
			 a national plan to reduce the rate of maternal mortality.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H79FE84730BD14FCDA1FA3B48FFD1E159" style="OLC">
 <section id="HA1088D26EECC4E4282E84EB4EB653112" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ending Maternal Mortality Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H75BD7E77C2D543CA8AB0B07B8A8B5E01"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds as follows:</text>
 <paragraph id="H7BD067DB19594B488452F8E2C27F3289"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Four million American women give birth each year, and an estimated 700 will die annually during pregnancy, childbirth, or the postpartum period.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H476CB3A7D16A4D4FB1814A1E71F544F1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United States ranks 47th for maternal mortality rate globally, and is one of only eight countries in which the maternal mortality rate is rising. It is estimated that, between 2000 and 2014, the United States maternal mortality rate grew by 26.6 percent.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF28ADCE40A6246B8A5C4DB4124F4CC4B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Common causes of maternal mortality include obstetric hemorrhage, hypertension and preeclampsia, sepsis, and substance use disorder and overdose.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA59A31DF187C4A788658195152393A28"><enum>(4)</enum><text>More than half of maternal deaths are likely preventable.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HECC6837903BF42F2BA0B94867DF8184B"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Additionally, 65,000 American women experience severe maternal morbidity (SMM) annually, meaning the physical and psychological conditions that result from, or are aggravated by, pregnancy have an adverse effect on the health of a woman.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H65F9E3FE199548879D88BEEDF02B7459"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Racial and ethnic disparities persist across the Nation, and Black women are three to four times more likely to die from complications of pregnancy or childbirth than White women.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H98AD598F548746788DA928FE492AD299"><enum>3.</enum><header>Plan for reducing maternal mortality</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Public Health Service Act is amended by inserting after section 229 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/237a">42 U.S.C. 237a</external-xref>) the following new section:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H147ABDD161DF443E849E9A3DA2C8E9C4" style="OLC">
				<section id="HBAA28417BF0046778B394A8167F272C9"><enum>229A.</enum><header>Plan for reducing maternal mortality</header>
 <subsection id="H4629532DE99E4F57A6884D36F4C7A282"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Ending Maternal Mortality Act of 2018</short-title>, and biennially thereafter, the Secretary shall develop and submit to the Congress a national plan to reduce the rate of preventable maternal mortality, with the goals of—</text>
 <paragraph id="H2E0A1FDF03244E84A4F19B1F0763469B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>cutting the rate in half over the 10 years following such date of enactment; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H7EDAE3EC79F94D9DBE88A2517DFBD007"><enum>(2)</enum><text>eliminating preventable maternal deaths by the date that is 20 years after such date of enactment.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H84D8C27D31E94635822475926920A006"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Objectives; strategy</header><text>In each biennial plan under subsection (a), the Secretary shall include—</text> <paragraph id="H233526F36FFB4B72836C69E030561D8B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a list of objectives for meeting the goals described in subsection (a); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2279572415DC4738A7CC3A1274E78F6E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a strategy for implementing the plan across the agencies and offices of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1E725EB0DD3F4D1A9AC37749BDCD0BDD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Specific issues</header><text>In each biennial plan under subsection (a), the Secretary shall address the following:</text> <paragraph id="H0A9DA7E88B02425AACCC0F0C60009183"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Increasing public understanding of maternal mortality and severe maternal morbidity, including risk factors, warning signs, and prevention of common causes like hemorrhage, preeclampsia, and substance use disorders and other mental health conditions.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H06981EB6E3CE4D698389CE20A19DA86C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Improving understanding of the root causes of maternal mortality and severe maternal morbidity, including both medical and socioeconomic factors.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8FC919CD66384BABAA64ACAD6BFAE3FB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Improving data collection, including State-level reporting.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H556C366931254F8DA908CC4697B30EEB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Identifying at-risk populations and eliminating disparities that persist based on a mother’s race, ethnicity, socioeconomic status, and geographic location.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAE7F06664C414055B651676445ACDDF7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Supporting and expanding maternal mortality review committees that bring together public and private relevant stakeholders to review cases of pregnancy-related and pregnancy-associated complications and deaths to make recommendations to improve the quality of care and outcomes.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB34218A29DBB47DBAC2981186EB0C44D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Assessing hospital culture of safety in maternity care and how best to provide resources to improve outcomes.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H579CAF0727BD4CD28C92575F9B28BB1F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Improving health and treatment services for expectant mothers struggling with substance use and mental health disorders.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1E5A11DDCC6448FFB87C94DE679EECE5"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Studying and supporting local and targeted responses to maternal death.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H2999B7A7BFA643FD92949DF2DF1DF4C5"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identifying Federal programs and activities to reduce maternal mortality and making recommendations for improving the effectiveness and coordination of such programs and activities.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAA0A8F32DEB74A33A524B00DD53912E3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Public posting</header><text>The Secretary shall make each plan submitted to the Congress under this section publicly accessible on the website of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HCA09650E61BB4714A36431133DB2C2FA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing each biennial plan under this section, the Secretary shall solicit input from organizations representing patients, health care providers, hospitals, other treatment facilities, public health departments and practitioners, and other entities, as appropriate.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H13C38EC54B7E4E3B9A5A6AB5B16F6416"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H0C3182FB20B74E9FAFFAB6FB931AD42F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>maternal mortality</term> refers to maternal deaths that occur during, or within the 12 months following, pregnancy.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2C297F609B4442E983971E0DD5171A08"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>maternal morbidity</term> refers to pregnancy-related and pregnancy-associated complications that do not result in maternal death.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H857A76C5C74A463F8AD47DC354666D65"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>severe maternal morbidity</term> includes unexpected outcomes of labor and delivery that result in significant short- or long-term consequences to a woman’s health.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


