<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H8D4322810AC640D7B7120AE8500BB397" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5816 IH: Postal Banking Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5816</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180515">May 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 39, United States Code, to provide that the United States Postal Service may provide
			 certain basic financial services, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H759EECAA5DAD4C84AD7F7EBEB490FD37" style="OLC">
 <section id="H650297B142124033B2904471402407D1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Postal Banking Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H5D5AA2383709450BAC4A903DE9F22082" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authority for the Postal Service to offer certain financial services</header> <subsection id="H0CD5E3B3172D4BEBB50F000CD07250A7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 404 of title 39, United States Code, is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H6E3FFEC3ABCD4AF8A8E0A497D7E2489F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="H482CF542B8854CAD8B1898B376A2EF30"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (7), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H927C799D65A6403D8F95B3D54E2AF8B9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (8), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E9A34CF0EDC416EA1268FC6E66E35D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE7C3B3F07C7F494FB790BE16311DE01C" style="USC">
 <paragraph id="H5649F66E0E98410090356BF9F3CC1A48"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide basic financial services, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H2521CE430B2741C8A2C11FDB069E8030"><enum>(A)</enum><text>low-cost, small-dollar loans, not to exceed $500 at a time, or $1,000 from 1 year of the issuance of the initial loan, as adjusted annually by the Postmaster General to reflect any change in the Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers of the Department of Labor;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H827A6FAAD02548648AE2E37139B3C629"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">alone, or in partnership with depository institutions, as defined in section 3 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813</external-xref>), and Federal credit unions, as defined in section 101 of the of the Federal Credit Union Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1752">12 U.S.C. 1752</external-xref>), small checking accounts and interest-bearing savings accounts, not to exceed the greater of—</text>
 <clause id="HE9601F6F2C894846A45DF1664B342C82"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$20,000 per account; and</text> </clause><clause id="HA9832231DC4B4A1B8AFE9154842612A4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>25 percent of the median account balance reported in the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation’s quarterly Consolidated Reports of Condition and Income;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F06937315E84E66AA89B1D46A1B2728"><enum>(C)</enum><text>transactional services, including debit cards, automated teller machines, online checking accounts, check-cashing services, automatic bill-pay, mobile banking, or other products that allows users to engage in the financial services described in this paragraph;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DC9CB481CC64F5EAEE95FC3D36AFD89"><enum>(D)</enum><text>remittance services, including the receiving and sending of money to domestic or foreign recipients; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC5BBE4C41DD46228BC100F28BFC9D91"><enum>(E)</enum><text>such other basic financial services as the Postal Service determines appropriate in the public interest;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H232FAD291AF34E54BCFF02EAAF3FD96C"><enum>(10)</enum><text>to set interest rates and fees for the financial instruments and products provided by the Postal Service that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H76DD177DA5804DAD99781F00872AFA95"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensures that the customer access to the products and the public interest is given significant consideration;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3359C69DCEBA481E9529C117742EFB45"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensures that interest rates on savings accounts are at least 100 percent of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation’s weekly national rate on non-jumbo savings accounts; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H98BEF8221E0D4C9684461477646080B4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ensures that the total interest rates on small-dollar loan amounts—</text> <clause id="HF29D71E97FBA4B1DB98894D65F95EC59"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are inclusive of interest, fees, charges, and ancillary products and services; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1AE2E2A74DE8484BA6A1A60E4D57B1A7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>do not exceed 101 percent of the Treasury 1 month constant maturity rate; and</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H681D59BF12E246A68A45FE42445E46DB"><enum>(11)</enum><text>allow capitalization of an amount deemed necessary by the Postmaster General that serve the purpose of this section, through an account separate from products not included or allowed in this section, for the purposes of enacting the provisions of this section.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3455099A36A845969A5D92FCAFD3A84E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H014223BEAA9345E2B06858DF11CE9F74" style="OLC"> <subsection id="HF2C96C6A575E4F0FA02321787E64FA1E"><enum>(f)</enum><text>Any net profits from services provided under this section that are not greater than the amount of initial capitalization—</text>
 <paragraph id="H847C5B9746074434B8DB54E5C9A6D783"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall be reported separately from mail service and delivery;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HD23B7E19360F4ECF96EAD4A691536A59"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of any amount appropriated, shall be returned to the general fund of the Treasury not later than 9 years after the date of enactment of this subsection; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4CBDA83D4D634E4C82826B3F11082C2D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>may be repaid to the offering organization or organizations if the Postmaster General determines that the services provided in this subsection are not reduced as a result.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H803B68DCBE2A4EF282CB9C5F28E3FA12"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No bank charter</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States Postal Service shall not be granted a bank charter, become an insured depository institution, as defined in section 3 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813</external-xref>), or engage in traditional banking activities such as lending, other than those activities permitted under section 404 of title 39, United States Code, as amended by this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H443D37E85EDB4430B3EB678C11B0DBBF"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">UCC</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States Postal Service shall be subject to the provisions of article 4 of the Uniform Commercial Code.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBF7735B8AF374B3BAC7BF697B220105D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Postmaster General, in consultation with the Secretary of the Treasury, the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, and the Federal banking agencies, shall promulgate regulations carrying out this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF4F2A3DEED704C9C83A3AB72D930887E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text>Section 404(e)(2) of title 39, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>The preceding sentence shall not apply to any financial service offered by the Postal Service under subsection (a)(9).</quote>.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H08E8F7F39B874D229B46E87BC585B031"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>The services offered by the United States Postal Service under section 404 of title 39, United States Code—</text>
 <paragraph id="H9821C29699E4413580ADE8C75234AF20"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall be considered permissible non-banking activities in accordance with section 225.28 of title 12, Code of Federal Regulations; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4351896569434DBC815B0558AA4CDDB9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall not be considered the business of banking under the seventh paragraph of section 5136 of the Revised Statutes (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/24">12 U.S.C. 24</external-xref>).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


