<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HE39D6D456D3C4BFAA9705C7739414D6A" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5343 IH: Prescription Transparency Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5343</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180320">March 20, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000800">Mr. Welch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000568">Mr. Griffith</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001189">Mr. Austin Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001093">Mr. Collins of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. McMorris Rodgers</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to nullify certain contractual provisions prohibiting or
			 penalizing a pharmacist’s disclosure of the availability of
			 therapeutically equivalent alternative drugs, or alternative methods of
			 purchasing the prescription drug, that are less expensive, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H5CAFF5182DE64AB887492A4048875C1D" style="OLC">
 <section id="H10EF32F2F8BC4DCEB85A3CED54A8D7C1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Prescription Transparency Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H1074A2114347484DBFBA299F8F37E190"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibited gag provisions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part B of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/243">42 U.S.C. 243</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDF35BB3945C64070B0E496752F7B9938" style="OLC">
				<section id="HEB580C72AA3346F89459ABEE6F050E8B"><enum>320B.</enum><header>Prohibited gag provisions</header>
 <subsection id="HF8DBD21F05C04CC2898DAD65D8ADF79D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No contract that is between—</text> <paragraph id="H798BEC34ECD344FBA4BA03174F74B960"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a health insurer or any entity that provides pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a health insurer (commonly referred to as a <quote>pharmacy benefit manager</quote>); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDDDC67C982054BC7977C33A2EB776A51"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a pharmacy, pharmacist, or a pharmacy's contracting agent, such as a pharmacy services administrative organization,</text>
						</paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">may contain a provision prohibiting or penalizing (including through increased utilization review,
			 reduced payments, or other financial disincentives) a pharmacist’s
			 disclosure to an individual purchasing a prescription drug of information
			 regarding the cost of the prescription drug to the individual (including
			 any copayment or coinsurance), or regarding the availability of any
			 therapeutically equivalent alternative drug, or alternative methods of
			 purchasing the prescription drug (including paying a cash price), that are
 less expensive than the cost of the prescription drug to the individual.</continuation-text></subsection><subsection id="H6B7DE424857D422CAA9AB75F7DC2930F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Null and void</header><text>Any provision described in subsection (a) in a contract described in subsection (a) is null and void.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H62CC4337783140E48B2E106F2EA0FA82"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (a) applies only with respect to contracts, and contract addenda, entered into or renewed on or after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Prescription Transparency Act of 2018</short-title>.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H863596EE26B64C519BF0610878EE59A2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Regulations and guidance</header><text>The Secretary may issue such regulations and guidance as may be necessary for implementation of this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HC798CC87E8994EE8B2F45C0A00CE229C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H41B5BA351E2047A28FA398ED28C05B8E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>drug</term> has the meaning given to such term in section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5F50D77CED3746CB991D51596390873B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>health insurer</term> means a health insurance issuer (as defined in section 2791) offering health insurance coverage (as defined in such section) in the individual or group market or a sponsor of a group health plan (as defined in such section).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H60DE0305B1D14AA282B63FB31B68BDEA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>prescription drug</term> means a drug subject to section 503(b)(1) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section></legis-body></bill> 

