<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HF821FB93484B438CA20FE84C2939041B" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5501 IH: End Corruption in the Northern Triangle Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5501</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180412">April 12, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of State to take certain actions to end corruption in the Northern Triangle
			 region of Central America, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H8BA592BA4D6844C3BBDD77B8D7FE1B73" style="OLC">
 <section id="HE33202CB74654B83B62F183319DD5845" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>End Corruption in the Northern Triangle Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H7787618E2F534A0088F45F58B3AD206A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
 <paragraph id="H842CE52403A94E4CAAB0018F7762F5BC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H4DBC91B89F184E099B2A6C5E630C24BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D12CC55E2EF44B79D4956A9E39611F7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8037E8A5801E43E18D08C734C57E5EF6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grand corruption</header><text>The term <term>grand corruption</term> means public corruption committed at a high level of government that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE1851DDC2A6F4E7B86A66C246D297213"><enum>(A)</enum><text>distorts policies or the central functioning of the country; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE37C2E1D6801453F92E2FF00478A3AA1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enables leaders to benefit at the expense of the public good.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FD38D551A5B4D978087C951DA77E72F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Northern triangle</header><text>The term <term>Northern Triangle</term> means the region of Central America that encompasses the countries of Guatemala, Honduras, and El Salvador.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H17DAECF9A4834F16BE5C046D2E3C386B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Northern triangle countries</header><text>The term <term>Northern Triangle countries</term> means the countries of Guatemala, Honduras, and El Salvador.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="H434FB7A9D57C4D33A9DACBBC5D7F3B81" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H4F09635B5C384FCA8A62C6E692E876A0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>According to the February 9, 2017, Presidential Executive order on <quote>Enforcing Federal Law with Respect to Transnational Criminal Organizations and Preventing International Trafficking</quote>, transnational criminal organizations <quote>are drivers of crime, corruption, violence, and misery</quote>, and <quote>a comprehensive and decisive approach is required to dismantle these organized crime syndicates and restore safety for the American people.</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3603D61034384BAC8BFD3F0CEFD7A668"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Since 2008, the United States has provided more than $1 billion through the Central America Regional Security Initiative in order to address violence, organized crime, and narcotics trafficking and in Central America.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H92A96B31115547E3AF1B8DE3FA071F60"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The 2017 International Narcotics Control Strategy Report stated that <quote>corruption within the Salvadoran political system remains a serious problem</quote>.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE9500B63F8074EB6ACE69AEDFF464F93"><enum>(4)</enum><text>According to the same report, in Guatemala <quote>widespread corruption permeates public and private institutions and exacerbates the country’s security, governmental, and economic challenges</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE1D67E9D275C446DB14110DAB16C365A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The same report notes that in Honduras, corruption has undermined progress on disrupting and degrading illegal trafficking, because <quote>trafficking organizations have infiltrated some military units in active drug corridors</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H54CCD014DBAB4331B09183828DFC3D2B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text> <paragraph id="H0E9CEAFE8E2A47569BFF1B14FFA0A17C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>systemic corruption constitutes a significant threat to the long-term prospects for democratic governance, prosperity, and security in the Northern Triangle, and is an impediment to United States efforts to reduce the flow of cocaine and other narcotics from South America to the United States;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H07133DA829EF43A1AD9E461340123A3F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the International Commission against Impunity in Guatemala and the Mission to Support the Fight against Corruption and Impunity in Honduras have made important contributions to the fight against corruption in Guatemala and Honduras, respectively; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC207412770CC492791525FD11CA62BC8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the lack of an international commission against impunity in El Salvador is a limiting factor in efforts to combat corruption in that country.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H1CC49A953C224F92BF6BFE020A7642F7"><enum>5.</enum><header>Anti-corruption strategy</header>
 <subsection id="H32F78384C8964427AB79F05E3D439051"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a strategy to enhance United States efforts to dismantle systemic corruption in the Northern Triangle.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HECBBE06EC75F4985B6A7DD7E0EF6B605"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The strategy shall include the following elements:</text> <paragraph id="H3A4CCDB4BA7547F094482F6AB3F166AB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Diplomatic and financial support for international commissions against impunity.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA4204728543D421288231C8BEF9D6252"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Enhanced cooperation with local prosecutors, investigative units within national and local police forces, and revenue and customs authorities of each Northern Triangle country.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD97F064DEA274FB785C11278DEE885FE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Exchange of information relevant to ongoing criminal investigations, where possible, with local prosecutors and the international commissions against impunity.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H0D785A7D41FC4F11A6C9692183688E98"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The designations of individuals within the Northern Triangle that meet the requirements for designations under—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HA4192F9EAE68415DBB4A6084FD884ED4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Foreign Narcotics Kingpin Designation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/1901">21 U.S.C. 1901</external-xref> et seq.);</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E30E69794C24A3FBB199B3B6BD20AE2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 212(a)(2)(C) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)(2)(C)</external-xref>); or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF67BAC9F1E5D4008A79206B40F8656A3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Global Magnitsky Human Rights Accountability Act (subtitle F of title XII of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/328">Public Law 114–328</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2656">22 U.S.C. 2656</external-xref> note).</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA8D4C6C7DF084D34AC79A561034D01D9"><enum>6.</enum><header>Report on corruption and narcotics trafficking</header>
 <subsection id="HD6CF8C546DA54948A9CEEC8464EE52D6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, in consultation with the intelligence community (as such term is defined in section 3(4) of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003(4)</external-xref>), shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report regarding corruption and illicit campaign finance in the Northern Triangle.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H3A74466AC3A34F4E993F81CB3DE3BA40"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text>The report required under subsection (a) shall include—</text> <paragraph id="HFE5971807631448294E97B80BA5115CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the names of senior government officials in any of the Northern Triangle countries who are known to have committed or facilitated acts of grand corruption or narcotics trafficking;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC15424C1C71F4004A321F5E72EACE534"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the names of elected officials in any of the Northern Triangle countries who are known to have received campaign funds that are the proceeds of narco-trafficking or other illicit activities in the last 2 years; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H58F1ED5AEFE34F73912405C2ADC1D4FF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the names of individuals who are known to have facilitated the financing of political campaigns in any of the Northern Triangle countries with the proceeds of narco-trafficking or other illicit activities in the last 2 years.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5DEA362B5FE04B829906B53C0686D166"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report submitted under subsection (a) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H484A963374EA44C18B5BE2216280E323"><enum>7.</enum><header>Central America Regional Security Initiative</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall make available on the website of the Department of State the total amounts of assistance under the Central America Regional Security Initiative that have been provided to each country within Central America since fiscal year 2008.</text>
		</section></legis-body>
</bill>


