<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB84D4723F93C4B9AB0D1AEBE2D13BE4F" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5513 IH: Big Bear Land Exchange Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5513</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180413">April 13, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001094">Mr. Cook</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for an exchange of lands with San Bernardino County, California, to enhance management
			 of lands within the San Bernardino National Forest, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H16F8670420204986AF2F1E51B78B375B" style="OLC">
 <section id="HF30A060AE3144EDC89BBB2BA3DC91E25" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Big Bear Land Exchange Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H844B0656E31B4168A8334B3B4601539E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
 <paragraph id="HF440CA8693874F3097A87968451118B9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>County</header><text>The term <term>County</term> means the County of San Bernardino, California.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H996C00EB81A9406D814F0316C9BF1A6B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal land</header><text>The term <term>Federal land</term> means the approximately 73 acres of Federal land administered by the Forest Service generally depicted as <quote>Federal Land</quote> on the Map.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H05FF30E6E66641789762EA916CB4F115"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Non-Federal land</header><text>The term <term>non-Federal land</term> means the approximately 71 acres owned by the County generally depicted as <quote>Non-Federal Land</quote> on the Map.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H285AB692BC16412192FAFB16D62E00BA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Agriculture.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE8108D0CF63649B5B49D8CBED2CE7E2C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Map</header><text>The term <term>Map</term> means the map titled <quote>Big Bear Land Exchange</quote> and dated August 10, 2017.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="H8BF26212A0814AEEAD51A15A03EF66C8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Exchange of land; equalization of value</header> <subsection id="H7C29C21731AA4AD486A70B928F1784EB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Exchange authorized</header><text>Notwithstanding the land use planning requirements of sections 202, 210, and 211 of the Federal Land Policy and Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1712">43 U.S.C. 1712</external-xref>, 1720–21), subject to valid existing rights, and conditioned upon any equalization payment necessary under section 206(b) of the Federal Land Policy and Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1716">43 U.S.C. 1716(b)</external-xref>), and subsection (b) of this Act, as soon as practicable, but not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, if the County offers to convey the non-Federal land to the United States, the Secretary shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE5E5F2C735BD4A45AE1ACE4912E5D963"><enum>(1)</enum><text>convey to the County all right, title, and interest of the United States in and to the Federal land; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H20B3436F58B843F5B32EC18597E3CEC2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>accept from the County a conveyance of all right, title, and interest of the County in and to the non-Federal land.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD78C863E239A41FBAC8399F068FA54B2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Equal value and cash equalization</header>
 <paragraph id="H41AC7F235FB54C13A39B6146D1387179"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Equal value exchange</header><text>The land exchange under this section shall be for equal value, or the values shall be equalized by a cash payment as provided for under this subsection.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HEB7EF6C5EDD64DF2B6ED902EA31B49F9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cash equalization payment</header><text>The County or the Secretary, as appropriate, may equalize the values of the lands to be exchanged under this section by cash payment without regard to any statutory limit on the amount of such a cash equalization payment.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE352704520F44B359AA8087F1181CB49"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Deposit and use of funds received from county</header><text>Any cash equalization payment received by the Secretary under this subsection shall be deposited in the fund established under <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/90/171">Public Law 90–171</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/484a">16 U.S.C. 484a</external-xref>; commonly known as the Sisk Act). The funds so deposited shall remain available to the Secretary, until expended, for the acquisition of lands, waters, and interests in land for the San Bernardino National Forest.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H26269B1207E34AE0969DEB414F7A7EE1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Source of funds for payment by Secretary</header><text>If the Secretary will make a cash equalization payment to the County under this subsection, the Secretary may use funds available from the Land and Water Conservation Fund, the Act of June 15, 1938 (Chapter 438; 52 Stat. 699, commonly known as the Receipts Act of 1938), or capital improvement funds.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2CC65F24F3B7497D85E201ACB60A3AD1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appraisals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The value of the land to be exchanged under this Act shall be determined by appraisals conducted—</text> <paragraph id="H1F5403C693F24BCFB828831362434F68"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by one or more independent and qualified appraisers; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H937ECB2F33814BE8AD2B159B04D969B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in accordance with nationally recognized appraisal standards, including, as appropriate, the Uniform Appraisal Standards for Federal Land Acquisitions and the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8E7B9687CCBE487B964445333CCD7A12"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Title approval</header><text>Title to the land to be exchanged under this Act shall be in a format acceptable to the Secretary and the County.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HEAAFE362E29C43598D9B51A5AEB2A815"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Survey of non-Federal lands</header><text>Before completing the exchange under this Act, the Secretary shall inspect the non-Federal lands to ensure that the land meets Federal standards, including hazardous materials and land line surveys.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H6514BD113B634A0AB7DE65984E5B4786"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Costs of conveyance</header><text>As a condition of conveyance, any costs related to the exchange under this section shall be paid by the County.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HB2B8C8FA4CE64291AF143ADDC6C5A719"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Management of acquired lands</header><text>The Secretary shall manage the non-Federal land acquired under this section in accordance with the Act of March 1, 1911 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/480">16 U.S.C. 480</external-xref> et seq.; commonly known as the Weeks Act), and other laws and regulations pertaining to National Forest System lands.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H594EDFD2A2FA4DC083A11070A98E22A2"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Pacific Crest National Scenic Trail relocation</header><text>Before completing the land exchange under this section, the Secretary shall relocate the portion of the Pacific Crest National Scenic Trail located on the Federal land to adjacent National Forest System land. The trail relocation shall be conducted without further environmental analysis.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H40CD78EF87E54613BF578F56389EA13F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Map and legal descriptions</header><text>As soon as practicable after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall finalize a map and legal descriptions of all land to be conveyed under this Act. The Secretary may correct any minor errors in the map or in the legal descriptions. The map and legal descriptions shall be on file and available for public inspection in appropriate offices of the Forest Service.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


