<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HE5D7AA2A68F649778AB510D81109E963" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5876 IH: Border Wall Trust Fund Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5876</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180518">May 18, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001273">Mrs. Black</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To allow the Secretary of the Treasury to accept public donations to fund the construction of a
			 barrier on the border between the United States and Mexico, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H12E57B5478A348828AB57C9097761D2E" style="OLC">
 <section id="H91FEB649878B45B2B6F3C27F0FEF1CC9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Border Wall Trust Fund Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H4DD5FA4090B640FF85826AB9C9FC9C34"><enum>2.</enum><header>Border wall trust fund</header> <subsection id="H4D88EA199C4A480AAACF884B069D9FC8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Border wall trust fund</header><text>At the end of subchapter III of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code, insert the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF111315462EE4A51B1A294B08740FA1D" style="USC">
					<section id="HD7657DF1E3274C39BFF92BD6E4D4BA92"><enum>3344.</enum><header>Border wall trust fund.</header>
						<subsection id="H1F7B4D28640D4491909970A6730C3216"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header>
 <paragraph id="H819509F3F1FD41F69FA48F5CCB179629"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Receive gifts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 3113 of title 31, the Secretary of the Treasury may accept for the Government a gift of money on the condition that it be used to plan, design, construct, or maintain a barrier along the international border between the United States and Mexico.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H417597D626FA4AAA8204115026A0774A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Trust fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary of the Treasury shall—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H811E8424AC5D411C80D89ECF76211249"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish an account, to be known as the <quote>Border Wall Trust Fund</quote>, into which money received as gifts under this section shall be deposited; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEF91D7E63E7E463BA2007E6E97EA5ADE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>create a publicly accessible website to receive such gifts.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DFDF97270084A9D87E0C977969F94AB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Appropriation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Money deposited in the Border Wall Trust Fund is appropriated to the Secretary of Homeland Security and may be expended to plan, design, construct, or maintain a barrier along the international border between the United States and Mexico. Such funds may not be used for any other purpose.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HEC0D308AEB794A31A9424C56D43FFD78"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents for such chapter is amended by inserting at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1AF92D4D3FA448319EF9CA4F70A4FC73" style="OLC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">3344. Border Wall Trust Fund.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection></section><section id="HF5BE6F39EB534606B708B76C68AEFC5F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Commemorative display</header> <subsection id="H6F75EE08FD2841B98E22969161CECB09"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall, at a time determined by the Secretary and in a manner consistent with the security mission of the border barrier, provide for a commemorative display as an integrated part of the barrier under section 3344 of such title, as enacted by section 2, recognizing individuals who contributed to the Border Wall Trust Fund.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H6EEF3E23F9024FD6B6016A3B7AD0C57D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Length</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The display described in subsection (a) shall be one mile in length, unless the Secretary determines that length to be impracticable, in which case it shall be as close to that length as the Secretary determines practicable consistent with the security mission of such barrier.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA01F9C3883BF48F382DA2BD97930F87A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Designation of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall provide a process by which a donor may designate the donation of that donor to fund construction of the commemorative display under this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H2822E3EFE47142C78C23BCA9CED70EF5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Notification to the public</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall display on the website described in section 3344(a)(2) of such title, as enacted by section 2, the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HD66C23787DB74FEEB87355633CA1C448"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A total estimated cost for the commemorative display.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H50734917DE7B4D5B98B4E1D2BA6412B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A notification that donations to the Border Wall Trust Fund not designated under subsection (c) will be used exclusively to plan, design, construct, or maintain a barrier along the international border between the United States and Mexico.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


