<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HF3234773F4E24BE697346581711DCE21" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5134 IH: STOP Straw Purchases Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5134</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180301">March 1, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to combat straw purchases of firearms.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HBF627BDE414D42269BCB8338E12FEF4A" style="OLC">
 <section id="H3D076149DFF74E1783B9B1DBD5FBA61E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>STOP Straw Purchases Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HD9D599D9AB584455AEDFFEDB43633D3D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Increase in penalties for straw purchasers of firearms</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 924(a)(2) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>, except that in the case of a violation of section 922(a)(6) involving deception as to the identity of the actual transferee of a firearm, the violator shall be fined not more than $750,000, imprisoned not more than 25 years, or both</quote> before the period.</text>
		</section><section id="H8EBFAEC4F3404808B5EDD6FBB32ADE9F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on continuing criminal enterprise involving straw purchases of firearms; prohibition on
			 obtaining firearm by inducing straw purchase</header>
 <subsection id="H937BC3B94F994F799D1B7D32C6443488"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 922 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCF24247D3554419A907285F74204FE53" style="OLC"> <subsection id="HFB53725797914A9E9C735821F61B614B"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>It shall be unlawful for any person, in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce, to—</text>
 <paragraph id="H833645FF7AC34AAD9B4BFEA1555B7EDB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>induce, or act in concert with, another person to engage in a continuing series of violations of subsection (a)(6) involving deception as to the identity of the actual transferee of a firearm, from which such person obtains substantial income or resources; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAEA3488BA9484B44B5D152B8D9768AB6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with respect to such other person, occupy a position of organizer, a supervisory position, or any other position of management.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H41EB0B8FE30649BBB93AB5E8FA445FA6"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful for any person, in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce, to obtain a firearm by inducing another person to violate subsection (a)(6) by falsely claiming to be the actual transferee of the firearm.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD10F0A2FF6F748DF85696BB30B167FA7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>Section 924(a) of such title is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H329D9808748849E0A54ABEB430E3580A" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HDC3DF8BA05D64524A5FCB1940C1C397B" indent="up1"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whoever knowingly violates section 922(aa) shall be fined not more than $1,000,000, imprisoned not more than 30 years, or both.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD24C316C30884EDFAD3684786A87FA62" indent="up1"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whoever knowingly violates section 922(bb) shall be fined not more than $750,000, imprisoned not more than 25 years, or both.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section><section id="H4BB1A4D6B0EC4E15AA92161509C60219"><enum>4.</enum><header>Inclusion in firearms transaction record form of outline of penalties for the straw purchase of a
 firearm</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Director of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives shall ensure that the Firearms Transaction Record form used by the Bureau includes a statement outlining the penalties for acting as the straw purchaser of a firearm. For purposes of this section, a person acts as the straw purchaser of a firearm if the person violates section 922(a)(6) of title 18, United States Code, through deception as to the identity of the actual transferee of the firearm.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


