<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H205ED7224BDE4B8E8DB6E2A2533F94C6" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5301 IH: To amend title 38, United States Code, to prohibit the Secretary of Veterans Affairs from requiring a surviving spouse of a veteran to return certain payments for a month in which the veteran dies.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5301</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180315">March 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000191">Mr. DeFazio</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="J000255">Mr. Jones</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000463">Mr. Turner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001170">Ms. Shea-Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001053">Mr. Cole</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000258">Mr. Peterson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000588">Mr. Pearce</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000571">Ms. Gabbard</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000608">Ms. Rosen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000293">Ms. Esty of Connecticut</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000470">Mr. Tipton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001069">Mr. Courtney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000379">Mr. Kennedy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001037">Mr. Capuano</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000591">Mrs. Roby</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to prohibit the Secretary of Veterans Affairs from requiring
			 a surviving spouse of a veteran to return certain payments for a month in
			 which the veteran dies.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H7AA86BDE02D24CDABC9FC3A647760A43" style="OLC">
		<section id="H2F33750C025F438EB4A56EB2965EEC2E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Prohibition on requirement for surviving spouse to return certain payments by Secretary of Veterans
			 Affairs</header>
 <subsection id="HB99B82DA6AEB4C8088394CC4EF4E8203"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Surviving spouse payment</header><text>Section 5310 of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H3B8F73EA1A0E4B62AA36F2E03151EA4F" style="USC">
 <subsection id="HB6595FD56EB14001AF44527F1458BA11"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Treatment of certain checks and payments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a surviving spouse who was a dependent with respect to whom additional compensation for dependents was payable under section 1115 of this title, or additional pension as a married veteran under chapter 15, as of the date of the veteran’s death, if a check or other payment issued to the veteran as a benefit payment under either such chapter for the month in which death occurs is negotiated, deposited, or otherwise accessed by the surviving spouse—</text>
 <paragraph id="H21B579E3E7E647F6B836F19C3F43279A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the check or payment shall be considered to be the benefit payable to the surviving spouse under subsection (a)(1), to the extent that the check or payment equals the amount which would otherwise be payable under such subsection; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H38B85C5BABAD44B79DF0BC09D4DD00C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary may not require the surviving spouse to return the check or payment.</text> </paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection><subsection id="H504F92A42CE84486875361E77DA44459"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act and shall apply with respect to deaths that occur on or after that date.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


