<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HFA7AC3B43EF44716AE915D259BB38196" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4761 IH: Compact Impact Relief Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4761</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180110">January 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001245">Ms. Bordallo</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="H001050">Ms. Hanabusa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000571">Ms. Gabbard</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001177">Mr. Sablan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To address the challenges of providing public services to citizens of the Freely Associated States
			 residing in the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H7CC210027D374BE7A3515CB6E25A42F2" style="OLC">
		<section id="HDA1E777558B744A980BB4D72D135301C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header>
 <subsection id="H2054F7BFEAAA4EDAAD690881DAAEA6BB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Compact Impact Relief Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H1098BF401E2B472E8D6CF59F7EC4FD6F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
				<toc container-level="legis-body-container" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration">
					<toc-entry idref="HDA1E777558B744A980BB4D72D135301C" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HBC61CA925897470CA599CC5E9EBB60DF" level="section">Sec. 2. FMAP adjustment for affected jurisdictions equivalent to Compact migrant expenditures.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H292B328F72CF412B90EACE36DB176FC7" level="section">Sec. 3. Payments relating to elementary and secondary education of citizens of Freely Associated
			 States.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H9E7A0B773AA04065B9064DBA5052F888" level="section">Sec. 4. Expansion of national service programs.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H6BD4575C4927427DB708AE155AA3D68E" level="section">Sec. 5. Independent study and assessment of Compacts of Free Association.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H615089EE5B704B1E9FA51B388FE4BCB7" level="section">Sec. 6. Census enumeration of Compact migrants in affected jurisdictions.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HB412B976627B401D9EB59A224E60F252" level="section">Sec. 7. Bureau of economic analysis data regarding affected jurisdictions and Freely Associated
			 States.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HA684C5442B7B4C0A82A626B16C56F905" level="section">Sec. 8. Native Hawaiian, other Pacific Islander, and Insular Areas health data.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H8FE03CF531BA4F5587B537554D218AF8" level="section">Sec. 9. Local matching requirements for territories and affected jurisdictions.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HCB85541539864CF3AB57FF41ABA481E5" level="section">Sec. 10. Local expenditures qualifying as in-kind contributions.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H3E3B2B37DE3044989CDDFA63A1459288" level="section">Sec. 11. Eligibility for Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act programs.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H9436A38A4C9640E6A8332CCD9A0803D9" level="section">Sec. 12. Amendments to Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act.</toc-entry>
				</toc>
			</subsection></section><section id="HBC61CA925897470CA599CC5E9EBB60DF" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>FMAP adjustment for affected jurisdictions equivalent to Compact migrant expenditures</header>
 <subsection id="H27133DD768C34B1486B66F74A5D6A258"><enum> (a)</enum><header>Payment of increased FMAP</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For calendar quarters beginning on or after January 1 of the first year beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall increase the FMAP for each affected jurisdiction (without regard for any limitation otherwise specified in section 1905(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(b)</external-xref>)) by the number of percentage points estimated under subsection (d).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H763EA31D75DB474CB5C605B9D8A1C783"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Estimation of amount of compact migrant expenditures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a), not later than 90 days before the beginning of the calendar quarter involved, the chief executive official of the affected jurisdiction shall submit to the Secretary of the Interior an estimation of the amount of Compact migrant expenditures that will be made by such jurisdiction for such quarter.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H33ECB72C5E924168AE57A3E7ACF8330E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Review by Secretary of the Interior</header><text>Not later than 60 days before the beginning of the calendar quarter involved, the Secretary of the Interior shall review the estimation submitted by the chief executive official under subsection (b), make any appropriate adjustments, and submit to the Secretary of Health and Human Services a final estimated amount of Compact migrant expenditures for such quarter.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H4C637277B4814BE783271050C88848DC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Estimation and notification by Secretary of HHS</header>
 <paragraph id="HCF1CB3B871A74438BC96A7EC9F89A7EB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall estimate the number of percentage points that the FMAP for each affected jurisdiction would need to be increased for a calendar quarter to result in an increase in the amount of total Federal payments to the affected jurisdiction under title XIX of the Social Security Act for such quarter that is equivalent to the final estimated amount of Compact migrant expenditures submitted under subsection (c) for such quarter.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H53CF1F8821D945D1A2876A06B904DEDC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Continued application of limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In no case may the increase in the FMAP estimated by the Secretary of Health and Human Services under paragraph (1) result in the payments to an affected jurisdiction under title XIX of the Social Security Act that exceed the limitations under subsections (f) and (g) of section 1108 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1308">42 U.S.C. 1308</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6D7C67FA790B4682B5CC3BB239EBB9A1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days before the beginning of the calendar quarter involved, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall notify each such chief executive official of the increase in the FMAP estimated by the Secretary under this subsection for the affected jurisdiction involved.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9D6989236519428CAE80402855436F61"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reconciling and payment adjustments</header>
 <paragraph id="HB91EADD40B874E188841A0A05E837074"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report by affected jurisdictions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each calendar quarter in which an increase in the FMAP is made for an affected jurisdiction under subsection (d), the chief executive official for the jurisdiction shall submit to the Secretary of the Interior an accounting of the total amount of Compact migrant expenditures made by such jurisdiction for such quarter. Such accounting shall be submitted in such form and manner as the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall specify.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H17F25392DABE41DF982293B3BACD9418"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Review by the Interior</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior shall review each accounting submitted under paragraph (1) for accuracy, make any appropriate adjustments, and submit a final accounting of the amount of Compact migrant expenditures for such quarter for each affected jurisdiction involved to the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HEFE463C20B99412B96C5B593498AB344"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Adjustment by HHS</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HC10972C74B8C407B9760993870F0220D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>review whether the increase in the FMAP for each affected jurisdiction under subsection (a) for a calendar quarter involved resulted in an increase in Federal payments to the affected jurisdiction under title XIX of the Social Security Act for such quarter in an amount that is equivalent to the final accounting of the amount of Compact migrant expenditures submitted under paragraph (2) for such jurisdiction; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3C249DEE1254D70871A04CC02FA705C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subject to the limitations under subsections (f) and (g) of section 1108 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1308">42 U.S.C. 1308</external-xref>), shall make appropriate adjustments to the FMAP for the affected jurisdiction for future quarters to account for any overpayment or underpayment occurring as a result of the increase in such FMAP under this section for the quarter involved for that jurisdiction.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC2D16937B3DE4E62BF3A4D441F1A9BE9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitation of FMAP to 100 percent</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In no case shall an increase in the FMAP applicable to an affected jurisdiction under this section result in an FMAP for that jurisdiction that exceeds 100 percent.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H4D149FD80D234920ACAD09B835380CF9"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>This section shall not be construed as treating Compact migrant expenditures as medical assistance under title XIX of the Social Security Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HACF584B63DC3475599D535375843173A"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H30F1FC8BBF0A444CBF8A531AFD69C4B0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Affected jurisdiction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>affected jurisdiction</term> has the meaning given such term in section 104(e)(2) of the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1921c">48 U.S.C. 1921c(e)(2)</external-xref>).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HA16D3D7C9366403EB74FA4CFCEEC8621"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compact migrant expenditures</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H66F22FA55ADD4482AF964592C4C16036"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Compact migrant expenditures</term> means, for a calendar quarter with respect to an affected jurisdiction, the amount of non-Federal funds expended by such jurisdiction for items and services described in section 1905(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(a)</external-xref>) for qualified nonimmigrants (as defined in section 104(e)(2) of the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1921c">48 U.S.C. 1921c(e)(2)</external-xref>)) and related administrative costs.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05E75A7C5669485083B96D7EDA486F46" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Such term includes payments made by an affected jurisdiction to health care providers for health care items and services provided to qualified nonimmigrants described in subparagraph (A), if such payment is not made under a State plan under title XIX of the Social Security Act, and such payment is not made from any other source of Federal funds.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F94D179E592471DB71228D91E1805AF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>FMAP</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>FMAP</term> means the Federal medical assistance percentage, as defined in section 1905(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(b)</external-xref>), as determined without regard to this section.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE5C2B5E1F1C44127812BDEA9C2591318"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 1905(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(b)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>subject to section 2 of the Compact Aid Relief Act</quote> after <quote>83 per centum, (2)</quote>.</text> </subsection></section><section id="H292B328F72CF412B90EACE36DB176FC7" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Payments relating to elementary and secondary education of citizens of Freely Associated States</header> <subsection id="H9957D9E370614CABBDA473F88F83BB71"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8001 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7701">20 U.S.C. 7701</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H65E9C9FEE9DF48EAA8A754F678E06F24"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>or</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H8BF3D3A2EB6A46B0B5DCAA9C2214DEB8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6DEA1199500E437A84A59B5A8B2B759A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCE703641F2EC44B5AA8D70C460D825E9" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HD6ACDB5D75D047CAA22D8BD13DFACA41"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">educate alien children admitted to the United States as citizens of one of the Freely Associated States.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF7F119624C154315B3163099D2749072"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Payments for eligible federally connected children</header><text>Section 8003(a) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7703">20 U.S.C. 7703(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HBEAD18FDB83C4B7489063EF8C2C50DC3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H56891535CBEA4A46AD5F4E25DA866C08"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (F), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA0982B00A204CFBA78C1EF12CC01004"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H800A06C7ADCF44AF8C0DED1955A9AA20"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFAEC1BC34FAB4915B7319AAD4C3F8C5C" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H6FE2A6B550234EE1B634F211E84EB8B3"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">resided in the United States pursuant to an admission into the United States as a citizen of the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, or the Republic of Palau.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF528E88E22194B67A522E81FAFA15E6D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2750B4E4DE0E4A19B2869D0ECE1B5D12" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H7F781F192AAA4D0487EFDC119DFB70DD"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Multiply the number of children described in paragraph (1)(H) by a factor of 1.25.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HD4516C568B9647F2B6A085B9E488BE6A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of additional funds for eligible federally connected children</header><text>Section 8014 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7714">20 U.S.C. 7714</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA143A6E47CA44E8BB21FF96904EF3B76" style="OLC"> <subsection commented="no" id="HB02A3EEEACD247A2B45856AFB676A5B7"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Additional funding for eligible federally connected children</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of making additional payments for federally connected children described in section 8003(a)(1) under this title, there are authorized to be appropriated $10,000,000 for fiscal year 2018 and for each succeeding fiscal year.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section><section id="H9E7A0B773AA04065B9064DBA5052F888" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Expansion of national service programs</header>
			<subsection id="H37EDEBB6FC4E4B77B78FC18C62522CE8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National and community service programs</header>
 <paragraph id="H7D32801DD1A94AFC9CF25CF864644DA1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Nonprofit capacity building</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 198S(a)(4) of the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12653s">42 U.S.C. 12653s(a)(4)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and the District of Columbia</quote> and inserting <quote>, the District of Columbia, American Samoa, Guam, the Northern Mariana Islands, Puerto Rico, and the Virgin Islands of the United States</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2C21ED6AA1D040B59BDBC938241E784A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compact migrant eligibility</header><text>Section 137(a)(5) of the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12591">42 U.S.C. 12591(a)(5)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H369CB3BFE5A846F09070337C0ACF0FD7" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="HE0456E4CE5EE432A835A397F69A2DC47"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is a citizen or national of the United States or lawful permanent resident alien of the United States, or is a citizen of the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, or the Republic of Palau and admitted to the United States as a nonimmigrant under the terms of the applicable Compact of Free Association with the United States.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7BC2F5AAD0024E719B9DC514A7D6FFF1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to any participant in a program under the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12501">42 U.S.C. 12501</external-xref> et seq.) selected after the date of enactment of this subsection.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H94519F51FD114951B88ED002D7A70272"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Youth conservation corps</header><text>The Youth Conservation Corps Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1701">16 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H28BFD73FD3B14E16BA871540840D1992"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 102(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1702">16 U.S.C. 1702(a)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>trust territories</quote> and inserting <quote>citizens of the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, or the Republic of Palau and admitted to the United States as nonimmigrants under the terms of the applicable Compact of Free Association with the United States,</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H35C01016F15945EFAEA4396928219BFA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 104 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1704">16 U.S.C. 1704</external-xref>)—</text> <subparagraph id="H038F40F47E5149A1A5BD3DF89CB1B9C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (a), by striking <quote>the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands,</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC6FA1753EE24411B9A910237D350355"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>, or the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands</quote> and inserting <quote>, or citizens of the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, or the Republic of Palau and admitted to the United States as nonimmigrants under the terms of the applicable Compact of Free Association with the United States</quote>.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H6BD4575C4927427DB708AE155AA3D68E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Independent study and assessment of Compacts of Free Association</header>
 <subsection id="H06C89888B6904B6883F4587E2AF11DCF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall enter into an agreement with an eligible organization described in subsection (b) to conduct an independent study and assessment of the Compacts of Free Association between the United States and the Freely Associated States of the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, and the Republic of Palau.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HADBE261F36634C4780C390E77B2DE03B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible organization described</header><text>An eligible organization described in this subsection is—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H7F63D14C58ED4427AE46262522EA3A2B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a federally funded research and development center sponsored by a Federal agency;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4B5E2D70B6264F79808B9D39F0DFC61E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Government Accountability Office; or</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H3B71BFACD6074E698E7966A777794CF6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDDF9A5DF2B294BEC9AD739CAA9D574C5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text>The study and assessment required under subsection (a) shall include—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H97556C18912F49EBB11F1C7CC7DC9843"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an assessment of implementation of the Compacts of Free Association by the United States, including Compact impact funding to affected jurisdictions (as such term is defined in section 104(e)(2)(A) of the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/188">Public Law 108–188</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1921c">48 U.S.C. 1921c(e)(2)(A)</external-xref>));</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H821917121A2C4965B41FB177D25B5B5F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of the capabilities, expertise, and shortfalls of effectively administering the Compacts of Free Association and providing assistance under such Compacts to affected jurisdictions as defined in paragraph (1), including recommendations on improvements to such capabilities and changes to processes or administrative reorganizations that may be necessary;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H74FEEF6F8CCE4421BBEC90F196419AE2"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of the management of trust funds established for each of the Freely Associated States and the United States financial contributions to such trust funds;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4CA356367DAC4A8B972EDBD32A90AE33"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recommendations regarding renewal and future administration or cessation of such Compacts;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H5F161AC53D994C3A8AF204ACA8DC7B7F"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of any outstanding claims by the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, and the Republic of Palau to lands or territorial waters belonging to the United States, including Wake Island (Wake Atoll); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCF82CCE2154A4D4F8C131774D929B15C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>any other matters the Secretary of State or the eligible organization that enters into an agreement under this section determines to be appropriate and that do not duplicate unnecessarily the matters addressed in the study required by section 1259D of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/91">Public Law 115–91</external-xref>).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFB1D37D4DB1F499584C7693DB12E02DC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report required</header>
 <paragraph id="H331E4B9F76824608BAE9132ECCA09B94"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date on which the Secretary of State enters into an agreement with an eligible organization under this section, the eligible organization shall submit to the Secretary and the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H7E96B03FB14B4A318C255E67D3DE4026"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the study and assessment required under subsection (a);</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H692B959F8FED407EB0EB03BA45EC049C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the matters to be included required under subsection (c); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CBFC1EB2D5E438A9C3BD19F1E9D4CBB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other matters the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0ABE149E93AA4882AA9693AFA175EE71"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required under paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex if necessary.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HED915A6231684927AB92CA2FEA5F0A83"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall publish the unclassified portion of the report required under paragraph (1) on a publicly accessible government website.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6F1A4146F9ED4B4CBE8672EF34839A47"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HA34762249179490492C50794A974F441"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDFFF476C42954DAE97E3476168EE09D7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF544A61B0D8C481D8B50F0CA39448FAC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Obtaining official data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The eligible organization that enters into an agreement under this section may secure directly from any department or agency of the United States information necessary to enable it to carry out this section. Upon request of such eligible organization, the head of that department or agency shall furnish that information to the eligible organization.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H615089EE5B704B1E9FA51B388FE4BCB7"><enum>6.</enum><header>Census enumeration of Compact migrants in affected jurisdictions</header>
 <subsection id="H3B4868618412415680B02935466B4F61"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Decennial Census</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 141 of title 13, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HAF86DB2E858B43608E5EC103CE13AFCB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (g) as subsection (h); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCE48D5C7E81B4A3F8B146C5789837559"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (f) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H39129387697542B6B885B0C18EE27EDA" style="USC"> <subsection id="H6B0AEC69FB1C42F3BB5A0B1EF7E3EA06"><enum>(g)</enum> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HF0E1C7A48C664FC5A66EA5E4722A89C0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>With respect to each decennial census of population conducted under subsection (a), the Secretary shall conduct an enumeration of qualified nonimmigrants in each affected jurisdiction.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8BD3B300CCB248AEB8BFB59A0DECB9E5" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>For purposes of carrying out this subsection, the terms <term>affected jurisdiction</term> and <term>qualified nonimmigrant</term> have the meaning given those terms in section 104(e)(2)(A) and (B), respectively, of the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/188">Public Law 108–188</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1921c">48 U.S.C. 1921c(e)(2)(A)</external-xref> and (B)).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H46D1D2FE63D640E9B7DF52BEC8F4DD5A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An enumeration conducted pursuant to section 141(g) of title 13, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), shall, for purposes of the year to which the applicable decennial census applies, satisfy the requirements of paragraph (4) of section 104(e) of the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/188">Public Law 108–188</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1921c">48 U.S.C. 1921c(e)(4)</external-xref>). The preceding sentence shall not be construed to supersede, alter, or otherwise affect the five-year requirement in subparagraph (A) of such paragraph.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HB412B976627B401D9EB59A224E60F252"><enum>7.</enum><header>Bureau of economic analysis data regarding affected jurisdictions and Freely Associated States</header>
 <subsection id="HBC0E2430807F4CD2B2E75295A8B4B6D9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Assessment and analysis</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Bureau of Economic Analysis of the Department of Commerce shall conduct an annual assessment and analysis of the economies of the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H4DDDF6EDDCD04BB1BBED330F64737484"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Affected jurisdictions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Affected jurisdictions (as such term is defined under section 104(e)(2)(A) of the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1921c">48 U.S.C. 1921c(e)(2)(A)</external-xref>)).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7E705845EBAD44F4B4B48782B0E4A817"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Freely associated States</header><text>The Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, and the Republic of Palau.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2900B0AC0CC94DC3847D6104A808D3A6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In conducting the economic assessment and analysis required by subsection (a), the Director shall—</text> <paragraph id="H317D13DEA89B429E940B8110FCA67FCA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consult with—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H0DD588A97C0B450B8E0406689ED7DD2C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of the Interior;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C91AC6219AD4904B622BCA8702F1F9B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Director of the Bureau of the Census;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70E9D1AA4B5A4316A9437426A7425FE7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Commissioner of the Bureau of Labor Statistics of the Department of Labor;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H874A4A08A93F43FBA27BBEA2C1BD27E3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>other Federal agencies as the Director considers appropriate; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86B8922F21234B62A03EB8884361268E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>local government agencies in the affected jurisdictions described in subsection (a)(1); and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EB72939BC75456EA382B58BA179CEC6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>consider the following:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H58D94C1F153A415E996DCBB573039511"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The gross domestic product of each of the affected jurisdictions and Freely Associated States described in subsection (a).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7592DAECAFA8421395E93AF12AC2D4A5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Remittance transfers from citizens of the Freely Associated States described in subsection (a)(2), the recipient of which is located in any country other than the United States.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAEAAD9398C514A3BBFEB38C2E001F593"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Government or similar public services consumed by citizens of the Freely Associated States described in subsection (a)(2) residing in the United States.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1325247642FC42B084334FCFECD5D779"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Refundable tax credits, tax deductions, or similar advantageous tax code provisions for low-income households, including the earned income tax credit under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/32">section 32</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and the child tax credit under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/24">section 24</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 claimed by citizens of the Freely Associated States described in subsection (a)(2) in Federal tax returns filed in the United States.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4EE200655F5342DBA70ACD1F3B39C1E4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Impact of citizens of the Freely Associated States described in subsection (a)(2) who are residing in the affected jurisdictions described in subsection (a)(1) on the local labor market, wages, and unemployment rate in such affected jurisdictions.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC27A1CE6455947588EE07CBAA0151A76"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Foreign direct investment by industrial sectors, by country of investor, and by type of transaction.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4AAC0109B39D402496277B17F8647559"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Other contributing components of the economies of such affected jurisdictions and Freely Association States described in subsection (a) as the Director considers appropriate.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5ED8BEDD6EAE46E0A62FCE0DCC9DA305"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act and each year thereafter, the Director shall make available to the Congress and the public on a government website an annual report on the findings of the Director with respect to the economic assessment and analysis conducted under this section.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="HA684C5442B7B4C0A82A626B16C56F905"><enum>8.</enum><header>Native Hawaiian, other Pacific Islander, and Insular Areas health data</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part B of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/243">42 U.S.C. 243</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by inserting after section 317T the following:</text>
			<quoted-block id="HED6997C9CFCA455FB1A41C151CF06142" style="OLC">
				<section id="H260B6969306447A6A24D9DF4989879B6"><enum>317U.</enum><header>Native Hawaiian, other Pacific Islander, and insular areas health data</header>
 <subsection id="H5DC2F9F5C2FC47CDA8C1E4FB341548E8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H77DC85EC970D4A0A8B87157A3090E239"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Native Hawaiians and other Pacific Islanders (NHOPI)</header><text>The term <term>Native Hawaiians and other Pacific Islanders</term> or <term>NHOPI</term> means people having origins in any of the original peoples of Hawai’i, American Samoa, Guam, the Northern Mariana Islands, the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, the Republic of Palau, or any other Pacific Island.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBB0F770D1B3D42E282039D274E504134"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Community group</header><text>The term <term>community group</term> means a group of NHOPI who are organized at the community level, and may include a church group, social service group, national advocacy organization, or cultural group.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA94F52B6F71A4497927D09FC6D3D02A0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Nonprofit, nongovernmental organization</header><text>The term <term>nonprofit, nongovernmental organization</term> means a group of NHOPI with a demonstrated history of addressing NHOPI issues, including a NHOPI coalition.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6F6889A76AB94DDA9E34D0890B07B60D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Designated organization</header><text>The term <term>designated organization</term> means an entity established to represent NHOPI populations and which has statutory responsibilities to provide, or has community support for providing, health care.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H37BBE9A298FC4637B834FC0842D09066"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Government representatives</header><text>The term <term>government representatives</term> means representatives from Hawai’i, American Samoa, Guam, the Northern Mariana Islands, the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, and the Republic of Palau.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H40961EC22F554828A82D3A9A2850EC33"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Insular Area</header><text>The term <term>Insular Area</term> means American Samoa, Guam, the Northern Mariana Islands, the Virgin Islands of the United States, the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, and the Republic of Palau.</text>
						</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF1C2B99BBF054CD98655D386D5964575"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National strategy</header>
 <paragraph id="HE50D19EB117146E6AAED625039B2B981"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of the National Center for Health Statistics (referred to in this section as <quote>NCHS</quote>) of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and other agencies within the Department of Health and Human Services as the Secretary determines appropriate, shall develop and implement an ongoing and sustainable national strategy for identifying and evaluating the health status and health care needs for each NHOPI population, by ethnicity or nationality, living in the continental United States, Hawai’i, American Samoa, Guam, the Northern Mariana Islands, the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, and the Republic of Palau.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H7138AAB355B24C44B9AD074E62E57617"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In developing and implementing a national strategy, as described in paragraph (1), not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of the Compact Impact Relief Act, the Secretary—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H0E22FE9BB04D4628AA6B8E99A384C0E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall consult with representatives of community groups, designated organizations, and nonprofit, nongovernmental organizations and with government representatives of NHOPI populations; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA7AB6CF492514CD8B49061F82602F595"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may solicit the participation of representatives from other Federal departments and agencies.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFAD9B2A6EF7A4A72B674DCF20067742A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Preliminary health survey</header> <paragraph id="HB1A72E4F67F84037A322AD267986A582"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of NCHS, shall conduct a preliminary health survey in order to identify the major areas and regions in the continental United States, Hawai’i, American Samoa, Guam, the Northern Mariana Islands, the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, and the Republic of Palau in which NHOPI people reside.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H37EBC9FA608048788DD5DF94703F3BC3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The health survey described in paragraph (1) shall include health data and any other data the Secretary determines to be—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HCCE503E7DC2C41AEB9825CE7DA4460CC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>useful in determining the health status and health care needs for each NHOPI population, by ethnicity or nationality, to the greatest extent practicable; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5E585C5A2DA43FEA81B3CB39B759A51"><enum>(B)</enum><text>required for developing or implementing a national strategy.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F9FA8C592944ABCA7FFD16F3E132E00"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Methodology</header><text>Methodology for the health survey described in paragraph (1), including plans for designing questions, implementation, sampling, and analysis, shall be developed in consultation with community groups, designated organizations, nonprofit, nongovernmental organizations, and government representatives of NHOPI populations, as determined by the Secretary.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFFA66BFC807549359A17E601002849B3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Timeframe</header><text>The survey required under this subsection shall be completed not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of the Compact Impact Relief Act.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD6C56B895A064755BE08B1AF4DEFEDF5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Progress report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of the Compact Impact Relief Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Congress a progress report, which shall include the national strategy described in subsection (b)(1), and make such report available on the public website of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="H3176818F4A644A31A903789892E2F91C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>HMD study and report</header>
 <paragraph id="H78E679C9D17B42E7B03F7043988B1B35"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall enter into an agreement with the Health and Medicine Division of the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine to conduct a study, with input from stakeholders in Insular Areas, on the following:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H271EA6AA7B8C41BB8EA7B8A64BE5137A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The standards and definitions of health care applied to health care systems in Insular Areas and the appropriateness of such standards and definitions.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94B8C76AEF8E4403862510F2580251B9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The status and performance of health care systems in Insular Areas, evaluated based upon standards and definitions, as the Secretary determines.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89C126E15EBD40A1967FD64A155DA9ED"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The effectiveness of donor aid in addressing health care needs and priorities in Insular Areas.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H72BC7E33B5404A8BAC60F059C08D4ECD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The progress toward implementation of recommendations of the Committee on Health Care Services in the United States—Associated Pacific Basin of the National Academy of Medicine, including recommendations that were set forth in the 1998 report, <quote>Pacific Partnerships for Health: Charting a New Course for the 21st Century</quote>, as applicable to all Insular Areas except the Virgin Islands of the United States.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H523CA055E23540C180E2B11B5A70BCB4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>An agreement described in paragraph (1) shall require the Health and Medicine Division to submit to the Secretary and to the Congress, and make readily available on a public website, not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of the Compact Impact Relief Act, a report containing a description of the results of the study conducted under paragraph (1), including the conclusions and recommendations of the Health and Medicine Division for each of the items described in subparagraphs (A) through (D) of such paragraph.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HECB5D40EBCDB41B7B4BC7AB9CFCB3BC8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for fiscal years 2018 through 2022.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="H8FE03CF531BA4F5587B537554D218AF8"><enum>9.</enum><header>Local matching requirements for territories and affected jurisdictions</header>
 <subsection id="H8D8889178E0E4B43ACFEC8278015F4F3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Expanded Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 501 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/95/134">Public Law 95–134</external-xref>, approved October 15, 1977 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1469a">48 U.S.C. 1469a</external-xref>), is amended as follows:</text>
 <paragraph id="H7A26B6A797CA4ACFA04678464BB925CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In subsection (d), by striking <quote>by law</quote> in the last sentence.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HEA2D72D5F10A4402BBE9625DD2D7DFE3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>By adding after subsection (d) the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE9DDD46C95744012A5677C9E76A53A7F" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="H33247BA1C33C44B689DF1545ACA89C29"><enum>(e)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, in the case of American Samoa, Guam, the Virgin Islands, and the Northern Mariana Islands, any Federal department or agency shall waive any requirement for local matching funds (including in-kind contributions) required to be provided by American Samoa, Guam, the Virgin Islands, the Northern Mariana Islands, or an eligible nongovernmental recipient in the aforementioned United States territories for any grant as follows:</text>
 <paragraph id="H79131DF379DC4FB9A318E5449CD0B6C2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>For a grant requiring matching funds (including in-kind contributions) of $400,000 or less, the entire matching requirement shall be waived.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2FAA995EB3114F748B2E748F53F99335"><enum>(2)</enum><text>For a grant requiring matching funds (including in-kind contributions) of more than $400,000, $400,000 of the matching requirement shall be waived.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA96B4FA73BAC47EB971AA96CF5E74FD5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For a grant requiring matching funds (including in-kind contributions) of $600,000 or less to be paid by an affected jurisdiction as defined by section 104(e)(2) of the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1921c">48 U.S.C. 1921c(e)(2)</external-xref>), the entire matching requirement shall be waived for unreimbursed impact expenses.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1650AA8574734E65AD8B1382D28C5142"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For a grant requiring matching funds (including in-kind contributions) of more than $600,000 to be paid by an affected jurisdiction as defined by section 104(e)(2) of the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1921c">48 U.S.C. 1921c(e)(2)</external-xref>), $600,000 of the matching requirement shall be waived for unreimbursed impact expenses.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H02FC4B417F5347CF8B4968B304246C0F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming Amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 601 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/96/205">Public Law 96–205</external-xref>, approved March 12, 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1469a">48 U.S.C. 1469a</external-xref> note; 94 Stat. 90), is amended by striking <quote>(d), and adding the following sentence</quote> and all that follows through the final period and inserting <quote>(d).</quote>.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HCB85541539864CF3AB57FF41ABA481E5"><enum>10.</enum><header>Local expenditures qualifying as in-kind contributions</header>
 <subsection id="H419AEDC6CA5943C89F90FD5DB722696F"><enum> (a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided under subsection (c), local matching requirements required of an affected jurisdiction for Federal programs may be paid in cash or in-kind services provided by the affected jurisdiction pursuant to the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H0E5F94C0FDB84A6DBB0750C597AB4FE2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Section 104 of the Compact of Free Association between the Government of the United States and the Government of the Republic of the Marshall Islands, approved in the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/188">Public Law 108–188</external-xref>; 117 Stat. 2781).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC00EAA907005406996B8E72711CCBF2A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Section 104 of the Compact of Free Association between the Government of the United States and the Government of the Federated States of Micronesia, approved in the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/188">Public Law 108–188</external-xref>; 117 Stat. 2781).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7BD83E65084241BAB91F33A43727A633"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Compact of Free Association between the Government of the United States and the Government of the Republic of Palau, approved in the Palau Compact of Free Association Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/99/658">Public Law 99–658</external-xref>; 100 Stat. 3672).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9B3B7F3EC91A48AEB2AB66D4D26FE1E6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Determination of amounts To be considered in-Kind contributions</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior shall determine the amounts that may be considered in-kind contributions for an affected jurisdiction under this section based on a reasonable estimate of the amount of impact expenditures for the Freely Associated States divided by a reasonable estimate of the number of citizens from the Freely Associated States residing in that affected jurisdiction.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H0BACDF1FDAF347B1A430DD805E98A19A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Affected jurisdictions</header><text>The term <term>affected jurisdiction</term> shall have the meaning given that term in section 104(e) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/188">Public Law 108–188</external-xref> (117 Stat. 2739).</text> </subsection></section><section id="H3E3B2B37DE3044989CDDFA63A1459288"><enum>11.</enum><header>Eligibility for Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act programs</header> <subsection id="HADE3BE1E3D8845AB9418B19326807C13"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Job Corps centers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 147(a) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3197">29 U.S.C. 3197(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HF94A548DE1164B45BB1E5C005DBD6FA3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1)(A), by inserting <quote>or similar agency of an outlying area,</quote> after <quote>local agency</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H6359966D8ECF447FBF44BE4EFBEE32A2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2)(B)(i)(III), by inserting <quote>(or outlying area)</quote> after <quote>State</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDE917C3F1E174FBBB0E9CCC2F3E4901C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Compact migrant eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 188(a)(5) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3248">29 U.S.C. 3248(a)(5)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>, and citizens of the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, or the Republic of Palau, who were admitted to the United States as nonimmigrants under the terms of the applicable Compact of Free Association with the United States</quote>.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H9436A38A4C9640E6A8332CCD9A0803D9"><enum>12.</enum><header>Amendments to Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act</header>
 <subsection id="H82E2B84CB5FC49BEBA767A2C04F58DB6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Snap eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 402(a)(2) of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1612">8 U.S.C. 1612(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H31E40CE8A5504BDCA8159765AC66FF7C" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H5DC3FFCC84A4445AA730C613ECF810E0"><enum>(N)</enum><header>Exception for citizens of the freely associated states residing in the united states</header><text>With respect to eligibility for benefits for the specified Federal program defined in paragraph (3)(B) section 401(a) and paragraph (1) shall not apply—</text>
 <clause id="HBED1E25D562546D280A745A6BF34552B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to any citizen of the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, or the Republic of Palau who lawfully resides in one of the several States or the District of Columbia as a nonimmigrant under the terms of the applicable Compact of Free Association with the United States; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD526B980168A47B1BF91B6294185688E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>at the request of the governors of Guam, the Northern Mariana Islands, American Samoa, Puerto Rico, or the Virgin Islands, to any citizen of the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, or the Republic of Palau who lawfully resides in the respective United States territory as a nonimmigrant under the terms of the applicable Compact of Free Association with the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HC3DA809C30694C1F9A67DF6DDF8794E3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>TANF and SSBG eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 402(b)(2) of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1612">8 U.S.C. 1612(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H2C6F90014688431AAC4535215569BD9A" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H34862ADDEC914BED90C8039C03DAD829"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Exception for citizens of the freely associated states residing in the United States</header><text>With respect to eligibility for benefits for the designated Federal program defined in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (3), section 401(a) and paragraph (1) shall not apply—</text>
 <clause id="HA51E5A14E13948C8A076CEA840DB3786"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to any citizen of the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, or the Republic of Palau who lawfully resides in one of the several States or the District of Columbia as a nonimmigrant under the terms of the applicable Compact of Free Association with the United States; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H2ED8029D117C4C09A06777AB04998E70"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>at the request of the governors of Guam, the Northern Mariana Islands, American Samoa, Puerto Rico, or the Virgin Islands, to any citizen of the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, or the Republic of Palau who lawfully resides in the respective United States territory as a nonimmigrant under the terms of the applicable Compact of Free Association with the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H0FC10A30691E4CC5852AA69A0AC00F80"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clarification on amounts provided to affected jurisdictions</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="H9CFB71EBA27A4E65B58030BB99C2E630"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>Any amounts provided to an affected jurisdiction for benefits to qualified nonimmigrants for the specified Federal program defined in section 402(a)(3)(A) of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1612">8 U.S.C. 1612(a)(3)(A)</external-xref>), or for the designated Federal program defined in section 402(b)(3)(C) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1612">8 U.S.C. 1612(b)(3)(C)</external-xref>), shall be used to supplement and not supplant, other Federal, State, and local funds, including under—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HFA90C845FE154DFA968B8825071CBCA7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the supplemental nutrition assistance program as defined in section 3 of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2012">7 U.S.C. 2012</external-xref>);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H2D82EDAD863546E994775C0F41924A86"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the program of block grants to States for temporary assistance for needy families under part A of title IV of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/601">42 U.S.C. 601</external-xref> et seq.); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5CF8175C31B1473E9F1BC0DAEF8D0F3E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the program of block grants<editorial></editorial> to States for social services under title XX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397">42 U.S.C. 1397</external-xref> et seq.).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DAE9F0D23FD403AAD3845FB22A900F8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection, the terms <term>affected jurisdiction</term> and <term>qualified nonimmigrant</term> have the meaning given such terms, respectively, in section 104(e)(2) of the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1921c">48 U.S.C. 1921c(e)(2)</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2F32B54815D245AF9E47AC8857647531"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Clarification of qualified alien</header><text>Section 431(b) of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1641">8 U.S.C. 1641(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H9C641A26DFA44C848923A9F119BD819A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking <quote>; or</quote> and inserting a comma;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H328ACA185FA947F6AFE2407B3F4F5C60"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (7), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>, or</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7B332D394D064F23AF1F6620FCE31E5F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H7B1AB70EBF624218AD52F081F1020BB0" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H0C5111DC201141E9827476EE6CB6DD11"><enum>(8)</enum><text>an alien who is a citizen of the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, or the Republic of Palau and admitted to the United States as a nonimmigrant under the terms of the applicable Compact of Free Association with the United States.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


