<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H3BC0760911AB4FD1B60DFD27482FE902" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5711 IH: Improving Access to Mental Health Services Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5711</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180508">May 8, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="G000568">Mr. Griffith</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title III of the Public Health Service Act to allow National Health Service Corps members
			 to provide obligated service as behavioral and mental health professionals
			 at schools, other community-based settings, or patient homes, and for
			 other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H6CBA9EDAB78F43A8881FAFA1B397DB9D" style="OLC">
 <section id="H15BE0CCA2DAE448BB6C9F3A41FA60A90" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Access to Mental Health Services Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HCAB9261861A343D1A99BDC1F7EABF845"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Health Service Corps behavioral and mental health professionals providing obligated service in schools, other community-based settings, and patient homes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subpart III of part D of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254l et">42 U.S.C. 254<italic>l </italic>et</external-xref> seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6B2450AE84BB42E68B5BD3F02E7194B9" style="OLC">
				<section id="HF3E73F5ACA5F479B8C719445E6539EB3"><enum>338N.</enum><header>Behavioral and mental health professionals providing obligated service in schools, other
			 community-based settings, and patient homes</header>
 <subsection id="H0AAD11576AAE494E96941F6EB3BA9115"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Schools and community-Based settings</header><text>An entity, to which a Corps member is assigned under section 333, may direct such Corps member to provide service as a behavioral and mental health professional at schools or other community-based settings located in health professional shortage areas.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF005B8B1B8C14116A987BC69401CD1B6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Patient homes</header><text>An entity, to which a Corps member is assigned under section 333, may direct such Corps member to provide service as a behavioral and mental health professional through visiting the home of a patient located in a health professional shortage area.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H6A9F548FC38242679EE58B1B73E29CEB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Obligated service</header><text>Any service described in subsection (a) or (b) that a Corps member provides may count towards such Corps member's completion of any obligated service requirements under the Scholarship Program or the Loan Repayment Program. The Secretary shall not impose any maximum limitation on the number of hours of service described in subsection (a) or (b) that a Corps member may count towards completing such obligated service requirements.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA1676F0EB5D9445F988658ECCCE5E43D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>The authorization under subsection (a) or (b) shall be notwithstanding any other provision of this subpart or subpart II.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


