<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA8154C26F25F421A9B1386408572086D" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5510 IH: Reentry and Reunification Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5510</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180413">April 13, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Al Green of Texas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="H000324">Mr. Hastings</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001304">Mr. Brown of Maryland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000515">Mr. Rush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000581">Mrs. Lawrence</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Danny K. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000126">Ms. Eddie Bernice Johnson of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000294">Mr. Jeffries</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000537">Mr. Clyburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000287">Mr. Lewis of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001270">Ms. Bass</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000288">Mr. Ellison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000535">Mr. Gutiérrez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001049">Mr. Clay</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Homeland Security to provide lawful permanent resident status to
			 previously removed alien parents and spouses of citizens of the United
			 States, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H558760EC383741D8BFD0FE307308BF83" style="OLC">
 <section id="H353B7EB9A04F470BB91555FAD7D605DF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Reentry and Reunification Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H8D0A31A3E9CC4D64ACAE192E955B6DAD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Lawful permanent resident status for previously removed spouses and parents of citizens of the United States</header> <subsection id="H244531E9A4C0473C90F4C1FA18CFAFED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Eligibility requirements</header> <paragraph id="H99C47C17A5584FD3A89A8FCB39BEADC2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall admit to the United States as an alien admitted for lawful permanent residence an alien who is inadmissible to or deportable from the United States if the alien demonstrates that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HCE085D80C0B2422A909034850087B240"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the alien is the spouse, parent, or guardian of a citizen of the United States;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBFE3311C2BAB423EB53E2592D0BE174A"><enum>(B)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H30FF9DB44AF7472BB8E6E3612460E846"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prior to the date of the enactment of this Act, the alien departed the United States pursuant to an order of removal; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="HE8D537097B1E440C91148883CD7058DF" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>as of the date of the enactment of this Act, is subject to an order of removal, or is in removal proceedings;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H180BF56090684C9CA703BDF4BA5AEB96"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the alien has been a person of good moral character (as defined in section 101(f) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(f)</external-xref>)) since the date the alien initially entered the United States;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE5E2DE0F8F945F3A7C391FA5809E247"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subject to paragraph (2), the alien—</text> <clause id="H398568B8574D4557B286674132FD6D89"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is not inadmissible under paragraph (1), (2), (3), (4), (6)(E), (8), (10)(A), (10)(C), or (10)(D) of section 212(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)</external-xref>);</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H8BC41AA6FB49450E9AB036D217551315"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is not deportable under paragraph (1)(E), (1)(G), (2), (4), (5), or (6) of section 237(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1227">8 U.S.C. 1227(a)</external-xref>);</text>
 </clause><clause id="H3EF9B1648A194079937573009890A526"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>has not ordered, incited, assisted, or otherwise participated in the persecution of any person on account of race, religion, nationality, membership in a particular social group, or political opinion; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H3AA0FC684DC7477EBB77554A71D21394"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>other than an offense under State or local law for which an essential element was the alien’s immigration status, a minor traffic offense, or a violation of the immigration laws, has not been convicted of—</text>
 <subclause id="H0E359005611E4AF5B8729959DDB4264F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any offense under Federal or State law punishable by a maximum term of imprisonment of more than 1 year; or</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H4DDBED0FF8744EE2B91316BA7EF0D441"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any combination of offenses under Federal or State law, for which the alien was imprisoned for a total of more than 1 year in the aggregate; and</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD366C5D2FF9145349349A166745E3D8E"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an alien described in subparagraph (B)(ii), the alien has been continuously physically present in the United States since the date that is 4 years before the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC359F006560416C99C8A608A2352976"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to any benefit under this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security may waive subclauses (I) and (II) of paragraph (1)(D)(iv), the ground of inadmissibility under paragraph (1),(4), or (6)(E) of section 212(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)</external-xref>), and the ground of deportability under paragraph (1) of section 237(a) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1227">8 U.S.C. 1227(a)</external-xref>), for humanitarian purposes or family unity or when it is otherwise in the public interest.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H673CCB5EC1C1491581523B460CD01BEB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application period</header><text>An alien seeking status under this Act may file an application during the period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act and ending on the date that is 3 years after such date.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H4C325C892169415580BD2C0F557C3EC1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Determination of continuous presence</header>
 <paragraph id="HC7ACAA6263564110B881CD6DB7E47D3A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Termination of continuous period</header><text>Any period of continuous physical presence in the United States of an alien described in subsection (a)(1)(B)(ii) who applies for status under this section shall not terminate when the alien is served a notice to appear under section 239(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229">8 U.S.C. 1229(a)</external-xref>).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HFA414DB74DE14039A8CAFC8B5C73B1C4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Treatment of certain breaks in presence</header>
 <subparagraph id="H2916F2C2734F4B0BAE7045E7ACB0B2A2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraphs (B) and (C), an alien shall be considered to have failed to maintain continuous physical presence in the United States under subsection (a)(1)(E) if the alien has departed from the United States for any period exceeding 90 days or for any periods, in the aggregate, exceeding 180 days.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1FD03A2F054948E897E7161A1EDA2548"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Extensions for extenuating circumstances</header><text>The Secretary may extend the time periods described in subparagraph (A) for an alien who demonstrates that the failure to timely return to the United States was due to extenuating circumstances beyond the alien’s control, including the serious illness of the alien, or death or serious illness of a parent, grandparent, sibling, or child of the alien.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB653228E6EFD4800AF977B531C9488C1"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Travel authorized by the secretary</header><text>Any period of travel outside of the United States by an alien that was authorized by the Secretary may not be counted toward any period of departure from the United States under subparagraph (A).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H79D892886B4F4DBA8C358D0930A80E15"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Numerical limitations</header><text>An alien admitted to the United States under this section shall not be subject to any numerical limitation under the immigration laws.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H249D0835B6BF4B7EADDF4E994F7F1149"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Except as specifically provided, the terms in this Act have the meanings given those terms in the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


