<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H2AEB7274A0A64B39B64345008DE70785" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5079 IH: DHS Field Engagement Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5079</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180223">February 23, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000386">Mr. Katko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to require the Department of Homeland Security to
			 develop an engagement strategy with fusion centers, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H90DD03B2DDC5437398A74747DD398C6F" style="OLC">
 <section id="H157B00DC2D32430D8DFB1E9A592E445B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>DHS Field Engagement Accountability Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HA3F684F57CBD4B8D80ABC98F0BABA230"><enum>2.</enum><header>Engagement strategy with fusion centers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 210A of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/124h">6 U.S.C. 124h</external-xref>) is amended by—</text>
 <paragraph id="H9229B6F3636341BBAF489999F182AE83"><enum>(1)</enum><text>redesigning subsections (j) and (k) as subsections (k) and (l), respectively; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H5691E5F574AC4B23BD5A2464ACDFF1C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>inserting after subsection (i) the following new subsection:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H92180118BE624828A797C99BA082A6BF" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="H29CBE69E80624072A402BABCEE2D5CB5"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Fusion center information sharing strategy</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall develop and update at least once every five years a strategy for Department engagement with fusion centers. Such strategy shall be developed and updated in consultation with the heads of intelligence components of the Department, the Chief Privacy Officer of the Department, the Officer for Civil Rights and Civil Liberties of the Department, officials of fusion centers, officers designated as Homeland Security Advisors, and the heads of other relevant agencies, as appropriate. Such strategy shall include the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HF7E3BADD711940B0BDA9634A14C3A1A2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Specific goals and objectives for sharing information and engaging with fusion centers—</text> <subparagraph id="HFC427D53CF3B4304B182E0AB7786DFEA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">through the direct deployment of personnel from intelligence components of the Department;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA51575B5CEA446C19474AC9D0620001A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>through the use of Department unclassified and classified information sharing systems, including the Homeland Security Information Sharing Network and the Homeland Secure Data Network, or any successor systems; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD004191A7A1548AD8F2AAA21E87C143D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>through any additional means.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H372E440B1BCC4D18875CC82B5D321237"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The performance metrics to be used to measure success in achieving the goals and objectives referred to in paragraph (1).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H79E91BB72D394CF88AB8E03B04CE3486"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A five-year plan for continued engagement with fusion centers.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></section><section id="H487931752D48449F928D3B75F71866E1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Office of Intelligence and Analysis field personnel support to fusion centers</header> <subsection id="H6A3EE3892B354A2C900A3CCA3FB09AE5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Performance metrics</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Under Secretary for Intelligence and Analysis of the Department of Homeland Security shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H4A55717318CE4F4F9D0C76DE175AB493"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consider the effectiveness of existing processes to identify and prepare field personnel for deployment to support fusion centers and internal mechanisms to ensure oversight and accountability of such field personnel, including field personnel assigned to one center and field personnel assigned to multiple centers; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5EB0D366EDC141A0B9F3096BC36DB4D4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>publish and disseminate performance metrics, taking into account, as appropriate, regional and threat diversity, for—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HC89A05317B194FB4948FA3350B55F407"><enum>(A)</enum><text>field personnel from the Office of Intelligence and Analysis assigned to an individual fusion center;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB1DA9E7C3B99491498700B38380BB889"><enum>(B)</enum><text>field personnel from the Office of Intelligence and Analysis assigned to multiple fusion centers; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H947CD1505E194D458EBF15D3E6600242"><enum>(C)</enum><text>regional Directors of the Office of Intelligence and Analysis to ensure accountability for monitoring all field personnel under the supervision of such Regional Directors.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H28BAC8A201B44D55944B5E5011F8683C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In consultation with the Chief Information Officer of the Department of Homeland Security, the Under Secretary for Intelligence and Analysis of the Department shall develop and implement a formalized training module for fusion center personnel regarding the classified Homeland Secure Data Network of the Department, or any successor system.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H1069811C3CD94492BECE7096CFD14564"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Fusion center defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>fusion center</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 210A of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/124h">6 U.S.C. 124h</external-xref>).</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HB829AC6E4F1D4B4883B311327F07FEEE"><enum>4.</enum><header>DHS component usage of the Homeland Security Information Network</header>
 <subsection id="H7795386B746F4473BB8D0D1CA64DEF17"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Chief Intelligence Officer of the Department of Homeland Security, in consultation with the Chief Information Officer of the Department, shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H84DC0E1B5C7A4691A295AA44B1986D5D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop policies and metrics to ensure effective use by components of the Department of the Department’s unclassified Homeland Security Information Sharing Network, or any successor system; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9BF8706D891F43A68BDD946D9BBF8FD0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop policies for posting unclassified products on the Homeland Security Information Sharing Network, or any successor system.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H678BB525478C43F397C73A911EBEFDB4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical enhancements</header><text>The Chief Information Officer of the Department of Homeland Security, in consultation with the Chief Intelligence Officer of the Department, shall assess and implement, as appropriate, technical enhancements to the Homeland Security Information Sharing Network (HSIN) to improve usability, including search functionality, data analysis, and collaboration capabilities.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


