<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB6660BA453574E2492D38F9524084A0A" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5634 IH: Medical Cannabis Research Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5634</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180426">April 26, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001250">Mr. Bishop of Utah</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000609">Mr. Rutherford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000477">Mr. Taylor</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000580">Mr. Garrett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000295">Mr. Joyce of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001078">Mrs. Handel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001107">Mr. Curbelo of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000598">Mr. Polis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000612">Mr. Denham</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000435">Ms. Ros-Lehtinen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000051">Mr. Sanford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001084">Mr. Cicilline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000409">Mr. Rohrabacher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000289">Mr. Goodlatte</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001177">Mr. McClintock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000324">Mr. Hastings</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To increase the number of manufacturers registered under the Controlled Substances Act to
			 manufacture cannabis for legitimate research purposes, to authorize health
			 care providers of the Department of Veterans Affairs to provide
			 recommendations to veterans regarding participation in federally-approved
			 cannabis clinical trials, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H5A44B5D7A9D54509B41A651D8275AFCA" style="OLC">
 <section id="H66C015A5ADB8407D827AC6E020AE9A13" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Medical Cannabis Research Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H97F46EA4EF2B496399C3A68CE5C58B19"><enum>2.</enum><header>Increasing the number of federally-registered manufacturers of cannabis for legitimate research purposes</header> <subsection id="H76EE1FBD16DB44AF8DC7B1D973B3BFE0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 303 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/823">21 U.S.C. 823</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H71D68057F87C416EB1E9411D17BC7051"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (k) as subsection (l); and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H5C7D72FA4304403EBEBC524CD36352E0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (j) the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7BB5A82029684DC0B1ACFC71056232D7" style="OLC">
						<subsection id="HC34B2B4EB8614B178A52D7972AA9EED0"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Registration of manufacturers of cannabis for legitimate research purposes</header>
 <paragraph id="H38C183CF50BA470DAD3F3D1E2CEDE44B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any manufacturer of cannabis for research shall obtain a separate registration under this subsection for that purpose—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H2E693CD7492A4EB087389ADBD84CF7C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>annually; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFB209690C280477EA7849D9C35EC38CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for a longer period as determined necessary by the Attorney General to supply cannabis for the full duration of a particular multi-year study for legitimate research purposes.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BFB5A660E6C454E8C78CA9E57508739"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Adequate and uninterrupted supply</header>
 <subparagraph id="HE899C7F171A54A81B49562D807692A7F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Annual assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On an annual basis, the Attorney General shall assess whether there is an adequate and uninterrupted supply of cannabis for legitimate research purposes.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6792EDDB55774CC9B6C065132881E93E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Initial year</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Medical Cannabis Research Act of 2018</short-title>, of the applicants meeting the requirements of this Act, the Attorney General shall register under subsection (a) and this subsection at least 2 applicants to manufacture cannabis for legitimate research purposes in addition to any manufacturers that are registered under subsection (a) to manufacture cannabis as of the date of enactment of the <short-title>Medical Cannabis Research Act of 2018</short-title>.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8EDB2F0BD9724A78B5FA1E40C17A6C5D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Subsequent years</header><text>For calendar year 2019 and each subsequent calendar year, of the applicants meeting the requirements of this Act, the Attorney General shall register (including any registration renewal) under subsection (a) and this subsection at least 3 applicants to manufacture cannabis for legitimate research purposes.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8F018C1B10F4F3498683A429CD4EA3E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>A manufacturer registered under this subsection shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HC40FBBBA690C487DBAAA2656AA02E91B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>comply with all applicable requirements of this Act;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F7A24BB503442399DEBA098E499DAA3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>limit the transfer and sale of any cannabis manufactured pursuant to this section—</text> <clause id="H73C3907B784E44BE9621FCE9A79D3384"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to researchers who are registered under this Act to conduct research with controlled substances in schedule I; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H7C6AB212B7BF4077ABC38C648CCA0805"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for purposes of use in preclinical research or in a clinical investigation pursuant to an investigational new drug exemption under 505(i) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E7AEEC2A1B6447BA20590234222C021"><enum>(C)</enum><text>transfer or sell any cannabis manufactured pursuant to this section only with prior, written consent for the transfer or sale by the Attorney General;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0293DE74634B4BE4A35921B480680F89"><enum>(D)</enum><text>have completed the application and review process under subsection (a) for the bulk manufacture of controlled substances in schedule I;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9323B58CBA274060AFEECC61F60669C3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>have established and begun operation of a process for storage and handling of controlled substances in schedule I, including for inventory control and monitoring security;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B77F4B1AD2C479CB636E9334EA45F1D"><enum>(F)</enum><text>have the ability to provide at least 10 unique plant cultivars to ensure plant diversity and scale up to produce bulk plant material on an uninterrupted basis sufficient to supply forecasted demand;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17E09B8101DD47D6879B44D5783AC9E2"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be licensed, by each State in which the manufacturer conducts its operations pursuant to this subsection, to manufacture cannabis;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1ADE1BF73D042D0A346F1ADC1D14F69"><enum>(H)</enum><text>have completed a criminal background check for all personnel involved in the operations of the manufacturer pursuant to this subsection to confirm that such personnel have no conviction for a felony or drug-related misdemeanor;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE72184F12034F5984EDD8214354C1AE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>have a letter of reference affirming the manufacturer’s good standing from each of the applicable State health care and law enforcement authorities in each jurisdiction of the manufacturer’s operations pursuant to this subsection; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9733A7E46F76499BBA3EB0515DDA51FB"><enum>(J)</enum><text>have the ability to test for and isolate at least 12 cannabinoids for the purposes of producing specific products for specific studies by compounding pharmacists or others, labeling, and chemical consistency.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H924619F1F86C4C6CB0E21B755502107F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Application contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As part of an application to be registered under this subsection, an applicant shall include a written explanation of how the applicant’s proposed manufacture of cannabis would augment the Nation's supply of cannabis for legitimate research purposes.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0CD67F013BF3461BB3130B66ACBA5B94"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date on which the Attorney General receives an application to be registered under this section to manufacture cannabis for research, the Attorney General shall—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H07985CD4506D4DABBC7EA7C193FAECF8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>grant, or initiate proceedings under section 304(c) to deny, the application; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CBC4C33E53F48BE83AD456D20A617C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>request supplemental information from the applicant.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE812D9E6C8747D98B2D56B2BBB4769B"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Rule of construction on registration for purposes other than research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to affect the provisions of this section prohibiting or otherwise pertaining to registration of manufacturers of cannabis for purposes other than research, including for purposes of strictly commercial endeavors funded by the private sector and aimed at drug product development.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9C531D48319E44CDBF2DE5A7AEDECB0F"><enum>(7)</enum><header>No discriminatory treatment by Federal Government</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no Federal department or agency shall deny or limit any funding, other assistance, licensing, or other privilege with respect to any person on the basis that such person is, or is legally receiving cannabis from, a manufacturer of cannabis that is—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H2DCA0B62C8984DD8B445D4482B6FDCAA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>registered under this subsection; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDAA31826E257401686FDFDBCE7A0F166"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in compliance with the requirements of this Act.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H989D09EAB6FA4F388B079C7A00E4E750"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text>If cannabis, or any component thereof, is placed in a schedule other than schedule I, the Attorney General may, as the Attorney General determines appropriate—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H1613AA7619B048C0A9B1BD459D111087"><enum>(A)</enum><text>treat the reference to <quote>subsection (a)</quote> in paragraph (2)(C) of this subsection as a reference to subsection (d); and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37209C0DF0E34740A10C7A6448517E75"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">treat the references to schedule I in paragraph (3) as references to the appropriate schedule.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H686CD458D8834BC29D25B40389E47612"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <term>legitimate research purposes</term> has the meaning given to such term for purposes of subsection (a)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9E39FF23F58A40E185E3FA47D0410431"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transitional provisions</header> <paragraph id="H2D21BDD322C44B879C03B917F4A9D52E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Current registrants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding paragraph (1) of section 303(k) of the Controlled Substances Act, as added by subsection (a), any manufacturer that is registered under section 303(a) of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/823">21 U.S.C. 823(a)</external-xref>) to manufacture cannabis as of the date of enactment of this Act shall not be required to obtain a separate registration under such section 303(k) for the 1-year period following the date of enactment of this Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H352AA8BA40D34EABA4B29868376C3076"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Pending applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General of the United States shall grant or deny, in accordance with section 303 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/823">21 U.S.C. 823</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (a), each application to manufacture cannabis to supply researchers in the United States that was submitted—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H958003C9DD6E440F83AB6C91655D3AC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>pursuant to the policy statement entitled <quote>Applications To Become Registered Under the Controlled Substances Act To Manufacture Marijuana To Supply Researcher in the United States</quote> published by the Drug Enforcement Administration in the Federal Register on August 12, 2016 (81 Fed. Reg. 53846); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B8679B492094FF7A72B04AC0591682C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>before February 12, 2017.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC09D6F63900D4ACEAD61F6C1D3CF12B4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Technical amendment</header><text>Section 102(16) of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802(16)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after <quote>The term <term>marihuana</term> </quote> the following: <quote>or <quote>marijuana</quote> or <quote>cannabis</quote></quote>.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H22B8E2CDE9C244F7A89B280A19F988A8" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Provision by Department of Veterans Affairs health care providers of information regarding veteran
			 participation in federally-approved cannabis clinical trials</header>
 <subsection id="H2C1D6EBF28384BE88CE256103345E566"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Provision of information and forms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, health care providers of the Department of Veterans Affairs may—</text>
 <paragraph id="HC90872D93A2641908CDCB27258E34C5F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide information to veterans regarding participation in federally-approved cannabis clinical trials; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H02F3BE0B220842A686FA852A61A631B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">complete forms relating to such participation.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9470E21603544204AD87417ED1048BAE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Receipt of information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Health care providers and other employees of the Department may accept information regarding federally-approved cannabis clinical trials provided by individuals who are not employed by the Department who are researchers registered under the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/801">21 U.S.C. 801</external-xref> et seq.) to conduct research with controlled substances in schedule I of section 202(c) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/812">21 U.S.C. 812(c)</external-xref>).</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H53136890E44C4D2AB57266A033DC8C0C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs may conduct research on cannabis if the employees of the Department who are conducting such research are researchers registered under the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/801">21 U.S.C. 801</external-xref> et seq.) to conduct research with controlled substances in schedule I of section 202(c) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/812">21 U.S.C. 812(c)</external-xref>).</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


