<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9FCFBA945ED042DAAB26329C13E31CD5" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5736 IH: Comprehensive Addiction Recovery through Effective Employment and Reentry Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5736</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180509">May 9, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff of Tennessee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney of West Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001180">Mr. McKinley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001045">Mr. Harper</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000598">Mr. Rothfus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001305">Mr. Budd</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000563">Mr. Gibbs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001243">Mrs. Blackburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000582">Mr. Roe of Tennessee</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to establish a pilot program to help individuals in recovery
			 from a substance use disorder transition from treatment to independent
			 living and the workforce, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H8621FE1BA89F424D9FF8A0A54ECD7BF8" style="OLC">
 <section id="H95A8515C714F42EDB354042DBBF4E2BB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Comprehensive Addiction Recovery through Effective Employment and Reentry Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CAREER Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HCC6DD60ED6864BBCB82255919E698D85"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pilot program to help individuals in recovery from a substance use disorder transition to independent living and the workforce</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part B of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/243">42 U.S.C. 243</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H916312FE699E46838C4BA200EBC9A2F4" style="OLC">
				<section id="H19F58E83C34D4A54B88449662BA346D5"><enum>320B.</enum><header>Pilot program to help individuals in recovery from a substance use disorder transition to
			 independent living and the workforce</header>
 <subsection id="HCE8835A5C64D49B890F93C56B28363BF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a pilot program to award 5-year grants under subsection (b)(1) to States, and 1-year grants under subsection (b)(2) to States or Indian tribes, for the purpose of making subgrants to entities under subsection (c) to help individuals in recovery from a substance use disorder transition from treatment to independent living and the workforce.</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="H32F09D8842ED4405B45FA98930C88E0C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants</header>
						<paragraph id="HCA57FC7F1576444B9A34D51730DD13F2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>5-year grants</header>
 <subparagraph id="HC9706A1F33BF4AFEA46529F51E3496D6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award 5-year grants under this paragraph to 5 States that submit an application under paragraph (3). Such States shall be selected—</text>
 <clause id="HD6768FB5DFA6485F975DACCFFF3777BA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>from among the 10 States with the highest rate of death due to drug overdose per 100,000 people, based on data from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention for calendar years 2013 through 2017; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H988D0F2755CA463C9AD8911A0A9BF8E6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>based on the merits of the proposal included in such application and the preferences described in subparagraph (B).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18F33B45DB444A66A140F32BBC666F01"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Preferences</header><text>The Secretary, in selecting States for a grant under this paragraph, shall give priority to States from among the States described in subparagraph (A) with the combination of—</text>
 <clause id="H55B605D7A35845868B893B472206FFE8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the highest average rates of unemployment based on data provided by the Bureau of Labor Statistics for calendar years 2013 through 2017;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA0B03B80F29740648EACE345264165E7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the lowest average labor force participation rates based on data provided by the Bureau of Labor Statistics for calendar years 2013 through 2017; and</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HE14BD009095C472F8D9186B4242869B0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the highest prevalence of opioid use disorder based on data provided by the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration for calendar years 2013 through 2017 as may be available.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE71CAB7ACF3A4599A49B368A674A15A3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Grant funds</header>
 <clause id="H005F5220FD9D4E87870D52CB3190C888"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The funds from a 5-year grant awarded under this paragraph shall be provided to each of the 5 selected States on an annual basis for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023.</text>
								</clause><clause id="H2B27ECA0C8E4423AA7B92E934BE8F2D5"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Carry over</header>
 <subclause id="H733E458D82034305AA351C644DD1D9C5"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The funds awarded under clause (i) for a fiscal year shall remain available for the State to make subgrants under subsection (c) for such fiscal year, except a State may carry over (subject to subclause (II)) not more than 10 percent of such funds for the following fiscal year for such purpose.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H7F95DACE5C6C4EC28D400D57ADCB86E7"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Request</header><text>A State may make a request to the Secretary to carry over more than 10 percent of the funds awarded under clause (i) for a fiscal year for the following fiscal year for such purpose, and the Secretary may grant such request as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HCFDE6257957741BC88A2A9B4BFBA7FAA"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Amount for following fiscal year</header><text>Any amount carried over under this clause shall not impact the amount of the funds the Secretary awards the State for such following fiscal year.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="HB1D85BF871CE43EC88797E05B1C2E85A"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Return of funds</header><text>Any funds awarded under clause (i) that are not expended during the fiscal year for which the funds are awarded and that are not carried over for the following fiscal year under clause (ii) shall be returned to the Secretary to carry out this section. Any funds returned to the Secretary after fiscal year 2023 shall be returned to the general fund of the Treasury.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3B2563B9A1B4139A71655130468B7F7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>1-year grants</header>
 <subparagraph id="HA06C53DF3B824EC2A0B566AEBB82F6F1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall, for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023, award 1-year grants to States or Indian tribes under this paragraph that submit an application in accordance with paragraph (3). Such States or Indian tribes shall be selected for a grant under this paragraph based on criteria established by the Secretary.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H739EC1E2F6B64036BEE6A4DFF3969C1D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Grant funds</header>
 <clause id="HC46D12DE98D54BC79A08462B5271F4D7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The funds awarded through a grant under subparagraph (A) for a fiscal year shall remain available for the State or Indian tribe to make subgrants under subsection (c) for such fiscal year and may not be carried over for such following fiscal year.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD2A811DF950E457D9902F2B0DD04C683"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Return of funds</header><text>Any funds awarded through a grant under subparagraph (A) that are not expended during the fiscal year of the grant shall be returned to the Secretary to carry out this section. Any funds returned to the Secretary after fiscal year 2023 shall be returned to the general fund of the Treasury.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE34E2A57FA68416FB8791ABF7F146928"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Applications</header>
 <subparagraph id="HE9651A5FBE764D38BEBEBDC7F9AADB63"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each State desiring a grant under paragraph (1) and each State or Indian tribe desiring a grant under paragraph (2) shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may reasonably require for such grant.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75D0148931714BC3B34F8E693DF1A6C3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contents</header>
 <clause id="HABA56A5A3D784ECC9BB62E1B1686CEE7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An application submitted under subparagraph (A) shall contain such information as the Secretary may reasonably require, including a proposal for awarding subgrants under subsection (c) and a method for evaluating such subgrants.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H02B3B7A094A64FB4863DD980516192B7"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>5-year grants</header><text>An application submitted under subparagraph (A) for a grant awarded under subsection (b)(1) shall include an assurance that not less than 50 percent of the funds awarded through the grant will be used towards making subgrants under subsection (c) to the entities applying for such subgrants that serve the areas in the State with the highest prevalence of substance use disorder, based on data determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8BF68866B89048F6A1B7488EA177EC4B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Subgrants</header>
 <paragraph id="HCD97537F022A4027AD7CE15186AFE01B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each State that receives a grant under subsection (b)(1) and each State or Indian tribe that receives a grant under subsection (b)(2) shall award subgrants on a competitive basis to entities that meet the requirements under paragraphs (2) and (3).</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H429D5E3E321649F8B75B4E79CED78AEF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subgrant requirements</header>
 <subparagraph id="H10D512E889434AC2A89F06226FE9E2B2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An entity that desires a subgrant under this subsection shall submit an application to the State or Indian tribe at such time and in such manner as the State or Indian tribe may reasonably require.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H474932F37BAA4525BDF7E3A25BCA290F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>An application submitted under subparagraph (A) by an entity shall contain such information as the State or Indian tribe may reasonably require, including a demonstration that the entity has one or more of the following abilities:</text>
 <clause id="HE82135732B2145CDAF3199596C565EE2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The ability to partner with local stakeholders, which may include local employers, community stakeholders, and local and State governments, to identify gaps in the workforce due to the prevalence of substance use disorders.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA06A85FD4F3A44FEA74458C35DC2313F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The ability to partner with local stakeholders, which may include local employers, community stakeholders, and local and State governments, to offer transitional services, including employment and career counseling or job placement, to help individuals in recovery from a substance use disorder transition into the workforce.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H20FFC8B1C8B74E45A3D84256362D27BD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The ability to partner with local stakeholders, which may include local employers, community stakeholders, and local and State governments, to assist employers with informing their employees of the resources, such as treatment options for a substance use disorder, that are available to them.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5647FDA57D2B4671A9A27CA8F2ED4C4A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An entity receiving a subgrant under this subsection shall use the subgrant funds for more than one of the following:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H3D55B8E924564DC989BACB87CB9797BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To hire specialists with an expertise in treating substance use disorders, including through residential treatment, to assist with the treatment provided through a subgrant under this subsection, which may include the use of medication-assisted treatment.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1DA81ACD39DA484D9D29E0B049A79114"><enum>(B)</enum><text>To provide wrap-around services to encourage substance use disorder prevention, treatment, recovery, and rehabilitation, with a focus on ensuring long-term recovery and symptom remission.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD52666E76D8C44579DED4B281E2E4DA1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>To help individuals transition from inpatient treatment for a substance use disorder to the workforce by providing—</text>
 <clause id="H72DF79B626BE465491F64C04E4E1145A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>career services described in paragraph (2), and training services described in paragraph (3), of section 134(c) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3174">29 U.S.C. 3174(c)</external-xref>); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8A39104AA7DD433FB2DE17DD13131E83"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>related services described in section 134(a)(4)(D) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3174">42 U.S.C. 3174(a)(4)(D)</external-xref>).</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6CCF38626CB4684B8C79D5F1D9A9898"><enum>(D)</enum><text>To implement innovative technologies to make substance use disorder treatment more affordable and accessible, which may include the use of telemedicine, and may assist individuals in finding and maintaining employment throughout recovery.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H701DFA6FEBBC4D2BAB76EA79B7B4060E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>To provide ongoing outpatient substance use disorder treatment programs, including peer support meetings, for individuals who have recovered or are in recovery from a substance use disorder while they transition from receiving treatment for such disorder to entering the workforce and maintaining employment.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E31E9A89B484CF0AA7BF861F3679D81"><enum>(F)</enum><text>To assist patients, including through hiring case managers, care coordinators, or trained peer recovery coaches, in recovery from a substance use disorder, including through programs to provide services to develop daily living skills, provide counseling, and provide housing assistance, and through other appropriate Federal Government assistance programs.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0387E53FAAC4B43B8C4A067EDF7E87E"><enum>(G)</enum><text>With respect to an entity that provides the full continuum of substance use disorder treatment services, which may include detoxification, residential rehabilitation, recovery housing, evidence-based treatments (which may include the use of medication-assisted treatment), counseling, and recovery supports, to expand such services to include services that may include—</text>
 <clause id="H9F91706A73BC4212BE8AC7DA58DF40F0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>short-term prevocational training services, such as the development of learning skills, communication skills, interviewing skills, punctuality, personal maintenance skills, and professional conduct;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H65E8EB19E219405F9C704DAB112F4261"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>vocational training, which shall emphasize the skills or knowledge necessary for a particular job function or trade; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC0D182823DC94D0B967766879244DC75"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>care coordination throughout the short- and long-term substance use disorder recovery process.</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE0C9235AB8243F4882EE4B91D3C335E"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Any other service determined by the Secretary as necessary for achieving the goal of transitioning individuals from treatment for substance use disorders to independent living and the workforce or to encouraging substance use disorder prevention in the workforce.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6518AF8533954FE69FE0C9D96A4DE7F7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Secretary may, in carrying out the pilot program under this section, consult with the Assistant Secretary for Substance Use and Mental Health, the Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration, the Secretary of Labor, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, and the Secretary of Education.</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="H431B3509706D4F6EB9A4146A41CD678D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header>
						<paragraph id="H8FD5F7CF5C6C46E9B2FEB9183805A504"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reports to the Secretary</header>
 <subparagraph id="H935E08B4C1094FFF804EBF1BFA244914"><enum>(A)</enum><header>5-year grants</header><text>Not later than December 31, 2021, each State that has received a grant under subsection (b)(1) shall report to the Secretary on its progress and effectiveness in meeting the objectives of the pilot program under this section, including the progress and effectiveness of the entities receiving subgrants under subsection (c) as demonstrated through reports of such progress and effectiveness submitted to the State by such entities.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB23C7F5D111C43D6BCB6B69A2F9C6C3C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>1-year grants</header><text>Not later than December 31 of the fiscal year following the fiscal year for which a grant is awarded under subsection (b)(2), the State or Indian tribe receiving such grant shall report to the Secretary on its progress and effectiveness in meeting the objectives of the pilot program under this section, including the progress and effectiveness of the entities receiving subgrants under subsection (c) which may be demonstrated through reports of such progress and effectiveness submitted to the State or Indian tribe by such entities.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H22A0FE6581464F8E819D0B77EC915C82"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than December 31, 2024, the Secretary shall submit a report to Congress, including any applicable authorizing committee of the Senate or House of Representatives, evaluating the grants awarded under this section.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H93A5F669376A4BE7A9DB70017898B55E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $200,000,000, for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023, to carry out this section. Out of such amount appropriated for each such fiscal year—</text>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H44B904A1410B49288F78E7B5780CD82A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>75 percent shall be used to make grants under subsection (b)(1); and</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H695B560422E34A20A4B3EDAA5C1CFF48"><enum>(2)</enum><text>25 percent shall be used to make grants under subsection (b)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="H540AF917B5394A3180E151728ECB6FC3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Transitional housing services</header>
 <subsection id="H60C03230094443F7B4193813252380C0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 105(a) of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5305">42 U.S.C. 5305(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H36C43DC7958B4CBA9CEAA5DDFFA2814F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (25)(D), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7D1DEB4C49AA42A68E4ADAD63C6E8257"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (26), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H7B2008E362E646DDBF08156A4E3410F9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1B31029DC67F4D858FD22CCE12D9D2F9" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H43766782DC7F49B29C27532CCAD953A3"><enum>(27)</enum><text>providing temporary housing services to individuals who are transitioning out of substance abuse treatment programs for—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H0D2189431C2D420FA71944916D1D02A1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a period of not more than 24 months or until the individual secures permanent housing, whichever is earlier; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD55E573C5C54601A4499EFD7A9615B1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such longer period as the Secretary determines necessary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H67719FFCE2654194AD62AEB2FBA451F7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional CDBG authorization of appropriations</header> <paragraph id="HDFDF9C189B504301B0F399F53D1E3280"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition of covered entity</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>covered entity</term> means—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H9A405D75D165484BB233529F6346D3A9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State (as defined in section 102(a) of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5302">42 U.S.C. 5302(a)</external-xref>) that is among the 10 States with the highest rate of death due to drug overdose per 100,000 people, based on data from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention for calendar years 2013 through 2017; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB41320A1A7554020B30AC33913971B5E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any entitlement community located in a State described in subparagraph (A).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC19DEF4EBCA44DCF894A020A35FBB3C0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>In addition to any amounts appropriated for the community development block grant program under title I of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5301">42 U.S.C. 5301</external-xref> et seq.), there are authorized to be appropriated $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023, to be allocated by the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development on a competitive basis to covered entities to carry out the activity described in paragraph (27) of section 105(a) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5305">42 U.S.C. 5305(a)</external-xref>), as added by subsection (a).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H816966BA78EE4708BBF398C420207BA9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Preferences</header><text>In allocating amounts authorized to be appropriated under paragraph (2), the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall give priority to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE41F503B3439499B98595AEB4CE48F7C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>States from among the States described in paragraph (1)(A) with a combination of—</text> <clause id="H51733355B4A74D5BA5B6F95986A1BAF2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the highest average rates of unemployment based on data provided by the Bureau of Labor Statistics for calendar years 2013 through 2017;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC94F1F3381CA428ABDD668F9A899D7A3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the lowest average labor force participation rates based on data provided by the Bureau of Labor Statistics for calendar years 2013 through 2017; and</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H2FC6FABC02034369A41200FDA6F29A99"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the highest prevalence of opioid use disorder based on data provided by the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration for calendar years 2013 through 2017 as may be available; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCEAC3B1818A24E4D9126F86E22D72352"><enum>(B)</enum><text>entitlement communities located in a State described in clause (i), (ii), or (iii) of subparagraph (A).</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HFDFA918622F34D3997F77EC36986C53F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Substance use disorder transition activities</header>
 <subsection id="HD934D92B0141497E961FA08C2B1409C7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reservations for State activities</header><text>Section 133(a)(1) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3173">29 U.S.C. 3173(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H1BF9E9CD6A984FB29AE0A35431D5CFE1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The Governor</quote> and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3C8ACB7D16514CE6A7FC35F7468D564F" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H2BE84B69A87A45E590E7C9A800DA26E8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Governor</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7D2F7556456D4AB399B6C17B26836A7D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFDAB978BE42843D69BB3E6A8017524AC" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H0665CB1E775F4B35B00A2B6B77546D27"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Substance use disorder transition activities</header> <clause id="H6CB47AC13F764236BD890C4C00442C2F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Adult and dislocated funds</header><text>Of the funds reserved as required under section 128(a)(1) and subparagraph (A), the Governor of a State with an application approved under section 134(a)(4) may reserve a sum of not more than 5 percent of each of the amounts allotted to the State under paragraphs (1)(B) and (2)(B) of section 132(b) for a fiscal year for substance use disorder transition activities described in section 134(a)(4). Notwithstanding sections 128(a)(2), 129(b), and 134(a), the Governor may not use an amount allotted under section 127(b)(1)(C) for those activities.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8AA97315E54648358735EB783355FF57"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Vocational rehabilitation funds</header><text>The Governor of a State with such an approved application may reserve funds as described in section 110(e) of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/730">29 U.S.C. 730(e)</external-xref>) for substance use disorder transition activities described in section 134(a)(4).</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0D23064DCE5847E1B0A5E83DC09C39E0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Statewide employment and training activities</header>
 <paragraph id="H0BE1DD0D7B244C5DBE0426404CBF1664"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 134(a)(1) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3174">29 U.S.C. 3174(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H361208E34BCA4AC283653B4B52E272E3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H38092F5FB7794CF495EC8165F3666BB0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), in the matter following clause (ii), by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB2AE88C67A544228F329FEF6F1332EC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA61D4FF545934B8FB28B13A62415C766" style="OLC"> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD97E0F6B4B7248619C9EA60FFDF29F18"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as described in section 133(a)(1)(B), may be used for substance use disorder transition activities as described in paragraph (4), regardless of whether the funds were allotted to the State under paragraph (1) or (2) of section 132(b).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H89C555F6B91347A785BAFE9BDAAE23AC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Substance use disorder transition activities</header><text>Section 134(a) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3174">29 U.S.C. 3174(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB3DD06FA28F445148CBFBA88A7240E38" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="HA24066BC8CCB4252A7B51A905D62D90C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Substance use disorder transition activities</header>
 <subparagraph id="HEB56E45F14FD42A68347FED25AAF147A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this paragraph:</text> <clause id="HABB8C8EC17F14EE78032995BA8E5B5E7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Appropriate secretary</header><text>The term <term>appropriate Secretary</term> means—</text>
 <subclause id="HB6E5E38EB3594386B3433DA55A20ADDB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>except as provided in subclause (II), the Secretary of Labor; or</text> </subclause><subclause id="H40C51E1020B7444F8B15F81BABD3063B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if the application involves funds reserved under section 110(e) of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/730">29 U.S.C. 730(e)</external-xref>), the Secretary of Labor and the Secretary of Education.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H6F256534FD824650BF9D2E1909D5AB38"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Substance use disorder</header><text>The term <term>substance use disorder</term> means such a disorder within the meaning of the term in title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290aa">42 U.S.C. 290aa</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
 </clause><clause id="H9AE9EDEDAE59416D95D5DCF5004F2618"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Substance use disorder transition activities</header><text>The term <term>substance use disorder transition activities</term> means activities authorized under subparagraph (D) or (E).</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0BAC20231F4741CAA5A2A39ECF003631"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Eligible states</header><text>To be eligible to use the funds reserved under clause (i) or (ii) of section 133(a)(1)(B) for substance use disorder transition activities described in this paragraph, a State shall—</text>
 <clause id="HEE60BAA4C0CF4E299D38756AE603B8C1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>submit to the appropriate Secretary an application seeking flexibility to use the reserved funds for such activities, and submit the application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the appropriate Secretary may require, including an assurance that the State will award subgrants to entities on the basis of the ability of the entities to provide the substance use disorder transition activities involved, including any programs that the entities propose to provide that lead to recognized postsecondary credentials; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H71206F9F892C4CEB845FF00FD71D0519"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>obtain approval of the application.</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C8930749FF14FD0995CF90AF3C5BB71"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Subgrants</header><text>An eligible State may use the funds reserved under clause (i) or (ii) of section 133(a)(1)(B) to make subgrants to one-stop operators and nonprofit organizations, to provide services under subparagraph (D) and (at the election of the State) subparagraph (E).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E92FD72C8D94E3FB487B37B52EFF94E"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Career services</header><text>An entity that receives a subgrant under subparagraph (C) shall use the subgrant funds to assist individuals in recovery from a substance use disorder in transitioning to the workforce, by providing career services (such as the services described in section 134(c)(2)) and related services, which may include one or more of—</text>
 <clause id="HDA97EB7CE71F42A28F0F2F962020910A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>providing ongoing career counseling, both before and after job placement, with a focus on individual employment preferences while weighing the skill needs of industries in the local area;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H32CC0D03D2984377B558D4AE9D6A1351"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>promoting systemic job development, by facilitating voluntary programs and relationships between participants and local employers to create potential employment opportunities;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H5A6CCA629943436ABB24CB13A19BF1AE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>providing benefits counseling—</text> <subclause id="H066C654528E445F8B119F999C4DFA003"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to ensure participants receive accurate information regarding how employment will affect access to various Federal programs, such as the Medicaid program established under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396</external-xref> et seq.) and the supplemental security income program established under title XVI of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1381">42 U.S.C. 1381</external-xref> et seq.); and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H0C44E63EEC3845009827EC4D8D3DEB2C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to advise participants on ways to transition away from the programs described in subclause (I) through maintaining employment;</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H3D4DDE9139E041ADAD5C465EEB595428"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>creating voluntary programs with employers to establish a work and treatment arrangement, such as an Employee Assistance Program, for employees in recovery from a substance use disorder;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H6655324509CF4825AEDBA6985839F90B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>providing educational materials or training to employers to enable the employers to inform their employees of the resources, such as treatment options for a substance use disorder, that are available to them; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H85D2D2AA6E5642ACB8F9F83DB8F27381"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>any other career services that are determined to be necessary by the appropriate Secretary and that would assist individuals in recovery from a substance use disorder in transitioning to the workforce.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0523450581F342FD9859CFC640C58736"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Training services</header><text>An entity that receives a subgrant under subparagraph (C) shall (at the election of the State) use the subgrant funds to assist individuals in recovery from a substance use disorder in transitioning to the workforce, by providing training services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBBCC041E268D4BEDB8D70D819F9E87E0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>Section 181 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3241">29 U.S.C. 3241</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H548A91D7472C47AA826EC173D6B8C619"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (g) as subsection (h); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0292D23C539D4EB5AE99ABEC37927963"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (f) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H86C6F8EC71EC4B26B2DCD4841CE33457" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H4789C3F78889477892E22860130FB7D1"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Relationship to other laws</header> <paragraph id="HF3C02B83D10B47848470A68F7946B605"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Disability nondiscrimination law</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), an employer that employs, or considers for employment, any individual who receives services under this section or under section 320B of the Public Health Service Act shall have an absolute defense to any claim (including a charge) of unlawful discrimination on the basis of disability under a covered law, that alleges that the employer discriminated against that individual (which may include refusing to hire or terminating the employment of the individual) based on alcohol addiction or past substance use disorder for which the individual receives such services.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA0A2C3A2963A4BFE92A1F7D37F01CE69"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in paragraph (1) shall be construed to eliminate the duty of the employer, to an employee who is an individual who receives such services, to provide a reasonable accommodation for an alcohol disorder, or a past substance use disorder, that is a disability under a covered law.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8AFBC147C0A6417588BD7C73064C6890"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H051A6F8115B04A95B33A045B42DDBD4B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Covered law</header><text>The term <term>covered law</term> means title I of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12111">42 U.S.C. 12111</external-xref> et seq.), title V of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/791">29 U.S.C. 791</external-xref> et seq.), or a State law (including local law), that prohibits discrimination on the basis of disability in employment.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H599283C44BCC434093F1A83A5BCD3B90"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Substance use disorder</header><text>The term <term>substance use disorder</term> means such a disorder within the meaning of the term in title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290aa">42 U.S.C. 290aa</external-xref> et seq.).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBB00A63DE0494476A01C1AE10D068126"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Other Core Programs</header><text>Section 110 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/730">29 U.S.C. 730</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE55BBD023A044D578BCB053E1EF4DA01" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H6AB890CCAF744C088658D60B22E77093"><enum>(e)</enum>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H3A000DC94B204C10A7F3CA5E31C9AB8E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the case of a transition State, from any State allotment under subsection (a) for a fiscal year, the State may reserve not more than 5 percent of the allotted funds for substance use disorder transition activities described in section 134(a)(4) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3174">29 U.S.C. 3174(a)(4)</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8A4E25052FC5407A9C6FAA339059EA26" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In this section, the term <term>transition State</term> means a State with an application approved under section 134(a)(4) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


