<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H64CAFBED56AD46A085E960527CDD2576" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5843 IH: The Benefits to Employment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5843</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180516">May 16, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001195">Mr. Smith of Missouri</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001172">Mr. Smith of Nebraska</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title IV–A of the Social Security Act, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HB1D1A156BDA04E6F9A2CFA265888B965" style="OLC">
 <section id="H45B3B7FC7C6543CEB020381ABB8DD389" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as <quote><short-title>The Benefits to Employment Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HC0CD88F364904AA3BE94E092E142D064"><enum>2.</enum><header>Expecting universal engagement and case management</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 408(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/608">42 U.S.C. 608(b)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE31D05C440C14749B6BBF69CCB18B57C" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="H49328CD0AB3C4ABDB24AD20A8294CD47"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Individual opportunity plans</header>
 <paragraph id="H0A60591E0C4748C2AEAA3153DCC823D6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The State agency responsible for administering the State program funded under this part shall make an initial assessment of the following for each recipient of assistance who is required to be engaged in work pursuant to section 407(c):</text>
 <subparagraph id="HBE0792CE52624D3E824A361B7E9AEF93"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The education obtained, skills, prior work experience, work readiness, and barriers to work of the individual.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC75A49A92FD14260B139F3B16DD76253"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The well-being of the children in the family of the individual and, where appropriate, activities or services (such as services offered by a program funded under section 511) to improve the well-being of the children.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H15BADC62A435470C849330CAB3D8ED7F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents of plans</header><text>On the basis of the assessment required by paragraph (1) of this subsection, the State agency, in consultation with the individual, shall develop an individual opportunity plan that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H732DE6C21DDA438AA8FB7CA59E35B89F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes a personal responsibility agreement in which the individual acknowledges receipt of publicly-funded benefits and responsibility to comply with program requirements in order to receive the benefits;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02521DC57DFC4A189327278DBF9EB34A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>sets forth the obligations of the individual to participate in work activities, and the number of hours per month for which the individual will so participate pursuant to section 407(c);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H727A786979E14310AFF04258775A24C3"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">sets forth an employment goal and planned short-, intermediate-, and long-term actions to achieve the goal, and, in the case of an individual who has not attained 24 years of age and is in secondary school or the equivalent, the intermediate action may be completion of secondary school or the equivalent;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H414364FB3F0E417EA5B500543DA3ADA8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>describes the job counseling and other services the State will provide to the individual to enable the individual to obtain and keep employment in the private sector;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82DED5E05057416A9F80F83D0B54C130"><enum>(E)</enum><text>may include referral to appropriate substance abuse or mental health treatment; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF66166CFE1A44C7DA4B98CB08AD0FB36"><enum>(F)</enum><text>is signed by the individual.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4B4BD3E08AE4CFBA3EF01FEB2986CC9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The State agency shall comply with paragraph (1) and (2) with respect to a work-eligible individual—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HA0C0904C24494B8598FF0E1D3CCA91E9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">within 180 days after the effective date of this subsection, in the case of an individual who, as of such effective date, is a recipient of assistance under the State program funded under this part (as in effect immediately before such effective date); or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0EEAA3EB345B4596BCD6343150F01F77"><enum>(B)</enum><text>within 60 days after the individual is determined to be eligible for the assistance, in the case of any other individual.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H190E1D4AD5C845CF9407510270D423DF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Penalty for noncompliance by individual</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to any other penalties required under the State program funded under this part, the State may reduce, by such amount as the State considers appropriate, the amount of assistance otherwise payable under the State program to a family that includes an individual who fails without good cause to comply with an individual opportunity plan developed pursuant to this subsection, that is signed by the individual.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HEA1718D100A54E229E298EDE41A648BD"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Periodic review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The State shall meet with each work-eligible individual assessed by the State under paragraph (1), not less frequently than every 90 days, to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HAD4D93B04EDD4F49A7563C0E3DFC76FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>review the individual opportunity plan developed for the individual;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8774ECB98B604DEA9041F88A56EECF3E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>discuss with the individual the progress made by the individual in achieving the goals specified in the plan; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC6A66B4131942EEBF464FAD85A454BD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>update the plan, as necessary, to reflect any changes in the circumstances of the individual since the plan was last reviewed.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H28BC2302A4C84757BCA960F509B7EA38"><enum>(6)</enum><header>State discretion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State shall have sole discretion, consistent with section 407, to define and design activities for families for purposes of this subsection, to develop methods for monitoring and reviewing progress pursuant to this subsection, and to make modifications to the plans developed pursuant to this subsection as the State deems appropriate to assist families in increasing their degree of self-sufficiency.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </section><section id="H5DE992A622BB406B9657A8E7A25C1FFE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The amendment made by this Act shall take effect on October 1, 2018.</text> </section></legis-body></bill> 

