<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H20ED19B56E9F4CDAA8BD8D95DC919055" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5330 IH: Iran Human Rights Accountability Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5330</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180319">March 19, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001084">Mr. Cicilline</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the imposition of sanctions on persons who are officials of the Government of Iran
			 or persons acting on behalf of that Government who are responsible for or
			 complicit in human rights abuses committed against citizens of the United
			 States or United States legal permanent resident aliens.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HD315392A2A864CB4A62DA2E2945F5258" style="OLC">
 <section id="H6BCD1AD3BB8E4224AD872F31D716E449" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Iran Human Rights Accountability Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H5552F3B6A8F5484CA41C82D71BEAE328"><enum>2.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions on persons who are officials of the Government of Iran or persons acting on behalf of that Government who are responsible for or complicit in human rights abuses committed against citizens of the United States or United States legal permanent resident aliens</header> <subsection id="HAF55DC2F43464904B5CC84BF900EA712"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 105(b)(1) of the Comprehensive Iran Sanctions, Accountability, and Divestment Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8514">22 U.S.C. 8514(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H2F9D245EE87545D7A532ED60FFC19C74"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the date of the enactment of this Act</quote> and inserting <quote>the date of the enactment of the Iran Human Rights Accountability Act of 2018</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H83387A11ACDB4C2F99E0CE865F720833"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or against citizens of the United States or United States legal permanent resident aliens,</quote> after <quote>June 12, 2009,</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9389814001BB4EA9BC0E3A7430DEB597"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming and clerical amendments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comprehensive Iran Sanctions, Accountability, and Divestment Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8501">22 U.S.C. 8501</external-xref> et seq.) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H4A6DC428DCDB4370A7F1EA1A39D43AE7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the heading of section 105, by inserting at the end before the period the following: <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">or against citizens of the United States or United States legal permanent resident aliens</header-in-text></quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HF313B635203A4703A6DCCD114F0B03DD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the table of contents, by amending the item relating to section 105 to read as follows:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC38F44BA1D6F4973AB3570E7EABDDDE9" style="OLC">
						<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
							<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 105. Imposition of sanctions on certain persons who are responsible for or complicit in human
			 rights abuses committed against citizens of Iran or their family members
			 after the June 12, 2009, elections in Iran or against citizens of the
			 United States or United States legal permanent resident aliens.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2DA7276B7449471F8B80C4B00381E86C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act and apply with respect to the commission of serious human rights abuses described in section 105 of the Comprehensive Iran Sanctions, Accountability, and Divestment Act of 2010 on or after such date of enactment.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


