<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H442DB3C2400F4114BBB515D7FB9AB623" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5642 IH: Restoring and Improving Merger Enforcement Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5642</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180426">April 26, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001084">Mr. Cicilline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000288">Mr. Ellison</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001038">Mr. Crowley</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Clayton Act with respect to mergers.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H34A9922C10134C62BD560E15DFB543E7" style="OLC">
 <section id="H9EC7C62AA9B147179FDC79481CC24A67" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Restoring and Improving Merger Enforcement Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H567004F631414CC3A02DBF893917F2D6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Merger-specific efficiencies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 7 of the Clayton Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/18">15 U.S.C. 18</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA3323BF3BD8E4DB9920B8C8C6BF6EC20" style="traditional">
 <paragraph id="H1BD2EF1E437E43638B881AED18C2BD41" indent="up1"><enum></enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining whether the effect of such acquisition may be substantially to lessen competition, or to tend to create a monopoly, a court may consider a claimed efficiency of such acquisition only if it could not be accomplished in the absence of such acquisition, it is verifiable, and it would promote competition.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H11612D41A35D4791834651BBB58EFC3A" indent="up1"><enum></enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person against whom an action is brought for a violation of this section shall have the burden to establish, by the preponderance of the evidence, that the claimed efficiency will eliminate the substantial lessening of competition that may occur as a result of such acquisition.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </section><section id="H892656DF4E87450DAAE156CE5B13F675"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report on claimed efficiencies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 7A of the Clayton Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/18a">15 U.S.C. 18a</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDE1C8CCFC6B04F65AFF3AEE67A6DBD1F" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H367B01FCFE214FB09896CC2F8AFFDD71"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Information required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each person who enters into an agreement with the Federal Trade Commission or the United States to resolve a proceeding brought under the antitrust laws or under the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41</external-xref> et seq.) regarding an acquisition with respect to which notification is required under this section shall, on an annual basis during the 5-year period beginning on the date on which the agreement is entered into, submit to the Federal Trade Commission or the Assistant Attorney General, as applicable, information sufficient for the Federal Trade Commission or the United States, as applicable, to assess the source, and the resulting magnitude and extent, of any cost-saving efficiencies or any consumer benefits that were claimed as a benefit of the acquisition and the extent to which any cost savings were passed on to consumers.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


