<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6D0B3A65C9044868B7B2C182857AFECD" public-private="private" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5189 IH: To authorize the President to award the Medal of Honor to Francis E. Normoyle for acts of valor during the Korean War while a member of the Navy.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">V</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5189</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180306">March 6, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the President to award the Medal of Honor to Francis E. Normoyle for acts of valor during the Korean War while a member of the Navy.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9C2F1A1DB48C4F12994C7F5E08B23C4F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD9722E11C61946B68E271A43AE26C3EF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Authorization for award of Medal of Honor to Francis E. Normoyle for acts of valor during the Korean War</header> 
<subsection id="HFEEBFB37D30D427B8D2C01983372B3BD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Waiver of time limitations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding the time limitations specified in section 6248 of title 10, United States Code, or any other time limitation with respect to the awarding of certain medals to persons who served in the Armed Forces, the President may award the Medal of Honor under section 6241 of such title to Francis E. Normoyle for the acts of valor during the Korean War described in subsection (b).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H504AFE7D794840A6A8E35A16DAD5BBB3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Acts of valor described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The acts of valor referred to in subsection (a) are the actions of then Hospital Corpsman Petty Officer Third Class Francis E. Normoyle on September 25, 1950, during the Korean War as a member of the Navy, for which he was previously awarded the Silver Star.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

