<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1BCF31B8428F45A9899FFA6066543B1F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5588 IH: To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to seek to enter into an agreement with the city of Vallejo, California, for the transfer of Mare Island Naval Cemetery in Vallejo, California, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5588</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180423">April 23, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to seek to enter into an agreement with the city of Vallejo, California, for the transfer of Mare Island Naval Cemetery in Vallejo, California, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HFA5AFD04C550438E95F694945DB4C2E4" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7673AB0935FF49ADA4CD49298389DB5F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Transfer of Mare Island Naval Cemetery to Secretary of Veterans Affairs for maintenance by National Cemetery Administration</header> 
<subsection id="H1C29EA8B0F8244FDB204A7512A9A95CF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall seek to enter into an agreement with the city of Vallejo, California, under which the city of Vallejo shall transfer to the Secretary all right, title, and interest in the Mare Island Naval Cemetery in Vallejo, California, at no cost to the Secretary.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H0CF31ACF4B164535864FD58D02777F52"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Maintenance by NCA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> If the Mare Island Naval Cemetery is transferred to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs pursuant to subsection (a), the National Cemetery Administration shall maintain the cemetery as a national shrine.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


