<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HE1877D3F44CD4D15830C27386B94E54B" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5532 IH: Reconstruction Era National Historical Park Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5532</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180417">April 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000537">Mr. Clyburn</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S000051">Mr. Sanford</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To redesignate the Reconstruction Era National Monument as the Reconstruction Era National
			 Historical Park, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H423F121F39714B1A875C3EC25625BD04" style="OLC">
 <section id="H9C484A4946464FC1AE86FEB515CF778E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Reconstruction Era National Historical Park Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H2D8B158CD6E04AF09E10FC5CCC8FFF2B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reconstruction Era National Historical Park</header> <subsection id="H2E5736E47CE442C5A9B55EAC0EFF41E5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
 <paragraph id="HBADF42B764FE4E2890C1009695AF972C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Historical Park</header><text>The term <term>historical park</term> means the Reconstruction Era National Historical Park.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H6DE291EC15CC48E995232188C818A954"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Map</header><text>The term <term>map</term> means the maps entitled <quote>Reconstruction Era National Monument Old Beaufort Firehouse,</quote> numbered 550/135,755 and dated January 2017; <quote>Reconstruction Era National Monument Darrah Hall and Brick Baptist Church,</quote> numbered 550/135,756 and dated January 2017; and <quote>Reconstruction Era National Monument Camp Saxton,</quote> numbered 550/135,757 and dated January 2017, collectively.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB75989BF0F61420BBDDD31858BB33D80"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Network</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Network</term> means the Reconstruction Era National Historic Network established pursuant to this Act.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H7AA8467ADF1649D089FFBE9EFB84A60A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5D10F2A73C6C48D887077DC6A7A3142C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header>
				<paragraph id="HE50BCE90216143DC938B6B7053710317"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Redesignation of Reconstruction Era National Monument</header>
 <subparagraph id="H9EA68E7AC665418FB0D7DB3726EB7D1D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Reconstruction Era National Monument is redesignated as the Reconstruction Era National Historical Park, as generally depicted on the map.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC938AC20A4414CEF904C5AE9E4B24B55"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Availability of funds</header><text>Any funds available for the purposes of the Reconstruction Era National Monument shall be available for the purposes of the historical park.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77B7CD00C6D04CD09467B77566BFF190"><enum>(C)</enum><header>References</header><text>Any references in a law, regulation, document, record, map, or other paper of the United States to the Reconstruction Era National Monument shall be considered to be a reference to the historical park.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E73D64D015D43D4A80EEA21420E6F78"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Boundary Expansion</header>
 <subparagraph id="HA654D753EB5142A995597F2E102257F2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Beaufort National Historic Landmark District</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary is authorized to acquire land or interests in land within the Beaufort National Historic Landmark District that has historic connection to the Reconstruction Era. Upon finalizing an agreement to acquire land, the Secretary shall expand the boundary of the historical park to encompass the property.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEB38701CFDAA48AEB5E563AA3A7E5DFA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>St. Helena Island</header><text>The Secretary is authorized to acquire the following and shall expand the boundary of the historical park to include acquisitions under this authority:</text>
 <clause id="H3C118EEB031549B19ECAB3D02974B4F7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Land and interests in land adjacent to the existing boundary on St. Helena Island, South Carolina, as reflected on the map.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H03E39F02DB6C4F198EAEA542651DBC59"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Land or interests in land on St. Helena Island, South Carolina, that has a historic connection to the Reconstruction Era.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H48E794E5F483492D86F41F58AB71AEEF"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Camp Saxton</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary is authorized to accept administrative jurisdiction of Federal land or interests in Federal land adjacent to the existing boundary at Camp Saxton, as reflected on the map. Upon finalizing an agreement to accept administrative jurisdiction of Federal land or interests in Federal land, the Secretary shall expand the boundary of the historical park to encompass that Federal land or interests in Federal land.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6C3BB9632DE24AC29D5FE65B93F06DB0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration</header>
 <paragraph id="H29062A7E7E444E5596F3F123606EF994"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall administer the historical park in accordance with this Act and with the laws generally applicable to units of the National Park System.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7DCD62B996824E14A7C713FAEE57B520"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Management Plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the management plan for the Reconstruction Era National Monument—</text> <subparagraph id="H094331A0B8D849F0AEAB539E5F838D8D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has not been completed on or before the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall incorporate all provisions of this Act into the planning process and complete a management plan for the historical park within 3 years; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF7DCC3DF58EF448082728E78B79CDE1A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has been completed on or before the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall update the plan incorporating the provisions of this Act.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H942301D915744E5EA48DFE906904355F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Reconstruction Era National Historic Network</header>
 <subsection id="HD3FB2F31E0AE4506B5F95ECBB829B6C4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="H5C7F731195024A08ACA993C9D9E903CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish, within the National Park Service, a program to be known as the <quote>Reconstruction Era National Historic Network</quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H98766D3A4B474E288F9978E82504B86B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, solicit proposals from sites interested in being a part of the Network; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF9B9CF48E43E4DD787A84A3DFF248FA2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>administer the Network through the Reconstruction Era National Historical Park.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H66D5E029762B47D19BAB3350A8513285"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties of Secretary</header><text>In carrying out the Network, the Secretary shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="HB124D85AF97E45A3B7C6A04F65EF24F5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>review studies and reports to complement and not duplicate studies of the historical importance of Reconstruction Era that may be underway or completed, such as the National Park Service Reconstruction Handbook and the National Park Service Theme Study on Reconstruction;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBF4C72A0A6944385BA6C892D1EB4466E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>produce and disseminate appropriate educational and promotional materials relating to the Reconstruction Era and the sites in the network, such as handbooks, maps, interpretive guides, or electronic information;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF33262BC7ABA404BA04F8E0B0F6585F5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>enter into appropriate cooperative agreements and memoranda of understanding to provide technical assistance;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H1857ED7421C24A718F081664C8870B37"><enum>(4)</enum>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H154803FD24824DDA917DDF4BA37D93B5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>create and adopt an official, uniform symbol or device for the Network; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H408D79A5A96E46C797B4FD981AB80D2B" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>issue regulations for the use of the symbol or device adopted under subparagraph (A); and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H65CBC1ADD6304D8B9C5252414F4DAED7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>conduct research relating to Reconstruction and the Reconstruction Era.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H83BE3824CA8C42068E8A353223CB55C1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The Network shall encompass the following elements—</text>
 <paragraph id="HF38593702F6E49B3B2959C5E011FF7F4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>all units and programs of the National Park Service that are determined by the Secretary to relate to the Reconstruction Era;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H093B850B16174B9C91EFD103DBF3B492"><enum>(2)</enum><text>other Federal, State, local, and privately owned properties that the Secretary determines—</text> <subparagraph id="H6AAA3343FB32447B83DBAFEA191FB5FC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>relate to the Reconstruction Era; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8638F83F15A44B78BB7F44A6B7E191CB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are included in, or determined by the Secretary to be eligible for inclusion in, the National Register of Historic Places; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA99C3B77415E46C88A9C9B5CB3EAA0D8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>other governmental and nongovernmental sites, facilities, and programs of an educational, research, or interpretive nature that are directly related to the Reconstruction Era.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE5260EEAD1C4F3097F1A1B0C3E67ED3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Cooperative agreements and memoranda of understanding</header><text>To achieve the purposes of this Act and to ensure effective coordination of the Federal and non-Federal elements of the Network and units and programs of the National Park Service, the Secretary may enter into cooperative agreements and memoranda of understanding with, and provide technical assistance to, the heads of other Federal agencies, States, units of local government, regional governmental bodies, and private entities.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA2412F39D41B487292868BCDFE58B722"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Network defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Network</term> means the Reconstruction Era National Historic Network established pursuant to this Act.</text> </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H05D9E05E90D54E74A6C17F9FEA62F9D6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this section $5,000,000 for each fiscal year.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


