<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9007E07ABD814C1B987AD11FF3DCD18A" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5603 IH: Access to Telehealth Services for Opioid Use Disorders Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5603</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180424">April 24, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to provide the Secretary of Health and Human
			 Services authority to waive certain Medicare telehealth requirements in
			 the case of certain treatment of an opioid use disorder or co-occurring
			 mental health disorder.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HAF3358CE68E44117A705756F73A08110" style="OLC">
 <section id="H3AC95BB83A124B73B11E30B2242F1620" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Access to Telehealth Services for Opioid Use Disorders Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H5C5B35703743418BA6FBA97004D4BE17"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authority to waive certain Medicare telehealth requirements in the case of certain treatment of an opioid use disorder or co-occurring mental health disorder</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1834(m) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(m)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H7CFBE4259CCA483398F2E3F4830F2CF1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(B)(i), by inserting <quote>and paragraph (7)(E)</quote> after <quote>subject to clause (ii)</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB3078A21F0E447DA9749EC5D809D3F6D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDD3F64EA6977446BA5FD5729644C8280" style="OLC">
					<paragraph id="H608A0AFC6FF4436786BDFE523E233625"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Authority to waive certain requirements in the case of certain treatment of opioid use disorder or
			 co-occurring mental health disorder</header>
 <subparagraph id="H0EDB51B1ADBD4648B86CEA593AAC2EA2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of payment under this subsection, in the case of telehealth services furnished on or after January 1, 2019, to an eligible beneficiary (as defined in subparagraph (F)(i)) for the treatment of an opioid use disorder or a mental health disorder that is co-occurring with an opioid use disorder, the Secretary may waive any of the requirements described in subparagraph (B) if the conditions described in clauses (i), (ii), and (iii) of subparagraph (D) are met with respect to such waiver.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D978AE603F842E18FB61A283EFF1031"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this paragraph, the requirements described in this subparagraph include—</text> <clause id="H2DCF995C0F864759862C5709DC93EF46"><enum>(i)</enum><text>requirements relating to qualifications for an originating site under paragraph (4)(C)(ii);</text>
 </clause><clause id="H7495CFCD857342C1899EC0EE7099C155"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>geographic limitations under paragraph (4)(C)(i) (other than applicable State law requirements, including State licensure requirements); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H46783184172B4AD7A3E6435D978CAA1A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any limitation on the use of store-and-forward technologies described in paragraph (1).</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF6CB03ECA57D411F88EF0321481EEE7A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Identification of part B codes for application of waivers</header> <clause id="HFA7CB5D0696843A3BDE0891503F8D323"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, the Secretary shall review evidence related to codes under this part for telehealth services for the treatment of substance abuse and behavioral health that have been approved by the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services as part of the process established under paragraph (4)(F)(ii) for purposes of determining the codes for which a waiver applied under this paragraph would meet one or more of the conditions described in subparagraph (B). In carrying out this clause, particular priority should be given to reviewing evidence related to codes for behavioral health services that would be appropriate to provide to individuals receiving treatment from an opioid agonist treatment practitioner.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H2B10D427EDA94E7DBEB49797E6193727"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Annual review process</header><text>The Secretary shall review evidence pertaining to substance abuse and behavioral health codes as part of the annual process under paragraph (4)(F)(ii) to determine if a waiver may be granted.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BE35767EF2443D5BBA8601279865493"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Conditions for waiver</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the conditions described in this subparagraph, with respect to a waiver of any requirement described in subparagraph (B), are each of the following:</text>
 <clause id="H494667ADBB184E8A84B304E53CF705B8"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary determines that the application of the waiver is expected to—</text> <subclause id="H49B283AB186E489C9BBEA59076AF1B82"><enum>(I)</enum><text>reduce spending under this title without reducing the quality of care;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H138FDF3013A348B0ABD869D1D83580AE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>improve the quality of care without increasing spending; or</text> </subclause><subclause id="HB49F0D67485146B593F0509734051225"><enum>(III)</enum><text>increase access to behavioral health and substance use services for individuals with opioid use disorders.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H8FDB8D59993541998851B488EC9A6630"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chief Actuary of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services certifies that the condition described in clause (i) or (iii) is met.</text> </clause><clause id="H91FAE589CB6D4364874730F4D2EC03FF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The Secretary determines that such waiver would not deny or limit the coverage or provision of benefits under this title for individuals.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0099F4F59214F939643843DD6A6E465"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Treatment of originating site facility fee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No facility fee shall be paid under paragraph (2)(B) to an originating site with respect to a telehealth service for which payment is made under this subsection by reason of a waiver under this paragraph if payment for such service would not be permitted under this subsection without such waiver.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H85F795D0775247D886D6BFB2F34EF343"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this paragraph:</text> <clause id="HD7AFC086757E4908AAB07D40B30D261F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Eligible beneficiary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>eligible beneficiary</quote> means an individual who—</text>
 <subclause id="H8E4CE26C8C0C47FD9D9EAAC1267E30BB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is entitled to benefits under part A and enrolled for benefits under this part;</text> </subclause><subclause id="H5C3DC002958443019BDF35D8086B64F1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is not enrolled in a Medicare Advantage plan under part C;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HCBA36DA803CF4A659CDCAD6A1FA6AB70"><enum>(III)</enum><text>has a diagnosis for an opioid use disorder; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H6237C4BF3C7E41AC8417715883F7B689"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>meets such other criteria as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H0500EE0373184C5E8357A8D77BE8D747"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Opioid agonist treatment practitioner</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>opioid agonist treatment practitioner</quote> means a practitioner who—</text> <subclause id="H1144E0E77FCF46BC8E96AA1C553621F4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is enrolled under section 1866(j); and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H44C1B786F9F04947BCC59115BFA5FE6C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is authorized to prescribe or dispense opioid agonist treatment medication for maintenance or detoxification treatment pursuant to a waiver under section 303(g)(2) of the Controlled Substances Act.</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3ACCA5F13A9943789A94BE742ADF12AB"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 5 years after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on the impact of any waivers granted under this paragraph on—</text>
 <clause id="HD6349F5FEFA443429FB47275EBB9B5D7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any change in utilization rates for behavioral health services for opioid use disorders;</text> </clause><clause id="H7A492BE419754D6595E5E4D3A73C70F8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any change in rates or average length of time of retention in treatment for opioid use disorders;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC7D7521C0D394A4483EF049A9BB91B41"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any change in emergency department visits related to opioid overdoses; and</text> </clause><clause id="H30B63F9314ED4ABD9B69C6FF52E68EAE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any change in overdose deaths related to opioids abuse.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0C1EA33269A495AB5D64BCCCE958C3A"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of carrying out this paragraph, in addition to funds otherwise appropriated, the Secretary shall provide for the transfer, from the Federal Supplementary Medical Insurance Trust Fund under section 1841, of $2,000,000 to the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services Program Management Account.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body>
</bill>


