<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB02988F7B0244CE3B504FDB3C2807043" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4881 IH: Precision Agriculture Connectivity Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4881</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180125">January 25, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000566">Mr. Latta</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000565">Mr. Loebsack</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Federal Communications Commission to establish a task force for meeting the
			 connectivity and technology needs of precision agriculture in the United
			 States.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H0BE056A0465C44658A4002B0AC02FEA2" style="OLC">
 <section id="H97DF101754E5483AA9E9908726A5BDE4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Precision Agriculture Connectivity Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H7E2CD5E20DAB427FAD1D98BBBBFF16C2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H4FC167D73933403C89FD7386BA5A40BA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Precision agriculture technologies and practices allow farmers to significantly increase crop yields, eliminate overlap in operations, and reduce inputs such as seed, fertilizer, pesticides, water, and fuel.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4AF9D16831F648ADA46396810A4AE77A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>These technologies allow farmers to collect data in real time about their fields, automate field management, and maximize resources.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5CCD7284389E4D57AF87FF3E330DB55C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Studies estimate that precision agriculture technologies can reduce agricultural operation costs by up to 25 dollars per acre and increase farm yields by up to 70 percent by 2050.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0A375F7316D947DBA9998E45AF1A197B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The critical cost savings and productivity benefits of precision agriculture cannot be realized without the availability of reliable broadband Internet access service delivered to the cropland and ranchland of the United States.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA16A33CD5F7A452FA329E0996865086A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The deployment of broadband Internet access service to unserved and underserved cropland and ranchland is critical to the United States economy and to the continued leadership of the United States in global food production.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H07A2590DBA664DCEB46D067C4AE5E4BF"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Despite the growing demand for broadband Internet access service on cropland and ranchland, broadband Internet access service is not consistently available where needed for agricultural operations.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAF38EFECE8734062BE5DCD4CBF88D793"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The Federal Communications Commission has an important role to play in the deployment of broadband Internet access service infrastructure on unserved and underserved cropland and ranchland to promote precision agriculture.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="HDFC6563A26BB41DE8E0009C837E41F80"><enum>3.</enum><header>Task force</header>
			<subsection id="HC28439EB17DD4C2EA64965FAEB2AF7E7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header>
 <paragraph id="H988CE119429C496783171FD76A821441"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In this section—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H99F0BF254B4D4CCE90787795A0BC5468"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <term>broadband Internet access service</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8.2 of title 47, Code of Federal Regulations, or any successor regulation;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A958F491C6743C39EF8873F32AA7429"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Communications Commission;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1CADF013BDEE4DACBED22E4CC6AB5F88"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the term <term>Department</term> means the Department of Agriculture;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37A020AC3D084B06A62789C01AA09213"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Agriculture; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H85EBC4696D52413186883EBF2CA28CCD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the term <term>Task Force</term> means the Task Force for Meeting the Connectivity and Technology Needs of Precision Agriculture in the United States, as established under subsection (b).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC90F0D2134E947A7AB5C0DE7FA8B6174"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Agricultural terms</header><text>For purposes of this Act, the Secretary shall define the terms <term>agricultural operations</term>, <term>cropland</term>, and <term>ranchland</term>.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H54389E963131429D8D8DA25A4D192C2E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall establish the Task Force for Meeting the Connectivity and Technology Needs of Precision Agriculture in the United States.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H6D60AACE71A84DDDBAC0E6A1FE6DD9B0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header>
 <paragraph id="H5F48AD468ECF47C6835490445C5E5CE8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Task Force shall collaborate with the Secretary and public and private stakeholders in the agriculture and technology fields to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H6876666E15A54C34ACE078C5732E5B10"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify and measure current gaps in broadband Internet access service coverage of cropland and ranchland;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32F23B75379B4F2E8D7C443437C0318A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>assemble a comprehensive guide of all Federal programs or resources working to expand broadband Internet access service on unserved cropland and ranchland;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H641C47A830D8426BA880931712593FCD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>develop policy recommendations to promote the rapid, expanded deployment of fixed and mobile broadband Internet access service on unserved croplands and ranchlands, with a goal of achieving reliable service on 95 percent of croplands and ranchlands in the United States by 2025;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC20C5800F9CF4150B7EDBF3DC900AE69"><enum>(D)</enum><text>promote effective policy and regulatory solutions that encourage the adoption of broadband Internet access service on farms and ranches and promote precision agriculture;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2BEA0D2C31F4CBD9B964EE65F15107F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>propose new rules of the Commission or amendments to existing rules of the Commission to achieve the goals and purposes described in subparagraph (C);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H396AD427E5B24682941D39A28C0FB2BC"><enum>(F)</enum><text>recommend specific steps that the Commission and other Federal agencies should take to obtain reliable and standardized data measurements of broadband Internet access service coverage as may be necessary to target funding support to unserved croplands and ranchlands in need of broadband Internet access service; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74CCE4A65F0F451E8ACB66B2CCAE7102"><enum>(G)</enum><text>recommend specific steps that the Commission should take to ensure that the expertise of the Secretary and available farm data are reflected in developing Federal programs to deploy broadband Internet access service infrastructure and to direct available funding to unserved croplands and ranchlands where needed.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC656762BFABE4662B2FB68E80E31EE0E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Task Force shall consult with the Secretary to develop recommendations for the Commission that utilize the expertise, data mapping information, and resources of the Department that the Department uses to identify croplands, ranchlands, and other areas with agricultural operations.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HCB45D267C43A4C2BB0B815568ED78302"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Task Force shall be—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H682D48B1279F4C4692AC99E3214FB582"><enum>(1)</enum><text>composed of not more than 15 members who shall—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H8EDACDA921314365906A5188997CF152"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be selected by the Chairman of the Commission in consultation with appropriate staff of the Commission and with the Secretary; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA397E4864C104E40A0DF73EBA4D74A37"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H6FC0A7789E024A749877864190008587"><enum>(i)</enum><text>agricultural producers representing diverse geographic regions and farm sizes, including owners and operators of farms of less than 100 acres;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HAFC0E18740B04A5D9E66A96D914D1167"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Internet service providers, including regional or rural fixed and mobile broadband Internet access service providers and telecommunications infrastructure providers;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H609762EA93BB422ABCDD863B14B501BE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>representatives from the satellite industry;</text> </clause><clause id="HF8B3C8F1730346BC87FFEC8339CE9C6E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>representatives from precision agriculture equipment manufacturers, including drone manufacturers, manufacturers of autonomous agricultural machinery, and manufacturers of farming robotics technologies; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H060747E374B44FC0A6EB9D1A80F908BF"><enum>(v)</enum><text>representatives from State and local governments; and</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H4E7B9F0548234215BD83CC68F00092C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>fairly balanced in terms of technologies, points of view, and fields represented on the Task Force.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6F34C5873BA040358755F5AED7922C50"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which the Commission establishes the Task Force, and annually thereafter, the Commission shall submit to Congress a report that details—</text>
 <paragraph id="HA22EFFFE569447C3B5BB28C8B2AC339E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the status of fixed and mobile broadband Internet access service coverage of croplands and ranchlands;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAAA68D8BE1444280A5FC678BBDE23DD7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the projected future connectivity needs of agricultural operations, farmers, and ranchers; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H6419A325E81644CCB36CD4868BD57323"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the steps being taken to accurately measure the availability of high speed broadband Internet access service on croplands and ranchlands and the limitations of current, as of the date of the report, measurement processes.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H833D086953FD47049A912E82086B2949"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Existing funds</header><text>The Commission shall use existing funds of the Commission to carry out the Task Force and the duties of the Commission under this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H31BE45562FCF473089812CAD193DF43D"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Task Force shall terminate on January 1, 2025.</text> </subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

