<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H1AC2119B66524B91A3C403A2B972A459" key="H" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5471 IH: American Gateway Communities Economic Development and Conservation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5471</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180411">April 11, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001084">Mr. Cicilline</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000592">Mr. Poe of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of the Interior to establish a Gateway Communities Improvement Program, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form> 
<legis-body id="H1403C53897834DCBA145EED0916D14F6" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA3D3D4A2F2DE407D8CD16D063AEA99A5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Gateway Communities Economic Development and Conservation Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> <section id="H6A6560484EFB4FF3B64BEE6330C9EFED"><enum>2.</enum><header>Gateway Communities Improvement Program</header> <subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC1FF8A7C413B48169B65C479C4A605DF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Interior shall establish an American Gateway Communities Economic Development and Conservation Program (in this section referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>) to assist covered entities to improve gateways to units of the National Park System.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H2D0E640618A74568AA0C7234B25FF2FF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant authority</header><text>In carrying out the Program, the Secretary may award a grant, on a competitive basis, to a covered entity.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="H0A5DD74AE67E434DAFD7AD62EF578A66"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for a grant under the Program, a covered entity shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such form, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. Applications should address the economic development benefits associated with the proposed activity.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H00C20011C87848D0A066CC7B30ED4683"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grant uses</header><text>Grant amounts awarded under the Program may be used to—</text> <paragraph id="HC916B0CB58CC44179E8CB799065F6CDE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>facilitate a planning, study, or design component of an activity described in paragraphs (2), (3), (4), (5), or (6) in collaboration with local residents, businesses, elected officials, representatives of the unit of the National Park System nearby and other affected public agencies;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1FF7D3422148419C8AF905E3029637FC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prepare a general plan and visual design guidance that reflect the goals of the Gateway Community and are in harmony with the visual, historic and cultural character of the nearby unit of the National Park Service;</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H7BB9F419EB25438AAA2C41DFF1D04812"><enum>(3)</enum><text>carry out, with respect to a public space, a landscaping project that is consistent with local character and with the scenic, historic and cultural character of the nearby National Park System unit;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H51CB86C35724427F8F966B8EB510D0D1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide wayfinding and interpretation markers to assist visitors to the relevant unit of the National Park System with orientation or interpretation, including but not limited to markers at key sites of scenic, historic, or cultural value, so long as all wayfinding markers have a non-intrusive design that keeps with the character of the gateway community and the unit of the National Park System;</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H93F58383F3134C1F93E5445E608BC373"><enum>(5)</enum><text>establish a scenic easement to protect a view of the relevant unit of the National Park System; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H72A0D3E8C5C34F3599CDE09F9D1BC550"><enum>(6)</enum><text>mitigation of visual blight including screening or removal of elements not in keeping with the desired visual, historic and cultural character of the Gateway Community and the unit of the National Park System.</text> </paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE39AB25F8AA6472F97B4A66F4BF61D14"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Federal Share</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal share of the cost of an activity assisted with grant amounts awarded under the Program shall be not more than 50 percent.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HD69C5B4315374C248479B5F534E4AB16"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $2,000,000 to carry out the Program.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="HDF141006E9044D6DA322C3B91C4EC141"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Covered entity defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>covered entity</term> means a local government entity that serves an area located within 5 miles of a public entrance to a unit of the National Park System. The Secretary shall have the discretion of waiving the 5-mile limit in cases where compatibility between the visual, historic and cultural character of a gateway community beyond the 5-mile limit and the unit of the National Park System is significant to both as jointly attested to by the local government entity and the National Park Service.</text> </subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


