<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HD7B0B68802644DDA8D7FA5A038C967EC" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5329 IH: Poison Center Network Enhancement Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5329</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180319">March 19, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001284">Mrs. Brooks of Indiana</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="E000179">Mr. Engel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000213">Mr. Barton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000197">Ms. DeGette</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to reauthorize and enhance the poison center national
			 toll-free number, national media campaign, and grant program, and for
			 other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H30C0D40FCADB4D96A924624A70B16E52" style="OLC">
 <section id="HF1A6E000570A474C9979DD22A0B3F336" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Poison Center Network Enhancement Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H9DB5E55324BD4ADF955BF82711BF7823"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reauthorization of poison control centers national toll-free number</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1271 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300d-71">42 U.S.C. 300d–71</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF3BDE8F2685E40ECA98C22598BCA77D6" style="OLC">
				<section id="H2C3B4C1F073945098B3CBB470AA4CB8F"><enum>1271.</enum><header>Establishment and maintenance of the national toll-free number and enhanced communications
			 capabilities</header>
 <subsection id="HBAB6E8707B4C4512B7F278F35F64AAF0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall provide coordination and assistance to poison control centers, and to nationally recognized professional organizations in the field of poison control for—</text>
 <paragraph id="H638A0BF04EA14BD693B52380B6194AA1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the development, establishment, implementation, and maintenance of a nationwide toll-free phone number; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H26B2DD1790DF423AAADBD476BBDB671B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the enhancement of communications capabilities, such as text capabilities.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA9C2BBD0F96B487AA3C1C91894B3C7F7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall consult with nationally recognized professional organizations in the field of poison control to determine the best and most effective means of achieving the goals described in paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (a).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD0F0CDC4A9064A049387CC501DD3AD30"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to restrict the work of poison control centers or the use of their resources by the Secretary or other governmental agencies in assisting with public health emergencies, responses, or preparedness.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H72C812B1C63D44A0A22877149EE0790C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Proper standards for the routing of poison control center contacts</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Poison Center Network Enhancement Act of 2018</short-title>, the Federal Communications Commission, in consultation with the Secretary, shall take all actions necessary to ensure that contacts with the nationwide toll-free number supported under subsection (a)(1) are routed to the geographically proper poison control center based on the physical location of the person attempting to reach the poison control center, rather than based on the area code of the contact device.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H19514470772545A08603330A47EF6353"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $700,000 for each of fiscal years 2020 through 2024.</text>
					</subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="HFB4642D7602A4619997FF7E9C4A85B4A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Reauthorization of nationwide public awareness campaign to promote poison control center
 utilization</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1272 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300d-72">42 U.S.C. 300d–72</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFD28AF95E71F4405A00499C86897D7DB" style="OLC"> <section id="H2922E3BD06514464936AB6235E5F0A0D"><enum>1272.</enum><header>Nationwide public awareness campaign to promote poison control center utilization and their public health emergency response capabilities</header> <subsection id="H37A4846441D3448A9C22CEFDBAF72278"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="HD19D456390574234912E2D6D161CBEED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>carry out, and expand upon, a national public awareness campaign to educate the public and health care providers about—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H3F7CAEC9E7544DBAA67929AD97BE8F04"><enum>(A)</enum><text>poisoning and toxic exposure prevention;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H29151B4B968C4C33A215E9B25FF778FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the availability of poison control center resources in local communities;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77A743FEF60D4C72AC024AA0BA8C9CD4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>poison control center drug information and misuse intervention; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A86DFE49E2B427082AEA345ABAE4CFD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>poison control center public health emergency response capabilities; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AAD1F6FCBAE4410A1E7BCAD9DB2E48C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as part of such campaign, highlight the nationwide toll-free number and enhanced communications capabilities supported under section 1271.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H75F878AFEC5E49A69D2B1B077F075C36"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out and expanding upon the national campaign under subsection (a), the Secretary shall consult with nationally recognized professional organizations in the field of poison control response for the purpose of determining the best and most effective methods for achieving public awareness.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HB1F57EAED7FE48B7A6F3FEBB6AA2A9E6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contract with entity</header><text>The Secretary may carry out subsection (a) by entering into contracts with one or more public or private entities, including nationally recognized professional organizations in the field of poison control and national media firms, for the development and implementation of the awareness campaign under subsection (a), which may include—</text>
 <paragraph id="HA6EDF0F6B52A482C813E6EC0A9D85BF6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the development and distribution of poisoning and toxic exposure prevention, poison control center, and public health emergency awareness and response materials;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H33F8D754F8E64E66B93A493D7B25650B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>television, radio, internet, and newspaper public service announcements; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H867A35D527C74079A763AD48C06A118A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>other means and activities to provide for public and professional awareness and education.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H79BB98FCCB1346729AFCB860ADCE589B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="HEC0CAB1DA8784365819C6AC80B6C2834"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish baseline measures and benchmarks to quantitatively evaluate the impact of the nationwide public awareness campaign carried out under this section; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HED6BDE231452470295208C86611DEC21"><enum>(2)</enum><text>on an annual basis, prepare and submit to the appropriate committees of Congress an evaluation of the nationwide public awareness campaign.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6309B0AFFC9A47758688A4DCB108881C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section, $800,000 for each of fiscal years 2020 through 2024.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="H55A10796B4514419830214E1724AC79C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reauthorization of the poison control center grant program</header>
 <subsection id="H03BF28DFF975465E928E83C6A3979E6F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1273 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300d-73">42 U.S.C. 300d–73</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4C3CF5EB2CE74530AE031E95D0C491C9" style="OLC"> <section id="H268B928B20404CC38F3156F72090DCB1"><enum>1273.</enum><header>Maintenance of the poison control center grant program</header> <subsection id="H55AA1573CA9F4FE586D37EB8816D6D3D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization of program</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants to poison control centers accredited under subsection (c) (or granted a waiver under subsection (d)) and nationally recognized professional organizations in the field of poison control for the purposes of—</text>
 <paragraph id="H83246366ECA04A8DA2CC99F6588D38B3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>preventing, and providing treatment recommendations for, poisonings and toxic exposures including opioid and drug misuse;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5A46324E280045CE97A42AD6C42F569A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assisting with public health emergencies, responses, and preparedness; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H22E6707DC5D140AE952C007994473F38"><enum>(3)</enum><text>complying with the operational requirements needed to sustain the accreditation of the center under subsection (c).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H02656DE91E8D46A6A9DD2803DE224838"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional uses of funds</header><text>In addition to the purposes described in subsection (a), a poison center or professional organization awarded a grant under such subsection may also use amounts received under such grant—</text>
 <paragraph id="H0509897E70AB48658D42738BC355F9F5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to research, establish, implement, and evaluate best practices in the United States for poisoning prevention, poison control center outreach, opioid and drug misuse information and response, and public health emergency, response, and preparedness programs;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H813BCA6FEE00490EB9544D94B487C607"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to research, develop, implement, revise, and communicate standard patient management guidelines for commonly encountered toxic exposures;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4BC114295EAF4C1399C1F30421DDCE27"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to improve national toxic exposure and opioid misuse surveillance by enhancing cooperative activities between poison control centers in the United States and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and other governmental agencies;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9AB2236F417042FCAEB6D2599DE62ECB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to research, improve, and enhance the communications and response capability and capacity of the Nation’s network of poison control centers to facilitate increased access to the centers through the integration and modernization of the current poison control centers communications and data system, including enhancing the network’s telephony, internet, data, and social networking technologies;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H35E1836DA824487687DC7E027F35BAD0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to develop, support, and enhance technology and capabilities of nationally recognized professional organizations in the field of poison control to collect national poisoning, toxic occurrence, and related public health data;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD995881A10F64960A928C0E7E210728A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to develop initiatives to foster the enhanced public health utilization of national poison data collected by such organizations;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4F61A17D14F24049B436B866E77AEB7C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to support and expand the toxicologic expertise within poison control centers; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H46645D76A59E4984B9E982A602EDB6CF"><enum>(8)</enum><text>to improve the capacity of poison control centers to answer high volumes of contacts and internet communications, and to sustain and enhance the poison control center’s network capability to respond during times of national crisis or other public health emergencies.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7A519CDCAD1B4DB295FE6F0EB972F077"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Accreditation</header>
 <paragraph id="HF3AE5F7CC6B24A6A8D4747F979C80B3C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (d), the Secretary may award a grant to a poison control center under subsection (a) only if—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF98B4F8B68BA42BF8800DC7A3EE626E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the center has been accredited by a nationally recognized professional organization in the field of poison control, and the Secretary has approved the organization as having in effect standards for accreditation that reasonably provide for—</text>
 <clause id="H1AA88D0686244A939D3BEB317F8D1240"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the protection of the public health with respect to poisoning; and</text> </clause><clause id="HA27E7E0F2D04427AA81728D9EA9D62C6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the maintenance of the related capabilities listed in subsection (a); or</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H716063B243B647A09E20857F9C724542"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the center has been accredited by a State government, and the Secretary has approved the State government as having in effect standards for accreditation that reasonably provide for—</text>
 <clause id="H53CF849E5CED44FDA32E7AA64AB8A5DC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the protection of the public health with respect to poisoning; and</text> </clause><clause id="HD0A98750F15647F7BEFEA42D7AE334B4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the maintenance of the related capabilities listed in subsection (a).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E9F9B8A15E546089D408A50EF8E0EE7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual report to Congress</header><text>The Secretary shall annually submit a report to Congress that certifies that the accreditation standards described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (1)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H359AC923F49142EC9F5A96A81CCBD693"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are consistent in their content; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H83FCF0D76BF941C2BAA13A5AD766084B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide for the protection of the public health with respect to poisoning and the maintenance of the related capabilities listed in subsection (a).</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDD8B3D9760AA402195BC15E2F7663BB9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Waiver of accreditation requirements</header>
 <paragraph id="HA84E61D360044D06A5DF857DED068DA4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may grant a waiver of the accreditation requirements of subsection (c) with respect to a nonaccredited poison control center that applies for a grant under this section if such center can reasonably demonstrate that the center will obtain such an accreditation within a reasonable period of time as determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDF77D2105AE540AD80AC240C651834A3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Renewal</header><text>The Secretary may renew a waiver under paragraph (1).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HBD4314F2804944E3992A92A7F5B762F8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>In no case may the sum of the number of years for a waiver under paragraph (1) and a renewal under paragraph (2) exceed 5 years.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1C0BD1137A0F45ED9B35460B0AA80C46"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Supplement not supplant</header><text>Amounts made available to a poison control center under this section shall be used to supplement and not supplant other Federal, State, or local funds provided for such center.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H1488FA56F575420EB40048F5F40EBBEE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort</header><text>A poison control center, in utilizing the proceeds of a grant under this section, shall maintain the annual recurring expenditures of the center for its activities at a level that is not less than 80 percent of the average level of such recurring expenditures maintained by the center for the preceding 3 fiscal years for which a grant is received.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF8D6AF958F854FEA8A9691B89C4EB291"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section, $29,600,000 for each of fiscal years 2020 through 2024. The Secretary may utilize an amount not to exceed 6 percent of the amount appropriated pursuant to the preceding sentence for each fiscal year for coordination, dissemination, technical assistance, program evaluation, data activities, and other program administration functions, which are determined by the Secretary to be appropriate for carrying out the program under this section.</text>
						</subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H1E2CFFCC295F46CAB52146F2360B021E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1273 of the Public Health Service Act, as amended by subsection (a), applies beginning on October 1, 2019.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


