<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HECB079FF020345A8A75E0E96F1FF71E8" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4819 IH: Defending Economic Livelihoods and Threatened Animals Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4819</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180118">January 18, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000449">Mr. Fortenberry</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000487">Mr. Royce of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000179">Mr. Engel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000435">Ms. Ros-Lehtinen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000581">Mrs. Lawrence</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001270">Ms. Bass</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To promote inclusive economic growth through conservation and biodiversity programs that facilitate
			 transboundary cooperation, improve natural resource management, and build
			 local capacity to protect and preserve threatened wildlife species in the
			 greater Okavango River Basin of southern Africa.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H9801B97D6A2846E3841A58E3C21F9EE7" style="OLC">
 <section id="HA014032EFA4441D48F8EE99735395E46" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Defending Economic Livelihoods and Threatened Animals Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>DELTA Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HA2644DA5045F40479FBF11F46E371A9D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HA18CB4A5ACB2489782ABACEA88C59950"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The greater Okavango River Basin, which ranges from the highland plateau of northern Angola to northeastern Namibia and northern Botswana, is the largest freshwater wetland in southern Africa.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAFED0B33236E4C69A66C7E69D3BB36A4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The greater Okavango River Basin is the main source of water and livelihoods for over a million people, and the effective management and protection of this critical watershed will help advance important conservation and economic growth objectives for such countries, local communities, and the broader region.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC7DCF4FC8A264F2E81EB037894C14892"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The greater Okavango River Basin is home to the largest remaining elephant population in the world, as well as other threatened wildlife species.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H46082A3FA9A840CE900B73F75D31B9DB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Poaching and trafficking of threatened wildlife species in the greater Okavango River Basin has increased in recent years, and has the potential to undermine regional stability by disrupting local governance and management of resources, and supplanting key economic opportunities for community members.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HF97588B0C3D04A6DB4F0DC3556F8E1AE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that it is in the strategic interest of the United States to engage with the Governments of Angola, Botswana, and Namibia, along with donors, regional organizations, nongovernmental organizations, local communities, and the private sector, to advance conservation efforts and promote economic growth and stability in the greater Okavango River Basin.</text>
 </section><section id="H128208A2C4C349F9A0780152ADE01572"><enum>4.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States to promote inclusive economic growth through conservation and biodiversity programs that facilitate transboundary cooperation, improve natural resource management, and build local capacity to protect and preserve threatened wildlife species in the greater Okavango River Basin.</text>
		</section><section id="H8B17F846EAFF4BA0928BDF5C84200775"><enum>5.</enum><header>Strategy</header>
 <subsection id="H88870659983545DA925A96A3E3B9BC30"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State and the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, in coordination with other relevant Federal agencies, shall seek to work with the Governments of Angola, Botswana, and Namibia, and in partnership with donors, regional organizations, nongovernmental organizations, local communities, and the private sector, to develop a strategy to—</text>
 <paragraph id="HB0D49A23A206428A9E0F16A45C26C7DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>create and advance a cooperative framework to promote sustainable natural resource and wildlife management practices in the greater Okavango River Basin;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HECE675D09FC14ADA8609DC380129D5C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>protect traditional migration routes of elephants and other threatened wildlife species;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H137F13DA4AC841BF946240E171329CD0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>combat wildlife poaching and trafficking;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0894FA9D01994C868B09496B92A040DA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>address human health and development needs of local communities; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE84CBAF72A3B4C1E9F9275737682A0D3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>catalyze economic growth in such countries and across the broader region.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44D1550BF44C4D2EB6644C4C7494B4E4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The strategy established pursuant to subsection (a) shall include a description of efforts to—</text> <paragraph id="H78F2B64DB57142AA8279CE2961770FD5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>promote cooperative and sustainable natural resource and wildlife management policies and practices within and among the countries of Angola, Botswana, and Namibia, with a particular focus on the greater Okavango River Basin;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H556EC4981365433D9291EE6B6D357F98"><enum>(2)</enum><text>protect and restore wildlife habitats and traditional migratory patterns of elephants and other threatened species;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE4BF5F1CB82549969F96D63A4791C372"><enum>(3)</enum><text>combat wildlife poaching and trafficking in Angola, Botswana, and Namibia, including within regional and national parks and reserves, by building the capacity of the governments of such countries, local law enforcement, community leaders, and park rangers to detect, disrupt, and prosecute poachers and traffickers;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6F177369FA3F449883EF204C91E85E8C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote conservation as a foundation for inclusive economic growth and development within a comprehensive assistance strategy that places Angola, Botswana, and Namibia on a trajectory toward graduation from the need for foreign assistance;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF7752FC04DFA46A58E77704D93AAE352"><enum>(5)</enum><text>identify opportunities and mechanisms to leverage public-private partnerships to contribute to support the implementation of this strategy; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF4DE91C82C6D42BE87FE8D5A0DA03249"><enum>(6)</enum><text>establish monitoring and evaluation mechanisms, to include measurable goals, objectives, and benchmarks of success, that are included in grants, contracts, cooperative agreements to ensure the effective use of United States foreign assistance.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H9C35B97F4C1E42228C566CA31240BFCE"><enum>6.</enum><header>United States support for responsible natural resource management and elephant conservation</header>
 <subsection id="HBFF525DCC48D4C488F4CA6D2283E2235"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of State and the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, in coordination with other relevant Federal agencies, are authorized to prioritize and advance ongoing efforts to—</text>
 <paragraph id="H2039D7330B3B443B9C66B81D771A28A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>promote inclusive economic growth through responsible natural resource management and wildlife protection activities in the greater Okavango River Basin;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCDFEE83CE5114FB186E6F2F3794CAA4E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide technical assistance to governments and local communities in Angola, Botswana, and Namibia to create a policy-enabling environment for such natural resource management and wildlife protection activities; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H76FB6D561D73434EA5FF07694A532AD4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>build the capacity of local law enforcement, park rangers, and community leaders to combat wildlife poaching and trafficking.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDF1C63B414D94D8991EEFA5F504DB4ED"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination with private sector</header><text>The Secretary, the Administrator, and other relevant Federal agencies are authorized to work with the private sector and nongovernmental organizations to leverage public and private capital to promote sustainable resource management, combat wildlife poaching and trafficking, and support inclusive economic growth and local livelihoods in the greater Okavango River Basin.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H2F1D45D7A1C94E3BAAAAEF3C97F1A4EC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Monitoring and Evaluation</header><text>The Secretary and the Administrator shall establish monitoring and evaluation mechanisms, to include measurable goals, objectives, and benchmarks, to ensure the effective use of United States foreign assistance to achieve the objectives of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HA41ACD58A3784995841EEC0A0630E3A8"><enum>7.</enum><header>Report</header>
 <subsection id="H592C2C4215C5483AAB892E68E211A69A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State and the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, in coordination with other relevant Federal agencies, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the implementation of this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H59EF8FCD89DD43EFB8B8BD36D6E6D3AC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required under subsection (a) shall include a description of the strategy required by section 5, including—</text>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="H3743A568F1F24F92B98A2A973AB726A7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the monitoring and evaluation plans and indicators used to measure performance under the strategy;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB0FF49F0DABE443481ED37E32E116DE9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any legislative impediments to meeting the objectives of such strategy;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5C514F0D2A1C46239D660E16EE402A14"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the extent to which Angola, Botswana, and Namibia have demonstrated a commitment and willingness to cooperate to advance efforts described in section 5(b); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H347804D391954BC8A70B605E47C2541D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>progress made to date in meeting the objectives of such strategy.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H647CAC0C6F4F494281D541808B1BFF01"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text>
 <paragraph id="HB716539A92914CF28EC677B542C208F4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA45796AC0EA14A78A05C33446FDFC13B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

