<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H93C1C6D3C4A14A65AD305CAA1842B9FC" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5723 IH: Expanding Oversight of Opioid Prescribing and Payment Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5723</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180509">May 9, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M001180">Mr. McKinley</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Medicare Payment Advisory Commission to report on opioid payment, adverse
			 incentives, and data under the Medicare program.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H890B7011BE404E7D918213206052C197" style="OLC">
 <section id="H544DCDC00B30442AA4C320AE189E0485" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Expanding Oversight of Opioid Prescribing and Payment Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HCF14CD958CA040BCB8AA2EEC35324F26" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Medicare Payment Advisory Commission report on opioid payment, adverse incentives, and data under the Medicare program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than March 15, 2019, the Medicare Payment Advisory Commission shall submit to Congress a report on, with respect to the Medicare program under title XVIII of the Social Security Act, the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HB17E9CC597864DFE9DB3BA941BEE1AB3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of how the Medicare program pays for pain management treatments (both opioid and non-opioid pain management alternatives) in an inpatient and outpatient hospital setting.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5343E9625AEB4F07A2A389E380A577CA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The identification of incentives under the hospital inpatient prospective payment system under section 1886 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ww">42 U.S.C. 1395ww</external-xref>) and incentives under the hospital outpatient prospective payment system under section 1833(t) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(t)</external-xref>) for prescribing opioids and incentives under each such system for prescribing non-opioid treatments, and recommendations as the Commission deems appropriate for addressing any of such incentives that are adverse incentives.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA5CAE0EA43554EECBC2595E2E4B14E16"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A description of how opioid use is tracked and monitored through Medicare claims data and other mechanisms and the identification of any areas in which further data and methods are needed for improving data and understanding of opioid use.</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


