<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H696D04C665194086AFC1450DA0381372" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5617 IH: No Enforcement, No Grant for Sanctuary Cities Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5617</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180425">April 25, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000625">Mr. Donovan</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000605">Mr. Perry</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001269">Mr. Barletta</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To prohibit sanctuary jurisdictions from receiving Federal funds under the State Criminal Alien Assistance Program, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HEF2B886407414F0FB77B89CDC4842FB5" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2C5A54D7AF984AC29F8F3BF7955F5AF8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Enforcement, No Grant for Sanctuary Cities Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE5DED0A3DC39407CA08AA65111F28D97"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sanctuary jurisdictions ineligible for certain Federal funds</header> <subsection id="H28B36235A38A4844A4F084A6DF524617"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A sanctuary jurisdiction is not eligible to receive any Federal funds under section 241(i) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1231">8 U.S.C. 1231(i)</external-xref>) for the fiscal year in which the jurisdiction was determined to be a sanctuary jurisdiction. </text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H20B9A09E76FF413E8B126C0813906AE3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Determinations</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall determine, on an annual basis, which jurisdictions are sanctuary jurisdictions.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H788924401E344CE4946F4BAB806022DF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sanctuary jurisdiction defined</header> <paragraph id="HF4564C7A47EE40E69954E960E1D7BCD5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), the term <term>sanctuary jurisdiction</term> means any State or political subdivision of a State that has in effect a statute, ordinance, policy, or practice that prohibits or restricts any government entity or official from—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB65544CD62FA4FDB801739A5CF0D679A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>sending, receiving, maintaining, or exchanging with any Federal, State, or local government entity information regarding the citizenship or immigration status (lawful or unlawful) of any individual; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HACB92A7E73B149A8BB2F7D0EC2D36900"><enum>(B)</enum><text>complying with a request lawfully made by the Department of Homeland Security under section 236 or 287 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1226">8 U.S.C. 1226</external-xref>, 1357) to comply with a detainer for, or notify about the release of, an individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFC3C91086BE645989FB1D3FBAE06FB26"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State or political subdivision of a State shall not be deemed a sanctuary jurisdiction based solely on its having a policy whereby its officials will not share information regarding, or comply with a request made by the Department of Homeland Security under section 236 or 287 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1226">8 U.S.C. 1226</external-xref>, 1357) to comply with a detainer regarding, an individual who comes forward as a victim or a witness to a criminal offense.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

