<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H7201F536B35148C6AF8707590ACD0012" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5213 IH: Expanding Rural Access to Broadband Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5213</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180308">March 8, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001053">Mrs. Hartzler</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the Rural Utilities Service from providing assistance for the provision of broadband
			 service with a download speed of less than 25 megabits per second or an
			 upload speed of less than 3 megabits per second, and clarify the broadband
			 loan and loan guarantee authority provided in section 601 of the Rural
			 Electrification Act of 1936, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H6CA0E76C9DDA441DA0CE89281DF55B59" style="OLC">
 <section id="HD92EF4A99C66471AA4C0762D0E8FFCF3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Expanding Rural Access to Broadband Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBE9F7A7A1FD34B8EA528C4319039D704" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Required minimum speed of broadband Internet access service for Rural Utilities Service broadband Internet access service deployment assistance programs</header> <subsection id="H244DAE3E2F7149A291062025148F0744"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Rural Utilities Service may not, under section 601 of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936, the Community Connect Broadband Grant Program, the Telecommunications Infrastructure Loan and Loan Guarantee Program, or the Distance Learning and Telemedicine Program, provide assistance for the provision of broadband service (as defined in section 601(b)(1) of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936) with a download speed of less than 25 megabits per second or an upload speed of less than 3 megabits per second.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H31CBA876F4274134AF910167E4732B25"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Section 601(e)(1) of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950bb">7 U.S.C. 950bb(e)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HC7DB05DED506474AACC56125FE9E4887"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>4</quote> and inserting <quote>25</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB72A1A8A70DD40428DBC292E5DEBE18F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>1</quote> and inserting <quote>3</quote>.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H70DCAC134DDA4F1C82ACFDEC4B1C1486"><enum>3.</enum><header>Clarification of broadband loan and loan guarantee authority</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 601(c)(1) of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950bb">7 U.S.C. 950bb(c)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>make or guarantee loans</quote> and inserting <quote>shall make loans and shall guarantee loans</quote>.</text>
 </section><section id="H9AC3B25F3F804F7AA0A1C76E1E5A74D9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Within 12 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Rural Utilities Service (in this section referred to as the <quote>RUS</quote>) shall submit to the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate a written report on the effectiveness of RUS loan and loan guarantee programs for the purpose of expanding broadband to rural areas (as defined in RUS regulations), which shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H05F83E07FF974450BBBB3A6A9135F76D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify administrative and legislative options for incentivizing private investment by utilizing RUS loan guarantee programs for the purpose of expanding broadband to rural areas;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4432C70620B34866A431C51E02BC6EEA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>evaluate the existing borrower and lending guidelines for RUS loan and loan guarantee applicants to incentivize participation in both programs; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5AF07C9B7CEF46A898AC89194C7A159E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>evaluate the loan and loan guarantee application processes for lenders and borrowers by eliminating burdensome and unnecessary steps in the application process and providing a more streamlined process to decrease the complexity of the application and the timeline from application to approval or denial.</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


