<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HD501D91887144EBCACCE20BE0A94DDA1" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4983 IH: Caring Homes and Improved Lives for Dependents (CHILD) Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4983</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180208">February 8, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001187">Mr. Meadows</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend part E of title IV of the Social Security Act to require States to provide for the
			 placement of a foster child in a cottage home, and to make a child so
			 placed eligible for foster care maintenance payments.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H82371044AE524BB290C7C16154EDED43" style="OLC">
 <section id="H06CC92754E5F4A3AB350273334ED83DA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Caring Homes and Improved Lives for Dependents (CHILD) Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H2E73402B63074784B3B753DFA2172E8D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Placement of foster children in cottage homes</header> <subsection id="H6DB5DFA127A44DE2ACAE986D9B63AE36"><enum>(a)</enum><header>State plan requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 471(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/671">42 U.S.C. 671(a)</external-xref>), as amended by the Family First Prevention Services Act, is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HA816605571444EF3BACA2E33C7A559BD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of paragraph (36);</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H03B21992BEB44729B3FE31EDD5DA2B26"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of paragraph (37) and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC9EB503A16C7440BB9A0A97F22C9E5FA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9B204DAA545743CB96342C482BB0A6A6" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H69A442CDBF5D4AB0AC8B00934CED4FD2"><enum>(38)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides that, with respect to a child who has attained 6 years of age and who is removed from the child’s home, if a suitable relative or other designated caregiver is not available as a placement for the child, placing the child in a foster family home or a cottage home shall be considered the least restrictive setting for the child.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAC345035B8D0426C983A1002F4A22D73"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility for foster care maintenance payments of certain children placed in a cottage home</header><text>Section 472(a)(2)(C) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/672">42 U.S.C. 672(a)(2)(C)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>home or child-care institution</quote> and inserting <quote>home, a child-care institution, or (if the child has attained 6 years of age and a suitable relative or other designated caregiver is not available as a placement for the child) a cottage home that is not a foster family home or child-care institution</quote>.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H4EA9318C754342F7BD77D3020CB10B25"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition of cottage home</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 472(c) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/672">42 U.S.C. 672(c)</external-xref>), as amended by the Family First Prevention Services Act, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H676DD8205E0441BB8F5812650BDCB534" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H5F89E0D0DE744C669485C09BDB6EA6BE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Cottage home</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>cottage home</term> means a residential operation—</text> <subparagraph id="H5DA262E6764649BAA7A6475B2FC5A747"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in which not more than 12 children reside;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA02055F1A903425BBA6416BCD47A06EC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that has and implements a trauma-informed treatment plan for its residents;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1AC4498ABA6B4BFAADD9047FDA1BC932"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that involves family members of a child in the treatment for the child, and maintains contact with the family of the child, if available and if the involvement is clinically appropriate for the well-being of the child;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F7BB88677854ACFBCB1AC69AD26E694"><enum>(D)</enum><text>that is licensed by the State in which it is situated or has been approved, by the agency of such State responsible for licensing or approval of institutions of this type; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C0012E5E5D24C1FA7F0E1D9FEAE95D9"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that is accredited by the Council on Accreditation or another national accrediting body.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection><subsection id="HFDE50574DD7144E08396B91FFA646061"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header> <paragraph id="H3248A09407B8499283773813AF9DB814"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act, and shall apply to payments under part E of title IV of the Social Security Act for calendar quarters beginning on or after such date.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7FD6B09343574A41B635486BB428C799"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Delay permitted if State legislation required</header><text>If the Secretary of Health and Human Services determines that State legislation (other than legislation appropriating funds) is required in order for a State plan under part E of title IV of the Social Security Act to meet the additional requirements imposed by the amendments made by this section, the plan shall not be regarded as failing to meet any of the additional requirements before the first day of the first calendar quarter beginning after the first regular session of the State legislature that begins after the date of the enactment of this Act. For purposes of the preceding sentence, if the State has a 2-year legislative session, each year of the session is deemed to be a separate regular session of the State legislature.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


