<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H4D619438C632457F9A72C460E770A7B6" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4934 IH: To prohibit assistance to the Government of Pakistan, and to require the Department of State and the United States Agency for International Development to transfer amounts to the Highway Trust Fund equivalent to historic levels of assistance to Pakistan.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4934</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180205">February 5, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000051">Mr. Sanford</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAP00">Appropriations</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit assistance to the Government of Pakistan, and to require the Department of State and
			 the United States Agency for International Development to transfer amounts
			 to the Highway Trust Fund equivalent to historic levels of assistance to
			 Pakistan.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H6FF242B2C18E45479A0B0E9002704384" style="OLC">
 <section id="HDB4FDACC2EE1421DAAC23ED43C213731" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Prohibition on assistance to Pakistan</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No amounts appropriated or otherwise made available to the Department of State or the United States Agency for International Development may be made available as assistance to the Government of Pakistan.</text>
		</section><section id="H24A3885EF40D4A3D9355251B5F2CC74F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Required transfers to the Highway Trust Fund</header>
 <subsection id="HD10127EB3134430CA6FA5BCA3EBF0BEE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Department of State</header><text>Upon receipt of appropriations for the balance of fiscal year 2018, the Secretary of State shall transfer $1,280,000,000 to the Highway Trust Fund.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H57BEDF009F4C4C328A76B9FC85433B8D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>United States Agency for International Development</header><text>Upon receipt of appropriations for the balance of fiscal year 2018, the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development shall transfer $852,000,000 to the Highway Trust Fund.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


