<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA35C2C61CB034D2FA9C39BAC28CDB219" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5473 IH: Better Pain Management Through Better Data Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5473</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180411">April 11, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001105">Mrs. Comstock</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="L000570">Mr. Ben Ray Luján of New Mexico</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services to update or issue one or more guidances
			 addressing alternative methods for data collection on opioid sparing and
			 inclusion of such data in product labeling, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HDA1A5A045F2547E39B6E529831E46160" style="OLC">
 <section id="H7CFD687CE0CA40AD8620BADF73F23622" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Better Pain Management Through Better Data Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H4FA1306018614E8D812270BDC93DED4E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Guidance addressing alternative approaches to data collection and labeling claims for opioid sparing</header> <subsection id="H0CE1F0004BB64F99B6086FDBAB38B6EF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of assisting sponsors in collecting and incorporating opioid-sparing data in product labeling, the Secretary of Health and Human Services (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall conduct a public meeting and update or issue one or more guidances in accordance with subsection (b).</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H57E2EC610B394E25ACB714D88F763435"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidance</header>
 <paragraph id="HB37862DD2787444C8B111554B88BC084"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, shall update or issue one or more guidances addressing—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H5EA833E592C242948D3B3F08B92EA948"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">alternative methods for data collection on opioid sparing;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H901CFD2224BB42AEA4E35F18CCF032C1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">alternative methods for inclusion of such data in product labeling; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EC8D8CF5DED4EA1997855E48754EE57"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">investigations other than clinical trials, including partially controlled studies and objective trials without matched controls such as historically controlled analyses, open-label studies, and meta-analyses, on opioid sparing for inclusion in product labeling.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF0101B06A8E4346ACEA0E953CADE5BA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The guidances under paragraph (1) shall address—</text> <subparagraph id="H2A5DF93AD1784269A5ACD02DD19FEFED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>innovative clinical trial designs for ethically and efficiently collecting data on opioid sparing for inclusion in product labeling;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC7B79C0DD1E4BDB9813738CAB095EF2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>primary and secondary endpoints for the reduction of opioid use while maintaining adequate pain control;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C75A4AE5D3E4F118125CD70519EE9C1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>use of real world evidence, including patient registries, and patient reported outcomes to support inclusion of opioid-sparing data in product labeling; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4ECE00157D0646D98EC57FF14B966D03"><enum>(D)</enum><text>how sponsors may obtain feedback from the Secretary relating to such issues prior to—</text> <clause id="H238A8C3B4BAD46C39D6B30C9DA934324"><enum>(i)</enum><text>commencement of such data collection; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD7CBF097FB764DB1BA09A2957A5C4C50"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the submission of resulting data to the Secretary.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEDE8006F6684FE4A1F7FB0F67D837DA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public meeting</header><text>Prior to updating or issuing the guidances required by paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consult with stakeholders, including representatives of regulated industry, academia, patients, and provider organizations, through a public meeting to be held not later than 12 months after the date of enactment of this Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCCA578AC1C934E0D98EB6C9DDE7E7E85"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H6583408A932748169A4A27985F770588"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 12 months after the date of the public meeting required by paragraph (3), update or issue the one or more draft guidances required by paragraph (1); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H269C383C50FE4CC681FABD892725283B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 12 months after the date on which the public comment period for such draft guidances closes, finalize such guidances.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1300B6CAA5A942E6B5346881CDDA486F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HD618A053DC26420AA13419D4B63D7047"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>opioid sparing</term> and <term>opioid-sparing</term> refer to the use of drugs or devices (as defined in section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/321">21 U.S.C. 321</external-xref>)) that reduce pain while enabling the reduction, replacement, or avoidance of oral opioids.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBC98B809495345EB9C5AF5908018F62B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

