<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H3E8F0EB1DCCE4815A9FDE237799FC02B" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5443 IH: To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to require electronic filing of the annual returns of exempt organizations and provide for making such returns available for public inspection.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5443</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180410">April 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001202">Mrs. Murphy of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to require electronic filing of the annual returns of
			 exempt organizations and provide for making such returns available for
			 public inspection.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H792D4AF225D54649A8FD8D5785549CAC" style="OLC">
		<section id="HCF7184E96C214F01AD10B3AAD24A9A43" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Mandatory electronic filing for annual returns of exempt organizations</header>
 <subsection id="H938D718B75E84B858E8BF546CE065D69"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6033">Section 6033</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by redesignating subsection (n) as subsection (o) and by inserting after subsection (m) the following new subsection:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC684966EEBA541A7B73E2048FE49BE6F" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="HC8E9D66F2B1743D292AB91A1993AD012"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Mandatory electronic filing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any organization required to file a return under this section shall file such return in electronic form.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA0D8326E07BF4BC5801623A74A23BA89"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inspection of electronically filed annual returns</header><text>Section 6104(b) of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>Any annual return required to be filed electronically under section 6033(n) shall be made available by the Secretary to the public in machine readable format.</quote>.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H10B12E197EBC4FFEB0F454E99B12EDE9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header>
 <paragraph id="H008EEB66AD084D6C8BBDB96E7DCDE518"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), the amendments made by this subsection shall apply to returns filed for taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HC289490E8EA64356B268B6D79DD77124"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transitional relief</header>
					<subparagraph id="H45F2B48983A144679404BF186CBAC348"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Small organizations</header>
 <clause id="HB1C2E3930E87401086080109D8D9B654"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any small organizations, or any other organizations for which the Secretary of the Treasury or the Secretary’s delegate (hereafter referred to in this paragraph as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) determines the application of the amendments made by subsection (a) would cause undue burden without a delay, the Secretary may delay the application of such amendments, but not later than taxable years beginning 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H81738FA4174942C4926A0D81A6B479FA"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Small organization</header><text>For purposes of clause (i), the term <quote>small organization</quote> means any organization—</text> <subclause id="H5C85CB12F455437BAA393E893F65BABE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the gross receipts of which for the taxable year are less than $200,000, and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H88312682458E47DABDEDFB8B532FDC47"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the aggregate gross assets of which at the end of the taxable year are less than $500,000.</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H821D4CB339F9471DBCC14F07C66F335E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Organizations filing form <enum-in-header>990–T</enum-in-header></header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/511">section 511(a)(2)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 which is subject to the tax imposed by section 511(a)(1) of such Code on its unrelated business taxable income, or any organization required to file a return under section 6033 of such Code and include information under subsection (e) thereof, the Secretary may delay the application of the amendments made by this section, but not later than taxable years beginning 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


