<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H4FE51D4EC4BF485DB0740CCCD5061677" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5767 IH: Teachers Are Leaders Act </dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5767</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180510">May 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000598">Mr. Polis</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001189">Mr. Messer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Education to award grants to establish teacher leader development
			 programs.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HB4023D4DD53640E4AA4EF496D716041A" style="OLC">
 <section id="H3C39FFA7F1D445928D257FD7C6530B60" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Teachers Are Leaders Act </short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HD5FC642C0AD84F41B9D3DB1D74949333"><enum>2.</enum><header>Teacher leader development program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title II of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1021">20 U.S.C. 1021</external-xref> et seq.) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HAF62B7A9364E4926B1CB37C5E94ACB86"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 200—</text> <subparagraph id="HCB7FE0DB646141F786F372ECAA3A5CC1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating paragraphs (21), (22), and (23), as paragraphs (22), (23), and (24), respectively; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D78055BCFD841F5A00B277C48282C8B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (20) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE51C31DDDF9249D8AA5DD803494EA969" style="OLC"> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H60A3F4528D424D19BE5070F696994528"><enum>(21)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Teacher leader</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>teacher leader</term> means a teacher who carries out formalized leadership responsibilities based on demonstrated school needs, while maintaining a role as a classroom instructor.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0BB1AA9DA874D3997AFB32FA0ED3A54"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 202—</text> <subparagraph id="H7CE38C6CCEEA494C929DEACDA88F66DC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(6)(C), by striking <quote>subsection (f) or (g)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (g) or (h)</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0A5D76BD07443EA9312093CE10ADF6C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text> <clause id="H54F44FDA245B4F35AFE932C9288B9879"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>a teacher leader development program under subsection (f),</quote> after <quote>subsection (e),</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H29DE60708D3C4425B6E2A646B6EC5E04"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>subsection (f)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (g)</quote>;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DD71901764642A1907B8537DD63C71D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (f), (g), (h), (i), (j), and (k), as subsections (g), (h), (i), (j), (k), and (l), respectively; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H623FFF3B57BB4DA9AA940F0C38290523"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (e) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H42AED7B629A9434EA9DF4732B1043C7B" style="OLC"> <subsection id="HEC33E79E8BDE45FBAD1FA480516B4CF8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Teacher leader development program</header> <paragraph id="H8589F25DB5344BFA8FFED02315FF8642"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A teacher leader development program carried out with a grant awarded under this section shall involve the professional development of teachers, as described in paragraph (2), who maintain their roles as classroom teachers but who also carry out formalized leadership responsibilities to increase the academic achievement of students and promote data-driven instructional practices that address the demonstrated needs at their schools, such as—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF30AA58D13D8472187FD1A45D62BC2EC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>development of curriculum and curricular resources;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5508639560E042E6BD9731DB760411C0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>facilitating the work of committees and teams;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC3C7638B2F284C368386B9418DE70C5C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>family and community engagement;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB31633B1AB594DF1AAB42731C428318A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>school discipline and culture;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5D5450C4A234D30AD6DA4192994F651"><enum>(E)</enum><text>peer observations and coaching; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA46EA1EA1DE464193DA5C934EE2C09B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>dual enrollment instruction.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H67C9BD92BA8D419595B3B4FB4616D2C2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Professional development</header><text>The professional development of teachers in a teacher leader development program carried out with a grant awarded under this section shall include—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H857569A8A68F4040B51CCA7698C253D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>one year of professional development, training, and support that may—</text> <clause id="H94C60C17F1D64660B331C6C727DA7702"><enum>(i)</enum><text>include—</text>
 <subclause id="HC3C3B73C18C8408F8620DE30B99B6051"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the engagement of teachers in rigorous coursework and fieldwork relevant to their role as a teacher leader, including available teacher leader standards; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H5C4D7BEBD18D4BE2A7AB86318F3474C8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>regular observations and professional support from—</text> <item id="H663B3F5B27AD418BA012AE693F945DA1"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a principal, vice principal, or a designated instructional leader of the school;</text>
 </item><item id="H8B1B79B94493489B9B34F2EAED76D814"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>a representative from the institution of higher education that is a partner in the eligible entity;</text> </item><item id="H2383BF90FFFA4655ACE12221D490B7E5"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>a representative from another entity that is a partner in the eligible entity; and</text>
 </item><item id="H1F7A0EB7D84B4E9B8B79BD5B50980826"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>another member of the teacher leader cohort, if applicable, or a peer teacher; and</text> </item></subclause></clause><clause id="H1D961D2B81914C988F0FC16F58E321EA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>result in the awarding of a credential in teacher leadership; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H38D1089122A142B9BC6ED89A091D38FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>one or 2 additional years of support from a principal, vice principal, or a designated instructional leader of the school, a representative from the institution of higher education that is a partner in the eligible entity, and a representative from another entity that is a partner in the eligible entity.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA50BDBCE4A14A47AA12B954563E6A5A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Teacher leader development program plan</header><text>In carrying out a teacher leader development program under this section, an eligible entity shall develop a plan that shall describe—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H9356610E6DCA41C8BDA0D152A985E0DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how the work hours of teacher leaders will be allocated between their classroom responsibilities and responsibilities as a teacher leader, which may include a description of whether the teacher leader will be relieved from teaching duties during their participation in the teacher leader development program;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB1375FEADB684665988F16B92583807B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how the partnership will support teacher leaders after the first year of professional development in the program; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDEE9A2D30FAF4B8CB623C64003059C9C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how teacher leader activities could be sustained by the eligible partnership after the program concludes, which may include a description of opportunities for the teacher leaders to assist in the educator preparation program at the institution of higher education in the partnership.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB9AC83439A847E59146D018DC058BB2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Selection of teacher leaders; use of funds</header><text>In carrying out a teacher leader development program under this section, an eligible entity—</text> <subparagraph id="H0451CF3B89144495B9295AC2DF476902"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall select a teacher for participation in the program—</text>
 <clause id="H085EE1B89FC94ADE87B98207F3ADC588"><enum>(i)</enum><text>who—</text> <subclause id="HD9AF57725E264478BA102FA81142B4FD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is fully certified to teach in the State in which the high-need local educational agency that is a partner in the eligible entity is located;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H06302FABC395476AB89D585470C6E92D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is employed by a high-need local educational agency that is a partner in the eligible entity;</text> </subclause><subclause id="H3861F0EB63C746598CF843ED53015B60"><enum>(III)</enum><text>has not less than 3 years of teaching experience; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HBDE54C2A7185432CB0831DEFF25B2254"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>submits an application for participation to the eligible entity; and</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="H3937CE4F56974D718F01A78A5ABCE28F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>based on selection criteria that includes—</text>
 <subclause id="H6C29986845B94B2EB2440308C4AB5ADE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>demonstration of strong content knowledge or a record of accomplishment in the field or subject area the teacher will support as a teacher leader; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HA1449E8C88AF4B199809C644258E6D81"><enum>(II)</enum><text>demonstration of attributes linked to effective teaching that is determined through interviews, observations, artifacts, student achievement, or performance assessments, such as those leading to an advanced credential;</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7E820CBEF04D454AAF9B1B94263C1BD3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may develop admissions goals and priorities for the teacher leader development program that—</text> <clause id="H48A6957B1BB84A94B09452EE8B8EC9D1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are aligned with the demonstrated needs of the school or high-need local educational agency in which the teacher is employed;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H355BACC3589B4F8E964F80B93AEEA3EB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>considers cultural competencies that would make the applicant effective in the applicant's teacher leader role; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB59FB89ACAE44292853A7458A061EDE1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>considers whether the teacher has substantial teaching experience in the school in which the teacher is employed or in a school that is similar to the school in which the teacher is employed;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC41B7D97376B449888FB105E22B9F5C2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall use the grant funds to pay for costs of training and supporting teacher leaders for not less than 2 years and not more than 3 years;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79BB3A0E393C4443860EDD272E812E66"><enum>(D)</enum><text>may use the grant funds to pay for a portion of a stipend for teacher leaders if such grant funds are matched by additional non-Federal public or private funds as follows:</text>
 <clause id="H8BFD03E8E1D8498489FE9003DDBEE55A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>During each of the first and second years of the grant period, grant funds may pay not more than 50 percent of such stipend.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H985863409F1049F3916DD4C6460E0EA6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>During the third year of the grant period, grant funds may pay not more than 33 percent of such stipend; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10E48EE0B6D04841ADE701B06F545DA0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>may require teacher leaders to pay back the cost of attaining a credential if they do not complete their term of service in the teacher leader development program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


