<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8F0E7883C17B45EC90A97DAAD73B5C3F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5548 IH: Water, Cosmetics, and Unwanted Pharmaceuticals Study Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5548</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180418">April 18, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency to conduct a study on the presence of pharmaceuticals and personal care products in sources of drinking water.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H74AFB7B145164494BF89052A04FAAA69" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA17D79C168FA4C4A99CEE374AD71E662" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Water, Cosmetics, and Unwanted Pharmaceuticals Study Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H170F8863B7374705A7954DC7416E276E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Presence of pharmaceuticals and personal care products in sources of drinking water</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (a) of section 1442 of the Safe Drinking Water Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-1">42 U.S.C. 300j–1</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H2A750B381D004EDEBD73CCDCA750C032" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H3D8CF1FBDDBC4DCF8522DCE29B166180" indent="up1"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Presence of pharmaceuticals and personal care products in sources of drinking water</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H48A416D0B757486B91A5C3904DB4F1B3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Administrator shall carry out a study on the presence of pharmaceuticals and personal care products in sources of drinking water, which shall—</text> <clause commented="no" id="HE25D3F7651724D248E523F9A1ECC7B00"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identify pharmaceuticals and personal care products that have been detected in sources of drinking water and the levels at which such pharmaceuticals and personal care products have been detected;</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H936369BE5E99463894FB8E2C42F346BA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identify the sources of pharmaceuticals and personal care products in sources of drinking water, including point sources and nonpoint sources of pharmaceutical and personal care products;</text></clause> <clause id="H91BA20FCD2164CE4B2E636438F69F729"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify the effects of such pharmaceuticals and personal care products on humans, the environment, and the safety of drinking water; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H1AF2DBD9CDA146A1B0846DB876195719"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify methods to control, limit, treat, or prevent the presence of such pharmaceuticals and personal care products.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H979B139D405A45C086131A60E118EB14"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Administrator shall conduct the study described in subparagraph (A) in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services (acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs), the Director of the United States Geological Survey, the heads of other appropriate Federal agencies (including the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences), and other interested stakeholders (including manufacturers of pharmaceuticals and personal care products and consumer groups and advocates).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H4F147EAF283E4E609EED8ED8289F6B9C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 4 years after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, the Administrator shall submit to the Congress a report on the results of the study carried out under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H5C48140553E349FF8A5C820D63258B9E"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this paragraph:</text> 
<clause commented="no" id="H663D211E3C8D4925A59C226F2F49D108"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The term <term>personal care product</term> has the meaning given the term <term>cosmetic</term> in section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H9815EABBDFD249089F90C98D964D0184"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The term <term>pharmaceutical</term> has the meaning given the term <term>drug</term> in section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


