<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H36C01E42845C4D9399E25B2075F39512" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4795 IH: Communications Facilities Deployment on Federal Property Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4795</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180116">January 16, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000820">Mrs. Mimi Walters of California</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Middle Class Tax Relief and Job Creation Act of 2012 to promote communications
			 facilities deployment on Federal property, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HA153A116EE574F6EAF0AE1A24C221E70" style="OLC">
 <section id="H4788C05761824FBC8515CFBC30F645A5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Communications Facilities Deployment on Federal Property Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H58031715AA3A4826881AE1A2014391C1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Communications facilities deployment on Federal property</header> <subsection id="HADF6C0EDF70843C29482108341AE7FF8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 6409 of the Middle Class Tax Relief and Job Creation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1455">47 U.S.C. 1455</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE4712E9B9576412695F16826B3BB6E68"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">Wireless</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">Communications</header-in-text></quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H4FD451982FB548ABA3702EB8085ADF59"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsections (b), (c), and (d) and inserting the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="HA5E6E1004BCC4E0BA70E9D79006B01D4" style="OLC">
						<subsection id="H4871D951273B49489EA18F364F05CC90"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal easements, rights-of-Way, and leases</header>
 <paragraph id="HAAB4C3977913426FAAF319E79198D238"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Grant</header><text>If an entity applies for the grant of an easement, right-of-way, or lease to, in, over, or on a building or other property owned by the Federal Government for the right to install, construct, modify, or maintain a communications facility installation, the executive agency that is authorized to grant such easement, right-of-way, or lease for the building or other property may grant to the applicant an easement, right-of-way, or lease to perform such installation, construction, modification, or maintenance.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD4DC80126B5144EF94578F51452C4A71"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application forms</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of the Communications Facilities Deployment on Federal Property Act of 2018, the Administrator of General Services shall develop a required common form for applications for easements, rights-of-way, or leases under paragraph (1). An executive agency may not require an applicant under paragraph (1) to use any form for submitting the application other than the common form developed by the Administrator of General Services under this paragraph and may not require any significant information beyond the information required by such common form.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H681503A8E40641169D8C9F14FE4B9EA6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Common fees</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H0342CE55010A4FB0A12280B9261D69D8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Communications Facilities Deployment on Federal Property Act of 2018</short-title>, the Administrator of General Services shall establish a common fee for the processing of applications under paragraph (1) and subsection (c).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HCF82DCFAAEDE4075AE2966787F93E902"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Fee guidelines</header><text>The application fees established pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall be—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H49D1ED97049340388D27F5F0A7BC2C12"><enum>(i)</enum><text>based on direct and actual cost recovery; and</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H95227AC986F24CC599F07229B936C5C2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>competitively neutral with regard to other users of the building or other property owned by the Federal Government.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H76E133D5FBA84BF0B6940A3B6D52D657"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>The Administrator of General Services may establish exceptions to the fee amount required under subparagraph (A)—</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="HC8CA777291FB45A6AF5D2761D5EA38E4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in consideration of the public benefit provided by a grant of an easement, right-of-way, or lease; and</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HFB20F081EAE64EDB897EFA84B55D6350"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the interest of expanding wireless and broadband coverage.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE68370995EF41D8B0D31927BE155F33"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Use of fees collected</header><text>Any fee collected by an executive agency pursuant to paragraph (3) may be made available, as provided in appropriations Acts, to such agency to cover the costs of granting the easement, right-of-way, or lease.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H36247AE9FAC74C54A1434485FA160AD0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Master contracts for communications facility installation sitings</header>
 <paragraph id="H74359095203A4F408BF2E6E2A3DB3486"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding section 704 of the Telecommunications Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/104/104">Public Law 104–104</external-xref>; 110 Stat. 151) or any other provision of law, not later 30 days after the date of the enactment of the Communications Facilities Deployment on Federal Property Act of 2018, the Administrator of General Services shall—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H2CA646C8D1084C978A1CC89A52FFCF73"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop one or more master contracts that shall govern the placement of a communications facility installation on a building or other property owned by the Federal Government, which shall include offers of lease terms for the communications facility installation of not less than 10 years with automatic lease renewals; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC03E4ADDA564A5ABAF316CE5787BC91"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in developing the master contract or contracts, standardize the treatment of the placement of a communications facility installation on a building rooftop or facade, the placement of a communications facility installation on a rooftop or inside a building, the technology used in connection with a communications facility installation placed on a Federal building and other property, and any other key issues the Administrator of General Services considers appropriate.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AD65EC295B64552A2E812E503FA5BA4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The master contract or contracts developed by the Administrator of General Services under paragraph (1) shall apply to all publicly accessible buildings and other property owned by the Federal Government. An executive agency may not enter into a contract governing the placement of a communications facility installation on a building or other property to which such a master contract applies, unless the contract entered into by the agency is consistent with, and does not contain any significant terms beyond the terms contained in, such master contract.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF25CA1FBC9474C56BFED9DA4A4B4ADAB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H5B974802FDD645B6B69A7730A98ED3C3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Communications facility installation</header><text>The term <term>communications facility installation</term> includes—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H82E5313A9D3541ECB9EB37F0D99DCACF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any infrastructure, including any transmitting device, tower, or support structure, and any equipment, switches, wiring, cabling, power sources, shelters, or cabinets, associated with the licensed or permitted unlicensed wireless or wireline transmission of writings, signs, signals, data, images, pictures, or sounds of all kinds; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBEC85639C5774A3894A0445F50754FB9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any antenna or apparatus that—</text> <clause id="H4910365C6E7E41B5BAD96AD5389FA1CE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is designed for the purpose of emitting or receiving radio frequency;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H64A37B4455844B1EACAB479A3E9D5EF4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is designed to be operated, or is operating, from a fixed location pursuant to authorization by the Commission or is using duly authorized devices that do not require individual licenses; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H78360CC3347B4CE38C5DF73AFD2619C1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is added to a tower, building, or other structure.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H093C88DCA0284B5C9C42F3801419AAEF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Executive agency</header><text>The term <term>executive agency</term> has the meaning given such term in section 102 of title 40, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB56AD588C03E4872AEC5E3F32C93F01E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This Act, and the amendments made by this Act, shall take effect 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HC9011F0029B74CA5B49BA825BF0EFF12"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effect on existing applications</header><text>An application for an easement, right-of-way, or lease that was made or granted under section 6409 of the Middle Class Tax Relief and Job Creation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1455">47 U.S.C. 1455</external-xref>) before the effective date of this Act shall continue, subject to such section as in effect on the day before such effective date.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


