<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H12B576031321411A81F069486CE3B6D1" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5729 IH: Transportation Worker Identification Credential Accountability Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5729</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180509">May 9, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000386">Mr. Katko</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000588">Mr. Richmond</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To restrict the department in which the Coast Guard is operating from implementing any rule
			 requiring the use of biometric readers for biometric transportation
			 security cards until after submission to Congress of the results of an
			 assessment of the effectiveness of the transportation security card
			 program.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H67C77D941D144412991D07FEAA5CB2E7" style="OLC">
 <section id="HD8E106B2C41E40BCB3A558CEF7EEE8CA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Transportation Worker Identification Credential Accountability Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H9F90BF40D2A34734930A82F3CBE3D74B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Restriction on implementation of Transportation Worker Identification Credential biometric reader rule</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The department in which the Coast Guard is operating may not implement the rule entitled <quote>Transportation Worker Identification Credential (TWIC)–Reader Requirements</quote> (81 Fed. Reg. 57651), and may not propose or issue a notice of proposed rulemaking for any revision to such rule except to extend its effective date, or for any other rule requiring the use of biometric readers for biometric transportation security cards under section 70105(k)(3) of title 46, United States Code, before the end of the 60-day period beginning on the date of the submission under paragraph (5) of section 1(b) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/278">Public Law 114–278</external-xref> (130 Stat. 1411 to 1412) of the results of the assessment required by that section.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


