<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HE8DBA7E91FF545DEABB45957BB02BF16" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5500 IH: Veterans’ Credit Protection Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5500</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180412">April 12, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000603">Mr. Rouzer</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to conduct outreach to veterans regarding the effect of
			 delayed payments of claims for emergency medical care furnished by
			 non-Department of Veterans Affairs medical providers by the Office of
			 Community Care and to direct the Secretary to submit to Congress an annual
			 report regarding such delayed payments.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H02AD39C2A6EA49D8A447CE04B31E69F8" style="OLC">
 <section id="H43E24D80AD01491C89F432EE9626AA4B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans’ Credit Protection Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H75573991AC7E4F6390DAD2DC4827C01A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Outreach to veterans regarding effect of certain delayed payments by Department of Veterans Affairs Office of Community Care</header> <subsection id="H843893D4FAF54D7782067EE86C07D947"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct outreach, including through national and local veterans service organizations, to inform veterans of how to resolve credit issues caused by delayed payment of an eligible claim for emergency hospital care, emergency medical services, or other emergency health care furnished through a non-Department of Veterans Affairs provider.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HF8B1531599CA4281803ACF5468EB0003"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual report</header>
 <paragraph id="HA5F91DEA241D4922845B63A546A8433D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the five-year period following the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall annually submit to Congress a report on the effectiveness of the Office of Community Care (or successor office) in providing timely payment of proper invoices for emergency hospital care, emergency medical services, or other emergency health care furnished through non-Department of Veterans Affairs providers by the required payment date.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HEB732A2F64B1415AACD3F449E1E1D335"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Periods covered</header>
 <subparagraph id="H9696CACE14F14B81BC76A7073A872289"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The first report submitted under paragraph (1) shall cover the five-year period preceding the date of the report, to the greatest extent practicable. With respect to covering the part of such period that occurred before October 1, 2014, the report shall evaluate the provision by the Veterans Integrated Service Networks of payments described in such paragraph.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE19F34E7B2B426DB07310954C0436A8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The reports following the first report shall each cover the period following the date on which the prior report was submitted.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F7974269A7C4C728206782D2EE38249"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Matters included</header><text>The reports under paragraph (1) shall include, for the period covered by the report, the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H914631DD99044278BA2369DF64D3C56B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The number of veterans who contacted the Secretary regarding a delayed payment that negatively affected, or will potentially negatively affect, the credit of the veteran.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72302B091B8747CB820C0D642E46876D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The number of proper invoices submitted, listed in a table for each quarter and fiscal year of each such period that includes—</text>
 <clause id="HAB86BD2A5F7248FFBD021F78C49132DC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the total amount owed by the Secretary under the proper invoices;</text> </clause><clause id="H4FBDED0E0AD2483D9879969B3917051E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the payment status of each proper invoice, as of the date of the report; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H73E512F9584B46C3B130BC90D965274E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the period that elapsed until each proper invoice was paid, including an explanation of any delayed payment.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09DFD35FB2CD4F3895B10A39C06C72BF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any comments regarding delayed payments made by medical providers.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D85B54C501846E9BFFF35B0525A58F9"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the best practices that the Office of Community Care (or successor office) can carry out to provide timely payment of a proper invoice, including a plan to improve such timely payments.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE14F40AC50149879D3A0F1B3C8FD3B8"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to pending claims for reimbursement for emergency hospital care, emergency medical services, and other emergency health care furnished through non-Department of Veterans Affairs providers—</text>
 <clause id="HF5C18F3E888F4505840D871333A2801C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the total number of such pending claims for each hospital system of the Department, as of the last day of the period covered by the report;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HBD5DA616BD5A4A50B7A4BE6217F38664"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total number of veterans who submitted such a pending claim in each State, as of such day;</text> </clause><clause id="HF0F918E3871C4AF3B5C880A6DABF1106"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the aggregate amount of all such pending claims in each State, as of such day;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H76D95F09089542ABB8DB44963014C849"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>as of such day—</text> <subclause id="H835C0C09116C4D7CAD46C7B0A152F61B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the number of such pending claims that have been pending for 30 days or longer;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HA390DFAD5129455A8146D59620D74D3B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the number of such pending claims that have been pending for 90 days or longer; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H2DBF08A076E9470CA919462600FCC8D1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the number of such pending claims that have been pending for 365 days or longer; and</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="HBBAC326FD9F3439DAFB6C113A5EAE965"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each hospital system, for the period covered by the report—</text> <subclause id="H9055237AFC9C4BB7ACB8EB580AEADC9D"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of claims for reimbursement for emergency hospital care, emergency medical services, and other emergency health care furnished through non-Department of Veterans Affairs providers approved during such quarter;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H52BECC678CED496D9308300006D6653F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the number of such claims denied during such quarter; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H23587A0271AA487D9ECD379D5DEA5531"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the number of such claims denied listed by each denial reason group.</text>
							</subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H65EE4A89F3494828BC6C2EA8E5EAF577"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Comptroller General study</header>
 <paragraph id="H0956FD917F204CE7A1ECD97AF00283D6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study that evaluates the effectiveness of the Office of Community Care in providing timely payment of a proper invoice for emergency hospital care, emergency medical services, or other emergency health care furnished through non-Department of Veterans Affairs providers by the required payment date.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8B0E70ADC5164AB2A5758EF31DEFC160"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Submittal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General shall submit to Congress a report on the study conducted under paragraph (1), including the total amount of interest penalties paid by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs under section 3902 of title 31, United States Code, by reason of a delayed payment.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3CD426A02E984B0E9B86FE3255A592A3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H830CE10D597548508D9E42BA2E5E73F1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>delayed payment</term> means a proper invoice that is not paid by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs until after the required payment date.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF9CBE580FCE64B3EB6068B5783A6A2E2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>proper invoice</term> has the meaning given that term in section 3901(a) of title 31, United States Code.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H7E5AD2F11D9B496FA27C342584356236"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>required payment date</term> means, with respect to proper invoices for emergency hospital care, emergency medical services, or other emergency health care, the date that payment is due pursuant to standards determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


