<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H2B926A31F1B04458901FBB99077921DD" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4798 IH: Inventory of Assets for Communications Facilities Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4798</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180116">January 16, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001092">Mr. Collins of New York</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for an inventory of Federal assets on which a communications facility could be
			 constructed or that could otherwise be made available for use in
			 connection with the construction or operation of a communications facility
			 or provision of communications service.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HFC5F9922CE5F4C6D8002962DDE14C863" style="OLC">
 <section id="H8A25CC24A39F4F1FAF3E5BA597FFD4BE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Inventory of Assets for Communications Facilities Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H40F8AAB10FAE416CAEC51B73AA36CB8C" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Inventory of Federal assets</header> <subsection id="H01404A382E7E430BB85E596C6477F591"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act—</text>
 <paragraph id="H47596A9356CD46CEA958D12FBD04CB41"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Administrator of General Services, in coordination with the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information, shall ensure that the database established under section 5(c) of Executive Order 13327 (69 Fed. Reg. 5895) includes an inventory of covered assets, which shall include the information provided under subsections (b) and (c);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H986C4A80FCA84109B56078C05995EE05"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Administrator shall make such inventory available to the Assistant Secretary for purposes of paragraph (3); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE3B95FAF29204E18942D0EA88BA5F663"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Assistant Secretary shall make such inventory available to any entity that constructs or operates communications facilities or provides communications service.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA448C58166F44BD8868EC7251F1AC4A3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Provision of information by Executive agencies</header>
 <paragraph id="HA8D146CA85A04D0CB9AC47852DFD4560"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 9 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the head of an Executive agency shall provide to the Administrator, in a manner and format to be determined by the Administrator, the information described in paragraph (2) with respect to a covered asset of such agency.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC6143B41AA174EDDB6D65BBEBDAD221B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information described</header><text>The information described in this paragraph is—</text> <subparagraph id="HDE9F3ECC62EE48A1AE17AAFD5C4519BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the location of the covered asset;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A9B243D2AAC4CA192CBE3923D84D1F7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the type of the covered asset, such as whether the asset is a building (and the type of building), land (and the type or use of the land), right-of-way, easement, utility pole, wireless communications tower, underground utility route, or cable on which capacity is available for lease;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H130B3A69A85A4FE2BD7775BC939E42EA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>contact information for an officer or employee of the agency who may be contacted for permitting or other information about the covered asset;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H63DC0FA39D3C47D59210F4F02DD6D9F2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>whether the covered asset is historic property (as defined in section 300308 of title 54, United States Code); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4427C780FE0942DBB1EFB9020E650FF1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>such other information as the Administrator considers appropriate.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9729B0ED73D4775ACFFE45F66360B1A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Provision of updated information</header> <subparagraph id="HC9D7B630F181405BB31EDA0AF6F51F82"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Change in information</header><text>In the case of a change in any of the information provided to the Administrator under paragraph (1) with respect to a covered asset of an Executive agency, the head of such agency shall provide updated information to the Administrator not later than 30 days after such change.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC509C5801744477DB83281BBEFCABF56"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Acquisition of new covered asset</header><text>In the case of the acquisition of a covered asset by an Executive agency after the date that is 9 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the head of such agency shall provide to the Administrator the information required by paragraph (1) with respect to such asset not later than 30 days after such acquisition.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HFEF739956ABB4A7787DA132646DCF7D8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Exclusion of information for national security reasons</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H5C5CC5498FC6461BB5CA1B864DF5F88E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Classified information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of an Executive agency may exclude classified information from the information provided to the Administrator under this subsection.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H221F876CBCB94EB8A41D06B3A8C269F2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Other information</header><text>If the head of an Executive agency determines, in consultation with the Administrator, that inclusion of information (other than classified information) about a covered asset of such agency in the inventory established under subsection (a) would harm national security, the head of the agency may exclude such information from the information provided to the Administrator under this subsection.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H45AD3A3071D7478E85A3993F930F6C51"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Classified information defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this paragraph, the term <quote>classified information</quote> means any information or material that has been determined by the Federal Government pursuant to an Executive order, statute, or regulation, to require protection against unauthorized disclosure for reasons of national security and any restricted data, as defined in section 11 y. of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2014">42 U.S.C. 2014(y)</external-xref>).</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8DF834B92A824EC3BC30ED3A69E651A3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Information on State and local assets</header>
 <paragraph id="H2783C489A72B4FF49941F3745273AF7D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Voluntary provision of information</header><text>A State or local government may provide to the Administrator for inclusion in the inventory established under subsection (a), in a manner and format to be determined by the Administrator, information with respect to a State or local asset that would be a covered asset if under the custody and control of an Executive agency.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE1218E84A1284A05B17267AD886B1127"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion of information</header><text>The Administrator shall include in such inventory any information provided by a State or local government in accordance with paragraph (1) in the same manner as information provided by an Executive agency under subsection (b).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H452BEBB99E404316BBFB53A496821CD3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Provision of updated information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a change in any of the information provided to the Administrator under paragraph (1) with respect to a State or local asset, the State or local government shall provide updated information to the Administrator not later than 30 days after such change. If a State or local government does not comply with the preceding sentence, the Administrator shall deny the State or local government access to the inventory established under subsection (a).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H02C29392D96B4D3F827FA0F615624070"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Updating of Inventory</header><text>After the establishment of the inventory under subsection (a), the Administrator shall include in the inventory information provided under subsection (b) or (c) not later than the date that is 7 days after the Administrator receives such information. The information with respect to each covered asset or State or local asset in the inventory shall include the most recent date on which such information was added or updated.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H3CC4B993122840599E581F66887117D5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Format of location information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The information in the inventory established under subsection (a) about the location of a covered asset or State or local asset shall be in Geographic Information System format or another format that the Administrator considers appropriate.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF24B903DD8D3438798F4B4CE1EEC9297"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Information security</header><text>The Administrator shall adopt measures to prevent unauthorized access to the information in the inventory established under subsection (a).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H16D7C83CFB624A30887F4ECADF60FE68"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HA6681B82457E4F9DB04BFAC62855D082"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator of General Services.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB7FEC498C2CE4AD2A6AAA5A00B115A89"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assistant Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Assistant Secretary</quote> means the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H0C8723D49A644258B715C5A64E74BE99"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Communications facility</header><text>The term <quote>communications facility</quote> includes—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HDC57C98BB5974AA3A164A59BC6122513"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any wireless or wireline infrastructure for the transmission of writing, signs, signals, data, images, pictures, or sounds of all kinds;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCCAEFB2F635844B6BFC936046ED8E534"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any transmitting device, tower, or support structure, and any equipment, switches, wiring, cabling, power sources, shelters, or cabinets, associated with the provision of communications services; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6BDB0D6C034F4801AA020FC115B0D389"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any antenna or apparatus that—</text> <clause id="H24AF5570C5F449C1A4BF0081F67269DD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is designed for the purpose of emitting radio frequency;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8A83A591FB3C497A875DD4570F8BDBA8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is designed to be operated, or is operating, from a fixed location; and</text> </clause><clause id="H13D245F9B54342F19CA2CAF5321551FE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is added to a tower, building, or other structure.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A295237F22A476CBBCF78B37B79763F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Communications service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>communications service</quote> means a service for the transmission of writing, signs, signals, data, images, pictures, or sounds of all kinds.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H12AAC11B2B5B445A847994FF28007C23"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Covered asset</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered asset</quote> means, with respect to an agency, any Federal real property (as defined in section 2(a) of Executive Order 13327 (69 Fed. Reg. 5895)) under the custody and control of such agency—</text>
					<subparagraph commented="no" id="H288EBE695544466CA32C12EDDC89EE81"><enum>(A)</enum>
 <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC792F0968DD04AD792F40829BE5EE3CF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>on which a broadband communications facility could be constructed; or</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="HF85EDBDCF4984D7080DF2EAF318207A5" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that could otherwise be made available to an entity that—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="H581CC1E5FC9D4F1A8D7550162A826E81"><enum>(I)</enum><text>constructs or operates broadband communications facilities for use in connection with such construction or operation; or</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H987844E8284C4D0BBED23F60A39CF6F8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>provides broadband communications service for use in connection with such provision; and</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H88AF59A3CB624739BD387D50EFBF45ED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that is suitable for the deployment, or use in connection with the deployment, of broad­band communications facilities or broad­band communications services.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HEAD33F43491142D681B73BDE48C0D09E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Executive agency</header><text>The term <quote>Executive agency</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 105 of title 5, United States Code.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

