<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H05885CC8338C4F15A8FC0CDC04355044" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5362 IH: IRS Information Technology Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5362</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180321">March 21, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000813">Mrs. Walorski</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to modernize and improve the management of Internal
			 Revenue Service information technology.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H7443D10FF9AD4A418FCB79B536E84EAE" style="OLC">
 <section id="H1C71737E29074AD2A360A7D56A033573" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>IRS Information Technology Accountability Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section commented="no" id="HF1A3BF7A440D4B778EA8979EDB61A1E5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Management of Internal Revenue Service information technology</header> <subsection commented="no" id="H937C1C4A3D1B4E4E9CBB98DC076347B3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Duties and responsibilities of Internal Revenue Service Chief Information Officer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/7803">Section 7803</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3E17E715044345899DAA70E77DE57DA1" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="HBBEBD9C0592347CFAC9728A495F8D859"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Internal Revenue Service Chief Information Officer</header>
 <paragraph id="HC86BA7D36FF04E898411EB6BF5C1075C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be in the Internal Revenue Service an Internal Revenue Service Chief Information Officer (hereafter referred to in this subsection as the <quote>IRS CIO</quote>) who shall be appointed by the Commissioner of Internal Revenue after consultation with the Chief Information Officer of the Department of the Treasury.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H78DC708ABCA9401D9168F56CF03B4977"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Centralized responsibility for Internal Revenue Service information technology</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commissioner of Internal Revenue (and the Secretary) shall act through the IRS CIO with respect to all development, implementation, and maintenance of information technology for the Internal Revenue Service. Any reference in this subsection to the IRS CIO which directs the IRS CIO to take any action, or to assume any responsibility, shall be treated as a reference to the Commissioner of Internal Revenue acting through the IRS CIO.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HED086223E84A457782376BECAC4BDE1E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>General duties and responsibilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The IRS CIO shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H13B4860D0E004F7DBE6D2E465F352B8B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be responsible for the development, implementation, and maintenance of information technology for the Internal Revenue Service,</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H60D525BC5E724EBCB2F5171188814A49"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that the information technology of the Internal Revenue Service is secure and integrated,</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF68E147EE259437AA7A94786284313EB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>maintain operational control of all information technology for the Internal Revenue Service,</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BCECCD2C5644622A9D103FA69C228C1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>be the principal advocate for the information technology needs of the Internal Revenue Service, and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3F695E809B47479C94406C2FCB07E4B4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>consult with the Chief Procurement Officer of the Internal Revenue Service to ensure that the information technology acquired for the Internal Revenue Service is consistent with—</text>
 <clause id="H66B34DC2320B4F8CB4F38264DD4988E0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the goals and requirements specified in subparagraphs (A) through (D), and</text> </clause><clause id="H70FDEA70E4AE45CFACDC4FB47B2F27DC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the strategic plan developed under paragraph (4).</text>
								</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H53F0A9DF42544416BF709AB6BCCD9CA5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Strategic plan</header>
 <subparagraph id="H493464D326BF4D5C88EC62408E648E69"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The IRS CIO shall develop and implement a multiyear strategic plan for the information technology needs of the Internal Revenue Service. Such plan shall—</text>
 <clause id="H2C9CB8C37E4F47A3AA7C4DACAE01E512"><enum>(i)</enum><text>include performance measurements of such technology and of the implementation of such plan,</text> </clause><clause id="H05759496FD01445D935B5A1E7CC9A519"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include a plan for an integrated enterprise architecture of the information technology of the Internal Revenue Service,</text>
 </clause><clause id="HE843CDF175D4406D8239CA85CEC676E5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>include and take into account the resources needed to accomplish such plan, and</text> </clause><clause id="HACB810EF74B84581B0A3A366B7E04CD7"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">align with the needs and strategic plan of the Internal Revenue Service.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAABA894C208E41348D5A85A7E408FA87"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Plan updates</header><text>The IRS CIO shall, not less frequently than annually, review and update the strategic plan under subparagraph (A) (including the plan for an integrated enterprise architecture described in subparagraph (A)(ii)) to take into account the development of new information technology and the needs of the Internal Revenue Service.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H52D0D928D2DE4FC995BE2D042E0E3FEC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Scope of authority</header>
 <subparagraph id="H6B919ABBF3764B868BB78B7F7CA6F25A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Information technology</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <quote>information technology</quote> has the meaning given such term by section 11101 of title 40, United States Code.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A20843B3CAE4F178E7956F2FE22194F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Internal Revenue Service</header><text>Any reference in this subsection to the Internal Revenue Service includes a reference to all components of the Internal Revenue Service, including—</text>
 <clause id="H555F641CC29740BFB7975F1EDE25591B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Office of the Taxpayer Advocate, and</text> </clause><clause id="H690E16150495495BBC159C3727769FA1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>except as otherwise provided by the Secretary with respect to information technology related to matters described in subsection (b)(3)(B), the Office of the Chief Counsel.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H28225567B0E248989DFB7731ECC395D4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Independent verification and validation of the Customer Account Data Engine 2 and Enterprise Case
 Management System</header><text>The Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall enter into a contract with an independent reviewer to verify and validate the implementation plans (including the performance milestones and cost estimates included in such plans) developed for the Customer Account Data Engine 2 and the Enterprise Case Management System. Such contract shall require that such verification and validation be completed not later than the date which is 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H0F8CE42E77BC46FAADFBACDB05810F15"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination of IRS CIO and Chief Procurement Officer of the Internal Revenue Service</header>
 <paragraph id="H57F2C3B4EB144496800246651F69873B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Chief Procurement Officer of the Internal Revenue Service shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HF4BEA6BF4EBE433FB5AEDC326969F97A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify all significant IRS information technology acquisitions and provide written notification to the Internal Revenue Service Chief Information Officer of each such acquisition in advance of such acquisition, and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9F65DC68B9240BA8D38ABFCDE1E4C4E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">regularly consult with the Internal Revenue Service Chief Information Officer regarding acquisitions of information technology for the Internal Revenue Service, including meeting with the Internal Revenue Service Chief Information Officer regarding such acquisitions upon request.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF56CBB40430D40CC9994F01A3B9C31A7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Significant IRS information technology acquisitions</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <quote>significant IRS information technology acquisitions</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HB1A8194510F74D7F9896147F8188EB48"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any acquisition of information technology for the Internal Revenue Service in excess of $1,000,000, and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC527A27DA72C4DC3A5A1DC342197E5C3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such other acquisitions of information technology for the Internal Revenue Service (or categories of such acquisitions) as the Internal Revenue Service Chief Information Officer, in consultation with the Chief Procurement Officer of the Internal Revenue Service, may identify.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA65F7B6EEAB445DDAE7E76D639C63AEC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Scope</header><text>Terms used in this subsection which are also used in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/7803">section 7803(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as amended by subsection (a)) shall have the same meaning as when used in such section.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


