<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HEA59222CCB5644ED97FAB1E75047E12F" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5327 IH: Comprehensive Opioid Recovery Centers Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5327</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180319">March 19, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000410">Mr. Gene Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000570">Mr. Ben Ray Luján of New Mexico</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title V of the Public Health Service Act to establish a grant program to create
			 comprehensive opioid recovery centers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H16AFAA1AB2B747228E815BD7C5A6E8BF" style="OLC">
 <section id="H3696E5BAF8B34C29874AE4602BBA97BE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Comprehensive Opioid Recovery Centers Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H9B97B9F9AC2D4800A7E4C948D2FD0994" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Comprehensive opioid recovery centers</header> <subsection id="H9FF1A79800314775A45851F1258DF846"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part D of title V of the Public Health Service Act is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H42BA7C799AEB49838E4D8B9902B06422" style="OLC">
					<section id="HBEB2EF81F8C64947BC211D0DC1A65A93"><enum>550.</enum><header>Comprehensive opioid recovery centers</header>
 <subsection id="H8F4029BB659940E9B78E0A521A7FFCEA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use, shall award grants on a competitive basis to eligible entities to establish or operate a comprehensive opioid recovery center (referred to in this section as a <quote>Center</quote>).</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="HD4D6B9EC36594415AA14798BD02D17FC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant period</header>
 <paragraph id="HC0A7389BB74C480D9318F0D2F5E4D665"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A grant awarded under subsection (a) shall be for a period not less than three years and not more than five years.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC32BDCB1458246448F2D33F08AFFD3F7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Renewal</header><text>A grant awarded under subsection (a) may be renewed, on a competitive basis, for additional periods of time, as determined by the Secretary. In determining whether to renew a grant under this paragraph, the Secretary shall consider the data submitted under subsection (h).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HBBA3AAB7AE0B40A3AAF76C99F0D5D96C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Minimum number of Centers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall allocate the amounts made available under subsection (i) in such amounts that not fewer than 10 Centers will be established across the United States.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF2281EBE70AD4D96B6BE747B4EF1AC9D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application</header><text>In order to be eligible for a grant under subsection (a), an entity shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may require. Such application shall include—</text>
 <paragraph id="H0CC10558C2BB4D44BBB7C22C3C1E8342"><enum>(1)</enum><text>evidence that such entity carries out, or is capable of coordinating with other entities to carry out, the activities described in subsection (g); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H566DEF7A79FD4FB6A5614E65705F437B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such other information as the Secretary may require.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC16FD740406A4FD697909026CC493B66"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under subsection (a), the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities located in a State or Indian country (as defined in section 1151 of title 18, United States Code)—</text>
 <paragraph id="H1CD8B32F3AA44F7FBF69F81A62A76300"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with a high per capita drug overdose mortality rate, as determined by the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE8FF1B663CF240CE961398CAD765D03E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>based on any other criteria or need, as determined by the Secretary.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H81DA2AD478D54A688A080A76EA224F34"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Use of grant funds</header><text>An eligible entity awarded a grant under subsection (a) shall use the grant funds to establish or operate a Center to carry out the activities described in subsection (g).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF8DD1FBD82B6472BB4F7C4DD1EE518CF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Center activities</header><text>Each Center shall, at a minimum, carry out the activities described in this subsection. In the case of a Center that determines that a service described in paragraph (2) cannot reasonably be carried out by the Center, such Center shall contract with such other entities as may be necessary to ensure that patients have access to the full range of services described in such paragraph.</text>
 <paragraph id="HD0705ED980794E2C991DD58A03633B29"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Community engagement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each Center shall carry out the following outreach activities:</text> <subparagraph id="HAB404FC32EFF4AEB809132B7DF85F6AF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Train and supervise outreach staff to work with schools, workplaces, faith-based organizations, State and local health departments, law enforcement, and first responders to ensure that such institutions are aware of the services of the Center.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B05FA171280497D953212DC6F472C2C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Disseminate and make available online evidence-based resources that educate professionals and the public on opioid use disorder and other substance use disorders.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBAAAB8110084906BDE8894F155E8177"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Treatment and recovery services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each Center shall provide the following treatment and recovery services:</text> <subparagraph id="HC925266A10C84E4E9B76EAC6BA8A3AD3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ensure that intake evaluations meet the clinical needs of patients.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1AF1669F3EDC458F9B1C4D66F1E06C09"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Periodically conduct patient assessments to ensure continued and meaningful recovery, as defined by the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43BCF139192F41C991CC4BAB85398F4A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Provide the full continuum of treatment services, including—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H82FFA2CF144C43CBBA627B2AFA7DD337"><enum>(i)</enum><text>all drugs approved by the Food and Drug Administration to treat substance use disorders, including opioid use disorder and alcohol use disorder;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H0220F714AFB447BF98FF0EA327F63CF2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>withdrawal management, which shall include medically supervised detoxification that includes patient evaluation, stabilization, and readiness for and entry into treatment;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H79C620943CC2456899E8B7C7AB584297"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>counseling and case management;</text> </clause><clause id="HE3FD871FCAF54446B663E241BEEF9112"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>residential rehabilitation;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1975036649BC4ED881048C6BDDEAE36F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>recovery housing;</text> </clause><clause id="H34FC837649BD40A3A11548FF0305E171"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>community-based and peer recovery support services;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8624807F83714704BC692FA8F9F19678"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>job training and placement assistance to support reintegration into the workforce; and</text> </clause><clause id="H1E98EECC2C334C65A876CA1B4406A21B"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>other best practices, as determined by the Secretary.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99FF731613B9409093B502BADF6D05C3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Administer an onsite pharmacy and provide toxicology services.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A9F769EB5E040B5A33BF235F07135B0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Establish and operate a secure and confidential electronic health information system.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5914733961AA43A48ACC38651105E6B0"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Data reporting and program oversight</header><text>With respect to a grant awarded under subsection (a) to an eligible entity for a Center, not later than 90 days after the end of the first year of the grant period, and annually thereafter for the duration of the grant period (including the duration of any renewal period for such grant), the entity shall submit data, as appropriate, to the Secretary regarding—</text>
 <paragraph id="HBA419BC7FBD642D389EAB80A25208FE2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the programs and activities funded by the grant;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB66BF80314484C91B64D4D570D5C1B25"><enum>(2)</enum><text>health outcomes of individuals with a substance use disorder who received services from the Center;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H239433E5CC5B450087191ECF826222B2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the effectiveness of interventions designed, tested, and evaluated by the Center; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H6966B5ABDCA44B21B100917651C22454"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any other information that the Secretary may require for the purpose of—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF28A19F34C41483791FBD3240FF05D56"><enum>(A)</enum><text>evaluating the effectiveness of the Center; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA37E33B70F834250AE10D774B217A3FD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensuring that the Center is complying with all the requirements of the grant, including providing the full continuum of services described in subsection (g)(2)(C) and providing drugs and devices for overdose reversal under such subsection.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7A6750A43E1B488B9E11503A67F58E3D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023 for purposes of carrying out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H5F729769DE31434B8A2D8CFF464B0F56"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header>
 <paragraph id="H1DD3242533BB4251B31BA90765CBC14B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Preliminary report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than three years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit to Congress a preliminary report that analyzes data submitted under section 550(h) of the Public Health Service Act, as added by subsection (a).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2C6190A7B3E5423CA4173DD35605CF71"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than one year after submitting the preliminary report required under paragraph (1), the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit to Congress a final report that includes—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HDBA0CAAD165542E49DB5F7C6B210D2BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an evaluation of the effectiveness of comprehensive opioid recovery centers established or operated pursuant to section 550 of the Public Health Service Act, as added by subsection (a);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H586E1A222638419395D5D4D5E4F0B26F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recommendations on whether the grant program established under such section 550 should be reauthorized and expanded; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC31BA44415774088A713BB3300040473"><enum>(C)</enum><text>standards and best practices for the treatment of substance use disorders.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

