<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="A1" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4988 IH: Conservation Assistance Loan Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4988</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180208">February 8, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001286">Mrs. Bustos</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish nonrecourse conservation assistance loans for loan commodities produced on certain
			 farms, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" id="HCE60D96EC66D4B5A983706DD4C1841BE" style="OLC">
 <section id="HC8808302347C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Conservation Assistance Loan Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H28A9C0DCC4FB4F9789EDBC65EBFF682B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Availability of nonrecourse conservation assistance loans for loan commodities</header> <subsection id="H9C2975AA714D416F88E2CE75ED6D39AA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Nonrecourse loans available</header> <paragraph id="HE2937301119143669E46DA7B52803EF2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For each of the 2018 through 2022 crops of each loan commodity, the Secretary shall make available to qualified producers on a farm nonrecourse conservation assistance loans for loan commodities produced on the farm.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFBF45AB6F60C4BFC877967C945805B41"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified producer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>qualified producer</quote> means a producer eligible for a nonrecourse marketing loan under section 1201 of the Agricultural Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/9031">7 U.S.C. 9031</external-xref>) that agrees to not apply for such loan for each of the 2018 through 2022 crops described in paragraph (1).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAACBF49FC9E54D5BBE797CC288F5F82B"><enum>(b)</enum><header> Eligible production</header><text>The producers on a farm shall be eligible for a conservation assistance loan under subsection (a) for any quantity of a loan commodity produced on the farm.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H9A1E5EBF752B4E349B4FA3D24DEA0CA6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Loan rates for nonrecourse conservation assistance loans</header>
 <paragraph id="H4ED0422376204AFDBCA4FD8098D9B7FB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), for purposes of each of the 2018 through 2022 crop years, the loan rate for a conservation assistance loan under this section for a loan commodity shall be—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H9476D30650564C439E9E2DB6140F09AA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for beginning farmers and ranchers (as determined by the Secretary), 75 percent of the national average price received by producers during the 12-month marketing year for the loan commodity for the most recent 5 crop years, excluding—</text>
 <clause id="H9632648631AD49F6BF83A3E2807F7B0F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the crop year with the highest price; and</text> </clause><clause id="H4E1062192005462782428C360C2A5C11"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the crop year with the lowest price; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC6F2B94CA644C33A0A0412B65755717"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for producers not described in paragraph (1), 60 percent of the national average price received by producers during the 12-month marketing year for the loan commodity for the most recent 5 crop years, excluding—</text>
 <clause id="HC3F290942A7A488091A6290F57B182C1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the crop year with the highest price; and</text> </clause><clause id="HCF4C7B6A0B534226962A3712F0210B6A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the crop year with the lowest price.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4FAF9231B474A01B1738553EFF61E10"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Special rule for cover crops</header><text>In the case of a producer who agrees to plant a cover crop on acres associated with the loan commodity, the applicable loan rate under paragraph (1) shall be increased by an amount equal to $0.20 per bushel.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6EF9A8E7BABB459AAB95AD60B166B37C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Terms of loans</header>
 <paragraph id="HE58B5295D474444EAD17A03553B60605"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of each loan commodity, a conservation loan under this section shall have a term of 9 months beginning on the first day of the first month after the month in which the loan is made.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H291C5279FF6C41109BA1BD82E5FB50D1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Extensions prohibited</header><text>The Secretary may not extend the term of a conservation assistance loan for any loan commodity.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFBA5D54C515F46C6B793FE53720FE8AC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Repayment of loans</header> <paragraph id="H2CC99581AAE5402DB3385168651B3E3D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall permit the producers on a farm to repay a conservation assistance loan under this section for a loan commodity at a rate that is the lesser of the following:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H0017E87398664CF7BD6ED8273FA83611"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The loan rate established under subsection (c).</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5667155B42647B5AD236F3A10CE7D34"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A rate that is equal to the expected market price for the loan commodity as calculated for crop insurance, as determined by the Secretary.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E3E65E1216B48799DA455F10CD66821"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Such other rate the Secretary determines will avoid or minimize potential loan forfeitures.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCAE4F27FCCFE4C1883F421AC06813BAC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Adjustments</header><text>The Secretary shall make all adjustments that the Secretary determines necessary to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H98F2A9818730435E8EE0855FF416DF18"><enum>(A)</enum><text>avoid forfeiture or the accumulation of stocks of the commodities placed under a loan under this section;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB940A11851564BAB9C8DEA0641241DE6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>minimize the costs incurred by the Federal Government;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H331A9CDC6D9C464EAA882AE21809C99D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>allow the commodity produced to be marketed freely and competitively, both domestically and internationally;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB269C45B60B441079C09AD19C3EE4B7C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>minimize discrepancies in conservation loan benefits across State boundaries and across country boundaries; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H665C557CF72C435F9C752506AEDA95E4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in the case of a producer who is prevented from planting a commercial crop due to weather or other natural events that interfered with cover crop determined (as determined by the Secretary), the Secretary may forgive the portion of the loan calculated under subsection (c)(2).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H354973203A0B4BF7B3E9B92105BB47E1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Compliance requirements</header><text>As a condition of the receipt of a conservation assistance loan under this section, the producer shall during the crop year of the loan—</text>
 <paragraph id="HFC2EA10F58CF4936B568A21E323D0F7A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>comply with applicable conservation requirements under subtitle B of title XII of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3811">16 U.S.C. 3811</external-xref> et seq.) and applicable wetland protection requirements under subtitle C of title XII of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3821">16 U.S.C. 3821</external-xref> et seq.);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H583FFC0053F245CFAF0F7D3B7DD485F5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>agree to use a reduced tillage method and nutrient management practices (as determined by the Secretary to be appropriate for soil health management) for the acres associated with the commodity covered by the loan; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H52B54B36CDEE4AE59DD29BE8263353AC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in the case of a loan calculated under subsection (c)(2), agree to plant a cover crop on the acres associated with the loan commodity, as determined by the Secretary to be appropriate.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9C3DCE3AE85C417C97062CD207A3940D"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Farm Service Agency report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Farm Service Agency shall submit an annual report to the Secretary that includes the information with respect to the compliance requirements specified in paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (f) relating to each conservation assistance loan under this section that was fully repaid in the preceding fiscal year.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


