<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H28D677CA33174C9DABC21D816433E8D4" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4841 IH: Standardizing Electronic Prior Authorization for Safe Prescribing Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4841</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180118">January 18, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000570">Mr. Ben Ray Luján of New Mexico</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to provide for electronic prior authorization under
			 Medicare part D for covered part D drugs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H3864014C9EC04B6E8D4E067A9AA1F817" style="OLC">
 <section id="H4AB31D9B599B450E845DCD79E7EFEE98" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Standardizing Electronic Prior Authorization for Safe Prescribing Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HE97C5859DD0849B79347402D4FC387BF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Electronic prior authorization for covered part D drugs</header> <subsection id="HEF331118E2944A3EB4D6B00D0FEDC6EF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Inclusion in electronic prescription program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1860D–4(e)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-104">42 U.S.C. 1395w–104(e)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H77FA0BEDAB3D4DD6ADD198BA902776A8" style="OLC">
					<subparagraph id="H57A54AFBF8D94DEEB2543ED96578052D"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Electronic prior authorization</header>
 <clause id="H7C50C62B8C25492E9542CD0A6B7BBD02"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective on and after January 1, 2020, the program shall provide for the secure electronic transmittal of—</text>
 <subclause id="HFAF4105759E4465E909F64DA53EAA0BF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a prior authorization request from the prescribing health care professional for coverage of a covered part D drug for a part D eligible individual enrolled in a part D plan (as defined in section 1860D–23(a)(5)) to the PDP sponsor or Medicare Advantage organization offering such plan; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HA743AF08DCF149F28AD674F8140AFE39"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a response, in accordance with this subparagraph, from such PDP sponsor or Medicare Advantage organization, respectively, to such professional.</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause id="H16D6E1A8249D4B02859C751685CCFF98"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Electronic transmission</header>
 <subclause id="HB2156F5CABE04C8387F40AE4E1D563CB"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, a facsimile, proprietary payer portal, or electronic form shall not be treated as an electronic transmission described in clause (i).</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H73A49F67BEE14BF9BDB6882A27155CF5"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to be treated, for purposes of this subparagraph, as an electronic transmission described in clause (i), such transmission shall comply with technical standards adopted by the Secretary in consultation with the National Council for Prescription Drug Programs, other standard setting organizations determined appropriate by the Secretary, and stakeholders including PDP sponsors, Medicare Advantage organizations, health care professionals, and health information technology software vendors.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H49BBF48483A440EC9B0C574FED105828"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress regarding electronic prior authorization</header><text>It is the sense of the Congress that—</text> <paragraph id="HA54B455CF49548409EF729535F9FF745"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">there should be increased use of electronic prior authorizations for coverage of covered part D drugs for part D eligible individuals enrolled in prescription drug plans under part D of title XVIII of the Social Security Act and MA–PD plans under part C of such title to reduce access delays by resolving coverage issues before prescriptions for such drugs are transmitted; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H41985B5A2C2148ECA557487EFB9B3560"><enum>(2)</enum><text>greater priority should be placed on increasing the adoption of use of such electronic prior authorizations among prescribers of such drugs, pharmacies, PDP sponsors, and Medicare Advantage organizations.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


