<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H24DC578154F14A85A6B644D9E1B5C702" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5766 IH: Securing Public Areas of Transportation Facilities Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5766</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180510">May 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve the security of public areas of transportation facilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H7C7522489C4D44A6BBEC1B3C14D3E74C" style="OLC">
 <section id="H9E23C39406514035B33F5D3DE0E45E68" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing Public Areas of Transportation Facilities Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HAB87192345644FF8BDE613F20F08E9AE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
 <paragraph id="HC1BEDE22E1B8438883AD5CDDB801303C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Public and private sector stakeholders</header><text>The term <quote>public and private sector stakeholders</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 114(u)(1)(C) of title 49, United States Code.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE8DA490501024F29802EA6C8D0A2728E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Surface transportation asset</header><text>The term <quote>surface transportation asset</quote> includes facilities, equipment, or systems used to provide transportation services by—</text>
 <subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H540EEC3D99E44E69AEB648DDA606B930"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a public transportation agency (as such term is defined in section 1402(5) of the Implementing Recommendations of the 9/11 Commission Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/53">Public Law 110–53</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/1131">6 U.S.C. 1131(5)</external-xref>));</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD05FC862B8D944C582E86A6E7AE020D8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a railroad carrier (as such term is defined in section 20102(3) of title 49, United States Code);</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8E08DD3FE454303A51CDBA05ADC9930"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an owner or operator of—</text>
 <clause id="H58AECAFB03134BC5B552491E7E5C15F6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an entity offering scheduled, fixed-route transportation services by over-the road bus (as such term is defined in section 1501(4) of the Implementing Recommendations of the 9/11 Commission Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/53">Public Law 110–53</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/1151">6 U.S.C. 1151(4)</external-xref>)); or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H4375D18CFE4D4DBE8CB1F987BE15A97E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a bus terminal; or</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61A4EAA9984E4039BC4C21DEE1FD35FA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>other transportation facilities, equipment, or systems, as determined by the Secretary.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HBC08269ECA66403899CF2F6AF74BF862"><enum>3.</enum><header>Public area security working group</header>
 <subsection id="H83E86AEB60CA4C4BBA606E934558545F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Working group</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall establish a working group to promote collaborative engagement between the Department of Homeland Security and public and private sector stakeholders to develop non-binding recommendations for enhancing security in public areas of transportation facilities (including facilities that are surface transportation assets), including recommendations regarding the following topics:</text>
 <paragraph id="H630B7C77739F43BD992D28D143E67E46"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Information sharing and interoperable communication capabilities among the Department of Homeland Security and public and private stakeholders with respect to terrorist or other threats.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9AB18F03DB144B1CAF45182327ACAA9E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Coordinated incident response procedures.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HA12682A1E9A04A0F92C0EAA6527CC2CD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The prevention of terrorist attacks and other incidents through strategic planning, security training, exercises and drills, law enforcement patrols, worker vetting, and suspicious activity reporting.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA1706D0D44F54111A51F6E60A661A365"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Infrastructure protection through effective construction design barriers and installation of advanced surveillance and other security technologies.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A849A1482BC4290BB8162EB42600C0D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than one year after the establishment of the working group under subsection (a) and annually thereafter for five years, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall report to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate on the working group’s organization, participation, activities, findings, and non-binding recommendations for the immediately preceding 12-month period. The Secretary may publish a public version of such report that describes the working group’s activities and such related matters as would be informative to the public, consistent with section 552(b) of title 5, United States Code.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H111BF5C574E44BF184A186815E9B0F8F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Inapplicability of the Federal Advisory Committee Act</header><text>The Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.) shall not apply to the working group established under subsection (a) or any subsidiary thereof.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H91022BED3B384A47B7A4165D505A4682"><enum>4.</enum><header>Technical assistance</header>
 <subsection id="HC628855F1B8843CD83B6C781CCFB9A3C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall—</text> <paragraph id="H60454860BE344B879D27CB1C9B2BC633"><enum>(1)</enum><text>inform owners and operators of surface transportation assets about the availability of technical assistance, including vulnerability assessment tools and cybersecurity guidelines, to help protect and enhance the resilience of public areas of such assets; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE28FBF4FD27A48C48C9F685AFD7E2603"><enum>(2)</enum><text>subject to the availability of appropriations, provide such technical assistance to requesting owners and operators of surface transportation assets.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H110A07CD29104E0E838068689507BA61"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Best practices</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall publish on the Department of Homeland Security’s website and widely disseminate, as appropriate, best practices for protecting and enhancing the resilience of public areas of transportation facilities (including facilities that are surface transportation assets), including associated frameworks or templates for implementation. Such best practices shall be updated periodically.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HF84AA782B4FF4D589079BA3E2C55E3D4"><enum>5.</enum><header>Review</header>
 <subsection id="HD02578588F984E7B807FF0B7C93E153E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Transportation Security Administration shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report that includes a review of regulations, directives, policies, and procedures issued by the Administrator regarding the transportation of a firearm and ammunition, and, as appropriate, information on plans to modify any such regulation, directive, policy, or procedure based on such review.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HBB72CE2D70DD4CF8B1120063DA3A6504"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In preparing the report required under subsection (a), the Administrator of the Transportation Security Administration shall consult with the Aviation Security Advisory Committee (established pursuant to section 44946 of title 49, United States Code) and appropriate public and private sector stakeholders.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


