<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H12505BC284D54FBEA49DDBF3825E3B97" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4845 IH: Connecting Communities Post Disasters Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4845</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180119">January 19, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="O000168">Mr. Olson</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide that the Federal Communications Commission and communications service providers regulated by the Commission under the Communications Act of 1934 shall not be subject to certain provisions of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 and the National Historic Preservation Act with respect to the construction, rebuilding, or hardening of communications facilities following a major disaster or an emergency declared by the President, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H385CAC00569840EC881054440DCB90C6" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0BDFAA1EB655412C94C7C9A73C602763" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Connecting Communities Post Disasters Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H999FDF75825F473391EBC336CD25C402"><enum>2.</enum><header>Application of NEPA and NHPA to covered communications projects</header> <subsection id="H9CE8DF9105EC4439A58B75DF2FA1212E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>NEPA considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Communications Commission shall treat covered projects as a class of action categorically excluded under section 1508.4 of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulation), from any requirement to prepare an environmental assessment or environmental impact statement under section 102(2)(C) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4332">42 U.S.C. 4332(2)(C)</external-xref>).</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H00C100AC12994C7E89A0FB2498936F09"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National historic preservation considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 306108 of title 54, United States Code, shall not apply with respect to a covered project for which the Federal Communications Commission is required to issue a permit or that is otherwise subject to the jurisdiction of the Federal Communications Commission.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6E0C13542A4942208A30FA1ECAD8712B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H66A02A80A53048BBA628A28F68BF0F43" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Communications facility</header><text>The term <quote>communications facility</quote> includes—</text> <subparagraph id="H58DC48C3CC9D4729BFFE33015F37229E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any wireless or wireline infrastructure for the transmission of writing, signs, signals, data, images, pictures, or sounds of all kinds;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEA0C14F6E53D4169BD0F1CC12CE199E7" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any transmitting device, tower, or support structure, and any equipment, switches, wiring, cabling, power sources, shelters, or cabinets, associated with the provision of communications services; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAF186A3ED01D4868AB94DD31555829C4" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any antenna or apparatus that—</text> 
<clause id="H64278F36ECF24075BC93370A6AA9EDCC" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is designed for the purpose of emitting radio frequency;</text></clause> <clause id="H886BCEE4222644298803C587D2645294" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is designed to be operated, or is operating, from a fixed location; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H79D5A13C599747D9B96CFF7DD3490123" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is added to a tower, building, or other structure.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC962FB2EFB0B419A88BBE2492FAC10F4" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Communications service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>communications service</quote> means a service for the transmission of writing, signs, signals, data, images, pictures, or sounds of all kinds.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3C264AD7CF2842838CAC731920450620"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered project</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered project</quote> means a project that—</text> <subparagraph id="HAB1E6B4327414F02B3BADE430F41C36B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is to be carried out within an area for which the President has declared a major disaster or an emergency under the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5121">42 U.S.C. 5121</external-xref> et seq.);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H650F17094FC4431989A6B8E9A94731A1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is to be carried out not later than 5 years after the date that the President made such declaration; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7E4F42493A16400992A4C9541B22EF6B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">replaces a communications facility damaged by such disaster or emergency or makes improvements to a communications facility in such area that could reasonably be considered as necessary for recovery from such disaster or emergency or to prevent or mitigate future disasters or emergencies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

