<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HC3535772FF0A4F86A94BEB75D781EB29" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4902 IH: Securing Required Funding for Water Infrastructure Now Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4902</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180130">January 30, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000386">Mr. Katko</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Water Infrastructure Finance and Innovation Act of 2014 to provide to State
			 infrastructure financing authorities additional opportunities to receive
			 loans under that Act to support drinking water and clean water State
			 revolving funds to deliver water infrastructure to communities across the
			 United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H7F13A3DE5925452CA9C2DC9433FE0270" style="OLC">
 <section id="H74470C9077B14312A89C6D4740777A0D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing Required Funding for Water Infrastructure Now Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SRF WIN Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H06A933267CF44ABCAE5DAA8138072CCB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Innovative financing for State loan funds</header> <subsection id="HB57354727FC54F98A6608D50E780EADE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Water Infrastructure Finance and Innovation Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/3901">33 U.S.C. 3901</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD0667561D0C84E8EA2C6E325DCC0094C" style="OLC">
					<section id="HD4293524266D4261B28BD7E313E9BDCD"><enum>5036.</enum><header>Innovative financing for State loan funds</header>
 <subsection id="H9E649BFAFD6D404BA174ABD6DC1D0140"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of State loan funds</header><text>In this section, the term <term>State loan funds</term> means—</text> <paragraph id="HB4A84120250A44629C2A605ADBA8469A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>State drinking water treatment revolving loan funds established under section 1452 of the Safe Drinking Water Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12</external-xref>); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4493D6FC56E849198606551454488487"><enum>(2)</enum><text><act-name parsable-cite="FWPCA">State water pollution control revolving funds established under title VI of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1381">33 U.S.C. 1381</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H04A69D0363D9472ABDF30CD54EA9B256"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Financial assistance to State loan funds</header><text>The Administrator may provide financial assistance under this section to State infrastructure financing authorities for State loan funds to carry out water and wastewater infrastructure projects in accordance with this section.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H92E21ACB86554E0EAB6C0720E47CBB6E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible activities</header>
 <paragraph id="H7C529093891B4988BEC3D0F6F83ABA79"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The following activities may be carried out by a State infrastructure financing authority with financial assistance made available under this section:</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE3D4EC900E4B467BAC8AD6E6A8445BBE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>One or more activities that are included in the intended use plan under section 606(c) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1386">33 U.S.C. 1386(c)</external-xref>).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8BAC0F694654742BFFA2DA5EA0398D5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>One or more activities that are included in the project priority list of the intended use plan under section 1452(b) of the Safe Drinking Water Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12(b)</external-xref>).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF37DAF84537E4578BE61A0612BFF89E1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header><text>Financial assistance provided under this section may be used to pay the reasonable costs of administration related to that financial assistance.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC83DE47E736D4AAB95C54C112D6B8B11"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application fees</header><text>Section 5029(b)(7) shall not apply to financial assistance made available under this section.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H694D45B6C7AD48A78D5A942E7282E57E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Treatment of projects</header><text>In determining whether to provide financial assistance under this section, the Administrator shall consider a project to be all of the activities included in an intended use plan described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of paragraph (1).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H989BFD0F35814901B7AE5076BF76C3FC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State and local decisionmaking</header><text>A State infrastructure financing authority that receives financial assistance under this section may use the assistance for any activity included in an intended use plan described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of paragraph (1).</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC429415AC75542FA8953294A0C540C07"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements</header>
 <paragraph id="H56CD0A68235C41BAAE1B2022E9DA392B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as otherwise provided in this section, the requirements and procedures under this subtitle shall apply to a project under this section.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H06DCC4F3DB194FA78AFCE13920B233AC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Interest rate</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HE35E2EED478042E981224E3929FD884E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the interest rate on a secured loan provided under this section shall be equal to the yield on United States Treasury securities of a similar maturity to the maturity of the secured loan on the date of execution of the loan agreement.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H43FB4EB6A5034BDCB471FAE0AA620003"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Certain States</header>
 <clause commented="no" id="H04FD3C43D7844F84AA5277B6E721594F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a State described in clause (ii)—</text> <subclause commented="no" id="H3CEFD0B1AFB84ED985BADCE730F18C41"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the interest rate on a secured loan provided under this section shall be 80 percent of the interest rate under subparagraph (A); but</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H1D00E9E69BC74D49B50960D650F6EA8E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if there is not sufficient demand for loans under this subparagraph (as determined by the Administrator), the Administrator may provide a secured loan at an interest rate that is not less than 50 percent and not more than 80 percent of the interest rate under subparagraph (A), as determined by the Administrator with respect to each loan.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HB39CD25DC5054EE1AF032AAF245C12D7"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>States described</header><text>A State referred to in clause (i) is a State—</text> <subclause commented="no" id="H5C249F4948554BE7BA75146593F340FE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>that received less than 2 percent of the total amount of funds made available to States for the State loan funds for the most recent fiscal year for which data is available; or</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H1C0789A1FA9544E88AAAD4175E5177BA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>for which the President has declared a major disaster in accordance with section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170</external-xref>) during the period beginning on January 1, 2017, and ending on the date of enactment of this section, if the secured loan is for a project related to wastewater or drinking water infrastructure damaged by the major disaster.</text>
										</subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H2C8B3F653DE3458DAA66DA93FA0E5606"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Distribution of loans</header>
 <clause commented="no" id="H02007B97623549BFB276A4526575BB93"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), of the total amount of funds made available to provide secured loans under this section—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="H2F09DD1C08FF46B280A11DAB2A4ACDEA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>50 percent shall be provided for secured loans at the interest rate described in subparagraph (A); and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H932B13407FFC44379356AC13237CA4C2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>50 percent shall be provided for secured loans at the interest rate described in subparagraph (B)(i) to States described in subparagraph (B)(ii).</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HE5BD9BB3E45D49BFA1B3958BFEE40114"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Reallocation</header><text>For any fiscal year, if amounts for loans described in clause (i)(II) remain available, the Administrator may reallocate the amounts to be used for loans described in clause (i)(I) to meet applicant demand.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H9A093FEC7C9B4D9385A5A335D5CB82C1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Certain State reviews</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H31C6140313114ED8842C405BB45E92D1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A project under this section shall comply with any applicable State environmental or engineering review requirements pursuant to, as applicable—</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="H1F420362C2A84C40BD60D65D42BBF5A6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>title VI of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1381">33 U.S.C. 1381</external-xref> et seq.);</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="H943865B05A4B41D1BC899DA78D95A269"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>section 1452 of the Safe Drinking Water Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12</external-xref>);</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H5E64C91E3A12479B84D4BD15C0D82701"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>section 35.3140 of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations); and</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="H2963D08C27FF48F4B5EA7728FD13BB5D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>section 35.3580 of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H78CCC89AD1F0477A892D3CD18EC89D17"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No new reviews required</header><text>Nothing in this section requires any additional or new environmental or engineering review for a project under this section other than any requirement otherwise applicable to the project.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA34C47852E0483CBA08108F90D521BF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text>Notwithstanding section 5029(b)(9), financial assistance for a project under this section may be used to pay up to 100 percent of the costs of the project.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD10D8B0F40014A9E9D6F0338D68D538D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Total amount per State</header><text>Financial assistance under this section shall be used to support loans in an amount not to exceed $7,000,000,000 per State for the period of fiscal years 2019 through 2023.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAE550560CEB44C67AC6B49CF3BF2D335"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Expedited review of applications</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which the Administrator receives a complete application for a project under this section, the Administrator shall, through a written notice to the State infrastructure financing authority—</text>
 <paragraph id="HFABD4A1AAA4D41E7BEF104ECD828BE44"><enum>(1)</enum><text>approve the application; or</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HF2816BABE43244C09E5F2B8A8B9BECC3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>deny the application and provide an explanation as to why the application was denied.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF2E79CC2B06D46FBBD58E6CA20712261"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Funding</header>
							<paragraph id="H6E2253D96A3D456EBCF43EB95BE66313"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header>
 <subparagraph id="H13CE42BD84EC40A5B4B7B2EDA10721F6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Administrator to carry out this section $200,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023, to remain available until expended.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFEE633D3F4DA4CF38D7566A9E17B5063"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the amounts authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section will support, for each fiscal year—</text>
 <clause id="H46CFB2A7E4EB4E0EB2CD570DF11703B2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>$10,000,000,000 in secured loans at the interest rate described in subsection (d)(2)(A); and</text> </clause><clause id="H1696B9E830CA4A61A05A68079E236BE4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>$850,000,000 in secured loans at the interest rate described in subsection (d)(2)(B)(i).</text>
									</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H269AE651D4B242A0B1971884CD0F440C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HD0EFAE47583C470C83891A9B816A5D37"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Of the funds made available to carry out this section, the Administrator may use for the administration of this section, including for the provision of technical assistance to aid State infrastructure financing authorities in obtaining the necessary approvals for eligible activities, not more than $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H53658FB8DFC64B01A69681A1BBDDA83F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Fee waivers</header>
 <clause commented="no" id="HCA1BF539F5184EB68FD83D62C0A0B5D8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Of the funds made available to carry out this section, the Administrator may use for costs related to processing and reviewing applications, including underwriting, such amounts as are necessary for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023, to remain available until expended.</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H7A4EADB4DCD64BDDA16C66813078304C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Other fees</header><text>The funds under clause (i) shall be used in lieu of fees collected under section 5030(b).</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H79E3A6BBE7D9419CAAC9AE8ED09101AA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>No impact on other Federal funding</header><text>No funds shall be made available to carry out this section if—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H14B380C54CB64171ADFDD7BB1696A35D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the total amount made available for a fiscal year for the State loan funds is less than the total amount made available for those funds for fiscal year 2018; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1E9BA003F36A490B9E57BFC5D72FCADD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the amount made available for a fiscal year for assistance under this subtitle (other than this section) is less than the amount made available for that assistance for fiscal year 2018.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H1D73BFC4612D411EA2C12D5C73042D9F"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Distribution and allotment of funds</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="H0C552BDDA27140B389F4C93866594D99"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Distribution of funds</header><text>In determining the distribution of funds between the State loan funds, the Administrator shall—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H581BA530CCA946199E18F6F1724DDC21"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide financial assistance based on need; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H70B306EC8314491BA355DE3986640AEE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>give equal consideration to drinking water projects and wastewater projects.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HD17D3F95EF394ACE993937B36338AFE8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>Notwithstanding section 5028(b), in providing financial assistance under this section, the Administrator shall select projects based on need, as determined by the Administrator.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0E0584892FB34CE2824F48AB25384B17"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authority to provide assistance under this section shall terminate on September 30, 2023.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection><subsection id="H1D8FAAC152F746C2AA5CEE39976267CB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>Section 5033 of the Water Infrastructure Finance and Innovation Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/3912">33 U.S.C. 3912</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>(other than section 5036)</quote> after <quote>this subtitle</quote> each place it appears.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HBB4AABA1EF00463FA3EE4E1F0CBC4888"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Removal of pilot designation</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H84BCE62D70C545FA8A43A77F1B77A035"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle C of title V of the Water Resources Reform and Development Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/3901">33 U.S.C. 3901</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by striking the subtitle designation and heading and inserting the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7425066356AF4D66ADD5B570ADAA61E5" style="OLC">
						<subtitle commented="no" id="H8D01268CFE124BD3B9630A2F300C964A" level-type="subsequent"><enum>C</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Innovative financing projects</header></subtitle><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4D681075ADDD4E888D9BC939380B91EF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 5023 of the Water Infrastructure Finance and Innovation Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/3902">33 U.S.C. 3902</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>pilot</quote> each place it appears.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDB1597F778864617BF609790851F708C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 5034 of the Water Infrastructure Finance and Innovation Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/3913">33 U.S.C. 3913</external-xref>) is amended by striking the section designation and heading and inserting the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3432412DF72C408FA5FABDBE7AD9B471" style="OLC">
						<section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H12E993F0CE9A4F9B885587091EC73594" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>5034.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Reports on program implementation</header></section><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBF950B6A72344FB283DDDC1F8075F0E8"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents for the Water Resources Reform and Development Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/113/121">Public Law 113–121</external-xref>; 128 Stat. 1195) is amended—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H538FD1487A214B2782B1B1FB1487949A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking the item relating to subtitle C of title V and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H061921D4ED44475EA339FD941EF7CC35" style="OLC"> <toc> <toc-entry bold="off" level="subtitle">Subtitle C—Innovative Financing Projects</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4B0DCC143CBB49B1B31BECFB8F013DD6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking the item relating to section 5034 and inserting the following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE3C5A73B463141CBA349EF634D5CAD07" style="OLC">
							<toc>
								<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 5034. Reports on program implementation.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 <continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">and</continuation-text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBB46BA8CB2604E47A7E01C3A70F54A01"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 5035 the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2634031026EF43F1BC04C2FEC26CA157" style="OLC"> <toc> <toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 5036. Innovative financing for State loan funds.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

