<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H7CCDF04BCD1B4278981835E7F3E7693E" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5641 IH: State Offices of Rural Health Reauthorization Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5641</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180426">April 26, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001190">Mr. Mullin</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001180">Mr. Schrader</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to provide grants to improve health care in rural areas.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H2A20F956110C4215964F31E731780558" style="OLC">
 <section id="H5F1A93D2C1854010B6D98945D6C04C79" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>State Offices of Rural Health Reauthorization Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H0AE1266AD297463680CCE05C9DBB6C4B"><enum>2.</enum><header>State offices of rural health</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 338J of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254r">42 U.S.C. 254r</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE60B2E48EC0C4D549B926459E27749F8" style="OLC">
				<section id="H3E5A59B9BE1444B8B9A0337C8569E94E"><enum>338J.</enum><header>Grants to State offices of rural health</header>
 <subsection id="H734C67FAB70549768B98DE1C6E56C240"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Federal Office of Rural Health Policy (established under section 711 of the Social Security Act), shall make grants to each State Office of Rural Health for the purpose of improving health care in rural areas.</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="H9C95E410691145D1AB03247C9B82B17C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirement of matching funds</header>
 <paragraph id="HEDDF065A7454493B931699744931A357"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), the Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless the State office of rural health involved agrees, with respect to the costs to be incurred in carrying out the purpose described in such subsection, to provide non-Federal contributions toward such costs in an amount equal to $3 for each $1 of Federal funds provided in the grant.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H71F78EE5726A4A9988568A5C17A93114"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver or reduction</header><text>The Secretary may waive or reduce the non-Federal contribution if the Secretary determines that requiring matching funds would limit the State office of rural health’s ability to carry out the purpose described in subsection (a).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDE86E7FD529B4EE8BBF4341A737DB222"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Determination of amount of non-Federal contribution</header><text>Non-Federal contributions required in paragraph (1) may be in cash or in-kind, fairly evaluated, including plant, equipment, or services. Amounts provided by the Federal Government, or services assisted or subsidized to any significant extent by the Federal Government, may not be included in determining the amount of such non-Federal contributions.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB3C4535FF17F4CC39FE18B85FD251A91"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Certain required activities</header><text>Recipients of a grant under subsection (a) shall use the grant funds for purposes of—</text> <paragraph id="H5BC259D4C4AD4F5E893D66CE7052ABB2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>maintaining within the State office of rural health a clearinghouse for collecting and disseminating information on—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE2A49B93A54F465F8DA3B4CD288E6D87"><enum>(A)</enum><text>rural health care issues;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC98BC6AD49184390A924983E8FD485FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>research findings relating to rural health care; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2AC309C0CD22438395E6D9D6AF115628"><enum>(C)</enum><text>innovative approaches to the delivery of health care in rural areas;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC56141AF7F3E4FD882EAB7BFDC2CD17F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinating the activities carried out in the State that relate to rural health care, including providing coordination for the purpose of avoiding redundancy in such activities; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDB1B8D5FB8D54E86B661EAC76B5F46F0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identifying Federal and State programs regarding rural health, and providing technical assistance to public and nonprofit private entities regarding participation in such programs.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H70B309E9254048E2893C9FC5AE7302DE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirement regarding annual budget for office</header><text>The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless the State involved agrees that, for any fiscal year for which the State office of rural health receives such a grant, the office operated pursuant to subsection (a) of this section will be provided with an annual budget of not less than $150,000.</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="HCCCA0A1BBB2447259AC1D6F28BB0CCA2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Certain uses of funds</header>
 <paragraph id="HE2F2A85EB6C44B09BBAB0506225FB72F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Restrictions</header><text>The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless the State office of rural health involved agrees that the grant will not be expended—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H5DA874BCE4C644A7AEDB613335E76312"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to provide health care (including providing cash payments regarding such care);</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB96AC8DA65C54D0597206DE46767D9C4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to conduct activities for which Federal funds are expended—</text>
 <clause id="H505B777CD471461AB307E6C9AE860057"><enum>(i)</enum><text>within the State to provide technical and other nonfinancial assistance under section 330A(f);</text> </clause><clause id="H7CC0E9C82ED7444B9B01EA54142D48F5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>under a memorandum of agreement entered into with the State office of rural health under section 330A(h); or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H0C6A197A5FBB4FDA997E3BD0111DEEFB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>under a grant under section 338I;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H39E801CFF1BB4D57871EDDF4A921AFAC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to purchase medical equipment, to purchase ambulances, aircraft, or other vehicles, or to purchase major communications equipment;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82BEE2F4AEA642CDA1F7099BCFFB4187"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to purchase or improve real property; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA940C0C2E1AA4FC9B0DD3FDEED98CFC8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to carry out any activity regarding a certificate of need.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H75F149F607EE43A18C19B1654476D35F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorities</header><text>Activities for which a State office of rural health may expend a grant under subsection (a) include—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H83AE932A4CD0445C8EAE6E28E699243D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>paying the costs of maintaining an office of rural health for purposes of subsection (a);</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2DDB47C37FC943FBA7DB1186A451EFF1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subject to paragraph (1)(B)(iii), paying the costs of any activity carried out with respect to recruiting and retaining health professionals to serve in rural areas of the State; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB05D934543EB43E79F5C531F951E4941"><enum>(C)</enum><text>providing grants and contracts to public and nonprofit private entities to carry out activities authorized in this section.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6163F7FC3BE643CF93CFB018C18AA04F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limit on indirect costs</header><text>The Secretary may impose a limit of no more than 15 percent on indirect costs claimed by the recipient of the grant.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF1D1DB5CF9E84E5D994D19C6556571F3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless the State office of rural health involved agrees—</text>
 <paragraph id="HEBDEC2216B4E4B7B810A51D6113CB1CF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to submit to the Secretary reports or performance data containing such information as the Secretary may require regarding activities carried out under this section; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD424A8C69ECE42968BF078733DD2024A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to submit such a report or performance data not later than September 30 of each fiscal year immediately following any fiscal year for which the State office of rural health has received such a grant.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1EFBC66DC94644D8B2888B96D40A0422"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Requirement of application</header><text>The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless an application for the grant is submitted to the Secretary and the application is in such form, is made in such manner, and contains such agreements, assurances, and information as the Secretary determines to be necessary to carry out such subsection.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H14937A994F5842BD82C25E9E59204321"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Noncompliance</header><text>The Secretary may not make payments under subsection (a) to a State office of rural health for any fiscal year subsequent to the first fiscal year of such payments unless the Secretary determines that, for the immediately preceding fiscal year, the State office of rural health has complied with each of the agreements made by the State office of rural health under this section.</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="H7766311012034472AAC81338297A9BEF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header>
 <paragraph id="H202BC56AC2DB4A35A18737C1933A3193"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the purpose of making grants under subsection (a), there are authorized to be appropriated $12,500,000 for each of fiscal years 2018 through 2022.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB85F969901E04991B8F449A728A3CBDE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>Amounts appropriated under paragraph (1) shall remain available until expended.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section></legis-body></bill> 

