<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1BDF3CF16B0D452EA11EDCFC3E50F54A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5598 IH: 340B Optimization Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5598</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180424">April 24, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001092">Mr. Collins of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to require certain disproportionate share hospital covered entities under the 340B drug discount program to submit to the Secretary of Health and Human Services reports on low-income utilization rates of outpatient hospital services furnished by such entities.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H7A0AF9D8B7B746F58AB806AA97B2517B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H574F1BDB9B2B4767BEC333E6E0D31D64" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>340B Optimization Act</short-title></quote>. </text> </section> <section id="H0DFE2CA637924F079F39F977CCF476EF" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requiring 340B drug discount program reports by DSH hospital covered entities on low-income utilization rate of outpatient hospital services</header> <subsection id="H6F17667B109E4B578BB357E45EE27B74"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 340B(d)(2) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/256b">42 U.S.C. 256b(d)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7B44E3872BAC4147B5B41588B9D98896"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)(i), by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>, including, with respect to such updates made on or after January 1, 2020, by requiring covered entities described in subsection (a)(4)(L) to submit (and to so regularly update) information described in subparagraph (C)</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9405FDC08E444C42B8D40BEB6150EC2E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFAF26BA5CAD9478794CDDD33A66C2B7A" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="H8260DFE9682440D2B23A5A04F439797C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Information on low-income utilization rate of outpatient hospital services</header> 
<clause id="H56623DFAB17D4C4AB9F9C98BED11B04B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (B)(i), the information described in this subparagraph, with respect to a covered entity described in subsection (a)(4)(L) and an update under such subparagraph (B)(i), is—</text> <subclause id="H813C69EB76F643E0A6E578F15D3708EF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the low-income outpatient utilization rate of such covered entity for the most recent fiscal year; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H7FD4112AD66D492688AC5D4680F1A949"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the low-income outpatient utilization rate of off-site outpatient facilities, clinics, eligible off-site locations, and associated sites of such entity identified as child sites of such entity pursuant to the identification system under subparagraph (B)(iv) for the most recent fiscal year.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H1F1AEEF1360B4FD4AB1B67F0A51E0A56"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Low-income outpatient utilization rate defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subparagraph, the term <term>low-income outpatient utilization rate</term> has the meaning given the term <term>low-income utilization rate</term> under paragraph (3) of section 1923(b) of the Social Security Act, except that—</text> 
<subclause id="H716B11DF55E047579B291C16894A0425"><enum>(I)</enum><text>clauses (i) and (ii) of subparagraph (A) of such paragraph shall be applied as if—</text> <item id="H0CDC753C29EB458A9EA4F7596710A2D3"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>each reference to <quote>patient services</quote> were a reference to <quote>patient services furnished on an outpatient basis</quote>; and</text></item> 
<item id="H54003648E727470EABAA505B69171610"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for purposes of clause (i)(II) of this subparagraph, each reference to <quote>hospital</quote> were a reference to <quote>off-site outpatient facilities, clinics, eligible off-site locations, and associated sites of the hospital that are identified as child sites of the hospital pursuant to the identification system under section 340B(d)(2)(B)(iv) of the Public Health Service Act</quote>; and</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="HEC43A609D845406A89955EFEB6B02981"><enum>(II)</enum><text>clauses (i) and (ii) of subparagraph (B) of such paragraph shall be applied as if—</text> 
<item id="H25ED6C26E50A439FA005976267E473F5"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>each reference to <quote>inpatient hospital services</quote> were a reference to <quote>outpatient hospital services</quote>; and</text></item> <item id="H6FB6FE968739452B8C5137CD25350F40"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>for purposes of clause (i)(II) each reference to <quote>hospital’s charges</quote> were a reference to <quote>charges of the off-site outpatient facilities, clinics, eligible off-site locations, and associated sites of the hospital that are identified as child sites of the hospital pursuant to the identification system under section 340B(d)(2)(B)(iv) of the Public Health Service Act</quote>.</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFC86F0C2B3634520B62864B670B950A2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 1, 2021, and annually thereafter, the Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration shall submit to Congress a report on information submitted by covered entities for the previous year pursuant to the amendments made by subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

