<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB49B9422F2964E90988653112254D1B5" key="H" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5467 IH: Purple Heart and Disabled Veterans Equal Access Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5467</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20180411">April 11, 2018</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000563">Mr. Lipinski</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="J000255">Mr. Jones</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001245">Ms. Bordallo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001037">Mr. Capuano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000598">Mrs. Davis of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000191">Mr. DeFazio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000625">Mr. Donovan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000449">Mr. Fortenberry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000378">Mr. Kinzinger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster of New Hampshire</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001185">Mr. Sean Patrick Maloney of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000015">Mr. Neal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000171">Mr. O'Halleran</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000258">Mr. Peterson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000611">Mr. Poliquin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000600">Mrs. Radewagen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000608">Ms. Rosen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000515">Mr. Rush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000577">Mr. Ryan of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001170">Ms. Shea-Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001191">Ms. Sinema</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001201">Mr. Suozzi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000132">Mr. Vela</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 10, United States Code, to extend certain morale, welfare, and recreation privileges to certain veterans and their caregivers, to authorize the appropriation of funds for the purpose of improving the electronic physical access control system used by military commissaries and exchanges, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HAC4156FB902943B59575F858EC1173D1" style="OLC"> 
<section commented="no" id="H6DFABE26DEB84A369787CA4294A97972" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Purple Heart and Disabled Veterans Equal Access Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> <section id="H63B513A9AA70497B9F27DEE2EC33EB97"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H32E10B442DD547398A968D7E9F1BC3B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2017, the Secretary of Defense determined that the addition of new patron categories to the commissary and exchange systems would support the growth of a robust customer base and help ensure the ability of both systems to provide benefits to members of the Armed Forces and their families.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H320C94EEB92C43A69CCC3C493340F042"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary previously opposed extending commissary and exchange privileges to large patron groups such as disabled veterans.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA2B1AF638B0240A9A76EF58156C4B8BD"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In January 2017, the Secretary of Defense approved limited online exchange shopping privileges for all veterans, effective November 11, 2017.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="HC2511E46E12943548A3019140CB7AAB0"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary determined that current patrons of exchanges did not perceive the extension of such privileges as diluting the benefit for members of the Armed Forces.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC7FF891BC0574016AE842131DC12FB9C"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Purple Heart is the oldest military decoration, awarded to members of the Armed Forces who have been wounded or died in combat, fighting for the United States. Since the modern incarnation of the award was established in 1932, approximately 1,800,000 members of the Armed Forces have been awarded the Purple Heart.</text> </paragraph></section> <section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF121FECC3194495FB339851DDEB955B8" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Commissary stores and MWR facilities privileges for certain veterans and veteran caregivers</header> <subsection id="HD3CB54C399E640BCA7C352E4DDDCFB8F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Extension of privileges</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/54">Chapter 54</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H2E7A7B1CDB034EF7B49DBB48C0A64F9C" style="USC"> 
<section id="HE77114EB5AC849FC96665FEA5B9EB022"><enum>1065.</enum><header>Use of commissary stores and MWR facilities: certain veterans and caregivers for veterans</header> 
<subsection id="HF67BE15237C147E1883428B65C7BE6BB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Eligibility of veterans awarded the Purple Heart</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A veteran who was awarded the Purple Heart shall be permitted to use commissary stores and MWR facilities on the same basis as a member of the armed forces entitled to retired or retainer pay.</text> </subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="HF88A5ECB992B4445B6CBB904BFFFDC2D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility of veterans who are Medal of Honor recipients</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A veteran who is a Medal of Honor recipient shall be permitted to use commissary stores and MWR facilities on the same basis as a member of the armed forces entitled to retired or retainer pay.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H4A4A02490F6746F09AF66D6F547F1DF6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligibility of veterans who are former prisoners of war</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A veteran who is a former prisoner of war shall be permitted to use commissary stores and MWR facilities on the same basis as a member of the armed forces entitled to retired or retainer pay.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="H9E9CD5A0F3EA4D34B08E6087BF74A230"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligibility of veterans with service-Connected disabilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A veteran with a service-connected disability shall be permitted to use commissary stores and MWR facilities on the same basis as a member of the armed forces entitled to retired or retainer pay.</text> </subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HABF95AEE8B6A432EBBD856235AE03A09"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Eligibility of caregivers for veterans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A caregiver or family caregiver shall be permitted to use commissary stores and MWR facilities on the same basis as a member of the armed forces entitled to retired or retainer pay.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="HA3F4A6DC343C4AC58F00B8551ECA3068"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H097B7062303C4B0E97E78073491FA1A8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>MWR facilities</term> includes—</text> <subparagraph id="HE7C8A9FA11184D758D633F32CD996BD0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>MWR retail facilities, as that term is defined in section 1063(e) of this title; and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H74AD5CD9A03C4770B06653B94AE91156"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">military lodging operated by the Department of Defense for the morale, welfare, and recreation of members of the armed forces.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCBFCA1CE995C48228E08DAE19BC08AD7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>Medal of Honor recipient</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 1074h(c) of this title.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H31C218BDCCBE41929BED135CCF2017D7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>veteran</term>, <quote>former prisoner of war</quote>, and <quote>service-connected</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 101 of title 38.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H0FBB635888AB4721A4654F2E858F247F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The terms <quote>caregiver</quote> and <quote>family caregiver</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section in section 1720G(d) of title 38.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection>
<subsection id="H695B66F1AA1B403ABF4B3921ACC5E1A3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections at the beginning of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/54">chapter 54</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text> <quoted-block id="H0B49DFE802814E17912032002159F718" style="USC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">1065. Use of commissary stores and MWR facilities: certain veterans and caregivers for veterans.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> <subsection id="H1C65737013D348DF9300DE6C7D22332A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>Section 1065 of title 10, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), shall take effect at the end of the 90-day period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act.</text> </subsection></section>
<section id="HEAA20D39A9BE40BC860D590D95F05337"><enum>4.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriation for updating ePACS for military commissaries</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is hereby authorized to be appropriated, out of any funds in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, $500,000 to the Secretary of Defense for the purpose of updating the electronic physical access control system used by military commissaries and exchanges so that the system may recognize and accept veteran health identification cards.</text> </section> <section commented="no" id="HBF5DA4DEF974455FA0978B42B745B563"><enum>5.</enum><header>Sense of Congress regarding individuals awarded the Purple Heart</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the Secretary of Defense, in coordination with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, should maintain a list of all individuals awarded the Purple Heart.</text> </section>
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


