<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H8F612C6CD6924BB684B8FFA3C03ABCEC" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5815 IH: Customer Online Notification for Stopping Edge-provider Network Transgressions</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5815</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180515">May 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001037">Mr. Capuano</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Federal Trade Commission to establish privacy protections for customers of online
			 edge providers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H19D035E9513841F6A726EF8641B33982" style="OLC">
 <section id="HA9DD69A2A61A47D1AD93FF2E40FFDD01" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Customer Online Notification for Stopping Edge-provider Network Transgressions</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CONSENT Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HE446077ED0884E86925868E4DEC560CB" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Privacy of customers of edge providers</header> <subsection id="H93BA9CC910694BDEA1096EF4E9CD41F3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text>
 <paragraph id="H23B860EEC39D4B50BE6AEC156F23B992"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>breach of security</term> means any instance in which a person, without authorization or in violation of any authorization provided to the person, gains access to, uses, or discloses sensitive customer proprietary information;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H280BBE8B734A4D758C670F0C27E6EAA0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Trade Commission;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HA85AAE72D2934B28874FA88121F92709"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>customer</term> means—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H508A2AC8B0D94992BC13C6183BC7EF3D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an individual who is a customer of an edge provider; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFE66D07DF4649C083A12DBF6554CC32"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an individual who is a user of an edge service provided by an edge provider;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H03F236AADA114BC78FD34D261B50FD38"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>edge provider</term> means a person that provides an edge service, but only to the extent to which the person provides that service;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCB5DB41240604C9D8231977A099208A4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>edge service</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="HAE15FF666EF5474693C6E7E8B520950A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a service that is provided over the Internet—</text>
 <clause id="HFBF854C4768644FAB39EDB990604ACA4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for which the edge provider requires the customer to subscribe or establish an account in order to use the service;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HCAFCE659F4424A86BC0CDE7257CC5CA1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that the customer purchases from the edge provider without a subscription or account;</text> </clause><clause id="H9EE1B3CCA401411A801285EB8FD5A48B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>through which a program searches for and identifies items in a database that correspond to keywords or characters specified by the customer; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF5DA811527954988AB71B93C9D552276"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>through which a customer divulges sensitive customer proprietary information of the customer; and</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA34649BC784E4775B67ABDC67B66E6BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes any service that is provided—</text>
 <clause id="HC442052823F94AD78AEE0EF6124E3489"><enum>(i)</enum><text>through a software program, including a mobile application; or</text> </clause><clause id="HD2B34726DEDF4F6D922EBE2720A48923"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>over the Internet, directly or indirectly, through a connected device;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1294A3B94F4740F88D856B133F18B9FC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the term <term>opt-in consent</term> means a method by which an edge provider may obtain from a customer affirmative, express consent to use, disclose, or permit access to the sensitive customer proprietary information of the customer after the customer has received explicit notification of the request of the edge provider with respect to that information;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6F244A0C3B5F4A74A227C333343181C8"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the term <term>personally identifiable information</term> means any information that is linked, or reasonably may be linked, to a specific individual or device; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD2901671EC684F05A42AE2486466FCD7"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the term <term>sensitive customer proprietary information</term> includes—</text> <subparagraph id="H694B849EDF79491DA2A7A336CD857298"><enum>(A)</enum><text>financial information;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE6F6BE6F7F644D4AB1473C0D51D4C73"><enum>(B)</enum><text>health information;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53E7D012D8A3421B8B9FE094F0BC6E47"><enum>(C)</enum><text>information pertaining to children;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB03C25DD2B364E7EABD275FDE7A701DA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Social Security numbers;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB70BC755BBC4F8A8CE4A49D1AE0EE9C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>precise geolocation information;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90A76D8F2FC04F1D9C6B0F6F344E54C5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>content of communications;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B092FFB4C2B4047BA905EEBF649A75F"><enum>(G)</enum><text>call detail information;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5475BFBEE6B430891BE614EF8052C5B"><enum>(H)</enum><text>web browsing history, application usage history, and the functional equivalents of either; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE2BFE0B99FF84D87AE61D9696125A5F7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any other personally identifiable information that the Commission determines to be sensitive.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5FC6404DE85843F087FC4368185F7E35"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Privacy of customers of edge providers</header>
 <paragraph id="H4F384992B0A24F96A53AE80AB00402FE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Act prohibited</header><text>It is unlawful for an edge provider to violate the privacy of a customer in a manner that violates a regulation prescribed under paragraph (2).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HA1D444FE73E34C2380170AB71C975554"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regulations</header>
 <subparagraph id="H38A8D6351871467196D35D8E86810D98"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out this Act, the Commission shall—</text> <clause id="H26FF9EE31397408E92BFDC0B55999898"><enum>(i)</enum><text>not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, promulgate, under section 553 of title 5, United States Code, regulations to protect the privacy of customers of edge providers; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF7E0F139753E422AB393E44938A82359"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure that the regulations promulgated under clause (i) take effect not later than 180 days after the date on which the regulations are promulgated.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10B116C9E10047E5B27BCFFFB8073DB8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements under regulations</header><text>In promulgating regulations under subparagraph (A), the Commission shall—</text> <clause id="H21F8183B67104AEAA768E5F068AE72BD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>require an edge provider to notify a customer about the collection, use, and sharing of the sensitive customer proprietary information of the customer, including by—</text>
 <subclause id="H99857DE66C8046D2A75DA1FA665B6284"><enum>(I)</enum><text>notifying the customer about the types of sensitive customer proprietary information the edge provider collects;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H3E6F6B61EBE04277ADD3D7BE4CD379BF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>specifying how and for what purposes the edge provider uses and shares sensitive customer proprietary information; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HC2A1C5A784634945B86F03CE18B81297"><enum>(III)</enum><text>identifying the types of entities with which the edge provider shares sensitive customer proprietary information;</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H731EBF2EF682479FB4DD52F25F10ED93"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>require an edge provider to—</text> <subclause id="HA0BA9E42F062486AA306E49295903E1B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>supply the information described in clause (i) when a customer initially subscribes to, establishes an account for, purchases, or begins receiving an edge service; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H328E9B2D75364D649B391E9152CBDBDC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>update a customer when the policies of the edge provider relating to the information described in clause (i) change in a significant way;</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="HE84FC13B5A9544DD96D9CBE2DCD5B87C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>require an edge provider to obtain opt-in consent from a customer to use, share, or sell the sensitive customer proprietary information of the customer;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H51A1EEF05D414023A3227162FA63DE47"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>implement strong protection for sensitive customer proprietary information that has been de-identified to prevent the restoration of any personally identifiable information that has been previously removed, including by—</text>
 <subclause id="H9104F7AF3C114077BAB8081AA9DD9F7D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>requiring an edge provider to alter the customer information so that the customer information cannot be reasonably linked to a specific individual or device;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H4A07C204D2994D0FBAA07730B2B03220"><enum>(II)</enum><text>requiring an edge provider to publically commit to maintain and use sensitive customer proprietary information in an unidentifiable format and to not attempt to restore any personally identifiable information that has been previously removed from the sensitive customer proprietary information; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H9B064AFF8CCC49B09F1B3F574A9C0EF1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>requiring an edge provider to contractually prohibit the practice of restoring any personally identifiable information that has been previously removed from sensitive customer proprietary information;</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H0636B3EC353948F096F1B02479C14084"><enum>(v)</enum><text>determine on a case-by-case basis the reasonableness of any program that relates the price of an edge service to the privacy protections afforded to customers, and require an edge provider to fully disclose plans that provide discounts or other incentives in exchange for a express affirmative consent of the customer to the use and sharing of the sensitive customer proprietary information of the customer;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HE2E92EC45E5F4B6E877C9C5E5CFA6ACF"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>prohibit an edge provider from refusing to serve a customer who does not consent to the use and sharing of the customer proprietary information of the customer for commercial purposes (commonly known as a <quote>take-it-or-leave-it offer</quote>) on the basis of that refusal to consent by the customer; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H6881FECEF3C04BA2A40DD130E2B396CB"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>require an edge provider to—</text> <subclause id="H4E4A42F17C7B4C5B8F6AF4F7EDD4590A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>develop reasonable data security practices; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H54778F1D71CA47568521841EBD44480F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>notify a customer if a breach of security has occurred if the edge provider determines that an unauthorized disclosure of the sensitive customer proprietary information of the customer has occurred and harm is reasonably likely to occur.</text>
							</subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1B58067A97FA4EFB9795C74221144FED"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement by the Commission</header>
 <paragraph id="H59A94EDDE28345B78369253A58F2DEEB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as otherwise provided, this Act and the regulations prescribed under this Act shall be enforced by the Commission under the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2AA7B9668F054A669D73AF7CEEE661A8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices</header><text>Subject to subsection (d), a violation of this Act or a regulation prescribed under this Act shall be treated as a violation of a rule defining an unfair or deceptive act or practice prescribed under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H525F33FEF584429B9000F6DB98C0D8AC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Actions by the Commission</header><text>Subject to subsection (d), and except as provided in subsection (f)(1), the Commission shall prevent any person from violating this Act or a regulation prescribed under this Act in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41</external-xref> et seq.) were incorporated into and made a part of this Act, and any person who violates this Act or such regulation shall be subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB9F8477CA86C4EDAAE756A55CB3A9B05"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Enforcement by certain other agencies</header><text>Compliance with the requirements imposed under this Act shall be enforced as follows:</text> <paragraph id="HD5FC5685B2A646C087EF042B6DA6B78C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Under section 8 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1818">12 U.S.C. 1818</external-xref>) by the appropriate Federal banking agency, with respect to an insured depository institution (as those terms are defined in section 3 of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813</external-xref>)).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7835DE0BBAF24644829B0B66EC836A03"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Under the Federal Credit Union Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1751">12 U.S.C. 1751</external-xref> et seq.) by the National Credit Union Administration Board, with respect to any Federal credit union.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H48C1ED49E46143AA8FEDC4D4FC5574ED"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Under part A of subtitle VII of title 49, United States Code, by the Secretary of Transportation, with respect to any air carrier or foreign air carrier subject to that part.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H781342DA4B4C4C26A293C2385B0C863E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Under the Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/181">7 U.S.C. 181</external-xref> et seq.) (except as provided in section 406 of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/226">7 U.S.C. 226</external-xref>; 227)) by the Secretary of Agriculture, with respect to any activities subject to that Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H60ABBC94B981492EB3584FE449CB708F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Under the Farm Credit Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/2001">12 U.S.C. 2001</external-xref> et seq.) by the Farm Credit Administration, with respect to any Federal land bank, Federal land bank association, Federal intermediate credit bank, or production credit association.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFE1653C02E0A4C379780EAD0689E7709"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Enforcement by State attorneys general</header>
				<paragraph id="HF04D381EB87E4D4AB425C0A7B764AAAC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header>
 <subparagraph id="H55A1DC2CDF9D43F0969E6DF0A7DB8665"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Civil actions</header><text>In any case in which the attorney general of a State has reason to believe that an interest of the residents of that State has been or is threatened or adversely affected by the engagement of any person in a practice that violates this Act or a regulation prescribed under this Act, the State, as parens patriae, may bring a civil action on behalf of the residents of the State in a district court of the United States of appropriate jurisdiction to—</text>
 <clause id="H1A5E1633A6BD4B959557C861A1C013D8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>enjoin that practice;</text> </clause><clause id="H3C4C8873E73A44E59A7A3380E4CE5D95"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>enforce compliance with this Act or such regulation;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H4835D88DFCB1409ABC51C49A4C053B76"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>obtain damages, restitution, or other compensation on behalf of residents of the State; or</text> </clause><clause id="H478134A9FBE6462E9F9B32570DFC134E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>obtain such other relief as the court may consider to be appropriate.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8836E10AF9D14C66812F50F3112574A4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notice</header>
 <clause id="H72726B5F32234622AA39E5E523D24B40"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Before filing an action under subparagraph (A), the attorney general of the State involved shall provide to the Commission—</text>
 <subclause id="H01790D6F23514021825A49CB12D5762E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>written notice of that action; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H160C29704597485483674709C41BFF40"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a copy of the complaint for that action.</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause id="H0D278C5EE5F84F009FF3774CFDEE5CB8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exemption</header>
 <subclause id="H7A893F177A004B6F83E8DB99DA8DA605"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Clause (i) shall not apply with respect to the filing of an action by an attorney general of a State under this paragraph if the attorney general determines that it is not feasible to provide the notice described in that clause before the filing of the action.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HB393611B4D4244D08D0869865CCF7DD3"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>In an action described in subclause (I), the attorney general of a State shall provide notice and a copy of the complaint to the Commission at the same time as the attorney general files the action.</text>
							</subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCED5095F953243CD9F2AC93C97D9DD19"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Intervention</header>
 <subparagraph id="H600B3AEA0AF543B696E4C2D782A206FB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On receiving notice under paragraph (1)(B), the Commission shall have the right to intervene in the action that is the subject of the notice.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2A8E68AD63F4A1E9CA16A6EDD1FC063"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Effect of intervention</header><text>If the Commission intervenes in an action under paragraph (1), it shall have the right—</text> <clause id="HDE28249764474F2A9CC3FBB813CA2AE4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to be heard with respect to any matter that arises in that action; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H3843170F43AB49FEADCD418A7BEB62C4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to file a petition for appeal.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3F52AADCA5D49B6831D831F33AC8917"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>For purposes of bringing any civil action under paragraph (1), nothing in this Act shall be construed to prevent an attorney general of a State from exercising the powers conferred on the attorney general by the laws of that State to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HC71854D04F354C92833BCF446D254519"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conduct investigations;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC5D699FAC4B46D0AE27A8B41C50139E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>administer oaths or affirmations; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H451DF49C90B4476888B79849782E4278"><enum>(C)</enum><text>compel the attendance of witnesses or the production of documentary and other evidence.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E6169F9EBBB41898E6F6F5D668FDAF1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Actions by the Commission</header><text>In any case in which an action is instituted by or on behalf of the Commission for violation of this Act or a regulation prescribed under this Act, no State may, during the pendency of that action, institute an action under paragraph (1) against any defendant named in the complaint in the action instituted by or on behalf of the Commission for that violation.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H017722C61506487780419FC06211774F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Venue; service of process</header>
 <subparagraph id="H4B2D9E381251458991AB5164D04896BD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Venue</header><text>Any action brought under paragraph (1) may be brought in the district court of the United States that meets applicable requirements relating to venue under section 1391 of title 28, United States Code.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H950A3660EAAA47D78C48F2C1BE6083D6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Service of process</header><text>In an action brought under paragraph (1), process may be served in any district in which the defendant—</text>
 <clause id="H6B29963318BA423B9F524FC27F58CF7A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is an inhabitant; or</text> </clause><clause id="H62DCACF5A2B348AFAA532B80CADD2B34"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may be found.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H281ED048DF244CE2B463D0823ED6EF1E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Telecommunications carriers</header>
 <paragraph id="HC0CDC274375A475BA0B23ADB0D834938"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>telecommunications carrier</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/153">47 U.S.C. 153</external-xref>).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H940D352DFD264DFC899418F5FD3A5831"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Enforcement by the commission</header><text>Notwithstanding section 5(a)(2) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45(a)(2)</external-xref>), compliance with the requirements imposed under this Act shall be enforced by the Commission with respect to any telecommunications carrier, but only to the extent that the telecommunications carrier is operating as an edge provider.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8306000CFE3D4E539629F5F93467DE94"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Relationship to other law</header><text>To the extent that the applicability of section 222, 338(i), or 631 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/222">47 U.S.C. 222</external-xref>, 338(i), 551) to a telecommunications carrier is inconsistent with this Act, this Act shall supersede those sections only to the extent that the telecommunications carrier is operating as an edge provider.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


