<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H452ACCC0D1C2454A85F797E84BC01A04" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5527 IH: Daniel Webster Congressional Clerkship Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5527</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180417">April 17, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001187">Mr. Stivers</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish the Daniel Webster Congressional Clerkship Program.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H1CBC7BA998894432850A031A7C905918" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H835B74F7CC72475E8ECAFFA5CD745C92" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Daniel Webster Congressional Clerkship Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA6EAD31F6D9240B4B53BE5415515079A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H18D92A3328924B4E88B1BD94FCDD0925"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Each year, many of the most talented law school graduates in the United States begin their legal careers as judicial law clerks.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HED448268C3A24913B6641B6B2ABEE971"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The judicial clerkship program has given the judiciary access to a pool of exceptional young lawyers at a relatively low cost.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE709A7827949432EBD280C861DA1A5BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>These same lawyers then go on to become leaders of their profession, where they serve a critical role in helping to educate the public about the judiciary and the judicial process.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H60E00F7F9B1E46388137ADCEBDF1C624"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The White House, the administrative agencies of the executive branch, the Administrative Office of the United States Courts, the Federal Judicial Center, and the United States Sentencing Commission all operate analogous programs for talented young professionals at the outset of their careers.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0A5CE95FE5A745B983FBB9C03E2E5042"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Congress is without a similar program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFF788E8ED0794563B7D4ED4C8DF91529"><enum>(6)</enum><text>At a time when our Nation faces considerable challenges, Congress and the public would benefit immeasurably from a program, modeled after the judicial clerkship program, that engages the brightest young lawyers in the Nation in the legislative process.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA0ECD9B288254BA980B5E03E1501B348"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Accordingly, the Congress herein creates the Daniel Webster Congressional Clerkship Program, named after one of the most admired and distinguished lawyer-legislators ever to serve in Congress, to improve the business of Congress and increase the understanding of its work by the public.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H73128D89DF1E4EF8BF9741E69A60559C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Daniel Webster Congressional Clerkship Program</header> <subsection id="H02BE6FC4C19C4D8BB51919D3DAEC6564"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Selection committees</header><text>In this Act, the term <term>Selection Committees</term> means—</text> 
<paragraph id="H8761FCEBA6FD43DBB69906AE4F9AF579"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Rules and Administration of the Senate; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H797E52399E4244EF86236BDE5C6FD985"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H747B91E0D37A4264A38F9264B420487E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of Program</header><text>There is established the Daniel Webster Congressional Clerkship Program for the appointment of individuals who are graduates of accredited law schools to serve as Congressional Clerks in the Senate or House of Representatives.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H7C8F281B1DD749648A51DBA187ACE650"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Selection of Clerks</header><text>The Selection Committees shall select Congressional Clerks in the following manner:</text> 
<paragraph id="HAE2305BAD4234E969AD6024B4F5512EB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Committee on Rules and Administration of the Senate shall select not less than 6 Congressional Clerks each year for a clerkship with an office of the Senate for a 1-year period.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6A67711C4DE94F7DA0C8708F6DA74A1D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives shall select not less than 6 Congressional Clerks each year for a clerkship with an office of the House of Representatives for a 1-year period.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H12E59865E9C749D7BED87B7759F5ECA3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Selection criteria</header><text>In carrying out subsection (c), the Selection Committees shall select Congressional Clerks consistent with the following criteria:</text> <paragraph id="H974A0CB040A64402803379631FE66B8E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Each Congressional Clerk selected shall be a graduate of an accredited law school as of the starting date of his or her clerkship.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H87D882AF1AA147A2BC65398E242B5FA8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each Congressional Clerk selected shall possess—</text> <subparagraph id="H0AE59A564106438ABDC99652B0E6EE54"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an excellent academic record;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H27AD781185E142F1B27BF404C77159F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a strong record of achievement in extracurricular activities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H571C6908E5D5410C82DF2F9F924A5BF5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a demonstrated commitment to public service; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBFC02FD37F9D45FBACCA193491880815"><enum>(D)</enum><text>outstanding analytic, writing, and oral communication skills.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCA3B86F4B4D343E888E848AF271AB904"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Process</header><text>After a Congressional Clerk is selected under this section, such Congressional Clerk may then interview for a clerkship in an office, and accept the clerkship if offered, as follows:</text> 
<paragraph id="HBEA64DE577CB4FACA85A4032B788DE9A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>For a Congressional Clerk selected under subsection (c)(1), the Congressional Clerk may interview for, and accept if offered, a clerkship with—</text> <subparagraph id="H4C42FFADC2CE44F092B67F2FFC39696A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an office of any committee of the Senate, including a select or special committee;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC49C6179CC964B32BE3BB05C7823B31B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an office of a joint committee of Congress the pay of the employees of which is disbursed by the Secretary of the Senate;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H83579343A5CF48629C448586E6105C56"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an office of any individual member of the Senate;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H75080E78467D47B4B3D04C6563351B1B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a leadership office of the Senate; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H31AE4B9C3FB24409A3FEA8D9DA671810"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Office of the Parliamentarian of the Senate, the Office of Senate Legal Counsel, or the Office of the Legislative Counsel of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H68CAEEABAC4A4C3EA79A7F45C89DFC77"><enum>(2)</enum><text>For a Congressional Clerk selected under subsection (c)(2), the Congressional Clerk may interview for, and accept if offered, a clerkship with—</text> <subparagraph id="HFDEB66649D084624B049769E896F39BE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an office of any committee of the House of Representatives, including any select or special committee;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC750CCE7384D4219832B2F119C705E7A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an office of a joint committee of Congress the pay of the employees of which is disbursed by the Chief Administrative Officer of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1AD9778DA1A34D90AFA67369E3423D22"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an office of any individual Member of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE986FC8CF4554BB7B4C6B5515E5669B4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a leadership office of the House of Representatives; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD658E428C211476FA5C7EBAA540888CB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Office of General Counsel of the House of Representatives, the Office of the Parliamentarian of the House of Representatives, or the Office of the Legislative Counsel of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC6D0CD079F184FF48E8093D75470440A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Placement requirements</header><text>The Selection Committees shall, to the extent practicable, ensure that Congressional Clerks selected and placed under this section are apportioned equally between majority party and minority party offices.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF596238B7F07413FAB69C142E05F49D2"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Exclusion from limit on number of positions</header><text>A Congressional Clerk shall be excluded in determining the number of employees of the office that employs the Clerk for purposes of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H36347AD68E3D45BEB059B94CE03885A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of the office of a Member of the House of Representatives, section 104 of the House of Representatives Administrative Reform Technical Corrections Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/5321">2 U.S.C. 5321</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA23077C6CE894492A4CDC3F19BFEE385"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of any other office, any applicable provision of law or any rule or regulation which imposes a limit on the number of employees of the office.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H16A90F01F3F745CA8C7E372AA8EC9DAC"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Funding for positions; adherence to rules</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF7FDC09396BB4C41879AC35C8F8FFCFC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Sense of the Senate</header><text>It is the sense of the Senate that—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEDB0EAB13FE24D8FA0CB2B9CC2ACBB07"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount of financial assistance provided to a Congressional Clerk under paragraph (3) should, if practicable, be comparable to the compensation and benefits provided for similar clerkships offered through the Federal judiciary and executive branches; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H40FA009682C94D388AA622E85C309079"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any financial assistance provided to a Congressional Clerk under such paragraph should not result in a net increase in the amounts appropriated for the legislative branch for any fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H01F5FEB9FB93450691F12CC1A12F9C7B"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of any financial assistance provided under paragraph (3) for a Congressional Clerk shall be—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H67E85C78FCBD4909931AA5D92AB3D2F0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">determined or approved by the office hiring the Congressional Clerk; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC878B0B4E51644639A6135984BC4066F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">based on the office's determination of the duties and responsibilities for such Congressional Clerk.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H065CC49FDD49474EA0CDC13887C16EC1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Financial assistance</header> 
<subparagraph id="H7E2E5FA511C344FCA1B52F168E34AB42"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Eligibility for fellowships</header><text>A Congressional Clerk that is placed with an office described in subsection (e) may accept a fellowship through an institution of higher education (as defined in section 101(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001(a)</external-xref>)) for the term of the clerkship with the approval of the office in accordance with paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD0F1B1F2A1614E01B6C3FAFEF4073126"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Payment provided by congressional office</header><text>An office described in subsection (e) may use amounts otherwise available to the office to provide compensation to a Congressional Clerk of the office for the term of the clerkship.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6A4FD517064140B3BA34B26A0EE21952"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Required adherence to rules</header><text>A Congressional Clerk that obtains a clerkship under this section shall be subject to all laws, regulations, and rules in the same manner and to the same extent as an individual serving in a similar position in the Senate or the House of Representatives, as the case may be.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3043C43602534CCD84119C05642F8508"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Rules</header><text>The Selection Committees shall develop and promulgate rules regarding the administration of the Congressional Clerkship program established under this section.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


