<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HEAD00C649FF848A292541726C8E1F164" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5891 IH: Improving the Federal Response to Families Impacted by Substance Use Disorder Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5891</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180521">May 21, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000588">Mr. Lamb</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish an interagency task force to improve the Federal response to families impacted by
			 substance abuse disorders.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H235C0E90C0674A6EB92DACB367D0132C" style="OLC">
 <section id="H41C33C41D96E4328B7D80AEF7378C7F3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving the Federal Response to Families Impacted by Substance Use Disorder Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H89E91DAB9AE74C17824816CAB0F3980D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Interagency Task Force to Improve the Federal Response to Families Impacted by Substance Use Disorders</header> <subsection id="HCC26781D028D4A9EB9F0EA68D2577849"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established a task force, to be known as the <quote>Interagency Task Force to Improve the Federal Response to Families Impacted by Substance Use Disorders</quote> (in this section referred to as “Task Force”).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H3BCDD67679D9445E8745EFCB132AF2DE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force—</text> <paragraph id="H10CFE772EBED473BAE9F2C2C9CE6E630"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall identify, evaluate, and recommend ways in which Federal agencies can better coordinate responses to substance use disorders and the opioid crisis; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7903D22EF30A43968CBAB126D4241B6F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall carry out the additional duties described in subsection (d).</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB31520B9FFE9449DB22163AE38941ADA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership</header> <paragraph id="H572EB310D7B84F669656F6439258B9CB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Number and appointment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force shall be composed of 12 Federal officials having responsibility for, or administering programs related to, the duties of the Task Force. The Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Secretary of Education, the Secretary of Agriculture, and the Secretary of Labor shall each appoint two members to the Task Force from among the Federal officials employed by the Department of which they are the head. Additional Federal agency officials appointed by the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall fill the remaining positions of the Task Force.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3C89020D403F4B4A85DCA580524D83C8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Chairperson</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall designate a Federal official employed by the Department of Health and Human Services to serve as the chairperson of the Task Force.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H55F5D825A31941C4A5C22F01A2802951"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Deadline for appointment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each member shall be appointed to the Task Force not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H976618DCC1FA4FC396761BF5926337DD"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Additional agency input</header><text>The Task Force may seek input from other Federal agencies and offices with experience, expertise, or information relevant in responding to the opioid crisis.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H3B3D13423D0A4F2CBC31E755279C25EE"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A vacancy in the Task Force shall be filled in the manner in which the original appointment was made.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H05BD635CE0454F37BE1A78695ADE1225"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Prohibition of compensation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members of the Task Force may not receive pay, allowances, or benefits by reason of their service on the Task Force.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDCF10EB079D64B8187AD72F55E1838E0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force shall carry out the following duties:</text> <paragraph id="H911E792780F84379865711ACFE4E6686"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Solicit input from stakeholders, including frontline service providers, medical professionals, educators, mental health professionals, researchers, experts in infant, child, and youth trauma, child welfare professionals, and the public, in order to inform the activities of the Task Force.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD5C6F1D043CE45288D7E71B386283FA2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Develop a strategy on how the Task Force and participating Federal agencies will collaborate, prioritize, and implement a coordinated Federal approach with regard to responding to substance use disorders, including opioid misuse, that shall include—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HFC41CECB0386473C872DF568795C81B0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifying options for the coordination of existing grants that support infants, children, and youth, and their families as appropriate, who have experienced, or are at risk of experiencing, exposure to substance abuse disorders, including opioid misuse; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1BA8117DB55D43EDB2D4E5525FF90F95"><enum>(B)</enum><text>other ways to improve coordination, planning, and communication within and across Federal agencies, offices, and programs, to better serve children and families impacted by substance use disorders, including opioid misuse.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H65ABBFAD3D044397B344DEEBBCEDB724"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Based off the strategy developed under paragraph (2), evaluate and recommend opportunities for local- and State-level partnerships, professional development, or best practices that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H90B2B5C4250342CAAECFA0FD7216E1A3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are designed to quickly identify and refer children and families, as appropriate, who have experienced or are at risk of experiencing exposure to substance abuse;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBCCF880F88A140308F7D75F05C9F6D3B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>utilize and develop partnerships with early childhood education programs, local social services organizations, and health care services aimed at preventing or mitigating the effects of exposure to substance use disorders, including opioid misuse;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2EE991A6B8147249382D5291FB2A2EB"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offer community-based prevention activities, including educating families and children on the effects of exposure to substance use disorders, including opioid misuse, and how to build resilience and coping skills to mitigate those effects;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H366C48FEE00D454F9123E07D451D7CA2"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in accordance with Federal privacy protections, utilize non-personally identifiable data from screenings, referrals, or the provision of services and supports to evaluate and improve processes addressing exposure to substance use disorders, including opioid misuse; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA6EC1EECE944B1FB5710B7FE399136D"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are designed to prevent separation and support reunification of families if in the best interest of the child.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C52BD5EA3A3466ABA167FB629ED0846"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In fulfilling the requirements of paragraphs (2) and (3), consider evidence-based, evidence-informed, and promising best practices related to identifying, referring, and supporting children and families at risk of experiencing exposure to substance abuse or experiencing substance use disorder, including opioid misuse, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HBDDCDACA9AE148B083543D8F96DC9155"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prevention strategies for those at risk of experiencing or being exposed to substance abuse, including misuse of opioids;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66E5C22D821541DBA084A475A9808DE9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whole-family and multi-generational approaches;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE141EA0DACAC42198514F7D36D447766"><enum>(C)</enum><text>community-based initiatives;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF29CCA7D1956438699ACB4325872EE34"><enum>(D)</enum><text>referral to, and implementation of, trauma-informed practices and supports; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2679ABF495DB4BB6BF33B74905F6D054"><enum>(E)</enum><text>multi-generational practices that assist parents, foster parents, and kinship and other caregivers</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H817249DDEC0C4ACCB8905E39D296E01C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>FACA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Advisory Committee Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc-appendix" parsable-cite="usc-appendix/5/2">5 U.S.C. App. 2</external-xref>) shall not apply to the Task Force.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H9D095076E5A040AABD03F90358F6C273"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Action plan; reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force—</text>
 <paragraph id="H1C93A848BF1C4EAEB1DB6354C380AE97"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall prepare a detailed action plan to be implemented by participating Federal agencies to create a collaborative, coordinated response to the opioid crisis, which shall include—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H4666EBCB93874111B0CAB8685AC8CB7D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>relevant information identified and collected under subsection (d);</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A546AE4AE884AD3A6400DAF2DB63C86"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a proposed timeline for implementing recommendations and efforts identified under subsection (d); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01037A74B2044BC28221173D1B86E969"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how other Federal agencies and offices with experience, expertise, or information relevant in responding to the opioid crisis that have provided input under subsection (c)(4) will be participating in the coordinated approach;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CE7EC94775946CBBFB5DC834A7C089A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall submit to the Congress a report describing the action plan prepared under paragraph (1), including, where applicable, identification of any recommendations included in such plan that require additional legislative authority to implement; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H071D7EBFBC3D48F698047E014B8903AE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall submit a report to the Governors describing the opportunities for local- and State-level partnerships, professional development, or best practices recommended under subsection (d)(3).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2070362110534877A705D6744DDA826E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Dissemination</header>
 <paragraph id="H4A0B92A5E2EF489E8E2C9C8AF47679A3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The action plan and reports required under subsection (f) shall be—</text> <subparagraph id="H0766D8F5553548A2BCE49869D2F4F73C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">disseminated widely, including among the participating Federal agencies and the Governors; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD65F2CFAE761470BAEF21E09A90027CA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>be made publicly available online in an accessible format.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3690666BD66B4F65A3B4285A9C53186C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The action plan and reports required under subsection (f) may be released on separate dates but shall be released not later than 9 months after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H0CA6CA3982C8442B812392FBA840B89A"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Termination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force shall terminate 30 days after the dissemination of the action plan and reports under subsection (g).</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HEEA6EA63C64A472F974DC1255135EBA9"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The administrative expenses of the Task Force shall be paid out of existing Department of Health and Human Services funds or appropriations.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HADCBBDB8F6024745A1DC22F5FF0799B7"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section:</text> <paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H16023E2AA4D949ED911873D0EC43626E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <quote>Governor</quote> means the chief executive officer of a State.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9ADBC4940E514EC8976D3EBDCAD0042D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>participating Federal agencies</quote> means all the Executive agencies (as defined in section 105 of title 5, United States Code) whose officials have been appointed to the Task Force.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H15C48C8F282B4CB7A142A7F6784DF799"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>State</quote> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


