<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H240F49D15C8C4D86A16D4045E1C1A9CA" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5731 IH: Securing Our Schools Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5731</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180509">May 9, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000210">Mr. King of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001197">Ms. McSally</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000625">Mr. Donovan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001269">Mr. Barletta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000386">Mr. Katko</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000605">Mr. Perry</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Department of Homeland Security to develop a strategy to secure elementary schools,
			 secondary schools, and institutions of higher education from acts of
			 terrorism, active shooters, and other homeland security threats, and for
			 other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H187BD94BC41B4ED795BFA94E9492AC24" style="OLC">
 <section id="H1874986E0E9949C98E773413B11A263C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing Our Schools Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H627E73EDE11E49E5B18D700E5C69B6B4"><enum>2.</enum><header>School security strategy</header> <subsection id="HC2A5BF47DA1F4A3F8B5E377A683B9555"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security, acting through the Under Secretary responsible for overseeing critical infrastructure protection, cybersecurity and any other related programs of the Department of Homeland Security referred to in section 103(a)(1)(H) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/113">6 U.S.C. 113(a)(1)(H)</external-xref>), shall develop a Department-wide strategy on efforts and activities of the Department related to securing elementary schools, secondary schools, and institutions of higher education from acts of terrorism, active shooters, and other homeland security threats.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H19ECC4093776484B8491B5E9B3558687"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Scope</header><text>The strategy required under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text> <paragraph id="H0228CDB162F246D4B20F75D4082A9A81"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the coordination among the components, directorates, and offices of the Department of Homeland Security regarding current and future efforts and activities related to securing elementary schools, secondary schools, and institutions of higher education from acts of terrorism, active shooters, and other homeland security threats.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9BE088B809304CFFBAA44E429497F09A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of ongoing efforts and activities across the components, directorates, and offices of the Department related to securing such schools and institutions from acts of terrorism, active shooters, and other homeland security threats.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3101C45A8C8C4DE0957A925ED14BF6A2"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the manner in which the Department works with State, local, tribal, and territorial government organizations on efforts and activities related to securing such schools and institutions from acts of terrorism, active shooters, and other homeland security threats.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9A1FCBC8C88B4CEE85B25CF1C063BF87"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations for future efforts and activities related to securing such schools and institutions from acts of terrorism, active shooters, and other homeland security threats, and the promotion of such efforts and activities.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H297943D47EA943C5BCF50FBD9C631BBA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header>
 <paragraph id="HB6FABF95E56F46798F31921232DB87FD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the development of the strategy required under subsection (a), the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate such strategy and brief such Committees on the operations and activities of the Department related to securing elementary schools, secondary schools, and institutions of higher education from acts of terrorism, active shooters, and other homeland security threats, and the policies and procedures developed for coordinating such efforts and activities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA309CFB1D30D4511BE74233D79073AEB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required under this subsection shall be submitted in unclassified form but may contain a classified annex.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H86F1DA2C17134E68B2DC2E70D3E97443"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HCFB165EA02544127AD9EA942DF4C543D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Elementary school; secondary school</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <quote>elementary school</quote> and <quote>secondary school</quote> have the meanings given such terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFB424B9745784536932FC7F84EFB9E82"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>institution of higher education</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 102 in the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H66ADF5CFB4A04331854998D69782B904"><enum>3.</enum><header>Homeland security grants</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2008 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/609">6 U.S.C. 609</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H45BCBBD6E07843A8AAC89A7ED4BC3F69"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(8), by striking <quote>preparedness</quote> and inserting <quote>security, including planning, training, exercises, information sharing, and target hardening activities</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H649B3B3698E9442CAADD227A2F22180B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H29B04196D70948728159488AE20417F6" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H5FD7E212B04E41828A60770C41B90A75"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Firearms</header> <subparagraph id="H71F0A5DAD2E84963B3922CF1AC48B6BC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A grant awarded under section 2003 or 2004 may not be used for the provision to any person of a firearm or training in the use of a firearm.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB578328FD487499D91A8B1B4C2C0428A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No effect on other laws</header><text>Nothing in this paragraph may be construed to preclude or contradict any other provision of law authorizing the provision of firearms or training in the use of firearms.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H92424C7CAF4245EBA77FA64055D4CD51"><enum>4.</enum><header>Office of Academic Engagement</header>
 <subsection id="H23D92ACB253249B1946591FA32746F1A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title VII of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/341">6 U.S.C. 341</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE89120D9D35C4DBEB31C9828942804CB" style="OLC">
					<section id="H8D335DA31FA7446F9617455ECEB626AB"><enum>710.</enum><header>Office of Academic Engagement</header>
 <subsection id="H77D172FEB5C4465D9E633961CE779394"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established within the Office of Partnership and Engagement of the Department an Office of Academic Engagement.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H4705EC26CD214CDBBE6F6B3244E1A06B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Executive Director</header><text>The Office of Academic Engagement shall be headed by an Executive Director, who shall report to the Assistant Secretary for Partnership and Engagement.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD1A69F3EE64444259899262EADAE17EB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Functions</header><text>In consultation with the heads of relevant components, directorates, and offices of the Department, as appropriate, the Executive Director shall be responsible for the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H355965303F1346998CC7069EBA39CC0A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Conducting outreach and serving as a liaison between the Department and stakeholders in the academic community, including elementary schools, secondary schools, and institutions of higher education.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6F77100927344E5B8963F79FAC85F2B1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Providing information on and awareness of Department programs and assistance related to securing such schools and institutions from acts of terrorism, active shooters, and other homeland security threats.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF309ECDE0FCD43678698CF3A0C41741E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Coordinating, as appropriate, exercises and vulnerability assessments related to securing such schools and institutions from acts of terrorism, active shooters, and other homeland security threats.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H624E61CF3F47420CB99929CA58D4A0F3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Other activities as determined by the Secretary.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1E66D77FA5424D3E963FFD890E12BDEE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text>
 <paragraph id="H95314A85A6974C419F07FFE1481D7783"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Elementary school; secondary school</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <quote>elementary school</quote> and <quote>secondary school</quote> have the meanings given such terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8AA819ACBED649129D427A2988BEA6E7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>institution of higher education</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 102 in the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H432974FD58034B03A29FE3B8216333A2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1(b) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 709 the following new item:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5ACCB0A9E2E84E1984B84FF9AB57BC6A" style="OLC">
					<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
						<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 710. Office of Academic Engagement.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


