<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H87406A1A73BE423EAAD101321820EDD3" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5574 IH: Homeland Procurement Reform Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5574</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180418">April 18, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000477">Mr. Taylor</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001301">Mr. Bergman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001170">Ms. Shea-Porter</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the use of funds appropriated or otherwise available to Department of Homeland Security
			 frontline operational components for the procurement of certain items that
			 do not meet specified criteria, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HB335EBE519304715A332A3F9B74499ED" style="OLC">
 <section id="H0B213CCE74EC46BDAE8A217492C7F2BE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Homeland Procurement Reform Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>HOPR Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H1B215054E03943A3ABC0BB4BDC245FB8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirements to buy certain items related to national security interests according to certain criteria; exceptions</header> <subsection id="H2EFCDFE6131C491E88A1F582AF64C1FE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to ensure that certain components of the Department of Homeland Security procure certain critical equipment of the quality and innovation necessary to carry out effectively their security, enforcement, and investigative missions, except as provided in subsections (d) through (g), the Secretary of Homeland Security shall ensure that funds appropriated or otherwise available to the Department of Homeland Security frontline operational components described in subsection (b) are used for the procurement of an item described in subsection (c) only if the item meets the following criteria:</text>
 <paragraph id="HE21B96350A7F4DB68B979E109668B1B1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any unit or agency insignia included with the item, including any patch, badge, emblem, or other insignia, that is not produced, applied, or assembled in the United States, the supplier of the item must agree to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H06C134D330F14C3A873106D2586472AE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">store the item in a locked area;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7E29C908E9F47A5A41038A391D61836"><enum>(B)</enum><text>report any pilferage or theft of the insignia occurring at any stage before delivery of the item to the Government; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33F21782DC334FBDA20ED2A1D4375EA9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>destroy any defective or unusable item with which the insignia is included in a manner established by the Secretary, and maintain records of such destruction that include the destruction date, a description of the item destroyed, the quantity of the item destroyed, and the method of destruction.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8D90F98E6BC437B8DF1A8692B32B07D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a uniform produced or assembled outside the United States, the uniform includes passive radio frequency identification (RFID), or any other such technologies that may be used for tracking and control of the uniform.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0124BF5BB36A43CE9570442673AC0036"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Each contractor and first-tier subcontractor for the item, including the end-item manufacturer—</text> <subparagraph id="H956366A0DE8F4FD5BE0E0EB57119578A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is an entity registered with the System for Award Management administered by the General Services Administration; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H783DA4B6E1B942C1BA7D1E368344F125"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is in compliance with ISO 9001:2015 of the International Organization for Standardization.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCCDBAD668BA3497AA00C139A2A453DC6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered components</header><text>A frontline operational component referred to in subsection (a) is any of the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HE06647AE66AE43549D03897429D06CD1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>U.S. Customs and Border Protection.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H4EB6EDF221EE41799C1971A2BEC4687D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H396965838A1E4124816E019F72D35956"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Transportation Security Administration.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9420988F74C2402891C0F1FB615580E4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Coast Guard.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6858D839BE944BA4B341ED194C0BFCBD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Secret Service.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8EB7996433854F3FB11AC86AA75AFEF3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Covered items</header><text>An item referred to in subsection (a) is any of the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HC2495F187347440A8FA011AC3702E81B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Body armor components intended to provide ballistic protection for an individual, consisting of one or more of the following:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H60F2BA5826E94481B940242EDE685523"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Soft ballistic panels.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE48D3805B034974AC711CB3E69A1005"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Hard ballistic plates.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD79DF1B6F4640BB956964C8150C4D54"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Concealed armor carriers worn under the uniform.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H695A7283D71C4E3DB699B7147FF37C54"><enum>(D)</enum><text>External armor carriers worn over the uniform.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB488185F02F43A09ED0804E72F8862D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Helmets that provide ballistic protection and other head protection and components.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H09889C0D3B02406BA6B53B494291AACE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Protective eyewear.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDA41FD8E1D3C4A7BBBE44E16DBACBE57"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Rain gear, cold weather gear, other environmental and flame-resistant clothing.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H8EDC82A0E6744F609C424B15FA9F3FDB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Footwear.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H420009D6F6794B4BBE741A191F8DE9A8"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Uniforms.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H8299D6695B54424B80CA1B4B54A2F19D"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Bags and packs.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAB476D4E33A14DB0899458511F50CC2A"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Holsters and tactical pouches.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H513C915426C84C6DBE25CC4D267B7EC0"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Patches, insignia, and embellishments.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H66B637085C7E41BD9CBAE5FB4480B759"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Respiratory protective masks.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB5D8107215CB415BB4E6A294AA250EBE"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Chemical, biological, radiological, and nuclear protective gear.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7A5545A17807417399803C73D4E951FE"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Hearing protection equipment.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H27188DD5A4934E9A94C2390E9C58BD68"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Any other critical safety item as determined appropriate by the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEC9C12E76FAD4CD58AF28636C003CF61"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Maximum uniform allowance for certain personnel</header>
 <paragraph id="H7F21707E649044B98D59C9A0D5A794F0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2)—</text> <subparagraph id="HB0AD024337DC497D833E648BBCECBC0E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the maximum uniform allowance set forth in section 591.103 of title 5, Code of Federal Regulations, shall not apply to an agent of any frontline operational components described in subsection (b); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF079F566F56C410CA7EF90B62D7BB66E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>notwithstanding section of 504 of the Department of Homeland Security Appropriations Act, 2004 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/453a">6 U.S.C. 453a</external-xref>), the maximum uniform allowance for an agent of such a component shall be $1,200.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E3C15EBF48D465B913697B435DD2391"><enum>(2)</enum><header>First year of employment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the first year of employment of an individual as an agent of any frontline operational component described in subsection (b), the Secretary may establish a maximum uniform allowance that is not more than $800 greater than the amount set forth in paragraph (1)(B).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H703F6560A7C44BE08BDF43991104982A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Availability exception</header><text>Subsection (a) does not apply to the extent that the Secretary of Homeland Security determines that satisfactory quality and sufficient quantity of any item described in subsection (c) cannot be procured as and when needed at United States market prices.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H18222B345CAF480B975AE3FC461402C7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Exception for certain procurements</header><text>Subsection (a) does not apply to the following:</text> <paragraph id="H9EDFD13634D84B01A3AA91071E7173AE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Any procurements by a vessel in foreign waters.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H27E4AF8083E44785B7D6F10CAE9BAE1C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Any procurement in response to a situation covered by a presidential disaster declaration.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4D3B1BA6B5D64F0788E5A29C1A33D67A"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Geographic coverage</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>United States</quote> includes the territories and possessions of the United States.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H635188ED4EC741C6A8557F1B8CCEB6D2"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Notification required within 7 days after contract award if certain exceptions applied</header><text>Not later than 7 days after the date of the award of contract for the procurement of an item described in subsection (c) for which an exception set forth in subsection (e) or (f) is applied, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall publish notification of such application the internet site maintained by the General Services Administration known as FedBizOps.gov (or any successor site).</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H66EA8C3B8B054E47807F248C624BFF3A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Training during fiscal year 2019</header>
 <paragraph id="H4433E59BE54A431B965C0297FDA62BCD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall ensure that each member of the acquisition workforce of the Department of Homeland Security who participates personally and substantially in the acquisition of items described in subsection (c) on a regular basis receives training in fiscal year 2019 on the requirements of this section and the regulations implementing this section.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H363CD336CA8040C9929903F9C2B6EF9F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion of information in new training programs</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that any training program for such acquisition workforce developed or implemented after the date of the enactment of this Act includes comprehensive information on the requirements of this section.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEDC38F4CACF94408A4DF98257DCB8A8C"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Consistency with international agreements</header><text>This section shall be applied in a manner consistent with United States obligations under international agreements.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE354E5E55AE447A9A78B63B709BA79CF"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section applies with respect to contracts entered into by the Department of Homeland Security or any of its component agencies on or after October 1, 2018.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


