<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H3D72B3DDF8894768A24E106BE2ABD690" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5107 IH: To direct the Secretary of Education to carry out a grant program to secure elementary schools and secondary schools.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5107</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180227">February 27, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000816">Mr. Williams</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Education to carry out a grant program to secure elementary schools and
			 secondary schools.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H0C80A88FEB4744FF9A4634862C3508ED" style="OLC">
 <section id="HEC2A0C5FFD34485EB11DDD5301A0B1F3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the top priority of the Department of Education should be to keep American children safe in schools.</text>
		</section><section id="H07B715C1D5064332AFB9167119CAC674"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant program to secure schools</header>
 <subsection id="HA30D401BED3447FBA89904F9D9A7C36A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts appropriated to carry out this Act, the Secretary of Education shall award grants to local educational agencies to secure the elementary schools and secondary schools served by such agencies.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H55E4B5DD0FD34E8689AC2D1725DFBE53"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To receive a grant under this Act, a local educational agency shall submit an application to the Secretary of Education at such time, in such manner, and containing such information that the Secretary may require, which shall include the results of an independent security assessment.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H8A1AE6C29A0E4CE8ADDE928EA64687EA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency receiving a grant under this Act—</text> <paragraph id="HA60C2E3CAAB44E36975922B09B44045B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall use such grant to make the necessary improvements to the security of the elementary schools and secondary schools served by the agency based upon the vulnerabilities determined in the individual security assessment completed by the agency under subsection (b);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDBFA19C6645E4DD986C54030DDB947C7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may use such grant to cover the cost of such assessment; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H979E7E089F23490F9683BC2B7708040A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>may not use such grant for expenses unrelated to the cost of such assessment or such necessary improvements.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H84313D623EFC4BCF9AA464F20D067BCB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any amounts appropriated or otherwise made available to the Secretary of Education for any purpose for a fiscal year may be made available for this Act for that fiscal year, notwithstanding any provision of law with respect to the purpose, reprogramming, or transfer of such amounts.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H85DBE352841D496387791E1DFA907CBC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H729FFAE82EC247D994617919FA657C64"><enum>(1)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text>The terms <quote>elementary school</quote>, <quote>local educational agency</quote>, and <quote>secondary school</quote> have the meanings given such terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA57783E9A357493EBB2B06CFEF995E1B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Independent security assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>independent security assessment</quote> means an assessment—</text> <subparagraph id="H1D0FDEB8C8874F1CB1F0B0645375975B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conducted by an organization that does not have a business relationship with the local educational agency for which the assessment is being conducted; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE419F39D87FA4925B22DA9A19BBD1F43"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for which the content is determined by the Secretary of Education.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

