<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H2E573E1B85254B6487BA1D36CE788FB0" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5464 IH: Pink Tax Repeal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5464</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180410">April 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001175">Ms. Speier</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001084">Mr. Cicilline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000579">Mr. Lowenthal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000087">Mrs. Carolyn B. Maloney of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000577">Mr. Ryan of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001286">Mrs. Bustos</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Ted Lieu of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Judy Chu of California</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the pricing of consumer products and services that are substantially similar if such
			 products or services are priced differently based on the gender of the
			 individuals for whose use the products are intended or marketed or for
			 whom the services are performed or offered.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H8554C96BA54D46A191D0E5E487D2C894" style="OLC">
 <section id="H5852B15AE7EE4C63A5B19F4A4A7D05AD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Pink Tax Repeal Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HEEED19F6451C495A877C5EF1449A4464"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on gender-based pricing of consumer products and services</header> <subsection id="HEF9A75A02E8B49FA9380A25CB6391A9B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibited practices</header> <paragraph id="HBF8589AEB8C84F5D81F40E30BD4B7570"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Consumer products</header><text>It shall be unlawful for any person to sell or offer for sale in interstate commerce any two consumer products from the same manufacturer that are substantially similar if such products are priced differently based on the gender of the individuals for whose use the products are intended or marketed.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4522A10D9BEF4907983F136DD372C582"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful for any person to sell or offer for sale any services that are substantially similar if such services are priced differently based on the gender of the individuals for which the services are performed, offered, or marketed.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBD2406CF7503401C8353A683C894B025"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Unfair and deceptive act or practice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A violation of subsection (a) shall be treated as a violation of a rule prescribed under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>) defining an unfair or deceptive act or practice in or affecting interstate commerce.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HAEBE333058714C6BBE969ACFDE760EE7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement</header>
 <paragraph id="HA64DE4BB1982438584353C2804826C2D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal Trade Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Trade Commission shall enforce this section in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction as though all applicable terms and provisions of the Federal Trade Commission Act were incorporated into and made a part of this Act.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HA535CC29EF7344169F677DFF443891B4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State Attorneys General</header>
 <subparagraph id="HF6B3B5CEC1B84AE9AC6D963DCD24866E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Civil action</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In any case in which the attorney general of a State has reason to believe that an interest of the residents of that State has been or is adversely affected by a violation of subsection (a), the attorney general may, as parens patriae, bring a civil action on behalf of the residents of the State in an appropriate district court of the United States—</text>
 <clause id="HC8AFEE4E7AA24606A9EA9896E9739C0F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to enjoin further violation of this Act by the defendant;</text> </clause><clause id="H0F29B77B40434FA6BE8159FFBB259D04"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to compel compliance with this Act; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1148718953FE4A938A2A87E4A0AEC179"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">obtain damages, restitution, or other compensation on behalf of residents of the State.</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04A886D8D7104D47B88075F195A54554"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notice to the FTC</header> <clause id="H1214E9F6ED774A6F95875C1312EA6656"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>Except as provided in clause (iii), the attorney general of a State shall notify the Commission in writing of any civil action under paragraph (2), prior to initiating such civil action.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H70BED26BAE0642E28CFF08371445FEF1"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The notice required by clause (i) shall include a copy of the complaint to be filed to initiate such civil action.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H16B036462DCF4FC9BA2E21B8208610A5"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>If it is not feasible for the attorney general of a State to provide the notice required by clause (i), the State shall provide notice immediately upon instituting a civil action under subparagraph (A).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAAD97A9E8D964712A8C6237B13B3D603"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Intervention by the FTC</header><text>Upon receiving notice required by subparagraph (B) with respect to a civil action, the Commission may—</text>
 <clause id="HDA8713D661944E5FB0679F20CFE4089E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>intervene in such action; and</text> </clause><clause id="HAB3FBDA3D2F74E0B8D9CC9962F3892A2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>upon intervening, be heard on all matters arising in such civil action and file petitions for appeal of a decision in such action.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H68A8FF1F1ADF4334ADD795AEAA566CEB"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Preemptive action by the FTC</header><text>If the Commission institutes a civil action for violation of this Act, no attorney general of a State may bring a civil action under this paragraph against any defendant named in the complaint of the Commission for violation of this Act that is alleged in such complaint.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HAFAAA84D60754F9ABD29EFD729CED136"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="HD298F8BB9D474BC18E1EA7F7A1E7CFD8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Substantially similar products</header><text>For purposes of this Act, two consumer products are substantially similar if there are no substantial differences in the materials used in the product, the intended uses of the product, and the functional design and features of the product. A difference in coloring among any consumer products shall not be construed as a substantial difference for purposes of this paragraph.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF1D2A757F32D43E19C55D13B637C35B9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Substantially similar services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this Act, two services are substantially similar if there is no substantial difference in the amount of time to provide the services, the difficulty in providing the services, or the cost of providing the services.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H38CC7A00D086472CB96F7DC3C25C639E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definition of consumer product</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>consumer product</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Consumer Product Safety Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/2052">15 U.S.C. 2052</external-xref>) and includes a device or cosmetics, as such terms are defined in section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/321">21 U.S.C. 321</external-xref>). Such term includes a child restraint system, as such term is defined in section 571.213 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


