<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA60EDC2B4281462EBAE527F831E0CE19" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5072 IH: Liberian Refugee Immigration Fairness Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5072</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180220">February 20, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000288">Mr. Ellison</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000559">Mr. Langevin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the adjustment of status of certain nationals of Liberia to that of lawful permanent
			 residents and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H5D59F9E7D4C241DD84F6D52204D3E222" style="OLC">
 <section id="HAF242D7C86614192ABC97269011A9249" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Liberian Refugee Immigration Fairness Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H0224DE10E61242BCB5D163A63C81BF71"><enum>2.</enum><header>Adjustment of status</header> <subsection id="H5D7A345990FB46C18914FCC88D94101E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Adjustment of status</header> <paragraph id="H406F5BBB9C324BC78395B84CB55268F4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header> <subparagraph id="H1ECC827C327E41908FAF05835EBBD207"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the Secretary of Homeland Security shall adjust the status of an alien described in subsection (b) to that of an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence if the alien—</text>
 <clause id="H93B6295960BF4B1D87E428F8E20929C7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>applies for adjustment not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text> </clause><clause id="H6870474928DA4A269EBB1876DF86C20D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is otherwise eligible to receive an immigrant visa and admissible to the United States for permanent residence, except that, in determining such admissibility, the grounds for inadmissibility specified in paragraphs (4), (5), (6)(A), and (7)(A) of section 212(a) of the <act-name parsable-cite="INA">Immigration and Nationality Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)</external-xref>) shall not apply.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H439D4DE33E0F41DE889A40198D09D302"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Ineligible aliens</header><text>An alien shall not be eligible for adjustment of status under this section if the Secretary of Homeland Security determines that the alien—</text>
 <clause id="H011561A424B64B2D92B332383B99757B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has been convicted of any aggravated felony (as defined in section 101(a)(43) of the <act-name parsable-cite="INA">Immigration and Nationality Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(43)</external-xref>));</text> </clause><clause id="HBB2C1E54FC6B46CFAD695624F721E5CA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has been convicted of two or more crimes involving moral turpitude; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC9BF891C47984C68BFE56B22D4A077C4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>has ordered, incited, assisted, or otherwise participated in the persecution of any person on account of race, religion, nationality, membership in a particular social group, or political opinion.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C98102E56EC4DF28FB912B94CE5B618"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Relationship of application to certain orders</header>
 <subparagraph id="HB8C9C2A0CF5149D49626DB0EF57A3BA3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An alien present in the United States who has been subject to an order of exclusion, deportation, or removal, or has been ordered to depart voluntarily from the United States under any provision of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> et seq.) may, notwithstanding such order, apply for adjustment of status under paragraph (1) if otherwise qualified under such paragraph.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H445F51AAEA484CA9AB399FD431F95AB2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Separate motion not required</header><text>An alien described in subparagraph (A) may not be required, as a condition of submitting or granting such application, to file a separate motion to reopen, reconsider, or vacate the order described in subparagraph (A).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC4A9AFE0414D4D5DB11FC0FC3F3709A0"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Effect of decision by Secretary</header><text>If the Secretary of Homeland Security adjusts the status of an alien pursuant to an application under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall cancel the order described in subparagraph (A). If the Secretary of Homeland Security makes a final decision to deny such adjustment of status, the order shall be effective and enforceable to the same extent as if the application had not been made.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCDDF7CC3BDE74C3CAF775D807021723E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Aliens eligible for adjustment of status</header>
 <paragraph id="H734296728F44410398AED2C3210FC937"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The benefits provided under subsection (a) shall apply to any alien—</text> <subparagraph id="H796C728F23F14AD8A870FB2B0EF0FE64"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who is—</text>
 <clause id="H394A3824E0484BB9B96F5E2343F22181"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a national of Liberia; and</text> </clause><clause id="H2C20816C7AEC4676A1946CE224C9C30F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has been continuously present in the United States between November 20, 2014, and the date on which the alien submits an application under subsection (a); or</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A0020B3784B43E98D6D7934423363D7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who is the spouse, child, or unmarried son or daughter of an alien described in subparagraph (A).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC573FA8FD702470DA674A16C65B14708"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination of continuous physical presence</header><text>For purposes of establishing the period of continuous physical presence referred to in paragraph (1)(A)(ii), an alien shall not be considered to have failed to maintain continuous physical presence by reasons of an absence, or absences, from the United States for any period or periods amounting in the aggregate to not more than 180 days.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF1395BF5915445B799FD54061E748453"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Stay of removal</header>
 <paragraph id="H047FCB91480C43429432208C7808A588"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall promulgate regulations establishing procedures through which an alien, who is subject to a final order of deportation, removal, or exclusion, may seek a stay of such order based upon the filing of an application under subsection (a).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H881F7FD5EAE84E19845EBBC2B0DDB6D8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>During certain proceedings</header><text>Notwithstanding any provision in the <act-name parsable-cite="INA">Immigration and Nationality Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> et seq.), the Secretary of Homeland Security may not order an alien to be removed from the United States if the alien is in exclusion, deportation, or removal proceedings under any provision of such Act and has applied for adjustment of status under subsection (a) unless the Secretary has made a final determination to deny the application.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H80100BF6315D4EB884F695A1D612BC99"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Work authorization</header>
 <subparagraph id="HCA1CC3FC401A4CA88390CD9EFFDA421E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may—</text> <clause id="H639E4B1A70C944B68AC639CEDAB8105C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>authorize an alien who has applied for adjustment of status under subsection (a) to engage in employment in the United States while a determination regarding such application is pending; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB45B6F0E8EE94DF592E020E1EE37FF62"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide the alien with an <quote>employment authorized</quote> endorsement or other appropriate document signifying authorization of employment.</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H67F997E3F1EC4CF4A3729A1C4690CB8A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Pending applications</header><text>If an application for adjustment of status under subsection (a) is pending for a period exceeding 180 days and has not been denied, the Secretary shall authorize such employment.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCF5DE9C28B9341528CD42B0C46EDF87C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Record of permanent residence</header><text>Upon the approval of an alien’s application for adjustment of status under subsection (a), the Secretary of Homeland Security shall establish a record of the alien’s admission for permanent residence as of the date of the alien’s arrival in the United States.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H228EF019AC4D4EE89B4DD0E84174B47A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Availability of administrative review</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall provide applicants for adjustment of status under subsection (a) with the same right to, and procedures for, administrative review as are provided to—</text>
 <paragraph id="H9711A84C25B94E83A4AF63472A836BE7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>applicants for adjustment of status under section 245 of the <act-name parsable-cite="INA">Immigration and Nationality Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1255">8 U.S.C. 1255</external-xref>); and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9AE5AD7C38F54F8A97EE82EB776CAA52"><enum>(2)</enum><text>aliens subject to removal proceedings under section 240 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229a">8 U.S.C. 1229a</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2DDDED74F5444EBD88776BB75D7AB418"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitation on judicial review</header><text>A determination by the Secretary of Homeland Security regarding the adjustment of status of any alien under this section is final and shall not be subject to review by any court.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HEFDCEE65197E45E68F2590CF34E02F3C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>No offset in number of visas available</header><text>The Secretary of State shall not be required to reduce the number of immigrant visas authorized to be issued under any provision of the <act-name parsable-cite="INA">Immigration and Nationality Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> et seq.) to offset the adjustment of status of an alien who has been lawfully admitted for permanent residence pursuant to this section.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HA1DEE9560BC043AC99A41B3D5D27F5D5"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Application of <act-name parsable-cite="INA">Immigration and Nationality Act</act-name> provisions</header>
 <paragraph id="H792B6CA07CB24DE9A4E0A984AF6D0346"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Except as otherwise specifically provided in this Act, the definitions contained in the <act-name parsable-cite="INA">Immigration and Nationality Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> et seq.) shall apply in this section.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HA4B4FF52C4664AFC841431713BA7B508"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Savings provision</header><text>Nothing in this Act may be construed to repeal, amend, alter, modify, effect, or restrict the powers, duties, function, or authority of the Secretary of Homeland Security in the administration and enforcement of the Immigration and Nationality Act or any other law relating to immigration, nationality, or naturalization.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HEF893630E0DA473E9F887D8A1216353E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effect of eligibility for adjustment of status</header><text>An alien’s eligibility to be lawfully admitted for permanent residence under this section shall not preclude the alien from seeking any status under any other provision of law for which the alien may otherwise be eligible.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


