<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA603B78D90F447DCA842CDC6DD7D6B40" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5457 IH: Quality Care for Moms and Babies Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5457</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180410">April 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000179">Mr. Engel</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001187">Mr. Stivers</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000570">Mr. Ben Ray Luján of New Mexico</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Y000033">Mr. Young of Alaska</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Y000062">Mr. Yarmuth</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000580">Ms. Michelle Lujan Grisham of New Mexico</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000486">Ms. Roybal-Allard</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XI of the Social Security Act to improve the quality, health outcomes, and value of
			 maternity care under the Medicaid and CHIP programs by developing
			 maternity care quality measures and supporting maternity care quality
			 collaboratives.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HFB44641D976D4FBC805B5FC79F65DDE6" style="OLC">
		<section id="HE83BDC4A42164745BAEA9CF803712D42" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header>
 <subsection id="HB7659E6FA61B414098CB3857B35C6AB3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Quality Care for Moms and Babies Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="HD8288B3080FD4D769384889AA47F0F4E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
				<toc>
					<toc-entry idref="HE83BDC4A42164745BAEA9CF803712D42" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H61942DD8382B4917A6F43AAE2BA4EE1E" level="section">Sec. 2. Quality measures for maternal and infant health.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HD914D3930829404A8D1694982A911D0B" level="section">Sec. 3. Quality collaboratives.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H6A5C5F12CABC43E2BA5533B417E4BDA0" level="section">Sec. 4. Facilitation of increased coordination and alignment between the public and private sector
			 with respect to quality and efficiency measures.</toc-entry></toc>
			</subsection></section><section id="H61942DD8382B4917A6F43AAE2BA4EE1E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Quality measures for maternal and infant health</header>
 <subsection id="H33458D1CD7134B29956DDBC2495E9866"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title XI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1301">42 U.S.C. 1301</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by inserting after section 1139B the following new section:</text>
				<quoted-block act-name="" id="H9E916E8D55794FB2827198C4DB96B539" style="OLC">
					<section id="H6DC0FDDD9DF54A0C940C51A558F89B83"><enum>1139C.</enum><header>Maternal and infant quality measures</header>
						<subsection id="H3D56281E9073448395AB39B5CCCE7511"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Development of core set of health care quality measures for maternal and infant health</header>
 <paragraph id="H0F1B39BF218F4B9DB7F8BE4AB9EAA02E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall identify and publish a recommended core set of maternal and infant health quality measures for women and children described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of section 1902(l)(1) in the same manner as the Secretary identifies and publishes a core set of child health quality measures under section 1139A, including with respect to identifying and publishing existing maternal and infant health quality measures that are in use under public and privately sponsored health care coverage arrangements, or that are part of reporting systems that measure both the presence and duration of health insurance coverage over time, that may be applicable to Medicaid and CHIP eligible mothers and infants.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9558E42E17784969817B857D0D376FCB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Alignment with existing core sets</header><text>In identifying and publishing the recommended core set of maternal and infant health quality measures required under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall ensure that, to the extent possible, such measures align with and do not duplicate—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H44B363B9F6084429829F675B0177194C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the core set of child health quality measures identified, published, and revised under section 1139A; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2856E39074B84047809210615A5CCC2D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the core set of adult health quality measures identified, published, and revised under section 1139B.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H84AA61231BA14AC9880A8D7DCA403F38"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Process for maternal and infant quality measures program</header><text>In identifying gaps in existing maternal and infant measures and establishing priorities for the development and advancement of such measures, the Secretary shall consult with—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF2D714249098484A99E4C16868CF04B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>States;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1E491B3BA82432897C82F3121729156"><enum>(B)</enum><text>physicians, including physicians in the fields of general obstetrics, maternal-fetal medicine, family medicine, neonatology, and pediatrics;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1E549B0170F3400592A7B1CF09735829"><enum>(C)</enum><text>nurse practitioners and nurses;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5629CC181E74AE08F30C4216FDB27BE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>certified nurse-midwives and certified midwives;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H079D9CA1482949F181ADFDEF858F9472"><enum>(E)</enum><text>health facilities and health systems;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64C511FF3A9A41D69B2F95E60D7D37CE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>national organizations representing mothers and infants;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCEE8F4357AF54D429DA597CBB189F048"><enum>(G)</enum><text>national organizations representing consumers and purchasers of health care;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7DEFF30711BE4EE8915D896D36E45450"><enum>(H)</enum><text>national organizations and individuals with expertise in maternal and infant health quality measurement; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C469B2E8B0C4CC8985F3A4CCDB89EE0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>voluntary consensus standard-setting organizations and other organizations involved in the advancement of evidence-based measures of health care.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6130A5AFAEF14CA0AFEBFC777E33D7DE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deadlines</header>
 <paragraph id="HD4C381D29B7A43BE84BD9BB6931699A6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Recommended measures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 1, 2021, the Secretary shall identify and publish for comment a recommended core set of maternal and infant health quality measures that includes the following:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H4EAB0F78B8FA493B827F54BA4AFC8094"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Measures of the process, experience, efficiency, and outcomes of maternity care, including postpartum outcomes.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD98F6D5933154219A3DC0782F910E79F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Measures that apply to childbearing women and newborns at healthy, low, and high risk, including measures of low-intervention birth.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H158A35FF3FB94D3DB3778AD6290C4F77"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Measures that apply to care during pregnancy, the intrapartum period, and the postpartum period.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H49E0239EC87B4F34806552BB3591D1EF"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Measures that apply to a variety of settings and provider types, such as clinics, facilities, health plans, and accountable care organizations.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18A1CED4842F4A2BA27DCBAFA6D0E5B5"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Measures that address disparities, care coordination, and shared decisionmaking.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB2A5D9E2A584DEFB03CD979016A560D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Dissemination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 1, 2022, the Secretary shall publish an initial core set of maternal and infant health quality measures that are applicable to Medicaid and CHIP eligible mothers and infants.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0D6F3B8990FC44DC8CC0529CD444B09E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Standardized reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 1, 2023, the Secretary, in consultation with States, shall develop a standardized format for reporting information based on the initial core set of maternal and infant health quality measures and create procedures to encourage States to use such measures to voluntarily report information regarding the quality of health care for Medicaid and CHIP eligible mothers and infants.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8F8137F7233040F8B2384396F4F8F40C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 1, 2024, and every 3 years thereafter, the Secretary shall include in the report to Congress required under section 1139A(a)(6) information similar to the information required under that section with respect to the measures established under this section.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H3DCC3C2DD8F04F0D9C50FA115D6917AE"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Establishment of Maternal and Infant Quality Measurement Program</header>
 <subparagraph id="H303902B5EB8140C0846CEA0262D0A6DD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 12 months after the release of the recommended core set of maternal and infant health quality measures under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall establish a Maternal and Infant Quality Measurement Program in the same manner as the Secretary established the pediatric quality measures program under section 1139A(b).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D0E7E8D8B514E1286622D21D25FF653"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Revising, strengthening, and improving initial core measures</header><text>Beginning not later than 24 months after the establishment of the Maternal and Infant Quality Measurement Program, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall publish recommended changes to the initial core set of maternal and infant health quality measures that shall reflect the results of the testing, validation, and consensus process for the development of maternal and infant health quality measures.</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04C4B4949C96423F9F9DE83B0DFE26FA"><enum>(C)</enum><header>eMeasures</header>
 <clause id="H008E71CF133D470ABCEAF0692A0F8D00"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An entity awarded a grant or contract by the Secretary to develop emerging and innovative evidence-based measures under the Maternal and Infant Quality Measurement Program shall work to advance eMeasures that are aligned with the measures developed under the Pediatric Quality Measures Program established under section 1139A(b) and the Medicaid Quality Measurement Program established under section 1139B(b)(5).</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1279F4C71F1F4240A04BF904AFD14552"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term eMeasure means an electronic measure for which measurement data (including clinical data) will be collected electronically, including through the use of electronic health records and other electronic data sources.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1A614F0EA991430B89FBF128C07537D4"><enum>(D)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amount available for grants and contracts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The aggregate amount of funds that may be awarded as grants and contracts under the Maternal and Infant Quality Measurement Program for the development, testing, and validation of emerging and innovative evidence-based measures shall not exceed the aggregate amount of funds awarded as grants and contracts under section 1139A(b)(4)(A).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4203DFA4764A45D9A3EBDE7B52F34F05"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed as supporting the restriction of coverage, under title XIX or XXI or otherwise, to only those services that are evidence based, or in any way limiting available services.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H04C12AB3C2F641AE90A7EA65C4FC7003"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Maternity consumer assessment of health care providers and systems surveys</header>
 <paragraph id="HF5EAD3C3CDB2471EB8493A0904EC6987"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Adaption of surveys</header><text>Not later than January 1, 2022, for the purpose of measuring the care experiences of childbearing women and newborns, where appropriate, the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality shall adapt Consumer Assessment of Healthcare Providers and Systems program surveys of—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H4257EF2091A942BC8C00A267353C2F72"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providers;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD686A204B41548EDA6FA6C8B31B91AD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>facilities; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0BC88AA7C63B4DB2A15D738362C1A5A0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>health plans.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H26D8306E70EB431DA4D1025023FC4533"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Surveys must be effective</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality shall ensure that the surveys adapted under paragraph (1) are effective in measuring aspects of care that childbearing women and newborns experience, which may include—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF6EFCB73B54847E79E1C8AE530D6C88C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>various types of care settings;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82390F6103B048F0949A8D1EC643C5BD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>various types of caregivers;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA2F65D45B9642EDBDE76EED839735A4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>considerations relating to pain;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3296882C2A05407286773523B3ECB30E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shared decisionmaking;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B4F383012EF49A3904332EC4F6BA251"><enum>(E)</enum><text>supportive care around the time of birth; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE250AE7D29A49BEA7B14EC06006D728"><enum>(F)</enum><text>other topics relevant to the quality of the experience of childbearing women and newborns.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B5CA2D3AF584760BFB91A5D469D4760"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Languages</header><text>The surveys adapted under paragraph (1) shall be available in English and Spanish.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H8560E829EECB4149904D24EFE7ECE20C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Endorsement</header><text>The Agency for Health­care Research and Quality shall submit any Consumer Assessment of Healthcare Providers and Systems surveys adapted under this paragraph to the consensus-based entity with a contract under section 1890(a)(1) to be considered for endorsement under section 1890(b)(2).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0B40CAE5E280428EA6F15CDC8B710BD0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The adaption of (and process for applying) the surveys under paragraph (1) shall be conducted in consultation with the stakeholders identified in paragraph (6)(A).</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H7759B9062BEA4AE8B622130A8100A0B9"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Stakeholders</header>
 <subparagraph id="H8A1E05C8207B49B4AFB24B03FC973905"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The stakeholders identified in this subparagraph are—</text> <clause id="H3F17E6A208B14D5D9981AF9BD43E06D0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the various clinical disciplines and specialties involved in providing maternity care;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H9BED2B1551B64C6AA9650EEEB482EE05"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>State Medicaid administrators;</text> </clause><clause id="HC83A39FDBC7D418EA68A74C11384C35D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>maternity care consumers and their advocates;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H40FA67D94D214BF987CB066F36EBBE65"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>technical experts in quality measurement;</text> </clause><clause id="H738C053F117E4C98B70650937102B11F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>hospital, facility and health system leaders;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H7B246BF2A3964DE5907B7C17BFB2D037"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>employers and purchasers; and</text> </clause><clause id="H50BD7B928E594F3DAD57292CFF337F95"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>other individuals who are involved in the advancement of evidence-based maternity care quality measures.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H75569858B7B141718F77A6BF0924E872"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Professional organizations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The stakeholders identified under subparagraph (A) may include representatives from relevant national medical specialty and professional organizations and specialty societies.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H60DF0AC8A54B4A38986FA83D98329041"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Annual State reports regarding State-Specific maternal and infant quality of care measures applied
			 under Medicaid or CHIP</header>
 <paragraph id="HDC19CDA0201946B29769B1CB7F9C5AAD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each State with a plan or waiver approved under title XIX or XXI shall annually report (separately or as part of the annual report required under section 1139A(c)) to the Secretary on—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF740A316F9DC42B19B329725A23A16DA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the State-specific maternal and infant health quality measures applied by the State under such plan or waiver, including measures described in subsection (b)(5)(B); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37E262BECCF7419FB6A3A33D55FF1316"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the State-specific information on the quality of health care furnished to Medicaid and CHIP eligible mothers and infants under such plan or waiver, including information collected through external quality reviews of managed care organizations under section 1932 and benchmark plans under section 1937.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H513CA44FB29F45A4A1F87B5DB8B58EC7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>Not later than September 30, 2024, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall collect, analyze, and make publicly available the information reported by States under paragraph (1).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE37DFF8A305C4CDABF648088A816CFE1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated $16,000,000 to carry out this section. Funds appropriated under this subsection shall remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA12C24809BFD4E5E997EDBE3FCD10A21"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical amendment</header><text>Section 1139B(d)(1)(A) of the Social Security Act (42 U.S.C. 1320b–9b(d)(1)(A)) is amended by striking <quote>subsection (a)(5)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (b)(5)</quote>.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HD914D3930829404A8D1694982A911D0B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Quality collaboratives</header>
 <subsection id="H1C4EE2B86C3543F18CAB1A761A19721C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the Secretary) may make grants to eligible entities to support—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE99732198F0D4014996C855349008584"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the development of new State and regional maternity and infant care quality collaboratives;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H91687310835A42C09F282743306F2B4F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expanded activities of existing maternity and infant care quality collaboratives; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8BF0FB6335DF4DDB8B913B33CEA227CE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maternity and infant care initiatives within established State and regional quality collaboratives that are not focused exclusively on maternity care.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4FD214D649344B199D635852814CDB8F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The following entities shall be eligible for a grant under subsection (a):</text> <paragraph id="H353779EE86984FCCAF2F0AE98971F0FC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Quality collaboratives that focus entirely, or in part, on maternity and infant care initiatives, to the extent that such collaboratives use such grant only for such initiatives.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H6DCF43BCF5B84F30BCFB1DB85D9EBAA1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Entities seeking to establish a maternity and infant care quality collaborative.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HEF1A2D3DB8464D2D9E91A63292797EFE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>State Medicaid agencies.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H879D992D8EA848C998CD143B2CF720F8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>State departments of health.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HA85DF62B2BC4431A86FB264E3A3AEAE8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Health insurance issuers (as such term is defined in section 2791 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-91">42 U.S.C. 300gg–91</external-xref>)).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0EE4CDEBEF4C44768AAB0677EB979BB8"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Provider organizations, including associations representing—</text> <subparagraph id="HFD48786AE9D24FB5868747EF20434B8D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>health professionals; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66302A8A97D645D9AB611FD6752F8A0B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>hospitals.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1C53D9B6EEC5414CA06233D1594B2875"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible projects and programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order for a project or program of an eligible entity to be eligible for funding under subsection (a), the project or program must have goals that are designed to improve the quality of maternity care delivered, such as—</text>
 <paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H91BE807D3F5C4F22984452D978F35883"><enum>(1)</enum><text>improving the appropriate use of caesarean section;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HF52A709C254F4BF2A189972235575215"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reducing maternal and newborn morbidity rates;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H85C21922A4E14C8FA54228302C98DBB6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>improving breast-feeding rates;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE6DE8C657BA044158E54261FF076B9FC"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reducing hospital readmission rates;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE5C8DC5C9E5144FD804DD96AE56B9A30"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifying improvement priorities through shared peer review and third-party reviews of qualitative and quantitative data, and developing and carrying out projects or programs to address such priorities; or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H28E5199A4DCB4FDC84348C487861F560"><enum>(6)</enum><text>delivering risk-appropriate levels of care.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD86901E1504A4850B0090F85E550BED1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>Activities that may be supported by the funding under subsection (a) include the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H8698DB0CD2D04031933604B45AC06BE8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Facilitating performance data collection and feedback reports to providers with respect to their performance, relative to peers and benchmarks, if any.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H75C4AE623EBF4EADB039C8812FB49AF0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Developing, implementing, and evaluating protocols and checklists to foster safe, evidence-based practice.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8C8D351AB38047FD87C4BE86A032783B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Developing, implementing, and evaluating programs that translate into practice clinical recommendations supported by high-quality evidence in national guidelines, systematic reviews, or other well-conducted clinical studies.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC715FA3E3FAA4DB9A622B6ED4796C513"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Developing underlying infrastructure needed to support quality collaborative activities under this subsection.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7FC6FDBE3704472D8AC5AE69CED587B2"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing technical assistance to providers and institutions to build quality improvement capacity and facilitate participation in collaborative activities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE7963D9532D94D46BA9A5E85EC7FA41F"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Developing the capability to access the following data sources:</text> <subparagraph id="HE17B593AD32F48929DA171899C696979"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A mother’s prenatal, intrapartum, and postpartum records.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5190DEE464964110915CFF05BC4842B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A mother’s medical records.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE9F2BD00FAE4FCF839D715F703A72D9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An infant’s medical records since birth.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6937D45D7BA14327AC780628AFC4EDBB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Birth and death certificates.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6A0E1AC1C7A40C5828B30D7E36CCB14"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Any other relevant State-level generated data (such as data from the pregnancy risk assessment monitoring system (PRAMS)).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H38DE6F122E9346BE8810E6AB98C8FF10"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Developing access to blinded liability claims data, analyzing the data, and using the results of such analysis to improve practice.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H740E5EDFC97048C58D4C1983A1F563F4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Special rule for births</header>
 <paragraph id="H697E208128DE4E3CBFDFE748FBB5292D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), if a grant under subsection (a) is for a project or program that focuses on births, at least 25 percent of the births addressed by such project or program must occur in health facilities that perform fewer than 1,000 births per year.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H69F7A59843654825B05DD871B81C8980"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>In the case of a grant under subsection (a) for a project or program located in a State in which less than 25 percent of the health facilities in the State perform less than 1,000 births per year, the percentage of births in such facilities addressed by such project or program shall be commensurate with the Statewide percentage of births performed at such facilities.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H687617C722384D7099E0A73E78D5F513"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Use of quality measures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Projects and programs for which such a grant is made shall—</text> <paragraph id="HAA051761383B457FAC6BBF6B3998340A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include data collection with rapid analysis and feedback to participants with a focus on improving practice and health outcomes;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6C6E96A35420468D9035AE40534E51E5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop a plan to identify and resolve data collection problems;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB1AEA3CEDF8F46238879449B291304CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify and document evidence-based strategies that will be used to improve performance on quality measures and other metrics; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE27598430A0A4F309C067F784834DAAF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>exclude from quality measure collection and reporting physicians and midwives who attend fewer than 30 births per year.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9D664A850C7244179DC3A66029506BCD"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Reporting on quality measures</header><text>Any reporting requirements established by a project or program funded under subsection (a) shall be designed to—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE6AE6B35809941C79811C35F1182C611"><enum>(1)</enum><text>minimize costs and administrative effort; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HADEE6A01921D4BCDA8B90ED96D1EBEF0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>use existing data resources when feasible.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFE4AC2B515D645B99E38D6BD09A2DFEF"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Clearinghouse</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish an online, open-access clearinghouse to make protocols, procedures, reports, tools, and other resources of individual collaboratives available to collaboratives and other entities that are working to improve maternity and infant care quality.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H7169BB9AC41B46BD88B0631C3C8BC1AA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A quality collaborative (or other entity receiving a grant under subsection (a)) shall—</text> <paragraph id="H1976035C391B42A4BC10991513397D2E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and carry out plans for evaluating its maternity and infant care quality improvement programs and projects; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6B675247FE7F4E7FA5D698EF9A6F8A9A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>publish its experiences and results in articles, technical reports, or other formats for the benefit of others working on maternity and infant care quality improvement activities.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HABE8D7C0479B48158CFFB5838F324BB9"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Annual reports to Secretary</header><text>A quality collaborative or other eligible entity that receives a grant under subsection (a) shall submit an annual report to the Secretary containing the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H20D90250DDB04966A40F945CFF471F69"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of the activities carried out using the funding from such grant.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H1E8926B949E84949ADA2465C4952E6F1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of any barriers that limited the ability of the collaborative or entity to achieve its goals.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H52971041FD1E4079BE225BDBABA5E8BE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The achievements of the collaborative or entity under the grant with respect to the quality, health outcomes, and value of maternity and infant care.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCE3D09C3A45C4D9FB13D47AFDB720A36"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A list of lessons learned from the grant.</text> </paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">Such reports shall be made available to the public.</continuation-text></subsection><subsection id="H0FEA839BCF96484E9FBD08CDE3DC1008"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Governance</header> <paragraph id="H835374D6106D4222BBE4757D7E06C9A7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A maternity and infant care quality collaborative or a maternity and infant care program within a broader quality collaborative that is supported under subsection (a) shall be governed by a multi-stakeholder executive committee.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1050151908804C188AD790396FC1BB46"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Composition</header><text>Such executive committee shall include individuals who represent—</text> <subparagraph id="HDC87334B347E4036B2CAA00241043CEC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>physicians, including physicians in the fields of general obstetrics, maternal-fetal medicine, family medicine, neonatology, and pediatrics;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1D573A5B26C435E9FA067161AC8062E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>nurse-practitioners and nurses;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9700B61D54B94A3589AB2AF2665ADD60"><enum>(C)</enum><text>certified nurse-midwives and certified midwives;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07EC5F0D993C4DF28F818108458DAD20"><enum>(D)</enum><text>health facilities and health systems;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC4196C553BE4FB6BD3A9559E8CCB1A1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>consumers;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36477DB038E54EE0A96DC906BB08CA81"><enum>(F)</enum><text>employers and other private purchasers;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF570F27CD81042DD9ADAD819A32A9EB2"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Medicaid programs; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1A8BC2E59234EBDABF89079DE786A82"><enum>(H)</enum><text>other public health agencies and organizations, as appropriate.</text> </subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">Such committee also may include other individuals, such as individuals with expertise in health quality measurement and other types of expertise as recommended by the Secretary. Such committee also may be composed of a combination of general collaborative executive committee members and maternity and infant specific project executive committee members.</continuation-text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H47094248FEAB4053B9CEDA68D51A500E"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A quality collaborative or other eligible entity that receives a grant under subsection (a) shall engage in regular ongoing consultation with—</text>
 <paragraph id="H988F8186C7D1400AA8964B87D58DB8CF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">regional and State public health agencies and organizations;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HD10A7CC93F654F08A5CC7FF6C3EF792A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>public and private health insurers; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H24AD080C52BA425CA83DEB6F3F16813C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>regional and State organizations representing physicians, midwives, and nurses who provide maternity and infant services.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H953D19A49762403EB7A9B0D30C720D1F"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated $15,000,000 to carry out this section. Funds appropriated under this subsection shall remain available until expended.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H6A5C5F12CABC43E2BA5533B417E4BDA0"><enum>4.</enum><header>Facilitation of increased coordination and alignment between the public and private sector with
			 respect to quality and efficiency measures</header>
 <subsection id="HC91189E1F9B04CD9AAB8964CF208C5CE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1890(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395aaa">42 U.S.C. 1395aaa(b)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after paragraph (3) the following new paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA85BEF15E7584E9399C8CC069AF0CF12" style="OLC">
					<paragraph id="HD7DE5AAEE01A4462921CF1924EF43222"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Facilitation of increased coordination and alignment between the public and private sector with
			 respect to quality and efficiency measures</header>
 <subparagraph id="HCB3523CFD172472BBA066FABA25DF2D8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The entity shall facilitate increased coordination and alignment between the public and private sector with respect to quality and efficiency measures.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32EF86C38BF2409C9C33E52DCE454125"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text>The entity shall prepare and make available to the public its findings under this paragraph in its annual report. Such public availability shall include posting each report on the Internet website of the entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDA5661B250C448D294C1260D3E980EB1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall take effect on the date of enactment of this Act.</text> </subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

