<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H8E8B6E08065C4AC0A7591F419557C7CD" key="H" public-private="public"><form><distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4800</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180116">January 16, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="M001180">Mr. McKinley</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 23, United States Code, to provide for the inclusion of broadband conduit
			 installation in certain highway construction projects, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HD56A0A9AEB57439583C18289CAB0B55A" style="OLC">
		<section id="H9C53DF87A98644B1BF848B040ED2BBE9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Broadband Conduit Deployment Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="H5F220B67F36649488871C0969E9781E2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Inclusion of broadband conduit installation in certain highway construction projects</header>
			<subsection id="HC2A1BF1A5745445FA4E220E445987376"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Chapter 3 of title 23, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H057768D262754A6DA74AB09B31A3E912" style="USC">
					<section id="HD7D7BD262D114F488916089426DF3D56"><enum>331.</enum><header>Inclusion of broadband conduit installation in certain highway construction projects</header>
						<subsection id="H1D33B0E470274325B58580A1720F3B57"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement</header>
							<paragraph id="H5A005E68061B408CB6BBD763DD497572"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall require States to evaluate the need for broadband conduit in accordance with
			 this section as part of any covered highway construction project.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H749F3E86186A481C9D1AA028F12F9304"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The evaluation shall be done in consultation with local and national telecommunications providers,
			 including telecommunications service and equipment providers.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H9BB5C5562BCA42E28C2AD9D5C7923333"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Results of evaluation</header><text>If the evaluation reveals an anticipated need in the next 15 years for broadband conduit beneath
			 hard surfaces to be constructed by the project, the conduit shall be
			 installed under the hard surfaces as part of the covered highway
			 construction project.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCBFFB73846E4449D88CF477803F34B4C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Installation requirements</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretary shall ensure with respect to a covered highway
			 construction project that—</text>
							<paragraph id="H93A5EA1CC8604FB9A2ACFD2D4C0BFE5F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an appropriate number of broadband conduits, as determined by the Assistant Secretary of Commerce
			 for Communications and Information, are installed along such highway to
			 accommodate multiple broadband providers, with consideration given to the
			 availability of existing conduits;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HDBD55442363A490C9F387997994D8D98"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the size of each such conduit is consistent with industry best practices and is sufficient to
			 accommodate potential demand, as determined by the Assistant Secretary of
			 Commerce for Communications and Information; and</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H87566C883FBC41DA974531F8277D3A08"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">hand holes and manholes for fiber access and pulling with respect to each such conduit are placed
			 at intervals consistent with industry best practices, as determined by the
			 Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBA692596C34C4294A37A5ED6FB555425"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in consultation with the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and
			 Information, shall establish standards, consistent with applicable
			 requirements in section 156 of this title, section 1.23, part 645, and
			 part 710 of title 23, Code of Federal Regulations, and the Approved
			 Utility Accommodation Manual, to carry out subsection (b) that consider—</text>
							<paragraph id="HAEB4855D5CA343178E01B97F367C4ADE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the ability to accommodate broadband installation without impacting the safety, operations, and
			 maintenance of the highway facility, its users, or others;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H2FC0508F90014B57856C17FE151D7027"><enum>(2)</enum><text>population density in the area of a covered highway construction project;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HBC4459FAEA614DD4A1A1382907A1D1BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the type of highway involved in such project; and</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H80B1FDC5DBA3424E93601E907EE52C7F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>existing broadband access in the area of such project.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFEB7431EADCE477B8F24E38F9157952A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Pull tape</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that each broadband conduit installed pursuant to this section includes
			 a pull tape and is capable of supporting fiber optic cable placement
			 techniques consistent with industry best practices, as determined by the
			 Secretary.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="HDCFA5236376543AE99229B22791DEDCE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Depth of installation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that each broadband conduit installed pursuant to this section is placed
			 at a depth consistent with industry best practices, as determined by the
			 Secretary, and that, in determining the depth of placement, consideration
			 is given to the location of existing utilities and the cable separation
			 requirements of State and local electrical codes.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="HF64C319EB1D24BC49469BDBD2F52AF58"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Access</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that any requesting broadband provider has access to each broadband
			 conduit installed pursuant to this section, on a competitively neutral and
			 nondiscriminatory basis, for a charge not to exceed a cost-based rate.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="HE2BBDBB417794B14A99FA923566DBD6C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Waiver authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may waive the application of this section if the Secretary determines that the waiver
			 is appropriate with respect to a covered highway construction project
			 based upon—</text>
							<paragraph id="HB04A1954E9354FA0815C1181DE49142B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a showing of undue burden;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H1D95FF3574A542A5A3F54838D7011381"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a determination that the installation of broadband conduit beneath hard surfaces to be constructed
			 as part of a covered highway construction project is not necessary based
			 on the availability of existing broadband infrastructure;</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H1C43F322C65F492B98CF38FE39D57EC2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a cost-benefit analysis; or</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H806F8E2982724488A870D64EBD6999CA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the consideration of other relevant factors.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H110A4270EAB848958FB50F10D79F25F2"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Coordination with FCC</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out this section, the Secretary and the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for
			 Communications and Information shall coordinate with the Federal
			 Communications Commission, including in making determinations with respect
			 to an appropriate number of broadband conduits under subsection (b)(1),
			 potential demand under subsection (b)(2), and existing broadband access
			 under subsection (c).</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H60ADAA3F357041BF8D68015D28F1FEC6"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Publication of conduit availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall provide
			 information to the Federal Communications Commission and the Assistant
			 Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information for inclusion
			 within the National Broadband Map.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H213CDF750FA1400A9EB06909AD3BF340"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the following definitions apply:</text>
							<paragraph id="HC3678DC45DCC4860A20A89C84AFCE4E4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Broadband</header><text>The term <term>broadband</term> means an Internet Protocol-based transmission service that enables users to send and receive
			 voice, video, data, graphics, or a combination thereof.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H27D1277D30684DD2AFB10DEE096D8862"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Broadband conduit</header><text>The term <term>broadband conduit</term> means a conduit for fiber optic cables that support broadband or, where appropriate, wireless
			 facilities for broadband service.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H898108017E48416FB2176D4118A75E96"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered highway construction project</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered highway construction project</term> means a project to construct a new highway or to construct an additional lane or paved shoulder
			 for an existing highway that is commenced after the date of enactment of
			 this section and that receives funding under this title.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="H1ADCE8510CF14AF9BFA94F1C5E87B734"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Hard surfaces</header><text>The term <quote>hard surfaces</quote> means asphalt and concrete pavement, curb and gutter, and sidewalk.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H898D38C86AC84E6DA28D9A5D871C3138"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The analysis for chapter 3 of title 23, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the
			 following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H42132C0B6BB941D1AD8450257526DA20" style="USC">
					<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
						<toc-entry level="section">331. Inclusion of broadband conduit installation in certain highway construction projects. </toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>
