<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HE49D60B018B44F699F82B6183FC43D5F" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4768 IH: National Strategy for Combating the Financing of Transnational Criminal Organizations Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4768</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180111">January 11, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff of Tennessee</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001191">Ms. Sinema</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the President to develop a national strategy to combat the financial networks of
			 transnational organized criminals, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HA1F6BB116DE34686B5A02F6E2EAB9064" style="OLC">
 <section id="HFF1A28ECB1E040C48229D1783D1F5333" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Strategy for Combating the Financing of Transnational Criminal Organizations Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H2AAAD73DB29F47C0A4563704A7AF4E7C"><enum>2.</enum><header>National strategy</header> <subsection id="H560C70FF6AFD44FE98FF8B4D4CA0524C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President, acting through the Secretary of the Treasury, shall, in consultation with the Attorney General, the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Homeland Security, the Director of National Intelligence, the Secretary of Defense, the Director of the Drug Enforcement Administration, the Commissioner of Customs and Border Protection, the Director of the Office of National Drug Control Policy, and the Federal functional regulators, develop a national strategy to combat the financial networks of transnational organized criminals.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H6601AFCFDE864DE1BBD40DDC37F8E4F5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transmittal to Congress</header>
 <paragraph id="H7EA78FC13D824FBD9BC4151579F5CFF9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the enactment of this Act, the President shall submit to the appropriate Congressional committees and make available to the relevant government agencies as defined in subsection (a), a comprehensive national strategy in accordance with subsection (a).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HEA95506FF9494B44ABC1C0DCDBB44BD6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Updates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After the initial submission of the national strategy under paragraph (1), the President shall, not less often than every 2 years, update the national strategy and submit the updated strategy to the appropriate Congressional committees.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE89E38368567416391E87E87E415B5C6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Separate presentation of classified material</header><text>Any part of the national strategy that involves information that is properly classified under criteria established by the President shall be submitted to Congress separately in a classified annex and, if requested by the chairman or ranking member of one of the appropriate Congressional committees, as a briefing at an appropriate level of security.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H683DD5151CDE4C6182AA4C6597128C6B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Contents of national strategy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The national strategy described in section 2 shall contain the following:</text> <paragraph id="H0F383C03572A4CAB8F76224FF1A13E06"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Threats</header><text>An identification and assessment of the most significant current transnational organized crime threats posed to the national security of the United States, including drug and human trafficking organizations, cyber criminals, and other relevant entities, including those identified in the President’s <quote>Strategy to Combat Transnational Organized Crime</quote> (published July 2011).</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="HB04599CDB892493C89708ECC6AA00DF2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Illicit finance</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC069E68F903B4B5696B797669BACA8FB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An identification of individuals, entities, and networks that provide financial support or financial facilitation to transnational organized crime groups, and an assessment of the scope and role of those providing financial support to transnational organized crime groups.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57227B1994E24A9F802F92006D6AB304" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An assessment of methods by which transnational organized crime groups launder illicit proceeds, including trade-based money laundering, bulk cash smuggling, exploitation of shell companies, and misuse of digital currencies and other cyber technologies, as well as an assessment of the risk to the financial system of the United States of such methods.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD8CD259AD35442A8A0199E20D9F7D7B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Goals, objectives, priorities, and actions</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H11193091AB2147D3889E1E9A9DB89B11"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A comprehensive, research-based, quantifiable discussion of short-term and long-term goals, objectives, priorities, and actions, listed for each department and agency described under section 2(a), for combating the financing of transnational organized crime groups and their facilitators.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1CAE1177B274C8880001C1200E5E7BE" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of how the strategy is integrated into, and supports, the national security strategy, drug control strategy, and counterterrorism strategy of the United States.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9ACFBD06E6E0466386F90500D0C7D94E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Reviews and proposed changes</header><text>A review of current efforts to combat the financing or financial facilitation of transnational organized crime, including efforts to detect, deter, disrupt, and prosecute transnational organized crime groups and their supporters, and, if appropriate, proposed changes to any law or regulation determined to be appropriate to ensure that the United States pursues coordinated and effective efforts within the jurisdiction of the United States, including efforts or actions that are being taken or can be taken by financial institutions, efforts in cooperation with international partners of the United States, and efforts that build partnerships and global capacity to combat transnational organized crime.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HCAEA40A050994CF08FA450C791D9A4B4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H9B445E057B024371B2A4C8D489FAF2F5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HBB38E678637541E9B4055AF619EB57BF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Financial Services, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Homeland Security, and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H81E32EAB7DB8420C9BF8AE938BF7BEE6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5788ED1B172B4CB6A5AA25F5BBE6EF16"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal functional regulator</header><text>The term <quote>Federal functional regulator</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 509 of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/6809">15 U.S.C. 6809</external-xref>).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HEE620E7B0CDB4F6A9814CAA9DC2BC1F3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Transnational organized crime</header><text>The term <quote>transnational organized crime</quote> refers to those self-perpetuating associations of individuals who operate transnationally for the purpose of obtaining power, influence, monetary or commercial gains, wholly or in part by illegal means, while—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H948FA49250DD4DCCAD43A39EE7402B82"><enum>(A)</enum><text>protecting their activities through a pattern of corruption or violence; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D3BBCF919C7429AB92FC42974DEB68F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>while protecting their illegal activities through a transnational organizational structure and the exploitation of transnational commerce or communication mechanisms.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


