<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H57E17AA8465B4B2BA4DCCB3ACE518678" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4818 IH: Pulled Pork Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4818</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180117">January 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000608">Ms. Rosen</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="J000255">Mr. Jones</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAP00">Appropriations</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the use of Federal funds made available in the form of an earmark, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H52A32FD4F04646418691A0167A8927F2" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5BAA69DC776F44478267DBD313790B57" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Pulled Pork Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB95FA877AE70449D81601BC73A812397"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on earmarks</header> <subsection id="H69BC24B4EFB240489A5105CB530E6F5E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No funds made available after the date of enactment of this Act to any Executive agency through an earmark may be obligated or expended by that agency, and any such funds are rescinded effective on the date the funds are so made available.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H489CA834909A43CDB2639222CC3CEA71"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Executive agency identification of earmarks and report</header> 
<paragraph id="H35029CD844B74C4686A2A895F0DCDC30"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency identification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of each Executive agency shall submit to the Director of the Office of Management and Budget an annual report that identifies each earmark for a project of the agency that is ineligible for funding under subsection (a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3C0802ABB8594BE48217F8E080FAB0DC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Office of Management and Budget shall submit to Congress, and publish on the Office’s public website, an annual report on earmarks that includes—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0A437742459141D382E944F700F45E29"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a listing and accounting for earmarks identified under paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H65A12C9CDB0C42F2B8519CC1122DB15B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the annual savings resulting from this section for the previous fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7D25EF1C990E46EDBE88C04709D9B1C7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HCB9CD710EB8F4886866715D8442B5910"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <quote>Executive agency</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 105 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5522BEB817A34322A77C33E60328E4B5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Earmark</header><text>The term <quote>earmark</quote> means a provision or report language included primarily at the request of a Member of Congress providing, authorizing, or recommending a specific amount of discretionary budget authority, credit authority, or other spending authority for a contract, loan, loan guarantee, grant, loan authority, or other expenditure with or to an entity, or targeted to a specific State, locality or congressional district, other than through a statutory or administrative formula-driven or competitive award process.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

