<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H56322C2633AD4AAAB192E296D6D7A7C3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5846 IH: Promoting Flood Risk Mitigation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5846</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180516">May 16, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S000051">Mr. Sanford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000614">Mr. Duffy</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000191">Mr. DeFazio</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Comptroller General of the United States to conduct a study regarding the buyout practices of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H808928514EC44D389531A688AB8644F2" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2EBDD8075CB146049BB2BBDAF75D2AB5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Promoting Flood Risk Mitigation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H0F91A448C0DE49D78611D6B75A926099"><enum>2.</enum><header> GAO study regarding buyout practices</header> <subsection id="HD8C5332410C44E389D496F39E4F98A94"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text> 
<paragraph id="H72B65182F3E549F28D801B4DDA8DC853"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H95691E4DFB6A447EB6F2D5515B56FA50"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2D0A1300672242579D787BF2D1DE5677"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB9D23391812A4BCEB49F51D51ABA5222"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H66CCAF48E5414D0FB5C263539D3AFFAB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3C92E8EF9ED44CC3B90BCA943BCABB09"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H147E3381187C4FBBA32C4523013E7915"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the terms <term>buyout practice</term> and <term>buyout program</term> mean a practice or program, as applicable, under which the Administrator provides assistance to State and local governments so that those entities may acquire flood-damaged properties;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H88D2B27F51704C03A0DB869651C7A71F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>eligible property owner</term> means a policyholder under the National Flood Insurance Program with a household income that is not more than 120 percent of the mean household income for the community in which the primary residence of the policyholder is located;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF3868DC3838943D0B872A47F97A0429C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>National Flood Insurance Program</term> means the program established under the National Flood Insurance Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4001">42 U.S.C. 4001</external-xref> et seq.);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H36EF0EF6F67C49E9A575EFC19844A7FB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the term <term>repetitive loss structure</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1370(a) of the National Flood Insurance Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4121">42 U.S.C. 4121(a)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE07F4E4320A24FB09E49FBA2A8094FA1"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the term <term>severe repetitive loss structure</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1366(h) of the National Flood Insurance Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4104c">42 U.S.C. 4104c(h)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H285F6E2C05144FD4A80766D8978B5F17"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study required</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study to assess—</text> 
<paragraph id="H92298E97866A4A47A4905690ED5CCE7B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the efficacy of buyout practices, as in effect on the date on which the study is conducted; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H82BFEAE1998C4DE0B3293A698B3ED42C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ways to streamline the buyout practices described in paragraph (1) in order to provide more timely assistance to a larger number of State and local governments.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H65CAA83C1A964037A9879C9710DB937A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Considerations and analysis</header><text>The study conducted under subsection (b) shall consider and analyze the following:</text> <paragraph id="H7BBF9985690A41C8A5FCE7A95D8E1076"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To the extent possible, current (as of the date on which the study is conducted) and future trends with respect to repetitive loss structures and severe repetitive loss structures that are insured under the National Flood Insurance Program, including, with respect to both inland and coastal areas—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAD9AB4A9C9A34F41899EBC2F7AE0B1F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>changes in flood risk, flood frequency, and flood magnitude since the inception of the National Flood Insurance Program; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H965F132DC696435D999997FE41BEE6F6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>projections for changes in flood risk, flood frequency, and flood magnitude by 2025, 2050, and 2075.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4FCBBCA53A9E4F2980986D13DC887930"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To the extent possible, buyout practices (as of the date on which the study is conducted), including—</text> <subparagraph id="H0B024DD4DC2846178CF0421555471A75"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the availability of funding sources for buyout programs through various grant programs;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB1FE440DCDA846949110273077B4BECB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the total number of properties acquired though buyout programs;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4DB8519513F747649AD68C0855F99BA7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the average length of time for a State or local government to acquire a flood-damaged property under a buyout program, with that period beginning on the date on which the State or local government, as applicable, begins participating in the buyout program;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3530DC8052584323B771C5191B1422CA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an estimate of the number of flood-damaged properties that could be acquired from willing property owners under buyout programs with the full cooperation of State and local governments;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDC15D300DC944DEE8E9751140B904A05"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the socioeconomic status of recipients of buyouts under buyout programs; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H48F1C6C1FC0D40B3AA9348682DF3B098"><enum>(F)</enum><text>examples of successful buyout programs, including best practices employed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8CEA7954E2A24DAE8004A15D7DA0F842"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Administrative, financial, or temporal constraints that may impede the timely acquisition of properties under a buyout program, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H21D63C193ECC47E3873D2FB9D7F5293F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a lack of communication or cooperation between the Administrator and the State and local governments that purchase properties under a buyout program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCF7B9672A8C742399A4AB9AB4827B25A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>pressures to redevelop a property after acquiring a property through a buyout program; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H348FB6974670489DA118A0A51A879F74"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a lack of adequate funding.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1E2434C37382417AB0906A4D76E21247"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Potential options, methods, and strategies to address the constraints identified under paragraph (3), including evaluating the feasibility of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAAE8E2EBE1AC498080FFD62CE4E2E5C0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a pilot program under which—</text> <clause id="H44C6BCD22B66495DA6541B5D5E29B9D9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an eligible property owner may agree, before a flood event occurs, to have the primary single-family residence of the eligible property owner purchased after the residence has been substantially damaged by a flood;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H673816C443604D458B0FA3053E8B807B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Administrator may provide—</text> <subclause id="H0E9522AD916B4EA29DC70B9144259949"><enum>(I)</enum><text>financial assistance to State and local governments that are willing to participate in the program to purchase and acquire the properties of owners that have incurred substantial damage from a flood event; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H942433823EEF47669885AA7B8F91CE7A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a premium credit as an incentive to eligible property owners to agree to participate in the program;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HBF88DEDC3DF44C0096E811436390777A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>properties that are acquired—</text> 
<subclause id="H2CD52D2D1CB748ACB63FA485DD905C8A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall be maintained as open space in accordance with buyout practices that are in effect as of the date on which the property is acquired; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H2261E313757B4379AF0EFF2BB49DF5DE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>may be used for non-structural mitigation, conservation, and recreational purposes; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HC7A6EA10A86146048365DD2FCF4F450E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>not fewer than 5 and not more than 10 State and local governments shall participate; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE5836A598E234CFFACF3626FE7F17A62"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the role that nonprofit organizations could play in making buyouts more readily available or more efficient, similar to the role that those organizations play in the acquisition of properties for conservation purposes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4E8CF333E7C2402F870136C3ACA3D3E4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The ecological, financial, and flood risk reduction benefits that buyout practices, as in effect on the date on which the study is conducted, provide, which shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HC2CCCDEBF0D14275BFD5E55FD5D0D2B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>take into account the differences between inland and coastal areas; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3B9AACE9F29A40188FD0DEFBC1521C8B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include—</text> <clause id="HE966756A571645408A0D44DF710CC23C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>examples in which ecosystem restoration and other nature-based approaches have enhanced the reduction of flood risk; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBAEC6C7E045444948B3EBDFD76A54ADD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>recommendations for best practices.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61B998DFC7F6447ABE7EE44696279301"><enum>(6)</enum><text>To the extent possible, an assessment of how the Administrator may use buyout programs to reduce future flood disaster recovery costs that are attributable to future projections of flood risk as a result of sea level rise, population changes, subsidence, and other factors.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H011B8131EF1748639B7F4ED35BCA3253"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header> 
<paragraph id="HA13494FB5C3F430486419500A8C211CA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress and the Administrator a report that sets forth the analysis, conclusions, and recommendations resulting from the study conducted under subsection (b).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4E0BE3936FA645EBAEA4906F4C965945"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report submitted under paragraph (1) shall detail the feasibility of the Administrator establishing, and the processes required for the Administrator to establish, an alternative buyout program, such as the pilot program described in subsection (c)(4)(A).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

