<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9D8725CAF30A4742ADB528CFED8C91C9" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5059 IH: State Insurance Regulation Preservation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5059</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180215">February 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000598">Mr. Rothfus</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Home Owners’ Loan Act with respect to the registration and supervision of insurance
			 savings and loan holding companies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HD9E62789846146ECAD500DA840E38154" style="OLC">
 <section id="HD4E8AA9DA97A4F2792D745D271D76C7C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>State Insurance Regulation Preservation Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H91D03E94B1754FBBB2E6CBA8AB916C35"><enum>2.</enum><header>Supervision of insurance savings and loan holding companies</header> <subsection id="HE9A5049692A9426FBD8909AA7B6D0C41"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Section 10(a)(1) of the Home Owners’ Loan Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1467a">12 U.S.C. 1467a(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="HEA29BC2956744618896869E1334B5CD5" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="HC6F7330E844449ABB3944697865EDF00"><enum>(K)</enum><header>Insurance savings and loan holding company</header><text>The term <term>insurance savings and loan holding company</term> means—</text> <clause id="HDA1370C47DA94CAA8FE0F426B60A0BA8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a top-tier savings and loan holding company that is an insurance underwriting company;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H870D340FC8E04CD0BB7D299511A7B7E9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a savings and loan holding company that held 75 percent or more of its total consolidated assets in an insurance underwriting company or insurance underwriting companies, other than assets associated with insurance for credit risk, during the 4 most recent consecutive quarters, as calculated in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles or the Statutory Accounting Principles of the National Association of Insurance Commissioners, as applicable; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H08A8EFE8D43D44AF8890B389B4F840B1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a top-tier savings and loan holding company that—</text> <subclause id="HC9B17B3A3BD54B0184A74871ED46C368"><enum>(I)</enum><text>was registered as a savings and loan holding company before July 21, 2010; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H012CB3803E214340A7BA7D2E0328D9C9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is a New York not-for-profit corporation formed for the purpose of holding the stock of a New York insurance company.</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H158705DFA60E4335ADC5D89D445C82DC"><enum>(L)</enum><header>Insurance underwriting company</header><text>The term <term>insurance underwriting company</term> means an entity that is—</text> <clause id="H957C5C98B8EA432D8D8F91CAF927249C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>engaged in the business of insurance;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H67C980DC46F640DC9FCE4D3C5A335DF2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>subject to regulation by a State insurance regulator; and</text> </clause><clause id="H6FCA733BFFB146FF8D05DDB44A66CE25"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>covered by a State law that is designed to specifically deal with the rehabilitation, liquidation, or insolvency of an insurance company.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9FE44AB5F9A423A808C6CB34CEF951D"><enum>(M)</enum><header>Material subsidiary</header><text>The term <term>material subsidiary</term>—</text> <clause id="HBC06AB751FE644219D43CAE310B15271"><enum>(i)</enum><text>means a subsidiary that has—</text>
 <subclause id="H3B7608D38575412CBAF658306E72E565"><enum>(I)</enum><text>off-balance sheet activities not less than $5,000,000,000;</text> </subclause><subclause id="HE6B58EC482424A6AAB929F7AD59A1B5D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>equity capital not less than 5 percent of the consolidated equity capital of the top-tier holding company; or</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H3579CDB64A484E92BE50A43DCFE8CC35"><enum>(III)</enum><text>consolidated operating revenue not less than 5 percent of the consolidated operating revenue of the top-tier holding company; and</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H9FD74CB6C68A4F2AB50D807BC19BE3EB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>does not include a subsidiary that is—</text> <subclause id="HCAACFFF574D043F8815BCE22A49E77B5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a functionally regulated subsidiary;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H32940D87794D4343960C070D9D8D861F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a nonoperating shell holding company; or</text> </subclause><subclause id="HA91C48611BF34565A66BB96F4F56220D"><enum>(III)</enum><text>primarily engaged in—</text>
 <item id="H67134E8C99CF48169A354F9328003400"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>servicing activities for the holding company or its affiliates, including the activities described in section 225.22(b)(2) of title 12, Code of Federal Regulations; or</text>
 </item><item id="HD82E18C081A94E959D3743477687833D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>internal financial activities, as that term is defined in section 10A(a).</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection><subsection id="H98668D87FF1E4ECEAE4219340B8C8849"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Registration and examination</header><text>Section 10(b) of the Home Owners’ Loan Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1467a">12 U.S.C. 1467a(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE39B64A309E54BAEA045C45FAC30CB0A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>, and which shall, if applicable, provide for a savings and loan holding company to register as an insurance savings and loan holding company</quote> before the period at the end of the first sentence;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4C48DC67604A4758A3710CC94C29CFAD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> <subparagraph id="HDC441EC25B4446A39D65B209C796B688"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>Each savings and loan holding company</quote> and inserting <quote>Subject to subparagraph (D), each savings and loan holding company</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB75BBB654AAD43ADB61BB764C6076A53"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)—</text> <clause id="H4A12CC229AF749FA8DBCA225C0AFC41B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Upon</quote> and inserting the following:</text>
							<quoted-block id="HC40719198D614880B9ADCFE49CF4CAC5" style="OLC">
 <clause id="H03B6363592034AF4A7ABC93D7381F19E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </clause><clause id="HFE301F470A3541F38E4DD41A675A88C0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
							<quoted-block id="HCBD8E45F7A65483DB50146C757707FBF" style="OLC">
 <clause id="H1E930393E6914289A3BFD088A7CAAB0E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Insurance savings and loan companies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an insurance savings and loan holding company—</text> <subclause id="HB355A98FDB5745E7B2F65EA156607D49"><enum>(I)</enum><text>clause (i) shall not apply; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H919E1858285D47849F65EE4188D4EF26"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the Board shall submit a request for any information described in clauses (i) through (iii) of subparagraph (B) to the appropriate Federal or State regulatory agencies.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H500A0A57D85F40A29AD7C3DD9B684993"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H5E634F2EBC5B415F87594103F5AA6DF3" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HA92BF2A89E8D41CC9476E2423ACDF694"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Insurance savings and loan holding companies</header><text>An insurance savings and loan holding company may be required only to file reports related to—</text>
 <clause id="H9397578B630C4EA58FA5982A2237219E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the organizational structure of the company and any changes in that structure;</text> </clause><clause id="H8FE949BF0B844BB4AC7A9F8D2C435ACB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>transactions between the company and its affiliates;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA06C899B4EF341CCA4EB68477A9D2DFE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>balance sheet and income statements of a material subsidiary of the company; and</text> </clause><clause id="H83B5F96C0E604CD482DC97CB92FB8ECD"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the capital holdings of the company in relation to applicable minimum capital standards.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFBD79E895DF744EBA8B1A0B1831D4A78"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by inserting <quote>, other than an insurance savings and loan holding company,</quote> after <quote>company</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HD1C36C1CED57483B89BEE5605E4FA776"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H4449269D1BE84CAC8AFC5A0B64F97517"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>and subparagraph (D)</quote> after <quote>2010</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H941FFC68761D4D40BDB077DF1464525C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
						<quoted-block id="H246343A11D0C44289130DD625ECA0F38" style="OLC">
							<subparagraph id="H31D39B63445441CBABAF87E137A1C422"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Insurance savings and loan holding companies</header>
 <clause id="H367F8CE4D1BE454990F7B3E78CC1E50B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Tailored examinations and supervision</header><text>Board examinations of, and supervisory guidance applicable to, an insurance savings and loan holding company shall be based upon a supervisory framework that is—</text>
 <subclause id="H2BBE1121102E4D898D2854A17076B17C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>tailored to the risks and activities of the business of insurance; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H912C1A1A1D6047CEBC37E00110C0FC2C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>developed in consultation with State insurance authorities to ensure that such framework does not duplicate or conflict with State insurance requirements.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H4B1D4D0AA9C94206A28A228AE8C7DD9F"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exemption for companies that meet applicable capital standards</header><text>Subject to clause (iii), the Board shall neither examine nor apply supervisory guidance to an insurance savings and loan holding company, or any subsidiary of an insurance savings and loan holding company (other than a material subsidiary), if such company—</text>
 <subclause id="H0E427B067BF74B1681706C30E781DAAC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>meets or exceeds applicable State insurance capital standards; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="HBB0D412CDA6B4CCCAA740B9A05EAC2DA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>meets or exceeds any minimum capital standards for an insurance savings and loan holding company promulgated by the Board under section 171 of the Financial Stability Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5371">12 U.S.C. 5371</external-xref>).</text>
									</subclause></clause><clause id="H6683CCA43A464E219CF8975E8BA73693"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Corrective action plan</header>
 <subclause id="HE95AF845FE5C479A96F785A86D5094C6"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If, based upon a capital report submitted pursuant to paragraph (2)(D)(iv), an insurance savings and loan holding company is not in compliance with any applicable minimum capital standards, the Board shall provide a notice of noncompliance to the company and require the company to submit, within 45 days of the receipt of such notice, a plan to restore the capital of the company to a level that meets the applicable minimum standards not later than the later of—</text>
 <item id="H41AE6AD163564CC985C94D864C2C2FD6"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>1 year after the date on which the plan is submitted; or</text> </item><item id="H238D118D909946BAA8AE3E669CE8E1C5"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>a date determined by the Board.</text>
 </item></subclause><subclause id="HCB9685CAD96345978B155A9629EBFD32"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Failure to submit plan</header><text>If a company fails to submit a required capital restoration plan, or fails to restore capital to applicable minimum standards within the time period specified in the plan, the Board, following notice and an opportunity for a hearing, may prohibit the application of clause (ii) to the company until the later of—</text>
 <item id="HDC067E8405A44C5488EA6855DE3B6F32"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the date on which the company has met applicable minimum capital standards for 2 calendar years; or</text> </item><item id="H5B32FAC5AE7D453BB6348C0F9416FC09"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>a date determined by the Board.</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H280B16F40EA242F2A3DE5AF34C23407F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration and enforcement</header><text>Section 10(g) of the Home Owners’ Loan Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1467a">12 U.S.C. 1467a(g)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H5C6FD91433104EEAB7FDBA7156FA2B06"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>In issuing any regulation, order, or supervisory guidance applicable to an insurance savings and loan holding company, including a regulation, order, or guidance related to capital, stress testing, and cybersecurity, the Board shall tailor such regulation, order, or guidance to the risks and activities of the business of insurance and shall consult with State insurance authorities to ensure that the regulation, order, or guidance does not duplicate or conflict with State insurance requirements.</quote> after the period at the end; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2F3C67D45D94419999621127949D19B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>In the case of an insurance savings and loan holding company, the authority of the Board to conduct investigations shall be limited to the material subsidiaries of the insurance savings and loan holding company.</quote> after the period at the end.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H17A442151FA44C5485F7C44947028BF0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Intermediate holding companies</header><text>Section 10A(d) of the Home Owners’ Loan Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1467b">12 U.S.C. 1467b(d)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H24D7B4AC34274C25870B01867FEDB944" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H6BE2E24437BF4A4389B6AA54FAEB866B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Insurance savings and loan holding companies</header><text>If the Board requires a grandfathered unitary savings and loan holding company that is an insurance savings and loan holding company to establish an intermediary holding company to engage in financial activities, the intermediary holding company shall be treated as an insurance savings and loan holding company for purposes of supervision and regulation by the Board.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE99221E58E144C819576511E6E0F4346"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Emergency supervisory authority</header><text>Section 10 of the Home Owners’ Loan Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1467a">12 U.S.C. 1467a</external-xref>) is amended by adding the following new subsection at the end thereof:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H998507B51EE74E6693B51F2078C43143" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="HEF343BAA9FCE46FCBDEB7FF1A2D3DBAC"><enum>(u)</enum><header>Emergency supervisory authority</header><text>The Board, by order, may suspend the application of paragraphs (2)(C)(ii), (2)(D), and (4)(D) of subsection (c) and the final sentences of paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (g) to an insurance savings and loan holding company and apply subsection (b)(3) to an insurance savings and loan holding company if the Board, after consultation with the State insurance authority for the insurance savings and loan holding company, reasonably determines that the operations and activities of the insurance savings and loan holding company pose a serious and imminent risk to the financial safety and soundness or stability of the insurance savings and loan holding company’s subsidiary saving association.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection></section><section id="HE8F4A466B732468FB8EBA527933717A0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Assessments and fees for insurance savings and loan holding companies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 11 of the Federal Reserve Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/248">12 U.S.C. 248</external-xref>) is amended, in the second subsection (s) (relating to assessments), by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block id="H381CEAA617254C418079BD15197EA9B3" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="HA706623F3ADE4F3694FE0D3F2311AAD6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Excluded assets</header><text>With respect to an insurance savings and loan holding company, as defined in section 10 of the Home Owners’ Loan Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1467a">12 U.S.C. 1467a</external-xref>), the total consolidated assets described in paragraph (2)(B) shall not include any asset of an insurance company.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


