<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H38BAA5364703466380BEE9CDAC259A8A" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5860 IH: Putting Our First-Responders First Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5860</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180517">May 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001058">Mr. Huizenga</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000461">Mr. Flores</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000582">Mr. Roe of Tennessee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000188">Mr. Kind</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001187">Mr. Meadows</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001094">Mr. Cook</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000616">Mr. DesJarlais</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000566">Mr. Latta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney of West Virginia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000575">Mr. Rogers of Alabama</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to allow first responders to continue to exclude
			 service-connected disability pension payments after reaching the age of
			 retirement.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H4FD460388D9F4083A15D777F38B0C813" style="OLC">
 <section id="HA21CCFBDD687497B99370BAD5C8F7456" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Putting Our First-Responders First Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H66F4649F91114D0783DF54E86900E195"><enum>2.</enum><header>Continued exclusion of first responder service-connected disability payments after age of retirement</header> <subsection id="HFEE5ABDA1E5A4B1BB1CE4ADDBCE46C5A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/104">Section 104</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by redesignating subsection (d) as subsection (e) and by inserting after subsection (c) the following new subsection:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H43722700039249A8B0AA18D5BA6B0659" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="HD6A8C10C9FEE484B8E04C680482BFBAB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Special rule for first responder service-Connected disability payments after age of retirement</header>
 <paragraph id="HA3D14CB8FE734C13A94987414298D135"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an individual who receives a service-connected disability excludable amount, gross income shall not include such amount of any retirement pension or annuity which—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HEB041C78858D483284A956BF5BBD224A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is received by such individual with respect to the service to which the service-connected disability excludable amount relates,</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C43735C170944739817B80096C31B4F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is determined by reference to the individual’s age, length of service, or contributions, and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4CC0D7313E0D457684CDBEBE56023CB5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>does not exceed the service-connected disability excludable amount (determined on an annualized basis under such regulations or other guidance as the Secretary may prescribe).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CCAF7409BF0434E871135CA4A198C52"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Service-connected disability excludable amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection, the term <quote>service-connected disability excludable amount</quote> means an amount received by an individual which ceases upon reaching retirement age and is not includible in gross income under subsection (a)(1) by reason of a service-connected disability as a law enforcement officer (as such term is defined in section 1204 of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968), an employee in fire protection activities (as such term is defined in section 3(y) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938), or an individual who provides out-of-hospital emergency medical care (including emergency medical technician, paramedic, or first-responder).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H7837B87E41A740FDAFCCCDD81EBF1316"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


