<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H61DE05638B884665A1D2EDA35C51628C" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5735 IH: Transitional Housing for Recovery in Viable Environments Demonstration Program Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5735</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180509">May 9, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the United States Housing Act of 1937 to establish a demonstration program to set aside
			 section 8 housing vouchers for supportive and transitional housing for
			 individuals recovering from opioid use disorders or other substance use
			 disorders, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HD0078F1D694C4F3089EF6876C4B01BCD" style="OLC">
 <section commented="no" id="H548887DCD12C424983CADF136CA0AA88" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Transitional Housing for Recovery in Viable Environments Demonstration Program Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>THRIVE Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HFF178EFE612F4580AB32DE1F893AD9CB" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Demonstration program to study the impact of using rental vouchers for supportive and transitional housing for individuals recovering from opioid use disorders or other substance use disorders</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8(o) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
			<quoted-block id="H095D8E304CCB47C09CECBEAE9C505DF0">
				<paragraph id="H9C30435141A447D4BEC5B92AEFECF5DB"><enum>(21)</enum><header>Rental Voucher Demonstration Program for supportive and transitional housing for individuals
			 recovering from opioid use disorders or other substance use disorders</header>
 <subparagraph id="H76CE05E5C2CD4372BD22390ACA7CCCDE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a demonstration program under which the Secretary shall set aside, allocate, and distribute directly to eligible entities, from amounts made available for rental assistance under this subsection, the amounts specified in subparagraph (B) for an eligible entity to provide a voucher for such assistance to a covered individual through a supportive and transitional housing program that provides treatment for opioid use disorders or other substance use disorders (as applicable), job skills training, and such assistance for a period of 12 to 24 months.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD307AA21D624861A7B43F47FE63545A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount specified in this subparagraph is, for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023, the amount necessary to provide the lesser of—</text>
 <clause id="H6D36A32FA3394B6E979A21ADD583BEC0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>0.5 percent of the total number of vouchers allocated under this subsection during the fiscal year ending immediately before the date of the enactment of this paragraph; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H14B518D012E04781A5C0FDF000138042"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>10,000 vouchers.</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA0B74B58C1154E51BCC5B86164314D58"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Criteria for eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity shall provide an evidence-based treatment program and a job skills training program for individuals recovering from an opioid use disorder or other substance use disorder, as applicable, that meet standards established by the Secretary.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA5E1CDA3E584712B2FB40EAB0AEAD00"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To receive a rental assistance voucher under this paragraph, an eligible entity shall submit an application to the Secretary that shall include—</text>
 <clause id="H94D3DA7BD55B442786FAAB3CCD5595DA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a description of the terms of treatment program, job skills training, and rental assistance to be provided to a covered individual, and assurances that such description shall be communicated to covered individuals that receive vouchers pursuant to the demonstration program established under this paragraph; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H6FEBF94EC2A44AF08134002B053DA032"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a transitional plan that begins on the date on which a covered individual completes the treatment program of the eligible entity that includes information on additional treatment, job skills training, and housing resources and services available to such covered individual.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H034CAFE46FD44663A5DB0EA0261909AD"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Selection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In selecting eligible entities to receive rental assistance vouchers under this paragraph, the Secretary shall—</text>
 <clause id="H908EE6C64CC846949E36E0546F6F1849"><enum>(i)</enum><text>ensure that such eligible entities—</text> <subclause id="H39EDC1C2F83B43F88BB4E9CAC96C1BFE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>are diverse;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H7AFE158DEAEB440A87F1045E0A0C8324"><enum>(II)</enum><text>represent an appropriate balance of eligible entities located in urban and rural areas; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="HD380C0F4478F41D7B17483AAFC74DA52"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide supportive and transitional housing programs in diverse geographic regions with high rates of mortality due to opioid use disorders or other substance use disorders, as applicable, based on data of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; and</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H57E13590F6324AC3959DE4FF9808A564"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consider—</text> <subclause id="HE74753671E024A5FA1454FCE044A948C"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the success of each recipient eligible entity at helping individuals complete the treatment program of the eligible entity and refrain from opioid or other substance usage, as applicable;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H975504FC365E483F99FC8818F598110B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the type of job skills training program provided by the eligible entity;</text> </subclause><subclause id="HACD79520419A4FB8ABC71778FCC310FC"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of participants in the job skills training program that gain and maintain employment;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H53CBFBD378F14CF58D9E9DC7D16E168A"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of participants in the treatment program of the eligible entity that—</text> <item id="HA1D51660F45F473BB946668ABBDB906B"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>do not relapse into opioid or other substance usage, as applicable; and</text>
 </item><item id="H4F714639830D45DEA9047E9D62BE5DB4"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">do not receive Federal assistance for treatment of an opioid use disorder or other substance use disorder, as applicable, after completion of the program.</text>
 </item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25B1BE61A5EA4FBCBC3E7D3D75524222"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Transfer of voucher</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon termination of the provision of rental assistance through a voucher to a covered individual, the eligible entity that initially offered such voucher may use such voucher to provide rental assistance to another covered individual.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC00B246DD99F4615A93142A9CFFA1D01"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Duration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall not make rental assistance available under this paragraph after the expiration of the 5-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this paragraph.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC11C553460174254A6064C7CEE9A8837"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Reports</header>
 <clause id="HBEE4BE678C4141E8B6801923E7846161"><enum>(i)</enum><header>By the eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity that receives a rental assistance voucher under this paragraph shall submit to the Secretary—</text>
 <subclause id="HFC013CE88F21400EB7B98C6541B09E56"><enum>(I)</enum><text>annually, the transitional plan described in subparagraph (D)(ii) and information on each covered individual’s housing upon termination of the provision of rental assistance through a voucher to such covered individual in a manner that protects the privacy of such covered individual; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H130A117C55AE47F197B1A0E3696FABA3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>not later than 4 years after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, a plan describing the treatment and housing options for any covered individual assisted by such voucher who will not have completed the program before the day that is 5 years after such date of enactment.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H195984E086DF4E2086929BDCD98D312C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>By the Secretary</header><text>The Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that analyzes the impact of rental assistance provided under this paragraph—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="HC3CF74E78DFD40A789CAF2BFFA1A54AF"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this paragraph; and</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H594B36225025481EA9C2C5586E71B6D6"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 4 years after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, that includes recommendations for the continuation or expansion of the program established under this paragraph and improving the process for providing such assistance.</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C2340BBFE3F4DE49A81D32660348462"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this paragraph:</text> <clause id="H430985AA608E45D295CBCB0CE0B753D3"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a nonprofit organization that meets the criteria described under subparagraph (C).</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF8E8A1E54FB741C6B3D11E7541F09316"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Covered individual</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered individual</term> means an individual recovering from an opioid use disorder or other substance use disorder.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section><section id="HC30FBCFE5029405580D8B0C95D762754"><enum>3.</enum><header>Repeal of Rental Voucher Demonstration Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Effective the day that is 5 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, paragraph (21) of section 8(o) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)</external-xref>), as added by this Act, is repealed.</text>
 </section><section id="H4843F228551446329DA1BDBA768289D5"><enum>4.</enum><header>Return of vouchers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">An eligible entity that provided vouchers for rental assistance under paragraph (21) of section 8(o) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)</external-xref>), as added by this Act, shall return any such vouchers to the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development on the day that is 5 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


