<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H52E8ED8C335C40E4890D7698AD8FE955" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5483 IH: Special Registration for Telemedicine Clarification Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5483</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180412">April 12, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001286">Mrs. Bustos</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001078">Mrs. Handel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster of New Hampshire</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000515">Mr. Rush</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To impose a deadline for the promulgation of interim final regulations in accordance with section 311(h) of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/831">21 U.S.C. 831(h)</external-xref>) specifying the circumstances in which a special registration may be issued to a practitioner to engage in the practice of telemedicine, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H615AC34E22C04A8FB7977F45FB2219BF" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD6D4BB01569643DBAD5991D47108418B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Special Registration for Telemedicine Clarification Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF0174FC92A164CB8AC59D999436B841A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Deadline for interim final regulations for a special registration To engage in the practice of telemedicine</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 311(h)(2) of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/831">21 U.S.C. 831(h)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>The Attorney General shall, with the concurrence of the Secretary, promulgate regulations</quote> and inserting <quote>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Special Registration for Telemedicine Clarification Act of 2018</short-title>, the Attorney General shall, with the concurrence of the Secretary, promulgate interim final regulations</quote>.</text></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill>


