<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H6324BA9A5D7D40D2AFB04B9D166F234C" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5855 IH: Consumer Protection and Fuel Transparency Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5855</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180516">May 16, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001189">Mr. Austin Scott of Georgia</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency to revise labeling requirements
			 for fuel pumps that dispense E15, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H80B8CD738E9D481CB0CC527B72A849E8" style="OLC">
 <section id="HE5C756DEC5C94CC5A8A366673DCDFA0E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Consumer Protection and Fuel Transparency Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H59E3E96F901842A68BABD8BEA901A4DC"><enum>2.</enum><header>E15 fuel dispenser labeling</header> <subsection id="HDF072493618E460BBB12D9109804ACE8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>E15 fuel dispenser labeling rule</header> <paragraph id="HAC478CA95F0E4DD18729F3A3F07917C3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Revision of rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall revise the labeling requirements for fuel pumps that dispense E15, including by revising the rule described in paragraph (3) with respect to such requirements.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB21AD3E9411D4A0EB1ED988FF4A16347"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Input and requirements for label</header><text>In revising the labeling requirements for fuel pumps that dispense E15 under paragraph (1), the Administrator shall—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HEC66FC19EB324EDBBF6014FE94FA0320"><enum>(A)</enum><text>solicit input from—</text> <clause id="HA836C498E2A04352B1638594A6D88226"><enum>(i)</enum><text>industries that manufacture vehicles, engines, and equipment that are prohibited from using E15, including boats, lawnmowers, chainsaws, motorcycles, snowmobiles, and pre-2001 model year vehicles;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H56C7DD2DB7344D3B8F1DDA4DFBF601B2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consumer groups that represent users of such vehicles, engines, and equipment; and</text> </clause><clause id="H6CD53682185E4C1BA7BCFD0782F5AA41"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any other party that the Administrator determines may be impacted by such labeling requirements;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H636D812EF9C44F06B13D587EE0EFBC42"><enum>(B)</enum><text>require that the label for fuel pumps that dispense E15—</text> <clause id="H51B9DE0EA27D4383B75BD392127DF9E1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>include the word <quote>WARNING</quote>;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HABE0498DFB2E4C95A365E159A27BDA6A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>include the words <quote>Check your owner’s manual</quote>;</text> </clause><clause id="HB07A90129D5C42AE95CF6BB4E04B0B8A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>be 5 × 7 inches or larger;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H2AC3550AD0864703848251F3317C76CA"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>include—</text> <subclause commented="no" id="H14635CF51375490085D1D438201C4C9D"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">indicators with respect to vehicles, engines, and equipment that are prohibited from using E15, including—</text>
 <item commented="no" id="HEB7B37406F304D3E85526E2F0DE3C130"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>pictograms depicting a boat, lawnmower, chainsaw, motorcycle, and snowmobile; and</text> </item><item id="HDD2A869105264A02AEA867FF76D648B0"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>warnings with respect to pre-2001 model year vehicles; and</text>
 </item></subclause><subclause id="H7873C1AAAB1D4C2EB9028FDEFDFD74AA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>other indicators developed by the Administrator, in consultation with the American National Standards Institute and the Federal Trade Commission; and</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="HA54E8FDD2DEE45DFAA20BD507EFFD7BE"><enum>(v)</enum><text>be focus group tested to ensure effectiveness; and</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEF4029232EDB48C5BCDAEDBECB593764"><enum>(C)</enum><text>with respect to blender pumps, in addition to the requirements under subparagraph (B), with input from industries, the Federal Trade Commission, and the American National Standards Institute, require an additional warning label on each such blender pump to warn consumers of the residual gasoline left in gasoline pump hoses from the previous individual dispensing.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A5F6EED8B9E43599A4DD65A79A9FB1B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The rule described in this paragraph is the final rule titled <quote>Regulation To Mitigate the Misfueling of Vehicles and Engines With Gasoline Containing Greater Than Ten Volume Percent Ethanol and Modifications to the Reformulated and Conventional Gasoline Programs</quote> published in the Federal Register on July 25, 2011 (76 Fed. Reg. 44406 et seq.).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8B47FF5CCE7545EB8EFCAF3BABBB0821"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator, in consultation with affected industries, shall develop and commence a public education campaign—</text>
 <paragraph id="H1E3C57E498FB4F02A1B49D1333EDD811"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to inform the public regarding—</text> <subparagraph id="H140D810E01D54A2CA2E79844FC9E48E0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the risks associated with the improper use of E15; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H38CD839CF7E141919D77BC78D37CDEA3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the vehicles, engines, and equipment that are prohibited from using E15, including boats, lawnmowers, chainsaws, motorcycles, snowmobiles, and pre-2001 model year vehicles; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H440A6C99DF914F77BCD0D79D9AD65CA7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that includes, with respect to an existing fuel pump that displays electronic messages, development of an electronic message inquiring if a consumer is aware that E15 is so prohibited, to be displayed on such fuel pump prior to E15 dispensing from such fuel pump.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H12F023560C134584A59EA599DB48E12A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to Congress a report on the public education campaign commenced under subsection (b), including data and metrics on consumer awareness of E15.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H0CA926508C03450688454CF55F8A416C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Registration entities education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, in collaboration with State entities responsible for boat registration, shall distribute, at the time of initial registration of a boat and at the time of the renewal of a registration for such boat, educational materials on E15 and its impact on marine engines.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H965DE3474253488AA1C78D4913059979"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H7EE57DDA68E74257A54923CF0D9DF604"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H75ED07E330CA423F8448D40F1550B381"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Blender pump</header><text>The term <term>blender pump</term> means a fuel pump that may dispense multiple blends of fuel, including E15.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HBAAB24C60A984C6FAEE255759CF0F210"><enum>(3)</enum><header>E<enum-in-header>15</enum-in-header></header><text>The term <term>E15</term> means gasoline containing 15 percent ethanol by volume.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


