<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H995C6480C516455B86A1009BA2FA8601" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4788 IH: Hospital Energy Conservation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4788</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180112">January 12, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000179">Mr. Engel</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Energy to establish a pilot program to award grants and loan guarantees
			 to hospitals to carry out projects for the purpose of reducing energy
			 costs and increasing resilience to improve security.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HCB4B2FDA8E2140E097CCCECE3005AD43" style="OLC">
 <section id="H2883304276E746A59B29B337458ADCA6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hospital Energy Conservation Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H17608192DB97415EAF1C1398B4B422B9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Energy Conservation Grant and Loan Guarantee Pilot Program</header> <subsection id="H085A0BA9D27448C6BFC11FEB43BF7C58"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Energy shall establish a pilot program to award grants and loan guarantees to hospitals to carry out energy conservation projects for the purpose of—</text>
 <paragraph id="HD1DD4F8AC1A7408AB3C60594C080DC5D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">significantly improving the energy efficiency of such hospitals; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H197451E129AE483486C4134215842D0E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">encouraging onsite power generation and energy storage, capable of operating independent of the grid, and providing sufficient onsite emergency backup power for essential hospital functions.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2858EA5A393C47E5B55F30E1BE254EC7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Number of hospitals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award grants and loan guarantees under the pilot program to no more than 6 hospitals during the period described in subsection (f).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H973B25668DE649B88C216B616C61E385"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A hospital seeking a grant or loan guarantee under the pilot program shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Secretary may require.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE000888B74914FCF82D19B8092743E47"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In selecting a hospital to award a grant or loan guarantee under the pilot program, the Secretary shall give special consideration to applications from such hospitals that can demonstrate that they are able to commence an energy conservation project more promptly.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HC773C7EC401E443382FFDC5ACD964538"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the terms <term>hospital</term> and <term>energy conservation project</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 391 of the Energy Policy and Conservation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6371">42 U.S.C. 6371</external-xref>).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H60A7250B141541AB8EB70154F69E8205"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated for carrying out this section such sums as may be necessary for fiscal years 2019 and 2020, to be derived from funds otherwise authorized to be appropriated for related purposes.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


