<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2330CBCBB79E49DB9801B64740BA7071" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5577 IH: Notification of Your Eldercare Rights Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5577</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180419">April 19, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Labor, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, to draft disclosures describing the rights and liabilities of customers of domestic care services and require that such services provide such disclosures to customers in any contract for such services.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HC693F9FD4DE34FA48E65FA887CFAC541" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H54161B04A3DF4940819E8BAA605B6A2F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Notification of Your Eldercare Rights Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD8C82E500F1242AC9C85405C078F7DF4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Disclosure of rights and liabilities of customers of domestic care services</header> <subsection id="HF0718342494442DA8F0619544A820CF3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Draft disclosure document and requirement To include in contract</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA3C73FB289684413BFB0C57E31B8CE51"><enum>(1)</enum><text>draft a two-page disclosure document including the disclosures described in subsection (b); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H760FAFED7A9E435897EA4845592AC8B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>require, by rule, that any provider of domestic care services—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H592B8E32913C408D8242E96CF7B75262"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide such disclosure document to each customer prior to entering into contract with such customer for the provision of such services; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4BD45C7B706B45F5920EB06F7EDADC89"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">disclose to the customer whether the individual or individuals who will provide such services are employees of the provider of domestic care services or independent contractors for purposes of treatment under the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAD885DB59BF94D05ADFC9A2EA4190760"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Required disclosures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The disclosures required to be included on the disclosure document described in subsection (a) shall include—</text> <paragraph id="H10EFC7CA738F4667BE65D7E40CE1F359"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information substantially similar to the information contained on Fact Sheets 79 and 79B issued by the Wage and Hour Division of the Department of Labor and relating to private homes and domestic service employment and live-in domestic service workers, respectively, under the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAAA888C1B86C4140BACF9F6A293706AB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">simple, plain-language explanation of the difference between employees of the provider of domestic care services or independent contractors, for purposes of treatment under the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9E37CC17BFB24DA8A646EE74908C5873"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">disclosures regarding—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7334B6ECA5134473BE2CFB3C1C8C84AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the rights and legal liabilities of the customer with respect to any employee or independent contractor, including rights of action;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H75B970E0C7764DE98DC6C44B5339C37D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the presence or lack of vicarious liability of the provider of domestic care services with respect to an employee or independent contractor; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5BFB85248BDE456C9051281EBB61735B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any liability the customer might have with respect to keeping their property free from unreasonable risk of harm.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HD4780F9208244AD088261C316E42DBDC"><enum>3.</enum><header>Enforcement</header> <subsection id="H654D523DEBD54740865B8A9BF6B9A5E1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibited Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the effective date of the rule required by section 2, it shall be unlawful for any provider of domestic care services to enter into contract with any customer for the provision of such services without first providing the prospective customer with the disclosure document required by section 2.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H475FE20B169146939F3D1548070578E7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>Any person who violates subsection (a) shall be subject to a civil penalty not to exceed $1,100 per violation. Any person who violates subsection (a) having previously been assessed a civil penalty under this section, or who knowingly violates subsection (a), shall be subject to a civil penalty not to exceed $5,000 per violation.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H4891885F40874789AE18A31ED26FE535"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">As used in this Act—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3A7EB0B7B3FC4A83AF50CCEFB5C04748"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>domestic care services</term> means those services described in section 13(a)(15) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/213">29 U.S.C. 213(a)(15)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H30CD3693EDD24639ABFD0CDCDC861E2C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>provider of domestic care services</term> means a business that employs or contracts with individuals who provide domestic care services to customers of the business.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


