<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H4B501B050603464A89FF3705461292CB" key="H" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5888 IH: Improving Access to Good Jobs for Parents Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5888</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180521">May 21, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000015">Mr. Neal</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000263">Mr. Levin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000287">Mr. Lewis of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000557">Mr. Larson of Connecticut</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001038">Mr. Crowley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Danny K. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001038">Mr. Higgins of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell of Alabama</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Judy Chu of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend part A of title IV of the Social Security Act to provide grants for coordination of the TANF program with career pathways.</official-title>
</form> 
<legis-body id="HD614645132704013AC7BFC7CB0994681" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H07D23382306B42E4B2F3684A07832856" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Access to Good Jobs for Parents Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> <section id="HFF693063D31342119AFC81CD3F34E712"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improving access to good jobs for parents</header> <subsection id="H0918B9D8D54146088E9399178D6A8AF1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 403(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/603">42 U.S.C. 603(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE59A9C8DB2AC4B3CB9908F8995CBFC3B" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H5D32BFB8858A41E6BC8A99F86CF46F43"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Grants for coordination of TANF with career pathways</header> 
<subparagraph id="HBA8C241C144A48D2B3BA4A2F64C88D83"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Formula grants</header> 
<clause id="H7B87C2C6B2B247ED9B88F845D189388F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Application requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible applicant desiring to receive a grant under this subparagraph shall submit to the Secretary an application that sets forth a plan for how the grant will be used to—</text> <subclause id="HC63341279865436687B4D20FFA3AC020"><enum>(I)</enum> <item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8D43D202A66742D98D70C5B5D3DA2842"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increase the number of recipients of assistance under a State or tribal program funded under this part with a secondary or recognized postsecondary credential (as defined in section 3(52) of the WIOA);</text> </item>
<item id="H491C08D01A9144919F36CF791B62A445" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increase the number of the recipients engaged in training services described in section 134(c)(3)(D) of the WIOA;</text> </item> <item id="HFCB45107D22449C1A3D507811515D115" indent="up1"><enum>(cc)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increase the ability of the recipients to enter or advance within an in-demand industry sector or occupation (as defined in section 3(23) of the WIOA);</text> </item>
<item id="H546E5028415E44F7ACA73FF687850DFE" indent="up1"><enum>(dd)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increase the use of career counselors, coordinators, or in-house navigators at providers of career and technical education (as defined in section 3(5) of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Improvement Act of 2006), including community colleges, in providing intensive support services for the recipients throughout their participation in education or training provided under the plan; and</text> </item> <item id="H9F7D6EAA76AA42A4A39E31B1EFEA39DE" indent="up1"><enum>(ee)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increase the ability of the recipients to get a good job with livable wages, access to health care, paid family, medical, and sick leave, predictable schedules, potential for advancement, and other employment benefits that help parents balance child-rearing and working;</text> </item></subclause>
<subclause id="H29D3B1090D5A44D59864789B6021B477"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support the coordination and alignment of the State or tribal program funded under this part with the use of career pathways (as defined in section 3(7) of the WIOA), through a collaboration, in 1 or more geographic areas in the State (or, if the applicant is an Indian tribe, tribal organization, or tribal consortium, in 1 or more geographical area under the jurisdiction of the Indian tribe, tribal organization, or any Indian tribe or tribal organization that is part of the tribal consortium), with a local board (as defined in section 3(33) of the WIOA) or State board (as defined in section 3(57) of the WIOA), and at least 2 other entities, each of which is any of the following:</text> <item id="H6EFBD61CF6214C9CA672DBA14248CA78"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">1 or more representatives of a business or other employers who may be in an industry or sector partnership (as defined in section 3(26) of the WIOA) that provides employment opportunities that, at a minimum, include high-quality, work-relevant training and development in an in-demand industry sector or occupation (as so defined) in the State (or, if the applicant is an Indian tribe, tribal organization, or tribal consortium, in the geographical area under the jurisdiction of the Indian tribe, tribal organization, or any Indian tribe or tribal organization that is part of the tribal consortium).</text> </item>
<item id="H8BB60CD5360E426BB539F09614985D21"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>A labor organization.</text> </item> <item id="HC8D6D6A1B33743C596E7E70E4DC6E686"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>An institution of higher education (as defined in section 3(28) of the WIOA).</text> </item>
<item id="HD7B191E17CD0487CA25E8A17CC2EBA49"><enum>(dd)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A tribal college or university (as defined in section 316 of the Higher Education Act of 1965).</text> </item> <item id="H068BDF16826845DBA083834EC2F087A4"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>A vocational rehabilitation program (as defined in section 3(64) of the WIOA).</text> </item>
<item id="HDF87730C220943A8AACECC8F6BDE466A"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>A program that helps those who are basic skills deficient (as defined in section 3(5) of the WIOA).</text> </item> <item id="H665697374AA04552BE1D123ED3D4742C"><enum>(gg)</enum><text>A provider of career and technical education (as defined in section 3(5) of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Improvement Act of 2006).</text> </item>
<item id="H5F2B68F689C541D2B68DEC78D20E322D"><enum>(hh)</enum><text>A community-based organization (as defined in section 3(10) of the WIOA) or other entity referred to in section 3(26)(B) of the WIOA; and</text> </item></subclause> <subclause id="H5414D8F137EA492AB601DF2234C84788"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">comply with the data reporting requirements prescribed under clause (vii).</text> </subclause></clause>
<clause id="HED545CE5229A42AB812A4882EE57BFF5"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Eligible applicants</header><text>In clause (i), the term <term>eligible applicant</term> means, with respect to an application, an entity that is—</text> <subclause id="HA5CEF77A1BE546AD89607C7BED38AD44"><enum>(I)</enum> <item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HFAFEC654BAD14CE9B0046BC2A555DEED"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a State agency administering a State program funded under this part;</text> </item>
<item id="HE033C3EAC20848B4B70E5CCA5DA76376" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a local agency administering the program in a sub-State area, if—</text> <subitem id="H203065EBCB5A4C42B28E52679A4EBC8F"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>such a State program is administered on a county level; and</text> </subitem>
<subitem id="HF8467561612F471AA7C16FC49BFAD926"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>30 days has elapsed since the Secretary began accepting applications for a grant under this subparagraph, and the State agency has not submitted an application pursuant to this subparagraph or publicly declared an intention to do so; or</text> </subitem></item> <item id="H70B508848FB04A5FBBCDB8181D0F96B4" indent="up1"><enum>(cc)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a tribal agency administering a tribal program funded under this part if 30 days has elapsed since the Secretary began accepting applications for a grant under this subparagraph, and the tribal agency has not submitted an application pursuant to this subparagraph or publicly declared an intention to do so; and</text> </item></subclause>
<subclause id="HD6FEE4AEBD6A46BA9D9D189E89792A5F"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">located in an eligible State with respect to the application.</text> </subclause></clause> <clause id="H6E6403E59A944127BA930A5A2605E297"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Eligible State</header><text>In clause (ii), the term <term>eligible State</term> means, with respect to an application, a State, Indian tribe, tribal organization, or tribal consortium, if—</text> 
<subclause id="HB230DBF7BF7D4E04A896FF316146287D"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a State, the total amount payable to the State under section 418(a)(2)(C) for the fiscal year preceding the fiscal year in which the application is submitted equals the amount allotted to the State under section 418(a)(2)(B) for such preceding fiscal year; and</text> </subclause> <subclause id="HD65D7265DE0F468C91DFF1692D9F7D76"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of any applicant, the applicant has in effect policies to prevent the imposition of a sanction under the program of the applicant funded under this part with respect to an individual who has not been offered employment or an opportunity to participate in a training program.</text> </subclause></clause>
<clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE1256FD5A41248CD8A6B2AD04BA20A57"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Core services</header><text>In clause (iii)(I)(bb), the term <term>core services</term> means the following:</text> <subclause id="H4D388F4485BD408FA9879EC66DE9097B"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Work-related activities provided under the State program funded under this part or any other State program funded with qualified State expenditures (as defined in section 409(a)(7)(B)(i)).</text> </subclause>
<subclause id="H48BD833B7E43489DB651E6992A9B4AC3"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provision of basic assistance to needy families under the State program funded under this part or any other State program funded with qualified State expenditures (as defined in section 409(a)(7)(B)(i)).</text> </subclause> <subclause id="H93438479CC884BEA8F155C9EAA9B9E11"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provision of child care using funds made available under this part or any other State program funded with qualified State expenditures (as defined in section 409(a)(7)(B)(i)), including funds transferred under section 404(d)(1)(B).</text> </subclause></clause>
<clause id="H6C7A9078E85F4CEC98A7998E3A982526"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Approval; disapproval</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 30 days after receiving an application submitted by an eligible applicant pursuant to this subparagraph, the Secretary shall—</text> <subclause id="H3D5D778F57DF4CA49FB007792873AA9B"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">approve the application if—</text> 
<item id="HA926E8D76385499C9E8F468885440E86"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the application meets the requirements of clause (i); and</text> </item> <item id="HCF43E8F650504A2AA05BAF9ADC615C75"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>there is sufficient research to support using the plan set forth in the application to achieve the results described in clause (i)(I); or</text> </item></subclause>
<subclause id="H0F50A47808A646AEAB0CED8FA8F316DD"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in any other case, disapprove the application, and provide the applicant with—</text> <item id="H73D6CE3829784931B979AC9E65435236"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a written notice of the disapproval and a statement of the reasons for the disapproval; and</text> </item>
<item id="HC5CB109583F74F3CB61B1C34FE272076"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>an opportunity to submit a revised application pursuant to this subparagraph.</text> </item></subclause></clause> <clause id="HBC3C5F3115A149D4AB3FF9F173E211AA"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Grant authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall make a grant to each applicant whose application is approved under clause (v), in an amount that gives—</text> 
<subclause id="H4FAAFE4BBCC44FEEABB2BC547636DD1F"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">two-thirds weight to the percentage of the population of the United States whose income is less than 125 percent of the poverty line (as determined according to data collected by the Census Bureau) and who reside in the geographical area or areas in which the plan set forth in the application is to be implemented; and</text> </subclause> <subclause id="HB540631037E048378573367185D57837"><enum>(II)</enum><text>one-third weight to the number of adults in the geographical area or areas that are recipients of assistance under the State or tribal program funded under this part.</text> </subclause></clause>
<clause id="HCABCEB8E71E542888EEF89610BB570A9"><enum>(vii)</enum><header>Use of funds</header> 
<subclause id="H58BF1C4D005C47E49B0522B2CC393ACD"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A grantee under this subparagraph shall use the grant to carry out the plan set forth in the approved application for the grant, subject to subclause (II).</text> </subclause> <subclause id="H9CA45DEE1F81432FA7B91C4D506E8201"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Not more than 10 percent of a grant made under this subparagraph may be used as described in clause (i)(III).</text> </subclause>
<subclause id="H40C0AAA8460B4AADA5F0BCA63D92D42E"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Supplement not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Funds made available to carry out this paragraph shall be used to supplement the level of Federal, State, and local public funds that, in the absence of the availability, would be expended to provide assistance to needy families, and in no case to supplant the Federal, State, or local public funds.</text> </subclause></clause> <clause id="HC2501898E23F49E4980F08A8E438253C"><enum>(viii)</enum><header>Data reporting requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall prescribe data reporting requirements for grantees under this subparagraph that, to the extent practicable, build on the structure of workforce development assessment systems, and measure how effective interventions are on addressing barrier removal, rehabilitation, and job readiness skills needed to enter work or career and technical education programs.</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H07B0106DED68481282A62D8D5957CF77"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Innovation grants</header> 
<clause id="HE916082406AE4A61B76042B65783C5B6"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Application requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible applicant desiring to receive a grant under this subparagraph shall submit to the Secretary an application that sets forth a plan that—</text> <subclause id="H6EBB25F639B241A2B641F383051125B0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>meets the requirements of subparagraph (A)(i); and</text> </subclause>
<subclause id="H3A16206C420742B284D06742330FEF3D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>provides for the applicant to—</text> <item id="H0E79B5328CEF4AF3A1FC931BB533EF19"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>conduct a rigorous evaluation of the implementation of the plan;</text> </item>
<item id="H6555CEEBE1764B03AC52E52EFFDD7177"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>submit the results of the evaluation to the Secretary; and</text> </item> <item id="H10E52031B4154D21A590AA1EA09B7385"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>make the results available to the general public.</text> </item></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HA3CA50A1E4B44F4DBAC34604BC8A8AF9"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Eligible applicants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In clause (i), the term <term>eligible applicant</term> means, with respect to an application, a public or nonprofit organization that—</text> <subclause id="H23E0B21DD0E0444E812404CB40AE18D3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>has not submitted an application pursuant to subparagraph (A);</text> </subclause>
<subclause id="H449FAF3D982D447AB9AFD508DE6E65A9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is not participating in a collaboration described in such an application; and</text> </subclause> <subclause id="H5E1AE579DD6D4849B9C3341F31FE1F4F"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is located in an eligible State (as defined in subparagraph (A)(iii)) with respect to the application.</text> </subclause></clause>
<clause id="HABFBCBB7518B42EDA1DB949924F58EBF"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Approval; disapproval</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subparagraph (A)(v) shall apply to an application submitted by an eligible applicant pursuant to this subparagraph.</text> </clause> <clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAABCD9D781F749A99F91A1FEE4A7042E"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Grant authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall make grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible applicants whose applications are approved under clause (iii).</text> </clause>
<clause id="H4468B8DBEC854CDB845AA3937FB64109"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Subparagraph (A)(vii) shall apply with respect to a grant made under this subparagraph.</text> </clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9885BAA43D9A40278A88CF76C2C7872B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limitation on use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Funds made available to carry out this section shall be used to supplement, and not supplant, the Federal, State, and local, or tribal, funds that, in the absence of such availability, would be expended to provide services to individuals receiving assistance under a State or tribal program funded under this part or in support of workforce development activities (as defined in section 3(65) of the WIOA).</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H62FBFC5870D745A98FFE99FD4E1206D5"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Appropriation</header><text>Out of funds in the Treasury of the United States not otherwise appropriated, there are appropriated to carry out this paragraph $1,000,000,000 for each fiscal year, of which—</text> <clause id="H03B4E4D9DE10481ABAE0179FEE1DE58B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>90 percent shall be available for grants under subparagraph (A); and</text> </clause>
<clause id="H6C1D5983CA1A45A5B576681EFCDE524D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>10 percent shall be available for grants under subparagraph (B).</text> </clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF0394FE2F302457E8128E51F312913B7"><enum>(E)</enum><header>WIOA defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this paragraph, the term <term>WIOA</term> means the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection>
<subsection id="H573EC8453AC14B5CB4DCFC30F9828DC6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exemption from limitation on payments to territories</header><text>Section 1108(a)(2) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1308">42 U.S.C. 1308(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>403(a)(6),</quote> before <quote>406</quote>.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="H1B4097F8C2AC4FD8B368367B150DBD7E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on October 1, 2018.</text> </subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


