<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H4B556F9436E64441A3570B6055B11DB6" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5093 IH: Measuring the Economic Impact of Broadband Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5093</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180226">February 26, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001106">Mr. Costello of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Commerce to conduct an assessment and analysis of the effects of
			 broadband deployment and adoption on the economy of the United States, and
			 for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H23B6C64F10EA4650AA14D578DD3904E8" style="OLC">
 <section id="HC4287C98043645448B2FBD2C27A1CC18" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Measuring the Economic Impact of Broadband Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H1A4B7352C6194AC484529EF6141BD99E" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Assessment and analysis of the effects of broadband deployment and adoption on economy of the United States</header> <subsection id="H250D4C7BD449423D86267C180D00AED2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Broadband defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>broadband</term> means an Internet Protocol-based transmission service that enables users to send and receive voice, video, data, or graphics, or a combination of those items.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HCAEB12AA4A68497FB1AD2887B936D45E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Assessment and analysis required</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce shall, acting through the Director of the Bureau of Economic Analysis, conduct an assessment and analysis of the effects of broadband deployment and adoption on the economy of the United States.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD7EB2068DAE841A4A153635668178662"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In conducting the assessment and analysis required by subsection (b), the Secretary shall consider matters relating to employment, including job creation, business headcount, online commerce, income, education and distance learning, telehealth, telework, agriculture, population growth, population density, broadband speed, and geography.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H6F3192484CC44D60BAA21028189CB539"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In conducting the assessment and analysis required by subsection (b), the Secretary shall consult with—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE03FA1B9181B4F32941289EFE3D80FC4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the heads of such agencies and offices of the Federal Government as the Secretary considers appropriate, including the Secretary of Agriculture, the Director of the Bureau of the Census, the Commissioner of the Bureau of Labor Statistics, the Administrator of the Small Business Administration, and the Federal Communications Commission;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD7BE8CAF89C8496BB5A6447D91B93BD4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>representatives of businesses, including rural and urban internet service providers and telecommunications infrastructure providers;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4E841F10395840378F333FDEE38389B7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>representatives from State, local, and tribal government agencies; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB5D81CEBEF56464580DE0C0E809B2D99"><enum>(4)</enum><text>representatives from consumer and community organizations.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0831D892BE82473DAFA7F8A8F1729E47"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header>
 <paragraph id="H1489D2E91CCD451AABE560830F1A3D71"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Commerce shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the findings of the Secretary with respect to the assessment and analysis conducted under subsection (b).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCA06118882194919B473970973120544"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H1D570209F82F472E80AD4AD33D615B5A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDAC5C76FE0B248D99DECDF1C242A71DE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16AE2A944D1B4302B87B231D5667EAEF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Committee on Small Business and Entrepreneurship of the Senate;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C16761C67A5451EB02523327E8F4D5C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H76D2E676D7C0419A839BCBFF035A861F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4626C6DF951C4AD88D6B0C3A2C3168D7"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Committee on Small Business of the House of Representatives.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

