<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H30644B83D8184FBE877D2F89C47728C3" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5254 IH: To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services to conduct a study on the feasibility of expanding eligibility for enrollment in Medicare Advantage plans to individuals enrolled under the Medicaid program or enrolled under a group health plan.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5254</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180313">March 13, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001305">Mr. Budd</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services to conduct a study on the feasibility of
			 expanding eligibility for enrollment in Medicare Advantage plans to
			 individuals enrolled under the Medicaid program or enrolled under a group
			 health plan.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HA823D8EACC2B481A89EB522B72F7A431" style="OLC">
 <section id="H9A4EFFEE39B5495CAB02F23B735247E3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Study of expansion of Medicare Advantage eligibility</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than December 31, 2020, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall conduct a study and submit to Congress a report on the feasibility of expanding eligibility for enrollment in Medicare Advantage plans offered under part C of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-21">42 U.S.C. 1395w–21</external-xref> et seq.) to individuals enrolled under a State plan (or a waiver of such plan) under title XIX of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396</external-xref> et seq.) or enrolled in a group health plan (as defined in section 2791 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-91">42 U.S.C. 300gg–91</external-xref>)). Such report shall include an analysis of whether such an expansion—</text>
 <paragraph id="HF79E2EE2D16F4467A05A7CEE8AA21DB7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>would increase access to health care for such individuals; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HCF0F2450CA064506B40E95ED8722355C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>lead to lower health care costs for such individuals.</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


