<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HBB63E38BF2654BAA87084058924F26DE" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5749 IH: Options Markets Stability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5749</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180510">May 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001059">Mr. Hultgren</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the appropriate Federal banking agencies to increase the risk-sensitivity of the capital
			 treatment of certain centrally cleared options, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HB135915A05E54C428AFD8500EA7A54F8" style="OLC">
 <section id="H651A0EDD3BA443348D967F907719D99C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Options Markets Stability Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H6F4675E613644BBB98DA11EF3D8AAF02"><enum>2.</enum><header>Credit exposure for guarantees of centrally cleared options</header> <subsection id="H3CB7FB88DA2A4B41BFA4E4DC3A998D05"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the terms <quote>affiliate</quote>, <quote>appropriate Federal banking agency</quote>, <quote>depository institution</quote>, and <quote>depository institution holding company</quote> have the meanings given those terms, respectively, in section 3 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813</external-xref>).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H685A0417631E438686D1A7AB85EAE429"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Treatment of certain centrally cleared option derivatives exposures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of calculating the counterparty credit risk exposure of a depository institution, depository institution holding company, or affiliate thereof, to a client arising from a guarantee provided by the depository institution, depository institution holding company, or affiliate thereof to a central counterparty in respect of the client’s performance under a derivative contract cleared through that central counterparty pursuant to the risk-based and leverage-based capital rules applicable to depository institutions and depository institution holding companies under parts 3, 217, and 324 of title 12, Code of Federal Regulations, the term <quote>effective notional principal amount</quote> with respect to such centrally cleared derivative contract means the hypothetical on-balance sheet position in the underlying asset that would evidence the same change in fair value (measured in dollars) given a small change in the price of the underlying asset.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE36E1F2F8A2A4E34A75104FADCD9B9EB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Calculation of exposure for centrally cleared derivatives</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of calculating the counterparty credit risk exposure of a depository institution, depository institution holding company, or affiliate thereof to a client arising from a guarantee provided by the depository institution, depository institution holding company, or affiliate thereof to a central counterparty in respect of the client’s performance under a derivative contract cleared through that central counterparty pursuant to the risk-based and leverage-based capital rules applicable to depository institutions and depository institution holding companies under parts 3, 217 and 324 of title 12, Code of Federal Regulations, the offsetting nature of significantly and reliably correlated positions within a netting set must be reflected in a manner consistent with the risk offsets provided by the central counterparty.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


