<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H50EF4F4B9D12490F8B6DA6D774A5FDFA" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5218 IH: DUI Reporting Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5218</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180308">March 8, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C000266">Mr. Chabot</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001106">Mr. Costello of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001107">Mr. Curbelo of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000388">Mr. Kelly of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000580">Ms. Michelle Lujan Grisham of New Mexico</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001179">Mr. Marino</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001180">Mr. McKinley</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 23, United States Code, with respect to national priority safety programs, and for
			 other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H38A1C3AD81834324B12023805BEEA7AF" style="OLC">
 <section commented="no" id="H7D4D104D225A4B218EAEBA703AE39C00" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>DUI Reporting Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HD91822C120DF4C62A106F6671CA49B44"><enum>2.</enum><header>Impaired driving countermeasures</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 405(d) of title 23, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE5E85587314C46C2AFF944F75EC2D701" style="USC">
				<paragraph id="H67279C3825B0458DA1473C7D7D583F2E"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Special rules relating to DUI reporting</header>
 <subparagraph id="H342B86693CB547059D5049EA23518F64"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this subsection, the Secretary shall withhold from a State, in accordance with this paragraph, each grant under this subsection for a fiscal year if the State does not appear on the most recent list provided to the Secretary under subparagraph (B)(ii)(I).</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B97D459426848E59C50F9262417BD17"><enum>(B)</enum><header>List</header>
 <clause id="H05B7BA07EDD44B6B8DDBAD7BA3A141B4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>The Attorney General shall provide to the Secretary a list identifying each State that, in the determination of the Attorney General, is ensuring, through law or policy, that all State and local law enforcement agencies in that State are appropriately reporting covered arrests to the appropriate Federal repository (which the Attorney General may determine to be the National Crime Information Center or the Next Generation Identification system).</text>
 </clause><clause id="H927BA82E50BC47FCAE8AF9E64F0AF9C4"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>Each year, the Attorney General shall provide the list required under clause (i)—</text> <subclause id="H82FE7534322E4BBB879722E8B7E3FB0A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>during the 30-day period ending on September 30; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H464AD423ABBA4626BED967D5773EE4B4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>on the date that is 90 days after the date on which the list is provided pursuant to subclause (I).</text> </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H099568AB3E51402EBF53C6D27BDFBCF6"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Availability to the public</header><text>The Attorney General shall make available to the public on an appropriate Federal website each list provided to the Secretary under this subparagraph.</text>
						</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB1FA46D210D84AA6A3FEF5B7AEB579D4"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Withholding</header>
 <clause id="HE8440B1ABA274FB4A8BFD85C8282C2C4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall withhold grants under subparagraph (A) in accordance with the following:</text> <subclause id="HE3D1651FD809404EAF7885CA1F96CB7B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>If the applicable State is subject to withholding under subparagraph (A) for the first time, the Secretary shall withhold 25 percent of the amount of the grant that would otherwise be made available to the State.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H10ED9D1132AB47A8AA6F73FF34136F6F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>If the applicable State is subject to withholding under subparagraph (A) for the second time, the Secretary shall withhold 50 percent of the amount of the grant that would otherwise be made available to the State.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H194B3202174B4A5EA2F8C630F4C172A5"><enum>(III)</enum><text>If the applicable State is subject to withholding under subparagraph (A) for the third time (or more), the Secretary shall withhold 100 percent of the amount of the grant that would otherwise be made available to the State.</text>
							</subclause></clause><clause id="H25ED3DFD55C0466B8C2F11A55AAFECBE"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>First year warnings</header>
 <subclause id="H7F4DBCDB09504E9BA09EAA2B9BAC5861"><enum>(I)</enum><header>No withholding</header><text>During the first fiscal year with respect to which the Secretary may withhold grant amounts under subparagraph (A), the Secretary, notwithstanding such subparagraph, shall not withhold any grant amounts from any State under such subparagraph.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H1123D17BB7F946A19958641BF103FE8A"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Warnings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall notify each State that would have been subject to withholding under subparagraph (A), if not for this clause, and such notice shall not be treated as a withholding for purposes of clause (i) of this subparagraph.</text>
							</subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5ED27A112B304F908091907A1C5A47A3"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Availability of withheld amounts</header>
 <clause id="HD6554695E4E941E5893AE83F8CBD7CC1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Amounts withheld from a State under subparagraph (A) shall remain available to be provided to the State until the end of the 90-day period beginning on the date of the withholding.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1AFCF4C27B68477F92E11B7F7E3F0129"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Return to compliance</header><text>At the end of a 90-day period described in clause (i), if the applicable State appears on the most recent list provided under subparagraph (B)(ii)(II), amounts withheld from the State shall be provided to the State.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HEB1528D67C7B45038F4BEC664979D04A"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Continued noncompliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the end of a 90-day period described in clause (i), if the applicable State does not appear on the most recent list provided under subparagraph (B)(ii)(II), amounts withheld from the State shall be reallocated consistent with subsection (a)(8).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H363505E436F740BE929FF691DF4F2DDC"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Use of grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this subsection, a State that receives a grant under this subsection may use grant amounts for costs associated with reporting covered arrests.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H49D9D74E0A95440989FF31C97E28F22D"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Covered arrests defined</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>covered arrests</term> means arrests for offenses involving driving under the influence of, or while intoxicated by, alcohol or drugs.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H060FD2129856410EA17F1ADBB86DE807"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>This paragraph shall apply to the second fiscal year beginning after the date of enactment of this paragraph and each fiscal year thereafter.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


