<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H24DA3BEC4E0F40278B6529BECD601F50" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4816 IH: Stop Civil Asset Forfeiture Funding for Marijuana Suppression Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4816</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180117">January 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Ted Lieu of California</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="A000367">Mr. Amash</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000598">Mr. Polis</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 28, United States Code, to prohibit the use of amounts from the Asset Forfeiture Fund for the Domestic Cannabis Suppression/Eradication Program of the Drug Enforcement Administration, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE4C9B364039B4434B350AB65E02FFD76" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H47359F1947D8469C83CBD9CA6BD16DCA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop Civil Asset Forfeiture Funding for Marijuana Suppression Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H3D5B6E88B1F843CDA797B38D927B6B2B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Restriction on use of the Asset Forfeiture Fund for the Domestic Cannabis Suppression/Eradication Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 524 of title 28, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA328E3ABCADC4332845F526C039981C8" style="USC"> 
<subsection id="H2275EBE9E1DF4F4CB8AB062F02282E38"><enum>(e)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subsection (c) of this section, beginning in fiscal year 2019, and for each fiscal year thereafter, no amounts in the Fund may be used for the Domestic Cannabis Suppression/Eradication Program of the Drug Enforcement Administration, or any substantially similar program.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section commented="no" id="H8BDA5EE0888F49708EC7E5ECF30B252A"><enum>3.</enum><header>No authority to transfer property for purposes of the Domestic Cannabis Suppression/Eradication Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 981(e) of title 18, United States Code, no property may be transferred to a Federal agency or a State and local agency, if that property is used for any purpose pertaining to the Domestic Cannabis Suppression/Eradication Program of the Drug Enforcement Administration, or any substantially similar program.</text></section> 
<section id="H0F8DD6D4FECC4B9FAA18F6ED2E118D76"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) expends a large amount of resources on enforcing prohibitions on marijuana. The comments of former DEA Administrator Chuck Rosenberg about the relative harm of marijuana support Congress’s belief that the DEA’s marijuana prohibition policy is an inappropriate use of resources.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

