<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H0EAFB831A7E346EE998E294F4E16F238" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5793 IH: Housing Choice Voucher Mobility Demonstration Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5793</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180515">May 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000614">Mr. Duffy</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development to carry out a housing choice voucher
			 mobility demonstration to encourage families receiving such voucher
			 assistance to move to lower-poverty areas and expand access to opportunity
			 areas.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H5E0C58C5334F4F13AE685E81D8927E6C" style="OLC">
 <section id="H0570950A21424E408C5EA597C2AFB5AB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Housing Choice Voucher Mobility Demonstration Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H2C22EA5166354197B1CC5F679DE95F27"><enum>2.</enum><header>Housing choice voucher mobility demonstration</header> <subsection id="HA4D065B30768472BBDBC260DF86C7E99"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) may carry out a mobility demonstration program to enable public housing agencies to administer housing choice voucher assistance under section 8(o) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)</external-xref>) in a manner designed to encourage families receiving such voucher assistance to move to lower-poverty areas and expand access to opportunity areas.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H83CE2BF125F5494D8265AF1C1EF76069"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Selection of PHAs</header>
 <paragraph id="H50CC6586E2DE45A1A20AF76220D08800"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish requirements for public housing agencies to participate in the demonstration program under this section, which shall provide that the following public housing agencies may participate:</text>
 <subparagraph id="HDCDF1C7DDC874A898908DB474CADB72D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Public housing agencies that together—</text> <clause id="H7E8AF40B89FD480CBA409E40867D92D1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>serve areas with high concentrations of holders of rental assistance vouchers under section 8(o) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)</external-xref>) in poor, low-opportunity neighborhoods; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H71B3182D30B6490D861EA19E88A2A563"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>have an adequate number of moderately priced rental units in higher-opportunity areas.</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6D3FC51C13847C9AE06C8F3999FF428"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Planned consortia or partial consortia of public housing agencies that—</text>
 <clause id="HD82118B0F8A341449A9B7B8FA9F205AF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>include at least one agency with a high-performing Family Self-Sufficiency (FSS) program; and</text> </clause><clause id="H4F7BF519D5924547A3B0A32F7D2F32AD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>will enable participating families to continue in such program if they relocate to the jurisdiction served by any other agency of the consortium.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A0154298BB148259CD863615647608D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Planned consortia or partial consortia of public housing agencies that—</text> <clause id="H298EAD9F5B594B159D571A26BE708543"><enum>(i)</enum><text>serve jurisdictions within a single region;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H80AB40182D684E8981B114E0F744E4C4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>include one or more small agencies; and</text> </clause><clause id="HBE19D607B6B94BBBAF839CF2F71DA18A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>will consolidate mobility focused operations.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16BAC396A2EC4C548D542A62C9E7D88C"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such other public housing agencies as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H20F08B99F5E745D8B201388A1D3D519D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection criteria</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish competitive selection criteria for public housing agencies eligible under paragraph (1) to participate in the demonstration program under this section.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6B80FBF33C094143AFC1B8826CA97A11"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Random selection of families</header><text>The Secretary may require participating agencies to use a randomized selection process to select among the families eligible to receive mobility assistance under the demonstration program.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC2EDD9FD5E0442E89D3E859E28511B01"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regional housing mobility plan</header><text>The Secretary shall require each public housing agency applying to participate in the demonstration program under this section to submit a Regional Housing Mobility Plan (in this section referred to as a <quote>Plan</quote>), which shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H2BC1F0CEC6964E8DAF0A842B243205F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify the public housing agencies that will participate under the Plan and the number of vouchers each participating agency will make available out of their existing programs in connection with the demonstration;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9D60CDE3A7914F70B59F95438E62E50B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify any community-based organizations, nonprofit organizations, businesses, and other entities that will participate under the Plan and describe the commitments for such participation made by each such entity;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8C52A6A3380A4841BA2C561C8DE87206"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify any waivers or alternative requirements requested for the execution of the Plan;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H2FBBFDBB970D4E39AE9D14AD2178E2A6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identify any specific actions that the public housing agencies and other entities will undertake to accomplish the goals of the demonstration, which shall include a comprehensive approach to enable a successful transition to opportunity areas and may include counseling and continued support for families;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5E78CAC0A6204BCCA5910DBC9AC1FADC"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">specify the criteria that the public housing agencies would use to identify opportunity areas under the plan;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB6E02251B97246FCB053E1DCE19E16E9"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide for establishment of priority and preferences for participating families, including a preference for families with young children, as such term is defined by the Secretary, based on regional housing needs and priorities; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5F47AC7397154311866B312B38581627"><enum>(7)</enum><text>comply with any other requirements established by the Secretary.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0B03FA0C9AFB4DC8B6583AE5F00B188F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Funding for Mobility-Related Services</header> <paragraph id="H8622D06B4B6A4A46AFE5617A50BD9817"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Use of administrative fees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Public housing agencies participating in the demonstration program under this section may use administrative fees under section 8(q) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(q)</external-xref>), their administrative fee reserves, and funding from private entities to provide mobility-related services in connection with the demonstration program, including services such as counseling, portability coordination, landlord outreach, security deposits, and administrative activities associated with establishing and operating regional mobility programs.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE6DCBC04113C49898E5B7451753F0EB1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of housing assistance funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Public housing agencies participating in the demonstration under this section may use housing assistance payments funds under section 8(o) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)</external-xref>) for security deposits if necessary to enable families to lease units with vouchers in designated opportunity areas.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4824B74A22424BE99D3337185E84308A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Waivers; alternative requirements</header>
 <paragraph id="H80BE660B0D0B4FC7AFAE991F17BE1CC2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Waivers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To allow for public housing agencies to implement and administer their Regional Housing Mobility Plans, the Secretary may waive or specify alternative requirements for the following provisions of the United States Housing Act of 1937:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H7431141F87C043C1851C833868FCFC88"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sections 8(o)(7)(A) and 8(o)(13)(E)(i) (relating to the term of a lease and mobility requirements).</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDCF45184708D411CA8CBC777BB7F063A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 8(o)(13)(C)(i) (relating to the public housing plan for an agency).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5458FD3CA7B147ECA7E3ACB23AD65089"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Section 8(r)(2) (relating to the responsibility of a public housing agency to administer ported assistance).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C79DD012B6847D0846C33A262727E50"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Alternative Requirements</header><text>The Secretary shall provide additional authority for public housing agencies in a selected region to form a consortium that has a single housing choice voucher funding contract, or to enter into a partial consortium to operate all or portions of the Regional Housing Mobility Plan, including agencies participating in the Moving To Work Demonstration program.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA6EC24ACA8234BD7922EC361BE849601"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>Any waiver or alternative requirements pursuant to this subsection shall not take effect before the expiration of the 10-day period beginning upon publication of notice of such waiver or alternative requirement in the Federal Register.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE54DA89A40404D48803246CCBCC74BD0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The Secretary may implement the demonstration, including its terms, procedures, requirements, and conditions, by notice.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H19BCBA5B5A7149239D11E318CC8E9A7E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than five years after implementation of the regional housing mobility programs under the demonstration program under this section, the Secretary shall submit to the Congress and publish in the Federal Register a report evaluating the effectiveness of the strategies pursued under the demonstration, subject to the availability of funding to conduct the evaluation. Through official websites and other methods, the Secretary shall disseminate interim findings as they become available, and shall, if promising strategies are identified, notify the Congress of the amount of funds that would be required to expand the testing of these strategies in additional types of public housing agencies and housing markets.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


