<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H177687C654374CEA82F1C92F496DA0B5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5845 IH: No Couches for Congress Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5845</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20180516">May 16, 2018</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000455">Ms. Fudge</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001200">Mr. McEachin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000537">Mr. Clyburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000627">Mrs. Demings</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001270">Ms. Bass</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000581">Mrs. Lawrence</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000324">Mr. Hastings</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000126">Ms. Eddie Bernice Johnson of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000984">Mr. Cummings</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001049">Mr. Clay</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Al Green of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HSO00">Ethics</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To prohibit Members of the House of Representatives from using their congressional offices for personal overnight accommodations and to amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to allow a deduction for living expenses incurred by Members of the House of Representatives, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H8F63BB140EEF4818843E9B6DEA5C0484" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF9D064E9A3B34C1AB38BFEE4E91E28C2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Couches for Congress Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H152C7D2FA46E4879AB7894C386D352FB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibiting Members of the House of Representatives from using offices for personal overnight accommodations; requiring Ethics Committee to respond to complaints filed by Members</header> <subsection id="H564CA23075894387840882E6837C2F42"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibiting Members from using offices for personal overnight accommodations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Rule XXIII of the Rules of the House of Representatives is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H43392F0699224D6894331957374EF1A2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating clause 18 as clause 19; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H31FABDC7CC6145F79EDCBAAE18FE0640"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after clause 17 the following new clause:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD33F915E6D034A29B08B0300FB341862" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<rules-clause id="HE625E34CC78B46CB916678DA09AC6CEB"><enum>18.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Member, Delegate, or Resident Commissioner may not use the Member’s, Delegate’s, or Resident Commissioner’s office for personal overnight accommodations, and may not use official resources of the House, including employees of the House, to support the use of such office for such purpose.</text></rules-clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEB2423836F854D1F87BCBB0F9C816D02"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requiring House Ethics Committee To respond to complaints filed by Members</header><text>Clause 3(b)(2) of rule XI of the Rules of the House of Representatives is amended by striking the period at the end of the first sentence in the matter following subdivision (C) and inserting the following: <quote>, and, in the case of a complaint from a Member, Delegate, or Resident Commissioner, shall promptly transmit to such Member, Delegate, or Resident Commissioner a written response containing an explanation for the delay in disposing of the complaint and the results of any investigation of the complaint.</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA4EFA52ECB274129BDDADF9F184E9F79"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exercise of rulemaking powers</header><text>The provisions of this section are enacted—</text> <paragraph id="H17D86E46984A430498EAB7DEFC21B804"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as an exercise of the rulemaking power of the House of Representatives, and as such they shall be considered as part of the rules of the House, and such rules shall supersede other rules only to the extent that they are inconsistent therewith; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H699CFD0667914907A0DB4909EC45E350"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with full recognition of the constitutional right of the House of Representatives to change such rules (so far as relating to the House) at any time, in the same manner, and to the same extent as in the case of any other rule of the House.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H02D9D799E2CD480EA35BB4FA18CEB1E1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Reinstating limited deduction for living expenses incurred by Members of the House of Representatives</header> <subsection id="H06196D50C7034D7C8148B0D097E79F3A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The second sentence of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/162">section 162(a)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting after <quote>for income tax purposes</quote> the following: <quote>in any amount in the case of a Senator or in excess of $3,000 in the case of a Member of the House of Representatives or a Delegate or Resident Commissioner to the Congress</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0874A11C78C648E2A8F0A17B4887A7C8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inflation adjustment</header><text>Section 162 of such Code is amended by redesignating subsection (s) as subsection (t) and by inserting after subsection (r) the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H86DF5B364CFE400AA9BF97C040D74C63" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H4E9E9C79BCF242FDA01D12F1FFE2EE12"><enum>(s)</enum><header>Inflation adjustment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a taxable year beginning after 2018, the $3,000 amount in subsection (a) shall be increased by an amount equal to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2539D32BF5F04BE0B167CE345B7065A8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such dollar amount, multiplied by</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8BC8EE848EB749D8BBDD83B2E35D89D1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the cost-of-living adjustment determined under section 1(f)(3) for the calendar year in which the taxable year begins, determined by substituting <quote>calendar year 1954</quote> for <quote>calendar year 2016</quote> in subparagraph (A)(ii) thereof.</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">If any amount as adjusted under paragraph (1) is not a multiple of $50, such amount shall be rounded to the next lowest multiple of $50.</continuation-text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H510285A421314B6791B0837D0A7D72C6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after December 31, 2018.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

