<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HD4BD8CBC29EB4C72A0D8E8DFB67A566B" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5890 IH: Assisting States’ Implementation of Plans of Safe Care Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5890</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180521">May 21, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000580">Mr. Garrett</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001202">Mrs. Murphy of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Health and Human Services to provide assistance to States in complying
			 with, and implementing, certain provisions of section 106 of the Child
			 Abuse Prevention and Treatment Act in order to promote better protections
			 for young children and family-centered responses, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H6BD1D25478894B8DA9CD9F505BA04AAD" style="OLC">
 <section id="H7521778A7B0F4706BB0B7ED5C017C1B4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Assisting States’ Implementation of Plans of Safe Care Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H8D4F915C8F4D48889119F87B338F5450"><enum>2.</enum><header>Assisting States with implementation of plans of safe care</header> <subsection id="H93B396B1DB8640ABB13F60606B329435"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall provide written guidance and, if appropriate, technical assistance to support States in complying with, and implementing, subsections (b)(2)(B)(iii) and (d)(18) of section 106 of the Child Abuse Prevention and Treatment Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5106a">42 U.S.C. 5106a</external-xref>) in order to promote better protections for young children and family-centered responses.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HAA213EB6B8F346C594184AB2202E8139"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The guidance and technical assistance shall—</text> <paragraph id="H74B5D5AC7E304CCE813D38F417159B66"><enum>(1)</enum><text>enhance States’ understanding of requirements and flexibilities under the law, including clarifying key terms;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H32124DEAB7924AA39EF82A7BFBB135B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>address State-identified challenges with developing, implementing, and monitoring plans of safe care;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H00685AB3BE3B4BD29B43C4BA94B69B36"><enum>(3)</enum><text>disseminate best practices related to developing and implementing plans of safe care, including differential response, collaboration and coordination, and identification and delivery of services, while recognizing needs of different populations and varying community approaches across States;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H656F5ED8836B488FB90DAA068FC7C084"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support collaboration between health care providers, social service agencies, public health agencies, and the child welfare system, to promote a family-centered treatment approach;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5801F51F8F9A4F4F881EFA12031DE45C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>prevent separation and support reunification of families if in the best interests of the child;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB94B8E4DB7D94C879A6C660F5CA9A633"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommend treatment approaches for serving infants, pregnant women, and postpartum women whose infants may be affected by substance use that are designed to keep infants with their mothers and families whenever appropriate, including recommendations to encourage pregnant women to receive health and other support services during pregnancy;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H99095C47E6094E5D9383C84AE956F60B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>support State efforts to develop technology systems to manage and monitor implementation of plans of safe care; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1AADF1EBEF874A14B180A1062BF2715D"><enum>(8)</enum><text>help States improve the long-term safety and well-being of young children and their families.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H440F9B6325704986B79E46A2C238FB90"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>The guidance and technical assistance shall not be construed to amend the requirements of the Child Abuse Prevention and Treatment Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5101">42 U.S.C. 5101</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H7275A382A8994D7984CBF3414DE02793"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <quote>State</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Child Abuse Prevention and Treatment Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5101">42 U.S.C. 5101</external-xref> note).</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


