<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H51F4293C579A46BE973F71C0588A72C0" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5709 IH: Preventing Illegal Radio Abuse Through Enforcement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5709</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180508">May 8, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000567">Mr. Lance</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001092">Mr. Collins of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000410">Mr. Gene Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000461">Mr. Flores</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000210">Mr. King of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000087">Mrs. Carolyn B. Maloney of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000464">Mr. Faso</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000602">Miss Rice of New York</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001185">Mr. Sean Patrick Maloney of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Communications Act of 1934 to provide for enhanced penalties for pirate radio, and for
			 other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H1011410A88194022B9D1E5DD23BE7AE8" style="OLC">
 <section id="H677209B539FE413D9FAB4A7DA5758C8E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Preventing Illegal Radio Abuse Through Enforcement Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PIRATE Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H5147D271571645D8BCF67E51D762BE01"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pirate Radio Enforcement Enhancements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title V of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/501">47 U.S.C. 501</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H537601D060A84DA4B9F22B79C0C4F08C" style="OLC">
				<section id="H29D69ED48F71444BBB1BFE58FCF938B3"><enum>511.</enum><header>Enhanced penalties for pirate radio broadcasting; seizure of illegal equipment; enforcement sweeps</header>
 <subsection id="H2E4EFA47109D4BB4B80058E813470440"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Increased general penalty</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who willfully and knowingly does or causes or suffers to be done any pirate radio broadcasting shall be subject to a fine of not more than $2,000,000.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H56AC1B9159C846529EF02E5AA3D74051"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Violation of this Act, rules, or regulations</header><text>Any person who willfully and knowingly violates this Act or any rule, regulation, restriction, or condition made or imposed by the Commission under authority of this Act, or any rule, regulation, restriction, or condition made or imposed by any international radio or wire communications treaty or convention, or regulations annexed thereto, to which the United States is or may hereafter become party, relating to pirate radio broadcasting shall, in addition to any other penalties provided by law, be subject to a fine of not more than $100,000 for each day during which such offense occurs, in accordance with the limit described in subsection (a).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H8358F64097744A63987AB874F43D3230"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Live pirate radio broadcasting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 503(b)(4) does not apply for a forfeiture penalty imposed on a person if the Commission has direct evidence that the person is responsible for a pirate radio broadcast and such broadcast is occurring in real time.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HDAE40753E3B54E2189FA2B5BDC1B3ACF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Facilitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who knowingly and intentionally facilitates pirate radio broadcasting shall be subject to a fine of not more than $2,000,000.</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="H175337170D924079B4594B9A632D776E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Enforcement sweeps</header>
 <paragraph id="H6EEE3CEF1444499F8D09F3DA76953BBF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Biannual sweeps</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less than twice each year, the Commission shall assign appropriate enforcement personal to focus specific and sustained attention on the elimination of pirate radio broadcasting within the top five radio markets identified as prevalent for such broadcasts. Such effort shall include identifying, locating, and terminating such operations and seizing related equipment under subsection (e).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE98CDC3BE93C43CCAD30B37586ED70CB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No effect on remaining enforcement</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (1), the Commission shall not decrease or diminish the regular enforcement efforts targeted to pirate radio broadcast stations for other times of the year.</text>
						</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCB489919238F45DFBBD2BE80953442FF"><enum>(f)</enum><header>State and local government authority</header>
 <paragraph id="HD7F4B0BF29774F93BA1D857368557E3E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Statutes or ordinances permitted</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State or local government may enact a statute or ordinance that imposes civil or criminal penalties for pirate radio broadcasting, or for knowingly and intentionally facilitating pirate radio broadcasting, provided that the determination whether a radio station is engaged in pirate radio broadcasting shall be made exclusively by the Commission.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H925F1A7CC53541BD843D6CECD35B0E46"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commission authority preserved</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Enforcement by a State or local government of a statute or ordinance under this section shall not preclude the Commission or Federal law enforcement authority from concurrently enforcing this section and section 301 of this Act, any other Federal law, or any regulation of the Commission thereunder.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE6F9AC24C063426A9DB1EFFC0D00D1EF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HBF44DA43BE8C44808E9FE505276C4B28"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Pirate radio broadcasting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>pirate radio broadcasting</term> means the transmission of communications on spectrum frequencies between 535 to 1705 kHz or 87.7 to 108 MHz without a license issued by the Federal Communications Commission, but does not include unlicensed operations in compliance with part 15 of title 47, Code of Federal Regulations.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCF088AF478F04999940CD45DC75B8026"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Facilitates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>facilitates</term> means providing access to property (and improvements thereon) or providing physical goods or services, including providing housing, facilities, or financing, that directly aid pirate radio broadcasting.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HB73072C588434AE588B449D87F78D12C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Knowingly and intentionally</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>knowingly and intentionally</term> means the person was previously served by the Commission with a notice of unlicensed operations, notice of apparent liability, or citation for efforts to facilitate pirate radio broadcasting.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


