<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H62203BA87ABF46F688BEC6C36F4B79AB" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5582 IH: Abuse Deterrent Access Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5582</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180423">April 23, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000565">Mr. Loebsack</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000585">Mr. Reed</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services to conduct a study and submit a report on
			 barriers to accessing abuse-deterrent opioid formulations for individuals
			 enrolled in a plan under part C or D of the Medicare program.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H80C7E57FBBBA4C60A57B2E2B916EC68A" style="OLC">
 <section id="HB7925A3BA17142C2B910CE4D7E4C4FB2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited at the <quote><short-title>Abuse Deterrent Access Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HE57E5A74DF144D62BB9BC6E470AE120D" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study on abuse-deterrent opioid formulations access barriers under Medicare</header> <subsection id="H29BB03A0A2864D39A3705A8F9B345DC9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall conduct a study and submit to Congress a report on the adequacy of access to abuse-deterrent opioid formulations for individuals with chronic pain enrolled in an MA–PD plan under part C of title XVIII of the Social Security Act or a prescription drug plan under part D of such title of such Act, taking into account any barriers preventing such individuals from accessing such formulations under such MA–PD or part D plans, such as cost-sharing tiers, fail-first requirements, and prior authorization requirements.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HC57F75CB01F547A4AC6848FA4110C886"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition of abuse-deterrent opioid formulation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>abuse-deterrent opioid formulation</quote> means an opioid with certain abuse-deterrent properties, such as physical or chemical barriers, agonist or antagonist combinations, aversion properties, delivery system mechanisms, or other features designed to prevent abuse of such opioid.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


