<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA2BF92671CBA4D278949FD222B29A027" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5822 IH: Executive Cyberspace Coordination Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5822</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180515">May 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000559">Mr. Langevin</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Ted Lieu of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000588">Mr. Richmond</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001064">Mr. Heck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000515">Mr. Rush</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a National Office for Cyberspace, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H414A27833D084C6D8C40C06D1034688D" style="OLC">
 <section id="HE54E832E083844079041876C3878032E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Executive Cyberspace Coordination Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H496E7C0F426E44789D359B9016B72CEF" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Office for Cyberspace</header> <subsection id="H469E97F27BE84433947A9978DCB2E0A9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Coordination of Federal information policy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/35">chapter 35</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code, is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H6979834D256F49299309F0999A822625"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 3552(b), by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0C69E4119DAA4D86BDF6114AA3484AFE" style="USC"> <paragraph commented="no" id="H1A4FA9E4DDCA45F0A39DF70D655210F3"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the National Office for Cyberspace.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA11599E7E2E742049D25218D76F68AB1"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The term <term>information infrastructure</term> means the underlying framework that information systems and assets rely on in processing, storing, or transmitting information electronically.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H747FE316B33F40888730543CCCB21896"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 3553(a)—</text> <subparagraph id="H25A3AEC79A4D4E949945AC41E698A602"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB667B5E7FAB541CAB8E66628A657C442"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H087F32F29D384EAAAE81A109BDB573B7"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after paragraph (6) the following new paragraphs:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCDA4861E74324E8BAC441E8F40FEBC1E" style="USC">
 <paragraph commented="no" id="H3606045E6A1B48C88734CF600025E34A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>reviewing at least annually, and approving or disapproving, agency information security programs required under section 3554(b);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H6EE38484A794443982B2982818C136D8"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinating the defense of information infrastructure operated by agencies in the case of a large-scale attack on information infrastructure, as determined by the Director;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HEDF1D26716A54B75AE79E608F01AD006"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinating information security training for Federal employees with the Director of the Office of Personnel Management;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H0C3364F1CE054BFBAA714DD93F537E30"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensuring the adequacy of protections for privacy and civil liberties in carrying out the responsibilities of the Director under this subchapter;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H7AA41DDDC48B4EA6A4A033BC0A314210"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">making recommendations that the Director determines are necessary to ensure risk-based security of the Federal information infrastructure and information infrastructure that is owned, operated, controlled, or licensed for use by, or on behalf of, the Department of Defense, a military department, or another element of the intelligence community to—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HAFA9862D79644FBABFA4616CC1A64CAD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Director of the Office of Management and Budget;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HBD6FDAD8709A4FBDA502C9C25BFDF665"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the head of an agency; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H984990BC4CE143569F1AB254AAD3B181"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to Congress with regard to the reprogramming of funds;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H36EB0DE511794361B31672048F9D6775"><enum>(12)</enum><text>ensuring, in consultation with the Administrator of the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs, that the efforts of agencies relating to the development of regulations, rules, requirements, or other actions applicable to the national information infrastructure are complementary;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HB3A738E9024349BC9EF84D3C88CD202E"><enum>(13)</enum><text>when directed by the President, carrying out the responsibilities for national security and emergency preparedness communications described in section 706 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/606">47 U.S.C. 606</external-xref>) to ensure integration and coordination; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H92CFBB21B57E413EA6C171D9D59B9627"><enum>(14)</enum><text>as assigned by the President, other duties relating to the security and resiliency of cyberspace.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB93981606D224BB9AAA05CB1ACB6C079"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end of section 3554, the following new subsection:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9FD46D8B58744290840B5F74BFFE4B6B" style="USC">
						<subsection id="HDF9F769D9CDF4439882F453A23EAA054"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Budget assessment and reporting</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="HCFE7718B91454BF983B51DC1B7E420BC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency submission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of each agency shall submit to the Director a budget each year for the following fiscal year relating to the protection of information infrastructure for such agency, by a date determined by the Director that is before July 1 of each year. Such budget shall include—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HF788B192BB8740D791949A7414145FAC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a review of any threats to information technology for such agency;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H9FBF167053734E76B25C55454A802579"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a plan to secure the information infrastructure for such agency based on threats to information technology, using the National Institute of Standards and Technology guidelines and recommendations;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7AC1272E2BBF48D4917D503E799CCB49"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a review of compliance by such agency with any previous year plan described in subparagraph (B); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5FDF6DA4279A434DB81A5C3429E3A16B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a report on the development of the credentialing process to enable secure authentication of identity and authorization for access to the information infrastructure of such agency.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H850CBD0ECE4C4CD1B6AAC191900DD396"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assessment and certification</header><text>The Director shall assess and certify the adequacy of each budget submitted under paragraph (1).</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HA2140DEC1892497985235882DF506B71"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Agency recommendations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than July 1 of each year, the Director shall submit to the head of each agency budget recommendations, including requests for specific initiatives that are consistent with the priorities of the President relating to the protection of information infrastructure. Such budget recommendations shall—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HCE1036014E574A6D87A27B97374B93CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>apply to the next budget year scheduled for formulation under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/11">chapter 11</external-xref> of title 31, and each of the 4 subsequent fiscal years; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HFAB6F003C1FE42D5BC09451DD2D17413"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">address funding priorities developed in the National Office for Cyberspace.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7F71BC27A39C4F35AF3B03F8B8DF03DA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Recommendations to the President</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall make recommendations to the President that the Director determines are appropriate regarding changes in the organization, management, and budget of each agency relating to the protection of information infrastructure in each such agency, and changes in the allocation of personnel to and within such agency, including monetary penalties or incentives necessary to encourage and maintain accountability of any agency, or senior agency official, for efforts to secure the information infrastructure of such agency.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8F53AF96B3E242B9AF32F36701085FBA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new section:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H08A2B40342664B1795382A82131C322D" style="USC"> <section commented="no" id="H4E09C912B40D4C318DD9F1DEEA112161"><enum>3560.</enum><header>National Office for Cyberspace </header> <subsection commented="no" id="HBF40DD4264A64694BB506AD3EFB1D53A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established within the Executive Office of the President an office to be known as the National Office for Cyberspace.</text>
							</subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H8FBC1045C66C44399595F161FBCC66A6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Director</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="HC7ABD0D3EEC0401598AAB8CFC9BB88F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There shall be at the head of the National Office for Cyberspace a Director, who shall be appointed by the President by and with the advice and consent of the Senate. The Director of the National Office for Cyberspace shall administer all functions designated to such Director under sections 3553 and 3555 and collaborate to the extent practicable with the heads of appropriate agencies, the private sector, and international partners. The Office shall serve as the principal office for coordinating issues relating to cyberspace, including achieving an assured, reliable, secure, and survivable information infrastructure and related capabilities for the Federal Government, while promoting national economic interests, security, and civil liberties.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H4639D9281F2944AF9ED7BC4291BA5BE7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Basic pay</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Office for Cyberspace shall be paid at the rate of basic pay for level III of the Executive Schedule.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HCA57EBFAF28341C1968A1B8CA301FC61"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Staff</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Office for Cyberspace may appoint and fix the pay of additional personnel as the Director considers appropriate.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H22452D6B6D21417BA7ED4D49E230CF26"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Experts and consultants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Office for Cyberspace may procure temporary and intermittent services under section 3109(b) of title 5.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H185CAC25FC22403A924A774CA6FA129D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/35">chapter 35</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H23375ABDAB9748C58A5A67867E0D647A" style="USC">
					<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
						<toc-entry level="item">3560. National Office for Cyberspace.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H1969ED3D30614D0C942D0463F9870482"><enum>(c)</enum><header>National strategy required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Office for Cyberspace shall establish a national strategy for improving agency information security.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HAA61EE89DE0A4F85B08F688751529B46"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section, and the amendments made by this section, shall take effect 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


