<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HDD203756D6BF409B9BEC21516A5BEAA2" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5479 IH: Military Taxpayer Assistance Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5479</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180411">April 11, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000799">Mr. Walz</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000188">Mr. Kind</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Commissioner of the Internal Revenue Service to establish a special unit within the
			 office of Stakeholder Partnership, Education and Communication to provide
			 members of the uniformed services with tax assistance, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H74A2F00CCE7840D1B4CEC60F778CF0EE" style="OLC">
 <section id="H54930C7CA458476892FA92DA663C1A39" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Military Taxpayer Assistance Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HF0303B11A1F1457CBF7347B914D69304"><enum>2.</enum><header>Special unit within the office of Stakeholder Partnership, Education and Communication to provide members of the uniformed services with tax assistance</header> <subsection id="H2658FA37E1F14210A9E2C04519DBA517"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commissioner of the Internal Revenue Service shall establish a special unit within the office of Stakeholder Partnership, Education and Communication in the Internal Revenue Service.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HDE6B7D8F57E545449C3F79EE978B83F0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The unit established under subsection (a) shall be responsible for developing and conducting outreach, education, and assistance concerning the tax issues applicable to members of the uniformed services and the organizations that provide tax assistance to these taxpayers.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA2312762CD594C2892BD745953D65AA6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Staffing</header><text>To the extent possible, the unit established under subsection (a) shall be staffed with veterans.</text> </subsection><subsection id="HF4A90AF4AB02482584BD83EA42D82A6B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Funding for VITA training overseas</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commissioner shall ensure that ample funding is allocated to the unit established under subsection (a) to provide face-to-face training for the military volunteers providing income tax assistance in overseas locations.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HB3EA640009F44377B76862EA8207C538"><enum>3.</enum><header>Other assistance for members of the uniformed services</header>
 <subsection id="HDFC0E229166549FF88968CDD4E8E6A37"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Toll-Free telephone line</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commissioner of the Internal Revenue Service shall establish and maintain a toll-free telephone number for members of the uniformed services and their families to answer tax law and filing questions and to resolve their tax account and compliance issues.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H25E21E92BF954E609D40C9C0350A5A64"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Website</header><text>The Commissioner shall ensure that the information on the website of the Internal Revenue Service relating to military taxpayers is current.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H24197ECA07C64DDF978EDD8B71ACA3F7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Unformed services</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this Act, the term <term>uniformed services</term> has the meaning given such term by section 101(a)(5) of title 10, United States Code.</text> </section></legis-body></bill> 

