<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H1866C16572B84F06AEF5EF344B265B08" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5193 IH: Veteran Entrepreneurship Training Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5193</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180307">March 7, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001294">Mr. Blum</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Committee on Small Business</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Small Business Act to codify the Boots to Business Program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HA72446E1C69F40A7A133B5BBAF95E0D5" style="OLC">
 <section commented="no" id="H881A2520CE0F4547A3C794BBA94FB4C2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veteran Entrepreneurship Training Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H30231E70A24B4EB2B7B1EC084D1DE908"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the Secretary of Defense should coordinate with the Administrator of the Small Business Administration to include relevant aspects of veterans assistance programs of the Small Business Administration in the Transition Assistance Program established under section 1144 of title 10, United States Code.</text>
		</section><section id="H516063F027ED475DB5F7D5BD19EAD334" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum>
 <header>Boots to Business Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 32 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/657b">15 U.S.C. 657b</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H43762A83732A48D1A6757487FA0B40D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (f) as subsection (g); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H687CDB088FA94EEF87B6F8C466B85716"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (e) the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8610A5B202F1435FAF821A96CC957860" style="OLC"> <subsection id="HD96285019A094538B9CA0B7C0A62F985"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Boots to Business Program</header> <paragraph id="H830837CA14B3402DAF9B911697AECD63"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD7ED62D9A60B46D2815A81630C3412D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <term>covered individual</term> means—</text> <clause id="H8A9CE63F11AE4FA48459B4B961AC7443"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a member of the Armed Forces, including the National Guard or Reserves;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC28D1065729D45CAB7AF7031C8B4E04E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an individual who is participating in the Transition Assistance Program established under section 1144 of title 10, United States Code;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA332F62BE7294E18947C27A3F0D44281"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an individual who—</text> <subclause id="H8D77B3F524D94FBB8B17F9D972628BF4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>served on active duty in any branch of the Armed Forces, including the National Guard or Reserves; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HE506E5301D824A42A16C460FFDAC1743"><enum>(II)</enum><text>was discharged or released from such service under conditions other than dishonorable; and</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="H6FA246036E494720A4EBCDA0050D4E23"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a spouse or dependent of an individual described in clause (i), (ii), or (iii); and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF7148ECB707D4FAFBA42F17FB8E243CA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>Vet Center</term> has the meaning given in section 1712A(h) of title 38, United States Code.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H995DD15D9D634F0FA2A521F167FEB2EC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Administrator shall carry out a program to be known as the <quote>Boots to Business Program</quote> to provide entrepreneurship training to covered individuals.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H58926AEFDACD4E07A66D1E66E9DEF69D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Goals</header><text>The goals of the Boots to Business Program are to—</text> <subparagraph id="H2DD505A6F31E44A6B914114C9AD3389A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide assistance and in-depth training to covered individuals interested in business ownership; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45918DD9915F41C2857813BA8EF4809B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide covered individuals with the tools, skills, and knowledge necessary to identify a business opportunity, draft a business plan, identify sources of capital, connect with local resources for small business concerns, and launch a small business concern.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7472591E18C4DD9B88B8BF9940B061F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Program components</header>
 <subparagraph id="HB35EB10997094A7EB5A6343D541A036A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Boots to Business Program may include—</text> <clause id="HDFB7B940D2EF48F1B4B3E360E78EFDD6"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a presentation providing exposure to the considerations involved in self-employment and ownership of a small business concern;</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8C1864FE424742E58A25891A92B2ECFD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an online, self-study course focused on the basic skills of entrepreneurship, the language of business, and the considerations involved in self-employment and ownership of a small business concern;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF134E2862B024AF4843B80F3ADEF44B2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an in-person classroom instruction component providing an introduction to the foundations of self employment and ownership of a small business concern; and</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H51AA83E778DF4068A61520B9B08F447B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in-depth training delivered through online instruction, including an online course that leads to the creation of a business plan.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95E87E4E5FC74ED1B438433CA10BA2D8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text>The Administrator may—</text> <clause id="H07319829F0524484B0E65146BB04A735"><enum>(i)</enum><text>collaborate with public and private entities to develop course curricula for the Boots to Business Program; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H110255A5DE0B40C2A0E3B354CCEA28DD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>modify program components in coordination with entities participating in a Warriors in Transition program, as defined in section 738(e) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2013 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1071">10 U.S.C. 1071</external-xref> note).</text>
								</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2F372AA1A6F4CFA877B80AB3B94F685"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Utilization of resource partners</header>
 <clause id="H86992A72FDCC4895A65CDC478D9C1716"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall—</text> <subclause id="H413855DCB2C04A73B80CC8A0AB8EEF3E"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that Veteran Business Outreach Centers regularly participate, on a nationwide basis, in the Boots to Business Program; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H6F0F3893EC5A4AA6BD21E877EC402073"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable, use a variety of other resource partners and entities in administering the Boots to Business Program.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H81B59769C708495E92A65F6924C4BC8C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Grant authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out clause (i), the Administrator may make grants to Veteran Business Outreach Centers, other resource partners, or other entities to carry out components of the Boots to Business Program.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9235DFF686C440CDAA5E28449B337B91"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Availability to Department of Defense</header><text>The Administrator shall make available to the Secretary of Defense information regarding the Boots to Business Program, including all course materials created for the Boots to Business Program, for inclusion on the website of the Department of Defense relating to the Transition Assistance Program, in the Transition Assistance Program manual, and in other relevant materials available for distribution from the Secretary of Defense.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD5816C8ED144D63A94D78B103D449A7"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Availability to Veterans Affairs</header><text>In consultation with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, the Administrator shall make available outreach materials regarding the Boots to Business Program for distribution and display at local facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs which shall, at a minimum—</text>
 <clause id="H0CA3712F61AE47F5A7CD1A18FFA9AB01"><enum>(i)</enum><text>describe the Boots to Business Program and the services provided; and</text> </clause><clause id="H08B95D58DCD34669BC99991740BECDE5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>include eligibility requirements for participating in the Boots to Business Program.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H80A8AF48CA574DCA8A4D74E2295661A7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Review</header><text>The Inspector General of the Administration shall submit to the Committee on Small Business and Entrepreneurship of the Senate and the Committee on Small Business of the House of Representatives an annual report regarding the awarding of grants to entities under paragraph (4)(C).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBF5E786FBEAF4DBB8AFCA4586D45A6A0"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this subsection and every year thereafter, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Small Business and Entrepreneurship of the Senate and the Committee on Small Business of the House of Representatives a report on the performance and effectiveness of the Boots to Business Program, which may be included as part of another report submitted to such Committees by the Administrator, and which shall include—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H8CE9B9FA9EB847AB8878E9287373D62F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of program participants using each component of the Boots to Business Program;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25F11259AC314891B7532A518C261304"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the completion rates for each component of the Boots to Business Program;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H65B9A165133742608E041DDFFA4E55EF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to the extent possible—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H887C69307E8D45C688B3C773A3F4E22B"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the demographics of program participants, to include gender, age, race, relationship to military, military occupational specialty, and years of service of program participants;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC2D8C3EAF8774097877DFB0D336282B5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of small business concerns formed or expanded with assistance under the Boots to Business Program;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HCE2EE2BFCDB94BDFBD4AE71B1DDF9E6F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the gross receipts of small business concerns receiving assistance under the Boots to Business Program;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H0282CC9876384C1B94CCC2EE3533F087"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the number of jobs created with assistance under the Boots to Business Program;</text> </clause><clause id="H0959C69964A044E38858E369C820C9F9"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the number of referrals to other resources and programs of the Administration;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H87D253D3145A4BEC9C2C547A703024AB"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the number of program participants receiving financial assistance under loan programs of the Administration;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC37A2405FD284E829E3EEB1240471660"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the type and dollar amount of financial assistance received by program participants under any loan program of the Administration; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H7272F4215D5E4377A019F13DCA67D44D"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>results of participant satisfaction surveys, including a summary of any comments received from program participants;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74F85E7DDD52489F8F4CC2DBE557EE5A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an evaluation of the effectiveness of the Boots to Business Program in each region of the Administration during the most recent fiscal year;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE2214E1E7844552B27A049A7BF1781D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an assessment of additional performance outcome measures for the Boots to Business Program, as identified by the Administrator;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11080618DF614506A1D6BA08B4DF9F19"><enum>(F)</enum><text>any recommendations of the Administrator for improvement of the Boots to Business Program, which may include expansion of the types of individuals who are covered individuals;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BC25C40F25048F0BBA2C4F295C6E0B8"><enum>(G)</enum><text>an explanation of how the Boots to Business Program has been integrated with other transition programs and related resources of the Administration and other Federal agencies; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H636111D498164496833E6303A09A751E"><enum>(H)</enum><text>any additional information the Administrator determines necessary.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

