<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H2E1C1057028C4F9989C21D2FF59123A3" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5883 IH: Unexploded Ordnance Removal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5883</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180518">May 18, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000592">Mr. Poe of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Defense, in concurrence with the Secretary of State, to develop and
			 implement a strategy for removing unexploded ordnance in Syria and Iraq,
			 and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HF2172C9423EE411B85394D8EC3B02709" style="OLC">
 <section id="HC914196D98004239B9B7BCB367FD9BEA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Unexploded Ordnance Removal Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HE991BE6AEA1E44D393808356A475D93F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Strategy for removing unexploded ordnance in Syria and Iraq</header> <subsection id="HF5294468AC724694A13DDDC884B79804"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense, in concurrence with the Secretary of State, shall develop and implement a strategy for removing unexploded ordnance in Syria and Iraq that includes the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H40B83F153A6D487B86631F2F3ED1E194"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the hazards posed by unexploded ordnance in Syria and Iraq, including with respect to U.S. strategic and military interests, the areas of concentration of unexploded ordnance, and schools, hospitals, or civil-service buildings that are proximate to unexploded ordnance.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H232703406E09431E82F24A5A9842986E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A detailed description and timeline for actions to eliminate the hazards posed by unexploded ordnance in Syria and Iraq.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H10DF4993328F40CBB68F287F611B9B63"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Multilateral coordination</header><text>In developing and implementing the strategy required under subsection (a), the Secretary of Defense is authorized to coordinate as appropriate with appropriate officials of foreign countries and multilateral institutions.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H3E420B64138D429C862319BBB96DD7C5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter until December 31, 2021, the Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the Secretary of State, shall submit to the congressional defense committees, the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate, and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives a report that includes—</text>
 <paragraph id="HDC3602784DEB48E1881D63C22D9FFDD6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the first such report, the strategy described in subsection (a), including—</text> <subparagraph id="H27C1CC513DCE42EE84961833AF808298"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the results of the assessment described in subsection (a)(1);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED01012E4F81495A9F76C1175B0C9B06"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the description and timeline required by subsection (a)(2); and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDEE9892BBE6944F8AD527BC4E051F0EA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of contributions of foreign partners in developing the strategy in accordance with subsection (b);</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1BD0330C7A441C3A1D63F79F5A66FB0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsequent reports, any updates from the previous report to such strategy, results, descriptions, or timeline; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H88CD2159AF2A476FB25049D3332C9A3A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the actions taken pursuant to the authorization under subsection (b) to implement such strategy, as so updated, through multilateral efforts.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


