<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HD617C11948594E43963C4CD3529589B8" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4817 IH: Promoting Exchanges for Enhanced Routing of Information so Networks are Great Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4817</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180117">January 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000576">Mr. Long</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information to make grants for
			 the establishment or expansion of internet exchange facilities, and for
			 other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H3CF159B1EFF648A0879F2047453C5DE2" style="OLC">
 <section id="HEDB2B640FE684BE6BED7D126F941F74B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Promoting Exchanges for Enhanced Routing of Information so Networks are Great Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PEERING Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HDC95C688B47041D88521C6DB34DE36E5"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Telecommunications and Information Administration grants</header> <subsection id="H2B8B9FF325CC47A1989B9D76914F0FAE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On and after the first day of the first fiscal year beginning after the date on which the Assistant Secretary establishes rules and timelines under subsection (d), the Assistant Secretary shall award grants to entities to acquire real property and necessary equipment to—</text>
 <paragraph id="H53E5244FCC254F9396AE719935B75CBA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish a new internet exchange facility in a core based statistical area in which, at the time the grant is made, there are no existing internet exchange facilities; or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8AE759C44BBC4DF8B49288491A172AE8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expand operations at an existing internet exchange facility in a core based statistical area in which, at the time the grant is made, there is only one internet exchange facility.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3F887DCBF119482EB7A88C9531B42468"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity may not receive a covered grant unless the entity certifies to the Assistant Secretary that the entity has sufficient interest from third-party entities that will use the internet exchange facility to be funded by the grant once the facility is established or operations are expanded, as applicable.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H813E0D44154F49B0B373ACC272D79F8F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text>The Federal share of the total cost of the establishment or expansion of operations at an internet exchange facility for which a covered grant is received may not exceed 50 percent.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H403151F3D38B4D29A4F3F5176DBF3EF1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header>
 <paragraph id="H67C91D066DA444DD840285227FD6A298"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Rules and timelines</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary shall establish rules and timelines for applications for covered grants.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA71F409F9E2C4048B5A4CE1C15809F63"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Third-party review</header><text>To prevent fraud in the covered grant program, the Assistant Secretary shall enter into a contract with an independent third party under which the third party reviews an application for a covered grant not later than 60 days after the date on which the application is submitted to ensure that only an entity that is eligible for a covered grant receives a covered grant.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB9696233C32A4032B3A72558A994FCCA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to authorize the Assistant Secretary to regulate, issue guidance for, or otherwise interfere with the activities at an internet exchange facility.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H196C092A1229428893AFDD1C6E4E58F5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>No additional funds authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No additional funds are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section. This section shall be carried out using amounts otherwise authorized.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="HC1C61CB699FC47A38B5949CA5CA05EB2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Use of E-Rate and Rural Health Care universal service support</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 254 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/254">47 U.S.C. 254</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD5CEC045838C4B968918D4C328A3F1E6" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="HE8EC79872AAB4C48B05E72170695834B"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Use of E-Rate and Rural Health Care support for costs relating to internet exchange facility
			 connection</header>
 <paragraph id="H8B50CB96D2EE4BCD81DA37F3C8083724"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law or regulation, including subpart F or G of part 54 of title 47, Code of Federal Regulations, a recipient of support under such subpart F or G may receive support under such subpart—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD5D9F6743C0D4D008CEF200852A1929E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to contract with a broadband internet service provider to obtain connection to an internet exchange facility; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H169C2B2381624FE1AD81B91349B4A1B9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for the costs of maintaining a point of presence at an internet exchange facility.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF954FE3FF06844A7AF80634595A52A8F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to authorize the Commission to regulate, issue guidance for, or otherwise interfere with the activities at an internet exchange facility.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8094A611BF3D4AEF85F07A40B91C4768"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Internet exchange facility defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>internet exchange facility</quote> means physical infrastructure through which internet service providers and content delivery networks exchange internet traffic between their networks.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </section><section id="HBBE820DDA4F44B9DA70BCA54C5B74865"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H2679703EE1D349BA9C60C69A1DFE2F58"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assistant Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Assistant Secretary</quote> means the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HEF512A9588F1446899B95156627E3E74"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Core based statistical area</header><text>The term <quote>core based statistical area</quote> has the meaning given such term by the Office of Management and Budget in the Notice of Decision entitled <quote>2010 Standards for Delineating Metropolitan and Micropolitan Statistical Areas</quote>, published in the Federal Register on June 28, 2010 (75 Fed. Reg. 37246), or any successor to such Notice.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H02D14AF5E69F4613BAE5BE81C390C887"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered grant</header><text>The term <quote>covered grant</quote> means a grant awarded under section 2(a).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H4E0EF137DEFB427D9DB7FA80A2F9CB89"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Internet exchange facility</header><text>The term <quote>internet exchange facility</quote> means physical infrastructure through which internet service providers and content delivery networks exchange internet traffic between their networks.</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


