<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEED5B3D1021342F5AB2E089E3FDEDB6E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5788 IH: Securing the International Mail Against Opioids Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5788</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180515">May 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001293">Mr. Bishop of Michigan</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000578">Mr. Reichert</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the processing by U.S. Customs and Border Protection of certain international mail shipments and to require the provision of advance electronic information on international mail shipments of mail, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H74A8EB91BB7140F6BD7DAEAFA08E8F9E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H9731407E0DF24BC6BF34D07FD512DDD8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing the International Mail Against Opioids Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H68ADEA86F40F4EA1B1658CEA278D937C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Customs fees</header> <subsection id="HE6002C072F8440C0AEFF9EFC3FFA8F0B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 13031(b)(9) of the Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/58c">19 U.S.C. 58c(b)(9)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7A5709AD51214BA39606C580720CBB7F" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H3AEDADB7A0C44E06B7904E481A5BF2EF" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H443FB0DFD14A47D1875E1FA7E521D446"><enum>(i)</enum><text>With respect to the processing of items that are sent to the United States through the international postal network by <quote>Inbound Express Mail service</quote> or <quote>Inbound EMS</quote> (as that service is described in the mail classification schedule referred to in section 3631 of title 39, United States Code), the following payments are required:</text> <subclause id="H1B7DC03B9F144F5281166539844A5AB4" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>$1 per Inbound EMS item.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H395A87957B64482785EB69EFC0572B13" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>If an Inbound EMS item is formally entered, the fee provided for under subsection (a)(9), if applicable.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HC025D2A5AF37465E9BC9F2FEA74B6F72" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Notwithstanding section 451 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1451">19 U.S.C. 1451</external-xref>), the payments required by clause (i), as allocated pursuant to clause (iii)(I), shall be the only payments required for reimbursement of U.S. Customs and Border Protection for customs services provided in connection with the processing of an Inbound EMS item.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H477F341D7E9E4E58896EBEF9AF75185A" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HEE69AF134A1B4005B87C2B8733BFABED"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The payments required by clause (i) shall be allocated as follows:</text> <item id="H125C92890C3A4458AF78A94DB3A7421C" indent="up1"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>50 percent of the amount of the payments shall be paid on a quarterly basis by the United States Postal Service to the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection in accordance with regulations prescribed by the Secretary of the Treasury to reimburse U.S. Customs and Border Protection for customs services provided in connection with the processing of Inbound EMS items.</text></item> 
<item id="HC23B9E45CA0947BC9F63539AC27C4750" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>50 percent of the amount of the payments shall be retained by the Postal Service to reimburse the Postal Service for services provided in connection with the customs processing of Inbound EMS items.</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H6B96E83AD04842C89AB9E629B86F70A2" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Payments received by U.S. Customs and Border Protection under subclause (I)(aa) shall, in accordance with section 524 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1524">19 U.S.C. 1524</external-xref>), be deposited in the Customs User Fee Account and used to directly reimburse each appropriation for the amount paid out of that appropriation for the costs incurred in providing services to international mail facilities. Amounts deposited in accordance with the preceding sentence shall be available until expended for the provision of such services.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H2161F8B5D6CC40CD8B85CE0E4F313D99" indent="up1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Payments retained by the Postal Service under subclause (I)(bb) shall be used to directly reimburse the Postal Service for the costs incurred in providing services in connection with the customs processing of Inbound EMS items.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H796F3599D2AA40B898C7D3493BEDE345" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Beginning in fiscal year 2021, the Secretary, in consultation with the Postmaster General, may adjust, not more frequently than once each fiscal year, the amount described in clause (i)(I) to an amount commensurate with the costs of services provided in connection with the customs processing of Inbound EMS items, consistent with the obligations of the United States under international agreements.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF261023F46C049B0B67CD12643FD8DEB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Section 13031(a) of the Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/58c">19 U.S.C. 58c(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H92DB63F8B0C54C51B4D5FD67505668CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (6), by inserting <quote>(other than an item subject to a fee under subsection (b)(9)(D))</quote> after <quote>customs officer</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H49A70424F2244663A6A772DA42D75C75"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (10)—</text> <subparagraph id="H2FFE8A242A474C1ABBF098CA123DEAF3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), in the matter preceding clause (i), by inserting <quote>(other than Inbound EMS items described in subsection (b)(9)(D))</quote> after <quote>release</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H255255D57A274AA78BF71944C0AA86B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the flush at the end, by inserting <quote>or of Inbound EMS items described in subsection (b)(9)(D),</quote> after <quote>(C),</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H92EBFB15B00B43FCA3D5630C9072BCC8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on January 1, 2020.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H0000F97E37F54B13BF4DC90B88A2C38D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Mandatory advance electronic information for postal shipments</header> 
<subsection id="HB20C65E567C0492EA3ACA71C29B5537D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Mandatory advance electronic information</header> 
<paragraph id="HBF2D468FBE9B4B8CBD90AA79C8FF5698"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 343(a)(3)(K) of the Trade Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/210">Public Law 107–210</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/2071">19 U.S.C. 2071</external-xref> note) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC0BA3332EE3E46FF9E26AF22721A46B1" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HEDE28C1A7352401C8DF705069BB81497"><enum>(K)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H073A01D12AA244FAAB89EFA24DF63F58"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Secretary, with the concurrence of the Secretary of State, shall prescribe regulations requiring the United States Postal Service to transmit the information described in paragraphs (1) and (2) to the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection for international mail shipments by the Postal Service (including shipments to the Postal Service from foreign postal operators that are transported by private carrier) consistent with the requirements of this subparagraph.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDB97CD3DFE184E64A43DF88529D9D385" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>In prescribing regulations under clause (i), the Secretary shall impose requirements for the transmission to the Commissioner of information described in paragraphs (1) and (2) for mail shipments described in clause (i) that are comparable to the requirements for the transmission of such information imposed on similar non-mail shipments of cargo, taking into account the parameters set forth in subparagraphs (A) through (J).</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H12BEE9E2C64444A7A604DD7A2B0A2F62" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The regulations prescribed under clause (i) shall require the transmission of the information described in paragraphs (1) and (2) with respect to a shipment as soon as practicable in relation to the transportation of the shipment, consistent with subparagraph (H).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H66F8E498481C4EF0ABB92898038AA396" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Regulations prescribed under clause (i) shall allow for the requirements for the transmission to the Commissioner of information described in paragraphs (1) and (2) for mail shipments described in clause (i) to be implemented in phases, as appropriate, by—</text> <subclause id="HFDDB108ED54F4571961D3714CF043D70"><enum>(I)</enum><text>setting incremental targets for increasing the percentage of such shipments for which information is required to be transmitted to the Commissioner; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H4FCE174652CB4D3D85E615FD534BCA96"><enum>(II)</enum><text>taking into consideration—</text> <item id="H1AB79E14072144CBAD839E1D1BDA933D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the risk posed by such shipments;</text></item> 
<item id="H8F60AEEF371C4DA9B3022668E91FD2B9"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the volume of mail shipped to the United States by or through a particular country; and</text></item> <item id="H50A8EF931031405EAF1089FD63493239"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the capacities of foreign postal operators to provide that information to the Postal Service.</text></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H080CA2A2E81145B4BED65E7760997831" indent="up1"><enum>(v)</enum> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H2698C39AD6BE4A98B3E91D84BF008140"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Notwithstanding clause (iv) and except as provided in subclause (II), the Postal Service shall, not later than December 31, 2018, arrange for the transmission to the Commissioner of the information described in paragraphs (1) and (2) for not less than 70 percent of the aggregate number of mail shipments described in clause (i).</text></subclause> <subclause id="H83BD10FEB9884893857AD0CE67A3DEAC" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum> <item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0AEC5C75F4064662A4BC11D79DAE6EEB"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>The requirements of subclause (I) may be waived for a period of not more than 180 days if, not later than December 31, 2018—</text> 
<subitem id="HCD6AC9B7700A452B970CFA17FA8FA013" indent="up1"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the Secretary and the Postmaster General, with the concurrence of the Secretary of State, determine that meeting those requirements is not feasible because of the lack of capacity of foreign postal operators to provide the Postal Service with the information described in paragraphs (1) and (2);</text></subitem> <subitem id="H8A78CC9ED3B04585B7615BB8B49879F9" indent="up1"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>the Secretary and the Postmaster General, with the concurrence of the Secretary of State, determine that meeting those requirements is not feasible because of extraordinary reasons other than lack of capacity of foreign postal operators that are outside the control of the Postal Service; or</text></subitem> 
<subitem id="HBDF08EA4CEC24B6999361DEC320B3468" indent="up1"><enum>(CC)</enum><text>the Secretary of State determines that such a waiver is in the national security interests of the United States.</text></subitem></item> <item id="HE0B498B3BE464F47A5286CD8D8D23391" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>A waiver under item (aa) may be renewed for one additional period of not more than 180 days if a determination described in item (aa) is made for that period.</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="HCD145F07E6E54F97976E1389D0FFDEBA" indent="up1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>If the requirements of subclause (I) are not met, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees, not later than January 31, 2020, a report—</text> <item id="H66E0AF0BAF964E63A8318FBC465D3DEC"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>assessing the reasons for the failure to meet those requirements; and</text></item> 
<item id="H2DDC74ADE3484A5FBDD67F5CC51A1969"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>identifying recommendations to improve the collection by the Postal Service of the information described in paragraphs (1) and (2).</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="H6322EDDA3FDB4E4291475CCBEB82CB26" indent="up1"><enum>(vi)</enum> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H64BA885C58944952B9729012FBCCAFE3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Notwithstanding clause (iv) and except as provided in subclause (II), the Postal Service shall, not later than December 31, 2022, arrange for the transmission to the Commissioner of the information described in paragraphs (1) and (2) for not less than 95 percent of the aggregate number of mail shipments described in clause (i).</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H4F9AD7B9E4684CE5AF87AA49DE160601" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The requirements of subclause (I) may be waived for a period of not more than one year if, not later than December 31, 2022—</text> <item id="H86577C561FA94615A5CC699E5BB419C1"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the Secretary and the Postmaster General, with the concurrence of the Secretary of State, determine that meeting those requirements is not feasible because of—</text> 
<subitem id="H4C8941A65BE24088ACBFBA6589592194"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the lack of capacity of foreign postal operators to provide the Postal Service with the information described in paragraphs (1) and (2); or</text></subitem> <subitem id="HF00800EAF59D46F5BF8675C0D83730C9"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>extraordinary reasons other than lack of capacity of foreign postal operators that are outside the control of the Postal Service; or</text></subitem></item> 
<item id="HFD6C73041799476999D9D9C5BC23D892"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the Secretary of State determines that such a waiver is in the national security interests of the United States.</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="H46908AC117F74A7A959D1D8DD36F3E76" indent="up1"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Not later than 15 days before making a determination under clause (v) or (vi) that meeting the requirements of that clause is not feasible, the Secretary and the Postmaster General shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a notification of the determination. The notification shall include—</text> 
<subclause id="H295D68FE189842B2907C51221C4126C5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the case of a determination under clause (v)(II)(aa)(AA) or (vi)(II)(aa)(AA)—</text> <item id="HB0A56F41E39E4FB8855E390F4855BB96"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a list of which foreign postal operators lack the capacity to provide the information described in paragraphs (1) and (2) to the Postal Service;</text></item> 
<item id="H00E87818900947FBA6C6A2C2B58A505D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>a description of the efforts by the Postal Service made to obtain that information from those operators; and</text></item> <item id="HF81867B4A5E64076970635328EBEE52C"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>a plan for obtaining that information from those operators; and</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H0D342EA982194695A3E7B978A5AB8366"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of a determination under clause (v)(II)(aa)(BB) or (vi)(II)(aa)(BB)—</text> <item id="H7853281825684503A2A001B2F789FAFE"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a description of the extraordinary reasons outside the control of the Postal Service; and</text></item> 
<item id="HD6E8E84A35B648F1830654F62083C2D9"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>a plan for obtaining the transmission of information described in paragraphs (1) and (2) as required by clause (v) or (vi), as applicable.</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="HBBAD6B9311DE4F1B8D67553B6419711A" indent="up1"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>The Secretary and the Postmaster General may, in consultation with the Secretary of State, as necessary, take all appropriate remedial measures necessary to ensure compliance with regulations prescribed under clause (i) and consistent with the obligations of the United States under international agreements, including refusal of shipments for which the information described in paragraphs (1) and (2) is not transmitted as required under this subparagraph.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H392A318763BD40E48507EE2E1F17D60B" indent="up1"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Nothing in this subparagraph shall be construed to limit the authority of the Secretary to obtain information relating to international mail shipments from private carriers or other appropriate parties.</text></clause> <clause id="HDCAF293C695B48CB9C28640AF9E707CB" indent="up1"><enum>(x)</enum><text>In this subparagraph, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> 
<subclause id="H146D7BEA558040A8ADEB4E0792C2BC6D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Committee on Finance and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H26DDB430686042CB9DF7DD43BD9105E3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the Committee on Ways and Means and the Committee on Oversight and Government Reform of the House of Representatives.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H13C966A82593489398A49E2043BF9DA5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Joint strategic plan on mandatory advance information</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Postmaster General shall develop and submit to the appropriate congressional committees a joint strategic plan detailing specific performance measures for achieving—</text> <subparagraph id="HC188CFA7B9AB447888D0CD5C40D8E12D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the transmission of information as required by section 343(a)(3)(K) of the Trade Act of 2002, as amended by paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1418F8F0E08D4EAAB8A214A37192B75C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the presentation by the Postal Service to U.S. Customs and Border Protection of all mail targeted by U.S. Customs and Border Protection for inspection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H159A66B3A74D4EFEB12875B96340504C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Capacity building</header> <paragraph id="H43FB2F1C3143485682E996EC453801FD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 343(a) of the Trade Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/210">Public Law 107–210</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/2071">19 U.S.C. 2071</external-xref> note) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC23DEF0DA7A44115BAF322D919009A00" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H80C888B355D941E9BAD9B5FD976CBDD5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Capacity building</header> 
<subparagraph id="HA5A54187ADB541589C310BAD120F0975"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, with the concurrence of the Secretary of State, and in coordination with the Postmaster General and the heads of other Federal agencies, as appropriate, may provide technical assistance, equipment, technology, and training to enhance the capacity of foreign postal operators—</text> <clause id="H8159BC69BBA842CAB926E926CDFB8AA9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to gather and provide the information required by paragraph (3)(K); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9D8AB966E87B4196BE8B00440B2D05EA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to otherwise gather and provide postal shipment information related to—</text> <subclause id="H7D303E77C3AD417D9FCCFB4094B9F439"><enum>(I)</enum><text>terrorism;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H20E44FA899B64C3A8D4A6481FB7B3E89"><enum>(II)</enum><text>items the importation or introduction of which into the United States is prohibited or restricted, including controlled substances; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HC816FFADBE6446EE817C9D109F2AE7D7"><enum>(III)</enum><text>such other concerns as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4236B2C66D7641BA83A0CED80EAEE491"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Provision of equipment and technology</header><text>With respect to the provision of equipment and technology under subparagraph (A), the Secretary may lease, loan, provide, or otherwise assist in the deployment of such equipment and technology under such terms and conditions as the Secretary may prescribe, including nonreimbursable loans or the transfer of ownership of equipment and technology.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA4BC244B213F45168A4EAD9F605D766C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Joint strategic plan on capacity building</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Postmaster General shall, in consultation with the Secretary of State, jointly develop and submit to the appropriate congressional committees a joint strategic plan—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEE828F56039C4EEDA2DF1F8EC3F9C423"><enum>(A)</enum><text>detailing the extent to which U.S. Customs and Border Protection and the United States Postal Service are engaged in capacity building efforts under section 343(a)(5) of the Trade Act of 2002, as added by paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H95AB92E2E3E64A19A54E0DF9FA1D5D8E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>describing plans for future capacity building efforts; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA9F422B69AF04434BBFFCBE05B290194"><enum>(C)</enum><text>assessing how capacity building has increased the ability of U.S. Customs and Border Protection and the Postal Service to advance the goals of this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H410B9877356845F8A357FFA112EBBED0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report and consultations by Secretary of Homeland Security and Postmaster General</header> <paragraph id="HB0316B822F834B88A4104D1896BB5EA3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter until 3 years after the Postmaster General has met the requirement under clause (vi) of subparagraph (K) of section 343(a)(3) of the Trade Act of 2002, as amended by subsection (a)(1), the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Postmaster General shall, in consultation with the Secretary of State, jointly submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on compliance with that subparagraph that includes the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7A173563587C43B18C551E809DC10EA6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An assessment of the status of the regulations required to be promulgated under that subparagraph.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H78B2AAC5A50842549945AECF43291AA7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An update regarding new and existing agreements reached with foreign postal operators for the transmission of the information required by that subparagraph.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0B25064E2E824D08AD3E236F5F3A79E6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A summary of deliberations between the United States Postal Service and foreign postal operators with respect to issues relating to the transmission of that information.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC0DF470EC4F14DFCB91B5373E34AAD48"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A summary of the progress made in achieving the transmission of that information for the percentage of shipments required by that subparagraph.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5E337A09B4EF40B9AC9C9C3813317814"><enum>(E)</enum><text>An assessment of the quality of that information being received by foreign postal operators, as determined by the Secretary of Homeland Security, and actions taken to improve the quality of that information.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAFDA59A64AF142AE8F3565F4A97B2BBE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A summary of policies established by the Universal Postal Union that may affect the ability of the Postmaster General to obtain the transmission of that information.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2DAFA60E8CD04D6688C51CF453921040"><enum>(G)</enum><text>A summary of the use of technology to detect illicit synthetic opioids and other illegal substances in international mail parcels and planned acquisitions and advancements in such technology.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8543FC9FFB0D4C438F0A65BE816E7103"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Such other information as the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Postmaster General consider appropriate with respect to obtaining the transmission of information required by that subparagraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA80AE5027A4D40E2860A1EB812977DE9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultations</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 180 days thereafter until the Postmaster General has met the requirement under clause (vi) of section 343(a)(3)(K) of the Trade Act of 2002, as amended by subsection (a)(1), to arrange for the transmission of information with respect to not less than 95 percent of the aggregate number of mail shipments described in clause (i) of that section, the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Postmaster General shall provide briefings to the appropriate congressional committees on the progress made in achieving the transmission of that information for that percentage of shipments.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD9F18A2A16A9447F8B49D9BE918FBA3E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Government Accountability Office report</header><text>Not later than December 31, 2020, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report—</text> 
<paragraph id="H11800F2B755E46909593E640A3C8A445"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assessing the progress of the United States Postal Service in achieving the transmission of the information required by subparagraph (K) of section 343(a)(3) of the Trade Act of 2002, as amended by subsection (a)(1), for the percentage of shipments required by that subparagraph;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF8ECDFEB93B749D28E8F9B6B23BDBD56"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assessing the quality of the information received from foreign postal operators for targeting purposes;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3CCB805732EA4D6CB54AA14F1D8BB859"><enum>(3)</enum><text>assessing the specific percentage of targeted mail presented by the Postal Service to U.S. Customs and Border Protection for inspection;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC568D28C799046219A3A78D16CC89B58"><enum>(4)</enum><text>describing the costs of collecting the information required by such subparagraph (K) from foreign postal operators and the costs of implementing the use of that information;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1F67803D810D42A585418CAA0CBA71E9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>assessing the benefits of receiving that information with respect to international mail shipments;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H88B6FAEF360D40D894C2C4603E448BFE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>assessing the feasibility of assessing a customs fee under section 13031(b)(9) of the Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1985, as amended by section 2, on international mail shipments other than Inbound Express Mail service in a manner consistent with the obligations of the United States under international agreements; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H63037F3527974F30A6EBA2ACDB00690C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>identifying recommendations, including recommendations for legislation, to improve the compliance of the Postal Service with such subparagraph (K), including an assessment of whether the detection of illicit synthetic opioids in the international mail would be improved by—</text> <subparagraph id="H48D16F66DC284DE59EBB3D831C803FD7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>requiring the Postal Service to serve as the consignee for international mail shipments containing goods; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5B59697E153849E7A912B89F91D816E7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>designating a customs broker to act as an importer of record for international mail shipments containing goods.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H7FBAF0C29B354F83B801016025FB926E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Technical correction</header><text>Section 343 of the Trade Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/210">Public Law 107–210</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/2071">19 U.S.C. 2071</external-xref> note) is amended in the section heading by striking <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">advanced</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">advance</header-in-text></quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H40F1E17DBCD6436CA482FD7A7C912398"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> <paragraph id="H18614ED762664F2C8D2BF656B75CF15E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Finance and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0249446E46C74473A71CF494D99133C6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Ways and Means and the Committee on Oversight and Government Reform of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HD7F926E6AF534682A965D46785872A6B"><enum>4.</enum><header>International postal agreements</header> <subsection id="H62D0F978F9F4402F8F2C6E54E1FCAAEA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Existing agreements</header><text>Any regulations prescribed under section 343(a)(3)(K) of the Trade Act of 2002, as amended by section 3(a)(1), shall be consistent with the obligations of the United States under international agreements.</text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HEF1EC395A86B4A67ACFD69DEC9D1D608"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Future agreements</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H8441A17638A0483D97508E416DD9C3E0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Consultations</header><text>Before entering into, on or after the date of the enactment of this Act, any postal treaty, convention, or other international agreement related to international postal services, or any amendment to such an agreement, that could restrict the ability of the United States to secure the provision of advance electronic information by foreign postal operators, the Secretary of State should consult with the appropriate congressional committees (as defined in section 3(f)).</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H9FAD9A9F0F634FCE885E1C380E4C4DDC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Expedited negotiation of new agreement</header><text>To the extent that any new postal treaty, convention, or other international agreement related to international postal services is necessary to secure the provision of advance electronic information by foreign postal operators as required by regulations prescribed under section 343(a)(3)(K) of the Trade Act of 2002, as amended by section 3(a)(1), the Secretary of State should expeditiously conclude such an agreement.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H7FCD66854E77433ABC4FA362ED45790E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Cost recoupment</header> 
<subsection id="H40D4BDA1C1CE4C46886EA732E9BC9354"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States Postal Service shall, to the extent practicable and otherwise recoverable by law, ensure that all costs associated with complying with this Act and amendments made by this Act are charged directly to foreign shippers or foreign postal operators.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H88F4B167338D4EE19047AA2247E9881A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Costs not considered revenue</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The recovery of costs under subsection (a) shall not be deemed revenue for purposes of subchapter I and II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/39/36">chapter 36</external-xref> of title 39, United States Code, or regulations prescribed under that chapter.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H56866F8DF98B483296DA1385EDCC3681"><enum>6.</enum><header>Development of technology to detect illicit narcotics</header> 
<subsection id="HBF087981667C48D48A11D6CA83C865BE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Postmaster General and the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, in coordination with the heads of other agencies as appropriate, shall collaborate to identify and develop technology for the detection of illicit fentanyl, other synthetic opioids, and other narcotics and psychoactive substances entering the United States by mail.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF029C85048D34660B2A5E9B3D2825D42"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Outreach to private sector</header><text>The Postmaster General and the Commissioner shall conduct outreach to private sector entities to gather information regarding the current state of technology to identify areas for innovation relating to the detection of illicit fentanyl, other synthetic opioids, and other narcotics and psychoactive substances entering the United States.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H17803D33FFB64BDABB63962734212C3D"><enum>7.</enum><header>Effective date; regulations</header> 
<subsection id="H5827B2A4BA8243C3922CCCE19EC751A3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This Act and the amendments made by this Act (other than the amendments made by section 2) shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H7318DBE0EE0B442FB54DBF97617E6490"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, such regulations as are necessary to carry out this Act and the amendments made by this Act shall be prescribed.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

