<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HF9FC2CF6244B4EA2B87FE654979302D8" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5831 IH: Keith Nolan Air Force Deaf Demonstration Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5831</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180515">May 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000620">Mr. Delaney</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000559">Mr. Langevin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a demonstration program on the accession as Air Force officers of candidates with
			 auditory impairments.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HE75D7880970041FA82F53048326AD169" style="OLC">
 <section id="H8929EDDE0BF54CDDA4DC279A0D15B924" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Keith Nolan Air Force Deaf Demonstration Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H150C9817FA6442DEA4E89E78E87B5E52" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Demonstration program on accession of candidates with auditory impairments as Air Force officers</header> <subsection id="H280FF89390234486B99DEC7D47101B4E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Demonstration program required</header><text>Beginning not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Air Force shall carry out a demonstration program to assess the feasibility and advisability of permitting individuals with auditory impairments (including deafness) to access as officers of the Air Force.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HF05BB7D803C14625BBA49253976F2EC7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Candidates</header>
 <paragraph id="H3BC17131A50B4DA590C5F07A5742CD0D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Number of candidates</header><text>The total number of individuals with auditory impairments who may participate in the demonstration program shall be not fewer than 15 individuals or more than 20 individuals.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCE4D05A220634D2D85DBC36F226A2361"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Mix and range of auditory impairments</header><text>The individuals who participate in the demonstration program shall include individuals who are deaf and individuals who have a range of other auditory impairments.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5B1C02B29CF6401CBEBA57CBFEE20A7E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Qualification for accession</header><text>Any individual who is chosen to participate in the demonstration program shall meet all essential qualifications for accession as an officer in the Air Force, other than those related to having an auditory impairment.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA13A6BFDAFA04520941185711BC46A2A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Selection of participants</header>
 <paragraph id="H21F42F9999DE4758908773F49AF73027"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Air Force shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H4D00413B9CE34BB58088D3993D9F2FCC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>publicize the demonstration program nationally, including to individuals who have auditory impairments and would be otherwise qualified for officer training;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H842EE22044BC4CB78892279A9BA9DB27"><enum>(B)</enum><text>create a process whereby interested individuals can apply for the demonstration program; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CE82E00F1564BE9A59D45523F3F2136"><enum>(C)</enum><text>select the participants for the demonstration program, from among the pool of applicants, based on the criteria in subsection (b).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HED7770B6C6CD4C1F97978AE18436141A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No prior service as Air Force officers</header><text>Participants selected for the demonstration program shall be individuals who have not previously served as officers in the Air Force.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF4B0D8C8B4574B16B18ECBA9DADE24B5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Basic officer training</header>
 <paragraph id="H369B7B0282114C7298C1744224E22A46"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The participants in the demonstration program shall undergo, at the election of the Secretary of the Air Force, the Basic Officer Training course or the Commissioned Officer Training course at Maxwell Air Force Base, Alabama.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9A9A0E984418424EA93D67C597B59A71"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Number of participants</header><text>Once individuals begin participating in the demonstration program, each Basic Officer Training course or Commissioned Officer Training course at Maxwell Air Force Base, Alabama, shall include not fewer than four, or more than six, participants in the demonstration program until all participants have completed such training.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H09C049D64B684333AE8431C614215195"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Auxiliary aids and services</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall ensure that participants in the demonstration program have the necessary auxiliary aids and services (as that term is defined in section 4 of the Americans With Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12103">42 U.S.C. 12103</external-xref>)) in order to fully participate in the demonstration program.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H908E0605148D4A02A26FC0A85EAEDEFC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Coordination</header>
 <paragraph id="H596B37C916C0484F9F883820C7AB4056"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Special advisor</header><text>The Secretary of the Air Force shall designate a special advisor to the demonstration program to act as a resource for participants in the demonstration program, as well as a liaison between participants in the demonstration program and those providing the officer training.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5094F35496624052AD4DBAA47AC57F7C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text>The special advisor shall be a member of the Armed Forces on active duty—</text> <subparagraph id="H690E6FB4DCD04B199873779B7BA91131"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who—</text>
 <clause id="H984292E549C846019EE3040957586699"><enum>(i)</enum><text>if a commissioned officer, shall be in grade O–3 or higher; or</text> </clause><clause id="H05BFCF5C87AC44C19D8ED6FDD8A8F825"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if an enlisted member, shall be in grade E–5 or higher; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3533262D671B41118EF9BEFEAF8B5C8D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who is knowledgeable about issues involving, and accommodations for, individuals with auditory impairments (including deafness).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H894FC5E3F744406C8D0F561A005038EE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The special advisor shall be responsible for facilitating the officer training for participants in the demonstration program, intervening and resolving issues and accommodations during the training, and such other duties as the Secretary of the Air Force may assign to facilitate the success of the demonstration program and participants.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H02FE69263F4D4DDF8362D53434848905"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Air Force shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the demonstration program. The report shall include the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HDB132943036D4D3AB064D2484A3E5119"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of the demonstration program and the participants in the demonstration program.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H287892F351C947B2A573500FA05E9A2D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The outcome of the demonstration program, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H14EE67778C984E87A7E37E58A6C8FA13"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of participants in the demonstration program that successfully completed the Basic Officer Training course or the Commissioned Officer Training course;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61DFE78D20A4445D9E476851AEBF0DBE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of participants in the demonstration program that were recommended for continued military service;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8208312E102A49A8863D44D0EF7F2B6B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the issues that were encountered during the program; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE393A722689B49B3BB7F259A5791582F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such recommendation for modifications to the demonstration program as the Secretary considers appropriate to increase further inclusion of individuals with auditory disabilities serving as officers in the Air Force or other Armed Forces.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H665339A14B7741AAB9F08E91E609497C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Such recommendations for legislative or administrative action as the Secretary considers appropriate in light of the demonstration program.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7D605A9404C4475080E37787B26548DB"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>appropriate committees of Congress</quote> means—</text> <paragraph id="H98561DC74D4B4586BD69A9A3F557867B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions, and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD19B878B494640E2830B0208AE9AD849"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


