<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H3FF4AA5F49C54AA58FFAEBFEC1F2EAD2" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5742 IH: Port of Whitman Economic Expansion Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5742</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180509">May 9, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. McMorris Rodgers</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for a land exchange of Federal and non-Federal land in Whitman County, Washington.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H1EB68CBB2058468BBD167F7E71DF9620" style="OLC">
 <section id="H6041D943DE3440A78C81276CE6D7F94F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Port of Whitman Economic Expansion Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H8DEF3BC3385240A8887790A2999431E8" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Port of Whitman County</header> <subsection id="H12137CC3663F4A298FFF4C425C8AE16B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
 <paragraph id="H01E4AE7712A74E21A19F342B21E5ADFB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal land</header><text>The term <quote>Federal land</quote> means the approximately 288 acres of land situated in Whitman County, Washington, contained within Tract D of Little Goose Lock and Dam.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF0F8B32E714D42C6A03CA0CBEEAF1C6E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Non-Federal land</header><text>The term <quote>non-Federal land</quote> means a tract or tracts of land owned by the Port of Whitman County, Washington, the fish and wildlife habitat value of which the Secretary of the Army determines, in coordination with the Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife and the Secretary of the Interior acting through the Director of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, to equal or exceed the fish and wildlife habitat value of the Federal land.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0F8EEAE6C7D343AF932C64629C0FA263"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Land exchange</header><text>On conveyance by the Port of Whitman County to the United States of all right, title, and interest in and to the non-Federal land, the Secretary of the Army shall convey to the Port of Whitman County all right, title, and interest of the United States in and to the Federal land.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H68EA7543F6E8413FAEAEFF8CFC0A216D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Deeds</header>
 <paragraph id="H1B9B6FB07B4144D2A273DA6143FE629A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deed to non-Federal land</header><text>The Secretary may only accept conveyance of the non-Federal land by warranty deed, as determined acceptable by the Secretary.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H76C459B152C3423CA6FA0206BC2114BD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deed to Federal land</header><text>The Secretary shall convey the Federal land to the Port of Whitman County by quitclaim deed and subject to any reservations, terms, and conditions the Secretary determines necessary to allow the United States to operate and maintain the Lower Snake River Project and to protect the interests of the United States.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE2A9567E53EC484CB8B4B4FFA2083A5B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Cash payment</header><text>If the appraised fair market value of the Federal land, as determined by the Secretary, exceeds the appraised fair market value of the non-Federal land, as determined by the Secretary, the Port of Whitman County shall make a cash payment to the United States reflecting the difference in the appraised fair market values.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H199F356BFCEB49ECB4D72C1EA4646D6B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Administrative expenses</header><text>The Port of Whitman County shall be responsible for the administrative costs of the transaction in accordance with section 2695 of title 10, United States Code.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H0AF9D121282C477DBD098B6273586165"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Liability</header><text>The Port of Whitman County shall hold the United States harmless from any liability with respect to activities carried out on the Federal land on or after the date of the conveyance.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H28D7FAF4DCFB4C90BF5D38147CA20DC5"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Applicability of real property screening provisions</header><text>Section 2696 of title 10, United States Code, shall not apply to the conveyance of the Federal land under this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H58922B985FC84F56B59DAB82CFA5E296"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Survey To obtain legal description</header><text>The exact acreage and legal description of the Federal land and non-Federal land shall be determined by a survey that is satisfactory to the Secretary.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


