<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H84EDA0E13AB34968BA0C4598816CDF6C" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5687 IH: Securing Opioids and Unused Narcotics with Deliberate Disposal and Packaging Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5687</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180507">May 7, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001067">Mr. Hudson</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001251">Mr. Butterfield</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001305">Mr. Budd</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act to require improved packaging and disposal
			 methods with respect to certain drugs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HA61B94558BFD45849F9FF0E2F8CD8688" style="OLC">
 <section id="H8DDB18D0CF5F40BE8FEEF95B95BDC39F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing Opioids and Unused Narcotics with Deliberate Disposal and Packaging Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SOUND Disposal and Packaging Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H7CC324B607AA47C19305084FA70A2934" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improved technologies, controls, or measures with respect to the packaging or disposal of certain drugs</header> <subsection id="H8CF756EFABAD4C1EB09B002460AED858"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Chapter V of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act is amended by inserting after section 505–1 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355-1">21 U.S.C. 355–1</external-xref>) the following new section:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1955626EE73044A7BCCA4EF3080A507D" style="OLC">
					<section id="H986586463A3D4485A2B0DFB2B028BBCC"><enum>505–2.</enum><header>Safety-enhancing packaging and disposal features</header>
						<subsection id="H8D5431DE0ADA4C5FA4863BB4AB675EE1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Orders</header>
 <paragraph id="H6CAB41653DD34BED930692C6266301E8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may, after consultation with relevant stakeholders, issue an order requiring the holder of a covered application to implement or modify one or more technologies, controls, or measures with respect to the packaging or disposal of one or more drugs identified in the covered application, if the Secretary determines such technologies, controls, or measures to be appropriate to help mitigate the risk of abuse or misuse of such drug or drugs, including by reducing the availability of unused drugs.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H95B9CF31BAC9439499FA94437093AABD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assuring access and minimizing burden</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Technologies, controls, or measures required under paragraph (1) shall—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H1EB9702E4FB34C1B92C559BFE44BC513"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be commensurate with the specific risk of abuse or misuse of the drug listed in the covered application;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H29B2885E46AF4E3B89F744618BFFFA61"><enum>(B)</enum><text>considering such risk, not be unduly burdensome on patient access to the drug, considering in particular the available evidence regarding the expected or demonstrated public health impact of such technologies, controls, or measures; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H770890DC0799401DA76092DC3AB1B953"><enum>(C)</enum><text>reduce the risk of abuse or misuse of such drug.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC37387667A9F4175ABFBF52AC20E59A1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Order contents</header><text>An order issued under paragraph (1) may—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD9145E08546348BDBA2FEE5F07502757"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide for a range of options for implementing or modifying the technologies, controls, or measures required to be implemented by such order; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD0018383C704F4C822AE17EA05C0E64"><enum>(B)</enum><text>incorporate by reference standards regarding packaging or disposal set forth in an official compendium, established by a nationally or internationally recognized standard development organization, or described on the public Internet website of the Food and Drug Administration, so long as the order includes the rationale for incorporation of such standard.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB349D4149DD14C388D1EC093A8CF1FE2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Orders applicable to drug class</header><text>When a concern about the risk of abuse or misuse of a drug relates to a pharmacological class, the Secretary may, after consultation with relevant stakeholders, issue an order under paragraph (1) which applies to the pharmacological class.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H586CD673C2AC4D48952745840B67939F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Compliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The holder of a covered application shall—</text> <paragraph id="HA400AD275CF44F0191834C0696AAEF20"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit a supplement containing proposed changes to the covered application to comply with an order issued under subsection (a) not later than—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H6A9E5C3CB73A4A25BF69B835046A7564"><enum>(A)</enum><text>180 calendar days after the date on which the order is issued; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB863A7E6E5E84A369AA09F6951F89F1B"><enum>(B)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H86D898355AC84FC7B1FE1668A04438CD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such longer time period as specified by the Secretary in such order; or</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H0CB687D44173477691748B352C2E4466" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if a request for an alternative date is submitted by the holder of such application not later than 60 calendar days after the date on which such order is issued—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="H9A7D9D9C29C54D308A6A381291902273"><enum>(I)</enum><text>such requested alternative date if agreed to by the Secretary; or</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H659C879B992D4660B81BC7DDD57570D1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>another date as specified by the Secretary; and</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C806F46E566499DA80D6EE62B49EF03"><enum>(2)</enum><text>implement the changes approved pursuant to such supplement not later than the later of—</text> <subparagraph id="H7F805FAF11A349E5A5F5B30454B16831"><enum>(A)</enum><text>90 calendar days after the date on which the supplement is approved; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF72FD41DED6248E6AA82E89BE2EECB88"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the end of such longer period as is—</text> <clause id="H76DCCC5819FC47D19B9258B78169BDD9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>determined to be appropriate by the Secretary; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H3F333883D532414CB9B76F2698EDB399"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">approved by the Secretary pursuant to a request by the holder of the covered application that explains why such longer period is needed, including to satisfy any other applicable Federal statutory or regulatory requirements.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF3541978D6B14FC8BFA476E7021FBD00"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Alternative measures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The holder of the covered application may propose, and the Secretary shall approve, technologies, controls, or measures regarding packaging, storage, or disposal other than those specified in the applicable order issued under subsection (a), if such technologies, controls, or measures are supported by data and information demonstrating that such alternative technologies, controls, or measures can be expected to mitigate the risk of abuse or misuse of the drug or drugs involved, including by reducing the availability of unused drugs, to at least the same extent as the technologies, controls, or measures specified in such order.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H7C8C78C0B6C8415CB0B40390ED740B64"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Dispute resolution</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a dispute arises in connection with a supplement submitted under subsection (b), the holder of the covered application may appeal a determination made with respect to such supplement using applicable dispute resolution procedures specified by the Secretary in regulations or guidance.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD8262D4339CF498591E7E87159BAB63E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section—</text> <paragraph id="HAD872D258EE14F5794DEC6A344554407"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>covered application</term> means an application submitted under subsection (b) or (j) of section 505 for approval under such section or an application approved under section 351 of Public Health Service Act, with respect to a drug that is or contains an opioid for which a listing in schedule II or III (on a temporary or permanent basis) is in effect under section 202 of the Controlled Substances Act; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5B9F63075E5844E89512E019C73C1252"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>relevant stakeholders</term> may include scientific experts within the drug manufacturing industry; brand and generic drug manufacturers; standard development organizations; wholesalers and distributors; payers; health care providers; pharmacists; manufacturers; poison centers; and representatives of the National Institute on Drug Abuse, the National Institutes of Health, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services, the Drug Enforcement Agency, the Consumer Product Safety Commission, individuals who specialize in treating addiction, and patient and caregiver groups.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H638B6FB10C3249C9A6BFF6D653E454AF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibited acts</header><text>Section 501 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/351">21 U.S.C. 351</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after paragraph (j) the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC7CCF54E1672421E944B5E234A263000" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="HA887648CF7B041E2AE90AD5C129C3E52"><enum>(k)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If it is a drug approved under a covered application (as defined in section 505–2(e)), the holder of which does not meet the requirements of paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (b) of such section.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H449E408752F048D594ECA2013C113794"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Required content of an abbreviated new drug application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 505(j)(2)(A) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(j)(2)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H446C424D83FD469BB9BD4AAE03CF33EC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (vii)(IV), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB965FF27326E4B02ACD5475D0B1B385D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (viii), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAA331BFFC2DE4A4BB8A1C9760BDB22DE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC85BEAF740DF434FB7B5355774F0169E" style="OLC"> <clause id="HF06FF18DD7974EBF8C1BC9821CEAD71F"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the drug is or contains an opioid for which a listing in schedule II or III (on a temporary or permanent basis) is in effect under section 202 of the Controlled Substances Act, information to show that the applicant has proposed technologies, controls, or measures related to the packaging or disposal of the drug that are comparably effective to those required for the applicable listed drug under section 505–2, if applicable.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFC04A9F3510D4412B4B92090188923BF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grounds for refusing To approve an abbreviated new drug application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 505(j)(4) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(j)(4)</external-xref>), is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H95C2EA702B3A458BBECD65E7B3257466"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (J), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H14BB6520FA074E07BBA436ADB889D354"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (K), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HD1691BB7929747748F2DC70B0AB3D02F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H168DEDF7FD0E42A48984C7F520B29A86" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="HE8E6F7BD3527481FBEC2FBDA0EE97FD1"><enum>(L)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the drug is a drug described in paragraph (2)(A)(ix) and the applicant has not proposed technologies, controls, or measures related to the packaging or disposal of such drug that the Secretary determines are comparably effective to those required for the applicable listed drug under section 505–2.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE03D1EEAF0E3403E8589ACD6B6AD0516"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header>
 <paragraph id="H07A54AC57BC947998E11BE2B8405A262"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Any labeling describing technologies, controls, or measures related to packaging, storage, or disposal intended to mitigate the risk of abuse or misuse of a drug product that is subject to an abbreviated new drug application, including labeling describing differences from the reference listed drug resulting from the application of section 505–2 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, as added by subsection (a), shall not be construed—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H589A8193634D45B6AAB9E332C3A6E657"><enum>(A)</enum><text>as changes to labeling not permissible under clause (v) of section 505(j)(2)(A) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(j)(2)(A)</external-xref>), or a change in the conditions of use prescribed, recommended, or suggested in the labeling proposed for the new drug under clause (i) of such section; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23D1C695870A4766A7610D5F1711E9AB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to prohibit approval of an abbreviated new drug application under subparagraph (B) or (G) of section 505(j)(4) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(j)(4)</external-xref>).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H90A3DECA493C44C4BB4B08A62215F306"><enum>(2)</enum><text>For a covered application that is an application submitted under subjection (j) of section 505 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355</external-xref>), subparagraph (j)(2)(A) of such section 505 shall not be construed to limit the type of data or information the Secretary of Health and Human Services may request or consider in connection with making any determination under section 505–2.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF41B342C75F249C6B41BF1F02AFD3230"><enum>(f)</enum><header>GAO report</header><text>Not later than 12 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall prepare and submit to the Congress a report containing—</text>
 <paragraph id="H9A632118E00B4483998DE300342C4BE8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of available evidence, if any, on the effectiveness of site-of-use, in-home controlled substance disposal products and packaging technologies;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB41C920E51E84017899493ABF88B596F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identification of ways in which such disposal products intended for use by patients, consumers, and other end users that are not registrants under the Controlled Substances Act, are made available to the public and barriers to the use of such disposal products;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8F5B927F85E74E4F8EF7778ED359B223"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identification of ways in which packaging technologies are made available to the public and barriers to the use of such technologies;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAE4183273AA4476EBBBE8746C6AD634A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a description of Federal oversight, if any, of site-of-use, in-home controlled substance disposal products, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H98856C423778433A87B8CC38E5367A47"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identification of the Federal agencies that oversee such products;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E0764037B2047F59EC3EC94984E22B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identification of the methods of disposal of controlled substances recommended by these agencies for site-of-use, in-home disposal; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H644BEA68B39046A88DD5EB20B97959A1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of the effectiveness of such recommendations at preventing the diversion of legally prescribed controlled substances;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB22DAB124294DC3A2BF5778261AA037"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a description of Federal oversight, if any, of controlled substance packaging technologies, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HCA28E7288DDD40BC9F319E77383ED37C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identification of the Federal agencies that oversee such technologies;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1DEB567AB8034625BDBD759C6EACDC87"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identification of the technologies recommended by these agencies, including unit dose packaging, packaging that provides a set duration, or other packaging systems that may mitigate abuse or misuse; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF37436DDF00A459083DB7154092E3018"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of the effectiveness of such recommendations at preventing the diversion of legally prescribed controlled substances; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H62AC192A246648BB89A88D297886F3BB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>recommendations on—</text> <subparagraph id="H7288AF99C16F405094E5096FA5D5CB6F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>whether site-of-use, in-home controlled substance disposal products and packaging technologies require Federal oversight and, if so, which agencies should be responsible for such oversight and, as applicable, approval of such products or technologies; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5EA8A99E492F480E871858AA2937DDCC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the potential role of the Federal Government in evaluating such products to ensure product efficacy.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


