<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA6D59F30F2F74360A80B096E230147CA" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4973 IH: Chiropractic Health Parity for Military Beneficiaries Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4973</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180207">February 7, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000575">Mr. Rogers of Alabama</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000565">Mr. Loebsack</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Defense to develop and implement a plan to provide chiropractic health
			 care services and benefits for certain new beneficiaries as part of the
			 TRICARE program.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H6A689998FC4B4D01A6A9A7B4B8C17096" style="OLC">
 <section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBD132B36BE414ACE9C5B62636D140381" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Chiropractic Health Parity for Military Beneficiaries Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H0893F95775904428816F9707E8FA6E95"><enum>2.</enum><header>Chiropractic health care for retirees, dependents, and survivors</header> <subsection id="H26B76A55BC014B12B3C5898F1ECFE976"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Plan required</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall complete development of a plan to provide chiropractic health care services and benefits, as a permanent part of the TRICARE program, for covered beneficiaries.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H2FEEEFE440F84DB2BE30D4A16C018EEC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of plan</header><text>The plan shall require that a contract entered into under section 1097 of title 10, United States Code, for the delivery of health care services shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H3B057B6F119946529C23D4771FBF2548"><enum>(1)</enum><text>include the delivery of chiropractic services;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H69DCFB9BAB2646329B830AAED8A5FDDB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>require that chiropractic services may be provided only by a doctor of chiropractic; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H096FF704D12743149DBB2A89E2637F3E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide that a covered beneficiary may select and have direct access to a doctor of chiropractic without referral by another health practitioner.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3F26D72CAB3244AAB95FD7300F3C53B8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Implementation of plan</header><text>The plan developed under subsection (a) shall provide for implementation of the plan to begin not later than 60 days after the date on which the plan is completed.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="HC2A0376FD4554E68BF6834168C8D61EB"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H261BB9C2416249DCA1E948D3F634C28F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>chiropractic services</term>—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H682F6472E1F44AA780F11C536362561C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes diagnosis (including by diagnostic x-ray tests), evaluation and management, and therapeutic services for the treatment of a patient's health condition, including neuro­mus­cu­lo­skel­etal conditions and the subluxation complex, and such other services determined appropriate by the Secretary and as authorized under State law; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H780BBD0E8084430096CE08178B272C33"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include the use of drugs or surgery.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H750195A14A574736A1E0319061960DBC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>covered beneficiary</term> has the meaning provided by section 1072(5) of title 10, United States Code.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8C33553BC33142D695BDB0E5A335F8AC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>doctor of chiropractic</term> means only a doctor of chiropractic who is licensed as a doctor of chiropractic, chiropractic physician, or chiropractor by a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory or possession of the United States.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA673088791FE4302BFED892BD5B77775"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>TRICARE program</term> has the meaning provided by section 1072(7) of title 10, United States Code.</text> </paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

