<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HD25545B910BD40879297A3A46117E910" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5056 IH: Confederate Commemorative Works Inventory and Joint Resource Study Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5056</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180215">February 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001200">Mr. McEachin</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001304">Mr. Brown of Maryland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000465">Ms. Tsongas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001270">Ms. Bass</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000324">Mr. Hastings</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of the Interior, the Secretary of Defense, and the Secretary of Veterans
			 Affairs to
			 inventory Confederate commemorative works on certain Federal lands, and
			 for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H626772BEC07C447A8049C9C7A73EF6FD" style="OLC">
 <section id="H6ABB6DC43A994BC5AFB999D54BEE380F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Confederate Commemorative Works Inventory and Joint Resource Study Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H1B0E4E87F8D841A485EB97C84AD6544E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HB1E04FCD7FC74E3CA611B9D463BA91A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The American Civil War was fought between 1861 and 1865.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H97F9254F25A4435BA790C4BF91860E24"><enum>(2)</enum><text>As early as 1864, efforts were underway to preserve places that had been the location of pivotal battles during the Civil War, even before surrender occurred.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC889B15F6D1C4424A7434E018A6625FB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The National Park Service preserves unimpaired the natural and cultural resources and values of the National Park System for the enjoyment, education, and inspiration of this and future generations, including sites dedicated to the interpretation of the American Civil War.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5F80F4D23AFF44BCB6A888E958B6D57F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The National Park Service, the Department of Veterans Affairs, and the Department of Defense administer public lands that are responsible for Confederate commemorative works.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H04095970718C4260A7231129C4066E44"><enum>(5)</enum><text>There are 147 national cemeteries in the United States. Fourteen are maintained by the Department of the Interior, through the National Park Service. The Department of Veterans Affairs, through the National Cemetery Administration, administers 131 cemeteries. The Department of Defense, through the Army, administers 2 cemeteries.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCA2DF3756F8347F19D62931A4A0FAA00"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Defense has jurisdiction over—</text> <subparagraph id="H89FC187230FB4318A28314FCF57FF2BF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>10 major United States military installations named in honor of Confederate military leaders; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4C3EEB6CB6F44AABFF731D125875C1A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Navy ships named after Confederate victories.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H07AB6BB830A340088BD7C62632E4766F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For the purposes of this Act:</text>
 <paragraph id="H24A8FE3BEC754190A4E371FBA1570733"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Confederate commemorative work</header><text>The term <term>Confederate commemorative work</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H67C080AC80A54819817C842516044702"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any work that mentions individuals or units who participated or served in the advancement of Confederate efforts; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2ADF5FF2DF34999A66C5A45ABAC19C0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes the Confederate flag and any other symbols or signage that honors the Confederacy, including any monument, statue, or plaque that honors a Confederate leader, soldier, or supporter of the Confederate States of America.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8AC26DAA9D3433B8B9DB61E2A2C9021"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Confederate Flag</header><text>The term <term>Confederate flag</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H044E9E63D38D4CBDB04048718E9AE878"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means the national flag of the Confederacy from 1861 through 1865; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H865786DBD053498DA63BB8E5673A4B8D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes the Stars and Bars, the Stainless Banner, the Blood-Stained Banner, the Confederate States Navy flag, the battle flag of the Army of Northern Virginia, any State or regimental flag as such flag was depicted during 1861–1865, and modern representations of the Confederate battle flag.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C24B5757ECD486D9107672C63B24A5C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the National Park Service.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE96366AB111F464A8A5844CB9FB40567"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary concerned</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Secretary concerned</term> means the Secretary of the Interior, the Secretary of Defense, and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, each in reference to Federal land under the jurisdiction of that Secretary.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="HB4A7D1E5FE38473394C3FDF5AFC9D1CC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Inventory and resource study</header>
 <subsection id="H288FFB36786B4C33844B12977AE9E2D4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each Secretary concerned shall—</text> <paragraph id="H1A6F8E57136F4BE0A29A2CDC9F30D3DD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct a full inventory of Confederate commemorative works under the administrative jurisdiction of that Secretary; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0523463EA83D4FB491977C50930B2A48"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit a copy of that inventory to the Director.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2961F62A449B4265BF1F28FB3B65CEC0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of study</header><text>Using the inventories received pursuant to subsection (a), the Director shall conduct a special resource study that—</text>
 <paragraph id="H09F6D3FCD31345C59D5006AC0F776187"><enum>(1)</enum><text>examines works, commemorating and interpreting the Civil War, the commemoration thereof, the soldiers, people on the home front and battle lines, and the related locations in the United States from 1861 through 1865; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H056395A614CF4975AD53AE7A426E0888"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identifies—</text> <subparagraph id="H3F5C6FBFB4E44548AF681F17A20DEA6A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a historical assessment, based on extensive research, of each inventoried Confederate commemorative work;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAFC97EE910CC46638923C18DE3FB7E34"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an evaluation of the suitability and feasibility of retaining the Confederate commemorative work;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5000A1C2D9C4824B4F6B5CAB7D1F505"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the identification of properties that could meet criteria for listing in the National Register of Historic Places or criteria for designation as National Historic Landmarks or if the Confederate commemorative work is already on the or part of, another designation or district;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7307F4B3A785476BA62F5A3A0F522119"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an evaluation of relevant historical research on, education about, interpretation of, and public awareness of the Confederate commemorative work; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0AA504E221564A41B038A0F5359C0A47"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any other matters that the Director determines to be appropriate for this study.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H964A11D783A046E98DF06C4333F3C414"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after funds are made available for the study, the Secretary of the Interior shall submit to the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate a report containing the findings of the study required under subsection (b) and any related recommendations.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


