<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA37BA99D04D64B188F8EC31D17715CD1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4805 IH: No Federal Funding to Benefit Sanctuary Cities Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4805</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180116">January 16, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001189">Mr. Messer</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ensure that State and local law enforcement may cooperate with Federal officials to protect our communities from violent criminals and suspected terrorists who are illegally present in the United States, to stop taxpayer dollars from flowing to jurisdictions that fail to comply with Federal law, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1768B90A8A954FBA8AAECB8CF4B349C0" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H35B237A31AEF4A6DBFA6E3F882A5E9CA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Federal Funding to Benefit Sanctuary Cities Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> <section id="H06EB3F22404D4011B5A89629A6DF9B7A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Protecting local and Federal law enforcement officers who cooperate to safeguard communities</header> <subsection id="H2F4A58C3646048B5AA13E5E668178CD3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State, a political subdivision of a State, or an officer, employee, or agent of such State or political subdivision that takes action to comply with a detainer issued by the Department of Homeland Security under section 236 or 287 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1226">8 U.S.C. 1226</external-xref> and 1357)—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF17E958BC6FB4175948D828A7E8205BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall be deemed to be acting as an agent of the Department of Homeland Security; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4483CEB01F574337AE25AB9E2AFCB298"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with regard to such actions, shall have all authority available to officers and employees of the Department of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H97FEECC6AB72406EBC86828132CED8E0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Legal proceedings</header><text>In any legal proceeding brought against a State, a political subdivision of a State, or an officer, employee, or agent of such State or political subdivision, which challenges the legality of the seizure or detention of an individual pursuant to a detainer issued by the Department of Homeland Security under section 236 or 287 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1226">8 U.S.C. 1226</external-xref> and 1357)—</text> <paragraph id="H37116F0193BE49189DDBCB9E89E53680"><enum>(1)</enum><text>no liability shall lie against the State or political subdivision of a State for actions taken in compliance with the detainer; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H14A2951A08D24AF4B9E298ADAF06A2F4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if the actions of the officer, employee, or agent of the State or political subdivision were taken in compliance with the detainer—</text> <subparagraph id="H22E8221CBAF040D38B52CB29DB38AA21"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the officer, employee, or agent shall be deemed—</text> 
<clause id="HBF560C415D3D4BA2A85F9D2D8FC0C16D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to be an employee of the Federal Government and an investigative or law enforcement officer; and</text></clause> <clause id="H607A403B614C4C5D864143E062EFE112"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to have been acting within the scope of his or her employment under section 1346(b) and <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/171">chapter 171</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H78C49A16A9D048ED9B8FBE977970FDAB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 1346(b) of title 28, United States Code, shall provide the exclusive remedy for the plaintiff; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE75C2E868487490E88832EF30394EEED"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the United States shall be substituted as defendant in the proceeding.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8D179C8591744E6488D74E9A58B6D8BC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to provide immunity to any person who knowingly violates the civil or constitutional rights of an individual.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HBDF09A35CF554EEB93E3D4BE7E115BF4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sanctuary jurisdictions ineligible for Federal funds</header> <subsection id="H3BEC695AD32D433DB9D305FB7C3B2926"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning with fiscal year 2019, a sanctuary jurisdiction is ineligible to receive Federal financial assistance (as defined in section 7501 of title 31, United States Code).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H10A2CDF600F54604922E26FE62D6EC5E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sanctuary jurisdiction defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <term>sanctuary jurisdiction</term> means any State or political subdivision of a State that has in effect a statute, ordinance, policy, or practice that prohibits or restricts any government entity or official from—</text> <paragraph id="HB893B5E2A2C44C0CAB90DBA8DDC454CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>sending, receiving, maintaining, or exchanging with any Federal, State, or local government entity information regarding the citizenship or immigration status (lawful or unlawful) of any individual; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0CDC4009BA4A409687D2B2F477D9D21F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>complying with a request lawfully made by the Department of Homeland Security under section 236 or 287 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1226">8 U.S.C. 1226</external-xref> and 1357) to comply with a detainer for, or notify about the release of, an individual.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0EF2E022655F43838B15E13E03D677E0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Returned amounts</header> <paragraph id="H17A80E4093BB4363A36137454B36EC87"><enum>(1)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a State is a sanctuary jurisdiction during a period in fiscal year 2019 or thereafter for which it receives Federal financial assistance (as defined in section 7501 of title 31, United States Code) from an Executive agency (as defined in section 105 of title 5, United States Code), the head of such agency—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H68071D63109643088C8FC10237F44F04"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall direct the State immediately to return any such amounts that the State received for that period; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF768777F694448B5B140C9E09DE4B75B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall reallocate amounts returned under subparagraph (A) to other States that are not sanctuary jurisdictions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1D4D873875F6403887F202ED4A5C3EB6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Unit of general local government</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a unit of general local government is a sanctuary jurisdiction during a period in fiscal year 2019 or thereafter for which it receives Federal financial assistance (as defined in section 7501 of title 31, United States Code) from an Executive agency (as defined in section 105 of title 5, United States Code), any such amounts that the unit of general local government received for that period—</text> <subparagraph id="H4094E816E73441CDA6445CD0605E586B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a unit of general local government that is not in a nonentitlement area, shall be returned the head of such agency for reallocation to States and other units of general local government that are not sanctuary jurisdictions; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0171C5EC30FC4929A5E40D4A6E14076F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a unit of general local government that is in a nonentitlement area, shall be returned to the Governor of the State for reallocation to other units of general local government in the State that are not sanctuary jurisdictions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection> </section> </legis-body></bill>

