<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H6D3BFC6B26A1459EBFDF796D2595E005" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4932 IH: Women and Climate Change Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4932</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180205">February 5, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000288">Mr. Ellison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001101">Ms. Clark of Massachusetts</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000390">Mr. Kihuen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000324">Mr. Hastings</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000486">Ms. Roybal-Allard</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To address the disparate impact of climate change on women and support the efforts of women
			 globally to address climate change, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HAE817EF3945744738AD230BAD4D24DA5" style="OLC">
		<section id="HB852D25DECC94C5F876CA0EF5E5476BB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header>
 <subsection id="HDDAD02B6B68841DA9EC4D871B234E469"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Women and Climate Change Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H4E4739228F8744D7AFBE276EF5978CE2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
				<toc container-level="legis-body-container" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration">
					<toc-entry idref="HB852D25DECC94C5F876CA0EF5E5476BB" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H7B62811D07944ADCB134B8E29973E6C0" level="section">Sec. 2. Findings.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H13DAD09B8B2442318186213E54B89E36" level="section">Sec. 3. Definitions.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H6ED6325E77DC4E54B3E569296B2D4D86" level="section">Sec. 4. Statement of policy.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H316056D2172642E1BDA7182FDC7CE0B4" level="title">Title I—Strategies, Policies, and Programs</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H70FB8125A4334F43878C93912C8A037B" level="section">Sec. 101. Federal Interagency Working Group on Women and Climate Change.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H569209C01B6147E6A08991A3C58DB54E" level="section">Sec. 102. Development and implementation of strategy and policies to prevent and respond to the
			 effects of climate change on women globally.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HF86A6183706A45E09BF20BC9A28A762B" level="title">Title II—Oversight and Accountability</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H2E5B64A6EB0D469B918FA5EABE6FE42D" level="section">Sec. 201. Senior coordinator for women and climate change.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HCAC8591BF2D346F9B9FE14DFB0ED5CB9" level="section">Sec. 202. Briefing and report.</toc-entry>
				</toc>
 </subsection></section><section id="H7B62811D07944ADCB134B8E29973E6C0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="HEA18D20FE8B341E7B753A6BF47CF9F06"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Women in the United States and around the world are the linchpin of families and communities and are often the first to feel the immediate and adverse effects of social, environmental, and economic stresses on their families and communities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H38BBAE65344A4900A9B15860051094E4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United Nations has recognized, as one of the central organizing principles for its work, that <quote>no enduring solution to society’s most threatening social, economic and political problems can be found without the full participation, and the full empowerment, of the world’s women</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE62438403BCC4B358BEE76A7CC49473D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The United Nations Development Programme 2013 Human Development Report has found that the number of people living in extreme poverty could increase by up to 3,000,000,000 by 2050 unless environmental disasters are averted by coordinated global action.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2120BF41A2FB48BBB665AC4573723384"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Climate change is already forcing vulnerable communities in developing countries to face unprecedented climate stress, including water scarcity and drought, as well as severe weather events and floods, which can lead to reduced agricultural productivity, food insecurity, and increased disease.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA9BB55B8A77E48A4A36271587EDA8AFC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Climate change exacerbates issues of scarcity and lack of accessibility to primary natural resources, forest resources, and arable land for food production, thereby contributing to increased conflict and instability, as well as the workload and stresses on women farmers, who are estimated to produce 60 to 80 percent of the food in most developing countries.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6EF1DFBE6D36458F98FB310C06C95072"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Women will disproportionately face harmful impacts from climate change, particularly in poor and developing nations where women regularly assume increased responsibility for growing the family’s food and collecting water, fuel, and other resources.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H26E109FCBB284ABA998585B7B9C09315"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Epidemics, such as malaria and zika, are expected to worsen and spread due to variations in climate, putting women (especially pregnant mothers and women who hope to become pregnant) and children without access to prevention and medical services at risk.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB1E6942681E949A7941154B350554200"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The direct and indirect effects of climate change have a disproportionate impact on marginalized women such as refugee and displaced persons, religious or ethnic minorities, adolescent girls, and women and girls with disabilities and those who are living with HIV.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5556803765854FA4B68C09179E1951D0"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Conflict has a disproportionate impact on the most vulnerable populations including women, and is fueled in the world’s poorest regions by harsher climate, leading to migration, refugee crises, and conflicts over scarce natural resources including land and water.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE8212847AAF04BCD8602949982797C55"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Displaced, refugee, and stateless women and girls face extreme violence and threats, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HA36F1BB4043D4D1A8756D123FF0CD61A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">being forced to exchange sex for food and humanitarian supplies;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD64FB429FF5A410FA4EDE39F0954BCCE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>being at increased risk of rape, sexual exploitation and abuse; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF36D89C021B848D5A1222EE87F74D091"><enum>(C)</enum><text>being at increased risk for HIV, STIs, unplanned pregnancy, and poor reproductive health.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9390A64419D64214B633BF2A7D7418A3"><enum>(11)</enum><text>It is predicted that climate change will lead to increasing frequency and intensity of extreme weather conditions, precipitating the occurrence of natural disasters around the globe.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2DAA52588BAB455EB8B696C65118523A"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The relocation and death of women, and especially mothers, as a result of climate-related disasters often has devastating impacts on social support networks, family ties, and the coping capacity of families and communities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2D0381318E4F4B0A949738623C9B9AE9"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The ability of women to adapt to climate change is constrained by a lack of economic freedoms, property and inheritance rights, as well as access to financial resources, education, family planning and reproductive health, and new tools, equipment, and technology.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6943B605158C40219F34396C809DFC08"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Despite a unique capacity and knowledge to promote and provide for adaptation to climate change, women often have insufficient resources to undertake such adaptation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA169A87C57014DB8AAD6133E65AF954B"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Women are shown to have a multiplier effect by using their income and resources, when given the necessary tools, to increase the well-being of their children and families, and thus play a critical role in reducing food insecurity, poverty, and socioeconomic effects of climate change.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H12C3B5C4DE5F47478B0DB6A0800CB16C"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Women are often underrepresented in the development and formulation of policy regarding mitigation and adaptation to climate change, even though they are often in the best position to provide and consult on adaptive strategies.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H13DAD09B8B2442318186213E54B89E36"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H116E1690C251409392E5362F95E22931"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD71DA319B4374477811C78D4F22C5459"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4FD16132A34D4C7D948C583626AE276B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4FC19D6B4444F37BE2778AE6AEA8083"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Climate change</header><text>The term <term>climate change</term> means a change of climate that is attributed directly or indirectly to human activity and altering the composition of the global atmosphere.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB94386C5AE7C4FACB70F0238971655F7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Developing country</header><text>The term <term>developing country</term> means those countries classified by the World Bank as having a low-income or lower-middle-income economy.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8FE66300CD0E4F3FA4E2D1629376FA73"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Disparate impact</header><text>The term <term>disparate impact</term> refers to the historic and ongoing impacts of the pattern and practice of discrimination in employment, education, housing, banking, health, and nearly every other aspect of life in the economy, society, or culture that have an adverse impact on minorities, women, or other protected groups, regardless of whether such practices were motivated by discriminatory intent.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD3945ACF01E94AB6959F79E49CC47718"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Environmental disasters</header><text>The term <term>environmental disasters</term> means specific events caused by human activity that result in seriously negative effects on the environment.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H36E5D44CE1EE4C5F89A4438D3550949E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Environmental refugees</header><text>The term <term>environmental refugees</term> means people displaced because of environmental causes, notably land loss and degradation, and natural disasters, who have left their community or country of origin.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H958885CC8F714BC38298EB2F82DD7DEF"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Extreme poverty</header><text>The term <term>extreme poverty</term> means having an income level or living standard at a level of extreme deprivation based on living with income below 50 percent of the poverty line as established by the individual country at issue, or below $1.90 per day as determined by the World Bank.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA6A51D1B96BC472B8C89241F3AAF25E6"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Extreme weather</header><text>The term <term>extreme weather</term> means unexpected, unusual, unpredictable, severe, or unseasonal weather that is at the extremes of the historical distribution range that has been seen in the past.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9F8E6571929C405BBB5477D5BC4F9583"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <term>Federal agency</term> means any executive department, Government corporation, Government-controlled corporation, or other establishment in the executive branch of the Government (including the Executive Office of the President), or any independent regulatory agency.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4DAAC7EBAAEC4D8FBC4BE983F99458D9"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Food insecurity</header><text>The term <term>food insecurity</term> means a lack of consistent access to food.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HFBEF5F4993604297BE227758C66832B1"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Most vulnerable communities and populations</header><text>The term <term>most vulnerable communities and populations</term> means communities and populations, including women, impoverished communities, children, people with disabilities, and indigenous peoples, who are at risk of substantial adverse impacts of climate change and have limited capacity to respond to such impacts.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF027350EFA37446DA8E34A34FCDEB408"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Poverty</header><text>The term <term>poverty</term> means an income level and living standard insufficient to meet basic needs.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="H6ED6325E77DC4E54B3E569296B2D4D86"><enum>4.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States, in partnership with affected countries, donor country governments, international financial institutions, international nongovernmental organizations, and civil society groups, especially those led by women, to combat the leading causes of climate change, mitigate the effects of climate change on women and girls, and elevate the participation of women in policy, program, and community decision-making processes with respect to climate change, by—</text>
 <paragraph id="HCB9B86C69A4648468FD218698E3D65B3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establishing the Federal Interagency Working Group on Women and Climate Change, mission of which is to prevent and respond to the effects of climate change on women globally; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBB2384E409E44DAB8A637191AC3869BD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>implementing a coordinated, integrated, evidence-based, and comprehensive strategy on Women and Climate Change throughout United States policies in the future.</text>
			</paragraph></section><title id="H316056D2172642E1BDA7182FDC7CE0B4"><enum>I</enum><header>Strategies, Policies, and Programs</header>
			<section id="H70FB8125A4334F43878C93912C8A037B"><enum>101.</enum><header>Federal Interagency Working Group on Women and Climate Change</header>
 <subsection id="H9385ED0E08F446BEB39F9F62C438392A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Department of State a Federal Interagency Working Group on Women and Climate Change, which shall be chaired by the Senior Coordinator for Women and Climate Change designated pursuant to section 201. Members of the Working Group shall be selected by their respective agency heads from the senior ranks of such agencies. The Working Group shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H1F378762C87F42DDBFEE28BBBE02EA03"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be composed of a senior representative from each of—</text> <subparagraph id="H51D5EA9C85824CC09C09900B4162CF99"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Department of State, including—</text>
 <clause id="H4294FD4BD5E24F66A9E69C91AB9F6B0B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Office of Global Women’s Issues;</text> </clause><clause id="HC9A9E9D27A574689B0BB4D38C60CEDCC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Office of Civil Rights;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H7383EF33EA384D609B3BD07225528D39"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Bureau of Oceans and International Environmental and Scientific Affairs;</text> </clause><clause id="H4D445103714E4A3199B84D2C57A69D7E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Bureau of Population, Refugees, and Migration;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H9140C74357144981813AA29C26FD4425"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor; and</text> </clause><clause id="H17F1DC8536F24B8E930A67A240E72237"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the Bureau of International Organization Affairs;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2F40F3FE51154A1CA3A6AF7295923960"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Agency for International Development;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCE605C43F7841969D7D843975664CD8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H136B16EA191F449F8DAC1314F8547D2B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Environmental Protection Agency;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H596E33EF53544AD2BB3FA605731F46D4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2351EF7F1447483EB6742B23A1B44FA3"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the National Institutes of Health;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC55FF595BB554873AB7B5D52B49980B0"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the National Science Foundation;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07E9075E58234F40A73E473D43130F2A"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the White House Council on Environmental Quality; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA624379E7DEE427E809106D499D0FFBD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>other members as designated by the Senior Coordinator;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C07A391CE4B4DCEAD00A557FB2B67DE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinate and integrate the development of all policies and activities of the Federal Government across all agencies relating to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H8B76396F63F746E6AC30CD287E9C5D2A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>combating the effects of climate change on women in the international sphere; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC19D580AE0F472AA8CEDF2041596E6B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>increasing the Federal Government response and strategy to fight climate change for the security of the United States and the international community;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBCCEF2BED5FC4488A44954AA24CEA41E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>allow each member of the Working Group to act as a representative for the Working Group within the Federal department or agency of such member to facilitate implementation of the Working Group policies within such department or agency;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6088A689682444458B016D70A12A49B1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>ensure that all relevant Federal departments or agencies comply with appropriate guidelines, policies, and directives from the Working Group, the Department of State, and other Federal departments or agencies with responsibilities relating to climate change;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H811A778109644CD0B990D5C1EE0FE775"><enum>(5)</enum><text>ensure that Federal departments or agencies, State governments, and relevant congressional committees, in consultation with nongovernmental organizations and policy experts in the field and State and local government officials who administer or direct policy for programs relating to climate change and women—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H2C25D33905D34F7E9A3EFAAF6F9A284A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>have access to, receive, and appropriately disseminate best practices in the administration of programs;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3CB2292D5EB44BDDB6621306D1DFD5BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have adequate resources to maximize the public awareness of such programs;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7DACCDC15EB34372B6E194D5E92B99DC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>increase the reach of such programs;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB27C2DF4E0794D938AF914CE1C53376A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>share relevant data; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC3D0BBE6C8734420944D2EFE128CE3AB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>issue relevant guidance; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF85543FE67EC44E280FE241683619A0C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>identify and disseminate best practices for improved data collection on the part of each agency and department relevant to the disparate impact of climate change on women, including in—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HC970EF01BDF94DE0B3C57D653060D555"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">unpaid care work;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3491EFFB4C06438AAC0CD65239EC144A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>community advocacy, activism, and representation;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1E707E2134564CDB837F5A2021DAB745"><enum>(C)</enum><text>women and girls’ access to education;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H792654098E7147C5A498EA204D28408E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>access to comprehensive health care, include reproductive health and rights;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H233F7308D3714A24A9093E2FDCC7FF68"><enum>(E)</enum><text>desertification and food insecurity;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H25FB6C88B5794F5286A7426CF6EE1A3E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>community infrastructure, multi-level Government adaptability, and climate-resilience;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1F5777ECDEB847D7A85A984CF1290F37"><enum>(G)</enum><text>climate and weather-related crisis response including safety from gender-based violence; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H15C36848021B461AB78E668085CE64E8"><enum>(H)</enum><text>women’s involvement and leadership in the development of frameworks and policies for climate resilience.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H53661EF58B9E41ED8F81B4960FF4B070"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation permitted</header><text>The Federal Interagency Working Group may consult and obtain recommendations from such independent nongovernmental policy experts, State and local government officials, independent groups and organizations, or other groups or organizations as the Senior Coordinator determines will assist in carrying out the mission of the Office.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HBC42C8B2F2F640138C856D2E0F28C02E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Frequency of meeting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Interagency Working Group shall meet on a quarterly basis to discuss and develop policies, projects, and programs, and shall meet with the Senior Coordinator for Women and Climate Change on a monthly basis to report on and discuss implementation of such policies, projects, and programs.</text>
				</subsection></section><section id="H569209C01B6147E6A08991A3C58DB54E"><enum>102.</enum><header>Development and implementation of strategy and policies to prevent and respond to the effects of
			 climate change on women globally</header>
 <subsection id="HCD983203041E4947845C810038B27803"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Initial strategy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Senior Coordinator for Women and Climate Change and the Ambassador-at-Large for the Office of Global Women’s Issues of the Department of State, in consultation with the Federal Interagency Working Group, shall develop and submit to the appropriate congressional committees a United States National and International Strategy to prevent and respond to the effects of climate change on women. The strategy shall include—</text>
 <paragraph id="HED9891AAE3C045CA8BC6015786F47EC1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recognizing the disparate impacts of climate change on women and the efforts of women globally to address climate change;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H85FD73D0E66C4E1FA5D09DF0687E238F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>taking effective action to prevent and respond to climate change and mitigate the effects of climate change on women around the world, as well as to promoting gender equality, economic growth, public health, racial justice, and human rights;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDD213B164A3B419BBDE143AF7161B5D4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>implementing the United Nations Sustainable Development goals listed in subsection (e), through and beyond 2030, as part of the strategy to prevent and respond to the effects of climate change on women globally;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H45BD633211124CAE9FC483055E506DFC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>implementing balanced participation of men and women, especially individuals from the communities most impacted, in climate change adaptation and mitigation efforts, including in governance and diplomatic positions within the United States Government;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H007AA15734A545D2A4D9EC32C65BDD5C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>working at the local, national, and international levels, including with individuals, families, and communities, to prevent and respond to the effects of climate change on women;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H06860AF8AE10450E9AEE11FE0A5E9CD2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>systematically integrating and coordinating efforts to prevent and respond to the effects of climate change on women internationally into United States foreign policy and foreign assistance programs;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9693BFE08C6C44C7AE5191004CAB8C2E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>investing in research on climate change through appropriate Federal departments or agencies and funding of university and independent research groups on the various causes and effects of climate change;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAC0CCD2CA6D442DD9C16B7C90157AB48"><enum>(8)</enum><text>developing and implementing gender-sensitive frameworks in policies to address climate change, which account for the specific impacts of climate change on women;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE3C10B3801F149F7B92738D5341A1688"><enum>(9)</enum><text>developing policies to support women who are particularly vulnerable to climate change impacts to prepare for, build their resilience, and adapt to such impacts, including a commitment to increase education and training opportunities for women to develop local resilience plans to address the effects of climate change;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6FDBF60A17BA44BF808914B271A694A0"><enum>(10)</enum><text>developing and investing in programs for the education and empowerment of women and girls in the United States and across the global community, including to gather information on how climate change is affecting their lives and for guidance on the needs of their families and communities in the face of climate change, in coordination with the diplomatic missions of other countries;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7FC1DCDCD3CF4208B6EE18D8042DA223"><enum>(11)</enum><text>consulting with representatives of civil society, including nongovernmental organizations, faith-based organizations, multilateral organizations, local and international civil society groups, and local climate change organizations and their beneficiaries with demonstrated experience in preventing and responding to the effects of climate change on women;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3FE1A154A20D4BCF9B1FF83CEC768B95"><enum>(12)</enum><text>supporting and building local capacity in developing countries, including with respect to governments at all levels and nongovernmental organizations (especially women-led), to prevent and respond to the effects of climate change on women;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE705946B7B59487AA933860A099932AA"><enum>(13)</enum><text>developing programs to empower women in communities to have a voice in the planning, design, implementation, and evaluation of strategies to address climate change so that their roles and resources are taken into account;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD444CEDDE2C642988EDD0E80B80E6C26"><enum>(14)</enum><text>including women in economic development planning, policies, and practices that directly improve conditions that result from climate change;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HEB162E8120614E9E849F2789A0BCD61D"><enum>(15)</enum><text>integrating a gender approach in all policies and programs in the United States that are globally related to climate change; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H317E4967FF9D45088584666C684E8A32"><enum>(16)</enum><text>ensuring that such policies and programs support women globally to prepare for, build resilience for, and adapt to climate change.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H0638538435954A95926D582A9DB0106E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Updates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Senior Coordinator for Women and Climate Change shall consult with the Federal Interagency Working Group to collect information and feedback, to update the strategy and programs to prevent and respond to the effects of climate change on women globally.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HB31C1356DA96464090376EA45B474041"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Implementation plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the submission of the strategy under subsection (a), the Senior Coordinator for Women and Climate Change shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees an implementation plan and budget for the strategy.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H6F5D303AA5F942909747A5AADC1A01E1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Assistance and consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Senior Coordinator for Women and Climate Change shall assist and provide consultation to the Secretary of State in preventing and responding to the effects of climate change on women globally.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5132554586F0470BAAD78DA69570D111"><enum>(e)</enum><header>United Nations sustainable development goals through and beyond 2030</header><text>The United Nations Sustainable Development goals listed in this subsection are the following:</text> <paragraph id="H39423ADB1E1742B38831E2FC9054EA20"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Ending poverty in all its forms everywhere.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA3119F4A778448179F88F999E3BDD7B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Ending hunger, achieving food security and improved nutrition, and promoting sustainable agriculture.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H30915C6DD2874749B39E5C5B754DC136"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Ensuring healthy lives and promote well-being for all and at all ages.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H36C03B0785BF4FD88DF851347A9F34C0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Ensuring inclusive, equitable, and quality education and promoting lifelong learning opportunities for all.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0AC4A432B303480E87C21604BD5C38F6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Achieving gender equality and empowering all women and girls.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HC08BAE8625B944F98A24C54566886C5E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Ensuring the availability and sustainable management of water and sanitation for all.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7B4D855523A0455C8E6EFBE2E64FF5F4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Ensuring access to affordable, reliable, sustainable and modern energy for all.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9CA176E48932417FA66F7BF22626A698"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Promoting sustained, inclusive, and sustainable economic growth, full and productive employment, and decent work for all.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H31CD66CBCC4B4696AA8B2678D0496C7D"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Building resilient infrastructure, promoting inclusive and sustainable industrialization, and fostering innovation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2A42079AA882446E9C491F33389F71BB"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Reducing inequality within and among countries.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HAD3141E2AC1A45F8A06CC02AC6BD62AD"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Making cities and human settlements inclusive, safe, resilient, and sustainable.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBB6F6161926E49DB84F24A68BEC147C8"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Ensuring sustainable consumption and production patterns.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9B3EA794D32942158B83941A9CC7DA3F"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Taking urgent action to combat climate change and its impacts.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H843A461DC55344DBAFACE1F445C6F022"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Conserving and sustainably using the oceans, seas, and marine resources for sustainable development.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD71547BA42D5479D9028A1CCCA0754A6"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Protecting, restoring, and promoting sustainable use of terrestrial ecosystems, sustainably managing forests, combating desertification, and halting and reversing land degradation and biodiversity loss.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H18F81A358EEC48C1AE182C500E076D8A"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Promoting peaceful and inclusive societies for sustainable development, providing access to justice for all, and building effective, accountable and inclusive institutions at all levels.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3A2144F20A314F8CB7D95D0EEDD98734"><enum>(17)</enum><text>Strengthening the means of policy implementation and revitalize the global partnership for sustainable development.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="HF86A6183706A45E09BF20BC9A28A762B"><enum>II</enum><header>Oversight and Accountability</header>
			<section id="H2E5B64A6EB0D469B918FA5EABE6FE42D"><enum>201.</enum><header>Senior coordinator for women and climate change</header>
 <subsection id="HD2439E1E588B43079EC4F2D8B0C3841B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Ambassador-at-Large of the Office of Global Women’s Issues shall designate a current employee serving as a Senior Advisor, or equivalent role, to serve concurrently as the Senior Coordinator for Women and Climate Change.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H8AB032BB1A5842EA8DFE89B29FE2FB22"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Senior Coordinator shall—</text> <paragraph id="H9FA8B58468C645C28ECEC6B97C6B5F36"><enum>(1)</enum><text>direct the activities, policies, programs, and funding of the Department of State relating to the effects of climate change on women, including with respect to efforts to prevent and respond to these effects;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF8BFDCD0F6814D998DA90A84C7F73732"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">advise the Secretary, the relevant heads of other Federal departments and independent agencies, and other entities within the Executive Office of the President, regarding the establishment of—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HAC2E99AC620241C3ADE05E1A90F5BE5C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">policies, goals, objectives, and priorities for addressing and combating the effects of climate change on women; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA256FF2A4DB4EF598ACB8EA052424AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>mechanisms to improve the effectiveness, coordination, impact, and outcomes of programs relating to addressing and combating the effects of climate change on women, in coordination with experts in the field, nongovernmental organizations, and foreign governments; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF19CBA7C760E4ED6957FF56D08ED79DD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify and assist in the resolution of any disputes that arise between Federal agencies relating to policies and programs to address and combat the effects of climate change on women or other matters within the responsibility of the Office.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H48B062842D514B128DC58685B4E5A1E6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Oversight</header><text>The Senior Coordinator for Women and Climate Change shall report to the Ambassador-at-Large for the Office of Global Women’s Issues and the Secretary of State.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="HCAC8591BF2D346F9B9FE14DFB0ED5CB9"><enum>202.</enum><header>Briefing and report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Ambassador-at-Large and Senior Coordinator for Women and Climate Change shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H3583E2B95C6D43EA882FE47B032F6B3E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>brief the appropriate congressional committees on—</text> <subparagraph id="H90FB6BE7030C493BB9387D07A192E4D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the effects of climate change on women; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H210B3285A57A47FEB2E686D549EC7983"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the prevention and response strategies, programming, and associated outcomes with respect to climate change; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBB7206222154EC287FEB0F827A5A51C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to the appropriate congressional committees an assessment of human and financial resources necessary to fulfill the purposes of and carry out this Act.</text>
				</paragraph></section></title></legis-body></bill>


