<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H8FAAF4CE61C84432AF66FBA041253369" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5755 IH: Tools On Our Local Streets to Rehabilitate Communities Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5755</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180510">May 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001048">Mr. Culberson</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000410">Mr. Gene Green of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize community development block grants for providing tools, equipment, and other
			 resources.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HD917E2CC3EDF4B2D8ABEA239BF60D5DB" style="OLC">
 <section id="HFF8A14E7330B453DBF9EAABCF36C0715" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Tools On Our Local Streets to Rehabilitate Communities Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>TOOLS to Rehabilitate Communities Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H2FD5A356C5DE471483112F127BAFB1DF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Strengthening community development partnerships with nonprofit organizations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 105(a) of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5305">42 U.S.C. 5305(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H37A947685E724164910A5D70AFB58B81"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (25)(D), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H7289C78A29E34990A0A53B4E0D4E8A1A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (26), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBE79C683E377450BA2E59863563DA2E7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H03B134B5A0AA44BCAB1BC7C16B443F5E" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H93932840DBEB4BF19B508DC76816E884"><enum>(27)</enum><text>creating or strengthening partnerships with nonprofit organizations that provide tools, equipment, or other resources to other nonprofit or volunteer organizations assisting in the completion of a community development, revitalization, or rehabilitation project authorized under this subsection.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H848A6BA0BA8F4885870DBA441DFFAA39"><enum>3.</enum><header>Increasing awareness</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For each fiscal year beginning after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall provide notice to grant applicants and awardees under section 103 of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5303">42 U.S.C. 5303</external-xref>) that awards provided under title I of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5301">42 U.S.C. 5301</external-xref> et seq.) may be used to create or strengthen partnerships with nonprofit organizations that provide tools, equipment, or other resources to other nonprofit or volunteer organizations that assist in the completion of a community development, revitalization, or rehabilitation project authorized under such section 103.</text>
		</section><section id="H98EE8C2B07E94DF9925FC8043E637024"><enum>4.</enum><header>Identifying opportunities to increase access to community development partnerships with non-profit
 organization</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than the end of the first fiscal year beginning after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall issue a report discussing—</text>
 <paragraph id="HCE9280CDFFDB4556B67A939AA1B4C9A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>opportunities in existence as of the date of the report for Federal, State, and local governments to partner with nonprofit organizations to complete community development, revitalization, and rehabilitation projects under title I of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5301">42 U.S.C. 5301</external-xref> et seq.); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H828872C9249F4C09961968C8DD0CF411"><enum>(2)</enum><text>existing barriers and challenges with respect to those projects.</text> </paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

