<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9DFDB7A4758D4E0490EF0528F10AD264" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4925 IH: FRA Safety Data Improvement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4925</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180205">February 5, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001201">Mr. Mitchell</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the Federal Railroad Administration to implement certain
			 recommendations for management and collection of railroad safety data.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HB6BC16E8E1414EC9B91D6E8DECF7C43A" style="OLC">
 <section id="HCC8E5F787F0248B1854D28626410BAD9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>FRA Safety Data Improvement Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HE2E09F28F5E84AAA861D954CF272337A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Recommendations for management and collection of railroad safety data</header> <subsection id="H9FEF190175E343DD8BEAF9F67234F269"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator of the Federal Railroad Administration shall develop a plan, and a timeline to carry out such plan, to implement the recommendations from the Inspector General Report No. ST2017045 of the Department of Transportation, issued on May 3, 2017, to the greatest extent possible, to improve the Federal Railroad Administration’s management and collection of railroad safety data.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H01BC08CF00514E17B3C188AAAE6B1FF4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text></text> <paragraph id="HAE62BCB1F98A424894590240591123CE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit the plan and timeline developed under subsection (a) to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H05557CB734E04AA0AAC1B89384F229F8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Administrator shall report annually to the committees on the implementation of such plan until implementation is complete.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H1DA5A2A0C03D4FD19A48474299DFECAA"><enum>3.</enum><header>No additional funds authorized</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No additional funds are authorized to carry out the requirements of this Act. Such requirements shall be carried out using amounts otherwise authorized.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


