<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HABA6DC1CA9044BD9B615972B12BC3D0E" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5286 IH: Mass Violence Prevention Reform Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5286</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180314">March 14, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000571">Ms. Gabbard</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000210">Mr. King of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To impose a 60-day moratorium on the transfer or receipt of an assault rifle, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H22A69DF53B2D46CFB1A06D7211F3E207" style="OLC">
 <section id="H8733FD7606A741628F8EC13A4FC582A5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Mass Violence Prevention Reform Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H72E666F2B6774B62922A29E2F4D2C40E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds as follows:</text>
 <paragraph id="HF972DCE5BA3E48D2BF7F6836D153FD6B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On March 11, 2018, President Donald Trump announced a commission on school safety.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HF80CCFCEEDFF4A7A96089297D8FF9ECB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Bureau of Investigation, having been alerted twice, failed to identify the threat posed by Nikolas Cruz.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H54CA9175C1B34ECD9772F4B36D57730E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Broward County Sheriff’s Office, having sent law enforcement officers to Nikolas Cruz’s home 39 times, failed to identify him as a threat.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3459B540936242E8AD15F5D8B848D318"><enum>(4)</enum><text>At least 3 State agencies, having investigated Nikolas Cruz, failed to identify him as a threat.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H55C335BBF4E04C3BB1F647F3855C9B67"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Mental illness was identified in Nikolas Cruz, but he was still sold a gas-operated semiautomatic rifle.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFCBB9CEFBE384B248D62BED58B1FB168"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Nikolas Cruz, who had been expelled by Marjory Stoneman Douglas High School, was still able to enter the school’s campus on February 14, 2018 in possession of a gas-operated semiautomatic rifle.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA01CD410D4184FA7870313DA72AD5B5B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Broward County Sheriff’s deputies, who have received extensive tactical training and were in possession of body armor and firearms, were paralyzed from executing an assault on 18-year-old Nikolas Cruz in possession of a gas-operated semiautomatic rifle.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5CC93CA881E74C00A302C0EB711096E8"><enum>(8)</enum><text>President Donald Trump proposed a ban on the rifle accessory known as a <quote>bump stock</quote>.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HFCB42D617AD74A87B2FC9F25A1AF7723"><enum>(9)</enum><text>President Donald Trump called on Members of Congress to draft legislation that would require background checks for all firearm sales.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6D61B54D5D4A402FA3E2A7608F5CFC5A"><enum>(10)</enum><text>President Donald Trump called on Members of Congress to draft legislation raising the age of all firearm purchasers to 21 years of age.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H505403EA501C4C768622E4522C059C65"><enum>(11)</enum><text>A gas-operated semiautomatic rifle was the weapon of choice for Nikolas Cruz, who killed 17 people at Marjory Stoneman Douglas High School, Parkland, Florida, on February 14, 2018.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9E8BAE9E439F469C9421368531ABE291"><enum>(12)</enum><text>A gas-operated semiautomatic rifle was the weapon of choice for Stephen Paddock, who killed 58 people at the Route 91 Harvest Music Festival in Las Vegas, Nevada, on October 1, 2017.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H89AC394CEB4B47C39EC9FAE665E10738"><enum>(13)</enum><text>A gas-operated semiautomatic rifle was the weapon of choice for Omar Mateen, who killed 49 people at the Pulse Nightclub in Orlando, Florida, on June 12, 2016.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDAAC23F327C64208BFB118013428659B"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Congress is developing legislation to provide behavioral detection training to those selling firearms.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4859A6B94CA748E4B456E0F735F82837"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Congress is developing legislation to provide funds for strengthening school security and physical security infrastructure.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0EE37A39DE344D03833A3AC37D3B6B6E"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Individuals adjudicated as posing a threat to themselves or others should not be permitted to purchase firearms.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H26C7AA0ACD7F445E8E4C0C4F08DE3B01"><enum>(17)</enum><text>A system of due process must be established to ensure that citizens are not deprived of their Second Amendment rights.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H928E8DED8BD34723BEA3E3B677D30E1E"><enum>(18)</enum><text>Americans have declining faith in the system of checks designed to preclude future sales of firearms to those who were clearly deemed a threat.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H4E46AA4C58794C05A7D9C7C00BE7A819"><enum>3.</enum><header>Moratorium on the transfer or receipt of an assault rifle</header>
 <subsection id="H2A661857AA9D47DCA21DA336FAEE0351"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the 60-day period that begins with the day after the date of the enactment of this Act, it shall be unlawful for any person to transfer or receive an assault rifle.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD47F8FFF508B4EBE9FB960DB25A92B0E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H138358F0807048FEB5736588133DB255"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assault rifle</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>assault rifle</term> means a gas-operated semiautomatic firearm with a rifled bore.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H932DAD0CCF634876B4C9C95601D19185"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Gas-operated</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>gas-operated</term> means, with respect to a firearm, that the firearm uses a portion of gas of a firing cartridge to extract the fired cartridge case and chamber the next round.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE1C89AE55A6343F2A7E793352DBF60B1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Semiautomatic</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>semiautomatic</term> means, with respect to a firearm, that the firearm is a repeating firearm that utilizes a portion of the energy of a firing cartridge to extract the fired cartridge case and chamber the next round, and that requires a separate pull of the trigger to fire each cartridge.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBB83CA6C9FF740B2852BB616CDF58CD6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rifled bore</header><text>The term <term>rifled bore</term> means, with respect to a firearm, that the firearm is designed or made to spin a fired projectile.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE3CE409BD430493684381D946F50B116"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Firearm</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>firearm</term> has the meaning given the term in section 921(a)(3) of title 18, United States Code.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6E96857C95AC4DE0866FB5062346E3F2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>Whoever knowingly violates subsection (a) shall be subject to the penalties provided for in section 924(a)(1) of title 18, United States Code.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HB2C8F4638AC84DC9928B509315A93524"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Presidential waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President of the United States may extend the moratorium established by subsection (a) until the earlier of—</text>
 <paragraph id="HACBF1AC08C59486BA20ABD27A84B796B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>30 days after the date of the submission of the report required by section 4; or</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H4B9FECC071C64D7FB5C46BDD69DE7F5E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>October 1, 2020.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H43371E7C10FB4B25B7547466983D6D52"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report to the Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Within 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, and the Deputy Director of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives shall jointly submit a written report to the Congress that—</text>
 <paragraph id="H21486874B298425EB8E90E976000EDDF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>recommends a legal definition of assault weapon, including classifying firearms based on lethality; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5B4147877624488BA489FBBFE14AA51B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>makes such other policy recommendations relating to firearms as are appropriate in the interest of public health.</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


