<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H05DCC44EE1A14DF9A27AF39373EC22FA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5557 IH: Safe Disposal of Opioids Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5557</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180418">April 18, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Comprehensive Addiction and Recovery Act of 2016 to authorize the Attorney General, in coordination with the Administrator of the Drug Enforcement Administration, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, and the Director of the Office of National Drug Control Policy, to award grants to covered entities to establish or maintain disposal sites for unwanted prescription medications, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H1F20DF016D724D2AAD038EBDA0EA3495" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD87826B7179941A6A568F10AEB57F467" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Safe Disposal of Opioids Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H3F47E7AA04E54BDFAB3E87F17DEA4EA2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grants for disposal sites for unwanted prescription medications</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 203 of the Comprehensive Addiction and Recovery Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/822a">21 U.S.C. 822a</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC7D12C31FB3C4C2D84C982DFA01B1319" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="HEE7EA75770F5496D9BA4F3783FF2A97E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grants for disposal sites for unwanted prescription medications</header> 
<paragraph id="HB981BAF7DA1F4026B1243FDFE105699D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Grants</header> 
<subparagraph id="HD9DD417CA69B4FA299D555066C3A7608"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Awards</header><text>In carrying out subsection (b), the Attorney General shall award grants to covered entities to establish or maintain disposal sites for unwanted prescription medications.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4A9FD1E401B1425E85614DF522509247"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the total amount of awards under subparagraph (A) for a fiscal year, the Attorney General shall not award more than 10 percent to covered entities that are—</text> 
<clause id="HCFFB1718590645108F6C88427DD301A9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>State, local, or tribal law enforcement agencies; or</text></clause> <clause id="H8AEE250D44234C999688CCD6C2B6B91F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>manufacturers, distributors, or reverse distributors of prescription medications.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD7703CC68BC14DE396943933EEE278B4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Discounts for eligible patients</header> 
<subparagraph id="HBAF5ABD2330C4BA08F5A44C7442FDDA4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall establish a mechanism by which amounts paid by an eligible patient for an active opioid are discounted at time of payment or purchase to ensure that such patient does not pay any amount attributable to a fee under paragraph (3), with as little burden on the patient as possible.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0BC14583556349C5A15196CE4088686D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the term <term>eligible patient</term> means—</text> 
<clause id="H1D9272FCB18C4783B94CB699D877D456"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a patient for whom any active opioid (as so defined) is prescribed to treat pain relating to cancer or cancer treatment;</text></clause> <clause id="H710D7BE24881403CA69B8E7AA4567188"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a patient participating in hospice care; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H06AA905B7E424A7DB6B7E24D595DBECB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the case of the death or incapacity of a patient described in subparagraph (A) or (B) or any similar situation as determined by the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the appropriate family member, medical proxy, or similar representative or the estate of such patient.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFE6F6DCB32F14D4CA8B41A85E1A594F4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Fees</header> <subparagraph id="H67FDD335753D4626B44CF8D8891D27E8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is hereby imposed on the sale of any active opioid by the manufacturer, producer, or importer a fee equal to 1 cent per 100 milligrams so sold.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE90D1C0680CF46B582EE8CFF5B34058C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Special rules</header> 
<clause id="H608F79E9FC9C4A4095EEA9C691ACA7F7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this paragraph, the term <term>active opioid</term>—</text> <subclause id="H2AA8FFF8E96F4C7E9CA8CEA971A90A69"><enum>(I)</enum><text>means any controlled substance (as defined in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act, as in effect on the date of the <short-title>Safe Disposal of Opioids Act of 2018</short-title>) which is opium, an opiate, or any derivative thereof; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HFDBE4067B9A14885812EF8EA9D681B2F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>excludes any prescribed drug which is used exclusively for the treatment of opioid addiction as part of a medically assisted treatment effort.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H24AEFF07CEDC4205BEB7717DBC18790C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exclusion of other ingredients</header><text>In the case of a product that includes an active opioid and another ingredient, subparagraph (A) shall apply only to the portion of such product that is an active opioid.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFF1139728932412E913168FF32D7E903"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>For fiscal year 2019 and each subsequent fiscal year, there is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this subsection an amount not to exceed the aggregate amount of the fees collected pursuant to paragraph (3).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> </legis-body> </bill> 

