<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9D04F816441247D4B55765F2C5B98A45" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5512 IH: To require the Administrator of the Small Business Administration to establish a grant program to address rising costs of tax compliance for small business concerns, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5512</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180413">April 13, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Committee on Small Business</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the Small Business Administration to establish a grant program to
			 address rising costs of tax compliance for small business concerns, and
			 for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H1096DA43F30F4471BC2914CB37C74A60" style="OLC">
		<section id="H3C1C15BDD5DF41C1BC8381637561A6F6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Grants to small business development centers and women’s business centers to address rising costs
			 of tax compliance for small business concerns</header>
 <subsection id="H470273A60EDD4CB4B7D7DC369F0CE4F7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Small Business Administration may award a grant under this section to a small business development center or a women’s business center for the purposes of assisting owners of small business concerns in complying with the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and communicating with the Internal Revenue Service.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H03CBABF415C24C7B9F48D16BD55E3B02"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each applicant for a grant under this section shall submit to the Administrator an application in such form as the Administrator may require. The application shall include information regarding the applicant’s goals and objectives for helping address the concerns of owners of small business concerns related to compliance with the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H05E4BC55FB744927B333F80868422CF5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability of grant requirements</header><text>An applicant for a grant under this section shall comply with all of the requirements applicable to a grantee under section 21 or section 29 of the Small Business Act, except that the matching funds requirements of such sections shall not apply.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HFCFEC490965845909DA85796662D461F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A recipient of a grant under this section shall use the grant only for the purposes described in subsection (a), including working with—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE34C5B6877C845498445F10A5480EA25"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Internal Revenue Service, including local offices of the Office of the Taxpayer Advocate, to help reduce tax compliance costs for such owners; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4C947C1A2BD146ADAFB4714B1CAB9181"><enum>(2)</enum><text>owners of small business concerns who are subject to an audit by the Internal Revenue Service.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE7A63D078D5C4F278BBE6F4401A6D5D2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Minimum grant amount</header><text>A grant awarded under this section may not be in an amount less than $200,000.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H55CA0B0E18054215B0DD557D32A49123"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Cooperative agreements and contracts</header><text>The Administrator may enter into a cooperative agreement or contract with the recipient of a grant under this section to provide additional assistance for the purposes described in subsection (a).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H69523DB3016645EBAA7B9CDE6BCDA663"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report to Administrator</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of receipt of a grant under this section, the recipient of the grant shall submit to the Administrator a report describing how the grant funds were used.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H3C1FC84A839544CE84F53632BDF5DDA4"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Evaluation of program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to Congress a report that contains an evaluation of the grant program established under this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H294BFFCFB33849C49BB4154FF58676E1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HB14EAC4B8F6844C6A08C35F5075A4C6C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Small Business Administration.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H70392C749381450FA943E0A9621320BD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Small business concern</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>small business concern</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HC64E922BB9854E6D9D796AD67A38BFF8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Small business development center</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>small business development center</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H37CDCA0D93E941E1A663901857E782AA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Women’s business center</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>women’s business center</term> means a women's business center described under section 29 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/656">15 U.S.C. 656</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFD941066DE89482486D83A4F4A21CC92"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Limitation on use of funds</header><text>The Administrator may carry out this section only with amounts appropriated specifically to carry out this section under subsection (k).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H6D5EDA8C155243C0BEE360A8C2A2DAB4"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2018 and 2019.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


