<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H5EAE2FB1CABA4154A5A90E66394B83B8" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5028 IH: Sunlight in Workplace Harassment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5028</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180214">February 14, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000608">Ms. Rosen</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 to require disclosure of payments for settlements of
			 disputes regarding sexual abuse and certain types of harassment and
			 discrimination, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H5786EBD8930946F38D946CFE09480062" style="OLC">
 <section id="HB0C221A9B75341D383ECE97E799C7458" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Sunlight in Workplace Harassment Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HBAC294C29EB041A1B01F615AAC6C1BB3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Disclosure of payments for settlements of disputes regarding sexual abuse and certain types of harassment and discrimination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 13 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78m">15 U.S.C. 78m</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H84983EADC775426284E86A6DD8E8F909" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="HA05B7B5BC1D64E398B09FC5238785292"><enum>(s)</enum><header>Disclosure of certain activities regarding settlements of disputes relating to sexual abuse and
			 certain types of harassment or discrimination</header>
 <paragraph id="H91757ED9B243415BBD9FC157299F2DD1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection—</text> <subparagraph id="HAA48AE9D254C4BA78C986496BCF82C5B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <term>covered discrimination</term> means—</text>
 <clause id="H12590FBDB64E47E18AF7FA419DBB6D9D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>discrimination described in any of clauses (i) through (vi) of subparagraph (B); or</text> </clause><clause id="HA738B5B749134448BEAD598EE4AC2CF8"><enum>(ii)</enum> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HBE87ED842BC64C10A9612EC149BFFB70"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a violation of section 704(a) of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000e-3">42 U.S.C. 2000e–3(a)</external-xref>) that is related to discrimination described in subparagraph (B)(i) or (B)(vi)(I);</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H9DBB2C18EB4E4B639161AAF7B56DE759" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a violation of section 4(d) of the Age Discrimination in Employment Act of 1967 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/623">29 U.S.C. 623(d)</external-xref>) that is related to discrimination described in subparagraph (B)(ii);</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H19F0743453F84B83B0C37EF34DBAD462" indent="up1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a violation of subsection (a) or (b) of section 503 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12203">42 U.S.C. 12203</external-xref>) that is related to discrimination described in subparagraph (B)(iii);</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HB6ECDE1BC7D94A89A731D155F813F3E3" indent="up1"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>a violation of section 207(f) of the Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000ff-6">42 U.S.C. 2000ff–6(f)</external-xref>) that is related to discrimination described in subparagraph (B)(iv);</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HAEF6591455304844A2288BBDF1A9635E" indent="up1"><enum>(V)</enum><text>a violation of section 4311(b) of title 38, United States Code, that is related to discrimination described in subparagraph (B)(v); and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H69231A6965784325BF92262C393563B3" indent="up1"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>a violation of section 40002(b)(13)(A) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(b)(13)(A)</external-xref>) that—</text>
 <item id="H5728C570378B452CBA101991B64EDEE4"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>may cover retaliation described in a provision specified in any of subclauses (I) through (V); and</text> </item><item id="H56716AA81A5F4785A041A47B9A2E6EEB"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>is related to discrimination described in subparagraph (B)(vi)(II);</text>
 </item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7A13905457304CDA9EB726A14A9CBF99"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>covered harassment</term> means harassment that is—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEC661030E6C94D1BA1A7DC92FDB04C51"><enum>(i)</enum><text>discrimination because of race, color, religion, sex, or national origin under title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000e">42 U.S.C. 2000e</external-xref> et seq.);</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4704091B36B2411083781C97D0EB189C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>discrimination because of age under the Age Discrimination in Employment Act of 1967 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/621">29 U.S.C. 621</external-xref> et seq.);</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8446BCFC4A57471695CAD2CEF54FBF98"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>discrimination on the basis of disability under—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF149C378F7EA4CE894E5C6D6DE7BE07A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>title I of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12111">42 U.S.C. 12111</external-xref> et seq.); or</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1AE8D144EEF942B7B9EADCE8040368FA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>section 501 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/791">29 U.S.C. 791</external-xref>);</text> </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H75586E5DF0D549139C12122D6309E598"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>discrimination because of genetic information under title II of the Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000ff">42 U.S.C. 2000ff</external-xref> et seq.);</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HACFF79DDD0E44E2DA4149F8549675B00"><enum>(v)</enum><text>discrimination on the basis of status concerning service in a uniformed service under section 4311(a) of title 38, United States Code; or</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF257D1A41B2D474FB6E8E0B4F032A8D1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>discrimination because of sexual orientation or gender identity under—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF26A94AB1414D9989A523D6B9FEAFD3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000e">42 U.S.C. 2000e</external-xref> et seq.); or</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H47299A604E024A0291511FC0DF715828"><enum>(II)</enum><text>section 40002(b)(13)(A) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(b)(13)(A)</external-xref>);</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB58FC7E3C7CD47E69847CAE5FA870AED"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the term <term>covered issuer</term> means an issuer that is required to file Form 10–K;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA65D751D69074FC681288DCA633B121C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the term <term>Form 10–K</term> means the form described in section 249.310 of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the date of enactment of this subsection;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6584738B406F4CB4A7B184B7F5DB158B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the term <term>gender identity</term> means the gender-related identity, appearance, mannerisms, or other gender-related characteristics of an individual, regardless of the designated sex of the individual at birth;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA51BF1EF00AB49CCA5008FD7F20E78BC"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the term <term>settlement</term> means any commitment or agreement—</text> <clause id="HDCAACF8AF28A4ED198B1F678875B4A56"><enum>(i)</enum><text>without regard to whether the commitment or agreement, as applicable, is in writing; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA4C02C8CE32C48B5B646CEB32866C7C2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>under which an issuer directly or indirectly—</text> <subclause id="H7AD14A9BEABC4FEF8E3CA13C2C8C98D4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>provides to an individual compensation or other consideration because of an allegation that the individual has been a victim of covered harassment, covered discrimination, or sexual abuse; or</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H429237517EA34066AD9037AE80D688FF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>establishes conditions that affect the terms of the employment, including by terminating the employment, of the individual with the issuer—</text>
 <item id="HB99C149208404CB886A56371A3A0C441"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>because of the experience of the individual with, or the participation of the individual in, an alleged act of covered harassment, covered discrimination, or sexual abuse; and</text>
 </item><item id="H390A731AF01543109F48CF1B73A65D6C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in exchange for which the individual agrees or commits not to—</text> <subitem id="HBED81EE34BF643A3B22264FA1505BBF5"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>bring legal, administrative, or any other type of action against the issuer; or</text>
 </subitem><subitem id="H15243AE3DF8B42B2A7EFB2471FBA8513"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>publicly disclose, for a period of time of any length, any portion of the alleged act described in item (aa) on which the commitment or agreement, as applicable, is based;</text>
 </subitem></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B778DFC04304BC48C72C6319C2F996A"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the term <term>sexual abuse</term> means any type of sexual contact or behavior that occurs without the explicit consent of the recipient, including forced sexual intercourse, forcible sodomy, child molestation, incest, fondling, and attempted rape; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4DB72B1D98D9493A991A95EF619770B0"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the term <term>sexual orientation</term> means homosexuality, heterosexuality, or bisexuality.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0768B13DFC924BD5B1CF0031AA78AB8B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disclosure requirements</header> <subparagraph id="H9418065339CF4139ADA7865C54BEE850"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning in the first fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this subsection, each covered issuer shall disclose annually on Form 10–K, to shareholders of the covered issuer, and to the public—</text>
 <clause id="H64CDEA7EA9A844F9ADB363268A859F13"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to the previous year—</text> <subclause id="H4116237D3C82433C941E97ECFF360B7B"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total number of settlements entered into by the covered issuer, a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, or a corporate executive of the covered issuer that relate to any alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination that—</text>
 <item id="HC8A2712945EA45B2ACAC1F845F93EA71"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">occurred in the workplace of the covered issuer or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer; or</text>
 </item><item id="H4AFEF3D6822F4AE3B06506982BC10C0C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>involves the behavior of an employee of the covered issuer, or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, toward another such employee, without regard to whether that behavior occurred in the workplace of the covered issuer or the subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor, as applicable;</text>
 </item></subclause><subclause id="HE36B279229D94A1FAB5A42A7D4FC1142"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the total dollar amount paid with respect to the settlements described in subclause (I);</text> </subclause><subclause id="H786B35047AB444F3AA6E9969B78A8486"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the total number of settlements entered into by the covered issuer, a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, or a corporate executive of the covered issuer that relate to any alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination that—</text>
 <item id="H638856EA6267417E8B612C0AC8A59803"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>was committed by a corporate executive of—</text> <subitem id="H37EE68C018F54C7F86D99401474D8861"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the covered issuer; or</text>
 </subitem><subitem id="HFCC1A336BE44442681225FA0C72F52A8"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer; and</text> </subitem></item><item id="H6D817BF5D3A6454BAC46A652DC8CF086"><enum>(bb)</enum> <subitem commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H906A9A4399FC405A9192756A9469490E"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>occurred in the workplace of the covered issuer or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, as applicable; or</text>
 </subitem><subitem id="H4164251EEA1040A3B1F04993B4C11E47" indent="up1"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>involved the behavior of a corporate executive described in item (aa) toward another employee of the covered issuer or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer, as applicable, without regard to whether that behavior occurred in the workplace of the covered issuer or a subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer;</text>
 </subitem></item></subclause><subclause id="H4DA0FBE0D6DA45F585A7CD0BC11075E9"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the total dollar amount with respect to the settlements described in subclause (III); and</text> </subclause><subclause id="HA8309F7E75B24880B954A5301410756E"><enum>(V)</enum><text>the average length of time required for the covered issuer to resolve a complaint relating to covered discrimination, covered harassment, or sexual abuse; and</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H1865EC2206CC423A8D2C3E8F3A266A31"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>as of the date on which the disclosure is made, the total number of complaints relating to covered discrimination, covered harassment, and sexual abuse that the covered issuer is working to resolve through—</text>
 <subclause id="H5145421E2758441A89697248DE38B14D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>processes that are internal to the covered issuer; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="HB874D570BFB44A71B19161EE0E189109"><enum>(II)</enum><text>litigation.</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD80E8C4516246D786F02508D58B5693"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Categories</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (C), in each disclosure required under subparagraph (A), a covered issuer shall report the total number of settlements in subclauses (I) and (III) of subparagraph (A)(i) and the total dollar amounts in subclauses (II) and (IV) of subparagraph (A)(i) in the aggregate and list each such settlement by any of the following categories that apply to the settlement:</text>
 <clause id="HA4BE1973B32941378604D39056E48DD3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Settlements relating to sexual abuse, covered discrimination, or covered harassment because of sex.</text> </clause><clause id="H95F207AF41A745BB94157CB042EDC70A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Settlements relating to covered discrimination or covered harassment because of race, color, or national origin.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA5F15B83D4964FC7B0D2B1E198E779E8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Settlements relating to covered discrimination or covered harassment because of religion.</text> </clause><clause id="HA71215B4EE1B46BE9C342D5167BEA821"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Settlements relating to covered discrimination or covered harassment because of age.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H404A3926D3224E5CA35F6176A517FECF"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Settlements relating to covered discrimination or covered harassment on the basis of disability.</text> </clause><clause id="HF75A23304C7B415DBF05FCC157814AB1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Settlements relating to covered discrimination or covered harassment because of genetic information.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H4F514293D4174CF894E99FE38CC9F117"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Settlements relating to covered discrimination or covered harassment on the basis of status concerning service in a uniformed service.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H359D50D9F4C644BA8211DA0BBB2EEF1A"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Settlements relating to covered discrimination or covered harassment because of sexual orientation or gender identity.</text>
							</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6510778EE4284E9883BB68EB0B11C4DE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Prohibitions on certain disclosures</header>
							<clause id="H815B04D81C80461ABD608C00C3C8576D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Prohibition on disclosures by covered issuers</header>
 <subclause id="H834BF1A2710C4965837BC7E83CD8F415"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A covered issuer may not—</text> <item id="H952D6E27061F425D9CCCAA5CE47A79F3"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in any disclosure made under subparagraph (A), or in any other public disclosure, disclose the name of a victim of an alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination on which a settlement or complaint, as applicable, described in subparagraph (A) is based; or</text>
 </item><item id="HD130C92BF05548C69FD769F4DCA99480"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>under subparagraph (B), categorize a settlement described in subclause (I) or (III) of subparagraph (A)(i) if the victim of the alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination on which the settlement is based objects to that categorization.</text>
 </item></subclause><subclause id="H0CB8536A51954AB3979B226C0355BCCA"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Indication of objection</header><text>A covered issuer shall indicate in any disclosure made under subparagraph (A) whether any objection has been made under subclause (I)(bb) of this clause.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="HA2BBF237A2B742C5B1266E7FB86A777E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Prohibition on disclosures by the Commission</header><text>The Commission may not disclose the name of a victim of an alleged act of sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination on which a settlement or complaint, as applicable, described in subparagraph (A) is based.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB26E1E3780854147AF1A7496C538C916"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Prevention of sexual abuse, covered harassment, and covered discrimination</header><text>In each disclosure required under subparagraph (A), the covered issuer making the disclosure shall include a description of the measures taken by the covered issuer and any subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer to prevent employees of the covered issuer and any subsidiary, contractor, or subcontractor of the covered issuer from committing or engaging in sexual abuse, covered harassment, or covered discrimination.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FDECC77906144E19FFF6269B862C87E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may promulgate such regulations as the Commission considers necessary to implement the requirements under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


