<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H60AC2BC11AA743E4A84DE7A50B66D58D" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4749 IH: Truth in Certification for Foreign Food Ingredients Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4749</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180109">January 9, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Agricultural Trade Act of 1978 to establish a program to enhance transparency and
			 traceability of food products and ingredients that are exported to the
			 United States in order to protect American consumers and American food
			 manufacturers against mislabeling, adulteration, and fraud.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H06FF791ABEC24A41B9B126D859A1E804" style="OLC">
 <section id="HBF40AFAF38EC482D8FB8476CD7279927" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Truth in Certification for Foreign Food Ingredients Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H9B05733D901147EFA24DDBE13A3F879E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Program of foreign capacity building to strengthen transparency, trace­abil­ity and fraud prevention of food products and ingredients exported to the United States</header> <subsection id="HF70F5A5F420D41258C97127CA5078306"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text>
 <paragraph id="HB5E6C057D3304FFEA43063FEF3F472D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Approximately 15 percent of the United States food supply consists of imported products.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HD3B59CB637434058B5C328964BB3AF6D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Food products and ingredients with special characteristics command a premium price in the United States market.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6B31A501A5644025B5346988078FBD86"><enum>(3)</enum><text>American food manufacturers rely on getting ingredients that consistently meet the specifications they need.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H712B8A3193364C6FBC4E5410EC513C37"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Many foreign governments lack the capacity or expertise to trace back food ingredients or protect against fraudulent changes in paperwork to ensure that ingredients exported to the United States were actually produced in accordance with the standards claimed.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H858E550A43C0492E8CB6A64D547AF9CF"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such frauds cheat consumers who are willing to pay premiums for food and feed with special characteristics, cheat producers and processors who use ingredients with special characteristics, and unfairly put American producers at a competitive disadvantage in marketing specialized products.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H556AEE9D645A4F03B2AD75341FFE5F41"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Fraudulent food imports also put consumers who have food allergies at risk when food labels are mislabeled and do not accurately reflect the ingredients contained in the food product.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6104982FC4954767913F9198F322F64F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Capacity building program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 503 of the Agricultural Trade Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/5693">7 U.S.C. 5693</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H6D3262E1E2F24BCD8A6683FDD2282020"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The Service</quote> and inserting <quote>(a) <header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">In General</header-in-text>.—The Foreign Agricultural Service</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2947A64B9C2E471EAF7C82A967ED5715"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H17CA9E883DD04CB98587CED6A644C8BB" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H2863D097E2434223B0CBF4DEC033D256"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transparency, traceability and fraud prevention program for food products and ingredients exported to the United States</header> <paragraph id="HCF26647361854CE6879D502EE64C9FAC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Program required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Foreign Agricultural Service shall carry out a program to enhance transparency and traceability of food products and ingredients that are exported to the United States in order to protect American consumers and American food manufacturers against mislabeling, adulteration, and fraud.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD62DFC8265DF4F6CB4BAE3AA9EE12771"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Program elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As part of the program, the Foreign Agricultural Service shall provide foreign government officials, foreign agricultural producers, and foreign exporters of food products and ingredients to the United States with technical assistance and best practices to improve—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H73F7E00A383244C186543C1368CC981A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>transparency, traceability and fraud prevention, including best practices for direct government inspection and certification of food products and ingredients in international trade; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H864ECAAA0117485990948C985A5DADF7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">cooperation with private certification and verification bodies to ensure the accuracy and integrity of their food product and ingredient certification and verification.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E9D50D1D59A4C949ECB205C54A164A3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Priorities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Foreign Agricultural Service shall prioritize the provision of technical assistance to those foreign countries determined to be at the greatest risk of exporting mislabeled, misbranded, or adulterated food products or ingredients or food products or ingredients that do not meet the special characteristics that are claimed for the products or ingredients in order to command premium prices.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H87745528983E48A38FE49436C40C8550"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Cooperation and coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Foreign Agricultural Service shall carry out the program in cooperation with the Administrator of the Agricultural Marketing Service and in coordination with the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


