<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HDF3923EF9BCA453DA6109EA6FBA9EBC9" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5628 IH: Access to Increased Drug Disposal Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5628</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180426">April 26, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001180">Mr. McKinley</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001179">Mr. Marino</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001084">Mr. Cicilline</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To establish a demonstration program under which the Drug Enforcement Administration provides
			 grants to certain States to enable those States to increase participation
			 in drug take-back programs.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H7F16C44A47EA4FB1BB5871C05E495EE2" style="OLC">
 <section id="HA752F4487DCC4FEAA84F06F12F5C8CB8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Access to Increased Drug Disposal Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H21CA55E8457940B485350C2C236A52E5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act—</text>
 <paragraph id="H380B80EFE5E14C6AB77C4AD4AE78B77B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>Attorney General</quote> means the Attorney General, acting through the Assistant Attorney General for the Office of Justice Programs;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD5F9B8AE02124D439000CC4D50AFDD0B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>authorized collector</quote> means a narcotic treatment program, a hospital or clinic with an on-site pharmacy, a retail pharmacy, or a reverse distributor that is authorized as a collector under section 1317.40 of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB2B03267EF914C7BB19631B115CC28BD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <quote>covered grant</quote> means a grant awarded under section 3; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9F6272515A8342D7827FB91699CF1650"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <quote>eligible collector</quote> means a person who is eligible to be an authorized collector.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HD27E236F90E34045B1661BA746BF2794"><enum>3.</enum><header>Authority to make grants</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General shall award grants to States to enable States to increase the participation of eligible collectors as authorized collectors.</text>
 </section><section id="H3DA9952841324AE2AE6E5702EEC0CDEA"><enum>4.</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A State desiring a covered grant shall submit to the Attorney General an application that, at a minimum—</text>
 <paragraph id="H3129C1E9E05E4DD3BFC78E98F3CD7246"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identifies the single State agency that oversees pharmaceutical care and will be responsible for complying with the requirements of the grant;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2B57AA80CC024387A9E225416A6038A7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>details a plan to increase participation rates of eligible collectors as authorized collectors; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H3EB7A0C11AEB4734808900EE9F2B0980"><enum>(3)</enum><text>describes how the State will select eligible collectors to be served under the grant.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H877A3DDDE8E04D68A75212F7C1CA5DF7"><enum>5.</enum><header>Use of grant funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A State that receives a covered grant, and any subrecipient of the grant, may use the grant amounts only for the costs of installation, maintenance, training, purchasing, and disposal of controlled substances associated with the participation of eligible collectors as authorized collectors.</text>
 </section><section id="H5D61A3F774824503B2DE2428291FEF1B"><enum>6.</enum><header>Eligibility for grant</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General shall award a covered grant to States and strongly consider States in the lowest quartile of States based on the participation rate of eligible collectors as authorized collectors, as determined by the Attorney General, as well as States in the highest quartile of overdose rates based on the most recent data from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text>
 </section><section id="HAEE746DB8094477EAD284B594C7C8AC0"><enum>7.</enum><header>Duration of grants</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General shall determine the period of years for which a covered grant is made to a State.</text>
 </section><section id="HB6F8164299D74AE7BCCC1DC8AED8E51D"><enum>8.</enum><header>Accountability and oversight</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A State that receives a covered grant shall submit to the Attorney General a report, at such time and in such manner as the Attorney General may reasonably require, that—</text>
 <paragraph id="H87D91747D999459A9B4C9219C5A8C6B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>lists the ultimate recipients of the grant amounts;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H1BBF04BB817044E0A82DC6401190D323"><enum>(2)</enum><text>describes the activities undertaken by the State using the grant amounts; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0821E97C9FED454FA233FCCD53B19DEC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>contains performance measures relating to the effectiveness of the grant, including changes in the participation rate of eligible collectors as authorized collectors.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HBEA81380AE42480AB3A1E35819FB7FEA"><enum>9.</enum><header>Duration of program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General may award covered grants for each of the first 5 fiscal years beginning after the date of enactment of this Act.</text>
 </section><section id="H3DFC9FB03CA9427284B25B047FE645CA"><enum>10.</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Attorney General such sums as may be necessary to carry out this Act.</text>
		</section></legis-body>
</bill>


