<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H2BE37E71EF104A859E0371460716984B" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5433 IH: Hack Your State Department Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5433</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180405">April 5, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Ted Lieu of California</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="Y000065">Mr. Yoho</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of State to design and establish a Vulnerability Disclosure Program (VDP)
			 to improve Department of State cybersecurity and a bug bounty program to
			 identify and report vulnerabilities of internet-facing information
			 technology of the Department of State, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HB3B9B48B757448669AD09F781E7F8AA2" style="OLC">
 <section id="H32F4F97E56084EE3984255B4A5D1CF32" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hack Your State Department Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H72F95DD946394EC59B67EBA0589A4778"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
 <paragraph id="H40A509A5F7F647278A46BD621E8CC761"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <quote>Department</quote> means the Department of State.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H1D465F7EC96D44459722D9864DCE80B8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information technology</header><text>The term <quote>information technology</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 11101 of title 40, United States Code.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF0537FD761B44C27942E36967BEED6B9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of State.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="HA0C58FBF3755402180C9F30D064CE148"><enum>3.</enum><header>Department of State Vulnerability Disclosure Program</header> <subsection id="HE98F9F3E89954601A96913D1B842438D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall design, establish, and make publicly known a Vulnerability Disclosure Program (VDP) to improve Department cybersecurity by—</text>
 <paragraph id="H5CE6A33B35AA4AE2A6F7F29ABA382540"><enum>(1)</enum><text>providing security researchers with clear guidelines for—</text> <subparagraph id="H987198111A9040E1BF60BF8DCC53EEEC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conducting vulnerability discovery activities directed at Department information technology; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2168310CD2644BDC81B8D4A98D58CF97"><enum>(B)</enum><text>submitting discovered security vulnerabilities to the Department; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H959BE7B176DC4E819B02BB4454D1A25D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>creating Department procedures and infrastructure to receive and fix discovered vulnerabilities.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFF60C60A4E9F45E89E636EC2266B1DFE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing the VDP pursuant to paragraph (1), the Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="HA99F98A79BB142D79C39B406B59E943D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify which Department information technology should be included in the program;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB54F71AF48D04718B236EF25D5811BD7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>determine whether the program should differentiate among and specify the types of security vulnerabilities that may be targeted;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H079AC36057254D77B98AAFD216315ED5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide a readily available means of reporting discovered security vulnerabilities and the form in which such vulnerabilities should be reported;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5B9A56FE74744CBDB582459BB0F972A4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identify which Department offices and positions will be responsible for receiving, prioritizing, and addressing security vulnerability disclosure reports;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H051B28D7D5454BF48B54B3FB8A545520"><enum>(5)</enum><text>consult with the Attorney General regarding how to ensure that approved individuals, organizations, and companies that comply with the requirements of the program are protected from prosecution under section 1030 of title 18, United States Code, and similar provisions of law for specific activities authorized under the program;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA83957F0EA1B4FD8B37A6F62170B66F5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>consult with the relevant offices at the Department of Defense that were responsible for launching the 2016 Vulnerability Disclosure Program, <quote>Hack the Pentagon</quote>, and subsequent Department of Defense bug bounty programs;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD79079DB531F4A85B486C2E4385BE90F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>engage qualified interested persons, including nongovernmental sector representatives, about the structure of the program as constructive and to the extent practicable; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H16C161EF43DA4C16B00BF16FDB5B814D"><enum>(8)</enum><text>award a contract to an entity, as necessary, to manage the program and implement the remediation of discovered security vulnerabilities.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6505A53E63CC420B92901414D8FF7DFF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the establishment of the VDP under subsection (a) and annually thereafter for the next six years, the Secretary of State shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on the following with respect to the VDP:</text>
 <paragraph id="HECB428E2CE564F91A43B01303E2D5FF3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number and severity, in accordance with the National Vulnerabilities Database of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, of security vulnerabilities reported.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H441FAE12F2EA4C889112DFA71F1EAF72"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The number of previously unidentified security vulnerabilities remediated as a result.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HAA96DC11F9084EBF99B907F48C83E5A4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The current number of outstanding previously unidentified security vulnerabilities and Department of State remediation plans.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB768BED7B935401BBF3151F4029B56CB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The average length of time between the reporting of security vulnerabilities and remediation of such vulnerabilities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HED3FBDB17C9E411AB9117D442B886C77"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An estimate of the total cost savings of discovering and addressing security vulnerabilities submitted through the VDP.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC06ED6B944714C76B27366FA6F54F291"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The resources, surge staffing, roles, and responsibilities within the Department used to implement the VDP and complete security vulnerability remediation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCF5170CB82E84AD38C86BC1F2F613337"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Any other information the Secretary determines relevant.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H886FA2AFC6564BA1A3F4CB5A4E8100BB"><enum>4.</enum><header>Department of State bug bounty pilot program</header> <subsection id="H6A9023A8EA8341AA90967FC9556FF557"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of pilot program</header> <paragraph id="HABC6C7E1866148D98EDB7FBEE43B7258"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a bug bounty pilot program to minimize security vulnerabilities of internet-facing information technology of the Department.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6E99428823A648E88B5C468CAC401E0C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In establishing the pilot program described in paragraph (1), the Secretary shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H4BD002A2FAA54C78815D59653A221996"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide compensation for reports of previously unidentified security vulnerabilities within the websites, applications, and other internet-facing information technology of the Department that are accessible to the public;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A8EA6F8EFC84A3CAA48F4A4F9E8725E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>award a contract to an entity, as necessary, to manage such pilot program and for executing the remediation of security vulnerabilities identified pursuant to subparagraph (A);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B7E28B701564516B6EFC42AA446F305"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identify which Department information technology should be included in such pilot program;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1871805292A845D3A057D6B56C4B8F44"><enum>(D)</enum><text>consult with the Attorney General on how to ensure that approved individuals, organizations, or companies that comply with the requirements of such pilot program are protected from prosecution under section 1030 of title 18, United States Code, and similar provisions of law for specific activities authorized under such pilot program;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDFFC6AAEB1AE4784A17B464FBA2448A5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>consult with the relevant offices at the Department of Defense that were responsible for launching the 2016 <quote>Hack the Pentagon</quote> pilot program and subsequent Department of Defense bug bounty programs;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6E17FFF653C4B4DAB06554698093B64"><enum>(F)</enum><text>develop a process by which an approved individual, organization, or company can register with the entity referred to in subparagraph (B), submit to a background check as determined by the Department, and receive a determination as to eligibility for participation in such pilot program; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A950211323F47FFB2CE2A75D68BF450"><enum>(G)</enum><text>engage qualified interested persons, including nongovernmental sector representatives, about the structure of such pilot program as constructive and to the extent practicable.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4C41E241E4254A5DAD71F364070F71BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date on which the bug bounty pilot program under subsection (a) is completed, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on such pilot program, including information relating to—</text>
 <paragraph id="HF2E3CA885234403D911D7369B38294CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of approved individuals, organizations, or companies involved in such pilot program, broken down by the number of approved individuals, organizations, or companies that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HAF28CB9CE713461CA575183249F06EA3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>registered;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37A1784E165F4F89BFF24B8B86A8A7B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>were approved;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B3960ED11CF4B869CBD823E3F7F444C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>submitted security vulnerabilities; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H930F8B6FD6FD4F64BCC4AD3AA845E54F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>received compensation;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C37E2D51E0C4ED7A94D9DC2753F1254"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number and severity, in accordance with the National Vulnerabilities Database of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, of security vulnerabilities reported as part of such pilot program;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H93507BFC278D45CBB199C5A1A60F91D4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the number of previously unidentified security vulnerabilities remediated as a result of such pilot program;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC8315D92FBF44DAFBC2D66EC848EA62A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the current number of outstanding previously unidentified security vulnerabilities and Department remediation plans;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA96C0934AD4E4A2BA6DE33D99D6F25A3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the average length of time between the reporting of security vulnerabilities and remediation of such vulnerabilities;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H465BE9740D37486A841CB268593A4CB3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the types of compensation provided under such pilot program; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H75C167DC0C6F457580A5717F42E26DE0"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the lessons learned from such pilot program.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


