<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H2BAF24821C1C45B3A80DE7EAE3A79DBD" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5810 IH: Medicaid Health Homes for Opioid-Use-Disorder Medicaid Enrollees Encouraged Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5810</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180515">May 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000567">Mr. Lance</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000800">Mr. Welch</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000598">Mr. Rothfus</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XIX of the Social Security Act to provide for an extension of the enhanced FMAP for
			 certain Medicaid health homes for individuals with substance use
			 disorders.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H20BE4ACE99A84455AF655CE53A538A0D" style="OLC">
 <section id="HE9187A590CA74C1D8E159D5C9E47ECD1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Medicaid Health Homes for Opioid-Use-Disorder Medicaid Enrollees Encouraged Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Medicaid Health HOME Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H1B0A7C72ACE440129031AF9A35A2DBDC" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Extension of enhanced FMAP for certain health homes for individuals with substance use disorders</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1945 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396w-4">42 U.S.C. 1396w–4</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H731CA5BB035143148D8131A361833A48"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text> <subparagraph id="H679C861DBD1B4BBEA6FF9696766A6E45"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>subject to paragraph (4),</quote> after <quote>except that,</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D82EF44C1064F9BA67AA752ABEC94D1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDA1707A23A0546FC9268A9AD87A9C6BD" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HE63757568DA748CEA22C7226D70524CB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Special rule relating to substance use disorder health homes</header> <subparagraph id="H400A0CCA1A2645A98AF8466A76AE486F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a State with an SUD-focused State plan amendment approved by the Secretary on or after October 1, 2018, the Secretary may, at the request of the State, extend the application of the Federal medical assistance percentage described in paragraph (1) to payments for the provision of health home services to SUD-eligible individuals under such State plan amendment, in addition to the first 8 fiscal year quarters the State plan amendment is in effect, for the subsequent 2 fiscal year quarters that the State plan amendment is in effect. Nothing in this section shall be construed as prohibiting a State with a State plan amendment that is approved under this section and that is not an SUD-focused State plan amendment from additionally having approved on or after such date an SUD-focused State plan amendment under this section, including for purposes of application of this paragraph.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0BD14D84CA1A479E8B4070606C3290B8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Report requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a State with an SUD-focused State plan amendment for which the application of the Federal medical assistance percentage has been extended under subparagraph (A), such State shall, at the end of the period of such State plan amendment, submit to the Secretary a report on the following, with respect to SUD-eligible individuals provided health home services under such State plan amendment:</text>
 <clause id="H71A911E6A34249D8BF325B9ABBD27E87"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The quality of health care provided to such individuals, with a focus on outcomes relevant to the recovery of each such individual.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HCF6D7D47C3B34EA897545FB054C5F818"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The access of such individuals to health care.</text> </clause><clause id="HDCAE01B4B27E4574AD355F122375FDAC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total expenditures of such individuals for health care.</text>
									<continuation-text continuation-text-level="clause">For purposes of this subparagraph, the Secretary shall specify all applicable measures for
 determining quality, access, and expenditures.</continuation-text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA7E0A695E50478582E8F35DA321466E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Best practices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than October 1, 2020, the Secretary shall make publicly available on the Internet website of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services best practices for designing and implementing an SUD-focused State plan amendment, based on the experiences of States that have State plan amendments approved under this section that include SUD-eligible individuals.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0AED1A2B7A94D7C8D9C3D1FB542882C"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this paragraph:</text> <clause id="H0C6498BB504841378C5646E4C772AE6C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>SUD-eligible individuals</header><text>The term <quote>SUD-eligible individual</quote> means, with respect to a State, an individual who satisfies all of the following:</text>
 <subclause id="H01733A7431584CC3A1D1478BB1C40344"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The individual is an eligible individual with chronic conditions.</text> </subclause><subclause id="HFFAE8CD6B81C4FF79C4F4C4500399B52"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The individual is an individual with a substance use disorder.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H335B7A314E5B44AD924F2F1155EDDC3F"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The individual has not previously received health home services under any other State plan amendment approved for the State under this section by the Secretary.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="HE93F95E3552C4B9B9F1DA4AE3722C5FB"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>SUD-focused State plan amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>SUD-focused State plan amendment</quote> means a State plan amendment under this section that is designed to provide health home services primarily to SUD-eligible individuals.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


