<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H48D155BF43914051B2DE49758A9A2BE5" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4990 IH: Rehab and Ahmed Amer Foster Care Improvement Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4990</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180208">February 8, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend part E of title IV of the Social Security Act to require States to follow certain
			 procedures in placing a child who has been removed from the custody of his
			 or her parents.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HE55BB7B4A01348B0B0DCB821EA53F713" style="OLC">
 <section id="HA6F25DF5623343F7BC20265E1145CC00" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rehab and Ahmed Amer Foster Care Improvement Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H717BB09CA5CF44A580516CE8FD2FD679"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirement that States follow certain procedures in placing a child removed from the custody of his or her parents</header> <subsection id="HD802B768990C48F2928958A18284B333"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 471(a)(29) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/671">42 U.S.C. 671(a)(29)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF1CD868FAF4E4BC4A0F4F214F4C0EA6C" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H7884B60CD46B46CCA9BAD97E039DF7D9"><enum>(29)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides that—</text> <subparagraph id="H9588DA08B96943F48F6D4EAF074ECCF1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>within 30 days after the removal of a child from the custody of the parent or parents of the child, the State shall exercise due diligence to identify and provide notice to all adult grandparents and other adult relatives of the child (including any other adult relatives suggested by the parents), subject to exceptions due to family or domestic violence, that—</text>
 <clause id="H0C3A99CFB599440FB96D1C9E77264CAE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>specifies that the child has been or is being removed from the custody of the parent or parents of the child;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H9BCA97976C8543FCB3D9B3F16B58B68A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>explains the options the relative has under Federal, State, and local law to participate in the care and placement of the child, including any options that may be lost by failing to respond to the notice;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1418ECB159A34796A485D26C4E438574"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>describes the requirements under paragraph (10) of this subsection to become a foster family home and the additional services and supports that are available for children placed in such a home; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H5CDBB59CCD6C47DE9285D1B5CDCEA984"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>if the State has elected the option to make kinship guardianship assistance payments under paragraph (28) of this subsection, describes how the relative guardian of the child may subsequently enter into an agreement with the State under section 473(d) to receive the payments;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA611BD7249946A5B53CA3FB7E3AF0E2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">within 90 days after the State makes a placement decision with respect to the child, the State shall provide notice of the decision and the reasons therefor to each parent of the child, each relative who has expressed to the State an interest in caring for the child, the guardian, and the guardian ad litem for the child, the attorney for the child, the attorney for each parent of the child, the child (if the child is able to express an opinion regarding placement), and the prosecutor involved; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H159416208CA0450C98DFAFA857C8568E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the State shall establish procedures to—</text> <clause id="HCB6EC88D573F4FF4BEB3AC68CFEB5C89"><enum>(i)</enum><text>allow a person who receives a notice pursuant to subparagraph (B) to request, in writing, within 5 days after receipt of the notice, documentation of the reasons for the decision involved;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H698A8E80D5314AFEAEE15505D564AE60"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>allow the attorney for the child to petition the court involved to review the decision; and</text> </clause><clause id="HDDE2D2BC83854F958E4B1C4B1C6D7011"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>require the court to—</text>
 <subclause id="H4BF757D7FE174AFB8DAEDAC6719D986E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>commence such a review within 7 days after receipt of a petition made pursuant to clause (ii); and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H3D731E47578448C2B2AEAC13358C44EF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>conduct such a review on the record;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H644EF0CFCF994A7081C4CD2A87DF8078"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header>
 <paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H86AFCBA441EF4357AF2ABD249EFF9996"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by subsection (a) shall take effect on the 1st day of the 1st fiscal year beginning on or after the date of the enactment of this Act, and shall apply to payments under part E of title IV of the Social Security Act for calendar quarters beginning on or after such date.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFCA922A968E34B05833B9A36EB78DAA4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Delay permitted if State legislation required</header><text>If the Secretary of Health and Human Services determines that State legislation (other than legislation appropriating funds) is required in order for a State plan approved under part E of title IV of the Social Security Act to meet the additional requirements imposed by the amendment made by subsection (a), the plan shall not be regarded as failing to meet any of the additional requirements before the 1st day of the 1st calendar quarter beginning after the first regular session of the State legislature that begins after the date of the enactment of this Act. For purposes of the preceding sentence, if the State has a 2-year legislative session, each year of the session is deemed to be a separate regular session of the State legislature.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


