<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HECA891A1F85D40A39709977168B58113" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4842 IH: Streamlining Permitting to Enable Efficient Deployment of Broadband Infrastructure Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4842</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180118">January 18, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000364">Mr. Shimkus</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Communications Act of 1934 to provide that the Federal Communications Commission is not required to perform any review under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 or division A of subtitle III of title 54, United States Code, as a condition of permitting the placement and installation of a communications facility, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H484F5E72CFAE43FAA3CF399041215DD8" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HDA4FCFCE60B4443D985C4FDA78A8148C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Streamlining Permitting to Enable Efficient Deployment of Broadband Infrastructure Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H0B9C848E825D44BDA59EE21E7109B5E9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Exemption from review for certain communications facilities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title I of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/151">47 U.S.C. 151</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HCB33F3B5650241B7A682FE716D756912" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H4D9F6218CC1F44FFBCE5DAE8EA533CBD"><enum>13.</enum><header>Exemption from review for certain communications facilities</header> 
<subsection id="H6C21A298013A4691845AE89BE84EE85E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>For permitting by Commission</header> 
<paragraph id="HD1388B05B37B40FBA815A5277A7FBDAA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any provision of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321</external-xref> et seq.) or division A of subtitle III of title 54, United States Code, the Commission shall not be required to perform, and may not require any entity regulated by the Commission to perform, any review under such Act or division as a condition of permitting the placement and installation of a communications facility if—</text> <subparagraph id="H3050ABF607AA4CC98EE1E4EB1884BCB7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the new facility—</text> 
<clause id="H2381AD770827499CABACA7590D3EF3CE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>will be located within a public right-of-way; and</text></clause> <clause id="H4D474FF8D20B41D09335E2BD0EC81DBA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is not more than 50 feet tall or 10 feet higher than any existing structure in the public right-of-way, whichever is higher;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6BA6D81AEF5B4C519EB6A4B02ADF1222"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the new facility is—</text> <clause id="H9267CC51F085407C9BACBF9F2821BE11"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a replacement for an existing communications facility; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8F5785DCF6A04AA7B5DFEBADB730BC62"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the same as, or substantially similar to (as such term is defined by the Commission), the communications facility that the new communications facility is replacing;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H09B6DAFEE91445E8BFCC998C4A794085"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the new facility is a type of communications facility that—</text> 
<clause id="H3B93C935A2724CEB857F3708BEE8D590"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is described in subsection (c)(2)(B); and</text></clause> <clause id="H1A6CDB4BC03F4A918AE1E37B8C548DEA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>meets the size limitation of a small antenna established by the Commission; or</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H33CEF0D80E884C83919172DCD92B2D7D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the placement and installation involve the expansion of the site of an existing facility not more than 30 feet in any direction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H45DB82561B9F4C9E9AFBE0587D7CC3A0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Savings clause</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to affect—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2E29D38CFD844FD484E4F41736432DDB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the obligation of the Commission to evaluate radiofrequency exposure under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321</external-xref> et seq.);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H74785DDA2CCA4C068C3EB57488042F3F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>except as explicitly provided in this subsection, the obligation of any provider of a communications service to comply with the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321</external-xref> et seq.) or division A of subtitle III of title 54, United States Code;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFE86DB3500E74E779ED84D4AF3E40DBB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the authority of a State or local government to apply and enforce the zoning and other land use regulations of the State or local government to the extent consistent with this subsection and sections 253, 332(c)(7), and 621; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8A3254DB7AA2495AB1FBA1FFF074094F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the authority or obligations established under section 20156(e) of title 49, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H27F483C1B132451DA4CF1142FBB03F37"><enum>(b)</enum><header>For grant of easement on Federal property</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No review shall be required under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321</external-xref> et seq.) or division A of subtitle III of title 54, United States Code, as a condition of granting a covered easement for a communications facility if a covered easement has been granted for another communications facility or a utility facility with respect to the same building or other property owned by the Federal Government.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H48F3CCF412B74BD9A18D0DCBB910FA63"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H051BD386F1EC479389FEB3DCC5DBFDD8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Antenna</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>antenna</quote> means communications equipment that transmits or receives electromagnetic radio frequency signals used in the provision of wireless services.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDF52A26B68E6429087A56C8E3FBEFEC3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Communications facility</header><text>The term <quote>communications facility</quote> includes—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE56FF9A22B1A4497B7B2F1E8F74893AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any infrastructure, including any transmitting device, tower, or support structure, and any equipment, switches, wiring, cabling, power sources, shelters, or cabinets, associated with the licensed or permitted unlicensed wireless or wireline transmission of writings, signs, signals, data, images, pictures, and sounds of all kinds; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9DC4D6BAA7214F75A1920A36324207BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any antenna or apparatus—</text> 
<clause id="H09FCAA3F0EF74C4CA902A48CE31234CD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that is designed for the purpose of emitting or receiving radio frequency;</text></clause> <clause id="H899053B41E834D30AF6D3F22309EEFB3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that—</text> 
<subclause id="HB4503547E7BE4C0AB1F7064E1BF63077"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is designed to be operated, or is operating, from a fixed location pursuant to authorization by the Commission; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H83A56D3630D54001AC50ADEB8782FE9D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is using duly authorized devices that do not require individual licenses; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H4F86BE53E58B4699AE4D7B39622A196E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>that is added to a tower, building, support pole, or other structure.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H932772A3B47A4CD6A8DF212D5BD9CDEC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered easement</header><text>The term <quote>covered easement</quote> means an easement, right-of-way, or lease to, in, over, or on a building or other property owned by the Federal Government, excluding tribal land held in trust by the Federal Government (unless the tribal government of such land requests that the Commission not exclude the land for purposes of this definition), for the right to install, construct, modify, or maintain a communications facility.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H594EA6D3524C49CD818EA627E720979F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Public right-of-way</header><text>The term <quote>public right-of-way</quote>—</text> <subparagraph id="HF3ABAFE6BF254885A7E2A1B5AF7F33A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means—</text> 
<clause id="HD91747E879804DA99C3FCAAC6E7A56DA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the area on, below, or above a public roadway, highway, street, sidewalk, alley, or similar property; and</text></clause> <clause id="HC52684D0872E4B28854BBD0062241849"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any land immediately adjacent to and contiguous with property described in clause (i) that is within the right-of-way grant; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBDCE5D0346BF44F286E6EF71D3678A55"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include a portion of the Interstate System (as such term is defined in section 101(a) of title 23, United States Code).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCAAD9FF2524C4DB2A3D280BA9B0C3643"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Support Pole</header><text>The term <quote>support pole</quote> means an upright pole or structure used or capable of being used to support a wireless service facility.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFC1BED65F8594054B29539F48EA4DE73"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Utility facility</header><text>The term <quote>utility facility</quote> means any privately, publicly, or cooperatively owned line, facility, or system for producing, transmitting, or distributing power, electricity, light, heat, gas, oil, crude products, water, steam, waste, storm water not connected with highway drainage, or any other similar commodity, including any fire or police signal system or street lighting system, that directly or indirectly serves the public.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEF33582922AA4EDEAD6467E7816BF9F6"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Wireless service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>wireless service</quote> means the transmission by radio communication of voice, video, or data communications services, including Internet Protocol or any successor protocol-enabled services, or any combination of those services, whether provided on a licensed or permitted unlicensed basis.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H99228785D42E4C66B083DCFB922C721E"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Wireless service facility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>wireless service facility</quote> means a facility for the provision of wireless service.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> </legis-body></bill> 

