<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H3FB4301A505A4DADB27F00A5545E7C52" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5064 IH: Whaling Convention Amendments Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5064</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180215">February 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="Y000033">Mr. Young of Alaska</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize aboriginal subsistence whaling pursuant to the regulations of the International
			 Whaling Commission and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H26FDF9AEB1BD461AACB4CB77EC5007A4" style="OLC">
 <section id="H340525F91877460BA96A2A0A6480E463" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Whaling Convention Amendments Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H53471155C4F446FCA745F3B7FE527036"><enum>2.</enum><header>Amendment of the Whaling Convention Act of 194</header> <subsection id="HD2767F71CF6E4C8C8FDD56935AD728D3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Aboriginal subsistence whaling</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Whaling Convention Act of 1949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/916">16 U.S.C. 916</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by inserting after section 6 the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H81C8B2B244B943F4B01B176A7722F671" style="OLC">
					<section id="H0577805F68D846A295B7F5EEA6B02E0C"><enum>6A.</enum><header>Aboriginal subsistence whaling</header>
 <subsection id="H5DA5EBECA0964DFB80931C76E4E4F162"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce, or such officer as may be designated by the Secretary, shall authorize aboriginal subsistence whaling pursuant to paragraph 13 of the regulations of the Commission (or any successor to such paragraph), if such whaling—</text>
 <paragraph id="H7D459D52018740889AA2ECF350307596"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is for subsistence purposes (including the sale of authentic native articles of handicrafts and clothing);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0562D02C761B4889AB201CFD4A95195E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>does not include the striking, taking, or killing of calves or any whale accompanied by a calf; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H6180B6E6078145BF944CA91E930E0ACE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>is not accomplished in a wasteful manner.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H14AB35A97F264B18998026464071EBE8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Catch limit</header>
 <paragraph id="H664C882C5F2B47AE89025C7F36E375F4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement to establish</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce shall establish catch limits for the Alaska Native aboriginal subsistence whale hunt for any year, if the Secretary determines that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H651364B5C770454980264E038B43C68B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Commission has failed to adopt catch limits applicable to the hunt for such year; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95ABE0BAEE864DAFAEF143D6BF9B1A2D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the biological status of the affected stock is such that, based on the most recent review of the status of such stock by the Scientific Committee of the Commission, the aboriginal subsistence needs statement submitted by the United States to the Commission of that year is sustainable.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H83723806B5DF49A086ECFD6210C943DB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The catch limits established by the Secretary under paragraph (1) shall satisfy the Alaska Native subsistence needs described in a statement submitted by the United States to the Commission, and shall include carryover at the level accepted by the Scientific Committee of the Commission in its most recent review of the subsistence whaling quota.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDAF1F2B76CFC4077956A63E9413CB498"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>Nothing in paragraph (1) relieves the United States Commissioner of the Commissioner's obligation to continue seeking adoption by the Commission, pursuant to the paragraph 13 of the regulations of the Commission (or any successor to such paragraph that permits aboriginal subsistence whaling), of catch limits that provide for Alaska Native aboriginal subsistence needs.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H8FC135D18AC54846A3214912DA3860AF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiver of environmental review</header><text>The Whaling Convention Act of 1949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/916">16 U.S.C. 916</external-xref> et seq.), as amended by subsection (a), is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H08811A81AB8B4CB8AC4222DA08781CAA" style="OLC">
 <section id="HC1BC842B210D4D9A838FDF6E78125B4C"><enum>17.</enum><header>Waiver of environmental review</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">An action taken under this Act, with respect to a stock of a whale species, shall be deemed not to require any review under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321</external-xref> et seq.) if the Secretary determines such action is sustainable based on the most recent review of the status of such stock by the Scientific Committee of the Commission.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section><section id="HA4A55643A5554DBABEA3BE6934503E44"><enum>3.</enum><header>Implementing regulations</header>
 <subsection id="HF90C953C02E045CEA514A2E4F50FED67"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Commerce shall issue any regulations necessary to implement section 6A of the Whaling Convention Act of 1949, as added by section 2(a).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H04EB6DBCDA794D62B13B384A0DD20A5B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Review and updates</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce shall review and update the regulations required by subsection (a) as needed, and at least once every 5 years, after the date on which the Secretary of Commerce issues the regulations as a final rule.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


