<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HC9ACA03C545F4FEAADC70D0AE82E41C4" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4905 IH: Improvement of Mapping, Addresses, Geography, Elevations, and Structures Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4905</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180130">January 30, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney of West Virginia</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for improvements to National Flood Insurance Program rate maps, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H0BDDDD29C9F84074AF999662B8B5547A" style="OLC">
 <section id="H030B1A34F9C04CFFBCC43F43F50441F3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improvement of Mapping, Addresses, Geography, Elevations, and Structures Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>IMAGES Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HFE5694D903384B26A5E74B73E3A69D95" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Flood Mapping Program</header> <subsection id="H7092BE02CF3041C1869D4404B907B1DD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Inclusion of planimetric features in rate maps</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 100216(b)(3) of the Biggert-Waters Flood Insurance Reform Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4101b">42 U.S.C. 4101b(b)(3)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H2F64AC2A3CEF4764B21D17B1D14321F1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H201DC6695E5D4937BAD81106ED677352"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE2E14BA12C254D8EAA137F068AB89308"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDAA23AA33B7840A8AB53280125BBECA9" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H0D89A9228A4243CE8863932B30D765D6"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">planimetric features, including, for each planimetric feature—</text>
 <clause id="H3988FEDBBE4B46108EF1CC47893D4619"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the associated parcel identification data for such planimetric feature; and</text> </clause><clause id="H5D90DD10FB264CF586A79D74A73C6467"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable, using public and private sector address data, the address of such planimetric feature.</text>
							</clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0407AF4694174676BC557F637C381CD4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Format of rate maps</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 100216(c)(2) of the Biggert-Waters Flood Insurance Reform Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4101b">42 U.S.C. 4101b(c)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H555C474BB5B44B64A05EC7869629EFDF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HEF00AB4CAFFB474EB57DDF7F9C674B35"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HACBA47B747A1493986346DFE9935B368"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD82E280421E949D29CF74A5DB5C3FF46" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HEACE1DCAAF8B4C1CAF5AF5D153727B6C"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 5 years after the date that the National Geodetic Survey completes the National Spatial Reference System 2022, updated to conform with the geospatial data provided by such system; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD753C9D3371249C38C421F55DF997787"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">spatially accurate in accordance with the common protocols for geographic information systems under section 216 of the E-Government Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/44/3501">44 U.S.C. 3501</external-xref> note).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC72EA92D3BF74EB4BEA63E842AB791DC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Additional considerations</header><text>Section 100216 of the Biggert-Waters Flood Insurance Reform Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4101b">42 U.S.C. 4101b</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HFD7C92590514432BB4CBB091B59BB47D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (f) as subsection (k); and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H0F0C466CE8194EE29926AACB27FC7806"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (e) the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2818080849A44FFC86DE112E753F8030" style="OLC">
						<subsection id="H94BE3F0CC43647D3B824E1807EB8B4A9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Stream flow networks</header>
 <paragraph id="H5E52946CF83149C3A1A074750058BE61"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall coordinate with the United States Geological Survey to ensure that, to the extent necessary to maintain the stream flow networks critical to the National Flood Insurance Program, flood risk mapping, and flood risk assessments—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HCEC36D01704F4FB69B8CA2A1034A9255"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the stream gage stations in such stream flow networks are operational and use modern hardware;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H321290A632A14CD990C74F4B711104A0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such stream flow networks are sufficiently densified by adding new stream gage stations in high-risk areas;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBDC4444B49A47B4ACACAF08839FC7BE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>inactive critical stream gage stations in such stream flow networks are reactivated; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22BA7CA50CDA4195BADA0629F807F777"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the speed of the geospatial real-time data feeds from such stream gage stations is increased.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H19ED6298C9EF49D397F531EA1E2298F5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text> <subparagraph id="H9A09D140E587402BB5ED27737F5A3BE7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Stream flow network</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>stream flow network</quote> means a network of stream flow gages maintained under the direction of the United States Geological Survey and its partners that is used to measure or record the flow of water down a stream or river, or through an entire watershed system, and transmit such information using a geospatial real-time data feed.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD5B58FDAA1042999C7FB4371AB0690F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Stream gage station</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>stream gage station</quote> means a device installed at the edge of a river or stream that measures or records the flow of water down the stream and additional information such as water height, water chemistry, and water temperature.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0E411D295A0F47B4A5C2E0BA1CAF0138"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Availability of data to public</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall make available to the public on the website of the Federal Emergency Management Agency a national geospatial data repository that—</text>
 <paragraph id="HA01EF12E2DC54BC18995FF56811AE6B3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides access to the raw data used to include the planimetric features and parcel identification data in National Flood Insurance Program rate maps;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H44E712D9F0054BD498B41076DEA42EE6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent that such data is available, allows users to view, query, and obtain such data at multiple levels of detail, including down to the property level;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2F0E6C86A090474AB78BE220A2333C06"><enum>(3)</enum><text>allows users to view flood risks, flood insurance zones, and flood elevations;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H3F84B043FCA84B4FBC1B2151C2014B8C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides access to flood mapping and related information such as—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H428A078C10BD45CF9807C741840C0B0E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>hydrologic and hydraulic models used in determining flood risk;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB1D04672BF34F92822BB2CA57E44CC6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>structure footprints where available;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A547257FBC24469B4C111F422D9F0F2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>flood depth grids;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A72E00C7DAD480DB124B91F096B52E2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>flood risk reports;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8824C9E5E6C4AF1B5E73695B00E33CB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>flood risk assessments (Hazus analyses);</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H531B34F0F34647CEBBBE765223A00B51"><enum>(F)</enum><text>hazard mitigation plans; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A0A583EC7B3444C8B518E2CFC15D816"><enum>(G)</enum><text>other flood risk products at the discretion of the Administrator; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HDF97F9C20E3041EA948C4962DF9D24A4"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maintains and disseminates such data in a consistent manner.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9A0ECA26091C4DF2B86A41B26AAC5CC6"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Ensuring current data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less frequently than once every 5 years, the Administrator shall verify that each National Flood Insurance Program rate map contains data that is current and credible.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H66708239F92F4679A49DE913E6892CDD"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Qualifications-Based Selection Contracting</header>
 <paragraph id="HF1F7406105D34A1297BB9AAE91E2F143"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a contract awarded by the Administrator under this Act, or by an entity receiving a grant under this Act, for program management, architectural and engineering services, or surveying and mapping, such a contract shall be awarded to a contractor selected in accordance with the procedures described in section 1103 of title 40, United States Code (or an applicable equivalent State qualifications-based statute). The Administrator, or entity, as the case may be, shall require such contractor, as a condition of such contract, to award any subcontract for program management, architectural and engineering services, or surveying and mapping in accordance with the procedures described in the previous sentence, or the applicable equivalent State statute.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H54372B0694F84B38B08A504B488400F6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Relationship to State law</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection shall supersede any applicable State licensing law governing professional licensure.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HC4B135D395CE4DFAAB8E46B7BC4CA0E9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection:</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HB5235D9B129343A898E47F260778B201"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Architectural and engineering services</header><text>The term <quote>architectural and engineering services</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 1102 of title 40, United States Code.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0D06A0D368B3402B9871578C711B8E71"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Surveying and mapping</header><text>The term <quote>surveying and mapping</quote> includes geospatial activities associated with measuring, locating, and preparing maps, charts, or other graphical or digital presentations depicting natural and man-made physical features, phenomena, and legal boundaries of the earth, including the following:</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="H179F2F8EE8CB4C3BB14C6E6C55306C35"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Topographic Engineering Surveying, including acquisition of topographic oriented surveying and mapping data for design, construction, master planning, operations, as-built conditions, precise structure stability studies using conventional and electronic instrumentation, photogrammetric, LiDAR, remote sensing, inertial, satellite, and other manned and unmanned survey methods as applicable.</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HEA5EEA26AC6247A5B1DA1CC1BA6E7E6C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Hydrographic Engineering Surveying, including acquisition of hydrographic oriented surveying and mapping data for design, construction, dredging, master planning, operations, and as-built conditions using conventional and electronic instrumentation, and pho­to­gram­me­tric, remote sensing, inertial, satellite, side scan sonar, subbottom profiling, and other surveying methods, as applicable.</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H5C1D3D5877BE490A94A28F48E0C969CE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Land Surveying, including property and boundary surveys, mon­u­men­ta­tion, marking and posting, and preparation of tract descriptions, using conventional, electronic instrumentation, pho­to­gram­me­tric, inertial, satellite, and other survey methods, as applicable.</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H4E443014CCD94ADB98132E7DC60CCBAE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Geodetic Surveying, including first, second, and third order horizontal and vertical control surveys, geodetic astronomy, gravity and magnetic surveys using conventional, electronic instrumentation, photogrammetric, inertial, satellite, and other survey methods, as applicable.</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H099A9CB99B38469BB91285E37772E763"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Cartographic Surveying, including acquisition of topographic and hydrographic oriented surveying and mapping data for construction of maps, charts, and similar products for planning, flood analysis, and general use purposes using conventional and electronic instrumentation, photogrammetric, inertial, satellite, mobile, terrestrial, and other survey methods, as applicable.</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HC573F02983054F53B2FBAF8713A2459A"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Mapping, charting, and related geospatial database development, including the design, compilation, digitizing, attributing, scribing, drafting, printing and dissemination of printed or digital map, chart, and related geospatial database products associated with planning, engineering, operations, and related real estate activities using photogrammetric, geographic information systems, and other manual and computer assisted methods, as applicable.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3EA839F5B839471D946DFCC8256D8A78"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H73E320216127430EA367C3871410F4CB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Planimetric feature</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>planimetric feature</quote> means the geographic elements and features—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H39611B112A824ABF8E715EE9EDA744A9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that are independent of elevation, such as roads, structure footprints, and rivers and lakes;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0030FF113E748BF9D75C6167EB74797"><enum>(B)</enum><text>which are represented on maps to show the true location and size of the elements in relationship to each other, as they are seen from the air; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H8FC20F32144842BE8C038061E0DDDA4E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>that are mapped from LiDAR or aerial photography by employing basic photogrammetry.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC29801C2579E49BF919E045056271135"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Parcel identification data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>parcel identification data</quote> means the information associated with a parcel of land, including the geographic location, unique parcel identifier, boundaries, structures contained within the parcel, zoning classification, and owner.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2E18A67197FA42B889F61E98A07BDCA6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Funding for elevation data</header><text>Section 1310 of the National Flood Insurance Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4017">42 U.S.C. 4017</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2EAF8A532FAC491984C56CB58D2B7775" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="H798477DB21C5456BACF166112299E500"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Allocation from the National Flood Insurance Fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each fiscal quarter the Administrator shall allocate from the National Flood Insurance Fund an amount equal to 5 percent of any revenue collected under section 1308(b)(3) for use for creating or maintaining current and accurate National Flood Insurance Program Rate Maps.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HBFC6D397D6A049D3BAC0DA5726AF0F4D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 100216(j) of the Biggert-Waters Flood Insurance Reform Act of 2012, as so redesignated by the preceding provisions of this Act, is further amended by striking <quote>$400,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2013 through 2017</quote> and inserting <quote>$500,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2018 through 2023</quote>.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


