<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0F53AF0FE0D645148C0B686229EC8DCA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5646 IH: Protecting against Opioid Prescription-abuse during Prenatal Year Study Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5646</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180427">April 27, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001250">Mr. Bishop of Utah</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001192">Mr. Stewart</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000600">Mr. Diaz-Balart</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000584">Mrs. Love</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Health and Human Services to submit to Congress a report on opioids prescribing practices for pregnant women.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H011E461565314826AF724B1A411AF04E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB76BEB22F4234B8A989C79A53B425933" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting against Opioid Prescription-abuse during Prenatal Year Study Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>POPPY Study Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H17A83709C3BE42B3BE26022543A81075" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on opioids prescribing practices for pregnant women</header> <subsection id="H4ABE637AF8124DD199C0A94362FF12AB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, in coordination with the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the National Institutes of Health, and the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration shall develop and submit to the Congress a report—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7153B20EB61746E59E18E23FABF371F2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>on opioids prescribing practices for pregnant women and recommendations for such practices;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4B322811DF784476A6C568DEF64C3748"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that provides recommendations for identifying and reducing opioids misuse during pregnancy; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8A4D2CA2C504431EAFF51D3059F41982"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on prescription opioid misuse during pregnancy in urban and rural areas;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA86E2C0987084999AC8DC2D2AACAFBAD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>on prescription opioid use during pregnancy for the purpose of medication-assisted treatment in urban and rural areas;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H51A1B4AE17F14D20B9A419F48F714F73"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evaluating current utilization of non-opiate pain management practices in place of prescription opioids during pregnancy;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE281473FB8CC4B278F83BC4F369D65B2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>providing guidelines encouraging the use of non-opioid pain management practices during pregnancy when safe and effective; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDF1FE0868B71406284A6897838F1C471"><enum>(7)</enum><text>that provides recommendations for increasing public awareness and education of opioid use disorder in pregnancy, including available treatment resources in urban and rural areas.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEA4576E5E99443F3BC55621C683CAB62"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No additional funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No additional funds are authorized to be appropriated for purposes of carrying out subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


