<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H425C56F45FE44B23A10214CDE7B853CB" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5000 IH: Free to Fly Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress>115th CONGRESS</congress>
		<session>2d Session</session>
		<legis-num>H. R. 5000</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180213">February 13, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001290">Mr. Brat</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title>To amend title 49, United States Code, to allow certain persons to own and control an air carrier
			 providing air transportation or intrastate air transportation, and for
			 other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H5D6A013489B8497AB4E1238522BE6E80" style="OLC">
 <section id="HB487574787FA481287F2C74F0369CB57" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Free to Fly Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="idD5785BACEEB8496ABD4B02BF248075EC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 40102(a) of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="id295ed131cd074b83936e671e87e9536e"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2) by striking <quote>citizen of the United States</quote> and inserting <quote>citizen of the United States, or other person organized under the laws of the United States or a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory or possession of the United States,</quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="idDFDFA115EBD7421E96240AE358ED94B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (15)(C)—</text> <subparagraph id="id23A3528C07E3453CA18E3A4D484018D6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>of which the president and at least two-thirds of the board of directors</quote> and inserting <quote>of which the president and at least 51 percent of the board of directors</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="idC2E66C4774A04A61BE901CEC23851DD0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>at least 75 percent of the voting interest</quote> and inserting <quote>at least 51 percent of the voting interest</quote>;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id6E0CC6B078554F969D2A2CC1F05BBBAE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (21) by striking <quote>not a citizen of the United States</quote> and inserting <quote>who is not organized under the laws of the United States or a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory or possession of the United States</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="id409002B9754C4C5F8A8E905BB06EB17E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in paragraph (26) by striking <quote>citizen of the United States</quote> and inserting <quote>citizen of the United States or other person organized under the laws of the United States or a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory or possession of the United States</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="id8AE1620509014992BB0E54A8349A25E4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Requirement for certificate</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 41101(b) of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="id02874159be754133b4a63112c7747960"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>citizen of the United States</quote> and inserting <quote>citizen of the United States or other person organized under the laws of the United States or a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory or possession of the United States</quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="id99E11B6C905B4E69BDFEDF1F4DF755FA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (1) by striking <quote>citizen</quote> and inserting <quote>citizen or other person</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="id00E88DD3153B48B6B1B8FB2E474E0CD2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (c) as subsection (d); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="idE8C102545DED4392910F68C8AF2C54AB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (b) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idAA6AD86D00EB43F5ACEF6AE6FCB82FDA" style="OLC"> <subsection id="id3208AEFB29C24C2D9E83B43BAC104BD0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Additional requirements for non-Citizens operating certain routes</header><text>In order for a person who is not a citizen of the United States and who is not a foreign air carrier to be issued and maintain a certificate for air transportation or intrastate air transportation, all employees and managing officers, other than the board of directors, must be citizens, nationals, or lawful permanent residents of the United States, and the person’s headquarters and base of operations must be located in the United States.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></section><section id="id4646C87266314B71BB5EB1D2376A425D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Issuance of certificates of public convenience</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 41102 of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="iddff80f85fc914dcab7c69a1ac3c96fd8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking the subsection heading in subsection (a) and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="USC">Issuance to a citizen</header-in-text></quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="id96D26EF9C3F0480DAE3B9B33591800BD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (b), (c), and (d) as subsections (c), (d), and (e), respectively;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="id1D2674D1D63C418EA1AC2B5F99637D09"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (a) the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id96A3D783531D48A0BDF38D28B6D46D47" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="idE109C6EA0CF4451C80273E500E616C5A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Issuance to other persons</header><text>The Secretary of Transportation may issue a certificate of public convenience and necessity to a person organized under the laws of the United States or a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory or possession of the United States, of which more than 49 percent of the board of directors are not citizens of the United States, which is not under the actual control of citizens of the United States, or in which more than 49 percent of the voting interest is owned or controlled by persons that are not citizens of the United States, to provide any part of the following air transportation the person has applied for under section 41108 of this title:</text>
 <paragraph id="id0b528d9a63244a33a0a1a61c6192020a"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Air transportation as an air carrier.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="idDF6E3ACC949D4EFEB4FA5C527C903FA3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Temporary air transportation as an air carrier for a limited period.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="idC3A9576DC7BC496CB0373F2A4D992136"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Charter air transportation as a charter air carrier.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph><paragraph id="idD2DC685DFC3249CBBA1AC024486E6F74"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (c), as redesignated—</text>
 <subparagraph id="id1B49BB61FA8A47F8A2E40A0E4626D2B3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>under subsection (a)</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>under subsection (a) or subsection (b)</quote> in each such place; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="idE6395E4021CD4D17AD9B357C84CEBD2A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>citizen</quote> and inserting <quote>citizen or other person</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idE4DA98ED7C0B4240BE88C2A138E036D8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by striking subsection (e), as redesignated, and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idFC67AAAD10D14748BF978D3D65977363" style="OLC"> <subsection id="idE85C95D4C446480AB2F95F815F9B4C6E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Presidential review of certain certificates</header><text>The Secretary shall submit each decision to the President under section 41307 of this title authorizing—</text>
 <paragraph id="idcb80e5e8c1ad42ae983aebe4e0b1bfbd"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the provision of foreign air transportation; or</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="id1cf9f7a45b754555af6778245d3044cc"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the provision of interstate air transportation or intrastate air transportation by a person who is not a citizen of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></section><section id="idE805614AE7DF41E888C1DD9171582C91"><enum>5.</enum><header>Civil Reserve Air Fleet eligibility</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 41106 of title 49, United States Code, is amended by striking subsection (d) and inserting the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6C63D83DEDDF4E13ACA74446F14467F5" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="id08C3D4A29DB140DBA409ABABA6CE70CB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The Secretary of Defense may contract with an air carrier that does not meet all requirements if—</text> <paragraph id="ida106cfd82641412fad1ffedcc5f11e9f"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary decides that no air carrier holding a certificate under section 41102 is capable of providing, and willing to provide, the airlift services; or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="id6E1E7422207F4C01B8B76D51B0B57839"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary decides to grant a waiver under section 9518 of title 10, United States Code, for a person who is not a citizen of the United States and who is organized under the laws of the United States that has a certificate of public convenience and necessity, from the Civil Reserve Air Fleet citizenship requirements for the purposes of eligibility and participation.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </section><section id="idC8B0B2572EBF4DB1A9DC6F3E556B8E67"><enum>6.</enum><header>Application for certificate of public convenience</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 41108 of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="idf2f7405658564bb88a00b298c8d46bee"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a) by striking <quote>citizen of the United States</quote> and inserting <quote>citizen of the United States or other person organized under the laws of the United States or a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory or possession of the United States</quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="idEFF45885EFC14FC2AE232AF38362E1DF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsections (b) and (c) by striking <quote>citizen</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>citizen or other person</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="idF44CF870419044BB9E13ECE8ECE30D97"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(3)(A) by striking <quote>interstate air transportation</quote> and inserting <quote>interstate air transportation provided by a citizen</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="id813B82AE56CD4E22BA35DF45B8C4B612"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(3)(B) by striking <quote>foreign air transportation</quote> and inserting <quote>interstate air transportation or intrastate air transportation by a person who is not a citizen of the United States, or foreign air transportation,</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="id412CE0EEA9724DF090386FEC4923DA31"><enum>7.</enum><header>Potential revocation of certificate</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 41110(a)(2)(B) of title 49, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>sections 41308–41310(a)</quote> and inserting <quote>sections 41101(c), 41308–41310(a)</quote>.</text> </section><section id="idA098F0551157430BB90EBF29A2DD8EAB"><enum>8.</enum><header>Liability insurance and financial responsibility</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 41112(a) of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="idff25c2ea905d4257bc9f663e1b4b83dd"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>citizen of the United States</quote> and inserting <quote>citizen of the United States, or other person organized under the laws of the United States or a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory or possession of the United States</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="idBA3046C2406D4A158FA465A52E655735"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>citizen</quote> the second place it appears and inserting <quote>citizen or other person</quote>.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="idBAD29A866ABE4099A50AEC90B5865D0E"><enum>9.</enum><header>Presidential review of foreign air carriers and other non-citizens</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 41307 of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="idc4683082a71049a58e70d818115a72df"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking the section heading and inserting <quote><header-in-text style="USC">Presidential review of actions about foreign air transportation and air transportation provided by non-citizens</header-in-text></quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="idA7988FD9C0E74B57AB0D08C389A9DC58"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>to provide foreign air transportation</quote> and inserting <quote>to provide foreign air transportation, or for a person who is not a citizen of the United States to provide air transportation or intrastate air transportation</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="id5ACA80DB829A4FC7B022FF992C297289"><enum>10.</enum><header>Joint pricing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 41503 of title 49, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>citizen of the United States</quote> and inserting <quote>a citizen of the United States or other person organized under the laws of the United States or a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory or possession of the United States</quote>.</text>
 </section><section id="idD5575178409445E9BA4E0035FDF3A7C3"><enum>11.</enum><header>Navigation of foreign civil aircraft</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 41703(a) of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="id40fc35d464f3407c9181349b5ec6908b"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (4) by striking the period and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="id4e3171bf89f64f439da76b8e13921a58"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idCD9B1A32240346DD94A7B9F9238E31A8" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="id98B801E4B3FF458CB0A71C230FFA6182"><enum>(5)</enum><text>if specifically authorized under sections 41102 and 41108, and if the airman holds a certificate issued or made valid by the Government.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph></section><section id="idFED225FFDD8248CBB3C0B6AC70B26F9E"><enum>12.</enum><header>Waivers for non-citizen air carrier participation in the Civil Reserve Air Fleet</header>
 <subsection id="idDD2D89D39AF24A40A94251EAA989659A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/931">Chapter 931</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idEC6AC1A78E4D475CAB9AAE8A514DBB2A" style="USC"> <section id="idD9BAA7C703194740A27795E0701D3850"><enum>9518.</enum><text>Non-citizen air carriers: waiver authority</text>
 <subsection id="id20D4D46A00284FF3A81C70690E8D6509"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Waiver authority</header><text>In the case of any air carrier described in subsection (b) or any aircraft owned by an air carrier described in subsection (b), the Secretary of Defense may waive any citizenship requirement under this chapter. Any such waiver—</text>
 <paragraph id="id34793895ce5d4e2ca0407772113d7668"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall be for a period not to exceed two years;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="id2E9F3B4760B246C7A603751CE2E5FC37"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may be revoked at any time by the Secretary; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="idEF6F9C55D2414E369CF8AD7F0C6D4559"><enum>(3)</enum><text>may be renewed for an additional two-year period for an unlimited number of times.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id667FB12D1C5749FBB2504035AAA601DD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Air carrier described</header><text>An air carrier described in this section is an air carrier—</text>
 <paragraph id="id79b3a4efad0d4a128c07d619c377c0d8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>owned by a person who is not a citizen of the United States and who is organized under the laws of the United States or a State, territory, or the District of Columbia; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="id2A7FDEB6DB0A4B978B96C4037DE6C592"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that holds a certificate of public convenience and necessity under section 41102 of title 49.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection><subsection id="idCB94F96B452C483D9909665705AF64FC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idCD4C5E54BCDC4AB8BB0C93C350A39926" style="OLC"><toc><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">9518. Non-citizen air carriers: waiver authority.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


