<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H11BAD927995B4B4292562F0780CE6D38" key="H" public-private="public">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4752 IH: Financial Technology Innovation and Defense Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4752</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180110">January 10, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001305">Mr. Budd</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish an Independent Financial Technology Task Force, to provide rewards for information leading to convictions related to terrorist use of digital currencies, to establish a FinTech Leadership in Innovation Fund to encourage the development of tools and programs to combat terrorist and illicit use of digital currencies, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form> 
<legis-body id="HE428E162B07D4015A7E5BC72BBDE8550" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H131F62C4206748DF830F220469B57CA7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Financial Technology Innovation and Defense Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> <section id="HDC39BDFB5D934F4DB66969C12F59BCFF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the Federal Government should prioritize the investigation of terrorist and illicit use of new financial technology, including digital currencies.</text> </section>
<section id="H38401C7019CE47DFA52FE898872103A8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Independent Financial Technology Task Force</header> 
<subsection id="H331EB1499D634270AF042CC5D369AFE7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established the Independent Financial Technology Task Force (the <quote>Task Force</quote>), which shall consist of—</text> <paragraph id="H13908670813E408AA71B48497E982C0B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Treasury, who shall serve as the head of the Task Force;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H421A7590AB31467780B09951F8D23F0C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Attorney General;</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C0BD69514414B75A8A5B6B2340A2BBD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Director of the Central Intelligence Agency;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H232A06D317C8482798AE7E9E7772F840"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Director of the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network;</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H522684423229434594401DE4E30E3EEE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Director of the Secret Service;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H68A9EFD2C6BC4BD780047BEF95AE9784"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigations; and</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="HF3A82D1B9C794855B113DA2E8E761673"><enum>(7)</enum><text>4 individuals appointed by the Secretary of the Treasury to represent the private sector (including the banking industry, non-profit groups, and think tanks).</text> </paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H017FC2B7E2D048E99597C4D2464C6268"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Task Force shall—</text> <paragraph id="H25F1988C4B7742E68A771EF7DD8FA54B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct independent research on terrorist and illicit use of new financial technologies, including digital currencies; and</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCEF9DFB5B57D4772901A89AB18890D42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop legislative and regulatory proposals to improve counter-terrorist and counter-illicit financing efforts.</text> </paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9C0C1A74DC614AC1986DF2DB10EB5783"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Annual congressional report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Task Force shall issue a report to the Congress containing the findings and determinations made by the Task Force in the previous year and any legislative and regulatory proposals developed by the Task Force.</text> </subsection></section>
<section id="HF0F82918B78B44CB8BB347D8EE0B8684"><enum>4.</enum><header>Rewards for information related to terrorist use of digital currencies</header> 
<subsection id="HA60AF12ED5CA414F8A206F5D9F189C6B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury, in consultation with the Attorney General, shall establish a program to pay a reward to any person who provides information leading to the conviction of an individual involved with terrorist use of digital currencies.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="HD6F4C544355746A498CD8EAFCC397C9E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of appropriated funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent provided in advance by appropriation Acts, the Secretary may use appropriated funds to pay a reward under this section with respect to information leading to a conviction described under subsection (a) if the amount of fines and forfeitures related to such conviction are not sufficient to pay such reward.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HC5AF5F34556844D696336AFC246D3360"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of fines and forfeitures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to fines and forfeitures related to the conviction of an individual involved with terrorist use of digital currencies, the Secretary of the Treasury shall, without further appropriation or fiscal year limitation—</text> <paragraph id="HC5367B221A7246CD9FE5F7A9EC1DEBCF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use such amounts to pay rewards under this section related to such conviction;</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6D9DC71BD2624D088FB5727437AE0077"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to any such amounts remaining after payments are made under paragraph (1), repay to the general fund of the Treasury—</text> <subparagraph id="H807BF6FF55124F4EA0E68219CF2B2205"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any reward amounts paid using appropriated funds under subsection (b); and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9B1B5E1FBF8B445CAD352269C7457AA8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amount of any funds appropriated to the FinTech Leadership in Innovation Fund established under section 5; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H32A9687399794DAE9D22FAC82227CB5D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to any such amounts remaining after payments are made under paragraphs (2) and (3), deposit such amounts in the FinTech Leadership in Innovation Fund.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HF227EA3A603643A6930DF7A257CAB8DA"><enum>5.</enum><header>FinTech Leadership in Innovation Fund</header> 
<subsection id="H0B169780EC834ED6AAC5EFFB36483567"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established a fund to be known as the <quote>FinTech Leadership in Innovation Fund</quote>, which shall be available to the Secretary of the Treasury, without further appropriation or fiscal year limitation, to carry out this section.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="HEE5D335CAE5242DFACBAEF96BB6F7479"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Innovation grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"></text> 
<paragraph id="H81233DCDABD141939F3135237D15ABD3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall make grants for the development of tools and programs to detect terrorist and illicit use of digital currencies.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H2837BB6A1F29499CA269910EAC57F52E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible recipients</header><text>The Secretary may make grants under this subsection to entities located in the United States, including academic institutions, companies, non-profit institutions, individuals, and any other entities locating in the United States that the Secretary determines appropriate.</text> </paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0E6F2E2A97834597A62A42340480D75D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to tools and programs described under paragraph (1), in addition to grants for the development of such tools and programs, the Secretary may make grants under this subsection to carry out pilot programs using such tools, the development of test cases using such tools, and research related to such tools.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H6EDCEBC069664BDCB53B0CA226B7862E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Preferences</header><text>In making grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall give preference to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H71CE38DB3CBC4F1FB6FA81E0A25A558B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">technology that is non-proprietary or that is community commons-based;</text> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC8E640636C214B12B1827CA9A4AA3075"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">computer code that is developed and released on an open source basis; and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H663B05938E0344538F5DCC1A043BAAC1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">tools that are proactive (such as meeting regulatory requirements under <quote>know your customer</quote> and anti-money laundering requirements for any entity that has to comply with U.S. Government regulations) vs. reactive (such as aiding law enforcement organizations in catching illegal activity after the fact).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H13638FF4ACB144D49759D0DEB5C6481C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Other requirements</header> <subparagraph id="H044317F0F4C1464AA8DBE125095CC51D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Use of existing global standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any new technology developed with a grant made under this subsection shall be based on existing global standards, such as those developed by the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) and the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C).</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB75D76945075449F8B3A747143AA467C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Supporting existing laws or regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Tools and programs developed with a grant made under this subsection shall be in support of existing laws or regulations, including the Bank Secrecy Act.</text> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H57A884B0E91D4CC68B572AC89FEB94AD"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Open access requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Tools and programs developed with a grant made under this subsection shall be freely accessible and usable by the public. This requirement may be fulfilled by publicly availing application programming interfaces or software development kits.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDC3C90C3DF1046A4B7B27E04BE32EDDE"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H586A689D4DF44E0EAD415BD219D80F61"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Bank Secrecy Act</header><text>The term <quote>Bank Secrecy Act</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC38DE37EAAA94BF8800749DCB32AE010"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">section 21 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act;</text> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF67A5B38B57B4FBCA9B16D0952EAFAD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>chapter 2 of title I of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/91/508">Public Law 91–508</external-xref>; and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBEC4CB78D41A48C99F02A8CF8C60F567"><enum>(C)</enum><text>subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEF207D21F8BD4C7BA0FF01F57A75C3CA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Digital currency</header><text>The term <quote>digital currency</quote>—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H79EB03C8263B42B3A7920479D8254B67"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means a digital representation of value that—</text> <clause id="H6A721BA0B4AF48A69B4DB7E7460DBF24"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is used as a medium of exchange, unit of account, or store of value; and</text> </clause>
<clause id="HFD7E18EB8A404D55B6EAE58E769D5F59"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is not legal tender, whether or not denominated in legal tender; and</text> </clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8002DA1A13AD4FF5837B643A189A2B78"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include—</text> 
<clause id="H2630034945B14BF4A3E2985DBCDCB036"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a transaction in which a merchant grants, as part of an affinity or rewards program, value that cannot be taken from or exchanged with the merchant for legal tender, bank credit, or digital currency; or</text> </clause> <clause id="H7D85FDC15D404AE79FB3178A62C974D7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a digital representation of value issued by or on behalf of a publisher and used solely within an online game, game platform, or family of games sold by the same publisher or offered on the same game platform.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8A95FF57F2CC4A50983E455DBA23BF3E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Terrorist</header><text>The term <quote>terrorist</quote> includes a person carrying out domestic terrorism or international terrorism (as such terms are defined, respectively, under section 2331 of title 18, United States Code).</text> </paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

