<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HE0BE423A9C4246569EEB69E540C1C0A4" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5622 IH: Purposefully Expanding and Reinforcing the Statutes we Insist Support our Troops Against Military Sexual Trauma Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5622</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180425">April 25, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000463">Mr. Turner</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="T000465">Ms. Tsongas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To improve the ability of the Department of Defense to address sexual offenses, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HC249F391604C4C99A70AF04516841211" style="OLC">
 <section id="H8ABBD2CD45DF4DD0B40B48590A8EAA43" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Purposefully Expanding and Reinforcing the Statutes we Insist Support our Troops Against Military Sexual Trauma Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PERSIST Against MST Act</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="HB93E94613C284F4E8F196715A5CACF32"><enum>2.</enum><header>Oversight of registered sex offender management program</header>
 <subsection id="H57A7A96AFF514B6FA5EF12E75189A86C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation of official or entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall designate a single official or entity within the Office of the Secretary of Defense to have the principle responsibility in the Department of Defense for providing oversight of the registered sex offender management program of the Department.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HCC7E8AAE668841058A8C436CE86FCD36"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The official or entity designated under subsection (a) shall—</text> <paragraph id="H08B0674F212E40CDB913C66DD4C9E46A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">monitor compliance with Department of Defense Instruction 5525.20;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6ACB7C4F216E4B018D334631832919FF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">compile data on service members who have been convicted of a qualifying sex offense, including data on the sex offender registration status of each member;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF1628B5E43734A7CB267357F1551496A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maintain statistics of the total number of service members, by military department, who are required to register as sex offenders; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H438A43186ADF42098C9D564F2B793F4C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">perform such other duties as the Secretary of Defense may require.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD62AB44F6723446D942F1E2E47A9ACD5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Briefing required</header><text>Not later than June 1, 2019, the Secretary of Defense shall provide to the Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives a briefing on—</text>
 <paragraph id="HAA34B3E84473491E932ED16FFD26E4DF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the compliance of the military departments with the policies of the Department of Defense related to registered sex offenders;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H39210623B2174842AD59E2B9FF6EAD32"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the results of the data compiled under subsection (b); and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H3E1CB5140F8B419795D022445EA1C10B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any other matters determined to be appropriate by the Secretary.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7933B7B9432A4978BBE831F1A4E15640"><enum>3.</enum><header>Policy on expedited transfers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall issue policy guidance to clarify that section 673 of title 10, United States Code (relating to expedited transfers for members of the armed forces who are victims of a sexual assault or related offense), applies to all active duty service members of who are victims of sexual assault or a related offense under article 120, 120a, or 120c of the Uniform Code of Military Justices regardless of whether the service member’s sexual assault report is handled by the Sexual Assault Prevention Program or the Family Advocacy Program.</text>
 </section><section id="H6F1FB898ACDC428B894B58538765C89A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Information from Federal agencies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 546 of the Carl Levin and Howard P. <quote>Buck</quote> McKeon National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2015 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/113/291">Public Law 113–291</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1561">10 U.S.C. 1561</external-xref> note) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H415B51265B9B4C5DB531EAB57BD271C9" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="H65B2C7B694984D12AA959EF37B7A269D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Information from Federal agencies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon request by the chair of a panel, a department or agency of the Federal Government shall provide information that the panel considers necessary to carry out its duties under this section.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body>
</bill>


