<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA98901FBECB2472FB533C0A0A07A46BC" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5790 IH: To amend title XI of the Social Security Act to provide for clinical psychologist services models to be tested by the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Innovation, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5790</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180515">May 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000184">Mrs. Noem</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Judy Chu of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XI of the Social Security Act to provide for clinical psychologist services models
			 to be tested by the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Innovation, and for
			 other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HE7E2E5DBFA8A4267A5E67603E00E0D29" style="OLC">
		<section id="H71992C17204D41E3AFFC12084C40D8B5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Clinical psychologist services models under the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Innovation; GAO
			 study and report</header>
 <subsection id="H8DC806083DED4D3788F4D77086F5639C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>CMI models</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1115A(b)(2)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1315a">42 U.S.C. 1315a(b)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new clauses:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H45D4B59CB11144E9A0CB08E650A3EE09" style="OLC">
 <clause id="H321D4A22259441D6882FD9F61862E204"><enum>(xxv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Supporting ways to familiarize individuals with the availability of coverage under part B of title XVIII for qualified psychologist services (as defined in section 1861(ii)).</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA6A3CBB8FB994A34867B7FDB940A3621"><enum>(xxvi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Exploring ways to avoid unnecessary hospitalizations or emergency department visits for mental and behavioral health services (such as for treating depression) through use of a 24-hour, 7-day a week help line that may inform individuals about the availability of treatment options, including the availability of qualified psychologist services (as defined in section 1861(ii)).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H9145AAB628B245A993B417A94BC9FDCC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>GAO study and report</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study, and submit to Congress a report, on mental and behavioral health services under the Medicare program under title XVIII of the Social Security Act, including an examination of the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HF18079FD608A48AD8D9CF01CDDB59DEA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Information about services furnished by psychiatrists, clinical psychologists, and other professionals.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H899721BB37D84B41B0B0E4B20876D576"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Information about ways that Medicare beneficiaries familiarize themselves about the availability of Medicare payment for qualified psychologist services (as defined in section 1861(ii) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(ii)</external-xref>) and ways that the provision of such information could be improved.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


