<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA3A3202C281E4EF9A11D4AC7DC1C1949" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5580 IH: Surveillance and Testing of Opioids to Prevent Fentanyl Deaths Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5580</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180423">April 23, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster of New Hampshire</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M001193">Mr. MacArthur</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000297">Mr. Jenkins of West Virginia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Health and Human Services to conduct programs to address the usage of
			 illicit drugs, particularly fentanyl, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H46FB38331A0D49EC8FDEF8D1D125364F" style="OLC">
 <section id="HD046F71EC392446FB6F460C23F19874A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Surveillance and Testing of Opioids to Prevent Fentanyl Deaths Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>STOP Fentanyl Deaths Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HBB78280F38224ADF92DBE13D4D9AC1B6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Public health laboratories to detect fentanyl</header> <subsection id="H686CCD7BE34241199173F3E55680E65A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall establish a program to award grants to Federal, State, and local agencies for the establishment or operation of public health laboratories to detect fentanyl, its analogues, and other synthetic opioids, as described in subsection (b).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HC4196C61A3614469B099125F3EA1C109"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use, and in consultation with the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H4E513F6FCBCE4BB3B340212D3C6FB53F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop standards for effectively handling and testing fentanyl, its analogues, and other synthetic opioids; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H140938E6251440D39C6FDDF328BB5AB9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include in such standards procedures for encountering new and emerging synthetic opioid formulations and reporting those findings to other Federal, State, and local public health laboratories.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5F8B2725D0D54380B328EE4247CDCE39"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Laboratories</header><text>Each public health laboratory funded under subsection (a) shall—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="HD562E8B2FF57483B83DF58BB68671218"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">agree to follow the standards established under subsection (b) and be capable of providing systematic and routine laboratory testing of drugs for the purposes of obtaining and disseminating public health information to Federal, State, and local public health officials, laboratories, and other entities the Secretary deems appropriate;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6B103219652A4818A9F47C2664F11E6C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">work with law enforcement agencies and public health authorities to develop real-time information on the purity and movement of fentanyl, its analogues, and other synthetic opioids;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2151889F377E45A6A413A549F7C28D6A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assist State and local law enforcement agencies in testing seized drugs when State and local forensic laboratories request additional assistance; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3E6050B45CF14517A8E2CAC0DE4FD21B"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide early warning information and advice to Federal, State, and local law enforcement agencies and public health authorities of potential significant changes in the supply of fentanyl, its analogues, and other synthetic opioids.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEEB1C24F11B5448D8FBCF7B82892E520"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $15,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2018 through 2022.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HF05EAC6A3002490AABA25A6B9F482CE3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Enhanced fentanyl surveillance</header>
 <subsection id="H32FF7E7B356147ACAF09BB5D15BAE546"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention shall enhance its drug surveillance program by—</text>
 <paragraph id="H3FE6EDD035DB438881AE60A406D30CFD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>expanding its surveillance program to include all 50 States and the territories of the United States;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H37814C3CF7E9422FADEB0D6194BCAC1C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>increasing and accelerating the collection of data on fentanyl, its analogues, and other synthetic opioids, including related overdose data from medical examiners and drug treatment admissions; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC9E1710EFD7441BDBAD2F349423C501B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>utilizing available and emerging information on fentanyl, its analogues, and other synthetic opioids, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE5E70E51128F4451B4E6A7A12202DCC7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the National Drug Early Warning System;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H326F9222D4814626A4FCAEEA44597120"><enum>(B)</enum><text>State and local public health authorities; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE602146A9CAC4B3EB215D60B3CB58916"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Federal, State, and local public health laboratories.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE568EFA35D884EA6A3F66ACDF9EEB4FB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2018 through 2022.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H905F851C418F43FF8F4E1A78ED74DF50"><enum>4.</enum><header>Pilot program for point-of-use testing of illicit drugs for dangerous contaminants</header>
 <subsection id="H03E554644A53424FAE22587272203CAA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use, in coordination with the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="HC0CC27BF499745E2A93FF33A4A5B5B19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish a pilot program through which 5 State or local agencies conduct, in 5 States, point-of-use testing of illicit drugs for dangerous contaminants;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDDEC10D0FB59476687FDD9CC2B066502"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish metrics to evaluate the success of the pilot program in reducing drug overdose rates; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HC46B5673EF6B467F910032D6F647C62B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>based on such metrics, conduct an annual evaluation of the pilot program and submit an annual report to the Congress containing the results of such evaluation.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H594EB4F350734CE88DC70F82F7CAAF9C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2018 through 2022.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


