<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HCEF03A744F2A4625AD8B22E60B717929" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5733 IH: DHS Industrial Control Systems Capabilities Enhancement Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5733</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180509">May 9, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000601">Mr. Ratcliffe</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to provide for the responsibility of the National
			 Cybersecurity and Communications Integration Center to maintain
			 capabilities to identify threats to industrial control systems, and for
			 other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HEC319B9AFBF84900AB7AD116D2CB5906" style="OLC">
 <section id="H6600819610DD4199B670A9B9D6707453" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>DHS Industrial Control Systems Capabilities Enhancement Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H9E41CE25C9484E719907EB6A0CEED492"><enum>2.</enum><header>Capabilities of National Cybersecurity and Communications Integration Center to identify threats to industrial control systems</header> <subsection id="HA2FD34E9588C463FAA82D44971FAA968"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 227 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/148">6 U.S.C. 148</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE1F9D03AA0F2446D89CA4C3AA48B28ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(1)—</text> <subparagraph id="HB3155E89DB5349618F0F0DFA2A5A0366"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A5022BB60B248B399BE7F2410A5ACC0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (H), by inserting <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61CC31AAE8E34619A6B5EAEFC73F52A6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
						<quoted-block id="H48240E7EF32C477088A289FFC2B590AB" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="HB9B836CB99734E84BF2F2FFC53D9BFC2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>activities of the Center address the security of both information technology and operational technology, including industrial control systems;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FD93867A54E4F06816D590817D92765"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (f) through (m) as subsections (g) through (n), respectively; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HF0F48C3674F545B6949FE9ABB24CD3BD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (d) the following new subsection:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H903D033F5C374179B3C5B8146F298AF7" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="H34595DD900FF462384D2218053E553BE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Industrial control systems</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Center shall maintain capabilities to identify and address threats and vulnerabilities to products and technologies intended for use in the automated control of critical infrastructure processes. In carrying out this subsection, the Center shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE1DCF5E14D0F474095E75529FFD1760D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>lead, in coordination with relevant sector specific agencies, Federal Government efforts to identify and mitigate cybersecurity threats to industrial control systems, including supervisory control and data acquisition systems;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBA6557EF9E2A4070A17B75D02E2D5DA5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>maintain cross-sector incident response capabilities to respond to industrial control system cybersecurity incidents;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H23C9F622842F4D2497C1DCBEE7518DEE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide cybersecurity technical assistance to industry end-users, product manufacturers, and other industrial control system stakeholders to identify and mitigate vulnerabilities; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7A8A5AA714BC42CB95CA33EF938A4E80"><enum>(4)</enum><text>conduct such other efforts and assistance as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0239BD66483D4D86AEC26CD81FAF8C6A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 6 months thereafter during the subsequent four-year period, the National Cybersecurity and Communications Integration Center shall provide to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a briefing on the industrial control systems capabilities of the Center under subsection (f) of section 227 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/148">6 U.S.C. 148</external-xref>), as added by subsection (a).</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


