<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H452B359DE4FA4995B51355F7167CF37E" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5353 IH: Eliminating Opioid Related Infectious Diseases Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5353</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180320">March 20, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000567">Mr. Lance</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000379">Mr. Kennedy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001092">Mr. Collins of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000213">Mr. Barton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to reauthorize and expand a program of surveillance and
			 education, carried out by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention,
			 regarding infections associated with injection drug use.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H652685D9C7084E4982BF24E4A1929BFC" style="OLC">
 <section id="H1FD301FCC3084A9EAC7BC87BB4DCFEE6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Eliminating Opioid Related Infectious Diseases Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H79EC94EE3FD44383B11C9B966B358F26"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reauthorization and expansion of program of surveillance and education regarding infections associated with injection drug use</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 317N of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247b-15">42 U.S.C. 247b–15</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6A8C1816057049C799BBED77A3608C46" style="OLC">
				<section id="HE8BBECC1684248D4A7AA8510E9182F56"><enum>317N.</enum><header>Surveillance and education regarding infections associated with injection drug use</header>
 <subsection id="HDBE31F8399B34EE4BC6956485049ED88"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, may (directly and through grants to public and nonprofit private entities) provide for programs to carry out the following activities:</text>
 <paragraph id="H0BB12E3C02F4428E8992845FB01040CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To cooperate with the States in implementing a surveillance system to determine the incidence of infections associated with injection drug use and to assist the States in determining the prevalence of such infections, including the reporting of chronic hepatitis C virus and human immunodeficiency virus cases.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H84BA24698B4246B5A56E90C73F28A53B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To identify, counsel, and offer testing to individuals who are at risk of infections as a result of injection drug use, receiving blood transfusions prior to July 1992, or other risk factors.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7D9B56C21DB74761ACD361A3908E17EC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>To provide appropriate referrals for counseling, testing, and medical treatment of individuals identified under paragraph (2) and to ensure, to the extent practicable, the provision of appropriate follow-up services.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7469821EA88640A6BE382AC9D02C3A9C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>To develop and disseminate public information and education programs for the detection and control of infections associated with injection drug use, with priority given to high-risk populations as determined by the Secretary.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H908FE7C6821A4044B7931CDC8188DD84"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To improve the education, training, and skills of health professionals in the detection and control of infections associated with injection drug use, with priority given to substance use disorder treatment providers, pediatricians, other primary care providers, and obstetrician-gynecologists.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF51E6DBA7E4C43C194F15AB614032D24"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Laboratory procedures</header><text>The Secretary may (directly and through grants to public and nonprofit private entities) carry out programs to provide for improvements in the quality of clinical-laboratory procedures regarding infections associated with injection drug use.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H282F332A9E9345959FEDE7B86BC29C6C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>injection drug use</quote> means—</text> <paragraph id="HFA20DA9DDC7941578ABDA9E192563893"><enum>(1)</enum><text>intravenous administration of a substance in schedule I under section 202 of the Controlled Substances Act;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H766547A591524822A8914A7BF904C4A9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>intravenous administration of a substance in schedule II, III, IV, or V under section 202 of the Controlled Substances Act that has not been approved for intravenous use under—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD8FF964860894F27A87EF0DEF9255677"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 505 of the Federal Food, Drug and Cosmetic Act; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16E6505D2B094AA180D6016466AF9732"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 351 of the Public Health Service Act; or</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H81F7B8272FEE4A9AAFA3298799E40138"><enum>(3)</enum><text>intravenous administration of a substance in schedule II, III, IV, or V under section 202 of the Controlled Substances Act that has not been prescribed to the person using the substance.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H000C380863694CF89AA9ECBC0143753F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>For the purpose of carrying out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated $40,000,000 for each of the fiscal years 2019 through 2023.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


