<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H150568853F294F1FA72554738562CF21" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4843 IH: To modify the presumption of service connection for veterans who were exposed to herbicide agents while serving in the Armed Forces in Thailand during the Vietnam era, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4843</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180118">January 18, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000821">Mr. Westerman</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000608">Ms. Rosen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001202">Mrs. Murphy of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000470">Mr. Tipton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000611">Mr. Poliquin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To modify the presumption of service connection for veterans who were exposed to herbicide agents while serving in the Armed Forces in Thailand during the Vietnam era, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H865493BDDEBB4F71898BE4A2116BAC57" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBC351685B5FF46A0AA35CFF33157CD6C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Modification of presumption of service connection for veterans who were exposed to herbicide agents while serving in the Armed Forces in Thailand during the Vietnam era</header> 
<subsection id="H3ED8A8FDE3EA405F8925A561C764B257"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall ensure that if the Secretary creates a presumption of service connection between the occurrence of a disease and exposure to a herbicide agent while serving in the Armed Forces during the Vietnam era at a military base in Thailand, such presumption also applies to exposure to a herbicide agent while serving in the Armed Forces during the Vietnam era at any military base located in Thailand without regard to where on the base the veteran was located or what military job specialty the veteran performed.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H44429684BB8E4B569EF697D71E7E6A0E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H6205258551814445B559BC324A0EF011"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Herbicide agent</header><text>The term <term>herbicide agent</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1116(a) of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5F204E17FAFF41129717E13916B19BAC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Veteran and vietnam era</header><text>The terms <term>veteran</term> and <term>Vietnam era</term> have the meaning given such terms in section 101 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HEC1C505E34C4449C8B97B0D31AA9E18A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Benefits for children of certain Thailand service veterans born with spina bifida</header> 
<subsection id="H2FA7BFFB2EB240A1A02FC8994E2AE1A6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter III of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/18">chapter 18</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HABC7CEA498254BFB8F6246BF58C8AF28" style="USC"> <section id="H00D5A46F2AAF4992AF48297F01ED2B6A"><enum>1822.</enum><header>Benefits for children of certain Thailand service veterans born with spina bifida</header> <subsection id="H6ABF97139FF84905B06D6A79A811DA4C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Benefits authorized</header><text>The Secretary may provide to any child of a veteran of covered service in Thailand who is suffering from spina bifida the health care, vocational training and rehabilitation, and monetary allowance required to be paid to a child of a Vietnam veteran who is suffering from spina bifida under subchapter I of this chapter as if such child of a veteran of covered service in Thailand were a child of a Vietnam veteran who is suffering from spina bifida under such subchapter.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0334C0132DCA42C7A95B915B84A6CFF3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Spina bifida conditions covered</header><text>This section applies with respect to all forms and manifestations of spina bifida, except spina bifida occulta.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H77AE74DB74AF43A09A59AC62C131BB59"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Veteran of covered service in Thailand</header><text>For purposes of this section, a veteran of covered service in Thailand is any individual, without regard to the characterization of that individual's service, who—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC8CA092418944C538856D380DC67B5B6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>served in the active military, naval, or air service in Thailand, as determined by the Secretary in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, during the period beginning on January 9, 1962, and ending on May 7, 1975; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8CBD0A2DB3E7484E8E1CEB5A0CD9115C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is determined by the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, to have been exposed to a herbicide agent during such service in Thailand.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEEDA1AB9EE624728A889C329182FB232"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Herbicide agent</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>herbicide agent</term> means a chemical in a herbicide used in support of United States and allied military operations in Thailand, as determined by the Secretary in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, during the period beginning on January 9, 1962, and ending on May 7, 1975.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HAA334EECFD1A4401BE20EFBFC64C8C23"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header> <paragraph id="H77EA37EE53F94E508409B884A74B5A31"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Subchapter heading</header><text>The heading for subchapter III of chapter 18 of such title is amended by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subchapter" style="USC">and Thailand</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="subchapter" style="USC">Korea</header-in-text></quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H72FE895946474CA7931BDD35B8209019"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Table of sections</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 18 of such title is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H1E142729849645B395E80F2063F6785B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking the item relating to subchapter III and inserting the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4DB688FFCA6E41928CF78C17CD2ED50D" style="OLC"> 
<toc> 
<toc-entry bold="off" level="subchapter">Subchapter III—Children of certain Korea and Thailand service veterans born with spina bifida</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph" indent="paragraph">and</continuation-text> 
<subparagraph id="H9B9246CDEED3426B88CF6E44A3A89B72"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 1821 the following new item:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1423870CE1A34124B1890AC4D33E5371" style="OLC"> <toc> <toc-entry bold="off" level="section">1822. Benefits for children of certain Thailand service veterans born with spina bifida.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill> 

