<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2A0AE4192A58403587C3DFFD7541DBB9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5539 IH: Thomas Jefferson Public Service Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5539</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180417">April 17, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000607">Mr. Francis Rooney of Florida</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001187">Mr. Meadows</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001294">Mr. Blum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001290">Mr. Brat</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To set the annual rate of compensation for a Member of Congress who has served six consecutive terms as a Member of the House of Representatives or two consecutive terms as a Senator at $1, to amend title 5, United States Code, to exclude any service of a Member of Congress occurring during any pay period for which the Member’s annual rate of compensation is $1 as creditable service for purposes of an annuity under that title, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HB4CCA7666BFD4DD9BDA182A605823647" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE4A8F57572734FE28A54604B57AA6B4F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Thomas Jefferson Public Service Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HCA99D33CF803451991CF03061629ADF6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of annual rate of pay of $1 for Members of Congress serving six consecutive terms in House or two consecutive terms in Senate</header> <subsection id="H928097B5D9E04D838DFFC00F55264920"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of annual rate of pay at $1</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 601(a) of the Legislative Reorganization Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/4501">2 U.S.C. 4501</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD7B88989634A42EEA6AF1AA5751BEE1B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The annual rate of pay</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as provided in paragraph (3), the annual rate of pay</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0456C93241744D2AA6BD4D8B6B1409EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="traditional" id="H575C587EC65A47AD83FEBC2DBF61579B" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H7ACFB3B8662F4213B1AA96474883C49C" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The annual rate of pay for an individual described in paragraph (1) shall be $1 for any pay period occurring—</text> <subparagraph id="HAA13025F41354BD7978F806E9C8CE91C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of an individual who is a Member of the House of Representatives, including a Delegate or Resident Commissioner to the Congress, after the individual has served 6 consecutive full terms as a Member of the House of Representatives; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEE5335ED12F0401D9E8C5B3728EFAC33"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of an individual who is a Senator, after the individual has served 2 consecutive full terms as a Senator.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB0EB9191101D4B7AA58C337E179653CE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by subsection (a) shall apply with respect to terms of service occurring during the One Hundred Sixteenth Congress or any succeeding Congress.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HB6E75F429B0E461F82D296944B8F01B1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Exclusion of Member service for purposes of retirement</header> 
<subsection id="H451928CFFF194CECA3F80872977359DE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, after an individual who is a Member of Congress has served for 6 consecutive full terms in the House of Representatives or 2 consecutive full terms in the Senate, any service of that individual as a Member of Congress after the end of that sixth or second term (as the case may be) shall not be creditable service for purposes of an annuity under chapter 83 or 84 of title 5, United States Code.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H97F12028744E475FBDBACE9F98F3BDE9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contributions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to any service as a Member of Congress excluded by operation of subsection (a), no individual or Government contributions shall be made on behalf of that Member under sections 8334, 8422, or 8423 of title 5, United States Code.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H120F77C5567947D79D49E736F664D3E2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section shall apply with respect to terms of service as a Member of Congress occurring during the One Hundred Sixteenth Congress or any succeeding Congress.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="H8AD00E2EC3EC41D6BE3CA430254A3652"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definition of Member of Congress</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Member of Congress</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Member</term> in section 8331(2) and 8401(20) (as the case may be) of title 5, United States Code.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


