<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HC4864F4AEA384248B0386CD86172E61C" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5778 IH: Promoting Outpatient Access to Non-Opioid Treatments Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5778</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180511">May 11, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001158">Mr. Marchant</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000263">Mr. Levin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to provide for review and adjustment of payments
			 under the Medicare outpatient prospective payment system to avoid
			 financial incentives to use opioids instead of non-opioid alternative
			 treatments, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HD6E2C33FC250440F9C6342CFBA84E706" style="OLC">
 <section id="H0B5C830EC8A3455AB85AA53D0F35B094" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Promoting Outpatient Access to Non-Opioid Treatments Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HBC01B02595A1449F941C4F88830F0CCC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Review and adjustment of payments under the Medicare outpatient prospective payment system to avoid financial incentives to use opioids instead of non-opioid alternative treatments</header> <subsection id="H32BDE90DA71C46788C2F5518283F9127"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Outpatient prospective payment system</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1833(t) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(t)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEE9B9CE167BC48B189C615A4B75064C3" style="OLC">
					<paragraph id="H71C056269EB74C83897C46A6CB11A6CB"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Review and revisions of payments for non-opioid alternative treatments</header>
 <subparagraph id="HDCB21B4BC9E045D28273EC4A78EBDAA6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to payments made under this subsection for covered OPD services (or groups of services), including covered OPD services assigned to a comprehensive ambulatory payment classification, the Secretary—</text>
 <clause id="H0CB3667278544BC99AD1754AF42BF1A3"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall, as soon as practicable, conduct a review (part of which may include a request for information) of payments for opioids and evidence-based non-opioid alternatives for pain management (including drugs and devices, nerve blocks, surgical injections, and neuromodulation) with a goal of ensuring that there are not financial incentives to use opioids instead of non-opioid alternatives;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H84A60474228545038355591CFCAC2669"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may, as the Secretary determines appropriate, conduct subsequent reviews of such payments; and</text> </clause><clause id="H4DE62354D1334168B043833B320A3CB2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall consider the extent to which revisions under this subsection to such payments (such as the creation of additional groups of covered OPD services to classify separately those procedures that utilize opioids and non-opioid alternatives for pain management) would reduce payment incentives to use opioids instead of non-opioid alternatives for pain management.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9CB79C812F204666AC45FA6539DCA107"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In conducting the review under clause (i) of subparagraph (A) and considering revisions under clause (iii) of such subparagraph, the Secretary shall focus on covered OPD services (or groups of services) assigned to a comprehensive ambulatory payment classification, ambulatory payment classifications that primarily include surgical services, and other services determined by the Secretary which generally involve treatment for pain management.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H982D4391BC4D4A41ACE4A457FA4A8DFB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Revisions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary identifies revisions to payments pursuant to subparagraph (A)(iii), the Secretary shall, as determined appropriate, begin making such revisions for services furnished on or after January 1, 2020. Revisions under the previous sentence shall be treated as adjustments for purposes of application of paragraph (9)(B).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBF56E11065540EEA6DFB45785C74176"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed to preclude the Secretary—</text> <clause id="H66645E1566B7400F956319AFD02F3493"><enum>(i)</enum><text>from conducting a demonstration before making the revisions described in subparagraph (C); or</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB0A1F546F5C64D40BCDF7E8F2D2BDA50"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>prior to implementation of this paragraph, from changing payments under this subsection for covered OPD services (or groups of services) which include opioids or non-opioid alternatives for pain management.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H83A60B7B42C14C4387D3B3ECECEB69AD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ambulatory surgical centers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1833(i) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(i)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H32053DA7C496403199D5B322667AE52F" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H7C601CB7375447559AFB67A61371E795"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall apply the provisions of paragraph (22) of section 1833(t), including the second sentence of subparagraph (C) of such paragraph, to payment for services under this subsection in an appropriate manner (as determined by the Secretary).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


