<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB13C5BECF13947ED879754D24C13E5A8" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4895 IH: Medgar Evers National Monument Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4895</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180129">January 29, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001250">Mr. Bishop of Utah</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Medgar Evers National Monument in the State of Mississippi, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HC26F7AD3097F420A84426ABDBB528B8B" style="OLC">
 <section id="HBCFEAE3CC6F441B7971EF95A66280FA1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Medgar Evers National Monument Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HFEEE4C19F28B4E8D8BCBA159572F9B6C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
 <paragraph id="HF8E3C3BD52684AA89C82B97277EF231F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Home</header><text>The term <term>Home</term> means the Medgar Evers Home in Jackson, Mississippi, as generally depicted on the Map.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H8071A55132814F509137A41BAB25ADB4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Monument</header><text>The term <term>Monument</term> means the Medgar Evers National Monument established by section 3.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE2ADBB12A6F14F0B99CE05ACFE92C23F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Historic district</header><text>The term <term>Historic District</term> means the Medgar Evers Historic District, as included on the National Register of Historic Places, and as generally depicted on the Map and located within the boundaries of the Monument.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBCFB7FD3EB0143DF992857BC386373B4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Map</header><text>The term <term>Map</term> means the map entitled <quote>Medgar Evers National Monument</quote>, numbered __/__, and dated January 2018.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H5F7B7FA190584037A801F7823A26FFBF"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior, acting through the Director of the National Park Service.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6E51E8F4CB30437982AF2F2E02C4A45B"><enum>(6)</enum><header>College</header><text>The term <term>College</term> means Tougaloo College, a private educational institution located in Tougaloo, Mississippi.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="HE93A7CE0CA5E4B27BC295373B02889D9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment of Medgar Evers National Monument</header> <subsection id="HE63859998F5F495394838FE04DB443B4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header> <paragraph id="H90B9BCEABFA34FD6838BEC5F76A97C0F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to paragraph (2), there is established the Medgar Evers National Monument in the State of Mississippi as a unit of the National Park System to preserve, protect, and interpret for the benefit of present and future generations the Home and the history of Medgar Evers’ pivotal role in the American Civil Rights Movement.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H871F8C385CEE474F983DDD448FBA103B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conditions</header><text>The Monument shall not be established until the date on which the Secretary—</text> <subparagraph id="HF3C1AB6EA2464AA4AAF501679EE71943"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has entered into a written agreement with the College providing that the Home shall be donated to the United States for inclusion in the Monument to be managed consistently with the purposes of the Monument; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF227548C27F1425F8A48EB44C2D37A94"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has otherwise acquired sufficient land or interests in land within the boundaries of the Monument to constitute a manageable unit.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBCA0A107DDCA41B8B2E6443E764DDF19"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Boundaries</header><text>The boundaries of Monument shall be the boundaries generally depicted on the Map.</text> </subsection><subsection id="HC886FA45525D45E3ADA23E4270D306D3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Availability of map</header><text>The Map shall be on file and available for public inspection in the appropriate offices of the National Park Service.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA3A0E40F1DAB4ABA9C8513F193126546"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Acquisition of authority</header><text>The Secretary may only acquire any land or interest in land located within the boundary of the Monument by—</text>
 <paragraph id="H75AE770615DB4334B7374DC12C7A8DAF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>donation;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H0DE0FAE1E078457EA58CAB173894CFEB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>purchase with donated funds; or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA837B503FECD49A8B4A657483BAA99F1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>exchange.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA76734DBE5D04730A16264077860787A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Administration</header> <paragraph id="H6FB07DA69955412AA8850430019B9538"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall administer the Monument in accordance with—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF5C020BFD6FA4F27995C993314A9016A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>this Act; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H623D021B0A2B4CCDA95ACCC0673C57AB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the laws generally applicable to units of the National Park System.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7764FE9386A49919EBB37CB5635FE10"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Management plan</header>
 <subparagraph id="H129FEC4597CA4318BF85ECE8496AD93B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Not later than 3 years after the date on which funds are first made available to the Secretary for this purpose, the Secretary shall prepare a general management plan for the Monument in accordance with section 100502 of title 54, United States Code.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42F0356D8B13459B8D66A070FA01B7AB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>On completion of the general management plan under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall submit it to the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H17429F79815C4E1F9E0E0C248F3C87B3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Cooperative agreements</header>
 <paragraph id="H10B3E5AF220043FB8286F414C4B5D2DD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Interpretation</header><text>The Secretary shall enter into a cooperative agreement with the College for interpretive and educational programming related to the Monument.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H589E4CFD5F1B4EC7BBBF6D8C720A1537"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Historic district</header><text>The Secretary may enter into cooperative agreements with the owner of a nationally significant property within the Historic District, to identify, mark, interpret, improve, restore, and provide technical assistance with respect to the preservation and interpretation of the property.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5B6114045C6043B6B98B56C50DCD3B3B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Written consent of owner</header><text>No private property or non-Federal public property shall be included within the boundaries of the Monument or managed as part of the Monument without the written consent of the owner of such property.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H683F350B59C648FF8A9489DB0AC6E7B7"><enum>(h)</enum><header>No buffer zones</header><text>Nothing in this Act, the establishment of the Monument, or the management of the Monument shall be construed to create buffer zones outside of the Monument. The fact that an activity or use can be seen, heard, or detected from within the Monument shall not preclude the conduct of that activity or use outside of the Monument.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


