<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H0503878ECDEF41F5B334BEDC369EAC32" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5020 IH: Collaboration for Today’s Education Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5020</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180214">February 14, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000565">Mr. Loebsack</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the establishment of a Department of Education program to award grants to secondary
			 schools that establish a project to encourage students in their junior and
			 senior school years to experience career and technical education courses
			 at a community college, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H678AA09204394C278B94D26178A0124B" style="OLC">
 <section id="HB1AC8C4E8D0D4C48AF940088A5CA1D3F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Collaboration for Today’s Education Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CTE Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H0D54A3297EE24EF9AC5F0AC02035EA7C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of grant program</header> <subsection id="HCA738C57069749FD97FCA0A3ADB48A05"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts appropriated to carry out this section, the Secretary shall establish a program to award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible secondary schools.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H7E66C657C0FF4DC38D9091E93001D659"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible schools</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to be eligible, a secondary school must form a partnership with a community college to allow students in their junior and senior school years to experience career and technical education courses at such community college.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H897B7B33FFA2488C842E8B882287944D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for a grant under this section, a secondary school shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such form, and containing such information as the Secretary determines appropriate, which shall include—</text>
 <paragraph id="H184FBB73BDAE47ADAF83CA503940A0A4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the proposed project to be carried out;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE21AE0D8A8B34E789977E8F3631EE993"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of the number of students who will be able to participate; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC5C84F37BFFA41E28F5BAC513B9E8731"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis of how the project will enable students in their junior and senior school years to experience career and technical education courses at a community college.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7F86D30A2A294A08B645D8B22C00A91F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grant uses</header>
 <paragraph id="H6F1F7DE3559A44A19DE0DE95C5FD283F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A secondary school receiving a grant under this section shall use such grant only for a project to encourage students in their junior and senior school years to experience career and technical education courses at a community college.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD2853A4876A24C9BB8F1C19F68738C65"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Payment to third parties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A secondary school receiving a grant under this section may use such grant to reimburse third parties, including a community college, for costs incurred as part of a project to encourage students in their junior and senior school years to experience career and technical education courses at a community college.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H46C8FC0AFF3741AC96A371FFE385033F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting requirement</header>
 <paragraph id="H4FAE43B12CF64AD48E3DF9F82EE3C158"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Recipients of grant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year following the date of receipt of a grant awarded under this section, a secondary school receiving such a grant shall submit to the Secretary a report analyzing the effect such grant had on encouraging students in their junior and senior school years to experience career and technical education courses at a community college.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H998DE2662CBB451FA9FC95BD2CD8B860"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>Not later than 2 years following the date of receipt of a report required pursuant to paragraph (1), and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report compiling the results of the reports submitted during the previous year pursuant to paragraph (1).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE6CFB4F1951643C0AD4D70E990D326D5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H62818FFEFB8A4BF08602F6B7D576465E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>career and technical education</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2302">20 U.S.C. 2302</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE46887363B8D4A2F89975B8A5370CD1C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>community college</quote> has the meaning given the term <quote>junior or community college</quote> in section 312 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1058">20 U.S.C. 1058</external-xref>), but does not include a for-profit institution.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFDCC583203EF4C87BA6DD054B5DA4F8E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>secondary school</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7C6B3568E7414123BC5EA92283C1D4CD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Education.</text> </paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

