<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H3D57B78285D34AC8867DEA2E3686F17B" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4811 IH: Securing Our Schools Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4811</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180117">January 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for grants from the Attorney General to local education agencies to purchase and install
			 devices that would allow for the immediate notification of appropriate
			 officials in case of emergency, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HE11E014B8FBC458BA84CAE4B5716BE71" style="OLC">
 <section id="H42338F44184C444C80E1CD7F76D52D76" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing Our Schools Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H517360D2887F414D94F8AE22C4933D14"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pilot program</header> <subsection id="H263DB2B947D84681A56F6BA42A5CCCDA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each of fiscal years 2019 through 2022, the Attorney General may make a grant to a local education agency to acquire and install a device that allows for immediate notification of emergency response personnel, law enforcement, or other appropriate officials (as determined by the local education agency) in the case of an emergency, including a health emergency, reports of an assailant armed with a weapon, an act of terrorism, a natural disaster, or other similar emergency, as determined by the local education agency.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5A73E54AE18D489F8698F42F134B4100"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An application for a grant under this section shall be submitted at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Attorney General may require.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H3F096BA068BF4FC0A8C81C3F4CAA931D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Matching requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The portion of the costs of a device acquired and installed pursuant to this section that is provided by a grant under subsection (a) may not exceed 75 percent.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE6F2DF8A1F804FBDB526D333F86539C1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Maximum amount of grant</header><text>A grant under this section may not be in an amount greater than $200,000 for fiscal year.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H9D144B879E6941319B13EDC4CD70F96E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Term of grant</header><text>A grant under this section shall be for a term of one fiscal year.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


