<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H83F3482B50474A9B93BCCF4AF2257F60" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4876 IH: Connecting Broadband Deserts Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4876</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180122">January 22, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000515">Mr. Rush</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Communications Act of 1934 to direct the Federal Communications Commission to conduct an annual inquiry on the availability of advanced telecommunications capability in broadband deserts, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD26754F02F074D0EA3492B4DC31BD55E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB66EE0A174D74005A812D5F29A392F5D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Connecting Broadband Deserts Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HEDC74509A24C46149B77036572CE6F12"><enum>2.</enum><header>Annual inquiry on deployment of advanced telecommunications capability in broadband deserts</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title I of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/151">47 U.S.C. 151</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H92C31815F12246D2BD627D093E4D0DEF" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H6AF63B2C0DC04F08B26A0D592CE6D8FB"><enum>13.</enum><header>Annual inquiry on deployment of advanced telecommunications capability in broadband deserts</header> 
<subsection id="H782D7602AA7E42C3A4B4F6BAAC9E2C90"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall, not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, initiate a notice of inquiry concerning the availability of advanced telecommunications capability in broadband deserts and shall complete the inquiry not later than 180 days after its initiation. In the inquiry, the Commission shall determine whether advanced telecommunications capability is being deployed in broadband deserts in a reasonable and timely fashion, including the extent to which digital redlining is occurring. If the Commission determines that advanced telecommunications capability is not being deployed in broadband deserts in a reasonable and timely fashion, it shall take immediate action to accelerate deployment of such capability in broadband deserts by removing barriers to infrastructure investment and by promoting competition in the telecommunications market.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1E95FF7298AD4D9ABEEF9B11AF67512D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="HEBCBC9709BEC46F48EC56215A5DF7572"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advanced telecommunications capability</header><text>The term <quote>advanced telecommunications capability</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 706 of the Telecommunications Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1302">47 U.S.C. 1302</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7451D8F3889A4BF9A10B81E3E73A64E0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Broadband desert</header><text>The term <quote>broadband desert</quote> means a census block—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA2018DEFF2E5461B982DB7A0EDA13C86"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that is located in an urban area; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1C6F74E3BCA7436380DFB2AFB9F46528"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in which fewer than 33 percent of end-user premises (as defined by the Commission for purposes of Form 477) do not have access to advanced telecommunications capability.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB7F911A92CE24B9488012A6261308C01"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Digital redlining</header><text>The term <quote>digital redlining</quote> means a practice whereby a provider of advanced telecommunications capability excludes certain areas when expanding or upgrading service due to income or other reasons.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H37B81513A7774DA4BB8E40A0CF611A34" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Urban area</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>urban area</quote> means an urbanized area or urban cluster area with a population equal to or greater than 25,000, as determined by the most recent rural-urban classification by the Bureau of the Census.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> 
</legis-body></bill>

