<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H02880CE94DC04506A422104130D693D4" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4912 IH: Rosie the Riveter Congressional Gold Medal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4912</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180202">February 2, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001175">Ms. Speier</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To award a Congressional Gold Medal, collectively, to the American women who joined the workforce
			 during World War II, providing the vehicles, weaponry, and ammunition to
			 win the war, that were referred to as <quote>Rosie the Riveter</quote>, in recognition of their contributions to the Nation and the inspiration they have provided to
			 ensuing generations.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HE0AA2C46FF0D410FAABCC05ADF940A22" style="OLC">
 <section id="H9E33641FB37D4B5FA853B21A26E6C2DE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rosie the Riveter Congressional Gold Medal Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section commented="no" id="H4C500BE297D2465184BF69799E4B9CA6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
 <subsection commented="no" id="HDAE0A4567F6C4862AEA29AB9478F5A7F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Rosie the Riveter</header><text>The term <quote>Rosie the Riveter</quote> includes any female individual who held employment or volunteered in support of the war efforts during World War II.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HCBED59B9A9B240BEAD2F4C3FF7407333"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of the Treasury.</text> </subsection></section><section id="HB5C88FED582B4A44ADEBD4472D1D6910"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional Gold Medal</header> <subsection id="HB50750A5F48B4AD59186F9750B68DDB8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Award authorized</header><text>The President pro tempore of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Representatives shall make appropriate arrangements for the award, on behalf of Congress, of a single gold medal of appropriate design to the Rosie the Riveters, collectively, in recognition of their contributions to the Nation and the inspiration they have provided to ensuing generations.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H7C70593096C64474A73018D2595A8ADC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Design and striking</header><text>For the purposes of the award referred to in subsection (a), the Secretary shall strike the gold medal with suitable emblems, devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HC41D24D321724B9FAA36DC5E04A773AD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>National Museum of American History</header>
 <paragraph id="HEC2D84A485AB465799046C68CB15B431"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Following the award of the gold medal in honor of the Rosie the Riveters, the gold medal shall be given to the National Museum of American History of the Smithsonian Institution, where it will be available for display as appropriate and made available for research.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H94CFFA34CD5E4ED8A701B707703AD7A0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the National Museum of American History should make the gold medal received under paragraph (1) available for display elsewhere, particularly at other appropriate locations associated with the Rosie the Riveters.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9AF3959308294F049D4690C13D86A7E8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duplicate medals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under such regulations as the Secretary may prescribe, the Secretary may strike and sell duplicates in bronze of the gold medal struck under this Act, at a price sufficient to cover the costs of the medals, including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, and overhead expenses, and amounts received from the sale of such duplicates shall be deposited in the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HBA437F7CEF5444819BEED8D7B54A7F75"><enum>4.</enum><header>Status of medals</header>
 <subsection id="HB3D5D007FECF480D97D063F07E4985B6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National medal</header><text>The gold medal struck under this Act is a national medal for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HEF87429E81494A4AA2D646450D11F4BC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Numismatic items</header><text>For purposes of section 5134 of title 31, United States Code, all medals struck under this Act shall be considered to be numismatic items.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


