<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2DB225356D8B4AFC9BB2B61FCBD905E4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5601 IH: Survey Our Military Impacted Schools Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5601</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180424">April 24, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001193">Mr. MacArthur</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000571">Ms. Gabbard</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to conduct a study on the renovation, repair, or expansion needs of certain elementary schools and secondary schools that educate dependants of active duty military personnel.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HDC84041FBC81400CAA1A0D915FABC13E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5DC90F95751948479E1E43B98FDAAB39" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Survey Our Military Impacted Schools Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H41EF1D91BDF3437E8E140F5ED7149A93"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study and report on construction grant program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the heads of any other relevant agencies, shall conduct a study and submit a report on such study to Congress on the unmet capital improvement needs (including renovation, repair, or expansion needs) of each elementary school and secondary school—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5A68379CD3F144B7B1355B87F2AA5DDA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in which the total student enrollment for the most recent school year was not less than 150 students; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA751A1FFE3A34338844F8B5A5EA5F9BF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that is not located within the boundaries of a Federal military installation; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H55ABDEAD1335475AA53E5AD2ADFFF0B7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>that is served by a local educational agency—</text> <subparagraph id="HE89736E5F6314BC8A606B44A54331688"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in which at least 15 percent, but not more than 40 percent, of the total student enrollment for the most recent school year in schools of the agency were children described in subparagraphs (B) and (D)(i) of section 7003(a)(1) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7703">20 U.S.C. 7703(a)(1)</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDFB5F52A41094B20BDB1040721C18B2D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that is eligible for assistance under title VII of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7701">20 U.S.C. 7701</external-xref> et seq.).</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> </section> </legis-body> </bill> 

