<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H15722CEFFB094278B3359D834B3B3535" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5289 IH: Restoring Integrity in our Elected Officials Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5289</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180314">March 14, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000592">Mr. Rokita</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to prohibit any individual serving as President or Vice
			 President or as a Member of Congress, or any individual who served as an
			 employee of the office of the President or Vice President or the office of
			 a Member of Congress, from engaging in any lobbying activity after serving
			 in such a position, to amend title 41, United States Code, to prohibit
			 executive agencies from awarding contracts to former elected officials,
			 and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HB88C70AF4D9545FBBF1BBA53F6447DF6" style="OLC">
 <section id="H968FCFAA5F72406ABF596661B5F3473D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Restoring Integrity in our Elected Officials Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HED893695B2ED47CCA1588FE77133C682"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibiting lobbying by former elected officials and their employees</header> <subsection id="HE03FE3E81F6142FB940E6191C68C6C27"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 207(e) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by striking paragraphs (1) through (7) and inserting the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6FECE809E4574F49AFF400774970F074" style="USC">
					<subsection id="H68C9A50FA95448078D8A253EA0BA377C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Restrictions on elected officials and their employees</header>
						<paragraph id="H87799F55837A42F09AA521A22038DD70"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Lifetime prohibition on lobbying any office of Federal Government</header>
 <subparagraph id="HB3F647F3DB99436AA5C3061379476176"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any individual who holds a position described in subparagraph (C), and any immediate family member of such an individual, who, at any time after such individual leaves such a position, knowingly makes, with the intent to influence, any communication to or appearance before any officer or employee of any department, agency, or office of the executive branch or the legislative branch on behalf of any person (except the United States) in connection with any matter on which such person seeks official action by any officer or employee of such department, agency, or office, shall be punished as provided in section 216 of this title.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB4B0D11300EC401CBA9DBF2C95EDEA39"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Treatment of employment with lobbying firms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any individual who holds a position described in subparagraph (C), and any immediate family member of such an individual, who, at any time after such individual leaves such a position, accepts a position as an officer, director, partner, or employee of a lobbying firm under the Lobbying Disclosure Act of 1995 (without regard to whether or not the individual engages directly in lobbying activity under such Act), shall be punished as provided in section 216 of this title.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC4A4E4E01FA4F818A34D263C1FAB6F8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Positions described</header><text>The positions described in this subparagraph are the following:</text> <clause id="H85C1B979842F46699E5A4D12DC15D692"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The President.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HDC2A20BEA93540E9BED39AA935C6946D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Vice President.</text> </clause><clause id="HD8322E9C7F7441CCB4F85CF6FEEFF2E8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A Member of Congress.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8A4C9AEA135E4387AC574395085926FD"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>An employee of the office of the President, the office of the Vice President, or the office of a Member of Congress.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H89ECD12D7201475F9BE8A337B4CD7017"><enum>(v)</enum><text>An employee of a committee of Congress.</text> </clause><clause id="HDF3F6E3EA4EE4E379160EE1563B1F550"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>An employee on the leadership staff of the House of Representatives.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD6F17D40718F4EC1B21F67E4CE97ED79"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>An employee on the leadership staff of the Senate.</text> </clause><clause id="H66703195C0EE45FB895B8764289BE471"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>An elected officer of the House of Representatives.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H4B424BBEBCA84066AEDE29ED92388E64"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>An elected officer of the Senate.</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H230589DABDC141AAA56EECFB8323C01A"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Immediate family member defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this paragraph, an <quote>immediate family member</quote> means, with respect to an individual, a father, mother, son, daughter, brother, sister, husband, wife, father-in-law, or mother-in-law.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA41040739B9940B186CCB4F19E1F1F2E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other legislative offices</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HDE6878F1434D46509E978190FBCCE8E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who is an employee of any other legislative office of the Congress to whom paragraph (7)(B) applies and who, within 1 year after the termination of that person's employment in such office, knowingly makes, with the intent to influence, any communication to or appearance before any of the persons described in subparagraph (B), on behalf of any other person (except the United States) in connection with any matter on which such former employee seeks action by any officer or employee of such office, in his or her official capacity, shall be punished as provided in section 216 of this title.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7479EBFE4644CA9813875AA49140A57" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The persons referred to in subparagraph (A) with respect to appearances or communications by a former employee are the employees and officers of the former legislative office of the Congress of the former employee.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA8196B57A09A4168943DB5F675455B9B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 207(e) of such title is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HEAB6F005B66D4F15B883911B276CE673"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (8) and (9) as paragraphs (3) and (4); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H99B22FB219AC42558CEF1C8081D0C0DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G) of paragraph (4), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>paragraph (1), (2), (3), (4), or (5)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraph (1) or (2)</quote>.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEDB30BA706C74D2FAF6292E6ABCECC32"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to treatment of Vice President</header><text>Section 207(d)(1) of such title is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H5F4CF02EE52A441E9DA552B93348D3B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (A); and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H54BCD86693974CB79DF530B7774F439A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (B) and (C) as subparagraphs (A) and (B).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H399C216FE71E4EE794B76B9750B474E6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section and the amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to any individual who leaves a position described in subparagraph (C) of section 207(e)(1) of title 18, United States Code (as amended by subsection (a)), on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HDEA5B40E1FF64EFC99F00C9B1FCC10FA" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on contracts with certain former elected officials</header>
			<subsection id="H6E2051C125DA4EE084D000D72F89F24E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition on contracts with certain former elected officials</header>
 <paragraph id="H58ADE2AA0BFD42EBBD02E29AA12432B1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/41/47">Chapter 47</external-xref> of title 41, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H031D27E7B6694FFE9AD8E51FE65D9775" style="USC">
						<section id="H6ADA4E706B8042E0BF7191424558BF22"><enum>4713.</enum><header>Prohibition on contracts with certain former elected officials</header>
 <subsection id="H828D911D41474D58B1A52C974EE7E95A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a contract the value of which would exceed $1,000,000 in any year of the contract period, an executive agency may not award such a contract to—</text>
 <paragraph id="HA26A5A1B4E794BFB80A379F9C9FFB3B1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any former elected official of the legislative branch of the United States Government;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9752E37E1FA94F639955C268CB97AFE9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an immediate family member of such former elected official;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAE6FA1CDF3A34C0AB6584C047D5E1174"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a former congressional employee of such former elected official; or</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE0FAE47E104A4AEEB14A4D062FDAA464"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any entity owned by an individual described in paragraphs (1) through (3).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H47182129698B405B9E7ACA5BA1A6C1B1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HB8E27E10D9AA41A894BBE6444C89E2B8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Former congressional employee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>former congressional employee</quote> means, with respect to a former elected official of the legislative branch of the United States Government, an individual who was a paid congressional employee of such former elected official for any period of time.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA484574741284754AA1F8667A2035228"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Former elected official of the legislative branch of the United States Government</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>former elected official of the legislative branch of the United States Government</quote> means each former—</text> <subparagraph id="HE6B6ECA48A114022BF2DA3E128B179E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Member of the United States House of Representatives;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5830DE124F3463FB786BC3D976058CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Delegate from the District of Columbia, American Samoa, Guam, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, and the Virgin Islands;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H478FA144371345D08490B2DC543B8DEE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Resident Commissioner of Puerto Rico; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD6A7274ACE345D7A688F6EB53FF299A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>United States Senator.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H499E4FA4DDDD4DBA8332D038C128D368"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Immediate family member</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>immediate family member</quote> means, with respect to a former elected official of the legislative branch of the United States Government—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H0EEDFB3AC9F64462BB4EFC068FD221EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the spouse of such former elected official;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H085B5FE8E6EE43298C70EB2FCBCA28B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a natural or adoptive son, daughter, brother, or sister of such former elected official;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA55B198F149141DB9366936D0471B57B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a stepson, stepdaughter, stepbrother, or stepsister of such former elected official; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D2DAB1862DD41B78C4A4A0825D4B01C"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a son-, daughter-, brother-, or sister-in-law of such former elected official.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2EC2580F1F244AC289D9B8CB12659583"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCEA9B8BA877D47608361D6CF3E6693C1" style="USC">
						<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
							<toc-entry level="section">4713. Prohibition on contracts with certain former elected officials.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H377D0C50B1B440D79EC97B51668C7B63"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a)(1) shall apply with respect to any contract awarded on or after January 1, 2019.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


