<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H08B3727F0ED44A4F815A058A765571D6" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5009 IH: Jessie's Law</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5009</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180213">February 13, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000798">Mr. Walberg</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000297">Mr. Jenkins of West Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001170">Ms. Shea-Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001181">Mr. Meehan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001193">Mr. MacArthur</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001053">Mrs. Hartzler</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000566">Mr. Latta</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To include information concerning a patient’s opioid addiction in certain medical records.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HF4B89D742D5543AD80B0EEF08E4C3E40" style="OLC">
 <section id="H2082A2D4F56646EB88B2C9BD33FEEC4B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as <quote><short-title>Jessie's Law</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H5AB749035699495093B00B7140889CC6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Inclusion of opioid addiction history in patient records</header> <subsection id="H3864C3FAC0D54E55BA2ED4483087A3FC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Best practices</header> <paragraph id="H21C7FCD08173451393155D782BD610F5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, in consultation with appropriate stakeholders, including a patient with a history of opioid use disorder, an expert in electronic health records, an expert in the confidentiality of patient health information and records, and a health care provider, shall identify or facilitate the development of best practices regarding—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H61F4AAA36EB940778A6AFB45E8C81CC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the circumstances under which information that a patient has provided to a health care provider regarding such patient’s history of opioid use disorder should, only at the patient’s request, be prominently displayed in the medical records (including electronic health records) of such patient;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DDF95BB4131451DBE2A16132CE9584F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>what constitutes the patient’s request for the purpose described in subparagraph (A); and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H73FCF67C75C0464381195D50C16EFC89"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the process and methods by which the information should be so displayed.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C0D167F79384A67A11E25588BD9562A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Dissemination</header><text>The Secretary shall disseminate the best practices developed under paragraph (1) to health care providers and State agencies.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H992BC1A583654BAB93A992D6E8543D23"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In identifying or facilitating the development of best practices under subsection (a), as applicable, the Secretary, in consultation with appropriate stakeholders, shall consider the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H276D9C98733A4011BFCDA0792A960B4C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The potential for addiction relapse or overdose, including overdose death, when opioid medications are prescribed to a patient recovering from opioid use disorder.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H891452535AA7468A9B352BFE92381BD3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The benefits of displaying information about a patient’s opioid use disorder history in a manner similar to other potentially lethal medical concerns, including drug allergies and contraindications.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H23C7291496764867B927191BA7D2D3E2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The importance of prominently displaying information about a patient’s opioid use disorder when a physician or medical professional is prescribing medication, including methods for avoiding alert fatigue in providers.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H313499BCE40E45E287FAB83E9047E829"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The importance of a variety of appropriate medical professionals, including physicians, nurses, and pharmacists, to have access to information described in this section when prescribing or dispensing opioid medication, consistent with Federal and State laws and regulations.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H95179DD87F1D4B1291DE16041CB9E84A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The importance of protecting patient privacy, including the requirements related to consent for disclosure of substance use disorder information under all applicable laws and regulations.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H622EDA9746A84331868E94608DE0C466"><enum>(6)</enum><text>All applicable Federal and State laws and regulations.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

