<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HAA85DC24E81F478F96C4BE9EAEF2A5AA" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5555 IH: FHA Foreclosure Prevention Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5555</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180418">April 18, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Maxine Waters of California</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To make necessary reforms to improve compliance with loss mitigation requirements by servicers of
			 mortgages for single family housing insured by the FHA and to prevent
			 foreclosures on FHA borrowers, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HDD7FA1F4A5B44DDCBFCC0A3C17886FEE" style="OLC">
		<section id="HC130D17D84244634A4127BC05264B14D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header>
 <text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>FHA Foreclosure Prevention Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H7F63F7CECECF4A58B9CFC3D4D160D98C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Documentation of loss mitigation efforts</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (a) of section 204 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1710">12 U.S.C. 1710(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFDE5C3F3EF484754972E55440BD83FE5" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="HB3CF2DB905124DFDA14C848B4C2BE8CC"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Documentation of loss mitigation efforts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this title, the Secretary may not pay insurance benefits to any mortgagee of a single family mortgage insured under this Act unless the mortgagee or other servicer for the mortgage has provided documentation to the Secretary that is sufficient to demonstrate compliance with any requirements of the Secretary applicable to such mortgage relating to loss mitigation. This paragraph may not be construed to limit the authority of the Secretary to impose civil monetary penalties.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </section><section id="HBAB3B13031284197A0F1F5D296431407"><enum>3.</enum><header>HUD oversight of servicers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 533 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1735f-11">12 U.S.C. 1735f–11</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8BDC1EB5F0984C4989ACC2E4FDC908BF" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="HF38862558327431DB34D8EED2470045C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Oversight of mortgage servicers</header>
					<paragraph id="H9180B87322DB4A18A832A552DE6D8967"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Oversight</header>
 <subparagraph id="H854842EBDEA141AB93335E4C2BFB3709"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall conduct oversight of servicers of single family mortgages insured under this Act on a regular and ongoing basis and in a manner designed to ensure that such servicers comply with the requirements of this Act and the standards and guidelines established by the Secretary for servicing of such mortgages and to identify systemic problems and trends with such compliance.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A27042AF96A4F899A326F4066FD2D8B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Loss mitigation requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such oversight shall include oversight designed to ensure that such servicers comply with the requirements under this Act, and the standards and guidelines established by the Secretary, for loss mitigation, and shall include appropriate sampling and review of such servicer compliance, including direct information collection through generally accepted means from borrowers whose files were sampled, such as surveys, focus groups, interview, or other similar measures.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H626075E16F6746ECA3E305DC37AA3ABF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Corrective action</header><text>The Secretary shall take such actions as may be necessary to remedy failures by servicers of single family mortgages insured under this Act to comply with the requirements of this Act and the standards and guidelines established by the Secretary for servicing of such mortgages, including ordering non-compliant ser­vi­cers to take corrective actions, including barring foreclosure and cancelling from the borrowers account balance and from any insurance claim any interest and other fees that accrued during periods of noncompliance.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </section><section id="HFC657489E87540ABA1023DAEF7A53965"><enum>4.</enum><header>Complaint procedure regarding loss mitigation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title V of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1731a">12 U.S.C. 1731a</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8A26C0874E284E09B5E101A9FC432346" style="OLC">
				<section id="H6B21E8220AFC4C549F49B4D203CE360A"><enum>543.</enum><header>Complaint procedure regarding loss mitigation</header>
					<subsection id="H3C2636AA09BB42B1BB7DE8E9CCEB99F9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Complaint procedure for borrowers</header>
 <paragraph id="HD2F852F2D64C456C88D9766239F91417"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Features</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish and maintain a procedure for mortgagors under single family mortgages insured under this Act to register complaints with the Secretary regarding servicing, including loss mitigation actions, which shall include making available to the public a website of the Department, an e-mail address, a phone number, and a mailing address for such purpose. Such procedure shall provide an opportunity for servicers to respond to such complaints and submit information regarding complaints.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2A7C01DF02924E2A9023BB26794071ED"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Attempt to resolve</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each complaint registered under the procedure established pursuant to this subsection, the Secretary shall review the complaint and any response by the servicer and shall seek to resolve any dispute between the mortgagor and the servicer and make a determination with regard to complaint.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7E4DAA73B3A749778EA4200F2D63D8F0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Use of information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making any determinations regarding servicers’ compliance with the requirements, standards, and guidelines for servicing, including in identifying systemic problems and trends with servicing, the Secretary shall take into consideration information obtained under the complaint procedure under this subsection.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBD28E7A185934A7AA92372D5E2C79FB0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notification of opportunity To appeal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon making a determination with respect to a complaint, the Secretary shall notify the complainant of such determination, of the opportunity for the complainant to appeal an adverse determination under the procedure established pursuant to subsection (a), and the requirements for and how to initiate such an appeal.</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="HE28CF45C594249079EBD6111706D1DA4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appeals procedure</header>
 <paragraph id="HD29081472C0447B4B566EBE94DDA53FA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide a procedure for mortgagors to appeal an adverse determination by the Secretary regarding a complaint registered under the procedure established pursuant to subsection (a), and, if appropriate, may take action pursuant to section 533(d)(2) pursuant to a decision on such an appeal.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFCDE9087E90D439AB793D4D926FFA214"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The Secretary shall provide that the procedure established pursuant to this subsection may not provide an appeal for any complaint that was previously appealed under such procedure.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H700F71F4820F43D58DC210D8E8FDA5D8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Prohibition on foreclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall prohibit the foreclosure of a mortgage during any period that a complaint or appeal regarding such mortgage is pending under the procedures established pursuant to this section and during a reasonable period after a complainant is notified of a determination regarding a complaint that provides the complainant an opportunity to appeal such decision.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HBB4B70FA12AA437CB9BF8AE39B424B56"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall submit a report to the Congress annually regarding complaints received under the procedure maintained pursuant to subsection (a), which shall specify the number of complaints received, disaggregated by types of complaints, status of complaints, geographic distribution of complaints, and average times for resolution of complaints, shall include relevant information submitted by servicers, and shall include any other information that the Secretary considers relevant. Such report shall comply with any applicable privacy protections.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </section><section id="H1E1B27743994437C8087C1B240943126"><enum>5.</enum><header>Notice to borrowers of loss mitigation status and decisions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (a) of section 204 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1710">12 U.S.C. 1710(a)</external-xref>), as amended by the preceding provisions of this Act, is further amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H941EDA9B5ABA4701B534E41B4DD941EC" style="OLC">
				<paragraph id="HA1C62CA3DD044286B15973061BE6C38E"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Notice to borrowers of loss mitigation status and decisions</header>
 <subparagraph id="HC135F0CDDB304E12A3E14070339599B2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Required notice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall require that before any acceleration of the indebtedness due under a mortgage, the servicer for the mortgage shall provide written notice to the mortgagor that includes—</text>
 <clause id="H3513CEB0B0004062942E9CE6AF0FE388"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a summary explaining how the servicer applied the loss mitigation option priority analysis established by the Secretary, including the loss mitigation review waterfall under section III.A.2.j.iii of the Secretary’s Handbook 4000.1 or any successor provision, and setting forth the actual information entered in applying such analysis;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H196DA96D0E9747B492DF50D43736701E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to any mortgage for which the servicer did not conduct the analysis referred to in clause (i) because the servicer determined that the mortgagor did not express any interest in loss mitigation or provide appropriate documents—</text>
 <subclause id="H5D1D7AC1100F4395B5EB6C9EE322F73B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a statement of such determination;</text> </subclause><subclause id="H6BBC8EDD1FCA4058B4686DC4093C55D7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a description of the actions that the servicer took to solicit the borrower for loss mitigation review and obtain appropriate documents; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HD681A231A8964A7CB81FF722F50B2315"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a statement of the dates that the servicer took such actions; and</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="HECB296164EB143D3A5B160E9F38B767C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a statement setting forth the results of the servicers’ monthly loss mitigation evaluations for the mortgage required under section 203.605(a) of the Secretary’s regulations (24 C.F.R. 203.605(a)) or any successor provision;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H3648EBA2C27043A68EE894AC911EB668"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>with respect to any loss mitigation action for which the mortgagor was determined to be ineligible, an explanation of, and documentation showing, why the mortgagor was determined to be ineligible;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H811C5B89DDAB405083FE7AC5BB27F762"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a statement informing the borrower that, upon the request of the borrower, the Secretary will provide the borrower with all loss mitigation evaluation documentation required by the Secretary with respect to the mortgage, including monthly evaluations referred to in clause (iii); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H56AB0553551347EAA0563B8FD3E055C6"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information describing the procedure under section 543(a) for registering complaints regarding loss mitigation and the procedure under section 543(c) for appealing a servicer’s decisions regarding loss mitigation actions.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7854CE3073A0444890ED9B0445D1365E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>References</header><text>Such notice shall contain references to the applicable provisions of applicable handbook of the Secretary regarding ongoing loss mitigation reviews and standards for such reviews and shall identify how such provisions may be accessed on a publicly accessible website of the Department.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </section><section id="H7860CA34DF914A2F97046E5DDE4F86C9"><enum>6.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act may be construed to supercede, or exempt any person from complying with, any provision of the Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/2601">12 U.S.C. 2601</external-xref> et seq.) or the regulations issued under such Act.</text>
		</section></legis-body>
</bill>


