<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE79C00D000C04BAD98F2C9B5E943ED33" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5182 IH: Curb Objectionable Redirection of Resources and Unconstitutional Payments to Trump Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5182</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180306">March 6, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Ted Lieu of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Brendan F. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000581">Mrs. Lawrence</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require annual reports on funds expended by the Federal Government with the Trump Organization, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBA3A2043551340D882420477716C1595" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H87947608D4BE47B6910CAEE663BFB208" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Curb Objectionable Redirection of Resources and Unconstitutional Payments to Trump Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CORRUPT Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H5CECB4978A2E448698118497FF7C565E" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H542C5E9E40BF4E438FE5DCA5ED0769BE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Kleptocracy is a tool used by autocratic leaders, including Vladimir Putin, to exploit state resources; it involves the operation of sophisticated networks for the purpose of self-enrichment.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE18A625B186B4CB395E1A6CBEC8572E3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Unlike prior presidents, President Trump has refused to sell his business interests or divest himself of assets that present potential conflicts of interest.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD66B0F296145491BA6E154F1E1F3A093"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Article I of the Constitution states that <quote>no Person holding any office of profit or trust under them, shall, without the consent of the Congress, accept any present, emolument, office, or title, of any kind whatever, from any King, Prince, or foreign State</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF386C180225B4F97804A62C774BA2015"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Foreign governments and foreign-held companies have already shifted business to the President’s companies in order to curry favor with the Administration.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9761F75759E24D77BB77DD7F8C1BD553"><enum>(5)</enum><text>According to reports, the Trump International Hotel has generated at least $19,700,000 in income for the President between September 2016 and April 2017.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD22E08FC8B4D4F059B0EB052D03E5669"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The National Security Council and State Department have allegedly used taxpayers’ money to pay for staff to stay at Trump hotels and resorts, thereby benefitting the President.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H94ABD4E3B9BE483FBF21B7D1E5B61CE0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of the Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text> <paragraph id="HD172DCE1F68E43F8B2DAC965805BF1FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>kleptocrats such as Vladimir Putin pose a threat to United States national security by undermining financial and Government institutions;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4B980D0859A7482B95C80BAC5477A6D2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the United States must take all steps necessary to defend itself against kleptocratic practices; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6070AF2B503D4B8793C9105CF223C298"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Federal funds should not be expended in a manner that enriches the President or any of his close relatives or associates.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H80ECBE6BBF1C47FD9B927BCB15B0CA4C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reports</header> 
<subsection id="HD62A51723F8144A2BECE906C84FE4A74"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Agency report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the head of each agency shall submit to the Office of Government Ethics a report on the amount expended by that agency in fiscal year 2017 at, or any payments made to, any covered property and shall include—</text> <paragraph id="HF748BCA9193444F8BB0545BF405887C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any hotel stay using per diem or other funds; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6FF226766B90493C95A70394A4C23D8E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the rental of any conference room or meeting facility.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H120E054794684F248D52E71C405DA0BC" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Office of Government Ethics Report</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Office of Government Ethics shall submit to Congress a comprehensive report on funds expended by any agency at, or any payments made to, a covered property in fiscal year 2017.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBC5A5368F9D94D97AFEE9CDCD96714D0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>At the end of the next fiscal year following the date of the enactment of this Act, and at the end of each fiscal year thereafter, the Director of the Office of Management and Budget shall submit to Congress a report on the direct and indirect ways that funds appropriated to agencies have benefitted a covered property, including—</text> <paragraph id="HA64EB57A6C824D3792CB06B007758689"><enum>(1)</enum><text>funds expended by any agency at, or any payments made to, a covered property in the previous fiscal year;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA6E816FB43D249C2A1C2B80D4A45F3B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>regulatory actions in the previous fiscal year with a beneficial impact on a covered property; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3871A41026574DD8AC58D072804A614E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>indirect expenditures with vendors conducting more than $1,000,000 in business with a covered individual or with the owners of a covered property in the previous fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HB9C3C95C17CB4B17A602917C7C302817"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HD7B69B3D2B884CABA0AAB9B3F95E5FFF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <term>agency</term>—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBEF13AC3740B4B44AB13B613231B0A30"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has the meaning given the term—</text> <clause id="HE20E267DB01846DE864DFF8046D3A125"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><quote>Executive agency</quote> under section 105 of title 5, United States Code; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9CF4EFBD31E3435486CC510C89520BB9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><quote>military department</quote> under section 102 of title 5, United States Code; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H19E2029B49E94FB384D1A2934DD1EA45"><enum>(B)</enum><text>means—</text> 
<clause id="H1734C8203C5D41B282DB04D4E3FCDB2E"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other establishment in the executive branch (including the Executive Office of the President, the United States Postal Service, and the Postal Regulatory Commission);</text></clause> <clause id="HAD38211DE25148E2835D217E2A26F2F1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an office, agency, or other establishment in the legislative branch; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE03664DFDAB445F297F5BF90BD87847C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an office, agency, or other establishment in the judicial branch.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H501224F1738E402EA1DDC0A780312381"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered individual</header><text>The term <term>covered individual</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD39D93EC55D3460EAB12DF51B3B78814"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the President;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEDBAAE99F720414599C3A113175BF7B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a relative of the President; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEB4871C7D770489F959105BD1C152D5E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>with respect to an agency that is an Executive department, the head of the Executive department.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6518FC2613114FF1A0CF3D42C1EB7826"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered property</header><text>The term <term>covered property</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5290699C5E9E4C55A0AE215D89B0259C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any property controlled by the Trump Organization; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB9588C52A7EE488988174AB657C2E776"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an organization or business controlled by or associated with a covered person (including any known shell company), any member of the President’s family, or any employee of the Trump Organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H371DA49654184D21ABCB7471D30FE800"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Executive department</header><text>The term <term>Executive department</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

