<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA755AA676CA0413BA8CBF0CF7FB661F6" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5679 IH: Jobs Plus Recovery Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5679</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180507">May 7, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001290">Mr. Brat</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Labor, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services,
			 to establish a pilot program for Jobs Plus Recovery programs, and for
			 other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H4E29AFEF03C649A195F00DB1FBD16D97" style="OLC">
 <section id="HBC9274105E8045929F2B849ABADD15B8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Jobs Plus Recovery Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H32D5BB5BD8DA4A82B562E4432B10ADAA" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pilot program for jobs plus recovery programs</header> <subsection id="H27ABD129CE724A4AB61D466B5609C552"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text>
 <paragraph id="HB68F69585E1B40449146A47C4B9AF956"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Education provider</header><text>The term <term>education provider</term> has the meaning given the term <quote>institution of higher education</quote> in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9541A26E6B9C46D7AD0D300950771A3D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Jobs plus recovery program</header><text>The term <term>Jobs Plus Recovery program</term> means a program carried out through a grant under this section.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA71F1CC6940F42FAAE4FAFB86AA39E6D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Local area; local board; one-stop operator</header><text>The terms <term>local area</term>, <term>local board</term>, and <term>one-stop operator</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H231FE2F0D0F248AC834D1962A81A1416"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Peer recovery support services</header><text>The term <term>peer recovery support services</term> means a collection of community services that—</text> <subparagraph id="H5DD1B6FE3ABA49A4820F87C22218921D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are designed and delivered by individuals who have experienced both substance use disorder and recovery from such disorder;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5007D4C9C008482A89A7B226CAB18A21"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are delivered to individuals with a substance use disorder; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B247993FF014285A64AAF9734332914"><enum>(C)</enum><text>include peer-to-peer programs, job and life-skills training, assistance in obtaining supportive housing or recovery housing, and other services that contribute to better overall health and well-being.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H202C337C9B9541FAA822C201326CEAA0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Program participant</header><text>The term <term>program participant</term> means an individual that is identified as having a substance use disorder and enrolls in a Job Plus Recovery program to receive any of the services described in subsection (d)(1).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HEF7C299B305C4D37BA9BED71AD9C3639"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Treatment providers</header><text>The term <term>treatment provider</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H109385C10A604C38B2E91D36D505042B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a health care provider that offers services for treating substance use disorders; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1F37B0769984C618309384929F64F96"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include—</text> <clause id="H7BDC73B3190C4B37BC12F711FDDBF93B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a nonprofit provider of peer recovery support services;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HDB98C3D1DD944CE98FA46A72CF8560FC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a community health care provider, or any other health care provider;</text> </clause><clause id="HCAE26B5D80A24FEB89B0594277CDC2B6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a federally qualified health center (as defined in section 1861(aa) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x</external-xref>)); or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H37DD4EF73AF3458AA2ABFE6ADACBD15F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any other health care provider or health-related organization that treats a substance use disorder, including a provider that offers medication-assisted therapy or a provider listed on the Behavioral Health Treatment Services Locator of the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C7FE2188AFA4690B7EBDF9A5B6D99E6"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Labor.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H940C1F69C26B4CAFA2BE2FA7ADBFF55D"><enum>(8)</enum><header>State board</header><text>The term <term>State board</term> means a State workforce development board established under section 101 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3111">29 U.S.C. 3111</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H80622A4BC0194388AE92D50ED7956FEE"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Substance use disorder</header><text>The term <term>substance use disorder</term> means such a disorder within the meaning of title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290aa">42 U.S.C. 290aa</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCC05E06AF54943179056E84C1D668860"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of the pilot program</header>
 <paragraph id="HB736247B00EB4F76A2D00A1D2DC6365D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall establish and carry out a pilot program to award grants to local boards (which, for purposes of this section, may include consortia of local boards) to carry out Jobs Plus Recovery programs through a partnership described in subsection (c)(1).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0F673959CB4B45AEAC410DB0C9B4A4B0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>A local board desiring a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time and in such form and manner as the Secretary may reasonably require. Such application shall include a demonstration that the local board has notified the applicable State board of its application for such grant.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H8B5F8683A5F1427DB049C6FFCCBD9D7B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Selection</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HDA42EDE6F0DC4014B0931EBE6137E8C5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall select grant recipients under this section based on each of the following criteria:</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="HD06F43B8DF824DE39BBF86A2017FF4F3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>An analysis of the demand for the Jobs Plus Recovery program in the local area served by the local board, including analyzing demand by determining whether the local board is in a local area with a high annual rate of—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="HD76EF962E8DC41CFA041A92765FCEF54"><enum>(I)</enum><text>individuals with a substance use disorder;</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H011546EF851A45E38E21BC1C6D7742EE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>drug and alcohol overdose and mortality;</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HC487857C54B945F9AA7A907B880FF010"><enum>(III)</enum><text>illicit drug use and binge drinking among adults;</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H73876494339C4F49AE0140FF0B4E1F17"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>suicide; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HE3325E4A3EAD4E388BDB12E4DACDEC1C"><enum>(V)</enum><text>underemployment or unemployment.</text> </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HD5B6D748748049FD90B297D8AF9FA633"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An analysis of the estimated performance of the local board in carrying out a Jobs Plus Recovery program, including—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="HDA17B881C3614D79A459C34ABCC2470C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>using key performance indicators to assess the estimated effectiveness of the program, including the estimated number of individuals with a substance use disorder who may be served by the program;</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HFA00658688F24C818F42701BB9605325"><enum>(II)</enum><text>analyzing the record of the local board in serving individuals with a barrier to employment; and</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H2FD6990D38B644F9A363174F0F6586FD"><enum>(III)</enum><text>analyzing the ability of the local board to establish the partnership described in subsection (c)(1).</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HDFFC5BD9D60942B3A9E98AC15AEA8554"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Consideration of geographic distribution (such as urban and rural distribution) of grants awarded under this section.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7FD787ED80044DA49211959450A63EBC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Analysis</header><text>The analysis described in subparagraph (A)(i) may include or utilize—</text> <clause commented="no" id="HB9E395A794FF405E8F0DEDE722A42468"><enum>(i)</enum><text>data from the National Center for Health Statistics of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HDA75C9B80C2940828EFC85B712730608"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>data from the Center for Behavioral Health Statistics and Quality of the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration;</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H4EFD07B0642548E1B9BB25BB96E1A921"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>State vital statistics;</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="HD968A931216E4FE9BB8597FB4411BDC7"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>municipal police department records; and</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H9152FE3A917D4300A956705B0C5DABBD"><enum>(v)</enum><text>local coroners' reports.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD56A762C6E3448BCB0C0E56D63E272F2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Partnership</header> <paragraph id="H709AB4FD03C846AF894DC3B4435E88FC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each local board receiving a grant under this section shall enter into a partnership to provide the services and carry out the activities under subsection (d), by contracting with at least 1 of each of the following entities:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H87B79F8D84FE4B20B583D18E0D1E47F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A treatment provider that—</text> <clause id="H4A4E1D243F6E4C838B296F69735C0463"><enum>(i)</enum><text>meets the standard under paragraph (2); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H4408F44909CF4C8FB4EBD296A20E6012"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is a nonprofit entity, unless no such entity that meets the requirements under this subparagraph is located in the local area.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E99C092B1454138BE3F74D32A9C358B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A one-stop operator, or other entity with experience in providing comprehensive job training services.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53F582D6752944B6BD3990CEA009C21E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An education provider.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H24380B334FE9482582E4DA683088D892"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A justice or law enforcement organization.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61ABFA2EA85D4BE9955FB8C4D99E1459"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A community-based organization.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D74E3DA6D9A41C09E8F6ABCA999E124"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Any other organization as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HB834E9053793462E94641FF3505F974F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Standard for treatment providers</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall establish a standard that each treatment provider entering into a partnership under paragraph (1)(A) shall meet based on best practices identified by the Secretary.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H0145AEE22D1143829623FA45DDF37340"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="H63B5B1F89CC3448BB8391995586A36A6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Services and activities</header><text>Each partnership described in subsection (c)(1) shall, through a Jobs Plus Recovery program, provide a minimum of each of the following services:</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H142AF8F6C4A342ABA8F768BBD80D8F30"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Screening services</header><text>Screening services, including—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H61406090ED7C4C2DA04556F0F6547863"><enum>(i)</enum><text>using an evidence-based screening method to screen each individual seeking participation in the Jobs Plus Recovery program to determine whether the individual has a substance use disorder;</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HC4D66C4BBF174989841D4F3AF5A72814"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>conducting an assessment of each such individual to determine the services needed for such individual to obtain or retain employment, including an assessment of strengths and general work readiness; and</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HC8ADFC5DAD064528B9AC83BE5D78518D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>accepting walk-ins or referrals from employers, labor organizations, or other entities recommending individuals to participate in such program.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H143E1F3E474F40F19E7DB9E5BF7014C1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Individual treatment and employment plan</header><text>Developing an individual treatment and employment plan for each program participant, which shall include providing a case manager to work with each participant to—</text>
 <clause id="H2BD8F890A320430AB90D382AEE37A18A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identify employment and career goals;</text> </clause><clause id="H948C4786725B4E149086E6E108FAA317"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>explore career pathways that lead to high-demand industries and sectors as determined by the State board and the lead State official responsible for the administration of workforce investment activities;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H6A688F2E060342D48B2CDBF6458F1D26"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>set appropriate achievement objectives to attain the employment and career goals identified under clause (i); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H21A58245F30541FC84002D05E23CDBDD"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>develop the appropriate combination of services to enable the participant to achieve such employment and career goals.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H34CBD68AECA14E40BD2F050A66D51981"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Outpatient treatment and recovery care</header><text>Individualized and group outpatient treatment and recovery services for program participants that are offered during the day, evening, weekends. Such treatment and recovery services—</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="HF4C49E5DCC0442F38CE091D70A8BA189"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall—</text> <subclause commented="no" id="HA0D92C01F7054C989F726AA7918232F7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>be based on a model that utilizes combined behavioral interventions and other evidence-based or evidence-informed interventions; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HABFF498B5B504013A63510F137928DD2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>comply with the standard described in subsection (c)(2); and</text> </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HA3C8FE8BA9FC41599683914822E410BB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may include additional services such as—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="HFA5B754B5B5545E8A3E6B08AF140AA0E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>health (including mental health) services, addiction services, or other forms of outpatient treatment that may impact opioid use disorder and co-occurring conditions;</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H57C01A6439354620A171A0EF50105017"><enum>(II)</enum><text>linkages to community services, including services designed to support program participants that are offered by the entities that compose the partnership described in subsection (c)(1); and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H00D9FCF6A3AE41D5B1793EF81972C699"><enum>(III)</enum><text>referrals to health care providers, including referrals to providers of substance use disorder treatment and mental health services.</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC9B9DF3BE71F431D9DB70C427140FFFB"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Supportive services</header><text>Supportive services provided to program participants to ensure that such participants maintain employment for at least 12 months. Such supportive services—</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="HA7BBA1A1149B42E3A208D40E5FDCD671"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall include—</text> <subclause id="H863BAF1299E54993B1840D87207366A5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>coordinated wraparound services to provide maximum support for program participants to ensure that the program participants maintain employment and recovery for at least 12 months;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H174E6E82ED584F7CAE3A71BFD1FEC92F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>assistance in establishing eligibility for assistance under Federal, State, and local programs providing health services (including mental health services), housing services, transportation services, or social services; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HCB5445F3C2EA4518AF550490C9A3AD1D"><enum>(III)</enum><text>peer recovery support services; and</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="H659BA34910BE411E92774162115C4885"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may include additional supportive services such as—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="H5D6CA71AB5E440B1876EF65925304310"><enum>(I)</enum><text>networking and mentorship opportunities; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="HB644574FAEF74E588235434FEF0A1626"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any other supportive services determined necessary by the local board.</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H35FA31FBC7164896AB464BA66D7FD9FF"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Career job training services</header><text>Career and job training services offered concurrently or sequentially with the services provided under subparagraphs (A) through (D). Such services shall include each of the following:</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="H4BF90BF0B9D04E31A9D9601419194A1E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Services provided to program participants in a pre-employment stage of the program, which may include—</text>
 <subclause id="H000DFDFD962248B9AB77486D0273A035"><enum>(I)</enum><text>initial education and skills assessments;</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H911725E784FD4FD7B34DD13718380CAE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>traditional classroom training funded through individual training accounts under section 134(c)(3)(F) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3174">29 U.S.C. 3174(c)(3)(F)</external-xref>);</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H47A7DB7C170A4904AC5DBC1F5F4FC2BF"><enum>(III)</enum><text>employability skills such as punctuality, personal maintenance skills, and professional conduct;</text> </subclause><subclause id="HB3819F195C0F47A3B8C9D443FF09BDB6"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>in-depth interviewing and evaluation to identify employment barriers and to develop individual employment plans;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HD00F0D2E7AB14C4282D729C2E2118927"><enum>(V)</enum><text>career planning that includes—</text> <item id="H4A1674428E444E70A2AF0ABB6B121615"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>career pathways leading to high-demand, high-wage jobs; and</text>
 </item><item id="H9E3CAFC68EDD4F96BF66983F2A45C7EB"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>job coaching, job matching, and job placement services;</text> </item></subclause><subclause id="HFAC895F3CF20479C85C5791A1CDF87CD"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>payments and fees for employment and training-related applications, tests, and certifications; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H31E08D265DBD4778B70299F393E95D75"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>any other appropriate training service described in section 134(c) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3174">29 U.S.C. 3174(c)</external-xref>).</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H0315C60DDD2F4A61B95D46C118A6C029"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Services provided to program participants during their first 6 months of employment to ensure job retention, which may include—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="H9087804835A746F3AD9BCF2C1C99EC8F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>case management and support services, including a continuation of the services described in clause (i);</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H2A3634CBE09348739044C986CA2035C0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a continuation of skills training, and career and technical education, described in clause (i) that are conducted in collaboration with the employers of such participants;</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H513339BC789E4F34A11545C03BCC2C53"><enum>(III)</enum><text>mentorship services and job retention support for such participants; or</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H6E2E31A16C6E4AE48A479E640F541E71"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>targeted training for managers, workers working with such participants (such as mentors), and human resource representatives in the business in which such participants are employed.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HCB4A751012644272B7DB9A9AFBA0ED19"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Services to ensure program participants maintain employment for at least 12 months.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HED4E76244171480E8A8A71372DA9D032"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Engaging employers</header><text>Each local board receiving a grant under this section shall, through the partnership under subsection (c)(1), engage with employers to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H64E3E5A6B21F4C17825C4BC1CA4C754E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>learn about the skill and hiring requirements of employers;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7BC5AE287794D3DB632ED15A2F013E1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>learn about the support needed by employers to hire and retain program participants, and other individuals with a substance use disorder, and the support needed by such employers to obtain their commitment to testing creative solutions to employing such participants and individuals;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7AF0F7E6B1A242899ECAC4E18ED62545"><enum>(C)</enum><text>connect employers and workers to on-the-job or customized training programs to help facilitate program participant employment;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2098FEF1021941228EDB281A6E22EB02"><enum>(D)</enum><text>connect employers with an education provider, or a provider of career and technical education under the Carl D. Perkins and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2301">20 U.S.C. 2301</external-xref> et seq.), to develop classroom instruction to complement on-the-job learning for such participants and individuals;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HFD38B7637B634DAC9CBF15BADB44CEC7"><enum>(E)</enum><text>help employers develop the curriculum design of a work-based learning program for such participants and individuals; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDAAF3B159B2D479B8C3BD52996015330"><enum>(F)</enum><text>help employers employ such participants or individuals engaging in a work-based learning program for a transitional period before hiring the participant or individual for full-time employment of not less than 30 hours a week.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F48B3001B714D3CB2AF470F6DB51B45"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Proven and promising practices</header><text>A local board receiving a grant under this section shall, in carrying out a Jobs Plus Recovery program, lead efforts in the local area to identify and promote proven and promising strategies and initiatives for meeting the needs of employers and program participants.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H79D68230CB6240D2989CF65AD56D1A1A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>A local board receiving a grant under this section may not use—</text> <subparagraph id="H3341F75B8E8B4282B0D27D0B5C46A178"><enum>(A)</enum><text>more than 5 percent of the funds received under such grant for administrative costs of the partnership described in subsection (c)(1);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0267794C0A154DE3BF816957D57C410E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>more than 10 percent of the funds received under such grant for the provision of outpatient treatment and recovery services described in subsection (d)(1)(C); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B424284454C4E94834B47243CFD2DC2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>more than 10 percent of the funds received under such grant for the provision of supportive services described in subsection (d)(1)(D).</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H81CF4E6920F1443DAD32E9D54481C690"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Performance accountability</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="H65FB856354F54BDCA24D02C809B0A392"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>The Secretary shall establish quarterly reporting requirements for recipients of grants under this section that, to the extent practicable, are based on the performance accountability system under section 116 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3141">29 U.S.C. 3141</external-xref>), including the indicators described in subsection (c)(1)(A), and requirements for local area performance reports under subsection (d), of such section.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE7E15B73452149F288EC286F9716DFBF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Evaluations</header>
 <subparagraph id="HC6B9432C523240A391CD0D8779272572"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Authority to enter into agreements</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that an independent evaluation is conducted on each Jobs Plus Recovery program to determine the impact of the program on employment of individuals with substance use disorders. The Secretary shall enter into an agreement with the local board carrying out the program to pay for all or part of such evaluation.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25EC76FCC0154310845CDE050F2845DC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Methodologies to be used</header><text>The independent evaluation required under this paragraph shall use experimental designs using random assignment or, when random assignment is not feasible, other reliable, evidence-based research methodologies that allow for the strongest possible causal inferences.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H20E8351C5FFA4BD08BED8D2DA48EC22C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as may be necessary.</text> </subsection></section><section id="H8366D5AEBDCB474DBCE4CC0D6264913D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Amendment to the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3(24) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102(24)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H4D21F09FBD9745BC89A68552E558CE8A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (N) as subparagraph (O); and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HC287AE26EE994DF486D1703E24BB27D1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (M) the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HECD2DCF6730F405E8C9C627432C46E07" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H3DACD87E99F6476A85C556E282AD4764"><enum>(N)</enum><text>Individuals with a substance use disorder (within the meaning of such term in title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290aa">42 U.S.C. 290aa</external-xref> et seq.)).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


