<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HBEB796EDCA454C2FA1027E8B19EA02BA" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4830 IH: Servicemembers Improved Transition through Reforms for Ensuring Progress Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4830</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180118">January 18, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster of New Hampshire</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000255">Mr. Jones</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000170">Mr. O'Rourke</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to provide for the disapproval of any course of education
			 for purposes of the educational assistance programs of the Department of
			 Veterans Affairs unless the educational institution providing the course
			 permits individuals to attend or participate in courses pending payment by
			 Department, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HC059B96E0FDD45A8A0396F27D8B09A50" style="OLC">
 <section id="HA0A673B14F19411CBF77F9CA15958C7D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Servicemembers Improved Transition through Reforms for Ensuring Progress Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SIT-REP Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HD0A59ED9E11343FCAB53523C5BCD506A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Disapproval for purposes of educational assistance programs of Department of Veterans Affairs of certain courses of education that do not permit individuals to attend or participate in courses pending payment</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3679 of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3DB6F7C5FE6C447383E48C406B2474C9" style="USC">
				<subsection id="H00F19A15DFF94F2294EF607509026C8E"><enum>(e)</enum>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0EED36BF45BD456499097EAA04523A0A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this chapter, beginning on August 1, 2018, a State approving agency, or the Secretary when acting in the role of the State approving agency, shall disapprove a course of education provided by an educational institution unless the educational institution has adopted the following policies:</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD2F0C990CEF5493C899104C8A59A02DF" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A policy that permits any covered individual to attend or participate in the course of education during the period beginning on the date on which the individual provides to the educational institution a certificate of eligibility for entitlement to educational assistance under chapter 30, 31, 33, or 35 of this title and ending on the earlier of the following dates:</text>
 <clause id="HCE315B41E7574CABB81E0C9C2C11D341"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The date on which the Secretary provides payment for such course of education to such institution.</text> </clause><clause id="H53EE27EC341F4F789E0F9A81FA2632B1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The date that is 90 days after the date on which the individual provides to the educational institution such certificate of eligibility.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBC3C167BE094C39B52B17B68F2A17EE" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A policy that ensures that the educational institution will not impose any penalty, including the assessment of late fees, the denial of access to classes, libraries, or other institutional facilities, or the requirement that a covered individual borrow additional funds, on any covered individual because of the individual’s inability to meet his or her financial obligations to the institution as a result of the delayed disbursement of any payment to be provided by the Secretary.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F2B6C52D7124411BC63204CC0575739" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>For purposes of this subsection, a covered individual is any individual who is entitled to educational assistance under chapter 30, 31, 33, or 35 of this title.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE0FCC9F89FDB489AB32CE302AA2ADD2D" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Secretary may waive such requirements of paragraph (1) as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section></legis-body></bill> 

