<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9F4BE78EB1A04D588A499A31BB943A25" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4969 IH: Improving Embassy Design and Security Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4969</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180207">February 7, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve the design and construction of diplomatic posts, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HCBCB6DAA3F00415083A01AA08D608B5D" style="OLC">
 <section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF89F7B86C46E4D92A77DA002C4FA3E6F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Embassy Design and Security Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H6410522576804F909879CCB7E7FEEF96"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improving embassy construction</header> <subsection id="HB67B416CAE604A82AD577383F827BC13"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds that the decision by the Department of State’s Bureau of Overseas Buildings Operations (<quote>OBO</quote>) to transition from Standard Embassy Design to Design Excellence has in many cases—</text>
 <paragraph id="HAF784EB5511645D2921EEAE515E595A0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>increased the cost of building new embassies and consulates;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H1C121822276541F9912D760C2FF71AC3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>delayed the move of thousands of staff from facilities that do not meet current security standards to new, secure facilities;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3CDE1B9C04F044CCA14CCCF5260434F8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>exacerbated certain deficiencies in the quality of the Bureau’s program management;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H66C4956323D94D6686474E2BF1B1F059"><enum>(4)</enum><text>been a factor in reduced competition for capital construction projects; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H71C8FE1DA59542439083D03A9D73B852"><enum>(5)</enum><text>been a complicating factor in achieving the Department’s own security requirements.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7C88A67FDFFC45448E565FB7613EF1CE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the OBO should give appropriate consideration to Standard Embassy Design, in which each new embassy and consulate starts with a standard design and keeps customization to a minimum.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H401553C4F9EE45D5831370064A1A68E0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Delivery</header>
 <paragraph id="H1C7B85DB56474A9E9552AA5AA624A05F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Design-build project delivery</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except in cases in which the Secretary of State determines that such would not be appropriate, the Secretary shall make use of the design-build project delivery system at diplomatic posts that have not yet received design or construction contracts as of the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC71CE1190D7D4FEAB7E0FCAA52AC56DF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Standard design</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall give preference to the use of a standard design, together with design-build delivery under paragraph (1).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H934D1D44799248AAA5BEE0B35211E7C0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Vertical standard design</header><text>The Secretary of State shall develop a vertical standard design that can be implemented according to the Department of State’s requisite security and spatial needs for diplomatic posts that are to be situated on a smaller plot of land.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H342397A44C804308A2C5F2CEBF905487"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Bridging</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall make use of bridging to adapt the standard design under paragraph (2) with design-build project delivery under paragraph (1) at diplomatic posts that require a more customized design due to climatic, geographic, or functional requirements.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HB79154B8E1804C8F946851CC2C57997C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Other application</header>
 <subparagraph id="H6D6437C5550B45F1A7E0AC0391B90E07"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State may make use of design-bid-build delivery with non-standard design in limited instances of particular diplomatic importance as determined by the Secretary.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE4D0D3F0244F40988F1C053788436077"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The Secretary of State may not delegate the authority of the Secretary under subparagraph (A) to make use of design-bid-build delivery with non-standard design.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H6CFF78402270483EB528651E677F662D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consultation regarding non-Standard designs</header><text>The Secretary of State shall carry out any new diplomatic post project that is in the design phase or pre-design phase as of the date of the enactment of this Act and that utilizes bridging or non-standard design under subsection (c) only after notification to and consultation with the appropriate congressional committees. Such notification and consultation shall include provision to the appropriate congressional committees, for each such project, of the following documentation:</text>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="H3CA08F7E71224E70BC79F7B5667398CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A comparison of the estimated full lifecycle costs of the project at issue to the estimated full lifecycle costs of such project if such project were to use a standard design.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H858376FDF0D4426EAC1AAFFCC5620550"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A comparison of the estimated completion date of such project to the estimated completion date of such project if such project were to use a standard design.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H644C83D316164CEA973179B9DD2482A1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A comparison of the security of such completed project to the security of such completed project if such completed project were to use a standard design.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H2841D605C0BF4A6ABCB7B3F8247DE286"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A justification for the Secretary’s selection of a non-standard design over a standard design for such project.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HC15EE41C676A438A9FE740A09E07DE84"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Performance evaluation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall report to the appropriate congressional committees regarding performance evaluation measures in line with GAO’s <quote>Standards for Internal Control in the Federal Government</quote> that will be applicable to the Bureau of Overseas Building Operations of the Department of State.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H8CD2192DA3A649EE97D2C56A0379B3AD"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H0915C66800D5444FA1F02B1090F9C7BD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H797E0744273349C8957319DF0BB06DB5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Bridging</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>bridging</quote> means a delivery method for construction projects that is a hybrid of the traditional <quote>design-bid-build</quote> and the <quote>design-build</quote> methods, whereby the Bureau of Overseas Building Operations of the Department of State first contracts with a design firm to develop a project-specific, partial design that a construction contractor and its design firm then complete, the objective of which is to retain the best features of the design-bid-build and design-build methods for the project owner and eliminate those aspects of each such method that often cause problems for such owner.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H331A1AADE0464F578BC788D9EB9481BC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Design-bid-build</header><text>The term <quote>design-bid-build</quote> means a method of project delivery in which a design entity is first contracted to provide a design and a construction entity is subsequently contracted to build the awarded design contract.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H083C4DC2A3144F66B39C9B291BEB306E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Design-build</header><text>The term <quote>design-build</quote> means a method of project delivery in which one entity, such as the design-build team, works under a single contract with the project owner to provide design and construction services.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H67736FBEDA644527B88B62258CA9EFC5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Non-standard design</header><text>The term <quote>non-standard design</quote> means a new diplomatic post design that does not utilize a standardized design template for the structural, spatial, and security requirements of such post.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1BC700902505475ABF1AE5A91EA718B3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Standard design</header><text>The term <quote>standard design</quote> means a diplomatic post design that utilizes a standardized design template for the structural, spatial, and security requirements of such post.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


