<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HBABDEBD24E2947BDBBDCFDEFC208559A" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4810 IH: Making Available Plans to Promote Investment in Next Generation Networks without Overbuilding and Waste Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4810</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180117">January 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information to carry out
			 activities relating to the development and maintenance of a broadband
			 inventory map through the National Telecommunications and Information
			 Administration and not through an agreement with any other agency.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HD2A68330183D4C6195E5415F31AD4CC5" style="OLC">
 <section id="H2885F64B308B4537BE6F5BC8D9ED46D9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Making Available Plans to Promote Investment in Next Generation Networks without Overbuilding and Waste Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>MAPPING NOW Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="HA681FC6E26C84B76A595D0DCDFF61162"><enum>2.</enum><header>Broadband inventory map</header>
 <subsection id="H66D4267C119342CBA3E25DBF53943FEE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>To be carried out by NTIA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information shall carry out subsection (l) of section 6001 of the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1305">47 U.S.C. 1305</external-xref>) through the National Telecommunications and Information Administration and not through a memorandum of understanding or other agreement with any other agency. Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to prohibit the Assistant Secretary from consulting with another agency in carrying out such subsection (l).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF42E120FD8124E30BC473ACC27877DED"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No additional funds authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No additional funds are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act. This Act shall be carried out using amounts otherwise authorized.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


