<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9DB4E22BA87849148B4C64B09176C198" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4975 IH: Nuclear Plant Decommissioning Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4975</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180207">February 7, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000800">Mr. Welch</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000179">Mr. Engel</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 to provide for consultation with State, tribal, and local
			 governments, the consideration of State, tribal, and local concerns, and
			 the approval of post-shutdown decommissioning activities reports by the
			 Nuclear Regulatory Commission.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HCD042DEB29514F69A992C2E690362037" style="OLC">
 <section id="H2BBA352B5A1C4AD7B522F1A2320743F2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Nuclear Plant Decommissioning Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H87BEF2E0AF7146A7AFBB78072FE4E5DD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Post-shutdown decommissioning activities reports</header> <subsection id="H2BB05649247542CC85F9C2A8429A0C24"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Chapter 10 of title I of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2131">42 U.S.C. 2131</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H36866F9419B148D1AB19238DA9A158CD" style="OLC">
					<section id="H7C571BFA81934DE69515C971EC9F9B54"><enum>113.</enum><header>Post-shutdown decommissioning activities reports</header>
 <subsection id="H1B1E2C65FF2749178CDA6BD497F2E863"><enum>a.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H07833AD4DBF34A3C969040AFCA69274E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Affected State</header><text><italic></italic>The term <term>affected State</term> means—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H06077A704C774BEC880ABF5918EBE3E9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the host State of a covered facility; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94783071B43849B48E2E910B2C9D367C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each State located within 50 miles of a covered facility.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D05B1A3D3CC4B0E8ED761C3091CB6D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the Nuclear Regulatory Commission.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H4C4D77304BB94C668E9050FB84DC7234"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered facility</header><text>The term <term>covered facility</term> means a facility of a licensee for which a PSDAR is required.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H53D9D5CC25644AA592975A3B8A88126F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Host State</header><text>The term <term>host State</term> means the State in which a covered facility is located.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HD322D97A5CDF4B15914EF7D17792727A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>License; licensee</header><text>The terms <term>license</term> and <term>licensee</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 50.2 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HEA2B912F0F8C4FD2AF3E7A1459B08170"><enum>(6)</enum><header>PSDAR</header><text>The term <term>PSDAR</term> means a post-shutdown decommissioning activities report submitted to the Commission and affected States under section 50.82(a)(4)(i) of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3CA1546D6FA249A6AE50734EE6B5B98B"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Transferee</header><text>The term <term>transferee</term> means an entity to which a licensee proposes to transfer a license for a covered facility.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HCF223F429683490FB30DC6D9D00790DD"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Tribal government</header><text>The term <term>tribal government</term> means the governing body of an Indian tribe (as defined in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>)).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEBF5366F4EE746968F1A974002BEF6F0"><enum>b.</enum><header>Consultation required</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law (including regulations), a licensee may not submit to the Commission a proposed PSDAR, or transfer to another entity the license, for a covered facility until the licensee and the transferee, if applicable, conduct consultation regarding the development of the proposed PSDAR or the proposed license transfer, as applicable, with—</text>
 <paragraph id="H16562BADD96E41B7BED31995C0A50DCC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>each affected State; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H056DD58B9ACD4F8B8B18EDB60F85E342"><enum>(2)</enum><text>each unit of State government or tribal government that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H6173AA3759D1418AB68015A3D0E259EC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is located in an affected State; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F79E64D105940F7BA0EF10AEE5CA33F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has jurisdiction over land located within 50 miles of the covered facility.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFEEA0337D8BB40F591C9501ED1E30F3F"><enum>c.</enum><header>Submission to Commission; additional consultation</header>
 <paragraph id="H01BF16A6D41D4B07A9A44F2AB5A6B609"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>After carrying out the consultation required under subsection b. with respect to a proposed PSDAR or transfer of a license for a covered facility, the licensee shall—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD4DEC47229CA46119BBECEFE51476071"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submit to the Commission, as applicable—</text> <clause id="HB058F22CA0CC436F9DDDE576BD788C56"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the proposed PSDAR; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H98A6B24F069043CAA2C214F4B2672DB2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an application for transfer of a license; and</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HADF7C18557F948DD9929AC1D47B8CA2E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subject to paragraph (3), make the proposed PSDAR or application for transfer of a license, as applicable, available to the public.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FFD940DFF604607BC4CEBB8270A5D20"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>On receipt of a proposed PSDAR or notice of a proposed license transfer under paragraph (1)(A), the Commission shall, subject to paragraph (3), make the proposed PSDAR or application for transfer of a license, as applicable, available to the public.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD9F2E3EC00BF41548FA1CBA54B98BF7E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exclusion of certain information</header><text>In making a proposed PSDAR or application for transfer of a license, as applicable, available to the public under paragraph (1)(B) or (2), the Commission or the licensee, as applicable, may redact such information as the Commission or the licensee, as applicable, determines to be necessary to protect—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H6FC4A39FC0D741EA943C6BE3AB384586"><enum>(A)</enum><text>trade secrets and commercial or financial information under section 552(b)(4) of title 5, United States Code; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C80F2A757234E2C9B7CE1CD302E44B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>national security.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H79D4B631E4B54D66A93A75D3842D0C3F"><enum>d.</enum><header>Public participation</header><text>For a period of not less than 90 days beginning on the date on which a licensee submits a proposed PSDAR to the Commission under subsection c. (1)(A) or the date on which the Commission dockets an application for transfer of a license under section 2.101 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations), as applicable, the Commission shall solicit in the host State public comments regarding the proposed PSDAR or notice of proposed license transfer, including through—</text>
 <paragraph id="HAD820CB8EC08429896FAE47C6465953F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the solicitation of written comments; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H2D2997F1DF8C4505ADC45F6E5264C42A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the conduct of not fewer than 2 public meetings.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF17B163D859C43A3AD3F646FB75AF9A5"><enum>e.</enum><header>Support, conditional support, or nonsupport by host State</header>
 <paragraph id="HC0AFC4E06B0D4FF5A900BB25E5E7F327"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of receipt of a proposed PSDAR or the date on which the Commission dockets an application for transfer of a license under section 2.101 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations), as applicable, for a covered facility, the Commission shall notify the host State of the opportunity to file with the Commission, by the date that is 60 days after the date on which the host State receives the notification—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF5F70AEBB0E244D7B4018C5C9E2EE4D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a statement of support for the proposed PSDAR or license transfer;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0106EC01179F451EBA556C33AE06CD90"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a statement of conditional support for the proposed PSDAR or license transfer, together with specific recommendations for changes that could lead the host State to support the proposed PSDAR or license transfer; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10EE371C5A80473CA359B896E49DB5AD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a statement of nonsupport for the proposed PSDAR or license transfer.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H50C7B09BE23B481E9C044615E2E5B354"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Statement of support or nonsupport; failure to submit</header> <subparagraph id="H202688C7618343D6B19906CBBF84CB1B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the host State files with the Commission a statement of support under paragraph (1)(A) or a statement of nonsupport under paragraph (1)(C), or fails to file a statement with the Commission by the deadline specified in paragraph (1), the Commission shall issue a determination regarding whether the proposed PSDAR is adequate or inadequate or a determination regarding whether to provide consent for the proposed license transfer, as applicable—</text>
 <clause id="H11AF428F1C86499EACCB9B6A525F3E41"><enum>(i)</enum><text>based on the considerations described in subparagraph (B); and</text> </clause><clause id="H6D9633DD36E04834AE5AF64E7757B65D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>after taking into consideration—</text>
 <subclause id="H04005EF2D8CE472B93320E889E7B3FD4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any written comments submitted by the host State, other affected States, and local communities with respect to the proposed PSDAR or license transfer; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H616B7692DAE6475CBC201EF07D2C5395"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any input from the public under subsection d.</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9FD17AAE5BBC48DD8DEB4ED5C713D70C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>The Commission shall consider a proposed PSDAR or license transfer to be adequate under subparagraph (A) if the Commission determines that—</text>
 <clause id="HC93A3B5D4814433AA31B1321DF46CB6C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the proposed PSDAR or license transfer provides for—</text> <subclause id="H76B42F27088F4ABDBE60C7186482FF65"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the overall protection of human health and the environment; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HBBFDC4DAB2D24CE88DA4DCD990831A67"><enum>(II)</enum><text>adequate protection to the health and safety of the public and the common defense and security;</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="HE1C1D81EB84440D390E0F1F1A26631E7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the licensee (and, if applicable, the transferee) has a substantial likelihood of implementing the proposed PSDAR or license transfer within the timeframe described in the proposed PSDAR or license transfer application;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H9F9C25DD046C4F92A36FE9BD8D3BC86C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the proposed PSDAR or license transfer is in accordance with applicable law (including regulations); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1859EFC33A1245F799F9581BD3ED9E0C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the licensee (and, if applicable, the transferee) has demonstrated that the licensee has, or will have, the funds required to fully implement the proposed PSDAR or license transfer within the timeframe described in the proposed PSDAR or license transfer application, based on—</text>
 <subclause id="H95C9B9F8D4E3411B95896ADF5DC975EF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a comprehensive radiological site assessment and characterization; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="HDFC953C7AC034258A533C8709CE76971"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a nonradiological site assessment and characterization conducted by the host State.</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9317E28DD3244524977DECAB7FF6ED45"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Determination of adequacy</header><text>Subject to paragraph (4), if the Commission determines that a proposed PSDAR or license transfer is adequate under subparagraphs (A) and (B), the Commission shall issue a decision document approving the PSDAR or license transfer.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5671D04DF8E848128F33E0BF5970D8FB"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Determination of inadequacy</header><text>If the Commission determines that a proposed PSDAR or license transfer is inadequate under subparagraphs (A) and (B)—</text>
 <clause id="HAF6C7C6FE9484168B983E38DEA601372"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Commission shall issue a decision document rejecting the proposed PSDAR or license transfer, including a description of the reasons for the decision, by the applicable deadline under paragraph (4); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H3C043023701747668D9110C8F6D97B3B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not later than 2 years after the date of cessation of operations at the applicable covered facility, the licensee shall develop and submit to the Commission a new proposed PSDAR or license transfer in accordance with this section.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3401C1DF5CB2460088FC798F3A9453E9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conditional support by host State</header>
 <subparagraph id="HACBBCA298A3440C48C5BB1E3B3D35A0F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In any case in which the host State files with the Commission a statement of conditional support of a proposed PSDAR or license transfer under paragraph (1)(B), the Commission shall determine whether the proposed PSDAR or license transfer is permissible under applicable law (including regulations).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16154AD97D3B4BC1933B8635F7BAA89E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Changes</header><text>Notwithstanding the adequate protection of public health and safety or the common defense and security, for each change recommended by the host State under paragraph (1)(B), the Commission shall—</text>
 <clause id="H951FB0CA93A34710A2979111384070A8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provide for the inclusion of the change into the final PSDAR or license transfer, unless the Commission determines the change to be inappropriate for inclusion, based on clear and convincing evidence that—</text>
 <subclause id="HDA693D95B39A49C4A8A5ADFBA9EBE882"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the change violates applicable law; or</text> </subclause><subclause id="H8F1BBD56863C42F4AA207607B56D0912"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the total costs of the change substantially outweigh the safety, economic, or environmental benefits of the change to the host State; and</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H93476215E4164CB79A62613403076F62"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if applicable, provide the rationale for each determination of inappropriateness under clause (i).</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF2F41E5C330C4162A6DD4FF2747F6068"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Decision document</header> <clause id="H833C53B9808946F28691DA324B1E02DD"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (4), based on the determinations made under subparagraphs (A) and (B), the Commission shall issue a decision document relating to a proposed PSDAR or license transfer that, as applicable—</text>
 <subclause id="HCB61C5E707604FFBBCAD3001B8E2455E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>approves the proposed PSDAR or license transfer with any changes recommended by the host State that are not determined to be inappropriate under subparagraph (B); or</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H9F6803AF8E5E46CFAAB8651117DF7542"><enum>(II)</enum><text>rejects the proposed PSDAR or license transfer.</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="H251282A6B15C4F65BB2655179E129854"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Applicable law</header><text>A decision document issued under clause (i) or subparagraph (C) or (D)(i) of paragraph (2) shall be considered to be a final order entered in a proceeding under section 189 a.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8082D3C9015642A09CD6AEA59BB0AA1F"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Treatment on approval</header><text>On approval by the Commission of a proposed PSDAR or license transfer under subparagraph (C)(i)(I) or paragraph (2)(C)—</text>
 <clause id="H31431BFD8339442591D12291A3FC5567"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the PSDAR or approval of the license transfer by the Commission shall be final; and</text> </clause><clause id="H932F29CD160A47C8975F5D8E190E6EF6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the licensee may begin implementation of the PSDAR.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8DA797A7C684A1E971B57B8AB6AC8FF"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Rejection</header><text>If the Commission rejects a proposed PSDAR or license transfer under subparagraph (C)(i)(II), not later than 2 years after the date of cessation of operations at the applicable covered facility, the licensee shall develop and submit to the Commission a new proposed PSDAR or license transfer in accordance with this section.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H38F7FA3DC9F248BF9797E51431571914"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Deadline for decision document</header>
 <subparagraph id="HD13D8CB75613480EACC99349883C822E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraphs (B) and (C), the Commission shall issue a decision document relating to a proposed PSDAR or license transfer under subparagraph (C) or (D)(i) of paragraph (2) or paragraph (3)(C)(i) by not later than 1 year after the date on which the proposed PSDAR or an application for transfer of a license, as applicable, is submitted to the Commission under subsection c. (1)(A).</text>
								</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E881323A9464331A210492D28981D9A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Proposed intermediate license transfers</header>
 <clause id="HDF9AE61014364EF0AA46C042FF8384F7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definition of proposed intermediate license transfer</header><text>In this subparagraph, the term <term>proposed intermediate license transfer</term> means a proposed transfer of license—</text> <subclause id="HA17FA550FB6E4076B83E61244A98799E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>for a covered facility on behalf of which a proposed PSDAR has been submitted by the licensee to the Commission under subsection c. (1)(A)(i); and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H3B7F6070B9754EA9BCEF5265CE4893AE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the notice of which is submitted to the Commission under subsection c. (1)(A)(ii) before the applicable deadline under subparagraph (A) for the issuance by the Commission of a decision document relating to the proposed PSDAR described in subclause (I).</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="HF21BC85F3E854E2FB2C3A2DF80D4E706"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (C), in any case in which a licensee submits to the Commission a notice of a proposed intermediate license transfer of a covered facility, the Commission shall issue a decision document relating to the proposed PSDAR of the covered facility by not later than 1 year after the date of receipt of the application for transfer of a license.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H98733E60FF69441C9C6EBD595DC26C29"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Extension</header><text>If there are unforeseen circumstances, including unexpected technical issues, site-specific characteristics, or other external factors that could affect the ability of the Commission to issue a decision document by a deadline specified in subparagraph (A) or (B)(ii), the Commission may extend the applicable deadline for a reasonable period of time, as determined by the Commission.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5B7D39437B4646A09A042F536F9EE27D"><enum>f.</enum><header>Additional requirements</header>
 <paragraph id="H154787EE1FA240CBA6AFA2247A053CB8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Action by transferees</header><text>On transfer of a license for a covered facility by a licensee to a transferee in accordance with this section, the transferee shall conduct consultation in accordance with subsection b. with respect to each proposed PSDAR developed by the transferee for the covered facility.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H18C77D1F8D9E4B22905855555E4EB9F8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State environmental law compliance</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this section, the Commission shall not approve a proposed PSDAR or license transfer under this section unless the proposed PSDAR or license transfer for a covered facility includes a requirement that the licensee and the transferee, if applicable, shall comply with applicable State law relating to air, water, or soil quality or radiological standards with respect to the implementation of the proposed PSDAR or license transfer in any case in which the applicable State law is more restrictive than an applicable Federal law.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H891EB8BA5C104D8A944AC94DA81D4968"><enum>g.</enum><header>Application to existing decommissioning activities</header>
 <paragraph id="H21DEB48BAD2D4A9CB38305727A8CDB9F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall notify—</text> <subparagraph id="HC3CEA903A3F040ABBB52BF6071BF8396"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each licensee or transferee, if applicable, of the opportunity to develop and submit to the Commission for approval a revised PSDAR for any covered facility of the licensee for which, as of the date of enactment of this section—</text>
 <clause id="HC8583D85CB1E4252839D9A83FF22D1CE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>decontamination and dismantlement activities described in the PSDAR have not commenced at the covered facility; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H07509681D4F84E808D9F8F82E8BF9653"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>decontamination and dismantlement activities described in the PSDAR have been commenced at the covered facility for a period of less than 5 years; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB87B082486124D12A71D2A030AC29DFC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each affected State with respect to a covered facility described in subparagraph (A) of the opportunity to consult with a licensee or transferee described in that subparagraph in accordance with subsection b.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H722A08BF9F984FD18F49E8522933978B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Process</header>
 <subparagraph id="H315426A0FDE6443BBEA5F0292DB563C6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraphs (3) and (4), if a licensee or transferee described in paragraph (1)(A) elects to submit to the Commission a revised PSDAR under that paragraph, the process for consideration and approval of the revised PSDAR shall be carried out in accordance with—</text>
 <clause id="HE0D18A5B45EF484CA85D052F783CD542"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the process for consideration and approval of a proposed PSDAR for a covered facility under subsections b., c., d., and f.; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1F75AB4291FB4E38B3E9E0DB716FD6BD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the process for support, conditional support, or nonsupport by the host State under subsection e.</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H84E69E8FC756457A90191244E6F37EAE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Nonselection</header><text>If a licensee or transferee described in paragraph (1)(A) elects not to revise an original PSDAR under that paragraph, the host State may file a statement of support, conditional support, or nonsupport for the original PSDAR in accordance with the process for support, conditional support, or nonsupport by a host State under subsection e.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HACD4B9AD78EE41EBB5E83FFA82296D09"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Decision document</header><text>A decision document for a revised PSDAR submitted under paragraph (1)(A), or for an original PSDAR in any case in which the licensee or transferee elects not to revise the original PSDAR, shall be issued in accordance with subparagraph (C) or (D)(I) of subsection e. (2) or subsection e. (3)(C), as applicable, except that the Commission shall issue the decision document by the date that is 1 year after the date on which the applicable decontamination and dismantlement activities commence at the applicable covered facility.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC3D63A6425A94DFD8078276B015931FA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Revision after determination of inadequacy</header><text>If the Commission rejects a revised PSDAR submitted by a licensee or transferee under paragraph (1)(A) in accordance with subsection e. (2)(D) or subsection e. (3)(E), the licensee or transferee shall develop and submit to the Commission a new revised PSDAR in accordance with this subsection by not later than 2 years after the date of the rejection.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H1DD98AA1AC1F469F85F4A5BE070373D4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header>
 <paragraph id="H099EB0836AF14FB68FE86F97F2B19CF4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Atomic Energy Act of 1954 is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H690F1410EF174C8D8937DE51C9F8C607"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 103 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2133">42 U.S.C. 2133</external-xref>)—</text>
 <clause id="HB8BBBB2D29D145F99F49EF331D404BBC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection d., in the second sentence, by striking <quote>any any</quote> and inserting <quote>any</quote>; and</text> </clause><clause id="HC2A0BC7672D64DB6AC47B53F6E700C04"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection f. as subsection e.; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A1A2BEAF3B1407C89EB0AB3C6EB269A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 111 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2141">42 U.S.C. 2141</external-xref>), by striking the section designation and all that follows through <quote>The Nuclear</quote> in subsection a. and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDB31CBC20151447398917E41E179BE13" style="OLC"> <section id="HC4A9AABA98A94A92B94F4067D0A9EA40"><enum>111.</enum><header>Licensing by Nuclear Regulatory Commission of distribution of certain materials by Department of Energy</header> <subsection id="H758ADA2195F24117BC0873BD82A9F8A1"><enum>a.</enum><text>The Nuclear</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C9B080F7649414DA0DEA0C685D78B30"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (68 Stat. 919; 126 Stat. 2216) is amended by striking the items relating to chapter 10 of title I and inserting the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H38E20A0243214BFC8BFF40ADECBB2291" style="OLC">
						<toc>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="chapter">Chapter 10. Atomic energy licenses</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 101. License required.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 102. Utilization and production facilities for industrial or commercial purposes.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 103. Commercial licenses.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 104. Medical therapy and research and development.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 105. Antitrust provisions.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 106. Classes of facilities.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 107. Operators' licenses.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 108. War or national emergency.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 109. Component and other parts of facilities.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 110. Exclusions.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 111. Licensing by Nuclear Regulatory Commission of distribution of certain materials by
			 Department of Energy.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 112. Domestic medical isotope production.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 113. Post-shutdown decommissioning activities reports.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


