<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H1AE288F7205F47CB93A9AE51501709B2" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5308 IH: Women’s History and Nineteenth Amendment Centennial Quarter Dollar Coin Program Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5308</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180315">March 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="P000611">Mr. Poliquin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 31, United States Code, to require the Secretary of the Treasury to mint and issue
			 quarter dollars in commemoration of the Nineteenth Amendment, and for
			 other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H4AC8705437434FE18254D77B03D25760" style="OLC">
 <section id="HEC86307B987644258065D8B943E92606" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Women’s History and Nineteenth Amendment Centennial Quarter Dollar Coin Program Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H66C53E18251B42FF80D19D6742CC4656"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HBF08F6ED60084210AAC689C1ECB01132"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The tireless and passionate efforts of the suffragists, their supporters, and other stakeholders contributed to the movement to grant and protect the right of all women to vote.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H974524D5404949F29AFC50BA960AD21F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On August 26, 1920, after a long campaign by suffragists across the country, the United States Constitution was amended with the 19th Amendment, granting women the right to vote.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFF712EC026E24C7B80F0E98879C50E83"><enum>(3)</enum><text>On June 24, 1924, all Native Americans were granted citizenship, and by extension the right to vote.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3DB920E4681841F99B290AFD049F80F3"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 1948, the legal victories of Native American veterans granted protections for the right of all Native men and women to vote.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA29E602E4D7241C78CC35FA5BB3F1543"><enum>(5)</enum><text>On June 27, 1952, the Immigration and Nationality Act of 1952 was enacted, granting citizenship to all individuals of Asian descent, and by extension, the right to vote.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD01266568C73486AAF10DDDBEBED7678"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Enactment of the Voting Rights Act of 1965 on August 6, 1965, granted Black women protections to overcome the legal barriers that prevented many from exercising their right to vote even though all Blacks had been granted citizenship in 1868 with ratification of the 14th Amendment.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H03135F7DEA3C4110AFCE914EE973E2D5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>On August 6, 1975, the amendments to the reauthorization of the Voting Rights Act of 1965 removed language barriers to mitigate discrimination against Hispanic, Asian, and Native American voters.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE0948069776644A9A745D754DCD773AE"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It was not until March 29, 1961, when the 23rd Amendment passed that women in Washington, DC, were allowed to vote in all elections.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7A5BC70AEA4A412F824F9E9292679183"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Women’s history and the movement for women’s rights that the suffragists began extends beyond ratification of the Nineteenth Amendment.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H91F2F3D4664940929E603CABE0149980"><enum>(10)</enum><text>August 26, 2020, marks the centennial of the day that women were granted the right to vote in America.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H1B354A6A8CAF477DA886F586119E041E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Issuance of coins commemorating the Nineteenth Amendment</header>
 <subsection id="H3608093DE0184B0E968D4422E9C9F94D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment to national sites quarter dollar program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (t) of section 5112 of title 31, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HA17D5F95D95D4407A6920812027BAFD7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A), by striking <quote>Notwithstanding the fourth sentence of subsection (d)(1) and subsection (d)(2)</quote> and inserting <quote>Subject to paragraph (8), and notwithstanding the fourth sentence of subsection (d)(1) and subsection (d)(2)</quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA17273488BB64951B29BB4B2696DDB37"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (7) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H96803980035041D98C9E0FB423602556" style="USC"> <paragraph id="H3A6EEBFF83E14F62886C18A60D04D065"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Period of issuance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to paragraph (2), the program established under this subsection shall continue in effect until a national site in each State has been honored and shall terminate not later than March 31, 2021.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H064C3C2BFA3B48E99962DC64F4EEC3C8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (8) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H445BA27717D04895A8C32085E2A8A580" style="USC"> <paragraph id="HE79497AD87174BBB9B6DF6E8E7628A0D"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Designs starting on January 1, 2021</header> <subparagraph id="H73C47249DB9447618FD77FA09026678F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Transition period</header><text>The design of the quarter dollar from January 1, 2021, to March 31, 2021, shall be as follows:</text>
 <clause id="H00EA85E257AD4178A20276949C2B8C04"><enum>(i)</enum><text>On January 1, 2021, the design shall be the final design of the national sites program established by this subsection.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1DEE36C96A7B4F3181C55CC2FBDF6F00"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>On a date selected by the Secretary that is not earlier than January 15, 2021, and not later than March 31, 2021, the design shall be the first design selected pursuant to the program described in subsection (w).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1B521EE07864A899A45864B41BB6523"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Design after end of program</header><text>As of April 1, 2021, the design of the quarter dollar shall be in accordance with subsection (w).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8A011ABF5BB44954B1692AF6BAF85742"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Issuance of coins commemorating the Nineteenth Amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 5112 of title 31, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4BE2E5DB3A444709929D884D23FA0BAD" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H1FC4E40C0B334A46A083CCB38BDA356B"><enum>(w)</enum><header>Redesign and issuance of quarter dollars commemorating the ratification of the Nineteenth Amendment</header>
 <paragraph id="H2CBA243DF3B1401E87F3D0E231E0A4EC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Redesign beginning in 2021</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding the fourth sentence of subsection (d)(1) and subsection (d)(2), quarter dollars issued during the period beginning on the date described in subsection (t)(8)(A)(ii) and ending on the date described in paragraph (8) shall have designs on the reverse selected in accordance with this subsection.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H4BF2E16CF6FC4ECA9E380FCF88BBE124"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Nineteenth Amendment quarter dollar design requirements</header>
 <subparagraph id="H7B4718FB57EE4B4EB9110FA22B2ED6F4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Flexibility with regard to placement of inscriptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subsection (d)(1), the Secretary may select a design for quarter dollars described in paragraph (1) in which—</text>
 <clause id="H77C2B8B9EC99485C832F6D955B87760E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the inscription described in the second sentence of subsection (d)(1) appears on the reverse side of any such quarter dollars; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H9073F889FE0148A0B10E85B357F34355"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any inscription described in the third sentence of subsection (d)(1) or the designation of the value of the coin appears on the obverse side of any such quarter dollars.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93B74E80BEC641CCAA87CAB1E1ACB513"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Single prominent American woman</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subsection (d)(1), the design on the reverse of each coin issued under this subsection shall—</text>
 <clause id="H131901625CA9461FA6BBCD1005D950CD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be emblematic of the accomplishments and contributions of a prominent woman who was a resident of a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HDA7774443B7D42B186C776D24D80474A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>bear the name of the prominent woman and the State, District of Columbia, or territory; and</text> </clause><clause id="H24DA445C56AE4FC2B25B87309A22F50A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>bear other appropriate inscriptions.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBAA49EC6B5B643A49FB5AC3808C9AE90"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Issuance of coins during each year</header>
 <subparagraph id="HED24A4351E8344E2A152E2397EF5E56B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The designs for the quarter dollar coins issued during each year of the period referred to in paragraph (1) shall be emblematic of a maximum of 5 States, the District of Columbia, or territories.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H636C6771892E4CDE840966FD26EBBC79"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Order of issuance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The quarter dollar coins issued during each year of the period referred to in paragraph (1) shall be issued in alphabetical order of the area represented, starting with Alabama.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2D2B8E426DE4EC882A84464251D3D80"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Number of each of coin designs in each year</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall prescribe the number of quarter dollars which shall be issued with each of the designs selected for each year.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA387F2D39AB45649480A0DDE2064B5B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Selection of design</header>
 <subparagraph id="H90EBDBDAD98F47C191C7E70B1AFDED36"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each of the designs required under this subsection for quarter dollar coins shall—</text> <clause id="H19CAD21DFE284C979D24541A49A938DB"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be approved by the Secretary after—</text>
 <subclause id="HA513A6F65CC14FD0B94DFC2594CD140F"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submission of a recommendation from the chief executive of the applicable State, the District of Columbia, or territory being commemorated;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HE857B7346A264BF69E6455883B4DF837"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consultation with women’s groups and organizations within the applicable State, the District of Columbia, or territory being commemorated that are pursuing a mission focused on increasing the inclusion of women, or improving the quality of life for women; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H9C7436DDBDDF453AB54D4178F92E6C95"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consultation with the Commission of Fine Arts;</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="H73C7517446DF4E81B78AFF00E0905157"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be reviewed by the Citizens Coinage Advisory Committee; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H0B3CB71767AE4675A4F13185895EE011"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">honor or commemorate a woman who has made significant contributions to the lives of individuals of the applicable State, the District of Columbia, or territory.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF5EA3455254E42B8BABC647D091F53DB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Selection and approval process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Designs for quarter dollars may be submitted in accordance with the design selection and approval process developed by the Secretary.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42A5D3A0BBB2431EB5B43E9CC946A25A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Participation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall include in design selection, to the greatest extent practicable, participation by—</text>
 <clause id="H46B539023BD24E66891FE5EEC6C698C2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the chief executive of the applicable State, District of Columbia, or territory;</text> </clause><clause id="H50BC28732E3443A7A341E9C2C41D772E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>artists from the States, District of Columbia, and territories;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H59257608C30A45CDA904EF5DE0C9D943"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>engravers of the United States Mint; and</text> </clause><clause id="H131E6AFB9D154496B3E6663666D97B39"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>members of the general public from groups or organizations that are pursuing a mission focused on increasing the inclusion of women or improving the quality of life for women.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H584C4FD5019841809690AF761BE858A2"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Because it is important that the Nation’s coinage and currency bear dignified designs of which the citizens of the United States can be proud, the Secretary shall not select any frivolous or inappropriate design for any coin minted under this subsection.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8397E447292B43C589C8FCA490CB7254"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Prohibition on certain representations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The design of any quarter dollar under this subsection may not include—</text> <clause id="HA41AB2C5D0A94718A585485F4BA299FD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a head and shoulders portrait or bust of any person, living or dead;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HE55A7AC26301404FA16C0336AFC13A45"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a portrait of a living person; or</text> </clause><clause id="H47E5C42A95BB42B0A56A14356A9CA348"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a depiction of an individual in a size such that the coin could be considered to be a <quote>2-headed</quote> coin.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE38D13184E7B48AE9A8EFB8D02423C4B"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Release of designs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than August 31, 2020, the Secretary shall publish each of the first 5 designs described in subparagraph (A).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8E51498F618040318E100D62B0527846"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Treatment as numismatic items</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of sections 5134 and 5136, all coins described under this subsection shall be considered to be numismatic items.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="HF23B1559E9EB4D68AC061BCD7A8D346F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Issuance</header>
 <subparagraph id="H2AE732070DF247378A34A0EAA48077AE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Quality of coins</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may mint and issue such number of quarter dollars of each design selected under paragraph (4) in uncirculated and proof qualities as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77C2B62EC5034B35859D6226FBAF5E61"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Silver coins</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subsection (b), the Secretary may mint and issue such number of quarter dollars of each design selected under paragraph (4) as the Secretary determines to be appropriate, with a content of not less than 90 percent silver.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7F5F48960894505B0CEBDE177D529FF"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Application in event of the admission of additional State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If any additional State is admitted into the Union before the termination date described in paragraph (8), the Secretary may issue quarter dollar coins, in accordance with this subsection, with a design which is emblematic of such State during any 1 year of the period described in paragraph (1), in addition to the quarter dollar coins issued during such year in accordance with paragraph (3)(A).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCBDFFDB6AE464C5EA04F04687F5A3C59"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Termination date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authority to issue quarter dollar coins pursuant to this subsection shall terminate on December 31 of the year in which the final State or territory has been commemorated with a design pursuant to paragraph (3).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0F9CF841CF9B4D7B92BF4A59B6F1F646"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Designs after end of program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On the first day of the year following the year of the date described in paragraph (8)—</text> <subparagraph id="HEE67ABD54A3B46A8B8500CA290DD37B3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the design on the obverse of the quarter dollar shall revert to the same design containing an image of President Washington in effect for the quarter dollar before the institution of the 50-State quarter dollar program; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H34F827F041FB413696D7C9416DFB6F00"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">notwithstanding the fourth sentence of subsection (d)(1), the design on the reverse of the quarter dollar shall contain an image of General Washington crossing the Delaware River prior to the Battle of Trenton.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H96EED657A7C4450FB5E78A140242D84F"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection:</text> <subparagraph id="HBA331C3504564B09AFEFF1CBB108EB90"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <quote>territory</quote> means the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, Guam, American Samoa, the United States Virgin Islands, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9CD0FC4FE8C641A4B126419E72B7C97B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <quote>resident</quote>, with respect to a State, the District of Columbia, or a territory, means that a woman resided in such State, the District of Columbia, or such territory for a period of at least 1 consecutive year.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2B1F31B74EA147F5BC5A37A53B64B18E"><enum>(x)</enum><header>Silver bullion investment product</header>
 <paragraph id="H7454CBF5D7F64264BE6A711AFB126329"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall strike and make available for sale such number of bullion coins as the Secretary determines to be appropriate that are exact duplicates of the quarter dollars issued under subsection (w), each of which shall—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H67BA822EA9BA43C9B8646B99C1D64CD9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>have a diameter of 3.0 inches and weigh 5.0 ounces;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8DC37B01F0984EFF9F8E2B8864911DC5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>contain .999 fine silver;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B0E2F3D81C94A5192369AD10DAE7B2D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>have incused into the edge the fineness and weight of the bullion coin;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE965A23B5BDB4AF18D86B72F5381F5DF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>bear an inscription of the denomination of such coin, which shall be <quote>quarter dollar</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0F4CDC1206545308BB4D23520673C61"><enum>(E)</enum><text>not be minted or issued by the United States Mint as so-called <quote>fractional</quote> bullion coins or in any size other than the size described in subparagraph (A).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFABA4B4FA4504D93954A4BAE49DE27B1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability for sale</header><text>Bullion coins minted under paragraph (1)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE0BF7B448DC84C1DB058A820D0BF9481"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall become available for sale no sooner than the first day of the calendar year in which the circulating quarter dollar coins of which such bullion coins are a duplicate are issued; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20C65116A61149078A877FAE13F987B2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may only be available for sale during the year in which such circulating quarter dollar coins are issued.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section><section id="HC49F39BE13B74FFEB957C607A3571FBD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Collection and Recognition Program</header>
 <subsection id="HB1CAC008DADA46CFA24398FC66C34D6D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than December 1, 2018, the Secretary of the Treasury shall initiate a program to promote the collection of, and recognition of the subjects of, the coins authorized under the amendments made by this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H62110189E51E4551B07D4017CE694786"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study required</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct a study on the progress of the program described in subsection (a).</text> </subsection><subsection id="HC174CB49E09E451B947ED8DD45DCF5B0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than March 1, 2019, the Secretary shall submit a report to the Congress on the results of the study conducted pursuant to subsection (b).</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


