<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H575DFE7896CB418E915CD05B89C7A768" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4878 IH: Federal Labor-Management Partnership Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4878</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180125">January 25, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000984">Mr. Cummings</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="Y000033">Mr. Young of Alaska</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Federal Labor-Management Partnership Council, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H0B0E00AA41AE443ABF91A0FF7A37B934" style="OLC">
 <section id="HD33237DBE968459A8BFDFA40ED6F46CC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Labor-Management Partnership Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H56FDEDBB1AF1478EA61A6CA0AE449E66"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of Federal Labor-Management Partnership Council</header> <subsection id="H73E5A5DC4F4D4819A3E8967AB3CC4697"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/71">chapter 71</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H842748629D73478AAD7B30505C4AD646" style="USC">
					<section id="H3D26B7B9052D4DB888ECC6111593DAB8"><enum>7107.</enum><header>Federal Labor-Management Partnership Council</header>
 <subsection id="H26F5672019F34983A7F7B3F51115C9FF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established a council to be known as the <quote>Federal Labor-Management Partnership Council</quote> (referred to in this section as the <term>Council</term>).</text> </subsection><subsection id="HB86D02DFDA1B4A118668CE483C1DE2E8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Council shall be composed of—</text>
 <paragraph id="HC90CB0E9293A4819BD48110A436A89E0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Director of the Office of Personnel Management;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HFFAAA96F647B47A4BB1CB8CC86DCE471"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Deputy Director for Management of the Office of Management and Budget;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H891443FC94294727BAD011DE6B669770"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a deputy secretary (or other officer with agency-wide authority) from each of 2 agencies not otherwise represented on the Council, who shall be appointed by the President;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE69B15872B1C42268AD861A389EEDE4E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Chairman of the Federal Labor Relations Authority;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE0519441D2734A4896E2B58C42EEB208"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Director of the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H00D9618789BC4F7E9AA0CA4650A9B50D"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">2 members who shall be appointed by the President to represent the respective labor organizations representing (as exclusive representatives) the first and second largest numbers of employees subject to this chapter or any other authority permitting employees to select an exclusive representative;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H5614C714876243B78FF6B0DA65754E9E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>4 members who shall be appointed by the President to represent labor organizations representing (as exclusive representatives) substantial numbers of employees subject to this chapter or any other authority permitting employees to select an exclusive representative—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H0BFE5931C6E54992B1896A3C5A880DAC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each of whom shall be selected giving due consideration to such factors as the relative numbers of employees represented by the various organizations; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H8F3B0D6E0C244A73A77C3DD824D022F7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not more than two of whom may, at any time, be representatives of the same labor organization or council, federation, alliance, association, or affiliation of labor organizations;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HFC98A4DEB549440499309701F6A993ED"><enum>(8)</enum><text>1 member who shall be appointed by the President to represent the organization representing the largest number of senior executives (as that term is defined in section 3132(a)(3)); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0E1148C511E741EEBCA0BCA11999BB58"><enum>(9)</enum><text>1 member who shall be appointed by the President to represent the organization representing the largest number of management officials.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1B342A8BA7E64EC495B04035A0901A46"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Responsibilities and functions</header><text>The Council shall—</text> <paragraph id="HD33479C6C991442EBFBE9D30C271D754"><enum>(1)</enum><text>advise the President on matters involving labor-management relations in the executive branch;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8BEAB391844E460D81AF5E836177D090"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support the creation of local labor-management partnership councils that promote partnership efforts in the executive branch;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF7BF45B25FEA47F8A793466B43955EDE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>collect and disseminate information about and provide guidance on partnership efforts in the executive branch, including the results of those efforts; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H305AE7569B3E4341912721011AB11C81"><enum>(4)</enum><text>use the expertise of individuals, both inside and outside the Federal Government, to foster partnership arrangements in the executive branch.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4CF769DE1AF343F5864F624F65EC1A00"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Administration</header>
 <paragraph id="H1F71A0AD8F554AFD9BEC881726B1FAC4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Co-chairs</header><text>The Director of the Office of Personnel Management and the Deputy Director for Management of the Office of Management and Budget shall serve as co-chairs of the Council.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF642F41164E4453F8845EC9532586ACA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Council shall meet quarterly and at the call of the co-chairs or a majority of the members of the Council.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDFE51B51D3BE44CABD38C9430F7FB53A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Outside input</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Council—</text> <subparagraph id="HC54AF59095024BA9AA6E468C9E8C1315"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall seek input from agencies not represented on the Council, particularly smaller agencies;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6E53BB58F9A4C9F903805815F78DB07"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may from time to time, in the discretion of the Council, invite experts from the private and public sectors to submit information; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF69C7E2970DA4C8CA70424907D4CE9A0"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall seek input from companies, nonprofit organizations, State and local governments, employees, and customers of Federal services, as needed.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2C637FFE04947CDBEF838EA0367FFDE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Assistance of the Office of Personnel Management</header><text>To the extent permitted by law and subject to the availability of appropriations, the Director of the Office of Personnel Management shall, upon request, provide such staff, facilities, support, and administrative services to the Council as the Director considers appropriate.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE475CF5144A84371A2DE81A40EFB510A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>No compensation</header><text>Members of the Council shall serve without compensation for their work on the Council.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H57C8555E35DA4F9B9185C8FE10F04C7A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Cooperation of other agencies</header><text>Each agency shall, to the extent permitted by law, provide to the Council such assistance, information, and advice as the Council may request.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0846CFC8E28A4C98B827976A1E91BAB9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>General provisions</header>
 <paragraph id="HD44C7214EDD94D4094357B72F0AF8CAD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reporting to Congress</header><text>Any reporting to or appearances before Congress that may be requested or required of the Council shall be made by a co-chair of the Council.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HB9720D110CD9454C9E5312885379B3F1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Terms of membership</header><text>A member appointed under paragraph (3), (6), (7), (8), or (9) of subsection (b) shall be appointed for a term of 3 years, except that any individual chosen to fill a vacancy under any of those paragraphs shall be—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HF1BAA0FE53B1466CA8D48802F05B50C1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>appointed for the unexpired term of the member replaced; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H23593987B3AB4117A2EF171F39541B1F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>chosen subject to the same conditions as applied with respect to the original appointment.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H88838B2691F347FD8B4671CDC02CF82E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Service after expiration of term</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A member appointed under paragraph (3), (6), (7), (8), or (9) of subsection (b) may serve after the expiration of that member’s term until a successor has taken office, but for not more than 60 days after the term expires.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HEAB7F6DE113E471192003C94BEEB3077"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Not special Government employees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A member who is not otherwise an employee shall not be considered a special Government employee for any purpose.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HD5D3307CB3514D94A413CB7133FBFC14"><enum>(5)</enum><header>No termination</header><text>Section 14(a)(2) of the Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.) shall not apply to the Council.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA753B2C77F1F4F579AD8B9A1A9A09676"><enum>7108.</enum><header>Implementation of labor-management partnerships throughout the executive branch</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The head of each agency that is subject to this chapter or any other authority permitting employees of the agency to select an exclusive representative shall take the following actions:</text>
 <paragraph id="H469635B206604A29A937E8470E853F0B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Create labor-management partnerships by forming labor-management committees or councils at appropriate levels, or adapting existing committees or councils if such groups exist.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H826BAE2983194131B35BF0792DE5C6B1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Involve employees and employee representatives as full partners with management representatives to improve the civil service to better serve the public and carry out the mission of the agency.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFA1EEBE89E2B461C81B3ABA7F2110C43"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Provide systemic training of appropriate agency employees (including line managers, first-line supervisors, and labor organization representatives) in consensual methods of dispute resolution, such as alternative dispute resolution techniques and interest-based bargaining approaches.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H5E6C6BD349BB44C8B3F89D32A381857B"><enum>(4)</enum>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H89F79384BDA2402D8DD8796E155B43B7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Allow employees and employee representatives to have pre-decisional involvement in all workplace matters to the fullest extent practicable, without regard to whether those matters are negotiable subjects of bargaining under section 7106.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD0A21A13AED4802A884D4C87F258CA5" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Provide adequate information on the matters described in subparagraph (A) expeditiously to employee representatives where not prohibited by law.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23BEAFEC5FB34A36A3C57F31892E4B01" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Make a good-faith attempt to resolve issues concerning proposed changes in conditions of employment, including those involving the subjects set forth in section 7106(b)(1), through discussions in the labor-management committees or councils established or adapted by the agency under paragraph (1) of this section.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB852A84C6C514F5FB21266B5AAC50147"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Evaluate progress and improvements in organizational performance resulting from the labor-management partnerships described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H69FF58638DA341BEAF0DEF3D18A3D956"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/71">chapter 71</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/7106">section 7106</external-xref> the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCEFB1ECEE3924E50882DCC6F41FEC178" style="OLC">
					<toc>
						<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">7107. Federal Labor-Management Partnership Council.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry bold="off" level="section">7108. Implementation of labor-management partnerships throughout the executive branch.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


