<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9D7C3027128F4E299104FC573327C6E2" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4804 IH: Continuation on Active Service Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4804</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180116">January 16, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000559">Mr. Langevin</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000604">Mr. Russell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000210">Mr. King of New York</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001037">Mr. Capuano</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 5, United States Code, to allow injured Federal law enforcement officers to continue
			 to serve their agencies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HBE10952D708B42CAB8EDD7F840E5BC79" style="OLC">
 <section id="H3AC5E902393445768CA28D15B2FF079C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Continuation on Active Service Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H0D589CDD07D84F09BD88B61D07796139"><enum>2.</enum><header>Continued service of injured federal law enforcement officers</header> <subsection id="HA5623A80E45C434FA8D2EEF3AA1045EB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/33">Chapter 33</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H48ADBD4B0D234F3EAC9EF6E85FBDEDFD" style="USC">
					<section id="HE7D50609EFEE487AAFE99EE4419B2C06"><enum>3330f.</enum><header>Law enforcement officers; continued service after injury</header>
 <subsection id="H5408ACB6F7C940E18F1A4482163EF29D"><enum>(a)</enum><text>An agency may waive any medical standards or physical requirements applicable to a position occupied by a law enforcement officer if the officer suffers a qualifying injury.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE0D335D197684AE2BD284DB9EC06F3CA"><enum>(b)</enum><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the employing agency—</text> <paragraph id="H892B49EEF30C43EEA1FE204693FEA180"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may utilize a medical review board as established under the authority granted by this title;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7D1705B9C911494DB756F8679F79D4BF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may assign the officer duties that take the qualifying injury into account;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HBC0221523DE3466082F671462351E30C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>may not reduce the general schedule pay scale of the injured law enforcement officer who returns to work full-time after the incidence of injury even if the duties are adjusted; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8E2F12448BB34B99A872FF6E4219C0C6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>shall take into account the health and safety of the officer and others.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H654EC3AECF3143B9A77FEEC396F194A6"><enum>(c)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Office of Personnel Management shall promulgate regulations to carry out this section. Such regulations shall provide consistent application of this section, to the greatest extent practicable, in each employing agency.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H35C1F5CA6A2C47F28CDC9CED1EA9985E"><enum>(d)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A law enforcement officer who receives a waiver under this section shall be subject to the retirement benefits provisions under chapter 83 or 84 that would otherwise apply to the officer had the officer not suffered a qualifying injury.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE5F1B22D9D424332ACCD31AF62C6DDFB"><enum>(e)</enum><text>In this section—</text> <paragraph id="H62A5BC0119C64DC2B1DBCAE27A3E5E05"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>law enforcement officer</quote> has the meaning given such term in sections 8331(20) and 8401(17), and includes any member of the Capitol Police, the Supreme Court Police, or the United States Secret Service Uniformed Division; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1EDF56ED92434A57B5E90D46463CC93D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>qualifying injury</quote> means an injury—</text> <subparagraph id="H9315ECC23C2044078124118FD7D3D342"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that results in the officer being unable to meet the medical standards or physical requirements otherwise required to occupy the applicable law enforcement position; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03705E5CE57647728ECF862C56C24B38"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is not due to misconduct, willful negligence, or incurred during an unauthorized absence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection><subsection id="H234C89782CBB42BCAD1D45C0314D479D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections of such chapter is amended by adding after the item relating to section 3330e the following new item:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H4B99AB91134641AABD115AE294E7048A" style="USC">
					<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
						<toc-entry level="section">3330f. Law enforcement officers; continued service after injury.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H83130B79422342729112952975310896"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Retroactive application permissible</header>
 <paragraph id="H422E3A17CA09461A84488DB370728581"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The authority provided by section 3330f of title 5, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), may be applied to any law enforcement officer who, before the date of enactment of this Act, suffered a qualifying injury (as that term is defined in such section).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE2B084AC8DD04E6FB25048E8BB47CFFD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>An agency head shall submit a report to Congress with respect to each instance that the authority provided in paragraph (1) is exercised.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


