<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H49B2B25C54C24EC282DB9528AFE3F5D6" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4884 IH: Defending Elections from Threats by Establishing Redlines Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4884</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180125">January 25, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000435">Ms. Ros-Lehtinen</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence (Permanent Select)</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To deter foreign interference in United States elections, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H35FA65DACF454C99A6A29788170EF2C3" style="OLC">
		<section id="HDF31BBEC98CC4D3CB7351B4A8B4891E5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header>
 <subsection id="HE2D5A4FB55C940978C5A83340D78236D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Defending Elections from Threats by Establishing Redlines Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H2DFA472E4B604E43A2E3C95FAEFB32AF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
				<toc>
					<toc-entry idref="HDF31BBEC98CC4D3CB7351B4A8B4891E5" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H3C8A24DF982E4BF0BADC5833F2E33CE2" level="section">Sec. 2. Definitions.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H6111B21AFFD746B5A33CC8264B7BA593" level="title">TITLE I—Determination of foreign interference in United States elections</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HF2380F4BCCE8459ABFF19E3A00F7A50C" level="section">Sec. 101. Determination of foreign interference in United States elections.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HCF3B6D0626FB4043A070A3AD196CE699" level="title">TITLE II—Deterring interference in United States elections by the Russian Federation</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H1675D7D79C6740BBB36ADCF7586EAA17" level="section">Sec. 201. Imposition of sanctions.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H870872F9C54B48D4A2BBD392298435D6" level="section">Sec. 202. Sense of Congress on coordination with European Union.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H1CB1D1AD86E443C89396E617F6890244" level="title">TITLE III—Deterring interference in United States elections by other foreign governments</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H873A91744EC3475D9744B81190BD3C6E" level="section">Sec. 301. Briefing on interference in United States elections.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HD91ADE78AEAC4141A8A64338E5D87717" level="section">Sec. 302. Sense of Congress on deterrence strategies for interference in United States elections by
			 China, Iran, North Korea, and other foreign governments of concern.</toc-entry></toc>
 </subsection></section><section id="H3C8A24DF982E4BF0BADC5833F2E33CE2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HAF99503B35304C228308646B981F7472"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Account; correspondent account; payable-through account</header><text>The terms <term>account</term>, <term>correspondent account</term>, and <term>payable-through account</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 5318A of title 31, United States Code.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HED1E1015DB704C8999F95A5CB2EE7C91"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H990C2A58DEC2413F88D3CD628A0309BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Finance, the Select Committee on Intelligence, and the Committee on Rules and Administration of the Senate; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H498CE772CEFB469DAE00668422DC192F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Financial Services, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Ways and Means, the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence, and the Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8EF65BBEA82640CE8D8517F65518CA90"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees and leadership</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees and leadership</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HEDC5F564C30943D6824D35FF3B1C06E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the appropriate congressional committees;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C6FD0DF5F9E4376B62CB5E7937448D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the majority leader and minority leader of the Senate; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37160530C9634A1BBF5B686053A15CB6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Speaker, the majority leader, and the minority leader of the House of Representatives.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HB0A0E8DDA47D4464AFE33C4F9B4BFA1D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Election and campaign infrastructure</header><text>The term <term>election and campaign infrastructure</term> means information and communications technology and systems used by or on behalf of—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HE85757D800DC4FBD92BACD1B709E75C8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Federal Government or a State or local government in managing the election process, including voter registration databases, voting machines, voting tabulation equipment, equipment for the secure transmission of election results, and other systems; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3420B05D81674DC38E819A265D35AE44"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a principal campaign committee or national committee (as those terms are defined in section 301 of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/30101">52 U.S.C. 30101</external-xref>)) with respect to strategy or tactics affecting the conduct of a political campaign, including electronic communications, and the information stored on, processed by, or transiting such technology and systems.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H809C9C314B074EB59FB3382C19519AA7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Interference in United States elections</header><text>The term <term>interference</term>, with respect to a United States election, means any of the following actions of the government of a foreign country, or any person acting as an agent of or on behalf of such a government, undertaken with the intent to influence the election:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H326BA336FC8B4E05ABA5074CDD9CECF9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Obtaining unauthorized access to election and campaign infrastructure or related systems or data and releasing such data or modifying such infrastructure, systems, or data.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H987B3E7DE33A4E84B62540001FC39634"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Blocking or degrading otherwise legitimate and authorized access to election and campaign infrastructure or related systems or data.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED71CD3E296C4779AA5AB9C776CC05AD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Contributions or expenditures for advertising, including on the internet.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59278CAB86444CD7B22F6C830152457B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Using social or traditional media to spread significant amounts of false information to individuals in the United States.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D722E0735E64C05BFCC3B12D3D66788"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Knowingly</header><text>The term <term>knowingly</term>, with respect to conduct, a circumstance, or a result, means that a person has actual knowledge, or should have known, of the conduct, the circumstance, or the result.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H11DDDC828CF640259D5D32DA8EC400F5"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Person</header><text>The term <term>person</term> means an individual or entity.</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H4DD99B0DFB08445AAB34AAE38AD533C3"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Presidential election cycle</header><text>The term <term>presidential election cycle</term> means the period beginning on the day after the date of the most recent election for the office of President of the United States and ending on the date of the next election for that office.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE4CCEEECFD4149529D9B10490E75A04C"><enum>(9)</enum><header>United States election</header><text>The term <term>United States election</term> means any United States Federal election.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H2D6BD2D48AA34C5F89DF0E1AE4C42BC0"><enum>(10)</enum><header>United States person</header><text>The term <term>United States person</term> means—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HC2BA29E21058401288C558093ADBA0D7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a United States citizen or an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence to the United States; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4F674B9C43D4D7D9598DB14F8CF7B44"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or of any jurisdiction within the United States, including a foreign branch of such an entity.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section><title id="H6111B21AFFD746B5A33CC8264B7BA593" style="OLC"><enum>I</enum><header>Determination of foreign interference in United States elections</header>
			<section id="HF2380F4BCCE8459ABFF19E3A00F7A50C"><enum>101.</enum><header>Determination of foreign interference in United States elections</header>
 <subsection id="H364978926A07434F88BB86D6DB6C410C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after a United States election, the Director of National Intelligence, in consultation with the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Director of the National Security Agency, and the Director of the Central Intelligence Agency, shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="HA1E05BBCCFD24F1EADCEFDD1A4E0748A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determine whether or not the government of a foreign country, or any person acting as an agent of or on behalf of that government, knowingly engaged in interference in the election; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAD78F8C8ECB74985921B5E42DC9F745B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to the appropriate congressional committees and leadership a report on that determination, including an identification of the government or person that interfered in the election if the Director determines that interference did occur.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD3CF0E01761E4546824CC916A2E35AD7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional reporting</header><text>If the Director of National Intelligence determines and reports under subsection (a) that neither the government of a foreign country nor any person acting as an agent of or on behalf of that government knowingly engaged in interference in a United States election, and the Director subsequently determines that that government, or such a person, did engage in such interference, the Director shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees and leadership a report on the subsequent determination not later than 30 days after making that determination.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H87B25571BA2F43679EE2448F0B595D3C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form of report</header><text>Each report required by subsection (a) or (b) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may include a classified annex.</text>
				</subsection></section></title><title id="HCF3B6D0626FB4043A070A3AD196CE699" style="OLC"><enum>II</enum><header>Deterring interference in United States elections by the Russian Federation</header>
			<section id="H1675D7D79C6740BBB36ADCF7586EAA17"><enum>201.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions</header>
 <subsection id="HD1F31C5C64A34CA8B619179E1D0B83EF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Director of National Intelligence determines under section 101 that the Government of the Russian Federation, or any person acting as an agent of or on behalf of that government, knowingly engaged in interference in a United States election, the President shall, not later than 10 days after such determination is made, impose the following sanctions:</text>
					<paragraph id="H752418C51C484186ABD07246BAE0EF1E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Blocking the assets of certain state-owned Russian financial institutions and restricting accounts</header>
 <subparagraph id="HD377BF661B7A4E2198A6A4369D9AF0EC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall impose one or more of the following sanctions on three or more entities specified in subparagraph (B):</text>
 <clause id="HFB4C5134A4B840CBBB8C1C987BAE8E32"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Pursuant to the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.), blocking and prohibiting all transactions in all property and interests in property of the entity if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF37846EBB880402FA7A7C5565ADED819"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Prohibiting, or imposing strict conditions on, the opening or maintaining in the United States of a correspondent account or payable-through account by the entity.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE34D72AAEB6742398B9A7B54E6A823CE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Entities specified</header><text>The entities specified in this subparagraph are the following:</text> <clause id="H9DAC39980D4442EB804311AD5F4A4B11"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Sberbank.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H4512EF62EC9245D2A678AB18D1286FDE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>VTB Bank.</text> </clause><clause id="HF4DEA29DBADF46B4B9177C76BEA843DF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Gazprombank.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8A32E61721F447AB87D0AABFC164A48E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Vnesheconombank.</text> </clause><clause id="H0C61EAA41B394A048628FE9A8FAA07DA"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Bank of Moscow.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC502BFF1092D42648C7FDC9F289E7EBE"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Rosselkhozbank.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5307886AC324300958D508FB9967CB0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Blocking the assets of certain Russian energy companies</header> <subparagraph id="H82CB725E1C77481A85748FCDD8E3D524"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall, pursuant to the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.), block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of two or more of the entities specified in subparagraph (B) if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEFC1524DE2DD45AC892DB38C7C7B3590"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Entities specified</header><text>The entities specified in this subparagraph are the following:</text> <clause id="H24CD3A0E6D284272B2212B811994EBF7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Gazprom.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB5DD0C9D68B949AAB81C511771B7BB40"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Rosneft.</text> </clause><clause id="HE637E4649EA44ED0BE6736B6881259DA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Lukoil.</text>
							</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H34AEE0BCE700488396B720B27655ADB6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Blocking the assets of entities in Russian defense and intelligence sectors</header>
 <subparagraph id="H076AA2F312404EF5981FAD3E921F76CE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall, pursuant to the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.), block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of any entity described in subparagraph (B) if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2FE0ACDD6D82463497A79FA294E4D310"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Entities described</header><text>An entity described in this subparagraph is—</text> <clause id="HAF71AC1246B74701B1B6477585273D93"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an entity that the President has determined under section 231 of the Countering Russian Influence in Europe and Eurasia Act of 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/9525">22 U.S.C. 9525</external-xref>) engages in a significant transaction with a person that is part of, or operates for or on behalf of, the defense or intelligence sectors of the Government of the Russian Federation; or</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H79F9FC290FB04FEABB55125112539569"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an entity in which an entity described in clause (i) has an ownership interest of 50 percent or more.</text>
							</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D68B4AFCF4143628C63000CFEA61815"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Blocking the assets of certain Russian state-owned entities</header>
 <subparagraph id="HDF89376E2DD347F1BCAED4CF29F5DA57"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall, pursuant to the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.), block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of any entity described in subparagraph (B) in which the Government of the Russian Federation has an ownership interest of 25 percent or more if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H820D8206B91A445F9FDCF6468406A2E8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Entities described</header><text>The entities described in this subparagraph are the following:</text> <clause id="HE16580076C9B40709CFB5A1AEC6455B3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Any entity in the railway or metals and mining sector of the economy of the Russian Federation.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HE46B93C770DA44FBAE1161D9DC87E189"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Any aerospace company or air carrier, including any subsidiary of such a company or carrier.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E9B4DEE76A344C4B974E165219C6E7A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Blocking the assets of entities acquired by Russian state-owned entities</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall, pursuant to the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.), block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of any entity in which an entity owned 50 percent or more in the aggregate by the Government of the Russian Federation acquires, on or after the date of the enactment of this Act, an ownership interest of 20 percent or more if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6030C7D66FD14A619C3F6B967722EBF7"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Prohibition on transactions involving certain Russian debt</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall, pursuant to such regulations as the Secretary may prescribe, prohibit all transactions within the United States or by a United States person, in—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HFDA2D130C88D4610ADB7E37C17DA39E9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>sovereign debt of the Government of the Russian Federation issued on or after the date of the enactment of this Act, including governmental bonds; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C947CEDBC0C434C91571CC0C5FE4723"><enum>(B)</enum><text>debt of any entity owned or controlled by the Russian Federation issued on or after such date of enactment, including bonds.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6203F7837F75436985ACE6143EF8A88D"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Blocking the assets of senior political figures and oligarchs and exclusion from the United States</header><text>The President shall impose with respect to any senior foreign political figure or oligarch in the Russian Federation described in subsection (a)(1) of section 241 of the Countering Russian Influence in Europe and Eurasia Act of 2017 (title II of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/44">Public Law 115–44</external-xref>; 131 Stat. 922) and identified in the report required by that section the following sanctions:</text>
 <subparagraph id="HC9FF70CC22F442E4A75CD2C40D8B7ABD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Pursuant to the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.), the President shall block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of the individual if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB4F73DEFC24849BCB68D67C6172D5C73"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The President shall deny a visa to, and exclude from the United States, the individual, and revoke in accordance with section 221(i) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1201">8 U.S.C. 1201(i)</external-xref>) any visa or other documentation of the individual.</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0970B46E830F4C43A4D5F81535D7AEC4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header>
 <paragraph id="H138BBDE683EE42D3B4EFB8E58B29D889"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the President shall submit to the committees specified in paragraph (2) a report—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HBB4D99F816FA4521913B54A5B2C15887"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifying the 6 largest financial institutions owned or controlled by the Government of the Russian Federation, determined by estimated net assets;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD269E7568DB84DECB0343C793F15F745"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identifying the 3 largest energy companies in the Russian Federation, in terms of estimated net assets; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H655120580FB2478181FC8E9BE9550114"><enum>(C)</enum><text>recommending entities that should be subject to sanctions pursuant to paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (a), as appropriate.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD40D47A684BB40C888D4DF41B592522C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Committees specified</header><text>The committees specified in this paragraph are—</text> <subparagraph id="H58EB48B579944F21AD5743BC68894359"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D7C2D0848154D9B96DB129BF6EC7ACF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Financial Services and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives.</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA2377A160EBE4CEB92EBFD6BBB93F60D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exceptions</header>
 <paragraph id="H51269BA8C4794EBBA610AD7AA97EF284"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Exception for importation of goods</header><text>The requirement to impose sanctions under subsection (a) shall not include the authority to impose sanctions with respect to the importation of goods (as defined in section 16 of the Export Administration Act of 1979 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4618">50 U.S.C. 4618</external-xref>) (as continued in effect pursuant to the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.))).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9B1D9879CBF4418D95DCFABB6B181FF9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compliance with United Nations Headquarters Agreement</header><text>Subsection (a)(7)(B) shall not apply with respect to the admission of an alien to the United States if such admission is necessary to comply with United States obligations under the Agreement between the United Nations and the United States of America regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, under the Convention on Consular Relations, done at Vienna April 24, 1963, and entered into force March 19, 1967, or under other international agreements.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4B1601669C604684A2889D9C2D9E4E94"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Implementation; penalties</header>
 <paragraph id="H29CDE840A7B843D89E208D0D8A563EB4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The President may exercise all authorities provided under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1702">50 U.S.C. 1702</external-xref> and 1704) to carry out this section.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H68D417572A394B80A07362BA8EB0C956"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>A person that violates, attempts to violate, conspires to violate, or causes a violation of this section or any regulation, license, or order issued to carry out this section shall be subject to the penalties set forth in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) to the same extent as a person that commits an unlawful act described in subsection (a) of that section.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6EC2D2E39A4A42ED8E1E7A19C8C2B5D1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Suspension</header><text>The President may suspend sanctions imposed under subsection (a) on or after the date on which the Director of National Intelligence, in consultation with the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Director of the National Security Agency, and the Director of the Central Intelligence Agency, submits to the appropriate congressional committees and leadership a certification that the Government of the Russian Federation has not engaged in interference in United States elections for at least 2 presidential election cycles.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H27FD94C173194BC3BD94A62D55255157"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The President may terminate sanctions imposed under subsection (a) on or after the date on which the Director of National Intelligence, in consultation with the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Director of the National Security Agency, and the Director of the Central Intelligence Agency, submits to the appropriate congressional committees and leadership a certification that—</text>
 <paragraph id="H63F15722D0874448887C5E15F23E95D3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Government of the Russian Federation has not engaged in interference in United States elections for at least 2 presidential election cycles; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H75D237530142410EA505025A526836C4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the President has received reliable assurances that the Government of the Russian Federation will not engage in such interference in the future.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H870872F9C54B48D4A2BBD392298435D6"><enum>202.</enum><header>Sense of Congress on coordination with European Union</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the United States should—</text> <paragraph id="H228B0C7727E249668D12E7850D02B158"><enum>(1)</enum><text>work in concert with the European Union and member countries of the European Union to deter interference by the Government of the Russian Federation in elections; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD208BDD4D7474F71806F56ED3127C032"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinate with the European Union and member countries of the European Union to enact legislation similar to this Act.</text>
				</paragraph></section></title><title id="H1CB1D1AD86E443C89396E617F6890244" style="OLC"><enum>III</enum><header>Deterring interference in United States elections by other foreign governments</header>
 <section id="H873A91744EC3475D9744B81190BD3C6E"><enum>301.</enum><header>Briefing on interference in United States elections</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 90 days thereafter, the President, or a designee of the President, shall brief the appropriate congressional committees and leadership on any government of a foreign country, or person acting as an agent of or on behalf of that government, that is determined by the President as having engaged in or being likely to engage in interference in a United States election.</text>
			</section><section id="HD91ADE78AEAC4141A8A64338E5D87717"><enum>302.</enum><header>Sense of Congress on deterrence strategies for interference in United States elections by China,
 Iran, North Korea, and other foreign governments of concern</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text> <paragraph id="HD603CD209A7B4A4F8DFF619B0F4E0653"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President should submit to the appropriate congressional committees and leadership a report that includes a strategy of the President to deter interference in a United States election by the Government of the People’s Republic of China, the Government of Iran, the Government of the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea, and any other foreign government determined by the President as having engaged in or being likely to engage in interference in a United States election, including any person acting as an agent of or on behalf of such a government; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDBA47183A5834C5AA01B98996EBC3790"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the report described in paragraph (1) should include—</text> <subparagraph id="H9652BE9C453449BAAD7D219A74D6F578"><enum>(A)</enum><text>proposed sanctions if that government engages in such interference and any authorities the President may require from Congress to impose such sanctions;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6ED4D68B76494ACC8D68D0A771F2D172"><enum>(B)</enum><text>other actions undertaken by Federal agencies or in cooperation with other countries to deter such interference; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB42BFCD2654741C9920AAB1F31437D7D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a plan for communicating such deterrence actions to those governments.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

