<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD217BF3188CD475D878E9983E141196C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5650 IH: Nicole’s Law Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5650</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180427">April 27, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Attorney General to make grants to States that have in place laws that expand the protections offered to victims of sex offenses who are not in a familiar or dating relationship with the perpetrators of such offenses.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H0F63998A5D02483FB1E2A8018FCC044C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H1AC017FCAD044A36A843E9FFF1B40245" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Nicole’s Law Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H82AD1B50B54A491FA0C8EB9D3912DEA4" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The term <term>covered formula grant</term> means a grant under—</text> 
<paragraph id="H74EC8C6DF5C349C892E799C1AD05AB07"><enum>(1)</enum><text>part T of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10441">34 U.S.C. 10441</external-xref> et seq.) (commonly referred to as the <quote>STOP Violence Against Women Formula Grant Program</quote>); or </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H76FC500E6C49425D86B24466C83816BA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>section 41601 of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12511">34 U.S.C. 12511</external-xref>) (commonly referred to as <quote>Sexual Assault Services Program</quote>).</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H4F11A03CF9B14D89BF23B037BD81C4E0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Increased funding for formula grants authorized</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General shall increase the amount provided to a State under the covered formula grants in accordance with this Act if the State has in place laws and policies that ensure that, with respect to criminal cases involving sex offenses (as defined by the State), protections similar to those offered to a victim of domestic violence are extended to a victim of a sex offense who is not in a familial or dating relationship with the perpetrator of such offense, including laws and policies that—</text> <paragraph id="H9A294FC0D4034A30AF616DAC2D4FBCC3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expressly authorize judges and courts to issue, as a condition of bail, parole, probation, or other supervised release, protection orders that prohibit a defendant charged with a sex offense from having any contact with the victim or with the victim's friends, co-workers, or relatives;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD9FB456F78B14A2DA8AB951C23D04937"><enum>(2)</enum><text>permit judges and courts, after finding a defendant guilty of a sex offense, to order a continuation of a protection order described in paragraph (1), or to otherwise restrict a defendant's contact with the victim, as a condition of bail, parole, probation, or other supervised release; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H53DDFCA9A1B147F1A393E7C8393D7500"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide judges and courts with the authority to grant or extend a protection order until further order of a judge or court, as an alternative to issuing protection orders that expire on a specific date or upon termination of a sentence or period of bail, parole, probation, or other supervised release.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HF57E3B1F25154B5DA1AF73E741516B52"><enum>4.</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> A State seeking an increase under this Act in the amount provided to the State under the covered formula grants shall include in the application of the State for each covered formula grant such information as the Attorney General may reasonably require, including information about a law or policy described in section 2.</text></section> <section id="H6C42AF8CF2E246F685D9B40D1AA9E41D"><enum>5.</enum><header>Grant increase</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The amount of the increase provided under this Act to a State under the covered formula grants shall be equal to not more than 10 percent of the average of the total amount of funding provided to the State under the covered formula grants under the 3 most recent awards to the State.</text></section> 
<section id="HA0551223C42A4F63B20C14892089B926"><enum>6.</enum><header>Period of increase</header> 
<subsection id="HB9CC7F69B19842A7B0B08AAB4D703A8D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall provide an increase under this Act in the amount provided to a State under the covered formula grants for a 2-year period.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD30EEAA9EA56448F8F329ADD9C6F447A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General may not provide an increase under this Act in the amount provided to a State under the covered formula grants more than 4 times.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HB1F972735E304D8AB1E56798B717B495"><enum>7.</enum><header>Allocation of increased formula grant funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General shall allocate an increase under this Act in the amount provided to a State under the covered formula grants such that—</text> <paragraph id="H64D5CA1992BE4A82BF3BDD4C7756C4E7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>25 percent the amount of the increase is provided for the program described in section 2(1); and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H018475E0C4DF4EB098D843BE378FB05B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>75 percent the amount of the increase is provided for the program described in section 2(2).</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HB46DAC9916554886A8F3D97025EAC5B0"><enum>8.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023.</text> </section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


