<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H645A41F8D591414B823992C70F07B2D2" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5171 IH: Ski Area Fee Retention Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5171</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180306">March 6, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000470">Mr. Tipton</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster of New Hampshire</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Omnibus Parks and Public Lands Management Act of 1996 to provide for the establishment
			 of a Ski Area Fee Retention Account.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H8924F04842E1435984C62D712AB3438E" style="OLC">
 <section id="H978193D65EBF48E998CCB6AC595B05BB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ski Area Fee Retention Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H8708CFDC13384142B51D8ADD5CB3FDDD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of Ski Area Fee Retention Account</header> <subsection id="H4DE2B1D6D89A46BC8A2974872E460C55"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 701 of division I of the Omnibus Parks and Public Lands Management Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/497c">16 U.S.C. 497c</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H05524361636B47C4B1235816EC0BEF27" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H5AF63B953F2247B784F0B5EB1EE0AA74"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Ski Area Fee Retention Account</header>
 <paragraph id="HE7E0E2A9A28D44519021BDE31590D001"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text> <subparagraph id="H4C1807B4A0C44E0E935C28EC69EF473F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Account</header><text>The term <term>Account</term> means the Ski Area Fee Retention Account established under paragraph (2).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H162C40994178413CA1AF9110E9B2E141"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Covered unit</header><text>The term <term>covered unit</term> means a National Forest which collects a rental charge under this section.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07E53485361E4298B4C036F67792D171"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Region</header><text>The term <term>Region</term> means a Forest Service Region.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04F5933379B54875BB7F5C3F99F3242D"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Rental charge</header><text>The term <term>rental charge</term> means a permit rental charge that is charged under subsection (a).</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1A4F19F28604FB7855D527DCE0C44DF"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Agriculture.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA847E6E6F3B44EE49B894EDE470F6F9F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall establish in the Treasury a special account, to be known as the <quote>Ski Area Fee Retention Account</quote>, into which there shall be deposited—</text> <subparagraph id="H78B77B0B765344E1823DFB81D9844800"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of a covered unit at which not less than $15,000,000 is collected by the covered unit from rental charges in a fiscal year, an amount equal to 50 percent of the rental charges collected at the covered unit in the fiscal year; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF920775663D746AE9C0F3DFE79465743"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of any other covered unit, an amount equal to 65 percent of the rental charges collected at the covered unit in a fiscal year.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H80C5B55F3A2B473B93AA770EE4C21E87"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>Subject to paragraphs (4), (5), and (6), any amounts deposited in the Account under paragraph (2) shall remain available for expenditure, without further appropriation, until expended.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H6D2C75AFBE0A44D9B27845BD245C2415"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Local distribution of amounts in the account</header>
 <subparagraph id="H481696B679D04392A51F7899C99788BC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), 100 percent of the amounts deposited in the Account from a specific covered unit shall remain available for expenditure at the covered unit at which the rental charges were collected.</text>
							</subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEEF82CAA66C6434791499FFFE9043114"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reduction</header>
 <clause id="HBC7451593FF9408FBCE3B74ECAEEF0BC"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to clause (ii), the Secretary may reduce the percentage of amounts available to a covered unit under subparagraph (A) if the Secretary determines that the rental charges collected at the covered unit exceed the reasonable needs of the covered unit for that fiscal year for authorized expenditures described in paragraph (5)(A).</text>
 </clause><clause id="H96CA155E5E0749F9B61B8FC65139F3C1"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The Secretary may not reduce the percentage of amounts available under clause (i)—</text> <subclause id="H5E51B0C5B2644E4191F9B951EE964E8D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the case of a covered unit described in paragraph (2)(A), to less than 35 percent of the amount of rental charges deposited in the Account from the covered unit in a fiscal year; or</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H11155138C3C6420FBDDD63833BCC480F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of any other covered unit, to less than 50 percent of the amount of rental charges deposited in the Account from the covered unit in a fiscal year.</text>
									</subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E7A91731BFF42F596EDD10593D5B00F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Transfer to other covered units</header>
 <clause id="H34202A3A429B45F98261606D96FB9060"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Distribution</header><text>If the Secretary determines that the percentage of amounts otherwise available to a covered unit under subparagraph (A) should be reduced under subparagraph (B), the Secretary may transfer to other covered units, for allocation in accordance with clause (ii), the percentage of the amounts withheld from the covered unit under subparagraph (B), to be expended by the other covered units in accordance with paragraph (5).</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC155A1F47E2C4ACAA724867A9ED935B9"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>In determining the allocation of amounts to be transferred under clause (i) among other covered units, the Secretary shall consider—</text>
 <subclause id="H7913BEA0445A469CB5500E60461D6BBC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the number of proposals for ski area improvements in the other covered units;</text> </subclause><subclause id="HF8DF03829AA34AAC93D8F72655213DB0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any backlog in ski area permit administration or the processing of ski area proposals in the other covered units; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H222E5928FF2A4665ABB1BE4418E6A0F4"><enum>(III)</enum><text>any need for services, training, staffing, or streamlining programs in the other covered units or the Region in which they are located that would improve the administration of the Forest Service Ski Area Program.</text>
									</subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A54B032284F4C809868CCD551C681D9"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Authorized expenditures</header>
 <subparagraph id="H847657BA5A114D5FBDCF9CBA052DC859"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Amounts distributed from the Account to a covered unit under this subsection may be used for—</text> <clause id="HEDE2F7E395A64B9A814690BFAC5A8149"><enum>(i)</enum><text>ski area special use permit administration and processing of proposals for ski area improvement projects in the covered unit, including staffing and contracting for such administration, process, or services through the unit or the Region;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H3E48CF237A304663A67D52017809C85F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any expenses that the Forest Service would have otherwise applied to ski area permittees through cost recovery pursuant to part 251 of title 36, Code of Federal Regulations;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H114525E9496347D89881D40D6A9BDDD1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>training programs on processing ski area applications, administering ski area permits, or ski area process streamlining in the covered unit or the Region in which the unit is located; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HBF2F9ABDE34E4FA8882A98C7B79FF46A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>interpretation activities, visitor information, visitor services, and signage in the covered unit to enhance—</text>
 <subclause id="H2829840D2BB747F3B3B6DD20BA0BFAFC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the ski area visitor experience on National Forest System land; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H270F77192262421A9F8095050FD44D97"><enum>(II)</enum><text>avalanche information and education activities carried out by the Forest Service.</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7F565DD249845DEA9D8B14C2CFC0346"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Other uses</header><text>If any amounts are still available in the Account after all ski area permit-related expenditures under subparagraph (A) are made, including amounts transferred to other covered units pursuant to paragraph (4)(C), such remaining amounts in the Account may be applied to permit administration for other (non-ski area) Forest Service recreation special use permits at the discretion of the Secretary. The Secretary shall first determine that all ski area-related permit administration, processing and interpretation needs have been met in all covered units and Regions before applying any remaining amounts in the Account to non-ski area uses.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9897F61750F24029ABC669FAA9706C2E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Amounts in the Account may not be used for—</text> <clause id="H5E9944E5C01F46A19A60170030C71218"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the conduct of wildfire suppression or preparedness activities;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB0542AAC55134407BF17F6D91BCED04B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the conduct of biological monitoring on National Forest System land under the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531</external-xref> et seq.) for listed species or candidate species, except as required by law for environmental review of ski area projects;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H6766554B6BAE442F8140CA116920FD6A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the acquisition of land for inclusion in the National Forest System; or</text> </clause><clause id="H7F48BAC11ADB436F91DC18F0F5F8EDEE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Forest Service administrative sites.</text>
								</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H76756F5B2D5748188A8B21636041FD08"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Savings provisions</header>
 <subparagraph id="H6A514A2DC97E4151A7318FCAF604173D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Nothing in this subsection affects the applicability of section 7 of the Act of April 24, 1950 (commonly known as the <quote>Granger-Thye Act</quote>) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/580d">16 U.S.C. 580d</external-xref>), to ski areas on National Forest System land.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C963B4B61D1488F8D908F8D36BFE13C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Revenue allocation payments</header><text>Rental charges deposited in the Account under paragraph (2) shall be considered to be amounts received from the National Forest System for purposes of calculating amounts to be paid under—</text>
 <clause id="H5FDA7B7F7BB24551BFFD5DBE59AF4DFA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Secure Rural Schools and Community Self-Determination Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/7101">16 U.S.C. 7101</external-xref> et seq.);</text> </clause><clause id="H808AEFA92E1644799161BDAEEE180690"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the sixth paragraph under the heading <quote>forest service</quote> in the Act of May 23, 1908 (35 Stat. 260; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/500">16 U.S.C. 500</external-xref>);</text>
 </clause><clause id="H4035E83AB49D49679601CFE9370443E5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>section 13 of the Act of March 1, 1911 (36 Stat. 963; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/500">16 U.S.C. 500</external-xref>); and</text> </clause><clause id="H57FF7DEF6880418893E332881A381245"><enum>(iv)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/69">chapter 69</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H730FF2FD1C79446FA9B0421FE267BFB3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Supplemental funding</header><text>Rental charges retained and expended under this subsection shall supplement (and not supplant) appropriated funding for the operation and maintenance of each covered unit.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5B921BDD78314E3D90255BDF237E6E30"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section (including the amendments made by this section) shall take effect on the date that is 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HB9DF43541FAA41048CC5B8678D112FBE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture shall not be required to issue regulations or policy guidance to implement this section (including the amendments made by this section).</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


