<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H219D99F01F634329BA4047191B37CD69" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5699 IH: Hospital Opioid Solutions Toolkit Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5699</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180508">May 8, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001107">Mr. Curbelo of Florida</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster of New Hampshire</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services to develop guidance on pain management and the
			 prevention of opioid use disorder for hospitals receiving payment under
			 part A of the Medicare program.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H48FC356FC1CC4624B316CF19C47035E4" style="OLC">
 <section id="HE6FC909288C24CE0BEC62C7128156627" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hospital Opioid Solutions Toolkit Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>HOST Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H6EB4A0CB893447C18B424C0737F757B8" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Developing guidance on pain management and opioid use disorder prevention for hospitals receiving payment under part A of the Medicare program</header> <subsection id="H40B7570CEBFE430D9EF9A32C0DC039E8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 1, 2019, the Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall develop and publish on the public website of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services guidance for hospitals receiving payment under part A of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395c">42 U.S.C. 1395c</external-xref> et seq.) on pain management strategies and opioid use disorder prevention strategies with respect to individuals entitled to benefits under such part.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H1B397195419F4D76B1D446F92B3737E6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In developing the guidance described in subsection (a), the Secretary shall consult with relevant stakeholders, including—</text>
 <paragraph id="H45CCC359717E4C6AA145F37B8B7695CE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>medical professional organizations;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H0E640757D7B04DD996DA77C6B8412F84"><enum>(2)</enum><text>providers and suppliers of services (as such terms are defined in section 1861 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x</external-xref>));</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H478EE870A4C04F208299A260689EA208"><enum>(3)</enum><text>patient advocacy organizations and organizations representing Medicare beneficiaries; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H768B5C7088A44455AB51D825B6C4DD35"><enum>(4)</enum><text>other entities determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H64AF73A6B7BA469AB391E942E9EC9B30"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The guidance described in subsection (a) shall include, with respect to hospitals and individuals described in such subsection, the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H821045B57F76421B99A1109B37D3FCDE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Best practices regarding evidence-based screening and practitioner education initiatives relating to screening and treatment protocols for opioid use disorder, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H33DBF62A0FEE4642B07CCF86EF0919F8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>methods to identify such individuals at-risk of opioid use disorder, including risk stratification;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9F6C98FA5F4438EB7F2871334DEA295"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ways to prevent, recognize, and treat opioid overdoses; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD2F4C5A3BAD484E9ECCA855393EB1C7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>resources available to such individuals, such as opioid treatment programs, peer support groups, and other recovery programs.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H323545DF7843483FB8580A07AF3739DA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Best practices for such hospitals to educate practitioners furnishing items and services at such hospital with respect to pain management and substance use disorders, including education on—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H3BA60084F301406CA887192366136F18"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the adverse effects of prolonged opioid use;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD17CA68C066449FBA5AA6CD926EFDDD5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>alternative, evidence-based, non-pharmacological pain management treatments;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23E73961EF894F9A9681C4CA78321C4D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>monitoring programs for individuals who have been prescribed opioids; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7EDCB1CC45B4C549A20347F6F0A6F9E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the prescribing of naloxone along with an initial opioid prescription.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F4168D8F44E4C2FAE38E53211DE507D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Best practices for such hospitals to make such individuals aware of the risks associated with opioid use (which may include use of the notification template described in paragraph (4)).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H724C68F7A5F8439193EB4BCEAC8A9C2D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A notification template developed by the Secretary for such individuals who are prescribed an opioid that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HA0B35DD545B24EC9B8BAF27BABD533A4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>explains the risks and side effects associated with opioid use (including the risks of addiction and overdose) and the importance of adhering to the prescribed treatment regimen, avoiding medications that may have an adverse interaction with such opioid, and storing such opioid safely and securely;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A9DAF7BE3174DF5B42A1685CF392664"><enum>(B)</enum><text>highlights multimodal and evidence-based non-opioid alternatives for pain management;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H26C23B31BBAF435A926AE4A09E2D152E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>encourages such individuals to talk to their health care providers about such alternatives;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H977BC27A227747A3A5F2E67FAE9D2028"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provides for a method (through signature or otherwise) for such an individual, or person acting on such individual’s behalf, to acknowledge receipt of such notification template;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C105406E4A34D30964F74BF55570891"><enum>(E)</enum><text>is worded in an easily understandable manner and made available in multiple languages determined appropriate by the Secretary; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF82EA6C7653444179C169D47A24F002A"><enum>(F)</enum><text>includes any other information determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H15A505E95A114194AFF40672475515D0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Best practices for such hospital to track opioid prescribing trends by practitioners furnishing items and services at such hospital, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HFA9F77D3172A49D1817CC2F38048BE62"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ways for such hospital to establish target levels with respect to opioids prescribed by such practitioners;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B937F6C4BBF469088FD7BABEE6CDCF7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>guidance on checking the medical records of such individuals against information included in prescription drug monitoring programs;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4706349E4714D8B88457C8BA0D0E3B6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>strategies to reduce long-term opioid prescriptions; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCAA0F418A1FF48FDB7E6C1FFA2D9A671"><enum>(D)</enum><text>methods to identify such practitioners who may be over-prescribing opioids.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H43266562022B4314AB9CBAFD93168D39"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Other information the Secretary determines appropriate, including any such information from the Opioid Safety Initiative established by the Department of Veterans Affairs or the Opioid Overdose Prevention Toolkit published by the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


