<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA1F4278F22314E6E9C1FF56C08DDD544" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5190 IH: Journalism Competition and Preservation Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5190</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180307">March 7, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001084">Mr. Cicilline</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide a temporary safe harbor for the publishers of online content to collectively negotiate
			 with dominant online platforms regarding the terms on which their content
			 may be distributed.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HA575AC07A1A8412886616F297CA5E711" style="OLC">
 <section id="HADCC2F34344A46209DFD3B03B038B9F6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Journalism Competition and Preservation Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H492B6C233C8B4E9986E4E92EDE6BC791"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H15D87ACB4D594EC48255F626306BF213"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A free and vibrant press is essential to the health of our democracy.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H5F378F302418449B9D5F78CAE009F997"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Fair and competitive markets are integral to maintaining a thriving press that can meet the demands of consumers and an informed citizenry.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2AF7A61DF119444E9B7EDC7F328508D7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>More and more Americans prefer to read news online. While some readers may go directly to a publisher’s website, many more find news through the use of one or more online platforms, such as search engines and social media websites.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2E4EF8EB5CE149B8A9D24EA2ADEF959F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Over the past decade, digital audiences for news publications have increased by over 200 percent. Nevertheless, over that same time period, digital news publishers’ revenues have fallen by nearly half.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE9FE25850564451899D9DFEC3F5464BD"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the absence of the robust enforcement of the antitrust laws to ensure a free and open marketplace of ideas, some dominant platforms serve as a de facto gateway to all online content for many web users, wielding an enormous amount of control over how readers find and interact with content produced by the press.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H212D5698703141AE92185F6BDF9131CD"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Dominant platforms often are able to dictate the terms on which a publisher’s content may appear on their platform, and some hold so much sway in the online ecosystem that they can control whether their users are able to find a creator’s content at all.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFCBF3ADF1CBD42F3B6B743D906A56FA5"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity with the power to dictate the terms of distribution of news has the power to dictate the content of the news.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H682341B4E68D46F2A4C27549E24E8B8F"><enum>(8)</enum><text>America benefits from, and depends upon, not only a free marketplace for goods and services, but also a free marketplace of ideas.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE4F62C62498646F582AB7D1C439DB3EE"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The antitrust laws were intended to and do provide both economic and civic benefits.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H353F283986CA4712963F905EC10B723F"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A central purpose of the antitrust laws is to promote and protect open markets, including those for the free and diverse press.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5F93CCB81CFB413391D33CA7CBA083D7"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">While antitrust exemptions are generally disfavored, should the application of the antitrust laws ever be applied in a manner that conflicts with their stated purpose—such as protecting the free and open marketplace of ideas online—it is the duty and prerogative of the Congress to resolve the conflict.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="HACCBCE6AAB2841B8A33CEEE696F7A52A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Safe harbor for certain collective negotiations</header>
 <subsection id="H5E0DB4592AD746A684375DA628181562"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section:</text> <paragraph id="HA8CC84EB759A4A5686146C306AA58258"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>news content creator</quote> means—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE5E4F5A794FC4C379DD8350286812F83"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any print or digital news organization that—</text> <clause id="HD0945FFF7C8147B9BBDB24ACD24FF2A0"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has a dedicated professional editorial staff that creates and distributes original news and related content concerning local, national, or international matters of public interest on at least a weekly basis; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC8639B167C0E489F8235813D9965395F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is commercially marketed through subscriptions, advertising, or sponsorship; and</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00461BDADDE3434C935C1BA2B86E6BDC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides original news and related content, with the editorial content consisting of not less than 25 percent current news and related content.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H199BCDFFB5DF4874B6E484DB31C8C0EA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Online Content Distributor</quote> means any entity that—</text> <subparagraph id="HE81FBFB534344F81AD56F3E4C6498FEF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">operates a website or other online service that displays, distributes, or directs users to news articles, works of journalism, or other content on the internet that is generated by third-party news content creators; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6521044FD764350A5A6ED7ED6D705AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has not fewer than 1,000,000,000 monthly active users, in the aggregate, of all of its websites or online services worldwide.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC2B3F9F11FE4E5C8F331DD3D2E03895"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>antitrust laws</quote> has the meaning given such term in subsection (a) of the first section of the Clayton Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/12">15 U.S.C. 12</external-xref>), and includes—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HB42A51BC44774D10A1E6332408904E19"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">section 5 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45</external-xref>) to the extent that such section applies to unfair methods of competition; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H98FB109B1FB44208A00B105D87DB2DCB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any State law, rule, or regulation that prohibits or penalizes the conduct described in, or is otherwise inconsistent with, subsection (b) of this section.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B333EF42ACA4208A65E573FD50E8C55"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>negotiation period</quote> means the period of time beginning on the date this Act goes into effect and ending 48 months later.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBAD812D6C4D5477BA26D1EB6ADD4D605"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation of liability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A news content creator shall not be held liable under the antitrust laws for engaging in negotiations with other news content creators during the negotiation period to collectively withhold content from, or negotiate with, an Online Content Distributor regarding the terms on which the news content creators’ news content may be distributed by the Online Content Distributor, if—</text>
 <paragraph id="H31EA6326DF4749BB87483129C0006988"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the negotiations with the Online Content Distributor—</text> <subparagraph id="H56799832D2D94F01B6C3FE629A180BEC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are not limited to price and are nondiscriminatory as to similarly situated news content creators, and directly relate to the quality, accuracy, attribution or branding, and interoperability of news; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H248086F295494D7DAFD1E5267DB9E102"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">pertain to terms that would be available to all news content creators;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H06E4A8460FE947F2BDADEC9C70840114"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the coordination among the news content creators is directly related to and reasonably necessary for negotiations with an Online Content Distributor that are otherwise consistent with this Act; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5850D883B9A743AC82A09AEF708B45E2"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the negotiations do not involve any person that is not a news content creator or an Online Content Distributor.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H6421572508B342DF984BF35123CF9729"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in this Act, this Act shall not be construed to modify, impair, or supersede the operation of the antitrust laws.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


