<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HCC68C1AAB67443DE8819809389F7DDB0" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5356 IH: National Security Commission Artificial Intelligence Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5356</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180320">March 20, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the National Security Commission on Artificial Intelligence.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H68C9F11DF82C47849F9AECA3172E274E" style="OLC">
 <section id="HABEEBDCF7D204EC8B7A83FE37F6BB1B3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Security Commission Artificial Intelligence Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H42DC88658C6C453EB4D510CB1C365404"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Security Commission on Artificial Intelligence</header> <subsection id="HBF35CB96E91843CC94159FB9F4D1433C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the executive branch an independent commission to be known as the National Security Commission on Artificial Intelligence (in this subtitle referred to as the <quote>Commission</quote>). The Commission shall be considered an independent establishment of the Federal Government as defined by section 104 of title 5, United States Code, and a temporary organization under section 3161 of such title.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H4B41B378EFA742478B78504F5F126F70"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header>
 <paragraph id="H4C50EBABCEB24CDB8C8A7DA9D87022AB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall carry out a review of the advances in artificial intelligence, related machine learning developments, and associated technologies. In carrying out such review, the Commission shall consider the methods and means necessary to advance the development of artificial intelligence, machine learning, and associated technologies by the United States to comprehensively address the national security needs of the Nation, including economic risk, and any other needs of the Department of Defense or the common defense of the Nation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H693C0CE72D694644BCF028717F7433E9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Scope of the review</header><text>In conducting the review under paragraph (1)(A), the Commission shall consider—</text> <subparagraph id="H429629C5112B4A2990691C1EF5E908EC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the competitiveness of the United States in artificial intelligence, machine learning, and other associated technologies, including matters related to national security, economic security, public-private partnerships, and investments;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54A5E3292263471EBFAC0322B297DA89"><enum>(B)</enum><text>means and methods for the United States to maintain a technological advantage in artificial intelligence, machine learning, and other associated technologies, including quantum computing and high performance computing;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66C85AF48BDD46AB8BF80AA24A3C31D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>developments and trends in international cooperation and competitiveness, including foreign investments in artificial intelligence, machine learning, and computer science fields;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE50884A4491B4C2383B3577888E6F180"><enum>(D)</enum><text>means by which to foster greater emphasis and investments in basic and advanced research to stimulate private, public, academic and combined initiatives in artificial intelligence, machine learning, and other associated technologies, including quantum computing and high performance computing;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4AD2FC0D26449A58FFA4714519A832B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>workforce and education incentives to attract and recruit leading talent in artificial intelligence and machine learning, including science, technology, engineering, and math programs;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAADE1F4BBD474E9E856EE3987743AD54"><enum>(F)</enum><text>risks associated with United States and foreign country advances in military employment of artificial intelligence and machine learning, including under the international law of armed conflict, international humanitarian law, and escalation dynamics;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0A30981F6974E068B027F0DE7908BCA"><enum>(G)</enum><text>associated ethical considerations related to artificial intelligence and machine learning as it will be used for future applications;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD51ACBC400E944FDBF66E927585B8C1A"><enum>(H)</enum><text>means to establish data standards and provide incentives for the sharing of open training data within related data-driven industries;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H700E597993F8486F9F20A08F675811AD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>development of privacy- and security-protecting measures for data in artificial intelligence, machine learning, and associated technologies; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7FE1FF2C39324B879D1E8EC8BC7FAAAD"><enum>(J)</enum><text>any other matters the Commission deems relevant to the common defense of the Nation.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0A3E3422DB8842DE962A01B9BA36F023"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership</header> <paragraph id="HDC623B6B99F14CDE93411365C094B544"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Number and appointment</header><text>The Commission shall be composed of 11 members appointed as follows:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H4DB8F936C6B44AD6839BE3FA00E988DA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Secretary of Defense shall appoint 3 members.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H421ED6E77DA44E2F9EC5F821447BC522"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Chairman of the Committee on Armed Services of the Senate shall appoint 2 members.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C97DE482F6544DA939B3F7EE2A8F860"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The ranking minority member of the Committee on Armed Services of the Senate shall appoint 2 members.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4AB2761FAF94C498A64F358228AD545"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Chairman of the Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives shall appoint 2 members.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2A7031D1C1114918B3A477606318E217"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The ranking minority member of the Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives shall appoint 2 members.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD732A56A2CC4C24939993F03342CBE7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadline for appointment</header><text>Members shall be appointed to the Commission under paragraph (1) not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA831BB50B94642CFA0D52E603A75E30F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effect of lack of appointment by appointment date</header><text>If one or more appointments under paragraph (1) is not made by the date specified in paragraph (2), the authority to make such appointment or appointments shall expire, and the number of members of the Commission shall be reduced by the number equal to the number of appointments so not made.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7891BB23BED0423D9B78CE6E99F50CBC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Chair and Vice Chair</header><text>The Commission shall elect a Chair and Vice Chair from among its members.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H914E3A5C8FB44021941458358E102ED6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Terms</header><text>Members shall be appointed for the life of the Commission. A vacancy in the Commission shall not affect its powers and shall be filled in the same manner as the original appointment was made.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA3B7DB0F34654F23836883DFBC6BFDD8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Status as Federal employees</header><text>Notwithstanding the requirements of section 2105 of title 5, United States Code, including the required supervision under subsection (a)(3) of such section, the members of the Commission shall be deemed to be Federal employees.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H6A0E87875935441FBFE424867329FA61"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>Of the amounts authorized to be appropriated for fiscal year 2019 for the Department of Defense, not more than $10,000,000 shall be made available to the Commission to carry out its duties under this section. Funds made available to the Commission under the preceding sentence shall remain available until expended.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HAD0AF33B3D0B4CE18492B6D2BD9735A3"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports</header>
 <paragraph id="HEDF8136583484E61945914BEDD5C3DE1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commission shall submit to the President and Congress an initial report on the findings of the Commission and such recommendations that the Commission may have for action by the executive branch and the Congress related to artificial intelligence and machine learning and associated technologies, including recommendations to more effectively organize the Federal Government.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H336A3CFF6FD64E7DB1F72B72BAEF9D2E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Comprehensive report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of this enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter until the date specified in subsection (j), the Commission shall submit to the President and to Congress a comprehensive report on the review required under subsection (b).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8A78CB03248A496DA2CCAC655402605F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definition of artificial intelligence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>artificial intelligence</quote> includes each of the following:</text> <paragraph id="HDA9AB697994D4A4CA5B5822AE82B9894"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any artificial system that performs tasks under varying and unpredictable circumstances without significant human oversight, or that can learn from experience and improve performance when exposed to data sets.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H64474099E64B4C7D929919CC8F553C1C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An artificial system developed in computer software, physical hardware, or other context that solves tasks requiring human-like perception, cognition, planning, learning, communication, or physical action.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H309E62B350F74C989947EDA89AE29079"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An artificial system designed to think or act like a human, including cognitive architectures and neural networks.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H16DCCC107ABC40A3AFB1260F3D76D42E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A set of techniques, including machine learning, that is designed to approximate a cognitive task.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE4051BDE14494872B91059978AA856D8"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An artificial system designed to act rationally, including an intelligent software agent or embodied robot that achieves goals using perception, planning, reasoning, learning, communicating, decisionmaking, and acting.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC418AF2986434583957D5CDB48737DB7"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Commission shall terminate on October 1, 2020.</text> </subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

