<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HFDC7D01DF03A45D2B5AAFD845FD3AAA1" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5277 IH: Financial Literacy College Education Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5277</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180314">March 14, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="S001187">Mr. Stivers</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Financial Literacy and Education Commission to establish and publish best practices
			 for teaching financial literacy for institutions of higher education, and
			 for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H3D63DB58F08B49E2AD9409185EADB3E6" style="OLC">
 <section id="H09AEFCB6DA1E4561AB2D9677D8F26CC7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Financial Literacy College Education Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H8831ECB3EA434B69B0024D9D2EA60670"><enum>2.</enum><header>Best practices for teaching financial literacy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 514 of the Financial Literacy and Education Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/9703">20 U.S.C. 9703</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block id="H124D3C7DA0FF4F1EA3D3F8FDA401C37B" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="idDD23D645AA50406E98681AC90E06AA5E" indent="down1"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Best practices for teaching financial literacy</header>
 <paragraph id="idD3F355DA93F04FF2868896CAE2EBEC69"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After soliciting public comments and consulting with and receiving input from relevant parties, including a diverse set of institutions of higher education and other interested stakeholders, including students, parents, and consumer advocacy groups, the Commission shall, by not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this subsection, establish best practices for institutions of higher education regarding methods to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="id53A430C8950647829E7DD6C6F999BA63"><enum>(A)</enum><text>teach financial literacy skills; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="id78FA6B6CD95F4639BEB949776C0375C4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide useful and necessary information to assist students at institutions of higher education when making financial decisions related to student borrowing.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id9CB6A414CE214416B566B3D6A0D0A731"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Best practices</header><text>The best practices described in paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text> <subparagraph id="id91E7ADC9CBAF4B11831A11E7BF3B5872"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Methods to ensure that each student has a clear sense of the student’s total borrowing obligations, including monthly payments, and repayment options.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="id225BC983A899443598ED8442EBDC38BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The most effective ways to engage students in financial literacy education, including frequency and timing of communication with students.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1D618ECA47444D65890AB9CDE1961441"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Information on how to target different student populations, including part-time students, first-time students, and other nontraditional students.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="id539C7129FF3D4CA9ACD7589846F01D42"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Ways to clearly communicate the importance of graduating on a student’s ability to repay student loans.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id6196B5846026498AB2D6E8ACA84D26A4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Maintenance of best practices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall maintain and periodically update the best practices information required under this subsection at least every 2 years and make the best practices available to the public.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="id633AFD8CAD434525BDA6120FB809E239"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to require an institution of higher education to adopt the best practices required under this subsection.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


