<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEE6503A03A954ED0AF054FE6453A86BD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5581 IH: Abuse Deterrent and Prescriber Training Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes"> I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5581</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180423">April 23, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001284">Mrs. Brooks of Indiana</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require training for prescribers of controlled substances, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H9772E45CB49444C79B78B7674340E518" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H966AB704D7634782BB40385146637135" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Abuse Deterrent and Prescriber Training Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ADAPT Act</short-title> of 2018</quote>.</text></section> <section id="H1FC761A5EA68453886C15C81394F7B2F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Practitioner education</header> <subsection id="H5D57D266443B48D895BBF434B16E781F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part C of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/821">21 U.S.C. 821</external-xref> et seq.) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7BFDC15FEB01400687C9EFACCB9B8ED9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 303 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/823">21 U.S.C. 823</external-xref>), by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H48AC15D6ABA544449095612FD4FB6E73" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H49FCF578F93D4BE78B83C161F6AF3904"><enum>(k)</enum> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H71D7F6372E0F400194FF8CEAB77A3048"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Attorney General shall not register, or renew the registration of, a practitioner under subsection (f) who is licensed under State law to prescribe controlled substances in schedule II, III, IV, or V, unless the practitioner submits to the Attorney General, for each such registration or renewal request, a written certification that the practitioner has completed 3 hours of training under a training program meeting the criteria in paragraph (2) during the period applicable under paragraph (5).</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFB6A8EDF25BC48C0948379CF43BB873D" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A training program meets the criteria in this paragraph if the program—</text> <subparagraph id="H9A30A2E831054AAE8FEDAC4EE1A8C122"><enum>(A)</enum><text>includes information on—</text> 
<clause id="H063D15DF95894B1BA7C5D2F2BF5B5245"><enum>(i)</enum><text>safe opioid prescribing guidelines, including the Guideline for Prescribing Opioids for Chronic Pain issued by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;</text></clause> <clause id="HF88C6B3439514F0A898481300A276832"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the risks of opioid medications and other prescription drugs that are controlled substances;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4C4DD2E61DD54D7D9241892CC4668041"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>pain management, including the need to provide individualized care particularly for active cancer treatment, palliative care, and end-of-life care;</text></clause> <clause id="H00E3ED92C611496780AA8134C2E11278"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>early detection of opioid and other substance use disorders;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H90425F80CF7643E7B39ADBC0E67FC7EB"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the risks of prescribing opioids to any individual in recovery from a substance use disorder;</text></clause> <clause id="H5492CC30491A45E3A500ACFC3B3720A5"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>a basic understanding of addiction;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H145C5F3F5141473FAB332C8C3CC8A607"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the treatment of opioid-dependent patients and their treatment options;</text></clause> <clause id="H19EFFE70C16748D6A2F280A078F15250"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>the risks of misuse of all prescription drugs that are controlled substances; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8D99FC1FE1FE40C788E86F68ADC86328"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>alternative non-opioid pain management medications and other effective treatments; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBAB32116E53647BC8DB621A0DE026DE8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is—</text> 
<clause id="H4536DB5BB8A34C1A95431ED9FCA12DD1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">approved by the State agency with primary responsibility for licensing the practitioner to prescribe controlled substances; or</text></clause> <clause id="H852B8F27FEA04C978176BCDC6CA76716"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if such State agency does not have in effect an approval of any training program for purposes of this subsection, conforms to the model training program in effect under paragraph (4).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9581CD79246D4340956CBC8CCE9B4F44" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (2), a training program on prescribing opioids used by a State for purposes of licensing health care practitioners is deemed to meet the criteria in paragraph (2) if the program has been in effect since before the date of enactment of the <short-title>Abuse Deterrent and Prescriber Training Act of 2018</short-title>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF0B0B95E5E784A9483C029470646B016" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text> The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H02E7615C67DA4E1F84ACFB4300F5A108"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Abuse Deterrent and Prescriber Training Act of 2018</short-title>, develop a model training program on prescribing opioids to be used for purposes of paragraph (2)(B)(ii); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1119B85BCB0B478B8EB2C4A955686DA4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by not later than 90 days after such date of enactment, provide information about such model training program to the Attorney General, prescribers, State licensing boards, and continuing medical education providers.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H352B1618698C40D79ABBAC60C97CB180" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum> 
<subparagraph id="H7C89B315BC2540D3B7CD70243950EC67" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a registration request, and in the case of the first renewal request of a practitioner after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Abuse Deterrent and Prescriber Training Act of 2018</short-title>, the training required by paragraph (1) shall occur during the 1-year period preceding the registration or first renewal request.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6CD3F87F31394AB2A15A48DDB92416D8" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a renewal request that is not the first renewal request of a practitioner after such date of enactment, the training required by paragraph (1) shall occur during the 3-year period preceding the renewal request.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC6B206C30467417DB553D3ACE12B8289" indent="up1"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Attorney General may—</text> <subparagraph id="H1A342D7C79094AB48A67E8B8F7D1FECC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>take steps necessary to verify that a practitioner has completed a training program as required under paragraph (1), including requiring a practitioner to provide information determined necessary by the Attorney General; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE52C9C03B90742B895601988B4654076"><enum>(B)</enum><text>investigate a practitioner described in paragraph (1) if the Attorney General has reason to believe the practitioner filed an inaccurate or fraudulent written certification under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDFD19F87F2B34CF181B5041E1DB091F3" indent="up1"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to prevent a practitioner from using the same training both for purposes of satisfying the registration requirements of this subsection and for other purposes, such as satisfying State licensing requirements.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H37CDF33A343243C9BC7DB31CF0333915"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 304(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/824">21 U.S.C. 824(a)</external-xref>), by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA7D7DF83621442F69F10C4147B2D36A9" style="OLC"> <quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="subsection">A registration pursuant to section 303(f) issued to a practitioner who is required to comply with section 303(k) may be denied or revoked by the Attorney General upon a finding that the practitioner has failed to comply with section 303(k).</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE0B2F40B921340BE86A05CADA709BD6F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall take effect on the date that is 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9578CD9560F04127BE47A79CDCCB095D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>Effective on the date that is 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the following provisions are repealed:</text> <paragraph id="HDEC4D595CD37416E8CEE2B4EAA290020"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Subsection (k) of section 303 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/823">21 U.S.C. 823</external-xref>), as added by subsection (a)(1) of this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H107E01FEADD045BD875AB7DF799F3AA8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The sentence added by subsection (a)(2) of this section to the end of section 304(a) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/824">21 U.S.C. 824(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H4FBBF93BFBE84E9DA85AFEFC298BDF40"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit a report to Congress on the effects of this Act and the amendments made by this Act, including an analysis of—</text> 
<paragraph id="HEF3DD2BC6BF24175AAFEB29B667218AA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether there has been a reduction in the volume of opioids prescribed;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF879A8971CFC44CF8304EE1FCBD8F88B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether there has been an increase in the likelihood that opioid-dependent patients receive substance use disorder treatment;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD9B4E93495D74FDFB9CC56B83E549BDC"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether there has been a reduction in opioid-related overdoses and deaths;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H673A67F00BEA4BE09FA7352D80E35E68"><enum>(4)</enum><text>whether training required by this Act and the amendments made by this Act has changed prescribing practices and increased patient referrals to treatment; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9AF2EF165EAD4202AD51D0B7824242CB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the extent to which prescribers have conformed their practices to those recommended in training pursuant to this Act and the amendments made by this Act. </text></paragraph> </section> </legis-body> </bill> 

