<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H83828FDA55BA44C69AAAFBAD115239F6" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5221 IH: To prohibit the use of funds to develop, test, deploy, implement, or administer the Disability Case Processing System, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5221</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180308">March 8, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000616">Mr. DesJarlais</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the use of funds to develop, test, deploy, implement, or administer the Disability Case
			 Processing System, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H11E30DEB40704DB19AC8AFD36E514243" style="OLC">
		<section id="H5B2E616CA1E444888A742C468E5E7178" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Elimination of Social Security Administration disability case processing system</header>
 <subsection id="HF67288D7FB384EAF9C1E8DFE0E175E21"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="H5C582752D5AC429BA5BAD52FC4159028"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2014, whistleblowers informed the Committee on Oversight and Government Reform that the Social Security Administration (in this Act referred to as the <quote>SSA</quote>) has spent nearly $300,000,000 on a failed information technology modernization project known as the Disability Case Processing System (in this Act referred to as the <quote>DCPS</quote>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF345515E5C0B45EFA1402B0DCBE66F24"><enum>(2)</enum><text>On July 25, 2014, the Chairman of the Subcommittee on Social Security of the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives requested that the SSA Inspector General (in this Act referred to as the <quote>SSA IG</quote>) conduct an <quote>investigation into the SSA’s management and failed implementation of the DCPS costing the taxpayers close to $300 million to date.</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5EA92D6C365A4466A2FE6E548FBB403A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The SSA IG, in its November 2014 initial report, stated that it had concerns with the SSA’s approach and recommended that the SSA not spend more funds until it determined whether the commercial-off-the-shelf (COTS) software could be used.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6E559310FC824D7BA2DBC946CD5E5328"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In May 2016, the SSA IG reported that the SSA had spent over $300,000,000 on the DCPS project, <quote>for which it would receive little benefit</quote>, and according to the SSA, it would still need $90,000,000 to $165,000,000 to deliver the first release of the new Core DCPS between July and December of 2016.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFCA6A8B7B9A148019FE18D3278F95D77"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The SSA IG reported in September 2016 that, since its inception 8 years earlier, the SSA’s reported costs for the DCPS project were $356,000,000. SSA estimated it would still need an additional $122,000,000 through 2019 for the project.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB8252185A1EF48F19D72CA4F75A1E0CB"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In its September 2017 report, the SSA IG reported that the SSA’s goals were to deliver full functionality of DCPS by April 2018 and full deployment systemwide by September 2019, bringing the total expenditure for the DCPS project to over $500,000,000. However, even after 3 years of reporting on DCPS, the SSA IG concluded that <quote>given the uncertainty of the future growth of the backlog and SSA’s ongoing development velocity, we were unable to conclude whether the Agency’s release goals were reasonable.</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H36F42D402BCF44A2A3A84DD8739F554F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on funding for DCPS</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds available to the Social Security Administration for any fiscal year may be used to develop, test, deploy, implement, or administer the Disability Case Processing System or any substantially similar program unless specifically authorized by Congress.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


