<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF52D91AE0C5847F0B60B2C67FD9C4355" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5359 IH: 2020 Census Improving Data and Enhanced Accuracy Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5359</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180321">March 21, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000087">Mrs. Carolyn B. Maloney of New York</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S000248">Mr. Serrano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000126">Ms. Eddie Bernice Johnson of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001069">Mr. Courtney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 13, United States Code, to require the Secretary of Commerce to provide advance notice to Congress before changing any questions on the decennial census, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBEB96D5508A94682BB5A73E39828D21B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB9431E723B354BCB886DA1A863D0BB05" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; findings</header> 
<subsection id="H1B0EFDB3FCBC4694AEC01C38F364B806"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>2020 Census Improving Data and Enhanced Accuracy Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>2020 Census IDEA Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H04907D4E04644B999AB485BD6601E42E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HBAE52BCF592E43DD8494A6F2D3682225"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The decennial census was embedded in article I of the Constitution of the United States by the founders of the United States to measure the progress of the country and help chart its future.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H05B0F98B0F8748ABAC8B8064DEFFB308"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The 2020 decennial census will, for the decade to follow, shape the reapportionment of the House of Representatives and the drawing of thousands of State and local political jurisdictions.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5CB560E8BF0C4AD5BEBB42D38FEBD143"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Nearly $700,000,000,000 in Federal assistance to State and local communities every year is informed by the results of the decennial census.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H05CCD94D59F24E12A0C1306B511D95C1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The President and Congress seek to make the 2020 decennial census the most complete, accurate, and fair decennial census in the history of the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCEEF504CDF6F455F84C195D6FA85CD92"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The decennial census is the largest peacetime mobilization undertaken by the Federal Government.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H49531AB5EAE546CC9B30AF1B2AF166B6"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any late, untested changes to the operational design of the decennial census will introduce great risk to the success of, the accuracy of, and public cooperation with the decennial census.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HF6EB00881EBA4C09ABB660B245444AA9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limitations and requirements for the decennial census</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 141 of title 13, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H18D9B7A2D0524C2B80408002B422D86E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (f)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF1D9C5B3D4674446AC69A81F791D77B1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H08C9573DEAD2432A89547C1D596F6F3A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a period; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HADDC80D4752E4A7F8ECC1809006B8427"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3);</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD77243980F88496CA7F674E46F185B23"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (g) as subsection (h);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H910441F7579343EC942141E7612CA59A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (f) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H432890A4680E4D0D98C207745458AC9E" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H3BD5CD816BC64AEDAC54FA226DD4D271"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Limitations and requirements</header> <paragraph id="HB18D9C47427D49008EB016F2F9BA59B2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice to Congress of operational design, subjects, types of information, and questions</header><text>In the 2020 decennial census of population and each decennial census thereafter, the Secretary may not—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5BFFACC172C949C5A2CEF5022EFCA965"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to the census or any survey conducted in connection with the census, implement any major operational design that has not been researched, studied, and tested for a period of not less than 3 years before the date on which the applicable census occurs; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5E46A59D99AC437380C225395941F16E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include on the questionnaire for the census any subject, type of information, or question that was not submitted to Congress in accordance with subsection (f).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H79FDDAE22C9D47C3948F7E455E27E969"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Biannual reports</header> 
<subparagraph id="H26E0E35BF735494FBC19FF010B0D2940"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Submission to Congress</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this subsection and biannually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that—</text> <clause id="H50D883B6E1BB44A7A579CBF5FB899506"><enum>(i)</enum><text>describes each component of the operational plan for the subsequent decennial census of population; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H54C12A72B9744CB19A57C70F4659145A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes a detailed statement on the status of all research, testing, and operations that are part of the Bureau's comprehensive plan for the decennial census.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4571C18C47A74B90B12E48601F1D19E5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Internet publication</header><text>On the date on which the Secretary submits a report under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall publish the report on the public Internet website of the Bureau.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEA1A36566E2D40FE846BD8CE11CCC361"><enum>(C)</enum><header>GAO analysis</header><text>Before the date on which a decennial census occurs, the Comptroller General of the United States shall certify to Congress that the subjects, types of information, and questions to be included in the census have been adequately researched, studied, and tested to the same degree as in previous decennial censuses.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCAED9FC0931E4A94BB4937B3B2208868"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (h), as so redesignated, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="USC">Definition</header-in-text>.—</quote> before <quote>As used in</quote>.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

