<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9BA08FE0AB674CB3902276FD3BFB5DED" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5759 IH: 21st Century Integrated Digital Experience Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5759</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180510">May 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000601">Mr. Ratcliffe</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000604">Mr. Russell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. McMorris Rodgers</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001106">Mr. Costello of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001048">Mr. Hunter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000581">Mrs. Lawrence</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001105">Mrs. Comstock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve executive agency digital services, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H7D6EC6E41E1E4947A23F7B619F5DEF97" style="OLC">
 <section id="H3D5652961B0C41A8925CF3FC9376AA1D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>21st Century Integrated Digital Experience Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>21st Century IDEA</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H08557C0C22C14D55856CDBC9E1A2B5D8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HB0787C8C13AA46F393C4B0B9239E909D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Restoring the United States Government’s global leadership position in technology and electronic government requires a new approach—one that narrows the growing gap between the digital demands of citizens and the fashion in which the Government provides digital services to the American people.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H92F0AF7AE1D9487F8A583FE3ABF58710"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Legislation is needed to accelerate the transition from an analog and paper-based Government to a 21st century digital Government.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3C39D959B95841208FD558E49C230208"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The recent passage of the Modernizing Government Technology Act and the Connected Government Act has laid the foundation for Government’s transformation to modern, digital platforms.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9C5D90F223DE47CA8B46B2A664CAA69C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Enhanced citizen-facing and internal digital service delivery will dramatically reduce the cost of Government operations and improve customer experience.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="HE0FB887C4ECB447EADA91174BB6F0059"><enum>3.</enum><header>Website modernization</header>
 <subsection commented="no" id="HC4C91B050A4841FCAE35ED176D553727"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements for Existing Executive Agency Websites and Digital Services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the head of an executive agency that maintains a website or digital service that is available to the public shall ensure that such website or service meets the following requirements:</text>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="HE51A9832E1CA432C86F64EABEF3B1C1D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Website Consolidation and Consistent Look</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Eliminate or consolidate websites or web pages that are duplicative or overlapping. Ensure a consistent look of public-facing websites and digital services.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H04DC22E0F13244AD97619EC606E690A4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Accessibility for Individuals with Disabilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ensure that each website, web-based form, and web-based application of an executive agency are accessible to individuals with disabilities in accordance with section 508 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794d">29 U.S.C. 794d</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF63612C88C7D482C8777CD41D5249C11"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Information Searchable and Discoverable</header><text>Contain a search function that allows users to easily search content intended for public use.</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE985C23B3AE04006A905037DE7E53E80"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secure Connection</header><text>Provision through an industry standard secure connection.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HAE2F9A2A1F174AF98D6459EFAB96E2B0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Data Analytics</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Designed around user needs with data-driven analysis influencing management and development decisions, using qualitative and quantitative data to determine user goals, needs, and behaviors, and continually testing websites and digital services to ensure that user needs are addressed. Notwithstanding any other provision of law, quantitative and qualitative research, including user testing, related to the development of websites or other public facing digital services shall not be considered a collection of information for the purposes of section 3507 of title 44, United States Code.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H33CB1676D13F4521AA9EA64EC7D825F0"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Content personalization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ensure users have the option for a more customized digital experience, allowing them to complete digital transactions in an efficient and accurate manner.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HBE1C255CB0864EEEB101ED2E938AFAB6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements for new websites and digital services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any website or digital service of an executive agency that is made available to the public after the date of the enactment of this Act shall meet the minimum requirements described in subsection (a).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD16756C1BD284F609F3CFD8C179B0401"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Internal Digital Services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of each executive agency shall ensure to the greatest extent practicable that any new Intranet conforms to the requirements in subsection (a).</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H6F12F2F9E03E45E6987A1F2D7FE2BE63"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Public reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of each executive agency shall submit to the Director an annual report on the progress an executive agency is making in implementing the requirements described in this section for the previous year and shall make the report available to the public.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HEF79AB3E61A84A4496FA26B84BDE4763"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Compliance with United States website standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any new website of an executive agency shall be in compliance with the website standards of the Technology Transformation Services of the General Services Administration.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HB98CD04D05834D79933F275AF843BF0A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Digitization of Government services and forms</header>
 <subsection commented="no" id="HD02E01FBF4FB4985A13C24C2AE34FF9D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Digital service option required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the head of each executive agency shall make available to the public an online, mobile-friendly, digital service option for any in-person Government transaction or paper-based process in a manner that decreases cost, increases digital conversion rates, and improves customer experience.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H139A54312CBA4BFBAA8A0E029A5F5108"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Forms and services required To be digital</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the head of each executive agency shall ensure that any paper-based form, application, or service that is related to serving the public is made available to the public in a digital format.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H9382909D106E4AD6B37D55FBD38B4AB9"><enum>5.</enum><header>Electronic signatures</header>
 <subsection id="H1EA9A3952F0348A28ECFEDF55040F442"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Plan for use of electronic signatures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the head of each executive agency shall submit to the Director and appropriate congressional committees a plan to accelerate the use of electronic signatures standards established in the Electronic Signatures in Global and National Commerce Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/7001">15 U.S.C. 7001</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HFDE72AE3118F47FD87A3D4942F70B991"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Executive agency compliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the head of each executive agency shall certify and report full compliance with the Electronic Signatures in Global and National Commerce Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/106/229">Public Law 106–229</external-xref>) and the OMB Circular A–130—Managing Information as a Strategic Resource guidance, to support the use of electronic signatures by the Federal Government.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H3305A0EBDB014C4FBBCBB2DD15224349"><enum>6.</enum><header>Customer experience and digital service delivery</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Chief Information Officer of each executive agency, or a designee, shall:</text> <paragraph id="H7D92EAC1B01B491898D0D27A7A185B33"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Coordinate and ensure alignment of the executive agency’s internal and external customer experience programs and strategy.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2DD2FC8279074DFA9B61EFA1EBD0DF67"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordinate with the executive agency management leaders (the head of the executive agency, the Chief Financial Officer, and any program manager) to ensure proper funding to support implementation of this bill.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD8D9C0C920CF412FA74914D476E6695E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Continually examine the digital service delivery strategy of the executive agency to the public and submit recommendations to the head of the relevant executive agency providing guidance and best practices suitable to the mission of the executive agency.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H465CD60A88234CE682368A06B4D91E14"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Using qualitative and quantitative data obtained from across the executive agency relating to customers’ experience and satisfaction, identify areas of concern that need improvement and improve the customer service delivery.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H46A931D5320B4528BD6DB0FC7BB000C1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordinate and ensure, with the approval of the head of the executive agency, executive agency compliance with section 3559 of title 44, United States Code.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H67F83A2B4A7244F3948F052264A86417"><enum>7.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HEDB483FE49334F28BB63BB7D27B72DED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Digital service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>digital service</term> means the delivery of electronic information (such as data or content) and transactional services (such as online forms or benefits applications) across a variety of platforms, devices, and delivery mechanisms (such as websites, mobile applications, or social media).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF283947E85FD4187A839D5E19F54A5B7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Director</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Office of Management and Budget.</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H5378EEC6841540278D082448A8B7B83A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Executive agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>executive agency</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Executive agency</term> in section 105 of title 5, United States Code.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H29204E199BA848139D6390C7DDC4351A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Intranet</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Intranet</term> means a network belonging to an organization or group of organizations and any sub department of the organization, accessible only by the authorized members and systems of the organization, employees of organizations, or others with secure authentication.</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


