<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H81350A904E884A10A18382EA253D2DEF" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5135 IH: Securing Children in Schools Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5135</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180301">March 1, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000377">Ms. Granger</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="D000600">Mr. Diaz-Balart</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000461">Mr. Flores</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 to provide for additional grants
			 for school security, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H5C3CD2F7844445F08DBDBDFBDC4189D1" style="OLC">
 <section id="H553979AE82574249A181F23C349A5096" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing Children in Schools Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H07E82C708CBC45C1A6AE0C5A4D7DD933"><enum>2.</enum><header>Additional grants for school security</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (34 U.S.C. et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0139EDCD81DF41F4AA27ADD7FE58572A" style="OLC">
				<part id="H385456B6276340FD9CBD10296CD64C76"><enum>OO</enum><header>Additional grants for school security</header>
					<section id="HF71CD4805CFF4D08930B47440947B81F"><enum>3040.</enum><header>Program authorized</header>
 <subsection id="H641C9A13F1E142B19FEC64B724243A90"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Office of Community Oriented Policing Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Director</quote>) is authorized to make grants to States, units of local government, and Indian tribes to provide for the placement and use of metal detectors and other screening technologies at schools and on school grounds.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HEC6BDCAD4D3F414A85B53117344D2891"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Grants awarded under this section shall be distributed directly to the State, unit of local government, or Indian tribe, and shall be used to improve security at schools and on school grounds in the jurisdiction of the grantee through the placement and use of metal detectors and other screening technologies.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD6B657081D9A4FA691E9E0135A61510B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Preferential consideration</header><text>In awarding grants under this subchapter, the Director shall give preferential consideration, if feasible, to an application from a jurisdiction that has a demonstrated need for improved security, has a demonstrated need for financial assistance, and has evidenced the ability to make the improvements for which the grant amounts are sought.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H486E9CF9DE39485A96A4DD37878B75CF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Equitable distribution</header><text>In awarding grants under this subchapter, the Director shall ensure, to the extent practicable, an equitable geographic distribution among the regions of the United States and among urban, suburban, and rural areas.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HBE623D45E2CD4E4FA98DB8A3E694E295"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header><text>The Director may reserve not more than 2 percent from amounts appropriated to carry out this subchapter for administrative costs.</text>
						</subsection></section><section id="H9B28E961D0D24342A15C6DC96C224D77"><enum>3041.</enum><header>Applications</header>
 <subsection id="HF15B81B0E22C47118400FE89DA2D22FB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To request a grant under this part, the chief executive of a State, unit of local government, or Indian tribe shall submit an application to the Attorney General at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Attorney General may require. Each application shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H2A85266BA6BA4C0EAFE549C0582671B6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>include a detailed explanation of—</text> <subparagraph id="HD2F453538C7744F2BADA1F04B0EEE890"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the intended uses of funds provided under the grant;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0F478A134D84E0996DB8CF58504E41C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how the activities funded under the grant will meet the purpose of this part; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0AC6856EB2234ED3B31F28C595E2C810"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how the school will limit their points of entry to ensure safety; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7248D893399F461C8E5B67C0221AAE49"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be accompanied by an assurance that the application was prepared after consultation with individuals not limited to law enforcement officers (such as school violence researchers, child psychologists, social workers, teachers, principals, and other school personnel) to ensure that the improvements to be funded under the grant are—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H6E8748DD82554E938C5025B047343B10"><enum>(A)</enum><text>consistent with a comprehensive approach to preventing school violence; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2913B9BF5B44E35A9EB3B6C71979BEF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>individualized to the needs of each school at which those improvements are to be made.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H31F4237CF8A34904B4E5459271A8A568"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidelines</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this part, the Attorney General shall promulgate guidelines to implement this section (including the information that must be included and the requirements that the States, units of local government, and Indian tribes must meet) in submitting the applications required under this section.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="HA842B92F24D6413E86EB2AA609BC8033"><enum>3042.</enum><header>Annual report to congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than November 30th of each year, the Attorney General shall submit a report to the Congress regarding the activities carried out under this part. Each such report shall include, for the preceding fiscal year, the number of grants funded under this part, the amount of funds provided under those grants, the activities for which those funds were used, and the number of weapons detected and confiscated by the use of metal detectors and other screening technologies placed and used using funds provided under this part.</text>
 </section><section id="H34D7D172FC9D43949C9A07FB94363AA7"><enum>3043.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this part—</text> <paragraph id="HBC0914588C4043D1BEF927012D9842B2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>school</quote> means a public elementary or secondary school;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCFEA25B9034B4C5EBD4F5FC073FB3F78"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>unit of local government</quote> means a county, municipality, town, township, village, parish, borough, or other unit of general government below the State level;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC589992D4D3941B2979ACBAF32BD31D8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <quote>Indian tribe</quote> has the same meaning as in section 4(e) of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/450b">25 U.S.C. 450b(e)</external-xref>); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H57123EBBB4874BD9A4BA8B4F5CF22318"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>screening technologies</quote> means technologies including—</text> <subparagraph id="HA06A42E6DFD04BA595EE48228C933F58"><enum>(A)</enum><text>walk through metal detection portals;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD17B51ADB418433E8CA03E6A8C953BC7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>stand-off screening technologies;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1EBDB8C64A643D585070B7CE8FE884E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>explosive trace detection; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H632DFC003AB2403ABB142EB8B0A07C27"><enum>(D)</enum><text>computed tomography equipment and X-ray imaging equipment for carried and personal belonging screening.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HDC5A144C9B5D46FCA356CF3A493043EF"><enum>3044.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this part $500,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2029.</text></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


