<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HFD789707CD6C4FAB85B9453E76E51DB1" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5540 IH: Disarm Hizballah Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5540</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180417">April 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001201">Mr. Suozzi</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000378">Mr. Kinzinger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Director of National Intelligence to prepare a National Intelligence Estimate on
			 Hizballah, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H6549757561984FC88E9A4EEE0277F81C" style="OLC">
 <section id="HDE62C5F40539437C9EE87A09D046D918" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Disarm Hizballah Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H9A6BB030D95145DB850D7E26EE4E0115"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text>
 <paragraph id="H48FA01A923BE4F9EA4EB4C1E032E1BBA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of State designated Hiz­bal­lah as a terrorist organization in 1997.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HEC68A7117ED4498E89DB03F5F525A0D2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Hizballah constitutes a grave and present danger to the United States and the interests and allies of the United States by conducting armed interference in multiple conflicts, most notably those of Yemen, Iraq, and Syria.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9DC79A308B2549C083250C10D31A0C97"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Hizballah has been sanctioned under the Hizballah International Financing Prevention Act of 2015 and designated pursuant to multiple executive orders and provisions of law to deter and prevent the financing of Hizballah’s operations. While impactful, the diverse and deadly arsenal of Hizballah, its procurement, and its continuous expansion have not been addressed.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HACB024B3F8844CACBF5B70AEBAEB6594"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The illegal transfer of weapons to Hizballah constitutes an imminent danger to the Middle East and the allies of the United States, as these weapons foment instability in an already volatile region.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H60BEC45D283D4D0F8190A943A69193D9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>According to an outgoing commander of the Israel Air Force, Israel has attacked dozens of convoys bringing arms to Hizballah and other groups on several Israeli fronts, including from Syria, over the past 5 years.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2A2F4F73C66B44B1A5BB6071DE9E194F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Pursuant to United Nations Security Council Resolution 1701, the United Nations Interim Force in Lebanon (hereinafter referred to as <quote>UNIFIL</quote>) has a responsibility to assist the Lebanese Armed Forces in taking steps towards the establishment of an area free of armed personnel, assets, and weapons other than those of the Lebanese government and of UNIFIL.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H53FEF9A713B649A8A8B5548AB158A686"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Pursuant to United Nations Security Council Resolutions 1701 (2006), 2373 (2017), and 1559 (2004), all Lebanese and non-Lebanese militias should disband and disarm, and the borders of Lebanon must be secured with a full deployment of the Lebanese Armed Forces as the only armed representative of the State.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H62940B97AE9F40DC94493D66F23C4375"><enum>(8)</enum><text>As noted in numerous reports discussing the implementation of United Nations Security Council Resolutions 1559 (2004) and 1701 (2006) no disarmament of Hizballah has occurred, and the borders of Lebanon, particularly in southern Lebanon, are not secure.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3D9F535E48BF4481813307C2438B8C79"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Pursuant to United Nations Security Council Resolution 1701 (2006) the sale or supply to any entity or individual within Lebanon of arms and related material shall be prevented.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFD99168DA43A4688B4440F5C397ECE31"><enum>(10)</enum><text>In September 2017, the mandate of UNIFIL was expanded to allow it to take all necessary action to stop its area of operations from being used for hostile activities and to step up its patrols and inspections to disrupt Hizballah’s illicit activities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H36308766F93E4B79B1094A16711FC0A9"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Pursuant to United Nations Security Council Resolution 2231, without proper authorization from the United Nations Security Council, it is forbidden to import, export, or re-export to, into, or from Iran, whether directly or indirectly, any significant arms or arms-related material.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H00D53948D29A41B98402F49E8FB1A895"><enum>3.</enum><header>Policy of the United States regarding UNIFIL and Hizballah</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States to—</text> <paragraph id="HB489604B65674DFD9A459FDE6C4F8B8E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">strengthen UNIFIL efforts to demilitarize southern Lebanon and neutralize the missile capabilities of Hizballah;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9A832E1B0BE14C4992C5751AFD6FA490"><enum>(2)</enum><text>use all available diplomatic, legislative, and economic means to detect and deter the illegal transfer of weapons from Iran to Hizballah, both regionally and internationally;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC5C94E4B9BFA4650B176100454B6539E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>implement the weapons embargo established in United Nations Security Council Resolution 2231 and to implement United Nations Security Council Resolution 1701 and the Taif accords, among other international resolutions; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCAA2411CA70746C7817530FCE177570B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>work with the Government of Lebanon, UNIFIL, and regional partners to develop a milestone timeline to implement a strategy towards the disarmament of Hizballah.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HF6ED81090BE44F27AA48AC8C5EB5DDFB"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sense of Congress regarding international cooperation in neutralizing Hiz­bal­lah</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the Sense of Congress that the United States should—</text> <paragraph id="HB2F069A7728C49A39EA58E775CC0F5C7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>cooperate closely with the Government of Israel in working to neutralize the capabilities of Hizballah and definitively halting the illegal transfer of weapons to and procurement of weapons for Hizballah; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H796AAB3A63444C0D88FB3271BD526E5B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>engage the Government of Lebanon to tactically secure its borders and disarm all militias operating in Lebanon.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H3DEE4F65488E40BC8E66DBC342652707"><enum>5.</enum><header>National Intelligence Estimate on Hiz­bal­lah</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after enactment of this Act, the Director of National Intelligence, in consultation with the Secretary of State, shall commission and produce a National Intelligence Estimate on Hizballah. Such National Intelligence Estimate shall include each of the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HDD12A3FBE5E04E34BDECEB473A095F74"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A full accounting of the entirety of Hizballah’s rocket arsenal.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H843C91CE227B45C0AEE4382AB6439033"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An evaluation of the success of the UNIFIL mandate.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HADCDA3A9FD8049848A060A41734A529A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An evaluation of the tactical capabilities of Hizballah, including such capabilities related to defense.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF8157FD1AA3D428986845B6004F8CAC4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A detailed description of the supply routes used in the illegal procurement of weapons for Hizballah.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE3B3829CBEF643CCBF73C38A80C90A8A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An estimate on the international operations that support Hizballah’s network.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H15642A98C50D4C10A64E43BBD72EC2E3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>An accounting of the effects of the interference of Hizballah in conflicts through the Middle East region.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBC6CE3074E4149A2AE8863E405699059"><enum>(7)</enum><text>An assessment of how Hizballah raises, holds, and spends funds in territories where UNIFIL operates.</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


