<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HF83CA9BB20694F94AD5A7FE088AB1D7F" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4821 IH: Iran Freedom Policy and Sanctions Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4821</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180118">January 18, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000580">Mr. Roskam</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001109">Ms. Cheney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000377">Ms. Granger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000813">Mrs. Walorski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001293">Mr. Bishop of Michigan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000619">Mr. Rodney Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001078">Mrs. Handel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000606">Mr. Pittenger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001096">Mr. Cramer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000210">Mr. King of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000592">Mr. Rokita</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000621">Mr. DeSantis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000598">Mr. Rothfus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000567">Mr. Lance</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000585">Mr. LaHood</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To impose sanctions against entities owned or controlled by the Armed Forces of Iran, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HECDE0188B65D48238CF1586D6E62EA95" style="OLC">
		<section id="H5FBB4D43DF82434D824B0B1BFEC636AE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title and table of contents</header>
 <subsection id="HDF2B7D0602044A1D8E746A67942AAB76"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Iran Freedom Policy and Sanctions Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H0ADD097232F54323B4F023783609DBB9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
				<toc container-level="legis-body-container" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration">
					<toc-entry idref="H5FBB4D43DF82434D824B0B1BFEC636AE" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title and table of contents.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HB20731B56CC14992AE2830AADDB344A8" level="section">Sec. 2. Findings.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HCBDA87A87C9D4F32B8757FA55DA8F21E" level="section">Sec. 3. Statement of policy.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H83DC232A24EE4D88B8C2922732A0BD24" level="section">Sec. 4. Definitions.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HD47E76BDF7134FACB7E8163692A9956D" level="title">Title I—Imposition of sanctions against entities owned or controlled by the Armed Forces of Iran</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H28AE9ABF65FB48BDA4A7DC2A3602B141" level="section">Sec. 101. Imposition of sanctions against entities owned or controlled by the Armed Forces of Iran.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HE709F52DDD7B4EC5881D58090F388F64" level="section">Sec. 102. Watch List and report.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HCE78F640E73E458A97EDAA37E3767E02" level="title">Title II—Reinstatement of sanctions imposed with respect to Iran that were waived, suspended,
			 reduced, or otherwise relieved pursuant to the Joint Comprehensive Plan of
			 Action</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H184768FBF4444A6181193E70BB8A0DB1" level="section">Sec. 201. Reinstatement of sanctions imposed with respect to Iran that were waived, suspended,
			 reduced, or otherwise relieved pursuant to the Joint Comprehensive Plan of
			 Action.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H4DCABB5580744CDCBCCAF05BC4C40F52" level="title">Title III—Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HF717942119D64CE28FEB7E130FFD15CE" level="section">Sec. 301. Short title.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H0D19A41850504BDEA83161940C8F733D" level="section">Sec. 302. Sense of Congress.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HB831896E82294C43A23090FD9542FD2F" level="section">Sec. 303. Expansion of sanctions with respect to efforts by Iran to acquire ballistic missile and
			 related technology.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H40F719EBA3D04D539AFDAEACA6C1F9AA" level="section">Sec. 304. Extension of Iran Sanctions Act of 1996 and expansion of sanctions with respect to
			 persons that acquire or develop ballistic missiles.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H35B6C84880234E91BA8A8ED107186830" level="section">Sec. 305. Imposition of sanctions with respect to ballistic missile program of Iran.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H5C721C8C98B04DD7B95E2358CF015551" level="section">Sec. 306. Expansion of mandatory sanctions with respect to financial institutions that engage in
			 certain transactions relating to ballistic missile capabilities of Iran.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HE57765D3EC1C4F6C8994A8965486C090" level="section">Sec. 307. Regulations.</toc-entry>
				</toc>
 </subsection></section><section id="HB20731B56CC14992AE2830AADDB344A8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="H737D41EDCCD140A790A133AF7B907C6B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A nuclear-capable Iran threatens United States national security and global stability.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3365F337003E4C93A68A6D74F6726F15"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Since the 1980s, Iran has engaged in a sustained and well-documented pattern of illicit and deceptive activities to acquire a nuclear weapons capability.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF3CCD2041CA04A0D86B22B928BED7091"><enum>(3)</enum><text>It is the policy of the United States to prevent Iran from acquiring a nuclear weapons capability.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HBC4F1B4541F54110B881866A2A7AD355"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Iran is developing an arsenal of advanced long-range ballistic missiles, including some already capable of reaching India, North Africa, western China, and parts of eastern Europe.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAF3F6426A17D45BAB0C1E5B2D03D8905"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Department of State has designated Iran as a state sponsor of terrorism since 1984 and has characterized Iran as the <quote>most active state sponsor of terrorism</quote> in the world.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCCD372E44FE94A93BEFC1D782C7E3BC7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Iran is a world leader in human rights violations, including the persecution of religious minorities and imprisonment of United States citizens.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9F616281958B4AC086A86D699D40C821"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on December 28, 2017, Iranians from all social sectors have participated in protests against the Iranian regime’s oppressive domestic policies and destructive foreign policy, in which over 1,000 protestors have been arrested and 21 have been killed.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H690137DC974247FB8A36A723B16A3E5A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action fails to permanently prevent Iran from obtaining a nuclear weapons capability and fails to provide the international community a legitimate inspections regime to monitor Iran’s nuclear program.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H336871E51A224F95B4138C58578AF2AA"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action allows key restraints on Iran’s nuclear program to expire within 10 to 15 years, including those on Iran’s domestic uranium enrichment program and heavy-water reactor at Arak.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAC5A40A379BB4F75A409E92A50014BD1"><enum>(10)</enum><text>United Nations Security Council Resolution 2231 (2015), which endorses the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action, allows for lifting international restrictions on Iran with regards to conventional military arms and ballistic missiles.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8538AE5A53534839AF0E41AA3867E95F"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action fails to address Iran’s egregious human rights record, Iran’s role as the world’s leading state-sponsor of international terrorism, and Iran’s unjust imprisonment of innocent United States citizens.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9F055F4339DB4DAAAAF0C3276E08EEC9"><enum>(12)</enum><text>On numerous occasions, Iran has violated both the letter and the spirit of the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action and its related agreements by exceeding the limits of heavy water production, testing ballistic missiles, seeking to acquire potentially illicit materials outside the mandatory procurement channel, and sending arms to terrorist groups around the Middle East.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H354A4FDF758247D3B85781463DBE9FEA"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The current Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action framework is insufficient in blocking Iran from developing a nuclear weapons capability, and it is in the United States national security interest to renegotiate this agreement to strengthen its terms or to abrogate the agreement and use all necessary measures to prevent Iran from developing a nuclear weapon.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HCBDA87A87C9D4F32B8757FA55DA8F21E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States that the United States should—</text> <paragraph id="H39202932A56747059B7CF0C0EFCC1A61"><enum>(1)</enum><text>deny the Government of Iran the ability to continue to oppress the people of Iran and to use violence and executions against pro-democracy pro­test­ors and regime opponents;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H84ED478414BC4E7596EBEEB6F73E8267"><enum>(2)</enum><text>fully and publicly support efforts made by the people of Iran to promote the establishment of basic freedoms that build the foundation for the emergence of a freely elected, open, and democratic political system;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H44644F4ABC5E4CF9930C55102667E272"><enum>(3)</enum><text>help the people of Iran produce, access, and share information freely and safely via the Internet and through other media;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDBB9EF0B53EE4DDAA50B0A44D5453F6A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>defeat all attempts by the Government of Iran to jam or otherwise obstruct international satellite broadcast signals, internet access, or social media access for the people of Iran;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCFCDFDA7AEE148CABFF18E325FB5C82A"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure Iran is permanently prevented from obtaining a nuclear weapons capability;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HC0A9B42E8665468BAB356D45F099375A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>extend indefinitely upon Iran restrictions on nuclear-related activities to prevent both the uranium and plutonium pathways to nuclear wea­pon­i­za­tion; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9836CE26DB30442BABDB2AD954307DBD"><enum>(7)</enum><text>seek a United Nations Security Council resolution permanently extending prohibitions on Iran’s ballistic missile and arms embargo as found in paragraphs 3 and 4 of Annex B of United Nations Security Council Resolution 2231 (2015).</text>
 </paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="H83DC232A24EE4D88B8C2922732A0BD24"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="HC52D281D9AE04AD684905BDB449D2EBF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> has the meaning given that term in section 14 of the Iran Sanctions Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/104/172">Public Law 104–172</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H267F7A5D1134455D80BB151162A1941A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Entity</header><text>The term <term>entity</term> means any corporation, business association, partnership, trust, society, or any other entity.</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE33FA3627F41496D88C2796604405E88"><enum>(3)</enum><header>IRGC</header><text>The term <term>IRGC</term> means Iran’s Revolutionary Guard Corps.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H2FF5A69A429249F5A9E1B3174B824D1B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action</term> means the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action, agreed to at Vienna on July 14, 2015, by Iran and by the People's Republic of China, France, Germany, the Russian Federation, the United Kingdom and the United States, with the High Representative of the European Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, and all implementing materials and agreements related to the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HC2E53FE690564048B7C1FC5D53A09B5D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>NPT Safeguards Agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>NPT Safeguards Agreement</term> means the Agreement between Iran and the International Atomic Energy Agency for the Application of Safeguards in Connection with the Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons, which entered into force on May 15, 1974.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HABAB50A085F44827A32E37EF2D665D0A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>person</term> means an individual or entity.</text> </paragraph></section><title id="HD47E76BDF7134FACB7E8163692A9956D"><enum>I</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions against entities owned or controlled by the Armed Forces of Iran</header> <section commented="no" id="H28AE9ABF65FB48BDA4A7DC2A3602B141"><enum>101.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions against entities owned or controlled by the Armed Forces of Iran</header> <subsection commented="no" id="HB1473809177A46FDAF9795EF73841BBA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall impose the sanctions described in subsection (c) with respect to any entity described in subsection (b).</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="H8C61447D38554C1A915047B6208761F1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Entity described</header>
 <paragraph id="H6D7D8209D78B4A0F81CB7FA43CFCEC0C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An entity described in this subsection is an entity, including an entity listed on the Tehran Stock Exchange, that is owned or controlled by the Armed Forces of Iran regardless of whether the entity itself is included on the list of specially designated nationals and blocked persons maintained by the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0B5062B2D5864E04BF4BB68DB7F2D042"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <term>Armed Forces of Iran</term> includes—</text> <subparagraph id="HEF8981C86D7145EF8AF8904420116284"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Iran’s Revolutionary Guard Corps;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H423B810BA9A741138D19E138651E7246"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Basij paramilitary;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C088FC465DB444B8829A5592B0D0A66"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the regular military;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93ED3E7E2D0E4E5098FF88C160879DCB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Ministry of Defense and Armed Forces Logistics (MODAFL);</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC0037F0542A41E8A9450BDE9B2EB540"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the police; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A110414721E44A68316E915C768D222"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the General Staff of the Armed Forces.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HA53EBB5BD8F64E91A462B0E62DEDDDB7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="H34C73D8905544EA89480D350531C7F86"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The blocking, in accordance with the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.), of all transactions in all property and interests in property of an entity if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE680F5A5CC2A46EDA18136353BAD29D7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inapplicability of national emergency requirement</header><text>The requirements of section 202 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref>) shall not apply for purposes of this section.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H912BE1DF7CED4970B96088967BE6D040"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H3EB3550D62BE4C4784784727A1A4742E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>United States person</header><text>The term <term>United States person</term> means—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HE367F8D06CC44CF7A9966D6A650C2387"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a United States citizen or an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence to the United States; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7C9BAA245BF244B69A32E472C2D8B59D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or of any jurisdiction within the United States, including a foreign branch of such an entity.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF59C966245A64FA5B7A1997407B57B71"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Own or control</header><text>The term <term>own or control</term> means, with respect to an entity—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H1697D11389D440B0B5E21DDBACBFA007"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to hold more than 20 percent of the equity interest by vote or value in the entity;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H01B8B131E33D4D0BB9AAB4034FB4E658"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to hold a majority of seats on the board of directors of the entity; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7A793241A7C241A988F6D04C3D0158FA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to otherwise control the actions, policies, or personnel decisions of the entity.</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE709F52DDD7B4EC5881D58090F388F64"><enum>102.</enum><header>Watch List and report</header>
 <subsection id="HAA0FBB9489E443688BCAA18AD0480264"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall establish, maintain, and publish in the Federal Register a list of each entity with respect to which the Armed Forces of Iran (as defined in section 101(b)(2))—</text>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="H9BDA5BBCED9A44A58780DE1144CB92A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>holds less than 20 percent of the equity interest by vote or value in the entity; or</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H2AB0271BF04843719D970EBA4236DCC0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>does not own any interest in the entity but maintains a presence on the board of directors of the entity or otherwise influences the actions, policies, or personnel decisions of the entity.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8C85FE3EAD784CBAB839291687D65A7A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of the Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of the Treasury shall submit to Congress a report on any changes to the list required by subsection (a).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HB586AED4E4C34F239F450AFB6A5FE534"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reference</header><text>The list required by subsection (a) shall be known as the <quote>IRGC Watch List</quote>.</text> </subsection></section></title><title id="HCE78F640E73E458A97EDAA37E3767E02"><enum>II</enum><header>Reinstatement of sanctions imposed with respect to Iran that were waived, suspended, reduced, or otherwise relieved pursuant to the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action</header> <section id="H184768FBF4444A6181193E70BB8A0DB1"><enum>201.</enum><header>Reinstatement of sanctions imposed with respect to Iran that were waived, suspended, reduced, or otherwise relieved pursuant to the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action</header> <subsection id="H23140C954B2F4DC682E58E177BB2946D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The reinstatement of sanctions imposed with respect to Iran pursuant to subsection (d) shall not take effect with respect to the 90-day period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act or any 90-day period thereafter for which a certification described in subsection (b) is in effect.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HBB9DEC4EC3C048718C389FA732A0EA03"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A certification described in this subsection is a certification submitted by the President to the appropriate congressional committees with respect to a 90-day period described in subsection (a) that contains a determination of the President that—</text>
 <paragraph id="HAD0B3C9C075A4B418F7B4B39C476B28F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Government of Iran has not—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1E6080A7AD5F4CE8BE373DF1B565AE04"><enum>(A)</enum><text>undertaken any activity related to ballistic missiles designed to be capable of delivering nuclear weapons, including launches using ballistic missile technology;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3FA0A329B806430796B287911CC26644"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">undertaken any activity to—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H7C4B64B43A1548168289D934FE8C2B70"><enum>(i)</enum><text>produce sufficient weapons-grade uranium or plutonium for a nuclear weapon in under 12 months;</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HE86DF6C0B4664A8392AE15015BDDA5CF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>maintain an excess of over 300 kilograms of Low Enriched Uranium; and</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="H6E350996EFFD419E83110CA9529C3413"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>maintain an excess of 130 metric tons of heavy water;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3128C8CDA7D04CDAB1FF60909C38F105"><enum>(C)</enum><text>undertaken any activity to—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H3AC3B3DBF5AD4756A88DE01D8165693E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>increase uranium enrichment levels beyond 3.67 percent;</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H632A6B1012294C009748CA5F0CF2D5C5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>develop, produce, or install advanced centrifuges; and</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="H27191532B28540119DBDACDD77F88F8C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>build new heavy water facilities or restore currently established facilities to operating capacity; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H6145CCFAA30F4632BBD4A00A35BB065A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>denied the international community unfettered, unannounced, and indefinite access to Iran’s nuclear program, including <quote>anywhere, anytime</quote> access and inspections of places, personnel, and paperwork, including physical access by the International Atomic Energy Agency to all suspicious sites, including military facilities, to monitor both overt and covert attempts by Iran develop a nuclear weapon; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H174CD1D789024B8D824272076EC57D9B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Government of Iran has—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H95FFD81874B4499D8389CD4948C57956"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ratified and implemented the Additional Protocol to the NPT Safeguards Agreement; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H20B672F5BAEF4EFBB26AE6054F06B118"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provided complete and full disclosure of the extent of Iran’s nuclear activities, including a report on any possible military dimensions of Iran’s nuclear program based on full access to suspected sites and all scientists involved in military dimensions of such program.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H71D814E4194543AAB5EA0A6496AEA0A7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Certification not submitted</header><text>In the event the President does not submit a certification described in subsection (b) to the appropriate congressional committees pursuant to subsection (b) with respect to a 90-day period described in subsection (a), the requirement to reinstate sanctions imposed with respect to Iran pursuant to subsection (d) shall take effect.</text>
				</subsection><subsection id="H2563FFBDD6E24E6086197519EF04F0A6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reinstatement of sanctions</header>
 <paragraph id="HDA665B21BE3041B1B09E523830FDF5A4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Statutory sanctions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any statutory sanctions imposed with respect to Iran pursuant to the provisions of law described in subsection (e) that were waived, suspended, reduced, or otherwise relieved pursuant to the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action, submitted pursuant to section 135(a) of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954, are hereby reinstated and any action by the United States Government to facilitate the release of funds or assets to Iran pursuant to the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action, or provide any further waiver, suspension, reduction, or other relief pursuant to the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action is hereby prohibited.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H85D2E2789BBF42DBA22A148C2A735469"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sanctions pursuant to Executive orders</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any sanctions imposed with respect to Iran pursuant to the Executive orders described in subsection (f) that were revoked pursuant to sections 1 and 2(a) of Executive Order 13716 of January 16, 2016 (Revocation of Executive Orders 13574, 13590, 13622, and 13645 With Respect to Iran, Amendment of Executive Order 13628 With Respect to Iran, and Provision of Implementation Authorities for Aspects of Certain Statutory Sanctions Outside the Scope of U.S. Commitments Under the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action of July 14, 2015) are hereby reinstated.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H42D2FFF8D5024937BD813DAEB93FE4CA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Provisions of law described</header><text>The provisions of law described in this subsection are the following:</text> <paragraph id="H2AF59D214A3444D1A8627C87034399CC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Iran Sanctions Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/104/172">Public Law 104–172</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H308471953F90480A9A4B9ADBE2C66645"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Section 1245(d)(5) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8513a">22 U.S.C. 8513a(d)(5)</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF822ABA1CBA1494392DBF872ED3C492A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sections 212(d)(1) and 213(b)(1) of the Iran Threat Reduction and Syrian Human Rights Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8722">22 U.S.C. 8722(d)(1)</external-xref> and 8723(b)(1)).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE848AD6EDF5B4C18A29C3EB4A5663BA2"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sections 1244(i), 1245(g), and 1247(f) of the Iran Freedom and Counter-Proliferation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8803">22 U.S.C. 8803(i)</external-xref>, 8804(g), and 8806(f)).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8B53ECCC2B494377BAB79017BC36F50E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Executive orders described</header><text>The Executive orders described in this subsection are the following:</text> <paragraph id="H9C034B24F4574862970F4E061DF56747"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Executive Order 13574 of May 23, 2011 (Authorizing the Implementation of Certain Sanctions Set Forth in the Iran Sanctions Act of 1996);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA856C50A928242348233F679BCBD4C96"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Executive Order 13590 of November 20, 2011 (Authorizing the Imposition of Certain Sanctions With Respect to the Provision of Goods, Services, Technology, or Support for Iran’s Energy and Petrochemical Sectors).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAE770456E68141F580997ED7F7DFD023"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Executive Order 13622 of July 30, 2012 (Authorizing Additional Sanctions With Respect to Iran).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H34C737F7184E4BA5AC027A847CA4D454"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Executive Order 13645 of June 3, 2013 (Authorizing the Implementation of Certain Sanctions Set Forth in the Iran Freedom and Counter-Proliferation Act of 2012 and Additional Sanctions With Respect To Iran).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBAD68DE0868046F6B38E92D341A9921F"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sections 5 through 7 of Executive Order 13628 of October 9, 2012 (Authorizing the Implementation of Certain Sanctions Set Forth in the Iran Threat Reduction and Syria Human Rights Act of 2012 and Additional Sanctions with Respect to Iran).</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H4DCABB5580744CDCBCCAF05BC4C40F52"><enum>III</enum><header>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</header>
 <section id="HF717942119D64CE28FEB7E130FFD15CE" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>301.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This title may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0D19A41850504BDEA83161940C8F733D" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>302.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text>
 <paragraph id="H90DC4864CA0C4A4295D4115B422D4E15"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the ballistic missile program of Iran represents a serious threat to allies of the United States in the Middle East and Europe, members of the Armed Forces deployed in the those regions, and ultimately the United States;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0327C110B37247D48C504C80A3012139"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the testing and production by Iran of ballistic missiles capable of carrying a nuclear device is a clear violation of United Nations Security Council Resolution 2231 (2015), which was unanimously adopted by the international community;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H82A9FDD775C14089A41CB0500C376233"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Iran is using its space launch program to develop the capabilities necessary to deploy an intercontinental ballistic missile that could threaten the United States, and the Director of National Intelligence has assessed that Iran would use ballistic missiles as its <quote>preferred method of delivering nuclear weapons</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA77275A7760142E29A537211585DFBEB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Government of the United States should impose tough primary and secondary sanctions against any sector of the economy of Iran or any Iranian person that directly or indirectly supports the ballistic missile program of Iran as well as any foreign person or financial institution that engages in transactions or trade that support that program.</text>
				</paragraph></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB831896E82294C43A23090FD9542FD2F"><enum>303.</enum><header>Expansion of sanctions with respect to efforts by Iran to acquire ballistic missile and related
			 technology</header>
 <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAF401D6002FD4573AA02DAF5D25C0B50"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Certain persons</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1604(a) of the Iran-Iraq Arms Non-Proliferation Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/102/484">Public Law 102–484</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note) is amended, in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>, to acquire ballistic missile or related technology,</quote> after <quote>nuclear weapons</quote>.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE98DEF343233457CB4179CF45A118426"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Foreign countries</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1605(a) of the Iran-Iraq Arms Non-Proliferation Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/102/484">Public Law 102–484</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note) is amended, in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>, to acquire ballistic missile or related technology,</quote> after <quote>nuclear weapons</quote>.</text>
				</subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H40F719EBA3D04D539AFDAEACA6C1F9AA"><enum>304.</enum><header>Extension of Iran Sanctions Act of 1996 and expansion of sanctions with respect to persons that
			 acquire or develop ballistic missiles</header>
 <subsection id="H6C0BA86D58BD49BBB45C2FB5E94C4978"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Expansion of mandatory sanctions</header><text>Section 5(b)(1)(B) of the Iran Sanctions Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/104/172">Public Law 104–172</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H33D8476AB799471BB982ED2D8A6F8A68"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>would likely</quote> and inserting <quote>may</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE36F0AB220A841E7A142D142B39EC94B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (ii)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HA8602F4ECA4F42E484324A7406B2CB42"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subclause (I), by striking <quote>; or</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6D5494F328344A33AD145C77FEA725EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subclause (II) as subclause (III); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8ADFBB0A47043CBB0D07A9C2FCD730B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subclause (I) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H678B094598B349D4A5D1A60BFF188B86" style="OLC"> <subclause id="H803E613201D647448B1B8B3920E6862E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>acquire or develop ballistic missiles and the capability to launch ballistic missiles; or</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HC7A4FAA8FE1146D3BA41975DD20281CC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Extension of Iran Sanctions Act of 1996</header><text>Section 13(b) of the Iran Sanctions Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/104/172">Public Law 104–172</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note) is amended by striking <quote>December 31, 2026</quote> and inserting <quote>December 31, 2031</quote>.</text>
				</subsection></section><section id="H35B6C84880234E91BA8A8ED107186830"><enum>305.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions with respect to ballistic missile program of Iran</header>
 <subsection id="HC4D2229F48CE4DADAA431D564BCBA0D3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title II of the Iran Threat Reduction and Syria Human Rights Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8721">22 U.S.C. 8721</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H96EE4CEE007D4B898C4E7E83EEEB99FD" style="OLC">
						<subtitle id="HA68585CCBE524E30B7EA2A981CA8C4B1" style="OLC"><enum>C</enum><header>Measures relating to ballistic missile program of Iran</header>
							<section id="HADC883AD58A14907B92E5DF180331BF7"><enum>231.</enum><header>Definitions</header>
 <subsection id="HD7353C3EF0F3465CB780AD05F22C859C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subtitle:</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H46E50CB5A8954988809E8141AD402E08"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Agricultural commodity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>agricultural commodity</term> has the meaning given that term in section 102 of the Agricultural Trade Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/5602">7 U.S.C. 5602</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA334E2E933304240AD09CC5BDCC21BC4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text>The term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H1D784CF246DD4D828D0D4FFABA2A0B44"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the committees specified in section 14(2) of the Iran Sanctions Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/104/172">Public Law 104–172</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDCA813AB3DAE4DB4ADC72C657085974F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the congressional defense committees, as defined in section 101 of title 10, United States Code.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD25336BCF2B45FF9B29676CD1AEECC0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Correspondent account; payable-through account</header><text>The terms <term>correspondent account</term> and <term>payable-through account</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 5318A of title 31, United States Code.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H953D353777D14F81982E3A101DAEDA94"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Foreign financial institution</header><text>The term <term>foreign financial institution</term> has the meaning of that term as determined by the Secretary of the Treasury pursuant to section 104(i) of the Comprehensive Iran Sanctions, Accountability, and Divestment Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8513">22 U.S.C. 8513(i)</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H80E2CC2C12054D4FA7E58E37AAB6B6A9"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Good</header><text>The term <term>good</term> has the meaning given that term in section 16 of the Export Administration Act of 1979 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4618">50 U.S.C. 4618</external-xref>) (as continued in effect pursuant to the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.)).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2F8FE9B3BDB04A758BF5387986548503"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Government</header><text>The term <term>Government</term>, with respect to a foreign country, includes any agencies or instrumentalities of that Government and any entities controlled by that Government.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2E9FA9B1450F41C9B92E651CF1853C38"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Medical device</header><text>The term <term>medical device</term> has the meaning given the term <term>device</term> in section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/321">21 U.S.C. 321</external-xref>).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H23B2FB84D82D4B7BA796BCFE4B5E82A8"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Medicine</header><text>The term <term>medicine</term> has the meaning given the term <term>drug</term> in section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/321">21 U.S.C. 321</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE8132FDF6A9A4ADBA9EA47EF1DC9367C"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Determinations of significance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subtitle, in determining if financial transactions or financial services are significant, the President may consider the totality of the facts and circumstances, including factors similar to the factors set forth in section 561.404 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations (or any corresponding similar regulation or ruling).</text>
								</subsection></section><section id="HBDCA17CD4DF24006A42E2249A01802EB"><enum>232.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions with respect to persons that support the ballistic missile program of Iran</header>
								<subsection id="H376EEC5881264264AB882AD7BFB1466F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Identification of persons</header>
 <paragraph id="HE108A87B189748EA9E8B2AFA44460FA6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title>, and not less frequently than once every 180 days thereafter, the President shall, in coordination with the Secretary of Defense, the Director of National Intelligence, the Secretary of the Treasury, and the Secretary of State, submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report identifying persons that have knowingly aided the Government of Iran in the development of the ballistic missile program of Iran.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFF995D9026974D60BEB1D81F10F9B4EE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each report required by paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H6568A51AB28F4EED85A30365A962B80B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An identification of persons (disaggregated by Iranian and non-Iranian persons) that have knowingly aided the Government of Iran in the development of the ballistic missile program of Iran, including persons that have—</text>
 <clause id="H178189258254458680906C43955F0293"><enum>(i)</enum><text>knowingly engaged in the direct or indirect provision of material support to such program;</text> </clause><clause id="HF4AF9114B6BC4AFB8CAD1D960F7A121C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>knowingly facilitated, supported, or engaged in activities to further the development of such program;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H3817C4347C9A431CB53667BE14D0F003"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>knowingly transmitted information relating to ballistic missiles to the Government of Iran; or</text> </clause><clause id="H89A7681B50D34017AB9DA8CE1918C5FE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>otherwise knowingly aided such program.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F6C0FEF3BA242A9B3630B1288C8029C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of the character and significance of the cooperation of each person identified under subparagraph (A) with the Government of Iran with respect to such program.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0E5F49D9569F45338B51C14C64FAC9DC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An assessment of the cooperation of the Government of the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea with the Government of Iran with respect to such program.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B3A6A2EA5A7463A8C5E14A0537D1B48"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Classified annex</header><text>Each report required by paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex.</text>
									</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3C3798E832504361BFB30CCE10660F08"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header>
 <paragraph id="HB0F41870B906436AADC421BE50F639C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 15 days after submitting a report required by subsection (a)(1), the President shall, in accordance with the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.), block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of any person specified in such report if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8A44A84FC9A640CBADC48211297CFD9E"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Inapplicability of national emergency requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements under section 202 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref>) shall not apply for purposes of this subsection.</text>
									</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0B01C541E4D34B8CB3AEC7103A3FA45F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exclusion from United States</header>
 <paragraph id="HA22316660F02457C9EAA517555A4A722"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the Secretary of State shall deny a visa to, and the Secretary of Homeland Security shall exclude from the United States, any alien subject to blocking of property and interests in property under subsection (b).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H871A67456FA94A8E925F4C57A1EA45E8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compliance with United Nations headquarters agreement</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to the head of state of Iran, or necessary staff of that head of state, if admission to the United States is necessary to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3779C6124DBD48E4978504C9CC024CED"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Facilitation of certain transactions</header><text>The President shall prohibit the opening, and prohibit or impose strict conditions on the maintaining, in the United States of a correspondent account or a payable-through account by a foreign financial institution that the President determines knowingly, on or after the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title>, conducts or facilitates a significant financial transaction for a person subject to blocking of property and interests in property under subsection (b).</text>
								</subsection></section><section id="HA15B13965C8B4DDE931A46490B0262AB"><enum>233.</enum><header>Blocking of property of persons affiliated with certain Iranian entities</header>
								<subsection id="H6F17B546920A4BD6AA5A99267E760B1E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header>
 <paragraph id="HBA0C2118ADFB41DB82113F43E3CC48EA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President shall, in accordance with the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.), block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of any person described in paragraph (3) if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H592341BA20934ECABB13EE3930DBE349"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Inapplicability of national emergency requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements under section 202 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref>) shall not apply for purposes of this subsection.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H78AED04E83FB42C89F2B2C9374A42B1B"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Persons described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person described in this paragraph is—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H68168F77B8F847DEB875B34E2A7A2DFD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an entity that is owned, directly or indirectly, by a 20 percent or greater interest—</text>
 <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H767EBE61E8644A7BAFA84DF999A4218C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by the Aerospace Industries Organization, the Shahid Hemmat Industrial Group, the Shahid Bakeri Industrial Group, or any agent or affiliate of such organization or group; or</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE1DAC87D51CB4C4CA28325B7F44A02A5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>collectively by a group of individuals that hold an interest in the Aerospace Industries Organization, the Shahid Hemmat Industrial Group, the Shahid Bakeri Industrial Group, or any agent or affiliate of such organization or group, even if none of those individuals hold a 20 percent or greater interest in the entity;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H360B79023D9A49DC85147691F53C3E38"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a person that controls, manages, or directs an entity described in subparagraph (A); or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H730195B488094A04BF67D6E069060768"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an individual who is on the board of directors of an entity described in subparagraph (A).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE14B40A2EC744BC4AF9BE2B0B7750DDE"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Facilitation of certain transactions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall prohibit the opening, and prohibit or impose strict conditions on the maintaining, in the United States of a correspondent account or a payable-through account by a foreign financial institution that the President determines knowingly, on or after the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title>, conducts or facilitates a significant financial transaction for a person subject to blocking of property and interests in property under subsection (a).</text>
								</subsection><subsection id="H7CC8FDF308144E89A2F589E917EB3B42"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Iran Missile Proliferation Watch List</header>
 <paragraph id="HC36B58EE6B0946C58449B5F5577D15D4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title>, and not less frequently than annually thereafter, the Secretary of the Treasury shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress and publish in the Federal Register a list of—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H62ACC05B29244A4C8A1CB48A30CF56DB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each entity in which the Aerospace Industries Organization, the Shahid Hemmat Industrial Group, the Shahid Bakeri Industrial Group, or any agent or affiliate of such organization or group has an ownership interest of more than 0 percent and less than 20 percent;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E3BFF1FAFF04E42A76C92625172565E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each entity in which the Aerospace Industries Organization, the Shahid Hemmat Industrial Group, the Shahid Bakeri Industrial Group, or any agent or affiliate of such organization or group does not have an ownership interest but maintains a presence on the board of directors of the entity or otherwise influences the actions, policies, or personnel decisions of the entity; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H193F2FA3A1924795B0C5846F59E655EE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>each person that controls, manages, or directs an entity described in subparagraph (A) or (B).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HAA447EF5DBA648939E53A3276419C77F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reference</header><text>The list required by paragraph (1) may be referred to as the <quote>Iran Missile Proliferation Watch List</quote>.</text>
									</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H84844A21D3A54E66952CD4C94144D007"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Comptroller General report</header>
 <paragraph id="H20CFC9D521B547989A2EB1A72429CF73"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H4BF6F689306B43E58B59B1F171A156D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conduct a review of each list required by subsection (c)(1); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF933AC71DAA84FE0A6A7FC579FA95B66"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than 60 days after each such list is submitted to the appropriate committees of Congress under that subsection, submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the review conducted under subparagraph (A) that includes a list of persons not included in that list that qualify for inclusion in that list, as determined by the Comptroller General.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H291A7F33EDDF4FC0A8E20F5F1E378124"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultations</header><text>In preparing the report required by paragraph (1)(B), the Comptroller General shall consult with nongovernmental organizations.</text>
									</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC85A0FEE035B4FFB83691974D1ADAAE9"><enum>234.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions with respect to certain persons involved in ballistic missile activities</header>
 <subsection id="HB16751588C24419B914D8634117BDEEE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title>, and not less frequently than once every 180 days thereafter, the President shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a certification that each person listed in an annex of United Nations Security Council Resolution 1737 (2006), 1747 (2007), or 1929 (2010) is not directly or indirectly facilitating, supporting, or involved with the development of or transfer to Iran of ballistic missiles or technology, parts, components, or technology information relating to ballistic missiles.</text>
								</subsection><subsection id="HAEF5F9E0F5D340A0AAB9BE2F71B6D6A4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header>
 <paragraph id="HF6519DA60DED4297A496FDDCF74F864F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the President is unable to make a certification under subsection (a) with respect to a person and the person is not currently subject to sanctions with respect to Iran under any other provision of law, the President shall, not later than 15 days after that certification would have been required under that subsection—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H01DDB2DAD34142FB99A1C72677AA434E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in accordance with the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.), block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of that person if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0676557148942D2A8557ABED8431174"><enum>(B)</enum><text>publish in the Federal Register a report describing the reason why the President was unable to make a certification with respect to that person.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H98D6832540644A00B7621DC1553A22B3"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Inapplicability of national emergency requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements under section 202 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref>) shall not apply for purposes of this subsection.</text>
									</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF41C613FB12649D78D0B6E277AA6DE3C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exclusion from United States</header>
 <paragraph id="H9FB10F222D97460A9B42B4D5EFA6FA3C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the Secretary of State shall deny a visa to, and the Secretary of Homeland Security shall exclude from the United States, any alien subject to blocking of property and interests in property under subsection (b).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5A8BD2EE11CB45188BCD90D7CE718A09"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compliance with United Nations headquarters agreement</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to the head of state of Iran, or necessary staff of that head of state, if admission to the United States is necessary to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H76CCD95006B04455A5E9C4A671ABF2A3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Facilitation of certain transactions</header><text>The President shall prohibit the opening, and prohibit or impose strict conditions on the maintaining, in the United States of a correspondent account or a payable-through account by a foreign financial institution that the President determines knowingly, on or after the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title>, conducts or facilitates a significant financial transaction for a person subject to blocking of property and interests in property under subsection (b).</text>
								</subsection></section><section id="HD208606D059F4170916DE76DB68FA308"><enum>235.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions with respect to certain sectors of Iran that support the ballistic missile
			 program of Iran</header>
								<subsection id="H5B6579F0ACF64DE6BF2D67236CF16461"><enum>(a)</enum><header>List of sectors</header>
 <paragraph id="H5B05F9D1F15143248B64FCE955EF2F85"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title>, and not less frequently than once every 180 days thereafter, the President shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress and publish in the Federal Register a list of the sectors of the economy of Iran that are directly or indirectly facilitating, supporting, or involved with the development of or transfer to Iran of ballistic missiles or technology, parts, components, or technology information relating to ballistic missiles.</text>
									</paragraph><paragraph id="HC41BA3E3C2234D7BAA048AD4D45C0332"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certain sectors</header>
 <subparagraph id="HB7EC977ECBDD448585DA081D8F0F5B68"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title>, the President shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a determination as to whether each of the automotive, chemical, computer science, construction, electronic, energy, metallurgy, mining, petrochemical, research (including universities and research institutions), and telecommunications sectors of Iran meet the criteria specified in paragraph (1).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9880E039A3134B3A9787D75E58C41FA6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion in initial list</header><text>If the President determines under subparagraph (A) that the sectors of the economy of Iran specified in such subparagraph meet the criteria specified in paragraph (1), that sector shall be included in the initial list submitted and published under that paragraph.</text>
										</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H82EE664E0FE64557A4F1C47B3CEEAD40"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sanctions with respect to specified sectors of Iran</header>
									<paragraph id="HF8179FC9BB8447ADBD562D51D55238FC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header>
 <subparagraph id="HC7DC405C68774DCB91583799CED5FF98"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President shall, in accordance with the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> et seq.), block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of any person described in paragraph (4) if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8E714287389A42F9B31F6BBF877C2F6B"><enum>(B)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Inapplicability of national emergency requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements under section 202 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref>) shall not apply for purposes of this paragraph.</text>
										</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2BC6E679E364D91AB4905F0B9DE0A0A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusion from United States</header>
 <subparagraph id="H82A083D341784E2BBC3328AB97F750BB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the Secretary of State shall deny a visa to, and the Secretary of Homeland Security shall exclude from the United States, any alien that is a person described in paragraph (4).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBBA19E4DB8242FEA07E1E19672A31BA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Compliance with United Nations headquarters agreement</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply to the head of state of Iran, or necessary staff of that head of state, if admission to the United States is necessary to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAA39AE215AE44162A61A19713BD8FFC6"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Facilitation of certain transactions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in this section, the President shall prohibit the opening, and prohibit or impose strict conditions on the maintaining, in the United States of a correspondent account or a payable-through account by a foreign financial institution that the President determines knowingly, on or after the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title>, conducts or facilitates a significant financial transaction for a person described in paragraph (4).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD46210EB34004773A255FFB0615C222A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Persons described</header><text>A person is described in this paragraph if the President determines that the person, on or after the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title>—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H2E33DEF608FA4C488E2E8F94F95ABEBB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>operates in a sector of the economy of Iran included in the most recent list published by the President under subsection (a);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7DEEA79AEA543C6A44FC4406387E0FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>knowingly provides significant financial, material, technological, or other support to, or goods or services in support of, any activity or transaction on behalf of or for the benefit of a person described in subparagraph (A); or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H776DBBA54DFA46BDA10143D0CA734F6A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is owned or controlled by a person described in subparagraph (A).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAB9034C221CC4848B57D1A914383DBE8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Humanitarian exception</header><text>The President may not impose sanctions under this section with respect to any person for conducting or facilitating a transaction for the sale of agricultural commodities, food, medicine, or medical devices to Iran or for the provision of humanitarian assistance to the people of Iran.</text>
								</subsection></section><section id="H8787C46647434B0EBCB0E86D4137AAF3"><enum>236.</enum><header>Identification of foreign persons that support the ballistic missile program of Iran in certain
			 sectors of Iran</header>
 <subsection id="H820B87AB66254BC09B18A7747AF64239"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title>, and not less frequently than annually thereafter, the President shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress and publish in the Federal Register a list of all foreign persons that have, based on credible information, directly or indirectly facilitated, supported, or been involved with the development of ballistic missiles or technology, parts, components, or technology information related to ballistic missiles in the following sectors of the economy of Iran during the period specified in subsection (b):</text>
 <paragraph id="H30EECA1E8C3C42ADAF9A8375DC274BDE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Automotive.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H737AA2E77577469A964B3B847482BDE9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Chemical.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFFB5F93CFEC24A9E85CB55991BBA90E4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Computer Science.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H4C10BE931DD4423B9046918773C92A21"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Construction.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3043E1E128344538AE955994CF9672BE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Electronic.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H207B5EC2C1D04E0699C04B47E89F9136"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Energy.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD0E35C344A624ECA9ED9342FBB952509"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Metallurgy.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HBF58DEB656FA4A2092AE80B41B6F746B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Mining.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFF7FE923CCB74A96BF7E9DE28C8D47C7"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Petrochemical.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H45B6955BD52E47BE8FB69E65B0A6A4A6"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Research (including universities and research institutions).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HEF9F2A87DF934995973A457F4F731CD6"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Telecommunications.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HFE0BF2283CA24CB79CE25CB204B1EA51"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Any other sector of the economy of Iran identified under section 235(a).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1AFAB8989EE74DE6946238E4E8C7A236"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Period specified</header><text>The period specified in this subsection is—</text> <paragraph id="HFDE95609B2EF49CCA946A32255C4CCD5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with respect to the first list submitted under subsection (a), the period beginning on the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Iran Ballistic Missile Sanctions Act of 2018</short-title> and ending on the date that is 120 days after such date of enactment; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2D3635DF143143CFA78150B869BA472E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with respect to each subsequent list submitted under such subsection, the one-year period preceding the submission of the list.</text>
									</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H43541E1879DA41749E6700FC4E047AF0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Comptroller General report</header>
 <paragraph id="H728053C8F47B448DA8F88E987C0E7168"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to each list submitted under subsection (a), not later than 120 days after the list is submitted under that subsection, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE750ED8909BE484E9731E48BE6BC5AE6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an assessment of the processes followed by the President in preparing the list;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC3B7C09E92B0489299561ED2F0FB3AD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an assessment of the foreign persons included in the list; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9028DADAA65E4A1D8FC7A82017DD8B92"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a list of persons not included in the list that qualify for inclusion in the list, as determined by the Comptroller General.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEA10F8FAB4143A8AF15DA0F81A6FE92"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultations</header><text>In preparing the report required by paragraph (1), the Comptroller General shall consult with nongovernmental organizations.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3FFCD1CF56C942A99B94F7EBF7C95E0E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Credible information defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>credible information</term> has the meaning given that term in section 14 of the Iran Sanctions Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/104/172">Public Law 104–172</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note).</text></subsection></section></subtitle><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HC590D43B27904D7794EA36B8F6BF53C3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents for the Iran Threat Reduction and Syria Human Rights Act of 2012 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 224 the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="HBC21CEBC544D4FC9BFDCC14308B50FE8" style="OLC">
						<toc>
							<toc-entry idref="HA68585CCBE524E30B7EA2A981CA8C4B1" level="subtitle">Subtitle C—Measures relating to ballistic missile program of Iran</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="HADC883AD58A14907B92E5DF180331BF7" level="section">Sec. 231. Definitions.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="HBDCA17CD4DF24006A42E2249A01802EB" level="section">Sec. 232. Imposition of sanctions with respect to persons that support the ballistic missile
			 program of Iran.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="HA15B13965C8B4DDE931A46490B0262AB" level="section">Sec. 233. Blocking of property of persons affiliated with certain Iranian entities.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="HC85A0FEE035B4FFB83691974D1ADAAE9" level="section">Sec. 234. Imposition of sanctions with respect to certain persons involved in ballistic missile
			 activities.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="HD208606D059F4170916DE76DB68FA308" level="section">Sec. 235. Imposition of sanctions with respect to certain sectors of Iran that support the
			 ballistic missile program of Iran.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="H8787C46647434B0EBCB0E86D4137AAF3" level="section">Sec. 236. Identification of foreign persons that support the ballistic missile program of Iran in
			 certain sectors of Iran.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</subsection></section><section id="H5C721C8C98B04DD7B95E2358CF015551"><enum>306.</enum><header>Expansion of mandatory sanctions with respect to financial institutions that engage in certain
 transactions relating to ballistic missile capabilities of Iran</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 104 of the Comprehensive Iran Sanctions, Accountability, and Divestment Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8513">22 U.S.C. 8513</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H24AE75E0863C4D2F9285423235EBADC9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (c)(2)—</text> <subparagraph id="H8C0C6871B50D4E6EAA81554CCBA3B4F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (A)—</text>
 <clause id="HD9592372BDFC44B9843F215A088D3DCE"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in clause (i), by striking <quote>; or</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text> </clause><clause id="H21529352A4034512BF63CE491961E8ED"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by redesignating clause (ii) as clause (iii); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H46CE7A70722042288AF613943B2E2B0E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (i) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2576204EA7E5492A9AB86B2A64B7DF76" style="OLC"> <clause id="HE249414224E24B1F834DCB6B254B60E9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to acquire or develop ballistic missiles and capabilities and launch technology relating to ballistic missiles; or</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A0EBFA832F1433694A4EAD31D40E964"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E)(ii)—</text> <clause id="HC9E4B6EAE0A8482D98FFF874B74AD975"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subclause (I), by striking <quote>; or</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HFEEAA3E8EEBD497F982D57E5FEC98639"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by redesignating subclause (II) as subclause (III); and</text> </clause><clause id="H04C5032837A14FDF9B07FBE2B897BB99"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting after subclause (I) the following:</text>
							<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3AC48ABB37924F6E9FBC2A9589FF0D97" style="OLC">
 <subclause id="HA250F1E2830C418BA6FEFB75C2CAC856"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Iran’s development of ballistic missiles and capabilities and launch technology relating to ballistic missiles; or</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H24BBC9F5CAE04B91B4D9CBFF70E27956"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (f)—</text> <subparagraph id="HEB235D1CC46447069984D1F3D4A6FFF7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) and (2) as subparagraphs (A) and (B), respectively, and moving those subparagraphs, as so redesignated, two ems to the right;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE009BD0611E465D90A9D037D0300BA0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Waiver</header-in-text>.—The</quote> and inserting “<header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Waiver</header-in-text>.—</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H80B6C25F96C341859F15B542C0CB8695" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HDFCF9BAC64224910AA1EABEA25810458"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HABB51828F372444CAC7BDA21BAB9A8D0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9300A9C19CDA4AA8A818E419D8B70554" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H5DA5EB8CD81B404984F0335FC2F40AB5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury may not waive under paragraph (1) the application of a prohibition or condition imposed with respect to an activity described in subparagraph (A)(ii) or (E)(ii)(II) of subsection (c)(2).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE57765D3EC1C4F6C8994A8965486C090"><enum>307.</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall prescribe regulations to carry out this title and the amendments made by this title.</text>
			</section></title></legis-body></bill>


