<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HF75C3F3412544BA78EDDAC3939FB1145" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5813 IH: Removing Onerous Obstacles in the Tax code for Mainstreet Businesses Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5813</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180515">May 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000578">Mr. Reichert</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001293">Mr. Bishop of Michigan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to exclude from the definition of personal holding
			 company income certain royalties and rents derived in the active conduct
			 of a trade or business.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H4A8836E058D04218932C50FA723ACF5E" style="OLC">
 <section id="HC499BD1969E949FEA3F9EC18FAA2AA59" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Removing Onerous Obstacles in the Tax code for Mainstreet Businesses Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or as the <quote><short-title>ROOT for Mainstreet Businesses Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HDF3FFBA942CD4B00BCF363F5E1D2F203"><enum>2.</enum><header>Certain royalties and rents derived in the active conduct of a trade or business not treated as personal holding company income</header> <subsection id="HFA2681BB9D254BCE89B6A875F4BCC682"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Royalties</header> <paragraph id="HC7CB81B7C0F84AC786B847B78722D516"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/543">Section 543(a)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of subparagraph (D), by striking the period at the end of subparagraph (E) and inserting <quote>, and</quote>, and by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H37608B9295CF481F8C7F9936A74AADA5" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="HE6EE71DAFB11451DA6EB5A6700A6A3D6"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">royalties derived in the active conduct of a trade or business which are received from a person other than a related person (within the meaning of section 267).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2281611CDAD94D298150E98D291B0985"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Copyright royalties</header><text>Section 543(a)(4) of such Code is amended by inserting <quote>or to any amount derived in the active conduct of a trade or business which are received from a person other than a related person (within the meaning of section 267)</quote> after <quote>active business computer software royalties</quote> in the last sentence thereof.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2CE402812FDE40199E8F70E7DF45E6FB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rents</header>
 <paragraph id="H0AFB70BA936844639B68FBEE24C0E4D3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 543(b)(3) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of subparagraph (D), by striking the period at the end of subparagraph (E) and inserting <quote>, or</quote>, and by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H03367292220D4FF8935B6583A0F9F1F5" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H32237611E26E4AB4A809C1FA1258D78D"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">amounts derived in the active conduct of a trade or business which are received from a person other than a related person (within the meaning of section 267).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9D73A436ABF947D4B7916288AAB87F3D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Produced film rents</header><text>Section 543(a)(5)(B) of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>Such term shall not include any amount derived in the active conduct of a trade or business which are received from a person other than a related person (within the meaning of section 267).</quote></text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1E0272AB06034E9D89BDB42D70A21271"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Section 543 of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H53CD1B27F6F440FA9B942D52208CBBF0" style="OLC"> <subsection id="HC4EE385DAED84A218D0A45C4999E9A9A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Determination of whether royalties and rents are derived in the active conduct of a trade or business</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall prescribe regulations or other guidance providing for the treatment of rents, royalties, and other amounts described in subsections (a)(1)(F), (a)(4), (a)(5)(B), and (b)(3)(F) as being derived in the active conduct of a trade or business consistent with the regulations and other guidance providing for such treatment for purposes of section 954(c)(2)(A).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H625149241D234F768A5F3457077CCA53"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years ending on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


