<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HF7B349677C1B4C2E96B591C8A067FBD7" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5892 IH: To establish an Advisory Committee on Opioids and the Workplace to advise the Secretary of Labor on actions the Department of Labor can take to address the impact of opioid abuse on the workplace.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5892</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180521">May 21, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000587">Mr. Lewis of Minnesota</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish an Advisory Committee on Opioids and the Workplace to advise the Secretary of Labor on
			 actions the Department of Labor can take to address the impact of opioid
			 abuse on the workplace.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H661F235E3A204B568BB76FE0AD36B8CF" style="OLC">
		<section id="H13D4F7E04D434FD1BBF211E0A11A8593" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Establishment of an Advisory Committee on Opioids and the Workplace</header>
 <subsection id="H302E3CDF82F84E89B0E30E50C3B468B3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor shall establish an Advisory Committee on Opioids and the Workplace (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Advisory Committee</quote>) to advise the Secretary on actions the Department of Labor can take to provide informational resources and best practices on how to appropriately address the impact of opioid abuse on the workplace and support workers abusing opioids.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H65260BDDBDAE4E389905784687BB504D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header>
 <paragraph id="H1780A5A472A84779B4F70A62C94AD983"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Composition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Labor shall appoint as members of the Advisory Committee 19 individuals with expertise in employment, workplace health programs, human resources, substance use disorder, and other relevant fields. The Advisory Committee shall be composed as follows:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H68039755C9D24B6FBF26E6B875121B19"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">4 of the members shall be individuals representative of employers or other organizations representing employers.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD353CE6AF824433B10D542445E2ADD6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">4 of the members shall be individuals representative of workers or other organizations representing workers, of which at least 2 must be representatives designated by labor organizations.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H136C3DB9D53744B7897472DEEF514491"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">3 of the members shall be individuals representative of health benefit plans, employee assistance plan providers, workers’ compensation program administrators, and workplace safety and health professionals.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD390FFF0A5974AAEA1FA294AE035022E"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">8 of the members shall be individuals representative of substance abuse treatment and recovery experts, including medical doctors, licensed addiction therapists, and scientific and academic researchers, of which 1 individual may be a representative of a local or State government agency that oversees or coordinates programs that address substance use disorder.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B179FE5DE394474923C035398BE5945"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Chair</header><text>From the members appointed under paragraph (1), the Secretary of Labor shall appoint a chairperson.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H62BACAE4120A4C3B9AA13EE1765CA5C9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Terms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each member of the Advisory Committee shall serve for a term of three years. A member appointed to fill a vacancy shall be appointed only for the remainder of such term.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H37BD660779D64A1A81ED81C1FCF9B7F9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A majority of members of the Advisory Committee shall constitute a quorum and action shall be taken only by a majority vote of the members.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBF76B2BFBC104B07BE8BF930C746C416"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Voting</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall establish voting procedures.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HC7A525CC8A0042E9926E020E48E86CB9"><enum>(6)</enum><header>No compensation</header><text>Members of the Advisory Committee shall serve without compensation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2CCAB37589334E408E10C8D7D7180AD6"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Disclosure</header><text>Every member of the Advisory Committee must disclose the entity, if applicable, that he or she is representing.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1997F0CFAF3C470A971293BDEDB4114C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header>
				<paragraph id="HE31A7DEF399046F4AA04F0524AF47288"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advisement</header>
 <subparagraph id="H9257B520FD8A4C82B792A28D85C73B80"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Advisory Committee established under subsection (a) shall advise the Secretary of Labor on actions the Department of Labor can take to provide informational resources and best practices on how to appropriately address the impact of opioid abuse on the workplace and support workers abusing opioids.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A60883D7DE14345A0A7A9B7470D2B3A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In providing such advice, the Advisory Committee shall take into account—</text> <clause id="HFC6BF551C65B465088F9600894ECB10F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evidence-based and other employer substance abuse policies and best practices regarding opioid use or abuse, including benefits provided by employee assistance programs or other employer-provided benefits, programs, or resources;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HE5CDF5D8DC254FC0AAB32B838CB67197"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the effect of opioid use or abuse on the safety of the workplace as well as policies and procedures addressing workplace safety and health;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H635349FD85394F3BAE9D5D9C9A69C011"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the impact of opioid abuse on productivity and absenteeism, and assessments of model human resources policies that support workers abusing opioids, such as policies that facilitate seeking and receiving treatment and returning to work;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1A94F795012F48E4A40615ED30EF79B6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which alternative pain management treatments other than opioids are or should be covered by employer-sponsored health plans;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H9FDC9383E37D4DEB8E8FCA69D7AF46EB"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the legal requirements protecting employee privacy and health information in the workplace, as well as the legal requirements related to nondiscrimination;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H6EF5C300DE1345F48574350373C7C861"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">potential interactions of opioid abuse with other substance use disorders;</text> </clause><clause id="H5401A5819B5E41FE80928E42F5770FF5"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>any additional benefits or resources available to an employee abusing opioids that promote retaining employment or reentering the workforce;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HFD4992D79B2349F29CF8FF8893DC0B8D"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evidence-based initiatives that engage employers, employees, and community leaders to promote early identification of opioid abuse, intervention, treatment, and recovery;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HCA1D8AEC86DE40ACB0604C259F876A66"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">workplace policies regarding opioid abuse that reduce stigmatization among fellow employees and management; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB68D3ACBBAC846E8955E717B72940C09"><enum>(x)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the legal requirements of the Mental Health Parity and Addiction Equity Act and other laws related to health coverage of substance abuse and mental health services and medications.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0448C0DBE0E6448688C8906D78873D7C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Prior to its termination as provided in subsection (j), the Advisory Committee shall issue a report to the Secretary of Labor and to the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, detailing successful programs and policies involving workplace resources and benefits, including recommendations or examples of best practices for how employers can support and respond to employees impacted by opioid abuse.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAA7550870EFE47159F2AAC95FB4D1FE9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall meet at least twice a year at the call of the chairperson.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H8B021F9FD3B34052BE5AD093A25C7C1C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Staff support</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Labor shall make available staff necessary for the Advisory Committee to carry out its responsibilities.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H7DF404F3845544039069759FBC3B61E6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Federal Advisory Committee Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Advisory Committee Act shall apply to the Advisory Committee established under this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HC1EF4EB0F247454F86250F00E8FFEFE3"><enum>(g)</enum><header>No appropriated funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No additional funds are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act. Expenses of the Advisory Committee shall be paid with funds otherwise appropriated to Departmental Management within the Department of Labor.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H32DA32C0652840E7935AE9A0AE7B21FC"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Ex officio</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Three nonvoting representatives from agencies within the Department of Health and Human Services whose responsibilities include opioid prescribing guidelines, workplace safety, and monitoring of substance abuse and prevention programs shall be appointed by the Secretary of Labor and designated as ex officio members.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H40913F7A5A424A90B544272E7E62C7CD"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Agenda</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Labor or a representative of the Secretary shall consult with the Chair in establishing the agenda for Committee meetings.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H008B6DAE88174EA898B0DA9F88FEE60F"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Termination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Advisory Committee established under this Act shall terminate three years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


