<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HC39DD63E405D472C83840C343328A381" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5118 IH: USAccounts: Investing in America’s Future Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5118</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180227">February 27, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001038">Mr. Crowley</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="E000288">Mr. Ellison</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish USAccounts, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H29CF0980BF61494399B571CAD50F044B" style="OLC">
		<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5F2C7E0E6DB14C67B0C15AA1A8D60767" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header>
 <subsection id="HD03FD7FFEAA84A6684655E2CD2B99E17"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>USAccounts: Investing in America’s Future Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H82FB54D4E9A94A0DAAABE0E58262B1E8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
				<toc container-level="legis-body-container" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration">
					<toc-entry idref="H5F2C7E0E6DB14C67B0C15AA1A8D60767" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HD05528E85D0549F7B9841E49F0EBDBDD" level="section">Sec. 2. Findings.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HFA267C97F8F44FC78698156D282AE776" level="section">Sec. 3. USAccount Fund.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H615489D4FB7548399AC8A283D56E7DEF" level="section">Sec. 4. USAccounts.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H89F63A37FD5D484BB9CEA88DCF0D04E6" level="section">Sec. 5. Assignment, alienation, and treatment of deceased individuals.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H9A3CDA77D3014F81973700FF322DAFD2" level="section">Sec. 6. Rules governing USAccounts relating to investment, accounting, and reporting.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H07EAE57F632649A2AF64F8D0A18EF66F" level="section">Sec. 7. USAccount Fund Board.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H46FC51F252C64E408668CE8D0923E9A3" level="section">Sec. 8. Fiduciary responsibilities.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H7405F887F60F47179F86278DF52BCC90" level="section">Sec. 9. Accounts disregarded in determining eligibility for Federal benefits.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H99FB5F420F0646E49B5B0007A8B3258B" level="section">Sec. 10. Reports.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HCD03C839FD2144F9BED891E57AB14E0D" level="section">Sec. 11. Tax provisions.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry committee-id="HFB04792D80D14BD482070F2F598C29E5" level="section">Sec. 12. Earned Income Tax Credit outreach.</toc-entry></toc>
 </subsection><subsection id="H0D131AF78D2B4E5F84D0D852583EDE1C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this Act—</text> <paragraph id="HE1100230635F425DBB14877518FD6B90"><enum>(1)</enum><header>U<enum-in-header>SA</enum-in-header>ccount Fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>USAccount Fund</term> means the fund established under section 3.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H141E8F27796D4A2B982A250480B51269"><enum>(2)</enum><header>U<enum-in-header>SA</enum-in-header>ccount</header><text>The term <term>USAccount</term> means an account established under section 4.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HA7FC89F991CA4B179355F4C65F33ADAD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Treasury or the Secretary’s delegate.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2CFE9DE3485A445D932C4D21BD32733E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>U<enum-in-header>SA</enum-in-header>ccount Fund Board</header><text>The term <term>USAccount Fund Board</term> means the board established pursuant to section 7.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HEB76D3145542424ABF4F24C2FDF536AD"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Executive Director</header><text>The term <term>Executive Director</term> means the executive director appointed pursuant to section 7.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD05528E85D0549F7B9841E49F0EBDBDD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="H06A9887EF85343849B7B67351D6A5DA3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Americans recognize the importance of savings to create a more secure financial future for their family but barriers to entry have blocked participation in savings programs, leading to drastic disparities in asset building and wealth creation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7A4FE4C4D6A449D697494F9B20D7901E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Most working families in America lack savings and face financial insecurity as a result. Forty-four percent of families are <quote>liquid asset poor</quote>, meaning they lack accessible savings to survive for three months at the Federal poverty level.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7EDF3A5102334AF597C4C4250AC14765"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Of that number, over two-thirds of African-Americans (67 percent) could be considered <quote>liquid asset poor</quote> as are nearly three-fourths of Latinos (71 percent).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HBE0D6FE340C8463A97CEEC0A7BC6A5EF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Families with children face additional barriers to building savings. These families are more likely than childless households to live in asset poverty.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4D393007A142495F930F9C966C60928A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>There is a strong link between savings and economic opportunity. Children in the poorest fifth of households who manage to move up the income ladder as adults have almost ten times the wealth of those who remain at the bottom.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE855F6E3232147718A62FB500B9B0A2E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Children's savings accounts programs are evidence-based and have been tested throughout the country. In 2003, the Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship, and Downpayment (SEED) national demonstration project was established to evaluate the policy and practice of savings accounts for children. SEED found that even very low-income parents will save and invest for their children's future if given the opportunity.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H20FE8E1C56D241D59DBA19F4F398078E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>In 2011, the city of San Francisco began offering child savings accounts, expanding them to all children enrolled in public kindergarten starting in 2013. Their experiment proves what SEED documented in 2003—very low-income parents will save and invest for their children's future if given the opportunity.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1B4D034C04774F0C85A6B1EF83B34E8E"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Data from San Francisco’s nascent Kindergarten to College Account program demonstrates that families, even those of lower income, are contributing their own funds towards their child’s education at a rate of four times higher than Americans of all income limits are towards tax advantaged 529 college savings plans.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8151953A4A6A430689AB51CECA87E878"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Even a small amount of children's savings can have a significant impact on college success, a key driver of economic mobility. Low- and moderate-income children with less than $500 saved for college are three times more likely to enroll in college and four times more likely to graduate than children with no savings.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDC73843693164FFE964206C538D06537"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Since the San Francisco program has been in existence, families have saved $5,200,000, helping build assets for participating families.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5C01494969C648B9BE2EE99117F0D3B3"><enum>(11)</enum><text>In order to expand economic opportunity and spur economic growth, the United States should promote savings and investments for all Americans.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="HFA267C97F8F44FC78698156D282AE776"><enum>3.</enum><header>USAccount Fund</header>
 <subsection id="H84059E6DEC72412CA3D13A005BBEE8B4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the Treasury of the United States a fund to be known as the <quote>USAccount Fund</quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H4106236B6A4D4DC1B5A9218BEC962C6E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amounts held by Fund</header><text>The USAccount Fund consists of the sum of all amounts paid into the Fund under this Act, increased by the total net earnings from investments of sums held in the Fund or reduced by the total net losses from investments of sums held in the Fund, and reduced by the total amount of payments made from the Fund (including payments for administrative expenses).</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H6873A6840B2042B38E5A67E5954848A5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of Fund</header>
 <paragraph id="H2296E9CC3FE241F18145415D107AF2C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The sums in the USAccount Fund are appropriated and shall remain available without fiscal year limitation—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H8634E044B92B49DC880BA84FD5B27C83"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to make contributions to USAccounts,</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70B79A2049474119A96CB76AB7220355"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to invest under section 6,</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD19BF0C32E1941F1AE23D00FE399A73D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to make distributions in accordance with this Act,</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78D2755EDC1E4D3CBC4E7B337B63D9BD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to pay the administrative expenses of carrying out this Act, and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H6A406D25706649C9929CE77C3B46CF3B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to purchase insurance as provided in section 8(c)(2).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5187477AD944D8FA060223ACD4C3C16"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusive purposes</header><text>The sums in the USAccount Fund shall not be appropriated for any purpose other than the purposes specified in this section and may not be used for any other purpose.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3B301528EDB64B36BB8F909449C6630C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Transfers to USAccount Fund</header><text>The Secretary shall make transfers from the general fund of the Treasury to the USAccount Fund as follows:</text>
 <paragraph id="H85AD03B4AE274EE9A179B1C220D7EAE5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Automatic contribution</header><text>Upon receipt of a certification under section 4(b)(2) with respect to an individual, the Secretary shall transfer $500 to the USAccount of the individual.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3F4FCDA2CBC74D5986EE1A203B334E13"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matching contributions</header><text>Upon receipt of each certification under section 4(d) with respect to an individual, the Secretary shall transfer the matching amount to the USAccount of the individual.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H034AA1342CD0477EB7A574056732662D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Private contributions</header><text>The Executive Director shall pay into the USAccount Fund such amounts as are contributed under section 4(c).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H20C58593EF74493A81619766783B89E7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Prohibition on Use of Payroll Taxes To Fund USAccounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The USAccount Fund and USAccounts are wholly separate and unique from the Social Security system. No amount from any tax on employment may be contributed to the USAccount Fund or USAccounts.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H615489D4FB7548399AC8A283D56E7DEF"><enum>4.</enum><header>USAccounts</header>
			<subsection id="H437FB9C743F145F1A92B33F9A52EBD06"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header>
 <paragraph id="H78761F2FF1334F9EA2B32F05DDFC35AE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Executive Director shall establish in the USAccount Fund an account (to be known as a <quote>USAccount</quote>) for each qualifying account holder certified under subsection (b). Each such account shall be identified to its account holder by means of a unique personal identifier currently recognized by the Internal Revenue Service and shall remain in the USAccount Fund unless transferred to private management under subsection (g).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3EED3521851E4A068D62CCF3C3561D12"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Account balance</header><text>The balance in an account holder’s USAccount at any time is the excess of—</text> <subparagraph id="H7F3B37506C94493F9300003744449328"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the sum of—</text>
 <clause id="HE0657EEE2DD2410EAE3B881F24D7525F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>all deposits made into the USAccount Fund and credited to the account under paragraph (3), and</text> </clause><clause id="H90A4BE06DBFB43A3ABFE8048C45E0E1A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total amount of allocations made to and reductions made in the account pursuant to paragraph (4), over</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC42FE5B8E3154692975E12CD40F44B47"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the amounts paid out of the account with respect to such individual under subsection (d).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H441FF28DB34B49019E1AAE2DD02C5564"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Crediting of contributions</header><text>Pursuant to regulations which shall be prescribed by the Executive Director, the Executive Director shall credit to each USAccount the amounts paid into the USAccount Fund under section 3(d) which are attributable to the account holder of such account.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H22A9CF5493BE4EC1B0DC78E199CB7663"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Allocation of earnings and losses</header><text>The Executive Director shall allocate to each USAccount an amount equal to the net earnings and net losses from each investment of sums in the USAccount Fund which are attributable, on a pro rata basis, to sums credited to such account, reduced by an appropriate share of the administrative expenses paid out of the net earnings, as determined by the Executive Director.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H9D8993BEFA084761872A570DD96954C9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualifying account holder</header><text>For purposes of this Act—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H254F58770B884A6F97112C5CE22B5933"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>qualifying account holder</term> means any individual who—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H5CBD9710D18043BB8D4861E9B5DE228D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>was born after December 31, 2018,</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HD78C7B3D9B86490CB69FA7215B5C6A07"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has not yet attained the age of 18 years, and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H14A24BC5E2C645CAB86149B281D38DBC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has a valid, unique, Federal Government issued identification number recognized by the Internal Revenue Service.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H14698505673C47D6862AAC1228A1BF80"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certification of account holders</header><text>On the date on which a qualifying account holder is registered for a USAccount, the Secretary shall certify to the Executive Director the name of such qualifying account holder.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6FD5C3451BB44A6C92D4CF7BBAA8A6E2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Private contributions</header>
 <paragraph id="HEEFB92A74E5C466E854C0B3881531BB0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Executive Director shall accept cash contributions from any person (including churches, charities, private foundations, businesses, or civic leagues) for payment into the USAccount Fund if such contribution is identified (in such manner as the Executive Director may require) with the account holder of a USAccount to whom it is to be credited at the time the contribution is made.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HB57F854DD09B409FB78984A07D98034C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Alternative methods of contribution</header>
 <subparagraph id="H0C29296876A344ADB0B3DF78ACB9F754"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Payroll deduction</header><text>Under regulations prescribed by the Executive Director and at the election of the employer, contributions under paragraph (1) may be made through payroll deductions.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66FE19893AD143FE89F51079FB7B8AC9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Tax refunds</header><text>Under regulations prescribed by the Secretary, contributions under paragraph (1) may be made by an election to contribute all or a portion of the tax refund of the contributor.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H428B0593E38E42CB9D8EC54D138F6710"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Annual limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No contribution may be accepted under paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H1DE3466587984750A5DD106AA7149EF6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>unless it is in cash,</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5D8B8AF7E444D31945190761A9FE925"><enum>(B)</enum><text>after the date on which the USAccount holder ceases to be a qualifying account holder, and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2961F35E788244E19A5B02117FBF6FD3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>except in the case of matching contributions under subsection (d), if such contribution would result in aggregate contributions for the calendar year exceeding $2,000.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE33A9DF1624040F68CB2D28C7A9F2113"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Government matching contribution</header>
 <paragraph id="HD43B0DA6049944D49C829C8635584B2E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon such showing as the Executive Director may require to establish the basis for certification, the Executive Director shall, with respect to each private contribution to the account of an account holder which is made before such account holder attains age 18, certify to the Secretary the matching amount with respect to such contribution.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H96A8A620D8FC4404B2B7D4A74E166EE1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matching amount</header>
 <subparagraph id="H259ACF02519543228FF66CE11D9671A5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>matching amount</term> means, an amount equal to 100 percent of contributions made by the account holder (or a legal guardian of the account holder) to the USAccount of an individual during any calendar year beginning after the calendar year in which the USAccount is established, not in excess of $500 for the calendar year.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71216748222C46A5AF57B3E98B63017B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Phaseout based on earned income credit phaseout</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The $500 amount in subparagraph (A) shall be zero if the adjusted gross income (or, if greater, the earned income) of the taxpayer for the taxable year as exceeds the phaseout amount. For purposes of this paragraph, terms used in the preceding sentence which are used in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/32">section 32</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 shall have the meanings given such terms by such section 32.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6BD3D96840E84B0B9E3E25BDD572C0AD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Distributions</header>
 <paragraph id="H0486DB518F31450DAB6B94845503AE71"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No amount may be distributed from a USAccount before the date on which the account holder attains the age of 18.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7903FCD866C849BEA2D906027B191395"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Higher education expenses</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to amounts paid for qualified tuition and related expenses (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/25A">section 25A(f)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) of the account holder if the account holder is an eligible student (as defined in section 25A(b)(3) of such Code) with respect to such expenses.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3AEA77791C464513982031B70073F86F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rollover</header>
 <subparagraph id="H4A922CC154C746178101D1680B79EC28"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which the account holder attains the age of 18, the balance of such individual’s account shall be transferred to a USAccount IRA established on behalf of the individual and shall be treated as a rollover contribution which meets the requirements of section 408(d)(3) of such Code.</text>
					</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9AEED97DB6774B48B64FD08D16F612BB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>U<enum-in-header>SA</enum-in-header>ccount IRA</header>
 <clause id="HA37964F22A90456997ECB85B14F4A3FB"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clauses (ii) and (iii), a USAccount IRA is an individual retirement account (as defined in section 7701(a)(37) of such Code) which is established by the Executive Director and designated at the time of the establishment of the account as a USAccount IRA.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA5C576195AA543C9B2EE49C002E49A70"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Distributions</header><text>No amount may be distributed from a USAccount IRA to an account holder or other beneficiary earlier than the account holder attains the age of 59<fraction>1/2</fraction>, except—</text>
 <subclause id="H482A67859B494BE3B2C9584D09A64925"><enum>(I)</enum><text>distributions which are made to a beneficiary (or to the estate of the account holder) upon death of the account holder,</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H6D7FFD3D65CE41D2B67C87410FC4BC0D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>distributions described in paragraph (2),</text> </subclause><subclause id="H4A35A4C1FCD247239C7260E4B47B46B3"><enum>(III)</enum><text>qualified first-time homebuyer distributions (as defined in section 72(t)(8) of such Code),</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HBB40174A130B48B2A0F94709AE64FB44"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>distributions for qualified medical expenses,</text> </subclause><subclause id="HCEE59EA3BEDB43CF920405F54CC74C2E"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any distribution which would not be includible in gross income if made from a qualified ABLE program (as defined in section 529A(b) of such Code) with respect to the account holder or a member of the family (as defined in section 529A(e)(4)) of the account holder,</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HCFC703B6DCE64FBE9EEE0C6742D54F97"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>any distribution used to prevent foreclosure on the principal residence of the account holder, and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H452509654D06409C8C13F87702C2CD8B"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>any distribution used to start a small business.</text>
 </subclause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="clause">Any distribution described in subclauses (I) through (VII) shall not be included in gross income.</continuation-text></clause><clause id="H75B6D8D4CAE348D6B6588A001C5B81BC"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>No rollovers from USAccount IRA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No amounts may be rolled over from a USAccount IRA.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCFE14B254F2C4749BAF9758ADA443D9B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rights of legal guardian</header><text>Until the account holder of a USAccount attains age 18, any rights or duties of the account holder under this Act with respect to such account shall be exercised or performed by the legal guardian of such account holder.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H35D8F40B6EAB4439BFBF8872CD449129"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Private management</header>
 <paragraph id="H5686BB0EEBF948A7A923B815F7363760"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The account holder of a USAccount may elect, under regulations prescribed by the Secretary, to transfer the USAccount to a trustee who meets the requirements of paragraph (2).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H14BF13C326554B8AB018F253F5D575C1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Trustee requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A trustee meets the requirements of this paragraph if the trustee—</text> <subparagraph id="HE62401B002CE445C8E8633BB25B88A25"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a bank (as defined in section 408(n)) or another person who demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Secretary that the manner in which that person will administer the USAccount will be consistent with the requirements of this Act or who has so demonstrated with respect to any USAccount,</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD88135AFAA864A3687B4976430EB79F1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">agrees to a reasonable cap on its fees and costs, as determined by the Treasury, for the management of USAccounts,</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3CCEBA18C1ED4FC38A492E436F2F4751"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provides an investment fund that maximizes growth over time while minimizing risk, and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBAB3156656BC4051ADB2FBD8416551E4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provides the safeguards with respect to USAccounts required by the Secretary.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CB37D68129C418D90376AC4AACB584E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional requirements</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, rules similar to the rules of paragraphs (3), (4), and (5) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/408">section 408</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 shall apply.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDAA5DEC3F2D1492585CA2B7375EEEA7F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Adjustment for inflation</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="H18D03D3A5E694AAFAB16D7E74B59D811"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For each calendar year beginning after 2019, the dollar amounts under sections 3(e)(1), 4(c)(3)(C), and 4(d)(2) shall each be increased by such dollar amount multiplied by the cost-of-living adjustment determined under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1">section 1(f)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 determined by substituting <quote>calendar year 2018</quote> for <quote>calendar year 2016</quote> in subparagraph (B) thereof.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4DC93B82D1144A14B88E5385C203BD01"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rounding</header><text>If any amount adjusted under paragraph (1) is not a multiple of $50, such amount shall be rounded to the next lowest multiple of $50.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H89F63A37FD5D484BB9CEA88DCF0D04E6"><enum>5.</enum><header>Assignment, alienation, and treatment of deceased individuals</header>
 <subsection id="H5921015C79D245A98764F3FDE6190E9E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Assignment and alienation</header><text>Under regulations which shall be prescribed by the Executive Director, rules relating to assignment and alienation applicable under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/84">chapter 84</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, with respect to amounts held in accounts in the Thrift Savings Fund shall apply with respect to amounts held in USAccounts in the USAccount Fund.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9E546F7F95AD4A9E81215E60C59342EC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Treatment of accounts of deceased individuals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a deceased account holder of a USAccount which has an account balance greater than zero, upon receipt of notification of such individual’s death, the Executive Director shall close the account and shall transfer the balance in such account to the duly appointed legal representative of the estate of the deceased account holder, or if there is no such representative, to the person or persons determined to be entitled thereto under the laws of the domicile of the deceased account holder.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H9A3CDA77D3014F81973700FF322DAFD2"><enum>6.</enum><header>Rules governing USAccounts relating to investment, accounting, and reporting</header>
 <subsection id="H4ACA23EE18C34E7BBA76AD349A585E6A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Default investment program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish, and the USAccount Fund Board shall invest in, a retirement savings bond that earns interest at the same annual percentage rate as securities issued to the Government Securities Investment Fund in the Thrift Savings Plan for Federal employees as determined under section 8438(e)(2) of title 5, United States Code, and shall be compounded daily at <fraction>1/260</fraction> of the annual percentage rate.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H7BACD082408B456C978F4681B5B46A1E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Other rules</header>
 <paragraph id="H80CD7701BE51448B9193762A89D064DB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Under regulations which shall be prescribed by the Executive Director, and subject to the provisions of this Act, the following provisions shall apply with respect to the USAccount Fund and accounts maintained in such Fund in the same manner and to the same extent as such provisions relate to the Thrift Savings Fund and the accounts maintained in the Thrift Savings Fund:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H72C0C2985098497F9AAFE1C110DF4C00"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Section 8438 of title 5, United States Code (relating to investment of the Thrift Savings Fund).</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H340839CF5FB842889A8C3665A48B6244"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Section 8439(b) of such title (relating to engagement of independent qualified public accountant).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7914CECEB1C34776882CFEC373A0B416"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Section 8439(c) of such title (relating to periodic statements and summary descriptions of investment options).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF8B9D3B457AE49918D2E485D72F584DA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Section 8439(d) of such title (relating to assumption of risk).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5049E0B1E1B14ABB83A4B711E250475F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application rules</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), references in such sections 8438 and 8439 to an employee, Member, former employee, or former Member shall be deemed references to an account holder of a USAccount in the USAccount Fund.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H667ABF1019274001B2009053794DBB91"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Confidentiality and disclosure</header>
 <paragraph id="H1E860BDE36D444B9BB2074B1A8F819EC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as otherwise authorized by Federal law, the USAccount Fund Board, the Executive Director, and any employee of the USAccount Fund Board shall not disclose information with respect to the USAccount Fund or any account maintained in such Fund.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H02989576ABB44F5581189B9CCD3A4134"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disclosure to designee of beneficiary</header><text>The Executive Director may, subject to such requirements and conditions as he may prescribe by regulations, disclose such information with respect to the USAccount of the beneficiary to such person or persons as the beneficiary may designate in a request for or consent to such disclosure, or to any other person at the beneficiary’s request to the extent necessary to comply with a request for information or assistance made by the beneficiary to such other person.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H07EAE57F632649A2AF64F8D0A18EF66F"><enum>7.</enum><header>USAccount Fund Board</header>
 <subsection id="H8EF025950624403EB4779E5A361C650E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is established in the executive branch of the Government a USAccount Fund Board.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H14B744B706E34162A8217393D5E048BC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Composition, duties, and responsibilities</header><text>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the following provisions shall apply with respect to the USAccount Fund Board in the same manner and to the same extent as such provisions relate to the Federal Retirement Thrift Investment Board:</text>
 <paragraph id="H5960CC8178254152922E90D1F3961DFC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Section 8472 of title 5, United States Code (relating to composition of Federal Retirement Thrift Investment Board).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H03F26A7C6A6D4E4FBD438C96A911C3F8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Section 8474 of such title (relating to Executive Director).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HC005C6A104F64E26BDDB5AA48B61BAC0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Section 8475 of such title (relating to investment policies).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8BCF2E299B784B67B805D248459CB012"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Section 8476 of such title (relating to administrative provisions).</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H46FC51F252C64E408668CE8D0923E9A3"><enum>8.</enum><header>Fiduciary responsibilities</header> <subsection id="H78A2B2461FCD464891EE7E283E389387"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Under regulations of the Secretary of Labor, the provisions of sections 8477 and 8478 of title 5, United States Code, shall apply in connection with the USAccount Fund and the accounts maintained in such Fund in the same manner and to the same extent as such provisions apply in connection with the Thrift Savings Fund and the accounts maintained in the Thrift Savings Fund.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H717B9052F0EA4E9E9D61D01CC63F57AB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Investigative authority</header><text>Any authority available to the Secretary of Labor under section 504 of the <act-name parsable-cite="ERISA">Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1134">29 U.S.C. 1134</external-xref>) is hereby made available to the Secretary of Labor, and any officer designated by the Secretary of Labor, to determine whether any person has violated, or is about to violate, any provision applicable under subsection (a).</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HF5B6FCE12A924C2AB6175662A7DC0A75"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exculpatory provisions; insurance</header>
 <paragraph id="HA4DCD1387A1E4F38BEC99869F05C243A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any provision in an agreement or instrument which purports to relieve a fiduciary from responsibility or liability for any responsibility, obligation, or duty under this Act shall be void.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H55120631BF5740258F17C60EEF3506E0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Insurance</header><text>Amounts in the USAccount Fund available for administrative expenses shall be available and may be used at the discretion of the Executive Director to purchase insurance to cover potential liability of persons who serve in a fiduciary capacity with respect to the Fund and accounts maintained therein, without regard to whether a policy of insurance permits recourse by the insurer against the fiduciary in the case of a breach of a fiduciary obligation.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7405F887F60F47179F86278DF52BCC90"><enum>9.</enum><header>Accounts disregarded in determining eligibility for Federal benefits</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Amounts in any USAccount shall not be taken into account in determining any individual’s or household’s financial eligibility for, or amount of, any benefit or service, paid for in whole or in part with Federal funds, including student financial aid.</text>
		</section><section id="H99FB5F420F0646E49B5B0007A8B3258B"><enum>10.</enum><header>Reports</header>
 <subsection id="H5E740B4A247046D09BC27E0F299A81B3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Executive Director, in consultation with the Secretary, shall annually transmit a written report to the Congress. Such report shall include—</text>
 <paragraph id="H03F97C882F944371B88F6CB7DFC1FB4C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a detailed description of the status and operation of the USAccount Fund and the management of the USAccounts, and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H380E157B0F6E4282BCC1544FB94939B1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a detailed accounting of the administrative expenses in carrying out this Act, including the ratio of such administrative expenses to the balance of the USAccount Fund and the methodology adopted by the Executive Director for allocating such expenses among the USAccounts.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H803B013BED6E46EC9E83D2AA02FFFA2F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports to account holders</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The USAccount Fund Board shall prescribe regulations under which each individual for whom a USAccount is maintained shall be furnished with an annual statement relating to the individual’s account, which shall include—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE554793359CE4DB3ABF69B9F96625149"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a statement of the balance of individual’s USAccount,</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HD26B7B2285DE4CAD89E1DA466DB4F4A7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a projection of the account’s growth by the time the individual attains the age of 18, and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8ABF4E4BF07B44B884450F4E3EFA6E2E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>such other information as the Secretary deems relevant.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HCD03C839FD2144F9BED891E57AB14E0D"><enum>11.</enum><header>Tax provisions</header> <subsection id="H39A3144848A542CA943BA7074178B8B9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Tax treatment of USAccounts</header><text>Subchapter F of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new part:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H15010DA13362466494F47C70D76AFA55" style="OLC">
					<part id="H9E1A553333D14BBC8861C5480D01A123"><enum>IX</enum><header>USAccount Fund and USAccounts</header>
						<toc container-level="part-container" idref="H9E1A553333D14BBC8861C5480D01A123" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration">
							<toc-entry idref="H1EF6D16CF34B454CAB9A81EA5A4F58B4" level="section">Sec. 530A. USAccount Fund and USAccounts.</toc-entry></toc>
						<section id="H1EF6D16CF34B454CAB9A81EA5A4F58B4"><enum>530A.</enum><header>USAccount Fund and USAccounts</header>
 <subsection id="HA4AEA1FD152C4EE48D7900788CD4B003"><enum>(a)</enum><header>General rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The USAccount Fund and USAccounts shall be exempt from taxation under this subtitle. Notwithstanding the preceding sentence, a USAccount shall be subject to the taxes imposed by section 511 (relating to imposition of tax on unrelated business income of charitable organizations).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H7C0B4422ACB04193ACF2CCD8232C7FBF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section, the terms <term>USAccount Fund</term> and <term>USAccount</term> have the meanings given such terms by the <short-title>USAccounts: Investing in America’s Future Act of 2018</short-title>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H64FABA1E23E241B69976BDFD53BB9F54"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Tax treatment of distributions</header><text>Any amount paid or distributed out of a USAccount—</text>
 <paragraph id="H5337BF08BC7D43B89FE2A79E98066A89"><enum>(1)</enum><text>which meets the distribution rules of the <short-title>USAccounts: Investing in America’s Future Act of 2018</short-title> shall not be includible in gross income, and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H4324918E562F49608178044B63F561C1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>which does not meet the distribution rules of section 4(e) of such Act shall be included in the gross income of the account holder.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H64B6892D7ED74AE5BB19072290907C21"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Enforcement provisions relating to private management of USAccounts</header>
 <paragraph id="H373B5D18FCFB445880FD0DB715D3EB86"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Excess contributions</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4973">Section 4973</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H7224A761D0F14C3B88E0434F49F5F9D6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of subsection (a)(4), by inserting <quote>or</quote> at the end of subsection (a)(5), and by inserting after subsection (a)(5) the following new paragraph:</text>
						<quoted-block id="H0502FBC56703421392EED6BA211CB19A" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="HFD9F6DF52402406E80F504D926FE00FD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a USAccount subject to management under section 4(g) of the <short-title>USAccounts: Investing in America’s Future Act of 2018</short-title>,</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>, and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H717B9F2EAF1B464A93447E1C6493EB7D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
						<quoted-block id="H5FF6F2FC5D944DFC8CBF01CA6450FF52" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="H4C4083E050F044C6BDC870ACC4330747"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Excess contributions to privately managed USAccounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, in the case of a USAccount subject to management under section 4(g) of the <short-title>USAccounts: Investing in America’s Future Act of 2018</short-title>, the term <term>excess contributions</term> means the sum of—</text>
 <paragraph id="HCD544CB0E5CB4F0F89016D2C6255DDBE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the aggregate amount contributed for the taxable year to the account, and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HEAF296B5B7EB4DB7A7F9302245920E34"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the amount determined under this subsection for the preceding taxable year, reduced by the sum of—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H67BCC4E6ADF04AFBA8937E0CBC527C7B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the distributions out of the account, and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B23D41799CB4DC49BCE4D26B541F5C1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the excess (if any) of—</text>
 <clause id="HE8C08CC1DE2342ED95B23179E490FE5A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the maximum amount allowable as a contribution under section 4(c)(3)(C) of the <short-title>USAccounts: Investing in America’s Future Act of 2018</short-title> for the taxable year, over</text> </clause><clause id="H439C32FEECE64FD5876D89E057D3DE35"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the amount contributed to the account for the taxable year.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D5CB1AB30E443109EC5B87ED1E69323"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibited transactions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4975">Section 4975</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H312C5E96B662441F944CA676116417DF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by adding at the end of subsection (c) the following new paragraph:</text>
						<quoted-block id="HA7373BD92F8544D6AC7015B3BD916B13" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H16E4B83C7D6E4F53A52BBC71723D7CD1"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Special rule for USAccounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual for whose benefit a USAccount subject to management under section 4(g) of the <short-title>USAccounts: Investing in America’s Future Act of 2018</short-title> shall be exempt from the tax imposed by this section with respect to any transaction concerning such account (which would otherwise be taxable under this section) if, with respect to such transaction, the account ceases to be a USAccount by reason of the application of section 530A(c)(2) to such account.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>, and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFDADFDE7A78D472690D6A4EF800733C5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(1) by redesignating subparagraph (G) as subparagraph (H) and by inserting after subparagraph (F) the following new subparagraph:</text>
						<quoted-block id="H6C15F74FB3F94B3BBE7606C1105F04B2" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H8DD763F07BB34ADFAE9E65B0A63B74D3"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a USAccount subject to management under section 4(g) of the <short-title>USAccounts: Investing in America’s Future Act of 2018</short-title>,</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDEA5D8D2A97A444FBF9FC3B65EB5F20F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Increase in child tax credit</header> <paragraph id="H64E57DB30C9C4433B6225B4FED82DFA0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/24">Section 24</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H64827551DD3346A8903BA7DB5C5BF681" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="H8995CD134BAD428EB4559317734A988F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>USAccount contributions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section—</text> <paragraph id="H8E49A0C18BBF428B9EAD3DEEEEADDFBB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The amount allowed as a credit under subsection (a) shall be increased by the USAccount contribution amount.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H968917FE216F4C79A391179CB6D9E9EF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>U<enum-in-header>SA</enum-in-header>ccount contribution amount</header><text>The term <term>USAccount contribution amount</term> means with respect to each qualifying account holder the amount contributed by the taxpayer to the USAccount of the taxpayer for the taxable year which is taken into account under section 4(d)(2)(B)(I) of the <short-title>USAccounts: Investing in America’s Future Act of 2018</short-title>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE00B53AE0B7F4DE5888E193364D8AA65"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The amount under paragraph (2) shall be reduced (but not below zero) under subsection (b)(1) in the same manner as the credit under subsection (a) is reduced under subsection (b)(1).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2F6709474005483399ECD512599A7CDC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Amount fully refundable</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The aggregate credits allowed to the taxpayer under subpart C shall be increased by the amount of the increase under this subsection and such amount—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H63965FE68A9C4788A22DB4597D2C132B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall not be treated as a credit allowed under this subpart, and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16EDBCE632304DA2990EAF9F1A113BF0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall reduce the amount of credit otherwise allowable under subsection (a) without regard to section 26(a).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEEE5DFCC74FC49E09D7CBF62FC583375"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after December 31, 2018.</text> </subsection></section><section id="HFB04792D80D14BD482070F2F598C29E5"><enum>12.</enum><header>Earned Income Tax Credit outreach</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/32">Section 32</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA15058C1892444D4A2B9D863FA3F6C28" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="H16CA9F2B06D643A39C69EEF40A32F866"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Earned income tax credit outreach</header>
 <paragraph id="H692585D209F14FF69268272CEF4C58D3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent practicable and not otherwise precluded by section 6511, in the case of any taxpayer who, based on information available to the Secretary, did not claim, but may be allowed, a credit under subsection (a) for a preceding taxable year, the Secretary shall annually provide to each such taxpayer notice that such taxpayer may be eligible to claim such credit.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC4891067C9C14FDBB26D83C4FC6A8952"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination of credit and deposit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not earlier than 60 days after providing notice under paragraph (1) to a taxpayer with respect to a taxable year, if such taxpayer fails to claim the credit under this section for such taxable year, the Secretary shall determine the credit on behalf of the taxpayer. Any refund attributable to such credit shall be—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HCD4151F1E6F04BD28D27A197CDF86BAB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>deposited in the USAccount of any dependents of the taxpayer (pro rata in the case of more than one USAccount), or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H274D8997F90244728D99DDB02AD03DCE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a taxpayer with dependents who do not have a USAccount or a taxpayer with no dependents, paid directly to the taxpayer.</text>
						</subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">For purposes of this paragraph, the term <quote>USAccount</quote> shall have the meaning given such term by section 4 of the <short-title>USAccounts: Investing in America’s Future Act of 2018</short-title>. The Secretary shall not collect any overpayment of the credit determined under this paragraph if
			 such overpayment is attributable to an error of the Secretary.</continuation-text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


