<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H589F4C97108F4865B56C0ADAF736C329" key="H" public-private="public"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5607 IH: Handgun Licensing and Registration Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5607</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20180424">April 24, 2018</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000034">Mr. Pallone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001165">Mr. Sires</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Judy Chu of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To provide for the mandatory licensing and registration of handguns, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HD533F4556D4048A299CD8298E0A89BA2" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H8CF2259FD6EA4E6C925381ADAE526ABF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Handgun Licensing and Registration Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> <section id="HEF10AC5B153242A4911B7549211E6624"><enum>2.</enum><header>Federal handgun licensing and registration system to apply in any State that does not have a handgun licensing and registration system that meets certain requirements</header> <subsection id="H73661F172F1749CABA208182F7D2D400"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/44">Chapter 44</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE3C5B5D273AA4A11B54ADA409E19E33C" style="USC"> 
<section id="H178D86B355864508B989E9E83D7F848C"><enum>932.</enum><header>Licensing and registration of handguns</header> 
<subsection id="H57F276BED5434E4582050970A1EE7DC3"><enum>(a)</enum> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9BE7DE11FE9A462B82F410EB399BA119"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Attorney General of the United States shall establish a Federal system for the licensing and registration of all handguns owned, possessed, or controlled in the United States—</text> <subparagraph id="H8C16FFB8DE114B23BD1390B5BB35AFCE" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">under which—</text> 
<clause id="HAE91FD99D63644F58059EC6A7AA505C1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a person shall not be eligible to receive such a license if the person—</text> <subclause id="HBA784C9C13F34713A636B91D31522E3F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>has not attained 21 years of age;</text> </subclause>
<subclause id="H22D453F4CB4741F2B4A9F64563EC678C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is not a citizen, national, or lawful permanent resident of the United States;</text> </subclause> <subclause id="H509877824CE64F64AD335CC3D0B14D9C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>has not completed training in firearms safety;</text> </subclause>
<subclause id="HBE33DFD1CF804D2D843985B720BFC1B3"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as part of the process for applying for such a license—</text> <item id="H2D1A90B50707448F9C2E49C25F9C7FC4"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>has not submitted to a background investigation and criminal history check of the person; or</text> </item>
<item id="HAEF83630A8334E41AEF6AA099EABB492"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>has not submitted the fingerprints of the person and a recent photograph that clearly shows the face of the person; or</text> </item></subclause> <subclause id="H46221F17B4464ABFACCA436C84B2CF3A"><enum>(V)</enum><text>is prohibited by Federal law from possessing a firearm; and</text> </subclause></clause>
<clause id="H74A1FA4EF3C740C4BE2F0441E7C09623"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such a license shall expire not more than 5 years after issuance; and</text> </clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7F7D4843071240669683E3E61C703643" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>which shall include a method for easily retrieving information sufficient to identify—</text> 
<clause id="HA39C97E189B24CDC9DB89C04F98E1547"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each resident of a State to which this subsection applies who owns, possesses, or controls a handgun; and</text> </clause> <clause id="H5ABDC73A671D4945A61BC5FEA2073476"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the handgun.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB10DDF01F4EC4A56AFF07F785809C66C" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>It shall be unlawful for a person to own, possess, or control a handgun in a State to which this subsection applies unless the person—</text> <subparagraph id="H48D81F5E5CC449FD99F86238DF66EA1F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is licensed to do so by the system established pursuant to paragraph (1); and</text> </subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5E5C16FBAC174ADCB26AC82D2C810536"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has registered the handgun with a Federal, State, or local law enforcement agency.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H47D831994F114DA5AED254CAB62CEE7D"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply in a State if there is in effect a certification by the Attorney General of the United States that the State has in effect a system for the licensing and registration of handguns owned, possessed, or controlled in the State that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H964C731043AF4F78B0EBABB500209416"><enum>(1)</enum><text>meets the requirements of subsection (a)(1)(A);</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="HB99D003D3BC249A49D0471AEFAEEFDA6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>includes a method for easily retrieving information sufficient to identify—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3E0A1D466FCF4C439D3E739F94DE6E22"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each resident of the State who owns, possesses, or controls a handgun in the State; and</text> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H66C2129FB5E74715BF657BC73CFB630D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the handgun; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA24DFBFC0B13450EAF07E3B9BE550E13"><enum>(3)</enum><text>at a minimum, imposes criminal penalties on any person who—</text> <subparagraph id="H8802A0D863C04D929DBF18B3F889C917"><enum>(A)</enum><text>owns, possesses, or controls a handgun in the State, and—</text> 
<clause id="HBCF5E979D6FA49FFB4DD8F43AEDF114F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is not licensed by the State to possess a handgun; or</text> </clause> <clause id="H5141C79913B542928D46A159970CE0A7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has not registered the handgun with a Federal, State, or local law enforcement agency; or</text> </clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H70FA8497D1F948269FC64E14502A088D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>transfers or receives handgun ammunition, unless the recipient—</text> <clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD2EFD4B5D2474F028B534CA2555EFADD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is a licensed importer, licensed manufacturer, or licensed dealer; or</text> </clause>
<clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8AABE59B234E45FCB200F7604BD39722"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>before the receipt, has presented to the transferor—</text> <subclause id="H5939645537F74DC19FD7F1ACBC5B55B7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a valid firearms purchaser identification card issued by the State to the recipient;</text> </subclause>
<subclause id="HC53F7E2830F34AC0B0896C392C0AE0CE"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a valid copy of a handgun purchase permit issued by the State to the recipient; or</text> </subclause> <subclause id="H2D51362607574C748228EF4C72204B5E"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a valid permit to carry a handgun issued by the State to the recipient.</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1AF250739AEB46BF9AFEE0B8FB8EDFF7"><enum>(c)</enum><text>A certification under subsection (b) with respect to a State shall have no force or effect on or after the date the Attorney General finds, after an opportunity for a hearing on the record, that the State does not have in effect the system described in subsection (b).</text> </subsection> <subsection id="HEE3ED19CACF343C48B9729E06D8A2B4B"><enum>(d)</enum><text>The Attorney General shall prescribe such regulations as may be necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection>
<subsection id="H6A07C8A1E4124D0A82F5C0BF6F973B9D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>Section 924(a) of such title is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35D130DED446497F9F447DA9F0081379" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HB50296A2D40847C8933B9CE6D9A05954" indent="up1"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whoever knowingly violates section 932(a)(2) shall be fined under this title, imprisoned, or both. The court shall not suspend a sentence of imprisonment imposed under this paragraph.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection>
<subsection id="HAE4839949FF84CD2BD9B0532EF1EAE65"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for such chapter is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section"><quote>932. Licensing and registration of handguns.</quote>.</toc-entry></toc> </subsection> <subsection id="H5D0B094B6FF14946B2A866294173685C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to conduct engaged in after the 2-year period that begins with the date of the enactment of this Act.</text> </subsection></section>
<section id="H3907CBF8C05444BAB847157363FAA619"><enum>3.</enum><header>Grants for State implementation of programs to license and register handguns</header> 
<subsection id="H9541AE46C5EA416AAE40854158D0A7B9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General is authorized to award grants to States, units of local government, and Indian tribes to comply with the requirements under subsection (a) of section 932 of title 18, United States Code, or to implement a system described in subsection (b) of that section.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="HD839D21C039A48B6898E26921F2F6D7D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts appropriated to carry out this section, and not later than 90 days after such amounts are appropriated, the Attorney General shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible applicants whose applications are approved under subsection (c) to assist such applicants in carrying out the activities described in subsection (a).</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="H2ADFF7AEC8204A20928E0CEDF94B8044"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a grant under this Act, a State, unit of local government, or Indian tribe shall submit to the Attorney General an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Attorney General may require, including—</text> <paragraph id="HB1C61340E122454B83DDD6A8C7AF09C5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>whether the applicant will use the grant to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H71A7E5CE97B94C5AB869547878D0830D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>comply with the requirements under subsection (a) of section 932 of title 18, United States Code; or</text> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H03E5A93CF3154C5181BFCE7398718052"><enum>(B)</enum><text>implement a system described in subsection (b) of that section, including a description of the law that the applicant has enacted to require a license for any purchase of a handgun including a description of any other exemptions to such law; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H18B7D2788D6846BCADEEC4288E49E3E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of the specific activities for which the applicant will use the grant.</text> </paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB9A85FF1F8DF42729B241CCCC5AB5F69"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A grantee under this Act shall use such grant to carry out the activities described in subsection (a).</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HBCB62CF3B2FB44C38D5120651545180A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Audits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall conduct an audit every 2 years of each applicant receiving a grant under this section, and may conduct such additional audits as the Attorney General determines necessary.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="HED1C5A581B484D34AA006A0E97C7EE67"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall submit an annual report to Congress on the grant program under this section, which shall include information on the progress made in establishing the Federal system described in subsection (a) of section 932 of title 18, United States Code, and the progress made by States in establishing a system described in subsection (b) of such section.</text> </subsection>
<subsection id="HAB189C5A17EC49E4A6C8FC50C8B4CAC6"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this Act.</text> </subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

