<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H31DAB9F903E84A0BB15AB8CCC7036864" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5086 IH: Innovators to Entrepreneurs Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5086</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180226">February 26, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000563">Mr. Lipinski</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Small Business</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Director of the National Science Foundation to develop an I-Corps course to support
			 commercialization-ready innovation companies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H4B655A40CF264052AC123FE6D70BF81A" style="OLC">
 <section id="H5D24BFB1D11647FA94C52F4BC78FADE3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Innovators to Entrepreneurs Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HB3C52E2F820A4044920234E91A8A55D6" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H266B6C028ABA42F4AA2A30176CA96BF3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The National Science Foundation Innovation Corps Program (hereinafter referred to as <quote>I-Corps</quote>), created administratively by the Foundation in 2011 and statutorily authorized in the American Innovation and Competitiveness Act, has succeeded in increasing the commercialization of Government-funded research.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H36D6BB8D726E48BA87A0A4A049CB46DB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>I-Corps provides valuable entrepreneurial education to graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, and other researchers, providing formal training for scientists and engineers to pursue careers in business, an increasingly common path for advanced degree holders.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB26781CEE0EA4BE3BCB015E2FF4D5652"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The I-Corps Teams program is successful in part due to its focus on providing the specific types of education and mentoring entrepreneurs need based on the early stage of their companies, however the program does not provide similar support to them at later stages.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H902B7D97D61F49388059F4BD427EE05A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The success of I-Corps in the very early stages of the innovation continuum should be expanded upon by offering additional entrepreneurship training to small businesses as they advance toward commercialization.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5956D09FB43048B4921A242BAEC68B6C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The excellent training made available to grantees of participating agencies through the I-Corps Program should be made available to all Federal grantees as well as other businesses willing to pay the cost of attending such training.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2509A3AB97844A48A3F2EED3876BA044"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The success of the I-Corps Program at promoting entrepreneurship within research institutions and encouraging research commercialization has been due in part to the National Science Foundation’s efforts to date on building a national network of science entrepreneurs, including convening stakeholders, promoting national I-Corps courses, cataloguing best practices and encourage sharing between sites and institutions, and developing a mentor network.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB94AFC80154A4B66820D4D1AFEDC9F4D"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As the I-Corps Program continues to grow and expand, the National Science Foundation should maintain its focus on networking and information sharing to ensure that innovators across the country can learn from their peers and remain competitive.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H0574A85378044D52BEAD49403DA51979"><enum>3.</enum><header>Expanded participation in I-Corps</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 601(c)(2) of the American Innovation and Competitiveness Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1862s-8">42 U.S.C. 1862s–8(c)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCA71C1E5D201463983D5533A62345B59" style="OLC">
				<subparagraph id="H0795FF4E4A9B4FAF913E26259423969D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Additional participants</header>
 <clause id="H85977D1BFF6149EC931E23B0F2E07FF5"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>The Director, in consultation with relevant stakeholders, as determined by the Director, which may include Federal agencies, I-Corps regional nodes, universities, and public and private entities engaged in technology transfer or commercialization of technologies, shall provide an option for participation in an I-Corps Teams course by—</text>
 <subclause id="H77AD56B750424CA5A562503D7970EDB2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Small Business Innovation Research Program grantees; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H3637597F87D94089A453BE2C635EAFC0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>other entities, as determined appropriate by the Director.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H5E389211088948718DD2CA90C0083E2E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Cost of participation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The cost of participation by a Small Business Innovation Research Program grantee in such course may be provided—</text>
 <subclause id="H5AACE1C098A0441BB5C595EB62A07F7D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>through I-Corps Teams grants;</text> </subclause><subclause id="H2A1DFA69B7DA4880ACC94BF9919A3A4D"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">through funds awarded to grantees under the Small Business Innovation Research Program or the Small Business Technology Transfer Program;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H57C39E014E374EE58708F2EBB8893602"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by the grantor Federal agency of the grantee using funds set aside for the Small Business Innovation Research Program under section 9(f)(1) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/638">15 U.S.C. 638(f)(1)</external-xref>);</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H104AAE952C334E50B08E9742B78402E4"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by the grantor Federal agency of the grantee using funds set aside for the Small Business Technology Transfer Program under section 9(n)(1) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/638">15 U.S.C. 638(n)(1)</external-xref>); or</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H2E5F3DB708794A3F8B7E14676A65BDF5"><enum>(V)</enum><text>by the participating teams.</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section><section id="H313EA6ACC1B44A81B5416FE37A992952"><enum>4.</enum><header>I-Corps course for commercialization-ready participants</header> <subsection id="H74DFEDE62C384CC1AEDFEA1584B0542F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the I-Corps program described in section 601(c) of the American Innovation and Competitiveness Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1862s-8">42 U.S.C. 1862s–8(c)</external-xref>), the Director shall develop an I-Corps course offered by I-Corps regional nodes to support commercialization-ready participants. Such course shall include skills such as attracting investors, scaling up a company, and building a brand.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H0904EF714C2F44C2869B57087E751AB3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Engagement with relevant stakeholders</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing the course under subsection (a), the Director may consult with the heads of such Federal agencies, universities, and public and private entities as the Director determines to be appropriate.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H023F6458EDAA46F6A4B6D2AB0FFC1752"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible participants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The course developed under subsection (a) shall—</text> <paragraph id="H0730283BC933444FB77F6BC1A075F361"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support participants that have completed an I-Corps Teams course;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDFB31CB6C05E482E95DA10AD992CF213"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support participants that have made the decision to take an innovation to market.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HACEE9122480149E0B9A99EE71671CAEC"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report containing an evaluation of the I-Corps program described in section 601(c) of the American Innovation and Competitiveness Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1862s-8">42 U.S.C. 1862s–8(c)</external-xref>). Such evaluation shall include an assessment of the effects of I-Corps on—</text>
 <paragraph id="H3B219DAC8A56463F81429EC29A936471"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the commercialization of Federally funded research and development;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HFEE07E6BE79A4533A83628291E8B7C44"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the higher education system; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE89E8C85F38B44B79300D08D24EBE966"><enum>(3)</enum><text>regional economies and the national economy.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="H79C3A107D5D645FB9BA62AC472E41D5F"><enum>6.</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">From funds otherwise provided to the National Science Foundation, a total of $5,000,000 shall be made available for fiscal years 2019 and 2020 to carry out the activities described in section 4 and the amendment made by section 3.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


