<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HF1C362DADEA2428F9FBFD8C90EB898D1" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5769 IH: Expanding Access to Treatment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5769</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180510">May 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000598">Mr. Rothfus</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Danny K. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to expand access under the Medicare program to
			 addiction treatment in Federally qualified health centers and rural health
			 clinics.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HCB430C879DC34719B73C5DC36C768FDB" style="OLC">
 <section id="H49C2F7D29AC34005A8751CAB25E504AC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Expanding Access to Treatment Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H5476B76A7D494044B50112E5ECDBCAA2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Expanding access under the Medicare program to addiction treatment in Federally qualified health centers and rural health clinics</header> <subsection id="HD42C61380DBB4E0285F47914AEAD0598"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federally qualified health centers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1834(o) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(o)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC42FDBBB9CFD442787FCA89010C30BB8" style="OLC">
					<paragraph id="H2764E147F94D4B9BB0024EA004F18B57"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional payments for certain FQHCs with practitioners receiving DATA 2000 certification</header>
 <subparagraph id="H89B0405FDDBD4FCA94C3778357BF28F5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a Federally qualified health center with respect to which, beginning January 1, 2019, Federally-qualified health center services (as defined in section 1861(aa)(3)) are furnished by a health care practitioner who first receives on or after such date a registration or waiver under section 303(g) of the Controlled Substances Act to prescribe or dispense methadone, buprenorphine, or suboxone for the purpose of maintenance or detoxification treatment, the Secretary shall, subject to availability of funds under subparagraph (B), make a payment (in accordance with such timing, method, and procedures as specified by the Secretary) to such Federally qualified health center in an amount determined by the Secretary, based on an approximation of the cost to receive training for purposes of such registration or waiver, as applicable. For purposes of the previous sentence, a Federally-qualified health center shall apply for a payment described in such sentence at such time and in such manner as specified by the Secretary and may apply for such a payment for each practitioner furnishing such services at such center who is described in such sentence.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDAEB719D49DF4B659C497C312FB92258"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of making payments under this paragraph, there are appropriated, out of amounts in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, $6,000,000, which shall remain available until expended.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HB6C7CDAE2B01446A946422847108EE78"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rural health clinic</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1833 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H8613DB6180A04142B514CB75121749F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating the subsection (z) relating to medical review of spinal subluxation services as subsection (aa); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H64D4DB66435A4FDFB90885CAA2CB7897"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD70E00D1E2A340D394F94E7C11702408" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H645B60C12935499689E2A88C585E0E90"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Additional payments for certain rural health clinics with practitioners receiving DATA 2000 certification</header> <paragraph id="HF3D7F1BAE8D64D93AB3BE90E029A1799"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a rural health clinic with respect to which, beginning January 1, 2019, rural health clinic services (as defined in section 1861(aa)(1)) are furnished by a health care practitioner who first receives on or after such date a registration or waiver under section 303(g) of the Controlled Substances Act to prescribe or dispense methadone, buprenorphine, or suboxone for the purpose of maintenance or detoxification treatment, the Secretary shall, subject to availability of funds under subparagraph (B), make a payment (in accordance with such timing, method, and procedures as specified by the Secretary) to such rural health clinic in an amount determined by the Secretary, based on an approximation of the cost to receive training for purposes of such registration or waiver, as applicable. For purposes of the previous sentence, a rural health clinic shall apply for a payment described in such sentence at such time and in such manner as specified by the Secretary and may apply for such a payment for each practitioner furnishing such services at such clinic who is described in such sentence.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE385F15351BA4F1C8B4FC046CE72617B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of making payments under this subsection, there are appropriated, out of amounts in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, $2,000,000, which shall remain available until expended.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


