<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3097C39371CA44C9AAAEB6C12044726E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5375 IH: To require the Secretary of the Treasury to submit to Congress a comprehensive customer service strategy for the Internal Revenue Service.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5375</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180321">March 21, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000585">Mr. Reed</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001293">Mr. Bishop of Michigan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of the Treasury to submit to Congress a comprehensive customer service strategy for the Internal Revenue Service.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDEDB8B5F9E154DD1B8E2BCD76B025360" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE0BD5BB8CCD9435797DB42D241C9A2A3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Comprehensive customer service strategy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than the date which is 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury, after consultation with the National Taxpayer Advocate, shall submit to Congress a written comprehensive customer service strategy for the Internal Revenue Service. Such strategy shall include—</text> <paragraph id="H692E576652C84059BFF6704E69B5A930"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a plan to provide assistance to taxpayers that is designed to meet reasonable taxpayer expectations and is in conformity with best practices of customer service provided in the private sector, including online services, telephone call back services, and training of employees providing customer services,</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H116A15923A6F4AB49D9B2A056D0344C2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a thorough assessment of the services that the Internal Revenue Service can offer as self-service options,</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HABE7405B0DFE41B5AC41A28CFE0AF8BF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>proposals to protect taxpayer identity and to reduce taxpayer identity theft,</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDC6A990377C54168857AC68CE714E04C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>proposals to improve Internal Revenue Service customer service in the short term (the current and following fiscal year), medium term (approximately 3 to 5 fiscal years), and long term (approximately 10 fiscal years), and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H32B0291AF54B4B8A8B1F70C00AFE8660"><enum>(5)</enum><text>identified metrics and benchmarks for quantitatively measuring the progress of the Internal Revenue Service in meeting each element of such strategy.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

