<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HFD7BA3FA9DCB4C6C825A6EAC23BA1E5D" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5303 IH: Full Count Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5303</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180315">March 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001250">Mr. Bishop of Utah</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000584">Mrs. Love</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001192">Mr. Stewart</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 13, United States Code, to provide for the more accurate and complete enumeration of
			 certain overseas Americans in the decennial census, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HAB9ACE342C524A7BA8B4E00673E6E209" style="OLC">
 <section id="H6BF1D856FB424A62A2447C5364F1B380" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Full Count Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HCE5389568D2C4B1596519E1201174D56" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Methods to improve the enumeration of certain overseas Americans</header> <subsection id="HBC81F42BE2CE4D3785FD57D68C5E56FF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 141 of title 13, United States Code, is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H1512FA1F2FA04B4F8AA7DDB73C9751CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (g) as subsection (h); and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H86E4227FAF0742C7BFDAE227008B095D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (f) the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCE17B037A6F84B55B7FB08AA87AAFABA" style="USC">
						<subsection id="H62C406C7D5E64E4F983EB86B0F13E61D"><enum>(g)</enum>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H6A20E1B456E1460799CB6D571818A3F8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective beginning with the 2030 decennial census of population, the Secretary shall take appropriate measures to ensure, to the maximum extent practicable, that all Americans residing abroad on the decennial census date are fully and accurately counted, and are properly attributed to their respective States, and within the State so attributed, to the appropriate unit of local government.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H207DB59FD02848AE9C39F53428D88967" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The measures under this subsection shall include at least the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H3D251FD4BC6B4BBE84DDB6B4E71D54B4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>One or more methods by which, at the request of a nongovernmental organization, administrative records of such organization may, if such records satisfy such criteria as the Secretary may establish, be used to enumerate members of such organization who are residing overseas as of the decennial census date.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7D1A5A3381147DB8FAC351B3EB2821B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>One or more methods under which an international <quote>Be Counted</quote> form may be completed at an embassy of the United States by Americans residing overseas as of the decennial census date.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30B70AE83E564CB3B5DED317BB90159D"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordination and consultation with Federal agencies to ensure that all appropriate databases involving Americans living overseas are referenced when compiling data for the decennial census. The head of any such agency shall provide the Secretary assistance and data as described under this subsection.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0175097C44D5419CBCB3D10E7E4A9B38" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be considered to affect the methods used in the enumeration of any civilian or military personnel of the United States.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H68AC7AA741334968BD92BE9E8050FB51"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The data obtained pursuant to section 141(g) of title 13, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), shall be used for the same purposes as other data and information collected under a decennial census of population, including the distribution of Federal funds and the apportionment of Representatives in Congress among the several States.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


