<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H9869052274BF4C74B2A51FEFD96FEEBF" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5138 IH: Bipartisan HSA Improvement Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5138</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180301">March 1, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000594">Mr. Paulsen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000188">Mr. Kind</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell of Alabama</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to improve access to health care through modernized
			 health savings accounts.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HF79B62404D5548899D398AEE488DAC50" style="OLC">
 <section commented="no" id="HF91C10E4B3CB482F8A24B9EDBF6A6E90" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Bipartisan HSA Improvement Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HBA3361E19EA54CB9BC6B39384B9E922F" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Excepted benefits allowed as permitted insurance</header> <subsection id="H958902910F604D6C84B192DC1E0664DB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (3) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/223">section 223(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HF82297308E434044BB2AFCB21DFCCDDC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating subparagraphs (B) and (C) as subparagraphs (C) and (D), respectively; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H578C4F7A9F9348A3849AE6C86237EC42"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting the following new subparagraph:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H73A3AB6CC6C44A968E7083500FD6A242" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H59AFA7B185BE429EA7451E5254B0C585"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">insurance consisting of coverage for any excepted benefits described in section 9832(c),</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF3929BABD0E64E3DB3448534D4E6BCDB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE4C81ABDB3B34023BAA202388727D8F4" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>On-site employee clinics and retail clinics</header>
 <subsection id="H3315BFFF64FA40D0B43A78C03B3FCE5F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (1) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/223">section 223(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3E36462C7CAE4625996BA1A0DDD08DC3" style="OLC">
					<subparagraph id="H948797B65BA9420ABC8757C99E98760A"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Special rule for qualified items and services</header>
 <clause id="H3E9D02CE346044FCBA3751FB2C5BFA4D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (A)(ii), an individual shall not be treated as covered under a health plan for purposes of subparagraph (A)(ii) merely because the individual is eligible to receive, or receives, qualified items and services at—</text>
 <subclause id="H83413FAF6A8C4FBB87F7104831AB2E14"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a healthcare facility located at a facility owned or leased by the employer of the individual (or of the individual’s spouse), or operated primarily for the benefit of such employer’s employees, or</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H297E112E1DEE4A41B76F713C82EE7612"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a retail health clinic.</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="H13F6B2141EFB4AE883DD2A18FE3718CF"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Qualified items and services defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <term>qualified items and services</term> means the following:</text>
 <subclause id="H404AA668A6B14852BB5FFDB1FB325068"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Primary care including physical examination.</text> </subclause><subclause id="H6A6999F630C7439C8CB9E4D261CEA9A7"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Immunizations, including injections of antigens provided by employees.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HC64A1ABBEC10476B90CD242F8558BD02"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Drugs or biologicals other than a prescribed drug (as such term is defined in section 213(d)(3)).</text> </subclause><subclause id="H3A104486984649C195A2293CA94D7EFB"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Treatment for injuries occurring in the course of employment.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HA27F778D18CD49CA828F14E861B90BD5"><enum>(V)</enum><text>Tests for conditions or infectious diseases.</text> </subclause><subclause id="HEAA218ABE5164A8CB5F9C7579D462B70"><enum>(VI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Management of medically complex chronic conditions.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H8A4AB99B70554E4AA93D47D4070C9001"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>Drug testing.</text> </subclause><subclause id="HE15A0CA5B8674F67B98FBBBA3F24639A"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>Hearing or vision screenings and related services.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HC32AC67FDB5249E3910913B8DC709D12"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>Other similar items and services.</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="HD6BDCB6E28154B36938A94F2D74C3587"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Retail health clinic defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <term>retail health clinic</term> means a health care facility located within a supermarket, pharmacy, or similar retail establishment that offers urgent care by a licensed healthcare provider.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HE047AC019E5B4602A4DC4B77257A8F5C"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Aggregation</header><text>For purposes of clause (i), all persons treated as a single employer under subsection (b), (c), (m), or (o) of section 414 shall be treated as a single employer.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5D31B3F453734A1BAEE8AF34B4947D84"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall apply to months in taxable years beginning after the date of enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HDA5D72034EF649E1BEDA7219F5E0A924"><enum>4.</enum><header>Contributions permitted if spouse has a health flexible spending account</header>
 <subsection id="H8369C972990544FD9DC435037E2820F7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Contributions permitted if spouse has a health flexible spending account</header><text>Subparagraph (B) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/223">section 223(c)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of clause (ii), by striking the period at the end of clause (iii) and inserting <quote>, and</quote>, and by inserting after clause (iii) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEC20DC54111A4490BE0566442AFC6342" style="OLC"> <clause id="HD3EB063FFE944C789F343DDA883294D5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coverage under a health flexible spending arrangement of the spouse of the individual.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H30C5D29A37C44B0B8F553233A624A24F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H90C427AD33064B10A88B5A6A4A5C6D00"><enum>5.</enum><header>Dependents to include children up to age 26</header>
 <subsection id="H754653B4815048CBB78B579F6ABBA6E9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subparagraph (A) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/223">section 223(d)(2)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>and any dependent (as defined in section 152, determined without regard to subsections (b)(1), (b)(2), and (d)(1)(B) thereof) of such individual</quote> in subparagraph (A) and inserting <quote>any dependent (as defined in section 152, determined without regard to subsections (b)(1), (b)(2), and (d)(1)(B) thereof) of such individual, and any child (as defined in section 152(f)(A)) of such individual who has not attained the age of 27 before the end of such individual’s taxable year</quote>.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE3FA692CCC83443AA18A6B71DD71AA6E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to qualified medical expenses incurred in taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H2AD23A873F7C4D3EB73D0DADC099C5EB"><enum>6.</enum><header>FSA and HRA interaction with HSAs</header>
 <subsection id="HB38668D469674E3790E3453AD343E6C8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Eligible individuals include FSA and HRA participants</header><text>Subparagraph (B) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/223">section 223(c)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended by this Act, is amended by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of clause (iii), by striking the period at the end of clause (iv) and inserting <quote>, and</quote>, and by inserting after clause (iv) the following new clause:</text>
				<quoted-block id="HCA0CE9425B2C44538964538C99DC71E3" style="OLC">
 <clause id="HD7DD3434EE034BA4802561924C345A6B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>coverage under a health flexible spending arrangement or a health reimbursement arrangement in the plan year a qualified HSA distribution as described in section 106(e) is made on behalf of the individual if, after the qualified HSA distribution is made and for the remaining duration of the plan year, the coverage provided under the arrangement is converted solely to one or more of the following:</text>
 <subclause id="H78A890AB87F3417192E8457B8640E417"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Post-deductible FSA or HRA</header><text>A health flexible spending arrangement or a health reimbursement arrangement that does not pay or reimburse any medical expense incurred before the minimum annual deductible under paragraph (2)(A)(i) (prorated for the period occurring after the qualified HSA distribution is made) is satisfied.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H67D28D4045B6496798B6326656C9D0EE"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Preventative care</header><text>A health flexible spending arrangement or a health reimbursement arrangement that, after the qualified HSA distribution is made, does not pay or reimburse any medical expense incurred after the qualified HSA distribution is made other than preventive care as defined in paragraph (2)(C).</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HE1553FD3B928452EA368D2E0C3BECC10"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Limited purpose health FSA</header><text>A health flexible spending arrangement that, after the qualified HSA distribution is made, pays or reimburses benefits for coverage described in clause (ii) (but not through insurance or for long-term care services).</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H6A9182014235453E9FF0FD967B4A446A"><enum>(IV)</enum><header>Limited purpose HRA</header><text>A health reimbursement arrangement that, after the qualified HSA distribution is made, pays or reimburses benefits for permitted insurance or coverage described in clause (ii) (but not for long-term care services).</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HCBBC44EB66774330B9B0AF87B4A771AF"><enum>(V)</enum><header>Retirement HRA</header><text>A health reimbursement arrangement that, after the qualified HSA distribution is made, pays or reimburses only those medical expenses incurred after an individual’s retirement (and no expenses incurred before retirement).</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H9384867C683C4C2F9B4B73804A1F6073"><enum>(VI)</enum><header>Suspended HRA</header><text>A health reimbursement arrangement that, after the qualified HSA distribution is made, is suspended, pursuant to an election made on or before the date the individual elects a qualified HSA distribution or, if later, on the date of the individual enrolls in an HSA-qualified health plan, that does not pay or reimburse, at any time, any medical expense incurred during the suspension period except as described in the preceding subclauses of this clause.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H2C122A01FD194CA89D4905825296FEA4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualified HSA distribution shall not affect flexible spending arrangement</header><text>Paragraph (1) of section 106(e) of such Code is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block id="HB2CC8908A58141C2801133169E82D594" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H259191BDECC845928A06AE1B6CD31B40"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A plan shall not fail to be treated as—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HB38E574D518641318B2BB55436CE32DA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a health flexible spending arrangement under this section, section 105, or section 125,</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37CD98606FDA45599785DFBCE332AE41"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a health reimbursement arrangement under this section or section 105, or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB29ABC8420DC4E78A5748F8D33B5D8ED"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an accident or health plan,</text> </subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">merely because such plan provides for a qualified HSA distribution.</continuation-text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection><subsection id="H9B6BA1ACAF144023B3422A921255674C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>FSA balances at year end shall not forfeit</header><text>Paragraph (2) of section 125(d) of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
				<quoted-block id="HBD2EA176B4D4484D87C7E07D032B30D9" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H88EC00BAA12B4123ADA043850EE83B11"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Exception for qualified HSA distributions</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply to the extent that there is an amount remaining in a health flexible spending account at the end of a plan year that an individual elects to contribute to a health savings account pursuant to a qualified HSA distribution (as defined in section 106(e)(2)).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HFF81D0DD358943B1A51A3E237F6B5434"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Simplification of limitations on FSA and HRA rollovers</header><text>Paragraph (2) of section 106(e) of such Code is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block id="HC470AD5989A04B4D96BB58C59528A113" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H35429EC2A24247CC8E6298B932B36F70"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified HSA distribution</header> <subparagraph id="HE83151E379234211BFEB8CC5C491B9C0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>qualified HSA distribution</term> means a distribution from a health flexible spending arrangement or health reimbursement arrangement directly to a health savings account of the employee to the extent that such distribution does not exceed the lesser of—</text>
 <clause id="HC732625E7A7F48D2A24172D98FC5B274"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the balance in such arrangement as of the date of such distribution, or</text> </clause><clause id="H86A0585D391C46158DCF7ADDFC16EAA1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the amount determined under subparagraph (B).</text>
							</clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">Such term shall not include more than 1 distribution with respect to any arrangement.</continuation-text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD41EBF6D7014E7CA541A12A41E7FF80"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Dollar limitations</header>
 <clause id="HB3F0F46506714222B8599593258A275E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Distributions from a health flexible spending arrangement</header><text>A qualified HSA distribution from a health flexible spending arrangement shall not exceed the applicable amount.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H58EE44BA91EE494AAC22093A93A2E0ED"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Distributions from a health reimbursement arrangement</header><text>A qualified HSA distribution from a health reimbursement arrangement shall not exceed—</text> <subclause id="H5EC31D48BAEB400CB6FF89CFFD9F9E54"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the applicable amount divided by 12, multiplied by</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HF12F919E3B164A8F864E017F4F674F15"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the number of months during which the individual is a participant in the health reimbursement arrangement.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H17DFBC7696204EF78767037BFA65B50B"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Applicable amount</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the applicable amount is—</text> <subclause id="H21E5EA07AFF646D4ABC890221BDD2207"><enum>(I)</enum><text>$2,250 in the case of an eligible individual who has self-only coverage under an HSA-qualified health plan at the time of such distribution, and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HF0068F1EC96142C3AD891C1708BA09DA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>$4,500 in the case of an eligible individual who has family coverage under an HSA-qualified health plan at the time of such distribution.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H8D23972D5CB142AB9807A4A38BB843F4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Elimination of additional tax for failure to maintain HSA-Qualified health plan coverage</header><text>Subsection (e) of section 106 of such Code is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HF29954F0064140AD876A38CF5941693D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (A) of paragraph (4) and redesignating subparagraphs (B) and (C) of such paragraph as subparagraphs (A) and (B) thereof, respectively; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB1F4AABB2A2043A59153212EE6EBDBAA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3) and redesignating paragraphs (4) (as so amended) and (5) as paragraphs (3) and (4), respectively.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEB70B0B622D54C53B3EEC1F7EE45812E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limited purpose FSAs and HRAs</header><text>Subsection (e) of section 106 of such Code, as amended by this section, is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block id="HF2B50E7701C84AAEA1F5F549FE478A6F" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H376473F92967470BB6467EFDB1AEDBE9"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Limited purpose FSAs and HRAs</header><text>A plan shall not fail to be a health flexible spending arrangement, a health reimbursement arrangement, or an accident or health plan under this section or section 105 merely because the plan converts coverage for individuals who enroll in an HSA-qualified health plan described in section 223(c)(2) to coverage described in subclause (I), (II), (III), (IV), (V), or (VI) of section 223(c)(1)(B)(iv). Coverage for such individuals may be converted as of the date of enrollment in the HSA-qualified health plan, without regard to the period of coverage under the health flexible spending arrangement or health reimbursement arrangement, and without requiring any change in coverage to individuals who do not enroll in an HSA-qualified health plan.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD8654C9EABD9493399EE52CB439C32FC"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Distribution amounts adjusted for cost-of-Living</header><text>Subsection (e) of section 106 of such Code, as amended by this section, is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H201C584BBA4B403F9CDC604D2275484E" style="OLC">
					<paragraph id="H16BD2CA9086C40F78AA6498BBAA9D2FB"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Cost-of-living adjustment</header>
 <subparagraph id="H8BDFDAE90FDF45DBAAD0FD002A8194BD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any taxable year beginning in a calendar year after 2018, each of the dollar amounts in paragraph (2)(B)(iii) shall be increased by an amount equal to such dollar amount, multiplied by the cost-of-living adjustment determined under section 1(f)(3) for the calendar year in which such taxable year begins by substituting <quote>calendar year 2017</quote> for <quote>calendar year 1992</quote> in subparagraph (B) thereof.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB62402A94AE34BC5AA2607FD9517892B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Rounding</header><text>If any increase under paragraph (1) is not a multiple of $50, such increase shall be rounded to the nearest multiple of $50.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HDCEC855CD3AF4EAFB9D33B72BD7BD8CC"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Disclaimer of disqualifying coverage</header><text>Subparagraph (B) of section 223(c)(1) of such Code, as amended by this section, is amended by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of clause (iv), by striking the period at the end of clause (v) and inserting <quote>, and</quote>, and by inserting after clause (v) the following new clause:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H59B173D5C70443ADAF6C85AAA2D9E7F0" style="OLC">
 <clause id="HE5C01D0BC518455CB8AF232CB49DE4CD"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any coverage (including prospective coverage) under a health plan that is not an HSA-qualified health plan which is disclaimed in writing, at the time of the creation or organization of the health savings account, including by execution of a trust described in subsection (d)(1) through a governing instrument that includes such a disclaimer, or by acceptance of an amendment to such a trust that includes such a disclaimer.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H7D79B8D2C1E54EE9860B08891DCB1626"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H021005BC56FD4ED2BDDEBC46376CCE83"><enum>7.</enum><header>Chronic disease prevention</header>
 <subsection id="H6297FC45A403461091C8D24F11A7E52C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/223">Section 223(c)(2)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by redesignating subparagraph (D) as subparagraph (E) and by inserting after subparagraph (C) the following new subparagraph:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H355674E605C74730B18AB5F7687E5B3D" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H64D641DE7300418287BC295AFBAF95FE"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Safe harbor for absence of deductible for care related to chronic conditions</header><text>A plan shall not fail to be treated as a high deductible health plan by reason of failing to have a deductible for care and prescription medications related to the treatment of medically complex chronic conditions which—</text>
 <clause id="HFEBE9C66D208486ABFA5619C25080397"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are substantially disabling or life threatening,</text> </clause><clause id="H380CD83A666B4CCEADD39ADEA4F42B94"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>have a high risk of hospitalization or other significant adverse health outcomes, and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H948AC4660C8E4C36BDFE49CCD2E1F701"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>require specialized delivery systems across domains of care.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection><subsection id="H826AB359BF2D4B87B4244ABC7D7D00D1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to coverage for months beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HB99DECE0D633485AAC544129F729EDD5"><enum>8.</enum><header>Certain amounts paid for physical activity, fitness, and exercise treated as amounts paid for
			 medical care</header>
 <subsection id="HD4AD3C6FE2354090B3529510466A23CD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/213">Section 213(d)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of subparagraph (C), by striking the period at the end of subparagraph (D) and inserting <quote>, or</quote>, and by inserting after subparagraph (D) the following new subparagraph:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H9E837883ECF2488CB93C6C0EBA65689D" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H34FF2A6C406A4FFCACA1726EA7860CE4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>for qualified sports and fitness expenses.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection><subsection id="H227C05C304B44B679C401739F4D83A1B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualified sports and fitness expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 213(d) of such Code, as amended by this Act, is amended by adding at the end the following paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H3034929C8B2F462388F73E21544F8D0B" style="OLC">
					<paragraph commented="no" id="H68B327E016154F14833BAF07CC0A2F87"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Qualified sports and fitness expenses</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HB712BD4B090E466CB22A8B5C51FC9BDC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>qualified sports and fitness expenses</term> means amounts paid exclusively for the sole purpose of participating in a physical activity including—</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="H006927FBD4754F5DBD388D6598E7419E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for membership at a fitness facility,</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="H778DD5ECEFD94F9DBF3E139CDB9D30D3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for participation or instruction in a program of physical exercise or physical activity, and</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H24644926D65C48BFB8513A535662F8EE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>for equipment for use in a program (including a self-directed program) of physical exercise or physical activity.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC67657687CF249C68C2EDFB1EDF8E4DC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Overall dollar limitation</header><text>The aggregate amount treated as qualified sports and fitness expenses with respect to any taxpayer for any taxable year shall not exceed $1,000 ($2,000 in the case of a joint return or a head of household (as defined in section 2(b))).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB0C8BB4A27AA4F768B543B36AC09763B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Fitness facility defined</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A)(i), the term <term>fitness facility</term> means a facility—</text> <clause commented="no" id="HDC45D7C4545D4F628A4EA57010CB065A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>providing instruction in a program of physical exercise, offering facilities for the preservation, maintenance, encouragement, or development of physical fitness, or serving as the site of such a program of a State or local government,</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H55EAE69511484CD4929B266DD11B499D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>which is not a private club owned and operated by its members,</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="H1987E9B19A3B476789FCBACC85C8BF79"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>which does not offer golf, hunting, sailing, or riding facilities,</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H62E42D276C014157858E6EAE4C888437"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>whose health or fitness facility is not incidental to its overall function and purpose, and</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="HF9EDB64949B8458AA74CF48670EA5DD1"><enum>(v)</enum><text>which is fully compliant with the State of jurisdiction and Federal anti-discrimination laws.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H867CEACA7E394F03A4A99DADEEE92D1A"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Treatment of exercise videos, etc</header><text>Videos, books, and similar materials shall be treated as described in subparagraph (A)(ii) if the content of such materials constitute instruction in a program of physical exercise or physical activity.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HDA18744C5FF44D6082D03141D38879E7"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Limitations related to sports and fitness equipment</header><text>Amounts paid for equipment described in subparagraph (A)(iii) shall be treated as a qualified sports and fitness expense only—</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="H3D02FF7D351541749EFEC88419DC3211"><enum>(i)</enum><text>if such equipment is utilized exclusively for participation in fitness, exercise, sport, or other physical activity programs,</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HF648DA47F1694E82B1ECCF0CCB953C99"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if such equipment is not apparel or footwear, and</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="H4EA7DF42A48A4C08B871C21C8C5C94D8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the case of any item of sports equipment (other than exercise equipment), with respect to so much of the amount paid for such item as does not exceed $250.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HABA8B63700EA481CB6EC3FB83A6CCE1B"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Programs which include components other than physical exercise and physical activity</header><text>Rules similar to the rules of section 213(d)(6) shall apply in the case of any program that includes physical exercise or physical activity and also other components. For purposes of the preceding sentence, travel and accommodations shall be treated as an other component.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HAA7A53B7F36841E6968ACE3F899FDB54"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


