<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCA3F49B3C39E4644986AFBF6CF6A7B9A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5762 IH: Joint Task Force to Combat Opioid Trafficking Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5762</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180510">May 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000559">Mr. Langevin</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000210">Mr. King of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to authorize a Joint Task Force to enhance integration of the Department of Homeland Security&#8217;s border security operations to detect, interdict, disrupt, and prevent narcotics, such as fentanyl and other synthetic opioids, from entering the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H897433CCD0CE4EADA73392AF91A01043" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H78DA4C240A8B4CBEB58CB55D599B6F91" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Joint Task Force to Combat Opioid Trafficking Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H75ACEED4B7FF4A219E9AAFDA14F07490"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authorization of Joint Task Force to counter opioids</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 708 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/348">6 U.S.C. 348</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H09EB94FCAEBA4B2DBA2AD32030A96594"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(2)(A), by adding at the end the following new clause:</text> <quoted-block id="HB312BD6095784EA0BB34F335C64B2F92" style="OLC"> <clause id="H16EF9D28DE0F46F9A724BA42609F1981"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Enhancing the integration of the Department’s border security operations to detect, interdict, disrupt, and prevent narcotics, such as fentanyl and other synthetic opioids, from entering the United States.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA0088018D07F421BA619091C3D8E70E9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="HD46110ECE741445690BDA1C7D4D6FD6E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (9) through (13) as paragraphs (11) through (15), respectively; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDC84281FB977465F84E191B9A1C9397A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (8) the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block id="H09B331E66993409DA0FA150DCBD4CFE4" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HB1AFE1BBD26F4C04880073F9D0A88082"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Engagement with the private sector</header> <subparagraph id="H47D4EFD901EC40909CABDEA19DB2840D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of a Joint Task Force may engage with representatives from a private sector organization for the purpose of carrying out the mission of such Joint Task Force, and any such engagement shall not be subject to the Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H530CF8BC939B4C30A1EA86C2B5557904"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Assistance from private sector</header> 
<clause id="H9C9609A31DB44FFD93A765A1CF228350"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subsection (b)(1), the Secretary, with the agreement of a private sector organization, may arrange for the temporary assignment of an employee of such organization to a Joint Task Force in accordance with this paragraph.</text></clause> <clause id="H8CEEA2E944ED437784A62880B644712C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Agreement</header><text>The Secretary shall provide for a written agreement between the Department, the private sector organization concerned, and the employee concerned regarding the terms and conditions of the assignment of such employee under this paragraph.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H936D26A5C504441993FA43AD0CB7F119"><enum>(C)</enum><header>No financial liability</header><text>Any agreement under this paragraph shall require the private sector organization concerned to be responsible for all costs associated with the assignment of an employee under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCE439719978F484481D807198668490B"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>An assignment under this paragraph may, at any time and for any reason, be terminated by the Secretary or the private sector organization concerned and shall be for a total period of not more than two years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H43444B91870844699A75A862A6BE92FA"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Collaboration with task forces outside DHS</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may enter into a memorandum of understanding by which a Joint Task Force established under this section to carry out any purpose specified in subsection (b)(2)(A) and any other Federal, State, local, tribal, territorial, or international task force established for a similar purpose may collaborate for the purpose of carrying out the mission of such Joint Task Force.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="HDC1C28B4C0B344588730C2D134BCE8DA"><enum>3.</enum><header>Notification; reporting</header> <subsection id="HE5AED713055E4512B80C532C110F91EA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3D7253FA994E4B5A82C92773B1D445CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>make a determination regarding whether to establish a Joint Task Force under section 708 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to carry out the purpose specified in clause (iv) of subsection (b)(2)(A) of such section, as added by section 2 of this Act; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H289B0E9B0AE44757BC8245A5046CD09F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate written notification of such determination, including, if such determination is in the negative, information on the basis for such negative determination.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD8C72618F9FD4E61BBC63BAA6F97B4A4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary of Homeland Security establishes a Joint Task Force under section 708 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to carry out the purpose specified in clause (iv) of subsection (b)(2)(A) of such section, as added by section 2 of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="H61884560354646729FD17ECDEEF622ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>beginning with the first report required under subsection (b)(6)(F) of such section 708, include with respect to such a Joint Task Force—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3461FB174F384902B8C8B49E15E0E118"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a gap analysis of funding, personnel, technology, or other resources needed in order to detect, interdict, disrupt, and prevent narcotics, such as fentanyl and other synthetic opioids, from entering the United States; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H74A903D1747A45AD9648795CD5556278" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of collaboration pursuant to subsection (b)(10) of such section (as added by section 2 of this Act) between such a Joint Task Force and any other Federal, State, local, tribal, territorial, or international task force, including the United States Postal Service and the United States Postal Inspection Service; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC3654597E27644E3A54E5D13F68D4CBC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in each report required under subsection (b)(11)(C) of section 708 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002, as redesignated by section 2 of this Act, an assessment of the activities of such a Joint Task Force, including an evaluation of whether such Joint Task Force has enhanced integration of the Department’s efforts, created any unique capabilities, or otherwise enhanced operational effectiveness, coordination, or information sharing to detect, interdict, disrupt, and prevent narcotics, such as fentanyl and other synthetic opioids, from entering the United States.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

