<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H09A3CAEADC044F0D823720DA0A5A773E" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5566 IH: To establish a technology-based job training and education program.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5566</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180418">April 18, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000570">Mr. Ben Ray Luján of New Mexico</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000580">Ms. Michelle Lujan Grisham of New Mexico</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a technology-based job training and education program.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H013AC694194F4A91A2BB5EEBB5034E43" style="OLC">
		<section id="HAA3FA50603E24234A9DE668E3F236234" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>TechSMART Workforce Development Program</header>
 <subsection commented="no" id="H6159C9E8AED742299AF7E530ADC72DEC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 12 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor shall establish a program, to be known as the <quote>Tech­SMART Workforce Development Program</quote>, under which the Secretary shall provide to eligible entities described in subsection (c), on a competitive basis, grants for technology sector job training and education programs that provide industry-recognized credentials during the 5-year grant period beginning on the date of enactment of this Act. Such training and education programs may include—</text>
 <paragraph id="HFD66F5E543D14CBFB95BCDCD4D3BF267"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">programs that provide a postsecondary credential;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H2A0CE2167086400EB4377455737B6A35"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">intensive coaching and other short-term, specialized services culminating in direct job placement; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB5F7AA6F7E0C402EB7FE232923F39674"><enum>(3)</enum><text>short-term or accelerated training that may or may not result in a postsecondary credential in high-growth occupations and industries.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H158FC641EC764E409DA9A17A90AAE328"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>A job training and education program that is awarded a grant under this section shall, to the extent practicable, provide technology-based training across two or more sectors, including—</text>
 <paragraph id="H01525887FEB54069AB28CF442BB9F332"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information technology;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HDF13806FBAC7426DB38E30D97D8E28CE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>computer coding and cybersecurity technology;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H62968E6DAFC84F8FAB67CA236C0B2DEC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>healthcare services technology;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H6A20B35795B9431EAD0EFC48776F7F5F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>advanced manufacturing technology;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE07B785AA6B64DB79F5DE5AC3C8AE713"><enum>(5)</enum><text>financial services technology; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H8A8CDA9DE7584BCC8B22D41581EB33AA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>educational services technology.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6FDA64BD82ED41E69130D9175098199A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an entity shall be a workforce intermediary, a public organization, or an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of that Code that—</text>
 <paragraph id="HD36DF2E2595D4CF9A19103239ECECDCA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>includes an advisory board, which may be—</text> <subparagraph id="H09FD5AECA3B8492F9FA4BF09B4DDAB8F"><enum>(A)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H2C55EBBF90B54264933D0F769B5FD421"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a local workforce development board;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD5D1BFF815DF4CCBA8B27F81BE515C48" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a State workforce development board; or</text> </clause><clause id="H1C62A703B77E4A3DAB2BED8FE7BA09FC" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an appropriate subgroup of a local workforce development board or a State workforce development board; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5BDB8DA56CFC44598A413CAA78CC4315"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a board of proportional participation, as determined by the Secretary of Labor, of relevant organizations, including—</text>
 <clause id="HBC13B90C25DE4BC59FB4770A83C2395A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>relevant industry organizations, including public and private employers;</text> </clause><clause id="H674E227D5AC5490A9D0ED959F728EDEA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>labor organizations;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA427CD1302464C5D8CB8EB29A3860A8B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>one or more units of local government;</text> </clause><clause id="HA8DA0DAD282B4088AA42AB0B0AACACDE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>postsecondary education organizations; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD6A68A63AA2F491B9B7E3AA9A074052C"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">industry or sector partnerships.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBBD1FEA44C3740BAA81BCD877843C3EC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>demonstrates experience in implementing and operating job training and education programs;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA4DA53B5D3884E559809711406A8896B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>demonstrates the ability to recruit and support individuals who plan to work in a relevant sector on the successful completion of relevant job training and education programs;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H3A169543903B47ADA60F76019622BEA6"><enum>(4)</enum>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H81F3146699E2488398597FE230E8A92B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provides students who complete the training and education program with a postsecondary credential; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42423A0D0D764C3D83BBB0F7368075D1" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">uses a customized training curriculum that is specifically aligned with employers, utilizing work place learning advisors and on-the-job training to the greatest extent possible; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA204B3AEFA554EE19C062371D2BCC344"><enum>(5)</enum><text>demonstrates successful outcomes connecting graduates of job training and education programs to quality jobs relevant to the job training and education programs.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3539FBC5EAC44FDC801DA5BE61CA7189"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>An eligible entity seeking a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary of Labor an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary of Labor may require.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H21767651BBF44B9CA5D2E4E80379EF0F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In selecting eligible entities to receive grants under this section, the Secretary of Labor shall prioritize applicants that meet one or more of the following criteria:</text>
				<paragraph id="H669818AA44104CF5AE4B448B14D95F26"><enum>(1)</enum>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H2C1304ED8F24451C9B9521E586828957"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Include a local workforce development board or State workforce development board; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1D93963468F4107B13BE30A09C4F534" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>demonstrate a strong partnership with a local workforce development board or State workforce development board.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBF6ED8470C140F78CB32D1C230B0DAB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>House the job training and education program in—</text> <subparagraph id="HC6A384F5F9CD4D6AAD50E8D6D9BB8B98"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a community college or institution of higher education that includes basic science, technology, and math education in the curriculum of the community college or institution of higher education;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H863A27F7D06D4307B71867E56B7B3909"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an apprenticeship program registered with the Department of Labor or a State; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF21AA590961F4960B50FB2E7DDD24412"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a customized training program developed in collaboration with employers that utilizes on the job training to the greatest extent possible.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H089228A7615247D09180F5CED3721074"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Work with the Secretary of Defense or veterans organizations to transition members of the Armed Forces and veterans to careers in a relevant sector.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4B390185BAD645DBB0E79AD54A47679B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Include in the application an entity that receives State funding or is operated by a State agency.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HCE3CB327EACD4E8793F5111998B29A7B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Include an apprenticeship program registered with the Department of Labor as part of the job training and education program.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H974F400CA76A485F8D775CFE871CC43C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Provide support services and career planning.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H8C93F23E039B412F83E5A8D922603217"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Provide entry-level technology workforce training aimed at matching workers with well-paying jobs.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H46A9BF59BF694A77BA00C1AC4E5BCCAC"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Propose to serve—</text> <subparagraph id="H55AF150284E24FD4B433E6A78958BF61"><enum>(A)</enum><text>young adults between the ages of 17 and 29; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H065A20A5A6CB42059177B6A1E16FCD08"><enum>(B)</enum><text>individuals with barriers to employment (as defined in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>)).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1C8A692C2EF34D15B5105739E6CFBADC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Additional consideration</header><text>In making grants under this section, the Secretary of Labor shall consider regional diversity.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H0C1D0B667359422CABA67269CB836420"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Limitation on applications</header><text>An eligible entity may not submit, either individually or as part of a joint application, more than 1 application for a grant under this section during any 1 fiscal year.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H0B2008819AC64EC89836F5E299368326"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Limitations on amount of grant</header><text>The amount of a single grant provided under this section for any 24-month period shall not exceed $5,000,000.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H55496C3975594B9F83DD406A78F68C7C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Non-Federal share</header>
 <text>The non-Federal share of the cost of a job training and education program carried out using a grant under this section shall be not less than 25 percent of the total cost.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HCDCFBC81D58C4ED18E70EE83C3FEF2E8"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Reduction of duplication</header><text>Before submitting an application for a grant under this section, each applicant shall—</text> <paragraph id="HE87CD85F86734DC38750F00CEA289320"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consult with the heads of appropriate Federal agencies; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBFDAD91DAA3C40D782FF81E48118A028"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinate the proposed activities of the applicant with existing State and local programs.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H29D730190B8043EEAADF3A5DA7E95CE1"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary of Labor may provide technical assistance to eligible entities under subsection (c) to leverage the existing job training and education programs of the Department of Labor and other relevant programs at appropriate Federal agencies.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HB549A543230C4C338A45F85CC236482B"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not less frequently than once every two years, the Secretary of Labor shall submit to Congress, and make publicly available on the website of the Department of Labor, a report on the program established under this section, including a description of—</text>
 <paragraph id="HB975851C771A4DFAA716519368ADE867"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any entity that receives a grant under this section;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE70EEF638823489B8F282691E326B07A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any activity carried out using the grants under this section;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4292E4293C5842738C974708711E0622"><enum>(3)</enum><text>best practices used to leverage the investment of the Federal Government under this section; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H865BDE6311CE44088FAC5FFE02CE0C9E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an assessment of the results achieved by the program established under this section, including the rate of employment for participants after completing a job training and education program carried out using a grant under this section.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H20F914A2EFC24F0DA74349BAB36691B9"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>As used in this Act—</text> <paragraph id="H4EFE56A4CA014F908B571F422C973096"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>institution of higher education</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0838A5D5552E41C2B19A635A39035F2A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>community college</quote> has the meaning given the term <quote>junior or community college</quote> in section 312(f) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1058">20 U.S.C. 1058(f)</external-xref>);</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H15BDDF25D55742E99961072CE58F7982"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the terms <quote>career planning</quote>, <quote>customized training</quote>, <quote>individuals with barriers to employment</quote>, <quote>industry or sector partnership</quote>, <quote>local workforce development board</quote>, <quote>on-the-job training</quote>, <quote>recognized postsecondary credential</quote>, <quote>State workforce development board</quote>, and <quote>workplace learning advisor</quote> have the meanings given such terms in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H38D83B1B5086429DB84143DFBB4EFF79"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <quote>workforce intermediary</quote>—</text> <subparagraph id="H92DAB93C552748F29ABE7265DAEBFBDD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means an organization that proactively addresses workforce needs using a dual customer approach, which considers the needs of both employees and employers; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB3D9F0F4834643F7A062FC737F9F6D3A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include a faith-based and community organization, employer organizations, a community college, a temporary staffing agency, a State workforce development board, a local workforce development board, or a labor organization.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H49D973C8FAE543C4B232F25BEDD295FC"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2018 through 2022.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


