<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7913E5F80B4D44DD8A3052893FA5B8C6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5534 IH: Give Useful Information to Define Effective Compliance Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5534</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180417">April 17, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000614">Mr. Duffy</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000593">Mr. Perlmutter</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 to provide procedures for guidance issued by the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HA8C05DB7951141D7986435312EB5AB58" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H46B33B0EB1824623B0E12314066A7FB3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Give Useful Information to Define Effective Compliance Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>GUIDE Compliance Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H79F0B11447474F3696BE0484F5680A6D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Procedures for Bureau guidance</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1022(b) of the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA7148D05E19043C88662D7198F80A372" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HE1A127E2080343E698CF8581FABD6EDE"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Procedures for Bureau guidance</header> 
<subparagraph id="HB9836F71C272468C8E6C035F5D373CF2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Guidance requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall issue guidance that is necessary or appropriate to enable the Bureau to carry out Federal consumer financial law, including facilitating compliance with such law.</text> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA3FCF5AF8A834034A53899DEBA75193E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Guidance defined</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>guidance</term>—</text> 
<clause id="H40D3E55F8E7C45248D7D4BAABF99AAB8"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means any written interpretive or legislative rule, interim final rule, bulletin, statement of policy, letter, examination manual, frequently asked question, or other document issued by the Bureau regarding compliance with a Federal consumer financial law that is exempt from notice and comment rulemaking requirements under section 553(b) of title 5, United States Code; and</text></clause> <clause id="HF8530DB8B44C466C834D6F9686A55616"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>does not include a complaint, consent order, judgment, or decision issued under subtitle E.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H64689FBA367347CE9B36CC6A7DFC2B71"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header> 
<clause id="HCACCEAB24C2D47CCA1A11BD50427AEF5"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Proposed rule</header><text>The Bureau shall publish in the Federal Register and on its website within 1 year after the date of the enactment of this paragraph a proposed rule defining—</text> <subclause id="H43E3448206E548738F598D98199F9209"><enum>(I)</enum><text>each type of guidance it shall provide;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H48BE8102A16E409FA83063AB4E1730CC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the criteria the Bureau will use for selecting each type of guidance;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HD3B9F0C051294CD49B21F9D11D74D4A0" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the process and timelines for requests for guidance;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HD621F7799C5A45C5B8D4320EA0D6983D" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the time periods for the response of the Bureau to a request for each type of guidance;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HED5DA1776A5542D99AD92CBE9FB251D6" commented="no"><enum>(V)</enum><text>a process for amending or revoking guidance issued under the rule, including a process for public notice and comment on any proposal to amend or revoke guidance, unless the Bureau determines public notice and comment is not required due to public exigency.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H1C2F3322604F4872BE4E14CED6EDB621"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Final rule</header><text>The Bureau shall publish a final rule based on the proposed rule described in clause (i) within 18 months after the date of the enactment of this paragraph.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HED621D36E476439F886DD17A711C2948" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Reliance on Bureau guidance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No person shall be held liable for any act done or omitted in good faith in conformity with any applicable guidance from the Bureau or any predecessor agency that was in effect at the time of such act or omission, even if such guidance is later revoked, amended, or rendered inconsistent by guidance or action by the Bureau or a determination by a court of competent jurisdiction.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDABD7C34C6E64D5AAC17694CD9616000" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Development of a penalty matrix</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this subparagraph, the Bureau shall publish in the Federal Register and on its website a proposed rule establishing guidelines for determining the size of any civil monetary penalties issued by the Bureau based on the severity of the actionable conduct in violation of a Federal consumer financial law and the level of culpability. The regulations prescribed under this paragraph shall, to the fullest extent possible, align with any chart, matrix, rule, or guideline published by the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency, the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, or the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

