<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD859702E5D434517A4591C946FF54758" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4847 IH: Broadband Deployment Streamlining Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4847</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180119">January 19, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001284">Mrs. Brooks of Indiana</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To streamline the process for consideration of applications for the placement of communications facilities on certain Federal lands, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9660CA93DA9947B0AD52BC73EFDBC5E3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7F5BA32AF3A047D9B2FB8F9BFD2359BE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Broadband Deployment Streamlining Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HC82678F41B1B4F829AC8D440D970DEBD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Streamlining the Department of the Interior and the Forest Service process for consideration of communications facility location applications</header> <subsection id="H1FBD926CEB424A589E282072C44DCF9B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H2744CB45FF564908BF8045DFBFD8EF9F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Communications facility</header><text>The term <term>communications facility</term> includes—</text> <subparagraph id="HBA0D40794FAF4E0EB6A95DE775119AA8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any infrastructure, including any transmitting device, tower, or support structure, and any equipment, switches, wiring, cabling, power sources, shelters, or cabinets, associated with the licensed or permitted unlicensed wireless or wireline transmission of writings, signs, signals, data, images, pictures, and sounds of all kinds; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCC03EEF70F4246CEA4333D0F0879E103"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any antenna or apparatus that—</text> <clause id="HBF283A8504CA4170A251CA9B17F00E5D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is designed for the purpose of emitting radio frequency;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6C3220D120AE490795E31124D7FC1039"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is designed to be operated, or is operating, from a fixed location pursuant to authorization by the Federal Communications Commission or is using duly authorized devices that do not require individual licenses; and</text></clause> <clause id="H96993E2BA59E4C269EA97C9182C95BB3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is added to a tower, building, or other structure.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD92B3A30AD9D40809C49BFC4BEAEECE9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Communications site</header><text>The term <term>communications site</term> means an area of covered land designated for communications uses.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0E900C3F137E4C89BA8F3EF8BD98539B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Communications use</header><text>The term <term>communications use</term> means the placement and operation of communications facility.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H067031D872144E5C916FA3A8692BE6AF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Communications use authorization</header><text>The term <term>communications use authorization</term> means an easement, right-of-way, lease, license, or other authorization to locate or modify a communications facility on covered land by the Department concerned for the primary purpose of authorizing the occupancy and use of the covered land for communications use.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB775471631BA41D69B9E3F147E07D181"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Covered land</header><text>The term <term>covered land</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1A8A04FF15AA4947950E68938721F668"><enum>(A)</enum><text>public land administered by the Secretary of the Interior; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA3DD78EFE2FC4B50A49DD18EDB5A924B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>National Forest System land.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H712DE2FBEB814532975FFC0156BFF93E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Department concerned</header><text>The term <term>Department concerned</term> means the Department of the Interior or the Department of Agriculture.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFDE09CDEE9A24623A2E317A70B82D55C"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Organizational unit</header><text>The term <term>organizational unit</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H179935D18C13437ABBC9444208769FEF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to public land administered by the Secretary of the Interior—</text> <clause id="H09233226AB324401B5B152BAC197B8BE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a State office;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9937EA4DB3E449BF9FD0C55245696302"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a district office; or</text></clause> <clause id="HABBAFD445D4B4947989535ED5B1B2C03"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a field office; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC36B349002554AF59822357A8DF79739"><enum>(B)</enum><text>within the Forest Service—</text> <clause id="H06E2C850995C401BB5A94A221E7703D1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a regional office;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF0F68266CBEF4D15B12E799B7F79B779"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the headquarters;</text></clause> <clause id="H4C7A3A7562C249A0B1DABE459FB416DC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a management unit; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0D600590BA684ACFBBD4654CEFFEA83E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a ranger district office.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H47A9ED0145ED47628711C08B33FD7621"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary concerned</header><text>The term <term>Secretary concerned</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3F26CFEFD34649F5823F0C7E0B348D03"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Interior, with respect to public land; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3D5F863E08F449BA8D440A1FC6665D57"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of Agriculture, with respect to National Forest System land.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD6D49171D2414DBCB56E11312A9429D7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned shall issue regulations—</text> <paragraph id="H4C2F8327D35A468E93E608C0DF7BACB2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to streamline the process for considering applications to locate or modify communications facilities on covered land of the Department concerned;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE083EFC3F76443E9BB31B59C71521F42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to ensure, to the maximum extent practicable, that the process is uniform and standardized across the organizational units of the Department concerned; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0728389CD4A248A1BEE1735B507B0335"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to require that the applications described in paragraph (1) be considered and granted on a competitively neutral, technology neutral, and non-discriminatory basis.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H18FD8E07C3B34653AE7881DF3A1733EA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The regulations issued under subsection (b) shall include the following:</text> <paragraph id="HC49BFD10AAF245868250A3309C2DEBD1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Procedures for the tracking of applications described in subsection (b)(1), including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF1765B1E46D74987BF727E95C2B6271A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifying the number of applications—</text> <clause id="HBEFE51BC7C9C4902860A71FF4390BC33"><enum>(i)</enum><text>received;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H875353896DD047B0A96ED338E62656B9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>approved; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA9ACB403B58843EFB2FB88485069B266"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>denied;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H81718D796AA3464B86637A184A69A212"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of an application that is denied, describing the reasons for the denial; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE02656D7865147A49C9F95E711BCD994"><enum>(C)</enum><text>describing the amount of time between the receipt of an application and the issuance of a final decision on an application.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H78EC379E5B744E6BAC4676715CEFE31A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Provision for minimum lease terms of not less than five years for leases with respect to the location of communications facilities on covered land.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3087B85674C04E708403DD187E01727B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A policy under which a communications use authorization renews automatically on expiration, unless the communications use authorization is revoked for good cause; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H02D5E3B88DC9433E819D88857A70BDC9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A structure of fees for—</text> <subparagraph id="HBEA4E67E8818426AAEAEBF80DCDC3165"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submitting an application described in subsection (b)(1), based on the cost to the Department concerned of considering such an application; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF1EEBF9AA2304EFF97AEAEBCF2F4AD40"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">issuing communications use authorizations, based on the cost to the Department concerned of any maintenance or other activities required to be performed by the Department concerned as a result of the location or modification of the communications facility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7DAD78CEE4FA4F36800CB4FEABC70502"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Additional considerations</header><text>In issuing regulations under subsection (b), the Secretary concerned shall consider—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC24CAF9F8C42447A96303139C3D98931"><enum>(1)</enum><text>how discrete reviews in considering an application described in subsection (b)(1) can be conducted simultaneously, rather than sequentially, by any organizational units of the Department concerned that must approve the location or modification; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA3295B5642E5446B8E47BAF1BD447D6A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>how to eliminate overlapping requirements among the organizational units of the Department concerned with respect to the location or modification of a communications facility on covered land administered by those organizational units.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE73CC4515B4F4C7284DB26B642967A03"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Communication of streamlined process to organizational units</header><text>The Secretary concerned shall, with respect to the regulations issued under subsection (b)—</text> <paragraph id="H93FB9B4A5A5D493086C2138F4D994984"><enum>(1)</enum><text>communicate the regulations to the organizational units of the Department concerned; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC0934082B34448618831242A974B0A87"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure that the organizational units of the Department concerned follow the regulations.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD8C86CE6E1BA4A71A9C41BA4CBBF6471"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Deposit and Availability of fees</header> <paragraph id="HAA786D902730427F9BE28A1034F9BD08"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Special account</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall establish a special account in the Treasury for each Department concerned for the deposit of fees collected by the Department concerned under subsection (c)(4) for communications use authorizations on covered land granted, issued, or executed by the Department concerned.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6B955D0E18B7445FAA708B2B86E944AD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements for fees collected</header><text>Fees collected by the Department concerned under subsection (c)(4) shall be—</text> <subparagraph id="HCEB131B660C8440AA098C164BC574A74"><enum>(A)</enum><text>based on the costs described in subsection (c)(4); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HED3D4077819141DDB5F04388A04889CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>competitively neutral, technology neutral, and nondiscriminatory with respect to other users of the communications site.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDFCE37D2628940F48CC07C1AF158A28A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Deposit of fees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fees collected by the Department concerned under subsection (c)(4) shall be deposited in the special account established for that Department concerned under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6FF2256973B04BE8BC7B9F20733F548A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Availability of fees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts deposited in the special account for a Department concerned shall be available, to the extent and in such amounts as are provided in advance in appropriation Acts, to the Secretary concerned to cover costs incurred by the Department concerned described in subsection (c)(4), including the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H3A6422739184408DBAAE960526E0336F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Preparing needs assessments or other programmatic analyses necessary to designate communications sites and issue communications use authorizations.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEE865FBE72884E37B70A2D3FA79DF020"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Developing management plans for communications sites.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA176F20340EB4455B6CE9CD17CE60372"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Training for management of communications sites.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6357A81CA5A34CD0A12900F00A29F6B7"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Obtaining or improving access to communications sites.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB37E1A06D2434831BD8AB36AE9E53348"><enum>(5)</enum><header>No additional appropriations authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (4), no other amounts are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H5C53EA4B4D974EC2A3700F6DC5E6B5C1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Wireless facilities deployment on Federal property</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6409(b) of the Middle Class Tax Relief and Job Creation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1455">47 U.S.C. 1455(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H6F8177875F024E919377AA34BD260908" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HF1FBB6600EB0444FB5F7BBA20CDB3F8A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Timely consideration of applications</header> <subparagraph id="H3B39A6C68D6B435DAF52FBB2D565EE52"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 270 days after the date on which an executive agency receives a duly filed application for an easement or right-of-way under this subsection, the executive agency shall—</text> 
<clause id="H26B351D4CC1B4C4194CD125EDC776D94"><enum>(i)</enum><text>grant or deny, on behalf of the Federal Government, the application; and</text></clause> <clause id="H532297629C454F06A26777DDDD53796C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>notify the applicant of the grant or denial.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF8AED2F674464326BD812BABE8FB05DF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Explanation of denial</header><text>If an executive agency denies an application under subparagraph (A), the executive agency shall notify the applicant in writing, including a clear statement of the reasons for the denial.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD1ED30B1747D4DDE9950BA97F2F53FB9"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Deemed granted</header><text>If an executive agency does not grant or deny a duly filed application under subparagraph (A) by the deadline set forth in such subparagraph, the executive agency shall be deemed to have granted the application.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3D5FFB3F999049F78D8795D177A381DF"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Applicability of environmental laws</header><text>Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed to relieve an executive agency of the requirements of division A of subtitle III of title 54, United States Code, or the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321</external-xref> et seq.).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA6364DD2411047C4A3742B990971D97E"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Point of contact</header><text>Upon receiving an application under subparagraph (A), an executive agency shall designate one or more appropriate individuals within the executive agency to act as a point of contact with the applicant.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H297655EB9E164A46B914E6619E8D9A46"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>An application shall not be considered duly filed for purposes of this paragraph unless the application is complete.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H3788BAE8853346069DF818CDDF70D97A" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>GAO report</header> <subsection id="H21B1157089F2466287319F9713B30D4D" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report evaluating—</text> 
<paragraph id="H866D799950CC4161B93553A149D12FF9" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>how the Federal Communications Commission ensures that the broadband data collected for the National Broadband Map is accurate, complete, and reliable, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H9825C8E0F0B7444F876D43F00C64289B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the source of the data; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H414D7A7C7D004BB2BC69E59A8337E453" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whether data may be available from alternative commercial sources;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0C28C7118E084830870FA19B2F1C37CC" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the extent to which Federal agencies or other entities authorized to distribute Federal grants or loans for broadband projects rely on data from the National Broadband Map to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H060A063A45D04A1F9AF244E9AB2CDFE1" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>award grants or loans for broadband projects; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H42C3C21E80954877BDD57019B58385E1" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>determine whether Federal Government funds will be used to deploy broadband in areas already served by private broadband providers;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFF58BC39424445978A4D4A5821C77663" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the actions the Federal Communications Commission has taken or plans to take to address the limitations, if any, in using data from the National Broadband Map for policy or funding decisions;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA7B0F4D78F9445A5B487BB994AE4103C" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the extent to which interested parties have challenged the accuracy of information on the National Broadband Map, including how the challenges were resolved; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H68F808879C044D0B86F05F4E027161DA" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>whether the Federal Communications Commission should collect data for the National Broadband Map from additional or alternative commercial sources.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9D4F2CE14C0240B78BC818C50CC5EE5A" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National Broadband Map defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>National Broadband Map</term> means the map established by the National Telecommunications and Information Administration under section 6001(l) of the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1305">47 U.S.C. 1305(l)</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>


