<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H306F78E00E1749F3A57686B5C24BB5B9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4867 IH: Child Marriage Prevention Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4867</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180119">January 19, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000515">Mr. Rush</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To clarify the definitions of certain terms relating to marriage under Federal law to prevent child marriages, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H70D9A6E21A344BFBA0ED237A7392D8CE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HFDD0D8924EC546FAB5DCB765B22EFE64" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Child Marriage Prevention Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H91F80643688A470198FE1848789EE083"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HF8E875BC6F7E4EC0B4B3BE7E5451B9AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A February 2017 study by Unchained At Last found that, between 2000 and 2010, 248,000 children had been married in the United States, mostly to adult men.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD0688F95BE1B4092A367122646AC41E8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United States Global Strategy to Empower Adolescent Girls, released last year by the State Department recognizes marriage before 18 to be a <quote>human rights abuse</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE961BBFA986640A6A169D43FD2149734"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Child marriages in the United States have included parties as young as 10.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H160FED1CF57B4AAD8BB865D1B2109278"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Marriages in the United States have given a semblance of legitimacy to relationships that would otherwise be illegal.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1FC2A13D506C4F1A9BA97F3F7E0BB011"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Women who marry at 18 or younger face a 23 percent higher risk of heart attack, diabetes, cancer and stroke than do women who marry between ages 19 and 25.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1A0309C6C13D429BAECC6B0F767E3597"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Women who wed before 18 also are at increased risk of developing various psychiatric disorders.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFEE1D52A6F7E49A28CD54C966EDF8EF0"><enum>(7)</enum><text>American girls who marry before 19 are 50 percent more likely than their unmarried peers to drop out of high school and four times less likely to graduate from college.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAD06652C550945C38F17AC1F7D751296"><enum>(8)</enum><text>A girl who marries young is 31 percentage points more likely to live in poverty when she is older.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9DEFE5683C924EC995F28B800254C201"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Women who marry before 18 are three times more likely to be beaten by their spouses than women who wed at 21 or older.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H738C8EBF13AA45DBA2C7B3258226EA53"><enum>3.</enum><header>Powers reserved to the states</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No State shall be required to give effect to any public act, record, or judicial proceeding of any other State respecting a relationship where one or both persons are below the marriageable age that is treated as a marriage under the laws of such other State, or a right or claim arising from such relationship.</text></section> 
<section id="HE7315E24B6D0474DB5BE0553395828D1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definition of marriage</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In determining the meaning of any Act of Congress, or of any ruling, regulation, or interpretation of the various administrative bureaus and agencies of the United States, the word <quote>marriage</quote> means only a legal union between two people of marriageable age, and the word <quote>spouse</quote> refers only to a person of marriageable age.</text></section> <section id="H28735D756B4045688EBD2FCA8A9D809D"><enum>5.</enum><header>Exceptions</header> <subsection id="H131F42F3351B482D833CE8C2ABDA3581" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Section 3</header><text>Section 3 shall be inapplicable to any marriage where the parties involved have received the approval of a judge appointed or elected pursuant to the laws of any State or the United States.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H27D532FFD65346D1B52FFF17C798B9FB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Section 4</header><text>Section 4 shall be inapplicable to any marriage where the parties involved have received the approval of a judge appointed or elected pursuant to the laws of any State or the United States.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HCE625935EE554380BAEE2F5A7FFCA635"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Independent Counsel</header><text>Subsections (a) and (b) shall only apply in cases where the minor in question was represented by independent counsel.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H67178A4D7B994AD79AC2006D2C7DE319"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H4055B9398DAF4709B06473EBD7F40D8E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <quote>State</quote> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, Guam, American Samoa, the United States Virgin Islands, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, any other territory or possession of the United States, and each federally recognized Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEC451DB8293C491E87B872891EBBFDE6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Marriageable age</header><text>The term <quote>marriageable age</quote> means the age of 18 or the age as defined by a State, whichever is older.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill> 

