<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H6F834A9CDB904FDD8A60A9A02A6D9677" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4900 IH: Metro Accountability and Investment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4900</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180130">January 30, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="H000874">Mr. Hoyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001304">Mr. Brown of Maryland</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize additional funding for the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, and for
			 other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HEA17546ADAA544C385AD016D68B027CB" style="OLC">
 <section id="H36836BD8D08E4622991ACBBD0AB9D306" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Metro Accountability and Investment Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HE49779A4A02F4CE4A5B7849909D6A65E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reauthorization of funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 601(f) of the Passenger Rail Investment and Improvement Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/432">Public Law 110–432</external-xref>; 122 Stat. 4970) is amended to read as follows:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F14782904D44B38A5EECE74BC54A362" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="HED88D417287948469253A026A2153BAD"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Amount</header>
					<paragraph id="H002DD2D1C2C94BABA7C0EC9514367664"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header>
 <subparagraph id="H9691580608DA43329ED5ACBEF869556C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Original funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Transportation for grants under this section an aggregate amount not to exceed $1,500,000,000 to be available in increments over 10 fiscal years beginning in fiscal year 2009, or until expended.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A1ABFF80F0444B59507F9D498B45DAB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Continuation of funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to paragraphs (2) and (3), there are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Transportation for grants under this section $2,000,000,000 to be available in increments over 10 fiscal years beginning in fiscal year 2020, or until expended.</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BAF48CF05F844F2806ACB3F8BBE0DF3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Restriction on use</header>
 <subparagraph id="H3E810F93F70F4578B6E5B190BDFB97A3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Operating expenses</header><text>$500,000,000 of the amount described in paragraph (1)(B) may only be used for operating expenses of the Transit Authority.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H657C2ECF7B0245E79936F6F0C58CD17B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inspector general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$100,000,000 of the amount described in subparagraph (A) may only be used for the Office of Inspector General of the Transit Authority.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5B0F2A6AAD445FAA5D7A70B6E456719"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Required modifications</header><text>The Secretary may not provide grants pursuant to paragraph (1)(B) unless the Secretary certifies that the Board of Directors of the Transit Authority has passed a resolution, and is making progress implementing such a resolution, that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE59B7575189F460EB04A83590424DF80"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishes an independent budget authority for the Office of Inspector General of the Transit Authority;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42F73349950D4C4B9A319A10015B9AF6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishes an independent procurement authority for the Office of Inspector General of the Transit Authority;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6D4A7E08233F44DEA4DEAD1B3F14416E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishes an independent hiring authority for the Office of Inspector General of the Transit Authority;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA361B4674EFB44F49AF467C4FAB7DF12"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensures the inspector general of the Transit Authority can obtain legal advice from a counsel reporting directly to the director of such office;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7401CD530BBF4E64BDF6EAC47E0F6927"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">requires the inspector general of the Transit Authority to submit recommendations for corrective action to the General Manager, the Board of Directors of the Transit Authority, and the appropriate congressional committees; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBB2FBF9876749E0B88097536833450D"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">requires the inspector general of the Transit Authority to publish any recommendation described in subparagraph (E) on the website of the Office of Inspector General of the Transit Authority, except that the Inspector General may redact personally identifiable information and information that, in the determination of the Inspector General, would pose a security risk to the systems of the Transit Authority.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H17C8319EFCE04964BCC9AEAE5822228B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Special rule for certain funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amounts described in paragraph (2) are not subject to the requirements of paragraphs (2) and (3) of subsection (b).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7DF07C8F05564A23AC115A344758B864"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure, the Committee on Oversight and Government Reform, and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="H18A0ED186ABE4B1E9000FE4C883B5954"><enum>3.</enum><header>Additional grants</header>
 <subsection id="H9466A0B72D244545BF46C65BE8FD0E16"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to other funding provided to the Transit Authority pursuant to any other provision of law, the Secretary of Transportation may make grants to the Transit Authority for the purpose of funding the capital and preventive maintenance projects included in the Capital Improvement Program approved by the Board of Directors of the Transit Authority.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HCEA16B8F89C54717ACE523E2936B2CA5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A grant made pursuant to this section shall be subject to the following limitations and conditions:</text> <paragraph id="H66FDB9A140334A94A0BDE61D9C56D0E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The work for which such grant is authorized shall be subject to the provisions of the Compact, including any future amendments to the Compact.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD9C9D4A992CB442798C4F5072C789214"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each such grant shall be for 50 percent of the net project cost of the project involved, and shall be provided in cash from sources other than Federal funds or revenues from the operation of public mass transportation systems. Consistent with the terms of the amendment to the Compact, or any future amendments to such Compact, any funds so provided shall be solely from undistributed cash surpluses, replacement or depreciation funds of reserves available in cash, or new capital.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H281889EB195F42B2A9FC676C6957745F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability of requirements for mass transportation capital projects receiving funds under
 federal transportation law</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as specifically provided in this section, the use of any amounts appropriated pursuant to the authorization under this section shall be subject to the requirements applicable to capital projects for which funds are provided under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code, except to the extent the Secretary determines that the requirements are inconsistent with this Act, its purposes, or any subsequent rules of guidance issued pursuant to this Act.</text>
			</subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H677D07EA134B4890992C53E0BF299AD4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Amount and requirement for first period</header>
 <paragraph id="H55766A4E62F0466B9593012D6FF98521"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Transportation for grants under this section $500,000,000 to be available in increments over 5 fiscal years beginning in fiscal year 2020, or until expended.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H07240A4C7FC246CEBDCF685AA2B804BD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may not award a grant authorized under this subsection unless the Secretary certifies, on an annual basis, that the Transit Authority is making progress toward goals and metrics for system performance established by the Secretary in collaboration with the signatories to the Compact on safety, reliability, and operation costs as measured by vehicle revenue hours.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE30F8F8C5B6C4364AAD56DE2BC47D26E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Amount and requirement for second period</header>
 <paragraph id="H884D9F69491E4065A80012339957E127"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Transportation for grants under this section $1,500,000,000 to be available in increments over 15 fiscal years beginning in fiscal year 2025, or until expended.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9003944D96D74897BEE0A4E7721CF156"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may not award a grant authorized under this subsection unless the Secretary certifies, on an annual basis, that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H416EA67D66BF4889B0B2D83F3302D64B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Transit Authority is making progress toward goals and metrics for system performance established by the Secretary in collaboration with the signatories to the Compact on safety, reliability, and operation costs as measured by vehicle revenue hours; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDBAEF8EF6F594B418C9A889BAABF25A5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the signatories to the Compact have established a dedicated funding source for capital projects for the Transit Authority that is expected to raise, in total, at least $300,000,000 annually.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4897520163B942859E0F8252B44F9BCB"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts appropriated pursuant to the authorization under this section shall remain available until expended.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H295A24774F6B402084101FFAA5F1CD08"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section—</text> <paragraph id="H758E2F5BEC0F4C34B565AFB23FCF5D49"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term “Transit Authority” means the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority established under Article III of the Compact; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDEE5BD6C46844F0C8B519E67519337F6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term “Compact” means the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority Compact (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/89/774">Public Law 89–774</external-xref>; 80 Stat. 1324).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


