<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H2AEBE6EA8C254807B5396D3AEE2E4AFB" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4914 IH: Supporting the Teaching profession through Revitalizing Investments in Valuable Educators Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4914</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180202">February 2, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To better support our early childhood educators and elementary school and secondary school
			 teachers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HB14EBBC7D96246E5A47489A020FBFD24" style="OLC">
		<section id="HAB8B616D7C554BBF893CCB892D4FC3CA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title and findings</header>
 <subsection id="H7B81E1B680134C53BE01888B2E46E73E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supporting the Teaching profession through Revitalizing Investments in Valuable Educators Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>STRIVE Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="HCE1DBB19902D42DF9450DE0DCE4D5DE1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H9F25A92C6A0B4C40A5B8F67DFED3AA1F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>States identified significant teacher shortages in their reports to the Department of Education during the 2015–2016 school year, with 48 States identifying shortages in special education, 42 identifying teacher shortages in mathematics, and 40 identifying teacher shortages in science. One reason for the shortages in these areas is because mathematics and science teachers can earn significantly higher starting salaries in the private sector. Further, rural communities face limitations in recruiting and retaining teachers for reasons such as funding issues, limited teacher supply, and geographic isolation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1BB9BD629BBB4A20B0633203BF96552F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Students in high-poverty and high-minority schools, both urban and rural, typically feel the largest impact of teacher shortages. These schools often experience difficulty hiring and high turnover on a regular basis, and they are the most severely affected when teacher shortages become widespread. This happens, in part, because inequitable funding of schools leaves many low-wealth urban and rural communities with inadequate resources, so they must pay lower salaries and typically have poorer working conditions.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA75F3F854B714B8D95AF7593F1F6469B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>According to a study by Mathematica, when high-performing teachers were offered large financial incentives to transfer to low-performing schools, their students’ scores climbed 10 points in reading and 9 points in math compared to students statewide over 2 years.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE7EFC3252E1F4239B0C62E8C104AFB33"><enum>(4)</enum><text>According to a survey conducted by Scholastic, 97 percent of teachers list supportive school leadership as essential or very important for retaining strong teachers and improving student achievement, more than any other factor.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFC5963A3B0944A3EA12852A48ADE5CDF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Research suggests that incurring postsecondary education debt can decrease the likelihood that high-achieving students, lower-income students, and students of color choose to work in lower-wage professions in general, especially in the education system. Therefore, loan forgiveness and service scholarships for teachers may be especially effective for recruiting teachers and school leaders from diverse, lower-income backgrounds.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB41F91F186F64E0398BC139EB7B9D882"><enum>(6)</enum><text>According to the Learning Policy Institute, teacher loan forgiveness and service scholarship programs can be successful in both recruiting and retaining teachers. To be effective, these programs should provide a financial benefit that meaningfully offsets the cost of a teacher’s professional preparation. This includes covering licensing and certification costs.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H88F74227C72C4E03BD18818A060FD54B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A 2015 Government Accountability Office study of Federal grant and loan forgiveness programs for teachers found that the structure of these programs matters. Further research shows effective loan forgiveness and service scholarship programs follow 5 design principles. These programs—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H65D02DF1E07148BD9AFD6282D4F6254B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>cover all or a large percentage of tuition;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E9CEA393AEE4474B5462AF92C1C3622"><enum>(B)</enum><text>target high-need fields or schools, or both;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C8DB09F86A14B3BA311ACF89FA8C08F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>recruit candidates who are academically strong, committed to teaching, and well-prepared;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7421C564324542EAB5895A2CEE8E36EC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>commit recipients to teach with reasonable incentives to fulfill their commitment; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF896FBEBDBD14FFD85D8791E6CC25088"><enum>(E)</enum><text>are bureaucratically manageable for participating teachers, local educational agencies, and institutions of higher education.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E4BA0451C6942AEB5F9613D1A9B7759"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The TEACH grant program under subpart 9 of part A of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070g">20 U.S.C. 1070g</external-xref> et seq.) provides up to $16,000 in grants to prospective teachers who agree to teach in low-income schools and high-need subject areas for 4 years. This is far below the Department of Education’s most recent estimate of the average annual cost of approximately $25,409 in tuition, fees, and room and board at the average full-time undergraduate 4-year institution.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF89E927A93E84BB699212D384E326365"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The National Center for Education Statistics found that more than <fraction>2/3</fraction> of the individuals entering the education field borrow money to pay for their higher education. Teachers with a bachelor’s degree have an average debt of $20,000 and teachers with a master’s degree have an average debt of $50,000. Teachers also start out earning 20 percent less than their peers with comparable degrees who pursue jobs outside of education. These compounding factors can disincentivize prospective teachers from entering the profession.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H138A6AAB169645979A4FF10454A9BCE9"><enum>(10)</enum><text>In evaluating the TEACH grant program, the Government Accountability Office found that almost <fraction>2/3</fraction> of the requests for assistance under the program from October 2011 through March 2014 cited problems submitting certification paperwork. The Government Accountability Office recommended improvements in the program’s design, including reducing burdensome annual paperwork, increasing awareness about the program, and streamlining the dispute process.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA8339AA6C3AF469CB14E72035C2AD259"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Spending by teachers on school supplies adds up to $1,600,000,000 nationally. According to the Education Market Association, most teachers spend around $500, with 10 percent spending $1,000 or more.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H067EB614FA444A9CB1A85F611E861903"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Teacher quality partnerships are designed to strengthen higher education-based teacher and school leader preparation. Studies show that teachers who are better prepared to enter the classroom stay longer and perform better than their underprepared peers. Teacher quality partnerships also fund programs like induction and mentoring that have been shown to increase teacher and school leader retention. Research indicates that the ongoing support for teachers provided by teacher quality partnerships, including mentoring and coaching, is an important part of early childhood education programs.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H85DD5B6DCE0D48598A968B3C0D095A2B"><enum>(13)</enum><text>According to the Center for Education Data and Research, a more diverse teaching workforce leads to better student outcomes, particularly in high-poverty environments with significant at-risk student populations. Further, researchers from Vanderbilt University found that greater racial and ethnic diversity in the principal corps benefits students, especially children of color. Three commonly cited rationales for this benefit are—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HBD4D038338C84BC0946D35C8A6CD9D5F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>students of color benefit from seeing minority adult role models in a position of authority;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AD7B4C5BA014C5BBD5B58DC71CBD246"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the higher expectations that teachers of color tend to place on students of color; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAFCC20FF8925428389E8D541C3035C62"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the effect of cultural differences between teachers of different backgrounds on instructional strategies and interpretation of students’ behavior.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H18A9EE78B2734F7D86CDA7594327654E"><enum>(14)</enum><text>According to the report entitled <quote>Empowered Educators: How Leading Nations Design Systems for Teaching Quality</quote>, effective teacher preparation successfully integrates theory and practice components. Further, according to the <quote>Preparing Teachers for a Changing World</quote> report sponsored by the National Academy Foundation, highly effective teachers vary in styles, yet have many teaching strategies in common. Research has identified a set of knowledge, skills, and dispositions essential for beginning teachers that should be incorporated into the teacher education curriculum. This includes the opportunity and capacity to reflect on and evaluate skills and to learn from practice. Evidence-based teacher preparation includes developing teacher skills, content knowledge, inquiry, and the capacity to provide effective learning experiences for a diverse set of students.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB593D56F23414456A99455E50EB8AE81"><enum>(15)</enum><text>As it does in medicine, the Federal Government should maintain a substantial, sustained program of service scholarships or loan forgiveness programs that cover training costs in high-quality preparation programs at the undergraduate or graduate level for those who will teach in a high-need field or location for at least 4 years, as candidates are much more likely to remain in the profession and to make a difference for student achievement after 3 years of teaching. State governments can augment such an approach with programs targeted to specific local needs.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4ABCACE6B4D34D088D684B6BE3B29690"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Research has shown the impact cultural competence can have on closing student achievement gaps and improving student outcomes by incorporating racial and ethnic minority contributions in curricula and diversifying pedagogical practices. Cultural competence is both a moral and ethical responsibility to create a welcoming environment for students to succeed. The impact of having educators who have the ability to challenge and motivate diverse student populations can dramatically improve our educational system and student outcomes.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><title id="H149135088B7F46B693764D2BAEA901D9" style="OLC"><enum>I</enum><header>Improving teacher support under the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965</header>
			<section id="H6BD3520C5076412B800C4D7657335786"><enum>101.</enum><header>Mandatory funding for programs preparing, training, and recruiting high-quality teachers,
 principals, or other school leaders</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2003 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6603">20 U.S.C. 6603</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H7CBD371A0C774BF9B65169CB994DF4C9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the section heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">Authorization of appropriations</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">Funding</header-in-text></quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H68F37E402579402E9FF09B1679518722"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking subsection (a) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA7B543FB19C94682919FBD3FCB809C97" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H7F5F3D17D12C48DE81A7C39733B7B289"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Appropriations for part A</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For fiscal year 2018 and each subsequent fiscal year, there are authorized to be appropriated, and there are appropriated, out of any funds not otherwise appropriated, $3,200,000,000.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></section></title><title id="H6199D1B463124A1B84A163C2DDFBABA4" style="OLC"><enum>II</enum><header>Teacher loan forgiveness programs</header>
			<section id="H40CBD3D8238E4C3CB0FD629475FBA6F0"><enum>201.</enum><header>Teacher loan forgiveness programs and grants</header>
				<subsection id="H2F101EB88C3C4E2CB66D32CF253C8C33"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Repayment plan for qualifying teachers</header>
 <paragraph id="H11EA71EA29064B2A90458C90A0E6CCA9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 455 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087e">20 U.S.C. 1087e</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC8A3EEC5F2E6489A965335BF00475D06" style="OLC">
							<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBCC5CC31F5DF409499AACDF8AB355C68"><enum>(r)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Repayment plan for qualifying teachers</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC7FAC5ADCBF14C2D8AC760B0638DC56A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall cancel a portion, in accordance with paragraph (2), of the balance of interest and principal due on any eligible Federal Direct Loan not in default for a borrower who, in a 12-month time period—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0AE02DD9F7434E9AAC988FD664910943"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has made 12 consecutive on-time monthly payments on the eligible Federal Direct Loan, in an amount equal to or greater than the amount of payments for the borrower under an income-based repayment plan under section 493C (regardless of whether some or all of those payments were made before the effective date of the <short-title>Supporting the Teaching profession through Revitalizing Investments in Valuable Educators Act</short-title>); and</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C742B0A2A6B42AF9A612A22C7D31608"><enum>(B)</enum>
 <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE1008C244DA04777B3C8890D47235896"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is employed in a qualifying teaching position at the time of such forgiveness; and</text> </clause><clause id="HC1765D13689D4CC6BFB0AD78F412CC96" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has been employed in a qualifying teaching position during the period in which the borrower made each of the 12 payments described in subparagraph (A).</text>
										</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HABFB0FF5A35E482DB022A70D338ED188"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Loan cancellation amount</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H912961ABB18C40069B4E777A07F9D68C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The portion to be cancelled under this paragraph shall be—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H45464DF098DE4FB7BE67C4ABF1D72B4B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for each of—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD1CAD0EEA9F64F379E68E2F0D9F86DB4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the first 5 years that the borrower qualifies under paragraph (1), in the case of a borrower employed for such year in a full-time qualifying teaching position in the subject of English as a second language, science, technology, engineering, mathematics, special education, or career and technical education, 15 percent of the balance of principal and interest due on all of the eligible Federal Direct Loans of the borrower, as of the final day of that 1-year employment period; or</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H36395D17411E427C802E0C3685DF1D36"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the first 6 years (or the equivalent calculated under subparagraph (B)(i)) that the borrower qualifies under paragraph (1)—</text>
 <item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEDE49BD63DB843539DAE5CD5B9B36665"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in the case of a borrower employed for such year in a full-time qualifying teaching position in a subject that is not described in subclause (I), 10 percent of the balance of principal and interest due on all of the eligible Federal Direct Loans of the borrower, as of the final day of that 1-year employment period; or</text>
 </item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5A099F47E38845578B88CE4C9BD0AA6F"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in the case of a borrower employed for such year in a part-time qualifying teaching position (regardless of subject), 5 percent of the balance of principal and interest due on all of the eligible Federal Direct Loans of the borrower, as of the final day of that 1-year employment period; and</text>
 </item></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2A359C004340426F8363AF44B4742349"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>after the borrower has received partial loan cancellation described in clause (i)—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB2A4A283793B45D298C4E6A8097264E0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>for 5 years, in the case of a borrower described in clause (i)(I), and then qualifies for loan cancellation under paragraph (1) for a sixth year, all of the borrower's remaining obligation to repay the balance of principal and interest due, as of the date of such calculation, on all of the eligible Federal Direct Loan made to a borrower; or</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9675598AEBCD434788357FB49E5A7BF1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>for 6 years (or the equivalent calculated under subparagraph (B)(i)), in the case of a borrower described in clause (i)(II), and then qualifies for loan cancellation under paragraph (1) for a seventh year (or the equivalent calculated under subparagraph (B)(ii)), all of the borrower's remaining obligation to repay the balance of principal and interest due, as of the date of such calculation, on all of the eligible Federal Direct Loan made to a borrower.</text>
											</subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF80916F8C6434CB0A3CC4A84FB4B52D2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Special rule regarding part-time teaching</header>
 <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDEA32E1F5A324AD9A8132E49D17A7E52"><enum>(i)</enum><header>General rule</header><text>In the case of a borrower who qualifies for loan cancellation under subparagraph (A) for one or more years through a part-time qualifying teaching position, the Secretary shall determine when the equivalent of 6 years of partial cancellation for full-time employment has been met for purposes of subparagraph (A)(ii)(II) by giving the borrower credit for one-half of a year for each year that the borrower receives partial part-time cancellation under subparagraph (A)(i)(II)(bb).</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB74EE0C3C1744AB2985765AB43CA6031"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Rule for final cancellation</header><text>A borrower who wishes to complete the equivalent of the seventh year of teaching necessary for complete cancellation under subparagraph (A)(ii)(II) through employment in a part-time qualifying teaching position—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5DBD64ACE08D4E6FAE721D2A8F365D9E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall be required to qualify for loan cancellation through a part-time qualifying teaching position for 2 additional years; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1C809FDD6D47463985F5278F20257C92"><enum>(II)</enum><text>notwithstanding subparagraph (A), shall receive partial cancellation, in accordance with subparagraph (A)(i)(II)(bb), for the first of such 2 years.</text>
											</subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H28F5C4C3465B48608F1BD969F45F4D3E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligibility provisions</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD812B88CCFF94D5D91302039BB119690"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>A borrower who desires to participate in the repayment plan under this subsection shall submit to the Secretary an employer certification, as required by the Secretary, of the employment dates for the qualifying service.</text>
									</subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC5BDEC0D7E7A40AF9A1253E57CA34C2C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Ineligibility for double benefits</header>
 <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDA0D7CDAB39E400B8CFE5224421E0037"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No borrower may, for the same service, receive a reduction of loan obligations under both this subsection and section 428J, 428K, 428L, or 460.</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAB421D9099BD4792912DE5305107E5CE"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Ineligibility of education award</header><text>No borrower may count any payments made from an education award received under subtitle D of title I of the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12601">42 U.S.C. 12601</external-xref> et seq.) toward the payments required under paragraph (1).</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3A76A0FC9B9D49AFAF3D8740925707B2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Continued eligibility</header><text>A teacher who is employed, for consecutive years (excluding a documented medical leave of absence or military service), in a qualifying teaching position at a school that meets the requirements of paragraph (6)(C)(i) for a school year but fails to meet such requirements in subsequent years, shall be deemed to be in a qualifying teaching position, for purposes of this subsection, for all of the consecutive subsequent years during which the teacher remains at the school.</text>
									</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H93FCAC24280544C08F99D1CA91DA8E5D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>State certification</header>
 <subparagraph id="H308E296D51F4453C873358AF6133CBEE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>State responsibilities</header><text>Each State educational agency that receives assistance under part A of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 shall provide to the Secretary an annual list of the elementary schools and secondary schools in the State that meet the requirements of subclauses (I) and (II) of paragraph (6)(C)(i).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE87C96CFD6B4C8E8D1A0DB708098944"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Dissemination of school lists</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> <clause id="H5D67E52244F74D76B1C1E192441C6A0A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in coordination with the Secretary of the Interior, develop a list of elementary schools and secondary schools that meet the requirement of paragraph (6)(C)(i)(III); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8BBE5D7CDFF6419989E0DB1A59154BA9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>make the lists developed under clause (i) and provided under subparagraph (A) easily accessible for applicants and recipients of TEACH Grants.</text>
										</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H286D07FD6A8048EE82272FF132B75DC0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Special deferral</header>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H3F85006D4F7642B1BC738BF829C830A0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In addition to any deferment for which a borrower of an eligible Federal Direct Loan may be eligible under section 455(f), a borrower shall be eligible for deferment, as described in section 455(f)(1), for a period not in excess of 2 years if—</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="HDD44EA3F189046DABF5CCC81489F2A35"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the borrower has qualified for partial loan forgiveness under paragraph (1) for the immediately preceding year; and</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H5E1E9C1AE64A4B1294E81FADCD928FB2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the borrower is unable to continue working in a qualified teaching position during the period of deferment, due to—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="H2E80125D3438458FBB371CC661CF608A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>extenuating or unforeseen financial circumstances or health reasons; or</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HDD7A6AFDC670459584D9CEF857F57F98"><enum>(II)</enum><text>other extraordinary circumstances as determined by the Secretary.</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0F4C0454D37D4DC0A80C9E22ED201B85"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text> <subparagraph id="H710A9B227122441DBB73C8B30F1D8DE8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Eligible Federal direct loan</header><text>The term <term>eligible Federal Direct Loan</term> means a Federal Direct Stafford Loan, Federal Direct PLUS Loan, Federal Direct Unsubsidized Stafford Loan, or Federal Direct Consolidation Loan.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D7426E861AF4177A0657A984BAA8E0E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Part-time</header><text>The term <term>part-time</term>, when used in reference to a teacher for a particular school year, means a teacher who works in such year a number of hours that is not less than 50 percent, but less than 100 percent, of the hours worked by an average full-time teacher in the local educational agency that serves the area where the teacher is employed.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF7DCF902219E4634A6EE0AC1969B9C78"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Qualifying teaching position</header><text>The term <term>qualifying teaching position</term> means part-time or full-time employment (not including a substitute teaching assignment)—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H7D2686B5AAAE44CA9A428914A6103982"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="H0F9CB8D6297D469881B10732ECF309B2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a public or nonprofit private elementary school or secondary school, that, for the purpose of this paragraph and for that year—</text>
 <item commented="no" id="H0A62E2B38B2B411F9582A00A45C0E2D1"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>has been determined by the Secretary (pursuant to regulations of the Secretary and after consultation with the State educational agency of the State in which the school is located) to be a school in which the number of children meeting a measure of poverty under section 1113(a)(5) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, exceeds 70 percent of the total number of children enrolled in such school; and</text>
 </item><item commented="no" id="HB499F7D83097409094176FDAF7B0942B"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>is in the school district of a local educational agency that is eligible in such year for assistance pursuant to part A of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965;</text>
 </item></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HD29C1C23692B40F1B131BE00FFC91FAE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a public or nonprofit private elementary school or secondary school served by an educational service agency, or a location operated by an educational service agency, that, for the purpose of this paragraph and for that year, has been determined by the Secretary (pursuant to regulations of the Secretary and after consultation with the State educational agency of the State in which the educational service agency operates) to be a school or location at which the number of children taught who meet a measure of poverty under section 1113(a)(5) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, exceeds 30 percent of the total number of children taught at such school or location;</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HEAABE3BF7EFB4E38822A80675C7851EF"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an elementary school or secondary school that is funded by the Bureau of Indian Education; or</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H7F310D0ADBCA43088BFBAD7D7DA46502"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>in the case of an individual who is an early childhood educator, an early childhood education program;</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H374DBC7416A04DD09633ED8F7344935B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>through which the individual provides direct classroom teaching, or classroom-type teaching in a nonclassroom setting, including—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="HA4D62F9A64684093B5D7C61BC40CB4F9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>special education teachers;</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H28892BB9C4DE465A8F96D395892AE2C9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>career and technical education teachers;</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H15D621AF2CD64913AD8C10E6242DBE8D"><enum>(III)</enum><text>teachers in the field of science, technology, engineering, mathematics, or other subjects;</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H54FF50B14CAF4C2C8DFCCC7C4B2C41E2"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>early childhood educators; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H394293DE66F844E888DD7C9DF2255270"><enum>(V)</enum><text>English as a second language teachers; and</text> </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H7BA2F7BBA3DA408E997EBD379EF271EC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>with respect to which the individual meets the requirements of an effective teacher or effective early childhood educator, as determined by the State in accordance with part A of title I and title II of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311</external-xref> et seq., 6601 et seq.).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6968F317D21B4CE5B038A4C4092AB376"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by this subsection shall be effective on the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8C53EB78DFC2427797CE086110C75F64"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Tax treatment of cancellation of student loans</header>
 <paragraph id="HB58B4C52163E44128E9B64B3C0DBF09D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (f) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/108">section 108</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF9B141125CA244B5A8D4A0E6D31DC023" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H1170D25B93E74447A6DC08F3378776D3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Cancellations under STRIVE Act teacher loan forgiveness programs</header><text>In the case of an individual, gross income does not include any amount which (but for this subsection) would be includible in gross income for the taxable year by reasons of the cancellation (in whole or in part) under section 455(r) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 of any eligible Federal Direct Loan (as defined in section 455(r)(6)(A) of such Act).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5122F17BD7F247C9B3742A044EF552C1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this subsection shall apply to cancellations of indebtedness after the date that is 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HAC62BCBA3A96431295F456DF29529672"><enum>202.</enum><header>TEACH Grants</header>
 <subsection id="H9524D4110AA84A4BAF0E72BF3CA3EB20"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendments</header><text>Subpart 9 of part A of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070g">20 U.S.C. 1070g</external-xref> et seq.) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HEF03D2F73DCA4CA4AB7196957AF5FB4B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 420M (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070g-1">20 U.S.C. 1070g–1</external-xref>)—</text> <subparagraph id="H9DDCB76FCEC54F66A7E888A35E27791C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1), by striking <quote>$4,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$12,000</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD83FF33BD0D14C388289E24A6822BD2F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text> <clause id="HB6128CCEFE4046AABB03AE984B2624DD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(B), by striking <quote>$16,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$48,000</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC13E0E8480774250AF93775874A54274"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>$8,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$16,000</quote>; and</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEAA668B8CD6454B8E5A4FAD30F82802"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 420N (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070g-2">20 U.S.C. 1070g–2</external-xref>)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H9EC45F99C58A4C56B11AB4453663D3CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(2)(B), in the matter preceding clause (i), by inserting <quote>, including an early childhood teacher (defined in this section as a teacher who has primary responsibility for the learning and development of children within an early childhood education program),</quote> after <quote>prospective teacher</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21658CFB9F2444D28C32D6DC3A812502"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H48A9B4E2AEF7469098C0476AA4639E84"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A), by striking <quote>4 academic years within 8 years</quote> and inserting <quote>8 academic years within 10 years</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD193F33A58C94CD0BBBDEA3A5765038F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking subparagraphs (B) and (C) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7B3389526A95445CA9B11FA4ADA33E71" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H24DA4CD742EA4684BD50E61A04EBC750"><enum>(B)</enum><text>teach in an elementary school, secondary school, or an early childhood education program;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H351B1F01D4CF43C38867A0C6C60161F0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>teach in—</text> <clause id="H9C08308A963A4298B2CB411D085E1D67"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a school described in section 465(a)(2)(A); and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA224AD7EBD8B499B8C81410DDF92442B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any of the following fields—</text> <subclause id="HBEBF4E6F7FF9445883F7B6C4AB7E36FA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>mathematics;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HFE0BDCCF51364FEA98C36832D9F502B4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>science;</text> </subclause><subclause id="HF7C1D4538402449A9B0480150ADD3F9D"><enum>(III)</enum><text>technology;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H730CF145F8624AD3ACC918BD066E3CB3"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>engineering;</text> </subclause><subclause id="H2A0D451225CC48E496C81CB7354CC1C4"><enum>(V)</enum><text>career and technical education;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HB9DA94EC3CB645678DF6F567A304406B"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>a foreign language;</text> </subclause><subclause id="H2D126455AF8A4135A729BC54E868A41A"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>bilingual education;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H51F7E8F1111F4869AC447F9D8EFE7752"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>special education;</text> </subclause><subclause id="HD7F5806236DE47F7A2A3D9A2AFD4BFE2"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>as a reading specialist;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H159761B57AB94C03B1E7277C989CADDE"><enum>(X)</enum><text>as a writing specialist; or</text> </subclause><subclause id="HB90E6F6547EF4CC9ACF240DBE1B91BAD"><enum>(XI)</enum><text>another field designated as high need by the most recent list described in subsection (d)(1);</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF750B2C9C03948ABA7269D0DED45F263"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text> <clause id="H1749BFA05CF84269ADF5D071DC517EC6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Service</header-in-text></quote> and all that follows through <quote>event</quote> and inserting the following:</text>
								<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE40186121BEA4AD8872870C2D2327B9C" style="OLC">
 <text><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Service</header-in-text>.—</text><paragraph id="H0C61441D1FBA48A1A99213EE49890A72"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In General</header><text>In the event</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </clause><clause id="H5E8BF34B18484DC3BE5FDAF5E3A59C06"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>paragraph (2) and the</quote> after <quote>in accordance with</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8AB43655F0C1496EB2376BEA9BF41C8A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA10026FE3F8E49018BEB680F443D5A5D" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H15A157198355460C90ED864CBE67F4B2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Partial forgiveness of repayment</header><text>In the event that a recipient described in paragraph (1) has fulfilled a portion of the service obligation in the agreement under subsection (b), the amount that is treated as a Federal Direct Unsubsidized Stafford Loan under part D of title IV and subject to repayment (together with the interest thereon) for that recipient shall be reduced by an amount that bears the same ratio to the total amount of the recipient's grant under this subpart as the amount of time the recipient has fulfilled of the recipient's service obligation bears to the total amount of time of the service obligation in the agreement under subsection (b).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1C86704DB2E4BCD9D2CFD6D52187265"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text> <clause id="H504DFEF6ED34486586FB66191BA15796"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) and (2) as paragraphs (2) and (3), respectively;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HCA690D4F7CC041B8A97E97641210C7A6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), as redesignated by clause (i), by striking <quote>subsection (b)(1)(C)(vii)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraph (1)</quote>; and</text> </clause><clause id="H1127EE6258944173B14A72FD1442A9E6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting before paragraph (2), as redesignated by clause (i), the following:</text>
								<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H94AA9D4F62A6473EB853CE1B615EC969" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="HD3162EAC41704AADBC66FE7DDEB1A495"><enum>(1)</enum><header>High-Need Designation</header><text>The Secretary shall develop, periodically update, and publish a list of designated high-need fields for purposes of this subpart.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7E871400E1AE4D1CA048B8192C6595D1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Simplification of the application process and streamlining the teach grant dispute process</header><text>Section 420P of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070g-4">20 U.S.C. 1070g–4</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H1716BE5157ED4F3F9CDC76589DEC8C1C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the section heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">; program improvement</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">Program report</header-in-text></quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H43F36D5D25294EE4A67974BC03EC6B9F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Not later</quote> and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5D3FF48DCCE64DE4A60E9E8AA02700D1" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H8DFA8C6C5A1E4DFFAC66337B2F7BCA99"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program report</header><text>Not later</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5FA344B6A3244022A70978837472360E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H10A36E0904B8448195370302E16AF567" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H6413B461B6EC42438B826EE2AF81289F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program improvement</header><text>By not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Supporting the Teaching profession through Revitalizing Investments in Valuable Educators Act</short-title>, and periodically thereafter, the Secretary shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H1287A130275F4CB08999B5885F298C7C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>work with States to identify and implement a process for increasing awareness of, and simplifying the application process for—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD079C9A66E9A4A97B2E77A7A13457358"><enum>(A)</enum><text>TEACH Grants;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBB079353922430695FB2CE944171185"><enum>(B)</enum><text>loan forgiveness, in accordance with section 420N(c)(2), for any amount of a TEACH Grant to a student that is converted to a loan under section 420N(c)(1); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE62E799F0B34B67B82359B5AB874F4A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>waivers of the service obligation for TEACH Grants, in accordance with section 420N(d)(3); and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFBF437B7F7248FDA709F20FD2DCC1D3"><enum>(2)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC0FFA56B171C46C9AC726BBB8B193F24"><enum>(A)</enum><text>review the procedures, including the dispute resolution procedures, of the process through which the service obligation of a recipient of a TEACH grant is converted to a loan under section 420N(c)(1) or waived under such 420N(d)(3); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE907D9D251384BD583DA0D12CFC3DB1D" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>disseminate and make publicly available and easily accessible to the appropriate audiences clear, consistent information on the procedures, including—</text>
 <clause id="HCD39424CF07346ABBD9882F293ED79A4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an explanation that recipients have an option to dispute the conversion or waiver decision;</text> </clause><clause id="H4EA65DD001104B8B9C285E92D2BCCEA5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>how a recipient can initiate a dispute; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H20F8C4F6758E4CCEAD0323420B69CCE7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the specific criteria considered in the adjudicating process.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H185D5A2094C641E1836CE7D5A7E4D736"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Data regarding Federal loan forgiveness and service scholarship programs</header><text>Each year, the Secretary of Education shall prepare and make publicly available data on the Federal loan forgiveness and service scholarship programs administered by the Secretary, including, for each program and for the most recent year for which data are available, the rates of loan cancellation under such program, the rates of completion of any service requirement required for the program, and the conversion rate regarding how many grants or scholarships are converted to loans for repayment based on the student's failure to complete the program or any required service obligation.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB76694C1AFA5401BB87AA1F0E6C47340"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section, and the amendments made by this section, shall take effect on July 1, 2018.</text> </subsection></section><section id="HF12D465C6F87428D8F302892FE79C0D9"><enum>203.</enum><header>Program To subsidize teacher certification and licensing fees</header> <subsection id="HE6733914FF1A46168AED8958F343F620"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart 9 of part A of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070g">20 U.S.C. 1070g</external-xref> et seq.), as amended by this title, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H95033019D1854025815C9A513437B16A" style="OLC">
						<section id="H9F8E67B3047746618B94D48B5F683CE0"><enum>420Q.</enum><header>Program to subsidize teacher certification and licensing fees</header>
 <subsection id="H7D3710867FE34CFABCF1B8C7FFEEBDB5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H4BC74BB2B690451B9E31F67FD9B042C0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Low-income individual</header><text>The term <term>low-income individual</term> has the meaning given the term in section 402A(h).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2ACBE64ACDA94DB888CD7BCA4135AC97"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Teaching profession</header><text>The term <quote>teaching profession</quote> includes elementary education, secondary education, and early childhood education.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H84AFC1B9B7654F1494E0408F9C10B687"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>From amounts appropriated under subsection (g), the Secretary shall carry out a program of awarding grants to State educational agencies, through allotments described in subsection (c), to enable the State educational agencies to subsidize teacher certification and licensing fees for low-income individuals who are entering the teaching profession.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H0AF13A5CE8FC44A196CEA9DFAF161E5E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Allotments</header><text>Each State submitting an approved application under this section for a fiscal year shall receive an allotment that bears the same ratio to the total amount made available under this section for such fiscal year as the number of local educational agencies located in the State bears to the total number of local educational agencies in all States with approved applications.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H3F8B567399304181852F48A58EB3B687"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application</header><text>A State educational agency desiring a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text>
							</subsection><subsection id="H3E78BD332ED84DE9BF9CFC7C8F54AA99"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of funds</header>
 <paragraph id="HC592A756EB08463F9D0780DA54AAE090"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State educational agency receiving a grant under this section for a fiscal year shall use grant funds to reimburse or subsidize the teacher or early childhood educator examination and other certification or licensure fees for a low-income individual entering the teaching profession who resides in, and attended a teacher preparation program in, the State, which may include fees for—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HDEAA401A60E949BAB0B7199D89268AAC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>additional certification or licensure for the individual in a high-need field included on the list described in section 420N(d)(1);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F1B5B6B17CC4B298FD0A8BA4D819B14"><enum>(B)</enum><text>National Board certification;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE66A9B595EF343CA9C51A0403D5C52FE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>maintaining active status with a professional disciplinary organization aligned with the high-need field included on the list described in section 420N(d)(1); or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H618F56E090A747DBB14820F263C43818"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in the case of early childhood educators, further education necessary in order to become highly competent and successfully take such examination or obtain such certification or licensure (such as English as a second language classes, community college courses, and continuing and distance education).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H309F89E02C484CED922392D35B3DA20C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority in reimbursement</header><text>A State educational agency receiving a grant under this section shall, in reimbursing or subsidizing fees in accordance with paragraph (1), give a priority to teachers and early childhood educators who are members of populations underrepresented in the teaching or early childhood care profession, respectively.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H74D35BCBFE994AAA965C1396B1C2BDF9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Additional funds</header><text>Grant funds made available under this section to a State educational agency shall remain available to the State until expended.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF019BF067E4D41B187D3C28DCD450067"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $50,000,000 for fiscal year 2019 and each of the 5 succeeding fiscal years.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H61CBB3E055F543EAB439E3D255280878"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall take effect on July 1, 2018.</text> </subsection></section></title><title id="H9C0BCADA561644F396E50730B8D2C801" style="OLC"><enum>III</enum><header>Teacher quality partnerships</header> <section id="HBEE799E7232C40CD814F1ABCF626B986"><enum>301.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this title are—</text>
 <paragraph id="H71C0199484CB4C39B79D1FDB1A4C76D4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to ensure that early childhood educators have the financial and academic support needed to remain in the profession; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2DBB1C6207694FFC9F2749151B26D740"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to strengthen the quality of early childhood education teaching supports.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="H1556718445B549B4B333BA1CC819840B"><enum>302.</enum><header>Providing access for early childhood educators to training programs</header> <subsection id="H5A7A486B168B48F696660FFDBD25312A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of early childhood education program</header><text>Section 103(8)(C)(i) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1003">20 U.S.C. 1003(8)(C)(i)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>age six</quote> and inserting <quote>age six, or the age of entry into elementary school, and</quote>.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H2C29104A169448D5AD4320CD15DA0B1E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Broadening definitions</header><text>Section 200 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1021">20 U.S.C. 1021</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H4613AFADAD024AF9AD780C69A825D200"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by inserting <quote>and includes an individual employed as a master teacher, lead teacher, or classroom aide</quote> before the period at the end;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H33AB5D40DFA345D087C153976FB5CB4F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (6)(A)(ii)(II), by striking <quote>as applicable,</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H3EBA70B74CE44087A6F3E06974C7C277"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (14)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE9728E41AFA845E6806C383160794611"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A)—</text> <clause id="H432D29AE51BD4D07BECEA0BFF4336EFD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, and for new early childhood educators during not less than the educators' first two years of teaching,</quote> after <quote>two years of teaching</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC6E5111A136D465BADD264D1123DD27F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or beginning early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>beginning teachers</quote>;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC541AE1302642CFAB6A8D1D52927990"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>teacher mentoring</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher and educator mentoring</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6ED49441DDA4F26B5FEACC2B097F6C6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text> <clause id="H4B90F3B08A6E4F38A16242173D0CE0E1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or early childhood educators, as the case may be,</quote> after <quote>with teachers</quote>;</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HB00876DE4DEE4E6C8F50B399778377CB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>mentor teachers</quote> and inserting <quote>mentor teachers or early childhood educators</quote>; and</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="H11812CB06E5A4C2DAE97E7F2D74E2A80"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>among teachers</quote>;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88CB7BF257BD4495A6CE252AA313B5FF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>new teachers</quote> and inserting <quote>new teachers and new early childhood educators</quote>;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E3D21C949644066A6B270DEBE392C33"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in subparagraph (F)(ii), by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>teachers</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B0DAC3DC108467182FFD22C89871CC5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G)—</text> <clause id="HD52DE3213BB44A66A7B0D8CA99BA2DFF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and exemplary early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>exemplary teachers</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H685231EC4BA0427DA3E99C87C4FDE913"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>new teachers</quote>; and</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71CCD01C509D4D13B0CD9FDEF6CBA488"><enum>(G)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>new teachers</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBCBBABFED3B74C44A7245DBB5398350A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in paragraph (21)—</text> <subparagraph id="H52C53BE39B1D433D8DDE89F8078EAB13"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the paragraph heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Teacher mentoring</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Teacher and educator mentoring</header-in-text></quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDEFBCD8ECD14DB086A615E9549C9BF5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A)—</text> <clause id="HC4F0381738EA40338A8CDC622A61DF01"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>teacher mentoring</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher and educator mentoring</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H95715D9EF16A438F9C74AB8B3F8F9CD4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>prospective teachers</quote>;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2F9E13221B9747F7B8F60DAD0341F03A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>teacher mentors</quote> and inserting <quote>mentor teachers or, in the case of prospective early childhood educators, mentor early childhood educators,</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B94B566B7574BEB8F1D955B109F087C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by inserting <quote>, or in a high-need early childhood education program,</quote> after <quote>local educational agency</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE160B7FAEEA436DB93C5614D0A9A1D1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in paragraph (22)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H3FB51F0BBF104F3BAEDC7FE69F31D8D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the paragraph heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">teaching residency program</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">teacher and educator residency program</header-in-text></quote>;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80D154C827744621B03EB0ACE0BF872C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subclause (A)—</text>
 <clause id="H8D75240B08E347BD995D9B691935BFF5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>teaching residency program</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher or educator residency program</quote>;</text> </clause><clause id="H0643641BC1904E3F9C88730DBE135F30"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, or an early childhood education program-based preparation program for early childhood educators,</quote> after <quote>teacher preparation program</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H0534944FF727401D99DAF718284B2CA8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or early childhood educator</quote> after <quote>prospective teacher</quote>;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H04F904AD88DE4431904DA15957B91066"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>mentor teacher</quote> and inserting <quote>mentor teacher or early childhood educator</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17D36BE2A1A143428F05E93656454BBC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by inserting <quote>or early childhood educator</quote> after <quote>the teacher</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA6724728874942C98D9C79C0757E02D0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (D) and inserting the following:</text>
							<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H80FC148CA4A44FDC94A96F19A752FD51" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H50026749D5A24C6691A1F0292A8F9B3A"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prior to completion of the program—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1605B92F18124BEC89A60EDDF6210DD5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of a prospective teacher—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5B185263978E48DDAB442B0B74080F25"><enum>(I)</enum><text>attains full State certification or licensure and, with respect to a special education teacher, meets the qualifications described in section 612(a)(14)(C) of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H616AB852FB7846099203ADEB3B885BAF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>acquires a master's degree not later than 18 months after beginning the program; and</text> </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5593BC47AB184A3B88D2D61395A7486C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a prospective early childhood educator—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H50B91938D3214F0291381122717CD83D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>becomes highly competent;</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDC0467053E9A45BEB79E60C22AA93392"><enum>(II)</enum><text>attains full State certification or licensure; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC2019BABB93847919522809D3B362F28"><enum>(III)</enum><text>acquires a baccalaureate degree or an associate's degree not later than 6 years after beginning the program.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFD65B35973ED4C388BCDA67D99F01014"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Expanding purposes</header><text>Section 201 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1022">20 U.S.C. 1022</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H953DDDA630C24C94817856B2F7B23D28"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HC4AE58FD876843FA810D36CA62C778F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>prospective and new teachers</quote>;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5DFF7651A0C1478E89D4C786E4F311E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>prospective teachers</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H84CA4C8342184A9A9D0E4B149929AE6A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>for new teachers</quote>;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD8ED4BC25AB4CB58635AAE4AE3005F2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>preparing teachers</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE19790814A5C4683AEB7B6A60314912E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by inserting <quote>and early childhood education</quote> before <quote>force</quote>.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAAE41D58648D4D55A40FD4F864929061"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Including early childhood educators in partnership grants</header><text>Section 202 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1022a">20 U.S.C. 1022a</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HF9674CB3089543EFBC933B6DBF608267"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="H36CA6F1A45D54948B87888276B167313"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>, as applicable,</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5560521BF47849179C4E323F86C159FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>teachers</quote>;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDDD9D6822D542A8B3285856A590AB6C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>teachers</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H967945C335CD4DB0A110B4016F593863"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)—</text> <clause id="H5169B56CF84A4DFB85516053F76BE011"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>or early childhood educator</quote> after <quote>teacher</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H7178E9E1738743618491ECFBBC07BB87"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by inserting <quote>or early childhood educator</quote> after <quote>teacher</quote>;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4CC543BEFC724DE8AB02235EF5B909BF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in paragraph (6)—</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="H8B6F9E892831461FAAD3EA51AE85637E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E)(i), by striking <quote>, as appropriate,</quote>;</text> </clause><clause id="H261C6500E2EC4B11881ADA847C895F12"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (F), by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>general education teachers</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD69CB75F4D584BA18D273EB6076ABE91"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G), by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>special education teachers</quote>; and</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H69CDB598C4704C12919BA95B3B41B929"><enum>(F)</enum><text>in paragraph (7)—</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="H49A3BEFD9D3941FFAAAE22730DDDEC8D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>prepare teachers</quote>; and</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="HFCBC5F1114BB4AEE8DEE291CF1820ACF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="H8C34C7DAAF4E4622BB46C19B935C195B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>new teachers</quote> each place the term appears and inserting <quote>new teachers and new early childhood educators</quote>;</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H4EAE6DC9A85D4255846DCE61224ED658"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>high-need local educational agency</quote> each place the term appears and inserting <quote>high-need local educational agency or early childhood education program</quote>; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H1577B419D7354B60A060FA190064C19C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by striking <quote>new teachers' teaching skills</quote> and inserting <quote>teaching skills of the new teachers and new early childhood educators</quote>;</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H50E834B275EE43358AD050B006F5FEA2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(1)—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="H4EE06134B21043CB947BC72A1516A163"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>teachers</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4F92FBB963EF4F42ABB4C36F82177327"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>teaching residency program</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher and educator residency program</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DE165D5330F4E74B37119890B33F571"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text> <subparagraph id="H51678A54D2134E7DAFCE4B7FEC35E627"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text>
 <clause id="HB2801247425F4A779BBF3249B048F1E4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text> <subclause id="HAC3F242819484D30BEE6CE93A53A9F60"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>, as applicable,</quote>;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H0A747FF4F75346B096B55BDCFFF56CA8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (i)—</text> <item id="HC0DCAEA0036646CEBF44314BE2A35428"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in subclause (II), by striking <quote>, as applicable,</quote>; and</text>
 </item><item id="H2ABEDE3FB39046B383D2212925792A54"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in subclause (III), by striking <quote>as applicable,</quote>; and</text> </item></subclause><subclause id="H4996AB97BF894AACA46AE220FFA1178E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>and, as applicable, techniques for early childhood educators</quote> and inserting <quote>and, for early childhood educators, techniques,</quote>; and</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H6566F59A6AE8473E962DBB7B02098CB5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)(ii)—</text> <subclause id="H487295B0E9C1465582330DF95BCF96FD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subclause (I), by striking <quote>, as applicable,</quote>; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H2B246F9E02D2485FA4B0E98D572C5CAA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subclause (IV)—</text> <item id="HE8CF1C903A044765AF7BB90BE08EF6B1"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in item (aa), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon;</text>
 </item><item id="HCEA5A7C1BD7B49A9B0F6B17D8CD8F1A2"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in item (bb), by inserting <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon; and</text> </item><item id="HFF66652993EE4313878DDB0DF611847E"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
										<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0AD3FDE630C04D0E9A422B5F03841414" style="OLC">
 <item id="H6EBC157E63B4466495CF1A1596E22395"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>provide culturally responsive and inclusive learning environments for all students;</text></item><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H303181A48A4C478D97F2FFE8EE7302FB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text>
 <clause id="H745F18F832844F769D237510342D0FA4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>, as applicable,</quote>;</text> </clause><clause id="HEF1AE0789C3E4243B001D9F10A716DB2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)(ii), by striking <quote>(as applicable)</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H9488DFD2FB90419EB62AB4D398554E41"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>teacher mentoring</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher and educator mentoring</quote>;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33F79E2C6A1347A08B95FE73581027E1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)—</text>
 <clause id="H93C17D3826144497A26C3325254522DF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the paragraph heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">and early childhood educator</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Teacher</header-in-text></quote>;</text> </clause><clause id="H277483E1C68E481CB77DE107B2E7ACEA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A)—</text>
 <subclause id="HA2468661C93E49E8B1AFEAFB5344F746"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>become teachers</quote>; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H45A938E32B274BB09E1A9CFC435C0DA2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>teaching profession</quote> and inserting <quote>teaching and early childhood education profession</quote>; and</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H336D1A42D6014C7F8BB04819BE4D26DF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by inserting <quote>or early childhood educator</quote> after <quote>teacher</quote>; and</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H112FB90DE960425EAF389B75D18267FD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>teachers</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB563CE4F3B494145A41395262AB64B20"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (e)—</text> <subparagraph id="H5F8B54BE463C4D22B7B94851BC2C3251"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the subsection heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Teaching residency</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Teacher and educator residency</header-in-text></quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC6EC00FDDB7429E83FD7EC18A073701"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>teaching residency</quote> each place the term appears and inserting <quote>teacher and educator residency</quote>;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8083F06CED32494A999F30E8772FB035"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text>
 <clause id="H5A28439FA0E9411880ECE7A10B4B1648"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>or high-need early childhood education program</quote> before <quote>in the partnership</quote>;</text> </clause><clause id="H7A55598CB1D54E62A881DABF04648836"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text>
 <subclause id="H73A481A4EC06481DA2449629091AD45B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or early childhood education program</quote> after <quote>receiving school</quote>; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H385B8328A17B4BD1AB74DA69FE6CCDF0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>mentor teachers</quote> and inserting <quote>mentor teachers or early childhood educators</quote>; and</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H5C8E0321D9FE4513A69AE550A5282BCD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)—</text> <subclause id="H729E6CD3DDB142B9BBB4345308BF089B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>teaching residents</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher or early childhood educator residents</quote>;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H003EC500950F44509A0AF3DB5D1E92D3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>teacher mentoring</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher and educator mentoring</quote>; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H9E497AE1E9304A85A839A7EE97FBFC23"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking <quote>new teachers</quote> and inserting <quote>new teachers or early childhood educators</quote>; and</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23C6369AAE6C44D2959DB5FEFE0B2089"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> <clause id="H40873B68354C454186C3982794EA71A6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the paragraph heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Teaching</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Teacher and Educator</header-in-text></quote>;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H5398759E6C1F4717B6CF9094B8F54303"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text> <subclause id="H087F9741125544699BAAE7B16792214C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the matter preceding clause (i)—</text>
 <item id="H20A2731BFE334D4F87BEB01EFDFA18F7"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by striking <quote>teaching residencies</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher and educator residencies</quote>;</text> </item><item id="HAC54EBDEA61C47C2A28AB2430550D224"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>teachers</quote>; and</text>
 </item><item id="H28A2E1BBA21D4CA09772F459EFC9E66D"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and high-need early childhood education programs</quote> after <quote>high-need schools</quote>;</text> </item></subclause><subclause id="H8B43147FE3DE4DDFB89611054C3E3335"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>teacher mentoring</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher and educator mentoring</quote>;</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H1C90C53A00EC4E39BE2E7B0CB1678665"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in clause (iii)—</text> <item id="HF7EA7FCEDA39432A84F8AA1B9A6FCCDF"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subclause (I), by striking <quote>mentor teacher</quote> and inserting <quote>mentor teacher or early childhood educator</quote>;</text>
 </item><item id="H201CC3DCE64B484CAFF9972AE2B2E227"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in subclause (II), by inserting <quote>and early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>new teachers</quote>;</text> </item><item commented="no" id="H4B29785B440A4CCAA658E149163A1E53"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>in subclause (III), by striking <quote>teaching duties</quote> and inserting <quote>teaching or educating duties</quote>; and</text>
 </item><item commented="no" id="HC7D2DD723233437F8CEFEEB5C09A41CD"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>in subclause (IV), by inserting <quote>or early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>teachers</quote>;</text> </item></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H80AD7BBC1AD94B3097E572A862075447"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>in clause (iv), by striking <quote>mentor teachers</quote> and inserting <quote>mentor teachers and early childhood educators</quote>;</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HA8EC299447C24D3A8F6AE61BC77B169C"><enum>(V)</enum><text>in clause (vi)—</text> <item commented="no" id="H6F811446AE5E4288B20BA1D31ADC4CDD"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in subclause (I)—</text>
 <subitem commented="no" id="HCCF2A1F8AAD9424FBF7284BD6CBC75ED"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or early childhood education program</quote> after <quote>local educational agency</quote>; and</text> </subitem><subitem commented="no" id="H5935723D58EF4726AA7EACB790F3A499"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or program</quote> after <quote>such agency</quote>; and</text>
 </subitem></item><item commented="no" id="H99D64C2AF5DC4606A5C96E1223752AAD"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in subclause (II), by inserting <quote>or early childhood education</quote> after <quote>teaching</quote>; and</text> </item></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HA86E895F69654246ABC6C4D1B74EFB8D"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>in clause (vii)—</text>
 <item commented="no" id="HF7884CC8D8A24208908C3382B641D75F"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by striking <quote>teaching residents</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher or educator residents</quote>;</text> </item><item commented="no" id="HD9F089ECE38D4E70B699828673F3114E"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>teachers</quote>; and</text>
 </item><item commented="no" id="H9333418994AA43489B981B6747735470"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or work as an early childhood educator</quote> after <quote>two years of teaching</quote>; and</text> </item></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H9F435446A1AF4DBA87B916F47F92E9E3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="HFD69BC6E599E496E97AC1887353DB06E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>teaching residents</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher and educator residents</quote>;</text> </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H07FAE081C55B43EA8B0E3631766FA0D2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>teacher residency</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher or educator residency</quote>;</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H89D41820EB084C2F9F54040D1742FA4B"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in clause (iii)—</text> <item commented="no" id="H2408386E7C5B423BAEEF6C20F2B88754"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in subclause (I), by inserting <quote>or early childhood educator</quote> after <quote>teacher</quote>;</text>
 </item><item commented="no" id="H069A4B52159D4864945BA88B72A9A833"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by striking subclause (II) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0AFB93525C604FEEB39B25A7E3884D40" style="OLC"> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H10D287D76A0E484EA709FE309AD5C2F5"><enum>(II)</enum> <item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1EC10975D83144B5AC1BCF0F7024D92E"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a teacher applicant, fulfill the requirement under subclause (I) by teaching in a high-need school served by the high-need local educational agency in the eligible partnership and teach a subject or area that is designated as high need by the partnership; or</text>
 </item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBAC27F1A016E4EEEAA6F2A987D0A22B2" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an early childhood educator applicant, fulfill the requirement under subclause (I) by teaching in a high-need early childhood education program;</text></item></subclause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </item><item id="HF3CB894C2D41432BA94959B1A55A08C5"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>in subclause (IV), by inserting <quote>, or, in the case of an early childhood educator, will be highly competent,</quote> after <quote>Act,</quote>; and</text> </item></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H97CADFD57C414562A778287897D44696"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>in clause (iv)—</text>
 <item commented="no" id="H79C91FD960904D2A8B428EBCEAEE7602"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in subclause (I), by striking <quote>A grantee carrying out</quote> and inserting <quote>Subject to subclause (II), a grantee carrying out</quote>;</text> </item><item commented="no" id="H483439980EFE4F3D9C32595BF34034CF"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by redesignating subclauses (II) and (III) as subclauses (III) and (IV), respectively;</text>
 </item><item commented="no" id="HE4CEE50ADE744B559B105562C83FF6E6"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>by inserting after subclause (I) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA9DEBA4167D6489784A0004AE4077DF5" style="OLC"> <subclause commented="no" id="H053E3BE28C524353B5AF9F7DD5AC473C"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Exceptions to repayment requirement</header><text>An eligible partnership carrying out a teacher and educator residency program under this paragraph shall not require repayment under this clause by a recipient if the recipient is unable to complete the teacher and educator residency program, or the service requirement, due to—</text>
 <item commented="no" id="H7042A9E39D4749B4A3483C305020DB33"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>extenuating or unforeseen financial circumstances, health reasons, or personal or family obligations;</text>
 </item><item commented="no" id="H1E8A0C8B52F44450B7A0A2B6876AF765"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>incapacitation;</text> </item><item commented="no" id="HB69EC78FB44D4858AA491AFFDAD4781F"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>inability to secure employment in a school served by the eligible partnership;</text>
 </item><item commented="no" id="H19DD825BF08F4FCDBD78412B342ED680"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>being called to active duty in the armed forces of the United States; or</text> </item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA75AD5B8B33F41B7972CFF3D6F2D0743"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>other extraordinary circumstances.</text></item></subclause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </item><item commented="no" id="H79C445CC414B4C60B545013ED555D052"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>in subclause (III), as redesignated by item (bb), by striking <quote>on grounds</quote> and all that follows through the period at the end and inserting <quote>on grounds not covered under subclause (II).</quote>;</text> </item></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E2B08FFB5814B5E904A7C2B4A264CE5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subsection (f)(1)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HCC600335FC424F2EA972F06CC2010EE3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text> <clause id="HF0AABE8223C04E70B021F13744882758"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i), by inserting <quote>or early childhood education program</quote> after <quote>school</quote>;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H37E1D32993A140DE97F42A50533E0479"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by inserting <quote>or early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>teachers</quote>;</text> </clause><clause id="H4DFF0906D3264DF6B06AD1449E540A8B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking <quote>teacher instruction and drive teacher and student learning</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher or early childhood educator instruction and drive the learning of teachers or early childhood educators, and students</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HCA553F4A73B24899912FD67F74F486F6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in clause (iv), by striking <quote>school environment</quote> and inserting <quote>school or early childhood education program environment</quote>; and</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H721289B03563440CAC180188A24D3BBF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D)(i)—</text>
 <clause id="HE3E3A47344F443E5A213B6A3AA75BBDC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subclause (I), by inserting <quote>, or in high-need early childhood education programs</quote> before the semicolon at the end; and</text> </clause><clause id="H83342782AD994CE5953A7770959522A8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subclause (II)—</text>
 <subclause id="HD4915A32EC524D2EBBB310449D30262C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>teachers</quote>; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H1852A693D1FE48BB9E7DD6ACF88D09A0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or high-need early childhood education programs</quote> before the period at the end; and</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE909D77F62E44FBD9FFBAE55403FE471"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in subsection (g)—</text> <subparagraph id="H26C098C8D53040008364253E329ECD39"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or early childhood educator</quote> after <quote>pre-baccalaureate teacher</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF552153566694CD79E6D18635227617C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or early childhood educators</quote> before the period at the end.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9EE27980FED24480809A1FE7E9E0EE5B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Accountability, evaluation, and information</header><text>Section 204 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1022c">20 U.S.C. 1022c</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H66E6213EF6C948D7B3D6A0CF369F16C8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="H811FA8FB15E048EF80CB1363CD85C8DF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>or early childhood educators</quote> after <quote>teachers</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C3A5297331941659513B6E4CE21486C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>, and early childhood educator retention in the first three years of an early childhood educator's career</quote> before the semicolon at the end;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAE94D883A3D424294D46D1FBE32D866"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text> <clause id="H87E1BD2892AE40398D62A1D0B6322AAE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(A)</quote> before <quote>improvement</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H713C5E0B0D424595A366739CA43F87DF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1D8295D66F4E4CA08DF3AE59105AD250" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HDE8AA9D30A204953AA2F72731B628608"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of eligible partnerships offering programs that lead to State certification or licensure of early childhood educators, improvement in the pass rates and scaled scores for initial State certification or licensure of early childhood educators; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB83B2AE144704C1F92057C7B2340DA3F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)(F), by striking <quote>as applicable,</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFFEE0A5BF3640DE85A15834E336A44A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H687081CB4B624D8AA0628A6457FE5638"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>shall ensure</quote> and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H769A027B30874210A14C5209E5788CAC" style="OLC"> <text>shall—</text><paragraph id="H0688830F910D4CED8BB610BC8D195209"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H91EBCA0E955A499B88986751DE4DAD4E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>part.</quote> and inserting the following:</text>
							<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H653BADD622344ACEAC3B8A8A58B0633E" style="OLC">
 <text>part; and</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H9E262CDABF32467BBAF69AC7063876CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of an eligible partnership that offers an early childhood education program that does not lead to State licensure or certification as an early childhood educator, clearly indicate that fact in the information provided regarding the early childhood program through the grant and any reports submitted under this part.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8D8E2E0009CE470689BDB4128387D32F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Accountability for preparation programs</header><text>Section 205 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1022d">20 U.S.C. 1022d</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H4E617ECB0D284023A6868A73FB5E9649"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the section heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">and early childhood educators</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">teachers</header-in-text></quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H66CE308C99534A10832A945CB45BE0F4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (c) through (e) as subsections (d) through (f), respectively;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H0E62F151F8C34337A1637D8C1ADF2B17"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (b) the following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7AECC9836D5D4E7EB64C97AEF02F1DDA" style="OLC">
							<subsection id="H58B45F486BA549DF8ABE6CCE3BF0BE3C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>State report card on the quality of early childhood educators</header>
 <paragraph id="HF936EEA8DA44482FAFEDFBA4DBD65793"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each State that receives funds under this Act shall provide to the Secretary, and make widely available to the general public, in a uniform and comprehensible manner that conforms with the definitions and methods established by the Secretary, an annual State report card on the quality of early childhood educator preparation programs that lead to early childhood educator licensure or certification in the State.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H98130B43934740CDBEF5D30FE3608C13"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional content</header><text>Each State report card issued under this subsection shall also include an explanation of—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H9AA7084325FA4F2E960AEFB395C31001"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how the State is making early childhood educators aware of available tax credit programs, scholarship programs, and loan programs; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB65F0ADE92E64DBBB695D9C335D6090A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how the State is implementing or designing flexible early childhood educator preparation programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph><paragraph id="H59DEE9430C32451FBF3A52053E6ACF02"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (e), as redesignated by paragraph (2)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H3B6D35EC18F44EE9BC6EF4338B5B63E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>and on early childhood educator qualifications and preparation in the United States, including the information described in subsection (c)(2)</quote> after <quote>subsection (b)(1)</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22C9F2B150B44C67842FE276FED1E762"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in each of subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (2), by striking <quote>teaching force</quote> and inserting <quote>teacher and early childhood educator force</quote>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H08280111591C430C90BA2E3F2F60ACB8"><enum>303.</enum><header>Mandatory Funding for Teacher Quality Partnership Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 209 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1022h">20 U.S.C. 1022h</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE8B66E3A82F4445D95682942727EAB6D" style="OLC">
 <section id="HCDE6EAD7D55C40D6903351807E0B4271"><enum>209.</enum><header>Authorization and appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this part, and there are appropriated, out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, $300,000,000 for fiscal year 2018 and each subsequent fiscal year.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</section></title><title id="H31754144549C413DB51240821C011B05" style="OLC"><enum>IV</enum><header>Increasing and expanding tax deduction for teachers</header>
			<section id="HCEFE489B08C64B6AAD6DC9449B5D50F3"><enum>401.</enum><header>Increase in and expansion of deduction for expenses of elementary and secondary school teachers</header>
				<subsection id="H849D6AF7ECC74DA88F2A453B64413CB6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Increase</header>
 <paragraph id="H5DDB286403534DC5AB4F240BF9E37CF5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subparagraph (D) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/62">section 62(a)(2)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>$250</quote> and inserting <quote>$500 ($1,500 in the case of an eligible educator teaching in a high-need school, as described in section 465(2)(A) of the Higher Education Act of 1965, or as an early childhood educator)</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H127C5F4A25AB41E59BE37D6FA5B4CB98"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inflation adjustment</header><text>Section 62(d)(3) of such Code is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HCD03B444037E4BD7B62A22582DC7AD8C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>2015</quote> and inserting <quote>2018</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H29B92712A1C84E70B2C5F8EEBCB6BAAD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the $250 amount</quote> and inserting <quote>each of the dollar amounts</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H708332BFC6AB4361B5C9C92317487A9B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>2014</quote> in subparagraph (B) thereof and inserting <quote>2017</quote>.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H493D9738BF1548619BCC1D32EB757A76"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Expansion to early childhood educators</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/62">Section 62(d)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H238518AA6542464EBC384213533092C2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>who is a kindergarten</quote> and inserting</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE02F60A115454825ABEF45E0900719F0" style="OLC">
 <text>who is—</text><subparagraph id="HA7FC0DEFCE5D41C89789CA061E20E6D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a kindergarten</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph><paragraph id="H099F5A7E9F4D42599184975062D5570A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>, and</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8481145ED2D74E9A82056CAECC75848F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8BC334F2D3FB48049FAB9BEE96ABEBC7" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HDFB3336C1EFA42F8ACA59ACEE6F6EDE4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an early childhood educator (as defined in section 200 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1021">20 U.S.C. 1021</external-xref>)) in an early childhood education program (as defined in section 103 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1003">20 U.S.C. 1003</external-xref>)) for at least 1,020 hours during a year.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDB0626B892F647F2B4927D45E4C5986E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to amounts paid or incurred in taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
				</subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill>


