<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HEF4FD810680840EA866F782BE3529E2F" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5387 IH: Consortia-Led Energy and Advanced Manufacturing Networks Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5387</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180322">March 22, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the establishment of clean technology consortia to enhance the economic,
			 environmental, and energy security of the United States by promoting
			 domestic development, manufacture, and deployment of clean technologies,
			 and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H67E4DBBABA604F80BEB951342D0E8E29" style="OLC">
 <section id="H963942AE09C04CCAB7935F9C27A2C982" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Consortia-Led Energy and Advanced Manufacturing Networks Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HA125DDDAC28E45EE800760BCFAC8E021"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
 <paragraph id="H8C982BED851744CEBD1FD07DE5E388E7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Clean technology</header><text>The term <term>clean technology</term> means a technology, production process, or methodology that—</text> <subparagraph id="H86EDA7F2C596411AA19FF230508281EE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>produces energy from solar, wind, geothermal, biomass, tidal, wave, ocean, or another renewable energy source (as defined in section 609 of the Public Utility Regulatory Policies Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/918c">7 U.S.C. 918c</external-xref>));</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E8738E39BB746CA9D620FEBE6B48898"><enum>(B)</enum><text>more efficiently transmits, distributes, or stores energy;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2220F41CA98B40C7AAA1AC32A5082AC9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>enhances energy efficiency for buildings and industry, including combined heat and power;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9FCDBFBBD20C461ABD4D7CA1E156A8ED"><enum>(D)</enum><text>enables the development of a Smart Grid (as described in section 1301 of the Energy Independence and Security Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/17381">42 U.S.C. 17381</external-xref>)), including integration of renewable energy sources and distributed generation, demand response, demand side management, and systems analysis;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6DB9EF21ABBD41C5A0B84AF57764F7AE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>produces an advanced or sustainable material with energy or energy efficiency applications;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A15B825ED1A4AD0A0C3DE3DD7DBBD43"><enum>(F)</enum><text>improves energy efficiency for transportation, including electric vehicles; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H307A884C17214DDD9AA1CB9AA1290C35"><enum>(G)</enum><text>enhances water security through improved water management, conservation, distribution, or end use applications.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC995DAA84C3042CD9B073C4773372308"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Advanced manufacturing</header><text>The term <term>advanced manufacturing</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H8CAB588EFE004D0F9FC22F0E00F36058"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means a manufacturing process that makes extensive use of computer, high precision, or information technologies integrated with a high performance workforce in a production system capable of furnishing a heterogeneous mix of products in small or large volumes with either the efficiency of mass production or the flexibility of custom manufacturing in order to respond quickly to customer demands; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78E2DAAC3CF148D39EBC9B0D405E3F20"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes both new ways to manufacture existing products and the manufacture of new products emerging from new advanced technologies.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2094326D86E4F71A097E51D2D00C000"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Cluster</header><text>The term <term>cluster</term> means a network of entities directly involved in the research, development, finance, and commercial application of clean technologies and advanced manufacturing whose geographic proximity facilitates the use and sharing of skilled human resources, infrastructure, research facilities, educational and training institutions, venture capital, and input suppliers.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4C6620F558974C348F24AAE6F4AF7034"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Consortium</header><text>The term <term>consortium</term> means a clean technology consortium established in accordance with this Act.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H7EBAB1C07C894970A86333E8F0E632FA"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Project</header><text>The term <term>project</term> means an activity with respect to which a consortium provides support under this Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H72DB5FAA17304578996BBE970B36C904"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Qualifying entity</header><text>The term <term>qualifying entity</term> means—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HC86DBE25D6E3478EA4384DA0DB5AF1FB"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an institution of higher education that has entered into a partnership agreement with a private-sector entity;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3D2E04C6A8584463BD73E884102F02FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a Federal or State entity with a focus on developing clean technologies or clusters, as determined by the Secretary;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H092CC0089E204FC6A120F34CA8A8BC9C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a nongovernmental organization with expertise in translational research, clean technology, or cluster development; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC6802C5AE9E4771A1C1293AF5446735"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other entity determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4902B0EE9A09422B90E9FAE551D1815E"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Commerce.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF4CB352C57ED4D489D11E6FAC95B4C51"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Translational research</header><text>The term <term>translational research</term> means the coordination of basic or applied research with technical applications to enable promising discoveries or inventions to achieve commercial application.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="HB744C33CFAFE4F26AE060DAE066780DE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment of clean technology consortia program</header>
 <subsection id="H66F0AB550FFE48AF85C0290D21F72F06"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish and carry out a program to establish clean technology consortia to enhance the economic, environmental, and energy security of the United States by promoting domestic development, manufacture, and deployment of clean, state-of-the-art technologies.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H154AD89114C14661A47721ADA310F175"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out the program established under subsection (a) by leveraging the expertise and resources of private research communities, institutions of higher education, industry, venture capital, National Laboratories (as defined in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>)), and other participants in technology innovation—</text>
 <paragraph id="HBF16A205DAAA4E21996B28CABC781190"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to support collaborative, cross-disciplinary research and development in clean technologies and advanced manufacturing; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD21B3F4354A848068484B9F16C05DD10"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to develop and accelerate the commercial application of innovative clean technologies and advanced manufacturing practices.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H721B6130F1E542168EBB4BD8B02517AD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Role of the Secretary</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="HD25B2F052ED64C489FD99CCC11E93C92"><enum>(1)</enum><text>carry out and oversee all aspects of the program established under subsection (a);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4F5094F6CD2A4DFBAB4C0D5F1D5E52A0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>select recipients of grants for the establishment and operation of consortia through a competitive selection process; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2A470F6CA6984C01B49A414BB5206A77"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate the innovation activities of consortia with activities carried out by the Secretary of Energy, the Secretary of Defense, other Federal agency heads, industry, and institutions of higher education, including by annually—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H33392647DAEB419489F0B04744B5E047"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">issuing guidance regarding national clean technology and advanced manufacturing development priorities and strategic objectives; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8EBB14548BE4BB782804FB13EFB4AB9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">convening a conference relating to clean technology and advanced manufacturing, which shall bring together representatives of Federal agencies, industry, institutions of higher education, and other entities to share research and commercialization results, program plans, and opportunities for collaboration.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0BCF18372EE1407DA0011C1C5F123E80"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Purposes of consortia</header><text>The purposes of the consortia shall include—</text> <paragraph id="H1AD0D22606E44D67AFA7D951A8C1C45A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>promoting new innovative clean technologies that have demonstrated interest and potential for commercialization;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9C30D27F7DB94172A979F3F29001749D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>expanding advanced manufacturing capabilities, networks, supply chains, and assets, in the area of clean technologies, that contribute to regional and national manufacturing competitiveness and potential for growth;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H87514923B00247A2BEDC59DF32D82715"><enum>(3)</enum><text>promoting job creation and entrepreneurship through the establishment of new companies, the expansion of existing companies, and commercialization of clean technologies;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFB5C4DBC90D547B98D98622B259CAD55"><enum>(4)</enum><text>providing technical or financial assistance to companies looking to invest in clean technologies, new products or services, or enhanced processes that will grow sales and jobs;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4F7701F8654344B5BFDA1A189F7D66CA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>determining opportunities and challenges that companies are facing and how to improve their use or production of clean technologies;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDEB8A70204B448D6AF81C1473CBDB973"><enum>(6)</enum><text>assisting individual small- and medium-sized enterprises with adopting and utilizing new clean technologies and related business and advanced manufacturing practices;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE82A662BD22C427F82F336B82C2DF58E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>accelerating investment in and deployment of clean technologies through public-private partnerships;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9EE9FC4E62004877B6E1ADCDD391B2B3"><enum>(8)</enum><text>encouraging partnering between and among emerging and established clean technology and advanced manufacturing enterprises; or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFA423E4D452A4245B8F84F669BD2F99B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>demonstrating a comprehensive and successful model for commercialization of clean technologies for promotion and emulation.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H5E06D3FBC2004348B92EBE85C24CA9D9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Applications</header>
 <subsection id="HF9F47964AC72478F8C2835AB4D587FF7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To receive a grant under this Act, a consortium shall submit to the Secretary an application in such manner, at such time, and containing such information as the Secretary determines to be necessary.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H45E4E379BF6A4D56B8A5BB77BCEAFF06"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>A consortium shall be eligible to receive a grant under this Act if—</text> <paragraph id="H1BF9E462D41540F6AAF7F5A99D0159A1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the consortium consists of—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H15B7811B3F54449499E3073F5EFF4766"><enum>(A)</enum><text>one or more research universities that can demonstrate a significant annual clean technology research budget, entrepreneurial support programs, and technology licensing expertise; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97E0D26D8B894A6B8F8AE5DC1A83A9E2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a total of three or more qualifying entities that can demonstrate expertise in translational research, clean technology, and cluster development;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H103DC6AE26754E92AA3946C10A6E4C20"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the members of the consortium have established a binding agreement that documents—</text> <subparagraph id="HCEC242E33FB54D9085EF50DA7F67F561"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the structure of the partnership agreement;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61D59668E2824BB6B8489D923C99D360"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a governance and management structure that enables cost-effective implementation of the program;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB4C4C4A3906D47A39FB972A7CF165D20"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a conflicts-of-interest policy, including procedures, consistent with those of the Department of Commerce, to ensure that employees and designees for consortium activities who are in decisionmaking capacities disclose all material conflicts of interest, including financial, organizational, and personal conflicts of interest;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36B44230D2894939B1D3926F6C6595B9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an accounting structure that meets the requirements of the Secretary and that may be audited under this Act; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BF9C913E5084B1C90296B1FCDDAD97C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the existence of an external advisory committee;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFAC17386F5844DEFBA755E422C4EFD88"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the consortium receives funding from non-Federal sources, such as a State and participants of the consortium, that may be used to support projects;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB292928B3CB849C692EB0637F3D7C463"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the consortium is part of an existing cluster or demonstrates high potential to develop a new cluster; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H24A931387D524F7EA9C26743462BC886"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the consortium operates as a nonprofit organization or as a public-private partnership under an operating agreement led by a nonprofit organization.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB33307FCE49C4B019BD20350D2FD9AFC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Disqualification</header><text>The Secretary may disqualify an application from a consortium under this Act if the Secretary determines that the conflicts-of-interest policy of the consortium is inadequate.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HC028A037C5154614A318E21732692366"><enum>(d)</enum><header>External advisory committees</header>
 <paragraph id="H07F41996C70941B2B611CCC27D2392E4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this Act, a consortium shall establish an external advisory committee, the members of which shall have extensive and relevant scientific, technical, industry, financial, or research management expertise.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5A89B3D257C447ED9C5C686004D8AC6B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>An external advisory committee shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H0BC986384111499E861DECFDF863CA70"><enum>(A)</enum><text>review the proposed plans, programs, project selection criteria, and projects of the consortium; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB74CAD673E74D559EFCE2DDBB29582E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that projects selected by the consortium meet the applicable conflicts-of-interest policy of the consortium.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CDE0EB1DAEA43FB97FAA76DE1AA72BF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Members</header><text>An external advisory committee shall consist of—</text> <subparagraph id="HAD4EB2C7F9AC48D685103E19A0A5F4AC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>representatives of the members of the consortium; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H566E493CEA6A491BA0232A6861BA0292"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such representatives of industry, including entrepreneurs and venture capitalists, as the members of the consortium determine to be necessary.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3FB6F4F42414BAA8C079E12DCF9D0A1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary as member</header><text>The Secretary shall join the external advisory committee of a consortium that receives a grant under this Act.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H975F37084DB242E2A56C51D05ECE9E27"><enum>5.</enum><header>Grants</header>
 <subsection commented="no" id="H60012BDEA439476490B989D66A2BD122"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants, on a competitive basis—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="HBC6FB8E1134A4C77ACD96DDC10B64C5B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, to at least 1 consortium; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H61CA845C37C341C0A383FD2B84A97143"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not later than 10 years after such date of enactment, to not fewer than 6 consortia.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDB7F5A19288246E4B0E5DA415865F890"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Terms</header> <paragraph id="HA9A854F262D443498B7553976666E31D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The initial term of a grant awarded under this Act shall not exceed 5 years.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE7B2E7128A884CF38B248B1156861A2B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Extension</header><text>The Secretary may extend the term of a grant awarded under this Act for a period of not more than 5 additional years.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5B2B5BECC88440C3A7A5F3BAF7D50579"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Amounts</header>
 <paragraph id="H3E6BC9421C9846D1B45E275B83067716"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A grant awarded to a consortium under this Act shall not exceed the lesser of—</text> <subparagraph id="H022EE7E80B7B41ED863437C43C248ABE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$30,000,000 per fiscal year; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6DA6385A3DA459E99CBD8776DEDD26F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the collective contributions of non-Federal entities to the consortium, as described under section 4(b)(3).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8C62665761C4F09998742E48525055D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Flexibility</header><text>In determining the amount of a grant under this section, the Secretary shall consider—</text> <subparagraph id="H6063EED678874959AFD5D577233E5D98"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the translational research capacity of the consortium;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D5E5F2137954C2C9FA885D80A0605BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the financial, human, and facility resources of the qualifying entities; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF3ADEFE50C7A420AAA80E85E7DB5F305"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the cluster of which the consortium is a part.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FFD8DEB28FF4465A51D137D649CF18F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Increases in amounts</header><text>Subject to paragraph (1), a consortium may request an increase in the amount of a grant awarded under this Act at the time the consortium requests an extension of an initial grant.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H25D635D99C3742CC8EBD7C9FBF3ED56F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of amounts</header>
 <paragraph id="H6C2B1B3F089F4426A803E008708DC971"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (3), a consortium awarded a grant under this Act shall use the amounts to support translational research, technology development, manufacturing innovation, and commercialization activities relating to clean technology.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA5950A83527348CD9D321345C539E45A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Project selection</header><text>As a condition of receiving a grant under this Act, a consortium shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H26A7E03D5AE94454AE4B8C59E2973CD2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop and make available to the public on the Web site of the Department of Commerce proposed plans, programs, project selection criteria, and terms for individual project awards;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B6104F518E444BBA92FB12CD1F5CF58"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establish policies—</text> <clause id="HCC81205B56B9491E89B6031E879BE365"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to prevent resources provided to the consortium from being used to displace private sector investment otherwise likely to occur, including investment from private sector entities that are members of the consortium;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H2D7334013CAA4A7AA1275B5D487BFC7E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to facilitate the participation of private entities that invest in clean technologies to perform due diligence on award proposals, to participate in the award review process, and to provide guidance to projects supported by the consortium; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H7041E730BCDF4C549CCF65D652295714"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to facilitate the participation of parties with a demonstrated history of commercial application of clean technologies in the development of consortium projects;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43072200186C4E5CBA20464C8B77B732"><enum>(C)</enum><text>oversee project solicitations, review proposed projects, and select projects for awards; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D2220242ACB4CCD85B0E2711397BE37"><enum>(D)</enum><text>monitor project implementation.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFD82ABC4471436D86FC83DD69FF498B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitations</header>
 <subparagraph id="H1481BBD007434A9381FB23B4F0EE5B9F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Administrative expenses</header><text>A consortium may use not more than 10 percent of the amounts awarded to the consortium for administrative expenses.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC37C2A78838E48749C625339897250D2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Prohibition on use</header><text>A consortium may not use any amounts awarded to the consortium under this Act to construct a new building or facility.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD1D407B1E6754EC08FC206C4C526EAA0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Audits</header>
 <paragraph id="H9FB51B6D1CB145639F09E9540D428D56"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A consortium that receives a grant under this Act shall carry out, in accordance with such requirements as the Secretary may prescribe, an annual audit to determine whether the grant has been used in accordance with this Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H87164CC938924AD7BAB0CC21BE3FE682"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The consortium shall submit a copy of each audit under paragraph (1) to the Secretary and the Comptroller General of the United States.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBB75413A453047F4837D76F4F4A74E54"><enum>(3)</enum><header>GAO review</header><text>As a condition of receiving a grant under this Act, a consortium shall allow the Comptroller General of the United States, on the request of the Comptroller General, full access to the books, records, and personnel of consortium.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2B00A75EB0B64565BFD232724C832190"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text>The Secretary shall submit to Congress annually a report that includes—</text> <subparagraph id="H7E4AFCE65E664BF8980C741AA928E46D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a copy of each audit carried out under paragraph (1); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7ED885951D34B8A8D191350AFE249D0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any recommendations of the Secretary relating to the clean technology consortia program.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1AEE909761784537B5C06C12EE6DCF5F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Revocation of awards</header><text>The Secretary shall have the authority—</text>
 <paragraph id="H08DDDC36039248D4870DB74BA88DCDF6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to review grants awarded under this Act; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H23B9EFD8E38645A7B4A629817D609E4C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to revoke a grant awarded under this Act if the Secretary determines that a consortium has used the grant in a manner that is not consistent with this Act.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3FB79F94EFF644A9B116DA9C3A036769"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this section $100,000,000.</text> </subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

