<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H1C189D4CF09A4589A414BB0131E31E10" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5179 IH: National Cyber Hacking Competition for our Youth Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5179</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180306">March 6, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Homeland Security to coordinate a National Cyber Hacking Competition for
			 high school students, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H7F27C03F39B44E1497BF67BFBD626853" style="OLC">
 <section id="H13CA20223562409DA688AAFC76FE5264" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Cyber Hacking Competition for our Youth Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H07AE58DD1B954B149520D75B2D4F8099"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of competition</header> <subsection id="H06E51C7F1BEB413C906DF130D5AA439A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Department of Homeland Security shall coordinate a National Cyber Hacking Competition for students at secondary schools, which shall be held each year among students in each congressional district. The Secretary shall coordinate with Members of Congress to promote the Competition with appropriate outreach to local educational agencies.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HB2C71977CD764EC4B7394B0F0F8198DB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security, in consultation with local educational agencies, shall establish rules and guidelines for the implementation of the competition described in subsection (a). The Secretary shall post such rules and guidelines on a publically-accessible webpage of the Department of Homeland Security.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5185AA69BE854CC2B0C9D9B0B4B76789"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of the Competition include the following:</text> <paragraph id="H8118539DCFF347D685488FA3AD62B9BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Promoting and developing a 21st century cybersecurity workforce for high school students by increasing awareness of emerging technologies to combat cybersecurity risks.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAD3337069F7D4FF89E89569527528C9D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Engaging students and State and local governments to collaborate with industries to strengthen and secure information systems and prevent vulnerabilities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA6BC3845A0CD46EC91F842DEC75FA2F0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Advancing cybersecurity’s role in preventing large scale data theft, scams, and malicious information operations that affect millions of Americans.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFE430E89DA2F4380894434E61175EC74"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Addressing best practices and privacy tools to combat cybersecurity risks for American households, State and local governments, and industries connected online.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAE1CD1F64A694C84B55DC0BB262C8FFB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Actively engaging students from communities that are traditionally under-represented or low performing in science, technology, engineering, or mathematics.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9FA78E2533B04B70BBE045F4D95ED148"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Initiating innovative policymaking by connecting State and local governments to secondary school students on new and emerging cybersecurity risks and prevention.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF855CE07B25D4DEA911E1926A231E4FF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this Act may be construed as requiring secondary schools to participate in the Competition.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE673927222F44DBF8F19F69849D94392"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H92AE718197FC471ABDC82DBBAB8BC5AE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Competition</header><text>The term <quote>Competition</quote> means the National Cyber Hacking Competition under this section.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBA75BD8A74C34372ACD55EC1398CDDFC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cybersecurity risk</header><text>The term <quote>cybersecurity risk</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 227 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/148">6 U.S.C. 148</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDD0438AD57384B569FFC40E5B5F6CC71"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Information system</header><text>The term <quote>information system</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 3502 of title 44, United States Code.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9A9C2338505C4C71962F54C5ECAD5D0C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Local educational agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>local educational agency</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAA8FD0C27401460BB4E2EB956707A8E4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secondary school</header><text>The term <quote>secondary school</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


