<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HE3F1BA6C92624EB9BCEFB597B273EADD" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5403 IH: Strategic Withdrawal of Agencies for Meaningful Placement Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5403</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180322">March 22, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001189">Mr. Messer</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To establish a competitive bidding process for the relocation of the headquarters of Executive
			 agencies, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H0D2D96CE390F44D98C817D2528C5664B" style="OLC">
 <section id="HD4521C7AE6F24188A65137B857A9200E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Strategic Withdrawal of Agencies for Meaningful Placement Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SWAMP Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H372018F3FCED4D5CA700B55009449C80"><enum>2.</enum><header>Relocation of headquarters of Executive agencies</header> <subsection id="HBCA871D25133452A855D68B3B6B80986"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
 <paragraph id="H5C9C782EA8184F56B5AE00CF0B3136FD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Executive agency</header><text>The term <quote>Executive agency</quote>—</text> <subparagraph id="HC2793D0335FE4BC8AEB4DEDC72EEA721"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has the meaning given the term in section 105 of title 5, United States Code; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H344F9E58B0444C958836A295B0BBD4A0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include—</text> <clause id="HCE0123607FCC419B9634332C1CE8E1E4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Executive Office of the President;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD8B3744F64014B8E865370C01FAFD6C7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Department of Defense, including the Defense Intelligence Agency, the National Security Agency, and the National-Geospatial-Intelligence Agency;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H7D81E357498E480A9CAD51A1F9514600"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Department of Energy;</text> </clause><clause id="H2225857A4BED45BB91AE0A1B42015314"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Department of Homeland Security;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H5E4EEE17CB9B438CB4975BA5AA734F70"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the Department of State;</text> </clause><clause id="H5DE5848F796942FC99C7EC5E3B8A9E51"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the Office of the Director of National Intelligence; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H4F3D1957B98F4F9E95DC2915D067B339"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the Central Intelligence Agency.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H4581F046F61E4A9ABA4932D08760CCB8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Headquarters</header><text>The term <quote>headquarters</quote>—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HBE3FECAE095047FB96DB4E8F2F02A333"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means the place or building serving as the managerial and administrative center of an Executive agency; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA65A9044016C484A83ECAF4B3DFF57B1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include an office that the head of an Executive agency may maintain separately from a place or building in the Washington metropolitan area.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H394683F2A533476CAC1331212D8356CD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <quote>State</quote> means each of the 50 States.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9B4C6F43EAA74AC781B9DED1E07560E6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Washington metropolitan area</header><text>The term <quote>Washington metropolitan area</quote> means the geographic area located within the boundaries of the following:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H4E63F1BBA8424B63B04ADB37604F3FBA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The District of Columbia.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A193F4BDB47434681C07B86693479AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Montgomery and Prince George’s Counties in the State of Maryland.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD6376D99B0FF43FBAE91D7320D560538"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Arlington, Fairfax, Loudoun, and Prince William Counties and the City of Alexandria in the Commonwealth of Virginia.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H2A0CBCEFE3CD45C5973CBDCA19E15676"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Repeal of headquarters location requirement</header><text>Section 72 of title 4, United States Code, is repealed.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H1D589086517448E18DB024F5B875803C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition on location of headquarters in Washington metropolitan area</header><text>With respect to a headquarters of an Executive agency that has the headquarters of the Executive agency located in the Washington metropolitan area as of the date of enactment of this Act, no new construction or major renovation may be undertaken, or lease agreement entered into or renewed, for the headquarters after the date of enactment of this Act, except as otherwise expressly provided by law.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HB6E5FA848DCA4553A4BBF992B4FF5C52"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Competitive bidding process for relocation of headquarters</header>
 <paragraph id="HD468ABA617C34AA58DB159761882C9B8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of General Services shall establish a process, in accordance with the requirements described in paragraph (2), through which—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HC7C09B57D4904D4AA34D9A55FF3A7DE9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the head of an Executive agency may submit a request for the Administrator of General Services to issue a solicitation for the relocation of the headquarters of the Executive agency; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H28147FC33F774DD69998D90F7720D1BA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if determined necessary, the Administrator of General Services may issue a solicitation for the relocation of the headquarters of an Executive agency.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C340FD6DFB04691A610182EFCF19CE1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>With respect to any solicitation issued for the relocation of the headquarters of an Executive agency pursuant to paragraph (1), the Administrator of General Services shall—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HBFE5A4D6884B42D1992094840BF1EF28"><enum>(A)</enum><text>allow any State and any political subdivision of a State to submit a bid for the relocation of the headquarters of the Executive agency;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2DCA280265BF49B5B486979150C5703E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide the public with notice and an opportunity to comment on the bid described in subparagraph (A); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BBB1C75149248988778E5A7A6A9AD5F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in consultation with the head of the Executive agency, select a State, or a political subdivision of a State, for the relocation of the headquarters using a competitive bidding procedure that considers—</text>
 <clause id="HF8FA738C49794021B8D373767191EB1B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the extent to which the relocation of the headquarters would impact the economy and workforce development of a State or political subdivision of a State;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA92371EB75204E9E82ECBF8957B14702"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whether a State, or a political subdivision of a State, has expertise in carrying out activities substantially similar to the mission and goals of the Executive agency; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HBDBCBD159BCD412CA7D1B84C66B59408"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the extent to which the relocation of the headquarters to a State, or a political subdivision of a State, would implicate national security interests.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id7828C943BF404DB68C3EC04B4961AEC3"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act may be construed to prohibit a political subdivision of the State of Maryland or the Commonwealth of Virginia that is located outside the Washington metropolitan area from submitting a bid under subsection (d)(2)(A).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD0603F7C55AA480DA70DA4A79E9A7F2E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Offset <enum-in-header>A</enum-in-header>llowed</header><text>The Administrator of General Services may use the proceeds from the sale of any Federal building or land to offset the cost of relocating the headquarters of an Executive agency.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H3F03CBC42ABD46B282466D7A8394F30B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>No additional funds authorized</header>
 <paragraph id="HCB81A4B23B4D4431A509B448B7B47742"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No additional funds are authorized to carry out the requirements of this Act.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H5A4D21C5C9B0481B86BE1E4A0D7968EB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amounts authorized</header><text>The requirements shall be carried out using amounts otherwise authorized.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


