<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H66A744600B3E46439B88EFC21A011455" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5172 IH: To assist Indian tribes in maintaining, expanding, and deploying broadband systems.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5172</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180306">March 6, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="O000171">Mr. O'Halleran</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000588">Mr. Pearce</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To assist Indian tribes in maintaining, expanding, and deploying broadband systems.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H9928F1933C7A4E15A8EF9CC003C8681E" style="OLC">
		<section id="H974CF87A91E34C538E70C55749216C27" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Technical assistance for Indian tribes in applying for financial assistance to maintain, expand, or
			 deploy broadband systems</header>
 <subsection id="HFB2E14E8D41C4C9998773CDF32AD9BEC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture, through the Office of Tribal Relations in the Department of Agriculture, shall, in consultation with the Office of Native Affairs and Policy of the Federal Communications Commission—</text>
 <paragraph id="H59008AD9170F46F2AC17E566707B117B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>create a database of Federal programs and activities under which Indian tribes and tribal organizations, and agencies and instrumentalities of Indian tribes and tribal organizations, may obtain financial assistance for the maintenance, expansion, or deployment of broadband systems;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE1AF6DC000644AEA9C61D02C6B694EA4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide technical assistance to entities described in paragraph (1) in applying for or using the financial assistance; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD7C45FF5309D47DCBCAB91B7DD767BEA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>submit to the Congress annual reports on—</text> <subparagraph id="HE742569A3586484D91F56F0372BF00F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of the entities to which the technical assistance was provided in the fiscal year covered by the report;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F4969AA59FC4DF4839BF02074743C34"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of applications for the financial assistance that the entities submitted in the fiscal year covered by the report; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6DB38EDE969A47999035E129ABAC68B9"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of efforts made to facilitate the efforts of the entities to obtain the financial assistance in the fiscal year covered by the report.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H296A8D9A79FB4F7BB377B42AA4D7117D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Model broadband development plan</header>
 <paragraph id="H068B8A6D22974790B563772D8180E36F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture, through the Office of Tribal Relations in the Department of Agriculture, shall develop and publish in the Federal Register a model broadband development plan using the database created under subsection (a)(1), that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H124B4B31C6DA4F03AA4A53B708607980"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifies overlaps and unique target areas in each programs listed in the database;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93EE05833AF145949425A46C3A9FA9C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identifies options for obtaining the financial assistance referred to in subsection (a)(1), and propose opportunities to enable the entities described in subsection (a)(1) overcome any obstacles in doing so;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1BF7F78994BD4EE294084296E2525A59"><enum>(C)</enum><text>describes the goals of technical assistance provided under subsection (a)(2); and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H956D766073C248C682DF28CAD795C63A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>proposes a course for the provision of the technical assistance that is proven to enhance broadband access on tribal lands.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H85A0066041854911946C407D1F696475"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultations required</header>
 <subparagraph id="H513E88B4D14240BC92FC2532C8C91E5C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), in developing the plan, the Secretary of Agriculture and the Federal Communications Commission shall jointly—</text>
 <clause id="H395205BAAF9B40749E4E9F069943933F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>conduct an in-person consultation with the Indian tribes and tribal members involved, in a forum open to the public;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HE8087E2904A34444AE5C7F60E3E34AD3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>publish in the Federal Register the date of the consultation not later than 14 days before that date;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H225850D50A184BCEBB39071794AE7404"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">within 30 days after the date of the consultation, transcribe or record the consultation, and make the transcription or record available to the public; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8A01032A5E5E4938B18518F22A666E88"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>not later than 30 days before finalizing the plan, make available to the public a document that demonstrates how the consultation affected the development of the plan.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B10AB04B15646FC82FB8AADA53EC292"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Waiver authority</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture and the Federal Communications Commission may jointly waive the requirement of subparagraph (A) with respect to a group of Indian tribes if at least <fraction>5/6</fraction> of the Indian tribes involved agree to the waiver.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1A9DFD5983D142C6A080C7FF24DB50BE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition of Indian tribe</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>Indian tribe</term> has the meaning given the term in section 102(2) of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H07C2ECE4DC0D45E58F284ED2C194CEE7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitations on authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To carry out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Agriculture not more than $500,000 for each fiscal year.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HF356CD31B7BC48F091A7F9DE5A6698FF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Parity for tribal regulatory commissions</header>
 <text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 306(a)(20)(E) of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1926">7 U.S.C. 1926(a)(20)(E)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H01929BDC38E644AAAF718F021E72EAB9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and tribal</quote> after <quote>State</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HA017D4EC979544A4A8B29EFD3839221E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>states</quote> and inserting <quote>States and tribal lands</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H400EBE47724548DEB9CE4D0D31685B57"><enum>3.</enum><header>Substantially underserved trust areas</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 306F of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/936f">7 U.S.C. 936f</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6D4589B8E16846518E00A2874823B7B5" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="H09941D3516264BE0AC9B11087A2110EA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Refinancing loans in substantially underserved trust areas</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, the Secretary or a designee of the Secretary may make or guarantee a loan to refinance a loan made to any person who has applied for, or has outstanding, a loan or loan guarantee from the Rural Utilities Service for a project under an eligible program, to improve or continue the availability of projects that serve communities in substantially underserved trust areas.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </section><section id="H769D7785B5494117A475F86916CA833E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Distance learning and telemedicine grants on Indian reservations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2333(d)(5) of the Food, Agriculture, Conservation, and Trade Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950aaa-2">7 U.S.C. 950aaa–2(d)(5)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>(including on and off an Indian reservation)</quote> after <quote>geographical diversity</quote>.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


