<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H287C92ECB63C448884CAD7DFBBE3A746" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5657 IH: Gladys Ricart Gun Offender Registry Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5657</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180427">April 27, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the registration of violent gun offenders, provide for sufficient notification of
			 their whereabouts, to honor the memory of Gladys Ricart and other gun
			 crime victims, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H214C9211AAC14E678008ED6688318F72" style="OLC">
 <section id="HA709495BD5064B58A169C9BE26059D77" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Gladys Ricart Gun Offender Registry Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H48673D7A1C8344E58FF933D2C053BFFA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text>
 <paragraph id="H5737EBD741DB42AB986D619C0591FA4C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Abused women are 5 times more likely to be killed if their abuser owns a firearm.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HA9EB036D3B4145858C05C892456F0A76"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Since New York City’s and Baltimore’s gun offender registries were put in place in 2006 and 2007 respectively, both cities have seen reductions in murders and violent crimes.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE958D0C8D436412BA19FAFDB6D0ED931"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Domestic violence assaults involving a gun are 12 times more likely to end in death than assaults with other weapons or physical harm.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H700B8746820A429090DA20E8478C95A5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>More than two-thirds of spouse and ex-spouse homicide victims between 1980 and 2008 were killed with firearms.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA63D95873FEC422792940F997423E119"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In 2011, nearly two-thirds of women killed with guns were killed by their intimate partners.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H311166F003EE43189B9DF1D92B2C37B9"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In nearly two thirds (64.5 percent) of cases in which a gun was present in a household shared by a domestic abuser and victim, the abuser had used the firearm against the victim, usually threatening to shoot or kill their intimate partner.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="HFD043B45B3CC416496C70320C6691353"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header>
 <text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H9CF2BC660C3340CD85F8DEFAEFDC6C75"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Gun offender</header><text>The term <term>gun offender</term> means an individual who was convicted of a gun offense.</text>
			</paragraph><paragraph id="H00768EB27DD144AAA6E40A723090498C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Gun offense</header>
 <subparagraph id="H1D4D3657605B4B658FDC23F2FA5B620B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subparagraph (C), the term <term>gun offense</term> means a criminal offense under subparagraph (B), whether under Federal, State, local, Tribal, or military law, that involved a firearm (as such term is defined in section 921 of title 18, United States Code).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H855BC3B0BB444CD7837373D22B85E56B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Offenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A criminal offense under this subparagraph is any one of the following:</text> <clause id="H08126E75CB604C54BABC77CD76B25D80"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Homicide</text>
 </clause><clause id="H299AAABF73674D2688EB5EBD689B1F0D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Manslaughter.</text> </clause><clause id="H0016C29942CF4A70BD7488F3FC8B5868"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Assault.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H0899A6ED22DA4A749A34DA6CCA4DC41B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A misdemeanor crime of domestic violence (as such term is defined in section 921 of title 18, United States Code).</text>
 </clause><clause id="H2E1EF5F138384E1C895776A90B9990B9"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Child abuse.</text> </clause><clause id="HDC96DA70631A4FCD9C6D5B5FEE8819A3"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Kidnapping.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HEB8B5C4646274E47B3E5C43ADF22DA35"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Theft.</text> </clause><clause id="H0E62D77C38D848C2B0D9ACA4792B637B"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Robbery.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1F835877B75C477084292D2EECE3EEF2"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Burglary.</text> </clause><clause id="H1DE35617ADD74D29927CAB5017809B66"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Terrorism or a terrorism-related offense.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H7C9BA8B86EE04C55AB5524308417EFF6"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>Rape.</text> </clause><clause id="H70678377EFF94F2588E47C5FAA6CC200"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>Sexual assault.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAB55A863DC0485D9863C73A026AF18C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The term <term>gun offense</term> does not include—</text> <clause id="H0B53FB56305D475A81E78722C7CAF2B0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an offense under subparagraph (B), during the commission of which the offender possessed, but did not use or threaten to use a firearm;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HFBBE0A9D71364F66AB7482AD09F8F19C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an attempt or a conspiracy to commit an offense under subparagraph (B) with a firearm; or</text> </clause><clause id="HB5C3C6D8407F408C83F1C2C06D664F78"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a foreign conviction.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H329A520F218045D486D3BAE44AE4A266"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Gun offender registry</header><text>The term <term>gun offender registry</term> means a registry of gun offenders and a notification program, maintained by a jurisdiction.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H80077F804D5B420D94D9982910EADAA8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Jurisdiction</header><text>The term <term>jurisdiction</term> means any of the following:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H3E6F0284374348A8BF03DDA21F27D1D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A State.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA14B373DDB5A4673A766744EB524AB3E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The District of Columbia.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08757ABDEC7849EAA77D5CFC6434C024"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Commonwealth of Puerto Rico.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1E0A32B361744ED4A5ADE3BEF26DA0B1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Guam.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDD4625CB3914EAB90AAD38B85F3B549"><enum>(E)</enum><text>American Samoa.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8DCABB67A9FC4670A0E277015337991F"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Northern Mariana Islands.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H291F8401B27D42128D58C237A161DCC8"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The United States Virgin Islands.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF74BFE86B0A2457994CA27921CB744B7"><enum>(H)</enum><text>In accordance with section 21, a federally recognized Indian Tribe.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC35337BD17F24293B49840CB40BFAEBC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Student</header><text>The term <term>student</term> means an individual who is enrolled in or attends an educational institution, including (whether public or private) a secondary school, a trade or professional school, and an institution of higher education.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H251EAFCCFFC945C58B69A6D049142C30"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Employee</header><text>The term <term>employee</term> includes an individual who is self-employed or works for any other entity, whether compensated or not.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8E821E89CB174045BDEB783B0B1E7E10"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Resides</header><text>The term <term>resides</term> means, with respect to an individual, the location of the individual’s home or other place where the individual habitually lives.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC44E11F2EA544E53AB2E7AEF60A63BD8"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Minor</header><text>The term <term>minor</term> means an individual who has not attained the age of 18 years.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="H7409C578A1874DB582E00F9BE3053C5D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Registry requirements for jurisdictions</header> <subsection id="HABE87747792149ADA421BE6CA9CC17A9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Jurisdiction To maintain a registry</header><text>Each jurisdiction shall maintain a jurisdiction-wide gun offender registry in accordance with the requirements of this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HEB823A6C0FA547D3AE9087A7325857E5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidelines and regulations</header><text>The Attorney General shall issue guidelines and regulations to interpret and implement this Act.</text> </subsection></section><section id="HFB23C1C6569B4C0DB48F67D9E44D595F"><enum>5.</enum><header>Gun offender registration requirements</header> <subsection id="H5F2FC5B6D4BD49DBA5E543B0F5302C3E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A gun offender shall register, and keep the registration current, in each jurisdiction where the offender resides, where the offender is an employee, and where the offender is a student. For initial registration purposes only, a gun offender shall also register in the jurisdiction in which convicted if such jurisdiction is different from the jurisdiction of residence.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HAB14CE5DD4274E1C9E6813EDDB020710"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Initial registration</header><text>The gun offender shall initially register—</text> <paragraph id="HDCD69E79EA8C4DFE874931E75AC7A567"><enum>(1)</enum><text>before completing a sentence of imprisonment with respect to the offense giving rise to the registration requirement; or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3B51E32F127048B9B27DCB9A9A25A5B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not later than 5 business days after being sentenced for that offense, if the gun offender is not sentenced to a term of imprisonment.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC30AD1D0965C4393A8FA92627F3D63D2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Keeping the registration current</header><text>A gun offender shall, within 5 business days after each change of name, residence, employment, or student status, appear in person in at least 1 jurisdiction involved pursuant to subsection (a) and inform that jurisdiction of all modifications in the information required for that offender in the gun offender registry. That jurisdiction shall immediately disclose that information to all other jurisdictions in which the offender is required to register.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H7170D3F3EC5649CF9B2C4C3EE4DCC0EC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Gun offenders not required To comply with subsection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements of this section shall not apply to any gun offender who was convicted prior to the date of the enactment of this Act, or to any gun offender who is a minor on the date that the individual is convicted of a gun offense.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H4B3E83E1A05247019BFBE9E8A012F669"><enum>(e)</enum><header>State penalty for failure To comply</header><text>Each jurisdiction, other than a federally recognized Indian Tribe, shall provide a criminal penalty that includes a maximum term of imprisonment that is not longer than 6 months for the failure of a gun offender to comply with the requirements of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H301A499B5770485EBD6FBE3834F54131"><enum>6.</enum><header>Information required in registration</header>
 <subsection id="H4362BD236BEF4AF2BC23A085092BAA26"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Provided by the offender</header><text>The gun offender shall provide the following information to the appropriate official for insertion in the gun offender registry:</text>
 <paragraph id="HAB3006612C244495B884A34100CB5B4A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The name of the gun offender (including any alias used by the individual).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H14244089ECC94492AC72EB67733ECF71"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Social Security number of the gun offender.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7138625B4AE1468C90F3A24FCC4D8A92"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The address of every residence at which the gun offender resides or will reside.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H188517511C19421084E5B874FB572A4D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The name and address of any organization where the gun offender is an employee or will be an employee.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H26FB6D9D78D241D3844334040EB4508F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The name and address of any institution where the gun offender is a student or will be a student.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H2AAC805BFB3B4B75BF942BA0E79E5DFD"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The license plate number and a description of any vehicle owned or used by the gun offender.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H89D636C560CD452388E1A49323939249"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Any other information required by the Attorney General.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC036D4C0A7D74F6D8165AAA1A6ECBFC2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Provided by the jurisdiction</header><text>The jurisdiction in which the gun offender initially registers or updates registry information shall ensure that the following information is included in the registry for that gun offender:</text>
 <paragraph id="HD8669CA12E6E41F9998DA7AF9E9EB4F2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description that accurately depicts the gun offender’s current physical state.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H643A46D5C95F49A78E1C02ABBCB55649"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The text of the provision of law defining the criminal offense for which the gun offender is registered.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD2C245185DF248F88B17677097E07CF8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The criminal history of the gun offender, including the date of all arrests and convictions, the status of parole, probation, or supervised release, registration status, and the existence of any outstanding arrest warrants for the gun offender.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD4D592A855A34DACB559212867BCC2DB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A current photograph of the gun offender.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H59383B07F9B94C22ACD7F3E07275D3AD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A set of fingerprints and palm prints of the gun offender.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8139215F86374C60A4DC2D6A81886E48"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A DNA sample of the gun offender.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H93DF0131718E477FB3757719B5A9B26B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A photocopy of a valid driver’s license or identification card issued to the gun offender by a jurisdiction.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H98B932C8FBB3424CA2AC2D8959218D64"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Any other information required by the Attorney General.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H01939E5C0C664FE4BC8A83729096EB38"><enum>7.</enum><header>Duration of registration requirement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A gun offender shall keep the registration updated and current for the full registration period (excluding any time the gun offender is in custody or civilly committed). The full registration period is—</text>
 <paragraph id="HDF903C5D991B47E99561626B57417ED1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>3 years; or</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H633F9905EE274DDDB5A952B54EB99D7A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if the offender’s supervised release, probation or parole is longer than 3 years, the offender will remain on the registry through duration of their supervision status.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HCA7E2DB00D474D03A5645CF619DB1594"><enum>8.</enum><header>Inveterate in-person verification</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A gun offender shall appear in person at an appropriate registration site within a jurisdiction the offender is registered to allow the jurisdiction to take a current photograph, and verify the information in each registry in which that offender is required to be registered not less frequently than one time each year.</text>
		</section><section id="HC1F5ADFFE1074F21B1E32F0839E57670"><enum>9.</enum><header>Duty to inform gun offenders of registration requirements and to register</header>
 <subsection id="H308F656E2121440589618A2F37012C6C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An appropriate official shall, soon before release of the gun offender from custody, or, if the gun offender is not in custody, immediately after the sentencing of gun offender, for the offense giving rise to the duty to register—</text>
 <paragraph id="HBCC5169444F14600A053B6C32519138D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>inform the gun offender of the duties of a gun offender under this Act and explain those duties; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCC57F43103C2439D8DC95B40DE2B0B6B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>require the gun offender to read and sign a form stating that the duty to register has been explained and that the gun offender understands the registration requirement.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7940D6155D2D48EF86631324CDD65FCA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notification of certain gun offenders</header><text>The Attorney General shall prescribe rules for the notification of offenders who cannot be registered in accordance with subsection (a).</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H06D2B504AF9F49349AEE0C3EEC97FB14"><enum>10.</enum><header>National gun offender registry</header>
 <subsection id="H9D2C69860B8948598F4265624FCB627C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General shall maintain a database for each gun offender and any other person required to register in a jurisdiction’s gun offender registry. The database shall be known as the <quote>Gun Offender Registry</quote>.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HEDD35E69C9B24A829B81BB9605BA9E46"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The Attorney General may—</text> <paragraph id="H509A1F0F19BA4460AB3D60B40FE18569"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish a new office to administer the program required by this Act; or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5C55AFA733544885A4A11117E89FB7DA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reassign current Department of Justice employees to permanently administer the requirements within this Act under the purview of an already existing division at the Department of Justice.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8F479F3154AF4E8F95B7E14B54236BBD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Electronic forwarding</header><text>The Attorney General shall ensure that all updated findings about a gun offender are immediately transmitted by electronic forwarding to all relevant jurisdictions.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HE116A96023A848D39CE0EB839B35D9B1"><enum>11.</enum><header>Gun offender public website</header>
 <subsection id="H5C94C75C6FA84152983D64665B35D62F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (b), the Attorney General shall establish and maintain a public website which shall include pertinent information, as determined by the Attorney General, for each gun offender required to register under this Act. The website shall provide a search function for the public to obtain information for each gun offender by a single query for any given zip code or geographical radius set by the user in a form and with such limitations as may be established by the Attorney General and shall have such other field search capabilities as the Attorney General may provide.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H31C6D21E22FD4C25942E81673075EB2A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Mandatory exemptions</header><text>The Attorney General shall exempt from disclosure—</text> <paragraph id="HE52C9D7393AE47DC99B1AAF341517583"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the identity of any victim of a gun offense;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4A8C2C47A71441D3863F729493F9AE80"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Social Security number of the gun offender;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9540829818A246A8ABBCAB3DC82472E9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any reference to arrests of the gun offender that did not result in conviction;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1C22E14210544CE8A2712A1759DDA01C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any information about a gun offender’s prior criminal history other than a specified violent crime that prompted the offender’s duty to register in accordance with this Act;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5FA14AFE8B5542C49519C749EC37824E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the name of an employer of the gun offender;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H7F02BEA9416C4454A6B423877AA8314B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the name of an educational institution where the gun offender is a student; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6D56AA5C3A884B63B0F8CD13E79143FE"><enum>(7)</enum><text>any other information exempted from disclosure by the Attorney General.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0F355C38A45F41F0B5A266C8470DC20A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Removal of information</header><text>The Attorney General shall ensure that at the conclusion of the period described in section 7 during which a gun offender is required to register, no information related to the gun offender, including the gun offender’s identity, is accessible on the website established under this section.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H0F873A2D35AA448FB4DFE53A0ACB2744"><enum>12.</enum><header>Public access to gun offender information through the internet</header>
 <subsection id="HC6A1DFEDCC78488FB8F70D20B7E8D10B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in this section, each jurisdiction shall make available on the internet, in a form that is readily accessible to all jurisdictions and to the public, all information about each gun offender in the registry. The jurisdiction shall maintain the internet site in a manner that will provide a search function for the public to obtain relevant information for each gun offender by a single query for any given zip code or geographic radius set by the user. The jurisdiction shall also include in the design of its internet site all field search capabilities needed for full participation in the website described in section 11, and shall participate in that website as provided by the Attorney General.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H88C2726F7AAE4A559F317168A70F30BE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Mandatory exemptions</header><text>A jurisdiction shall exempt from disclosure—</text> <paragraph id="H03702EFE0D104FD2A927CDA5C14C4151"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the identity of any victim of a gun offense;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB71F0B166404417AA63EBCBA0D7F5BA7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Social Security number of the gun offender;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H1B6E6BC40D204FDC81C7D458B5C03070"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any reference to arrests of the gun offender that did not result in conviction;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1D88937AF34E4F1AB98492DC72F7F7C7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any information about a gun offender’s prior criminal history other than a specified violent crime that prompted the offender’s duty to register in accordance with this Act;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF78B8B9F666946C8B086AFC256DE0441"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the name of an employer of the gun offender;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE55BDA2B37F745C8A8794D600A23B12E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the name of an educational institution where the gun offender is a student; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE2365115E4A448C5ADAD233F8828122E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>any other information exempted from disclosure by the Attorney General.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H99BDE2CA705A4A26B0329FE33BB3E5B2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Links</header><text>The site shall include, to the extent practicable, links to gun safety and education resources.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD06754F5186C4D5FBA05E42257D46B60"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Correction of errors</header><text>The site shall include instructions on how to seek correction of information that an individual contends is erroneous.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H8F44AAEB7D0849219193B6ABE59133EB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Warning</header><text>The site shall include a warning that information on the site should not be used to unlawfully injure, harass, or commit a crime against any individual named in the registry or residing or working at any reported address. The warning shall note that any such action could result in civil or criminal penalties.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H5A78D55C08FC4DB1943EB165DF78D686"><enum>13.</enum><header>Period for implementation by jurisdictions</header>
 <subsection id="HDECA787764E74A899B145BF860EBD7BD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text>Each jurisdiction shall implement this Act before the date that is 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H2B474713D8FD4B46A99B7667780CF381"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Extensions</header><text>The Attorney General may authorize up to two 1-year extensions of the deadline under subsection (a).</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HB1CCCC6C60284A23BAEE8DAD73CA0FAE"><enum>14.</enum><header>Failure of jurisdiction to comply</header>
 <subsection id="H0A2639A73A484E0080DCC4A6CF0F47BD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For any fiscal year which begins after the deadline under section 15, a jurisdiction that fails, as determined by the Attorney General, to substantially implement this Act shall not receive 10 percent of the funds under the Edward Byrne Memorial Justice Assistance Grant Program under subpart I of part E of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10151">34 U.S.C. 10151</external-xref> et seq.) that would otherwise be allocated for that fiscal year to the jurisdiction.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HEB384022B2F7483C96A2FA38A99B2F48"><enum>(b)</enum><header>State constitutionality</header>
 <paragraph id="H76C1D5AAAD374F8085F37B2118CB4451"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>When evaluating whether a jurisdiction has adequately implemented this Act, the Attorney General shall examine whether the jurisdiction is incapable of implementing this Act because of a displayed inability to implement certain provisions that would place the jurisdiction in violation of its constitution, as determined by a ruling of the jurisdiction’s highest court.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0E88DEA4341F494E968AAF2D5FBE22FD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Efforts</header><text>If the circumstances under paragraph (1) appear, the Attorney General and the jurisdiction shall demonstrate faithful efforts to fulfill considerable implementation of this Act and to reconcile any incompatibilities between this Act and the jurisdiction’s constitution. In considering whether acceptance of the requirements of this Act may violate the jurisdiction’s constitution or an exposition by the jurisdiction’s highest court, the Attorney General shall consult with the chief executive and chief legal officer of the jurisdiction concerning the jurisdiction’s exposition of the jurisdiction’s constitution.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4FE3F241DEFE4F84BE4B4FAF4A18D3B4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Alternative procedures</header><text>If the jurisdiction is unable to substantially implement this Act because of a limitation imposed by the jurisdiction’s constitution, the Attorney General may determine that the jurisdiction is in compliance with this Act if the jurisdiction has made, or is in the process of implementing reasonable alternative procedures or accommodations, which are consistent with the purposes of this Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4792CA047B9948C0AE7E8A64CC923157"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Funding reduction</header><text>If a jurisdiction does not comply with paragraph (3), then the jurisdiction shall be subject to a funding reduction as specified in subsection (a).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2B49814C8E6C4220A8D4628722E590CF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reallocation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts not allocated under a program referred to in this section to a jurisdiction for failure to substantially implement this Act shall be reallocated under that program to jurisdictions that have not failed to substantially implement this Act or may be reallocated to a jurisdiction from which they were withheld to be used solely for the purpose of implementing this Act. Under these circumstances, the process for selecting jurisdiction that will receive re-allocated funding will be at the discretion of the Attorney General.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HCB771562337943649EDFF4EC8378D353"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>The provisions of this Act that are cast as directions to jurisdictions or their officials constitute, in relation to States, only conditions required to avoid the reduction of Federal funding under this section.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H7961CC09D1A2440D817A9656BFC04241"><enum>15.</enum><header>Gun Offender Registry Act; failure to register</header>
 <subsection id="H7A124FBA276A4FCF96995772A98273D7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Whoever—</text> <paragraph id="H0AA69ADE259D4E7ABFC5AB48736572EA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is required to register under this Act;</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HE92C3AD9771F4E3C9D48A8865DEF2FFC"><enum>(2)</enum>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HBC54139317684E7BA4ECAD40E5B7B764"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a gun offender by reason of a conviction under Federal law (including the Uniform Code of Military Justice), the law of the District of Columbia, Indian Tribal law, or the law of any territory or possession of the United States; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B23AD41B7FC48ED9661EFB93A7AAB79" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>travels in interstate or foreign commerce, or enters or leaves, or resides in, Indian country; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H73CED1C18B054478B1E7B08FCA0F8CA6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>knowingly fails to register or update a registration as required under this Act,</text>
 </paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">shall be fined under title 18, United States Code, or imprisoned not more than 6 months, or both.</continuation-text></subsection><subsection id="HFA6B2F6B649E46E5B6ABE7AEC2419029"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Affirmative defense</header><text>In a prosecution for a violation under subsection (a), it is an affirmative defense that—</text> <paragraph id="H0BFE70B3E726487D8802B6E63933E3B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>uncontrollable conditions prevented the individual from adhering to this Act;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC5A2793C4FB5477D8F2E00549FF24ECA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the individual did not cause the creation of such circumstances to disregard the requirement to comply; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H89CAA9F3B3EF47D9852FA918782095CB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the individual complied as soon as such circumstances ceased to exist.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H8438AC3BFADA4D3293E87AA53E7FDB76"><enum>16.</enum><header>Actions to be taken when gun offender fails to comply</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">An appropriate official shall inform the Attorney General and other accountable law enforcement agencies of any noncompliance by a gun offender to comply with the requirements of a registry. The appropriate official, the Attorney General, and each such law enforcement agency shall take any appropriate action to ensure compliance.</text>
 </section><section id="HF1927117AAD4473E9BF3D244B3708FE3"><enum>17.</enum><header>Federal assistance with respect to violations of registration requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General shall use the resources of Federal law enforcement, including the United States Marshals Service, to assist jurisdictions in locating and apprehending gun offenders who violate gun offender registration requirements.</text>
		</section><section id="H9A676ECB59084289B3F7B08609099158"><enum>18.</enum><header>Federal assistance in identification and location of gun offenders relocated as a result of a major
 disaster</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General shall provide assistance to jurisdictions in the identification and location of a gun offender relocated as a result of a natural disaster or other major disaster.</text>
		</section><section id="HA319922280DF4B43AD2834D06885978C"><enum>19.</enum><header>Election by Indian Tribes</header>
			<subsection id="H16546B22A56747A39C4AAC48FA889148"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Election</header>
 <paragraph id="HA7C01D3A75DE4BE5BC2BD1A21BB727B8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A federally recognized Indian Tribe may, by resolution from their local governmental body—</text> <subparagraph id="H64414849DE8B4BBE80298EBEB17EBDFC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>opt to carry out this Act as a jurisdiction subject to its provisions; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HADDF5B1F24F641DA9BAFEC582664AA9D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>elect to delegate its functions under this Act to another jurisdiction or jurisdictions within which the territory of the Tribe is located and to provide access to its territory and such other cooperation and assistance as may be needed to enable such other jurisdiction or jurisdictions to carry out and enforce the requirements of this Act.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A00F9EF2DB348B29DFFDD4CE8D3407A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Imputed election in certain cases</header><text>A Tribe shall be treated as if it had made the election described in paragraph (1)(B) if—</text> <subparagraph id="H8ABDC5485AB64F0F8903CA5CDDBD45EA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>it is a Tribe subject to the law enforcement jurisdiction of a State under section 1162 of title 18, United States Code;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA152B203818D42359959A90347B7536E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Tribe does not make an election under paragraph (1) within 1 year of the date of the enactment of this Act or rescinds an election under paragraph (1)(A); or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8840FDFFC34477FB962E64623296724"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Attorney General determines that the Tribe has not substantially implemented the requirements of this Act and is not likely to become capable of doing so within a reasonable amount of time.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEB29DF1688824376932CC1CF910435A6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Cooperation between Tribal authorities and other jurisdictions</header>
 <paragraph id="H43178337F4E3418AA66CF1C37E88DAB6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Nonduplication</header><text>A Tribe subject to this Act is not required to duplicate functions under this Act which are fully carried out by another jurisdiction or jurisdictions within which the territory of the Tribe is located.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H543887FBEDDE490CBAB7E91D97979BCC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cooperative agreements</header><text>A Tribe and another jurisdiction within close proximity to the Tribe, may enter into a cooperative agreement to carry out the functions in this Act.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE63AC363CFC24784A0272295A1D11042"><enum>20.</enum><header>Registration of gun offenders entering the United States</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary of State and the Secretary of Homeland Security, shall establish and maintain a system for informing the relevant jurisdictions about persons entering the United States who are required to register under this Act. The Secretary of State and the Secretary of Homeland Security shall provide such information and carry out such functions as the Attorney General may direct in the operation of the system.</text>
 </section><section id="H7F955F9EF96B4B1689D4AA9D4AE5921B"><enum>21.</enum><header>Annual report on enforcement of registration requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than July 1 of each year, the Attorney General shall submit a report to Congress, which shall include—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE516EB743D994577A7053D00EB8B757C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the use, by the Department of Justice, of the United States Marshals Service to assist jurisdictions in locating and apprehending gun offenders who fail to comply with gun offender registration requirements, as authorized by this Act;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD7DC2E31D7FD459889AD2B347F391FF3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a detailed explanation of each jurisdiction’s compliance with this Act;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H252099707BC845E794714B4951B09C8B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a detailed description of the efforts of the Department of Justice to ensure compliance with the requirements under this Act, including information related to any jurisdiction that was subject to a funding reduction under section 16, and the basis for any decision to reduce funding or not to reduce funding under such section; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H690161C6AA084784BE8FDC2A54AE81AF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>disclosure of any extensions of any applicable deadline to comply with this Act, and the reasons for the denial or grant of such an extension.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HBAE8A090D664468F9C6DE5183822D9D0"><enum>22.</enum><header>Immunity for good faith conduct</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Federal Government, jurisdictions, political subdivisions of jurisdictions, and their agencies, officers, employees, and agents shall be immune from liability for good faith conduct under this Act.</text>
		</section><section id="H9133CB0CF8EE453FB6F9371FB312690E"><enum>23.</enum><header>Study of the effectiveness of firearm offender registry to reduce the occurrence of repeat offenses</header>
 <subsection id="HE01567F8FDC14FF8905E37D19B9CC5D6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Attorney General shall conduct a study to evaluate the effectiveness of monitoring and disclosing the history of gun offenders to reduce the occurrence of repeat offenses by such gun offenders, through conditions imposed as part of supervised release or probation conditions. The study shall evaluate—</text>
 <paragraph id="H57A3D8BF339E4AB88DABE8A2FDA35386"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the effectiveness of methods used for recording, monitoring and disclosing the location and criminal history of gun offenders;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB37CA1D30FB54059946BB65C5D858C21"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the ability of law enforcement agencies and courts to employ data in prosecutorial and law enforcement efforts; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC0184C8F4B8D47B2864BF9A0BE7ED546"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the efficacy of any other restrictions that may reduce the occurrence of repeat offenses by gun offenders.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H38710DE0E34F4C1199DAE233BD6E8599"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall report to the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate the results of the study under this section.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H3940D63ED2E14E75AC53F13D122156E8"><enum>24.</enum><header>Grant program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General shall establish a grant program, with such criteria as the Attorney General may determine, to provide funds to jurisdictions seeking to comply with this Act.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


