<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HAB27BB3D52484A2480E3FEC6C3FF3B98" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5094 IH: Enhancing Suspicious Activity Reporting Initiative Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5094</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180226">February 26, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000210">Mr. King of New York</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000386">Mr. Katko</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Homeland Security to improve suspicious activity reporting to prevent
			 acts of terrorism, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H8828B7FC47594847AD31F1020581B2CE" style="OLC">
 <section id="H35A09FC601894991A85E38AA5393080B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Enhancing Suspicious Activity Reporting Initiative Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H9163A411C5DC451290AA8B08E6CFE3FE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Enhancing Department of Homeland Security suspicious activity reporting operations</header> <subsection id="HA507C645892D47F599518B28C4E3FC41"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Strategy required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security, in consultation with other appropriate Federal officials, shall develop a strategy to improve the operations and activities of the Department of Homeland Security related to training, outreach, and information sharing for suspicious activity reporting to prevent acts of terrorism.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HAF2EF1C12C1E49B491C46D2562837991"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of strategy</header><text>The strategy required under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text> <paragraph id="H8D5185B5B73843C282886C29B7D9E73F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description and examples of the types of information that would meet the definition of critical information for the purpose of suspicious activity reporting as well as information, including information associated with racial, religious or national origin, that would not meet the definition of critical information.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H40C0ACF0EDD94D75A9BE8D503CAC72BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Training for appropriate personnel of State and major urban area fusion centers, emergency response providers, and, as appropriate, the private sector on—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H6012A23F47994F00954DA10877148BC1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>methods for identifying, analyzing, and disseminating critical information, including the indicators of terrorism;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64B8826603354A4C9BAF0A98D6C17E82"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">methods to protect privacy and civil liberties, including preventing racial, religious, or national origin discrimination; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17B93A8F686E4156AC07E3B71E91C0F2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">response protocols for submitting suspicious activity reports.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H58BCE40EF78E451AB4637B1FF857029F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Methods to improve outreach to appropriate State and major urban area fusion centers, emergency response providers, and the private sector related to suspicious activity reporting to prevent acts of terrorism.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB59540476213429BB26CFB6647835A58"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A plan to ensure that critical information is shared in a timely manner with State and major urban area fusion centers, emergency response providers, and the private sector, as appropriate, including nationwide trend analysis and other information related to terrorist threats.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC0CCFD89182B481A88E1A9E66D7FA8E1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Methods to measure the effectiveness of the activities conducted under the strategy with respect to improving the operations and activities of the Department related to training, outreach, and information sharing to prevent acts of terrorism that have been validated through peer-reviewed empirical studies to the extent practicable.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB2671424F67346138BBD36E76922147D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Working group recommendations</header><text>In developing the strategy required under subsection (a) the Secretary shall take into consideration the recommendations of the working group established under section 3.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF9AA6183DE274DAF92F477F3F9CC9AA6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Congressional notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less than 30 days before the release of the strategy required pursuant to subsection (a), the Secretary shall provide to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a notification of the release of the strategy and a copy of the strategy. Such notification shall include the recommendations provided by the working group established under section 3 and how such recommendations were incorporated into the strategy.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H691478A872164321A2B86943DB885AA0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Suspicious activity reporting working group</header>
			<subsection id="HCE9F7E13084D466C8E4615CD168F6DFD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header>
 <paragraph id="H39B7FD4C041940E3B5B3024451D42EC8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall establish a working group on suspicious activity reporting.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H07E19ED742F84702809AF10E8C5E3429"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Department liaisons</header><text>The Secretary shall appoint as liaisons to the working group—</text> <subparagraph id="H0412A203578E4F1DB7944C37F321E48A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Chief Privacy Officer of the Department of Homeland Security;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A1D8AF6C3D44EF2A88D2E2DABB1EA72"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Officer for Civil Rights and Civil Liberties of the Department; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61A5DC1B47BE4A48B3F66DD63E764FE9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>such other officials of the Department as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9FFB0D7012DD4D998270316C7CFCA03E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The working group established under subsection (a) shall carry out the following responsibilities:</text> <paragraph id="H8063D1F1781846D6AECB44408970C8E3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Provide advice to the Secretary regarding improvements to the operations and activities related to suspicious activity reporting to prevent acts of terrorism.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0081924F9FDC44CAA124FA0DF29F685A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the request of the Secretary, for purposes of section 2(c), develop recommendations to improve suspicious activity reporting to prevent acts of terrorism with respect to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H2278128026AF46608CCC615B402E5B90"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">outreach to relevant stakeholders;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2F27F5FCC2054A39A1F273B24417381A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information sharing;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BF2105320A445279368292F0C2F0E19"><enum>(C)</enum><text>protecting personally identifiable information;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C3B7C3421B245039AD0F26FA42C0896"><enum>(D)</enum><text>protecting the privacy, civil rights, and civil liberties of individuals who report suspicious activity and individuals who are the subjects of such reports;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE989FA23FE554AF4BDD26EFE6D74F232"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">preventing racial, religious, or national origin discrimination;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA6C2F2E05584480AF84879922F5BB38"><enum>(F)</enum><text>training for emergency response providers and the private sector; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97F1029374CF43EFBDB18C590833D29C"><enum>(G)</enum><text>other matters, as determined by the Secretary.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H826374DA74A84F23B3F1A428D841C58D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Working group membership</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall seek the voluntary participation of not more than 20 individuals representing at least 12 diverse regions of the United States to serve as members of the working group. Members of the working group shall serve without pay. The Secretary shall seek to ensure that the working group includes members who are representatives from each of the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HC6B902666B484BE096D4C4BBA6F10694"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">State and major urban area fusion centers.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HBFD28A9E512C4B888245859D27CCB220"><enum>(2)</enum><text>State, local, tribal and territorial law enforcement agencies.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAE6DD9999FB34062B2398198A9D33F14"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Firefighters.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H024A534665B74EC99F429D04B860B87E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Emergency medical services.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H06EA03F6C2454BEC8209BB29D95CA4E3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Private sector security professionals.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H14E33BA2568F41C1A68C7A0F0D68DC9A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Nongovernmental privacy and civil liberty organizations.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA670A08FEABC406FA13B2E32A443DC38"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Any other group the Secretary determines appropriate.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2CF7C1D5978B4445AF0FCD0C92FB94A0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Congressional briefing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon request, the Secretary shall provide to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a briefing on the operations and activities of the Department of Homeland Security related to training, outreach, and information sharing for suspicious activity reporting to prevent acts of terrorism, including copies of materials developed under this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HB22B33E6E21440D694508886D8EE33D2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The working group under this section shall terminate on the date that is two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, except that the Secretary may extend such working group if the Secretary determines necessary.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF09D4793629249AEAE463D93CC413615"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Nonapplicability of FACA</header><text>The Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.) shall not apply to the working group established under this section.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


