<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H6F270E1E408A49E58BE573897F98A183" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5865 IH: Addiction Prevention and Responsible Opioid Practices Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5865</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180517">May 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish programs related to prevention of prescription opioid misuse, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H3C9A68BCCA1D43D99D72C8B66F38D967" style="OLC">
 <section id="H9ACE17902FFB4F3A99925AAD146BF26C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Addiction Prevention and Responsible Opioid Practices Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H9DCF7AB516B7466F9502F067AF9FE618"><enum>2.</enum><header>Federal licensure of pharmaceutical representatives who promote certain opioids</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subchapter E of chapter V of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360bbb">21 U.S.C. 360bbb</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3954237D431A443582E3F11C375351E4" style="OLC">
				<section id="H489CEF24D54648F896DE622AE24D9063"><enum>569D.</enum><header>Federal licensure of pharmaceutical representatives who promote certain opioids</header>
 <subsection id="H4B1FFF30EB814B7DAB1366F57D769457"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Attorney General, shall establish a licensure program for pharmaceutical representatives described in subsection (b).</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="H253C862239294E56B746298C5335E060"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Licensure program</header>
 <paragraph id="HE63530A4BF364FFDB645104C07EAB59B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>Beginning on January 1, 2020, no individual described in paragraph (2) may engage in the marketing or promoting of opioid drugs unless such individual is licensed under this section.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H86D55DCED44145379846D8CA14BFFF85"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Individuals required to obtain licensure</header><text>An individual required to obtain a license under this section is any individual who, on behalf of a drug manufacturer, engaged, on more than 15 days in a calendar year, in the marketing or promotion to health care professionals, including educational or sales communications, meetings or paid events, and the provision of goods, gifts, and samples, of any opioid drug (other than methadone) that is listed in schedule II of section 202(c) of the Controlled Substances Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H8C889E2AF45949BCAEF0D5C03E7C0937"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Licensure period</header><text>Each license issued under this section shall be valid for 3 years, and may be renewed for additional 3-year periods.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H73CEE7A2AFB941A99C43261CF0ED3963"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>An individual required to obtain a license under this section shall—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H09DA0240B20D446E845D0653582C7273"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submit to the Secretary, at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may require—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HB31752A4C4394AD9A648B200737A76E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such information as the Secretary may require; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE0C1E4860D394180AA84B38A9494BD5D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a registration fee in the amount of $3,000;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H1A9435DD74BD420F847D75D2E3C75BA1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>certify that such individual has completed training on ethics, pharmaceutical marketing regulations, the <quote>CDC Guidelines for Prescribing Opioids for Chronic Pain</quote>, published by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in 2016 (or any successor document) or the <quote>FDA Blueprint for Prescriber Education for Extended-Release and Long-Acting Opioid Analgesics</quote>, and applicable Federal laws pertaining to drug marketing, labeling, and clinical trials, as the Secretary may require;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H18AF53A2E3B746E1A8DE111173ED982F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>certify that such individual will not engage in any illegal, fraudulent, misleading, or other deceptive marketing of schedule II opioid drugs; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H859871383D0F4FD4B6469824E7A6FEF6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>file with the Secretary annual reports disclosing the names of providers visited and any drug samples or gifts such individual gives any such provider.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HCFD1EF2D34474AA6A0A88BE5C927B74D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Manufacturer reporting requirements</header><text>The manufacturer who employs or contracts with any individual required to obtain a license under this section shall include in reports required under section 1128G of the Social Security Act the name of each such licensed individual that provides payments or other transfers of value required to be reported under such section 1128G that relates to an opioid drug that is listed in schedule II of the Controlled Substances Act.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="H3EAFF5F9027E4BF29E6B90C353F58166"><enum>3.</enum><header>Withdrawal of approval of certain opioids</header>
 <subsection id="H826DC56BC07449CEA1D2678A93752C53"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, any ultra-high-dose opioid shall be considered a drug that presents an imminent hazard to the public health within the meaning of section 505(e) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(e)</external-xref>), and the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall suspend the approval of such drug, in accordance with such section 505(e).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HBD5EA1A4555B433399F95B2A0BFC6B37"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>ultra-high-dose opioid</term> means an opioid drug for which the daily dosage provided for in the approved label exceeds the morphine milligram equivalents per day outlined in the report entitled <quote>CDC Guidelines for Prescribing Opioids for Chronic Pain</quote>, published by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in 2016 (or any successor document).</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H84A591D29DFB41AEB419AB1F244C0918"><enum>4.</enum><header>Expanding availability of information in the ARCOS database</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 307(d) of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/827">21 U.S.C. 827(d)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF234E2E6DFFC4249BD6F0C1A0CC1D811" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H8CC7B67BA3384F708AEDADDE0D86DF81" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Attorney General shall make available to the medical licensing board and board of pharmacy for each State the information in the Automation of Reports and Consolidated Orders System, or any subsequent automated system developed by the Attorney General to monitor the sale, delivery, and disposal of controlled substances within such State.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </section><section id="H57F9D06FD9C942F68C6EA07E57276C33"><enum>5.</enum><header>Continuing medical education and prescription drug monitoring program registration for prescribers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 303 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/823">21 U.S.C. 823</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDE837CEE07AC4542AB863C0FB6F0137B" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="HBC9213577E1F425480BCCD671C6BA9AF"><enum>(k)</enum>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H77B2705BF6A74C5B8FF2A319AADD7CB6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Attorney General shall not register, or renew the registration of, a practitioner under subsection (f) who is licensed under State law to prescribe controlled substances in schedule II, III, or IV, unless the practitioner submits to the Attorney General, for each such registration or renewal request, a written certification that—</text>
						<subparagraph id="HA7C41BF2BB904A98BF45FCEC256AF480" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum>
 <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC0C3365B814E4A1EA066A573E34AED3D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the practitioner has, during the 1-year period preceding the registration or renewal request, completed a training program described in paragraph (2); or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8C10542CD3E74CB5A5A8FA6B349704EB" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the practitioner, during the applicable registration period, will not prescribe such controlled substances in amounts in excess of a 72-hour supply (for which no refill is available); and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2F1037E22E1407B917F49498602FB2C" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the practitioner has registered with the prescription drug monitoring program of the State in which the practitioner practices, if the State has such program.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HACC30BDB14424DE5A1E4F7C81458B055" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A training program described in this paragraph is a training program that—</text> <subparagraph id="HD73D914A5E28480C93955ABD584C4C53"><enum>(A)</enum><text>follows the best practices for pain management, as described in the <quote>Guideline for Prescribing Opioids for Chronic Pain</quote> as published by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in 2016, or any successor thereto, or the <quote>FDA Blueprint for Prescriber Education for Extended-Release and Long-Acting Opioid Analgesics</quote> as published by the Food and Drug Administration in 2017, or any successor thereto;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5AAABD564BFD44E48F893A34C80AA1EA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes information on—</text> <clause id="HA844CEF5F8D04483885A599FA4718B65"><enum>(i)</enum><text>recommending non-opioid and non-pharmacological therapy;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HAFA9A635F5A24370979BDEDE135459B4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>establishing treatment goals and evaluating patient risks;</text> </clause><clause id="H45479C8A4C08430AAD077546CFABCFDA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>prescribing the lowest dose and fewest number of pills considered effective;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HDF736B1E834648ADAEECE69A7B90F060"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>addictive and overdose risks of opioids;</text> </clause><clause id="H473481ADDAC945548D38465A6F65FB58"><enum>(v)</enum><text>diagnosing and managing substance use disorders, including linking patients to evidence-based treatment;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H59F4E83CBB594FEF9D89D608906F6058"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>identifying narcotics-seeking behaviors; and</text> </clause><clause id="HE49B06CF7725451D8F1A93D739F511B5"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>using prescription drug monitoring programs; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAC64AA410F2B4F4FB380456A4046107E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is approved by the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section><section id="H77F46BCC52CF4ED29F6AAF508CF451B3"><enum>6.</enum><header>Report on prescriber education courses for medical and dental students</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Each school of medicine, school of osteopathic medicine, and school of dentistry participating in a program under title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070a">20 U.S.C. 1070a</external-xref> et seq.), as a condition for such participation, shall submit an annual report to the Secretary of Education and the Secretary of Health and Human Services on any prescriber education courses focused specifically on pain management and responsible opioid prescribing practices that such school requires students to take, and whether such courses are consistent with the most recently published version of the <quote>Guideline for Prescribing Opioids for Chronic Pain</quote> of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention or the <quote>FDA Blueprint for Prescriber Education for Extended-Release and Long-Acting Opioid Analgesics</quote>, as published by the Food and Drug Administration in 2017. The Secretary of Education and the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall compile the reports submitted by such schools and submit an annual summary of such reports to Congress.</text>
		</section><section id="H7630C96C88BA481CBC4FD05C4D388B14"><enum>7.</enum><header>Requirements under Prescription Drug Monitoring Programs</header>
 <subsection id="HE0638E30DA974EA8ADED16D730FE29A1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, each State that receives funding under any of the programs described in subsection (c) shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="HFFCC558C2DD84BA3BA7756D38E0A497A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>require practitioners, or their designees, in the State to consult the database of the prescription drug monitoring program before writing prescriptions for controlled substances (as such term is defined in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>)) in schedule II, III, or IV under section 202 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/812">21 U.S.C. 812</external-xref>);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3EB3F5537C5C4FF5AB8FAF89C36B3BC4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>require dispensers of controlled substances in schedule II, III, or IV, or their designees, to input data into the database of the prescription drug monitoring program within 24 hours of filling a qualifying prescription, as required by the Attorney General and the Secretary of Health and Human Services, including patient identifier information, the national drug code of the dispensed drug, date of dispensing the drug, quantity and dosage of the drug dispensed, form of payment, Drug Enforcement Administration registration number of the practitioner, Drug Enforcement Administration registration number of the dispenser;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H42D374AD845B452A84A3A094B11B91D5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>allow practitioners and dispensers to designate other appropriate individuals to act as agents of such practitioners and dispensers for purposes of obtaining and inputing data from the database for purposes of complying with paragraphs (1) and (2), as applicable;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2A463F4098494E59AC456B2CF29ED70A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide informational materials for practitioners and dispensers to identify and refer patients with possible substance use disorders to professional treatment specialists;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H72B60A692941415F872E48F796A70B78"><enum>(5)</enum><text>establish formal data sharing agreements to foster electronic connectivity with the prescription drug monitoring programs of each State (if such State has such a program) with which the State shares a border, to facilitate the exchange of information through an established technology architecture that ensures common data standards, privacy protection, and secure and streamlined information sharing;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H33DC7096985F4EED9F68D2E0F231DFCD"><enum>(6)</enum><text>notwithstanding section 399O(f)(1)(B) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/280g-3">42 U.S.C. 280g–3(f)(1)(B)</external-xref>), authorize direct access to the State's database of the prescription drug monitoring program to all State law enforcement agencies, State boards responsible for the licensure, regulation, or discipline of practitioners, pharmacists, or other persons authorized to prescribe, administer, or dispense controlled substances; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA934D08A4CBA4625866CD516393904A1"><enum>(7)</enum><text>in order to enhance accountability in prescribing and dispensing patterns, not fewer than 4 times per year, proactively provide informational reports on aggregate trends and individual outliers, based on information available through the State prescription drug monitoring program to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H93A057110FDB4CA8959A293A04470D18"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the State entities and persons described in paragraph (6); and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59C4C9CDE1484E8DA54927498FB02AD4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Medicaid agency and the department of public health of the State.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD3B9030037EF4AA2819E3F3C836879AD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transparency in Prescribing Practices and Intervention for High Prescribers</header>
 <paragraph id="HE2763F888C6C4A1986EFF8CC83AAF9CA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>State reporting requirement</header><text>Each State that receives funding under any of the programs described in subsection (c) shall, twice per year, submit to the Secretary of Health and Human Services and the Administrator of the Drug Enforcement Administration—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE7C9F69D9C11449A8B3FCB61204CD5BF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a list of all practitioners and dispensers who, in the applicable reporting period, have prescribed or dispensed schedule II, III, or IV opioids in the State;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H35D371DA14FD42EA8D24A5CEFF81202B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the amount of schedule II, III, or IV opioids that were prescribed and dispensed by each individual practitioner and dispenser described in subparagraph (A); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCCE351B46B644A25AD577E0BE46079EF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any additional information that the Secretary and Administrator may require to support surveillance and evaluation of trends in prescribing or dispensing of schedule II, III, or IV opioids, or to identify possible non-medical use and diversion of such substances.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF86DFA298336402B89968A1C55F7ABF4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, in consultation with the Administrator of the Drug Enforcement Administration, the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, and the Director of the Indian Health Service, shall submit to Congress, and make public, a report identifying outliers among the medical specialties and geographic areas with the highest rates of opioid prescribing in the Nation, by ZIP code.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="H17D7FC564BCA4BB8908E9E224A66017F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Development of action plan</header>
 <subparagraph id="HAAE198CCE64E4812ABDC7E3B59746B08"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial plan</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, in consultation with the Administrator of the Drug Enforcement Administration, the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, and the Director of the Indian Health Service, shall submit to Congress a plan of action, including warning letters and enforcement mechanisms, for addressing outliers in opioid prescribing practices and ensuring an adequate Federal response to protect the public health.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H021C843E84B243D18C4753C830D6836F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Updated plan</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit to Congress updates to the plan of action described in subparagraph (A), as such Secretary, in consultation with the heads of agencies described in such subparagraph, determines appropriate.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5DF03D66FC9742BFB730968663449972"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Programs described</header><text>The programs described in this subsection are—</text> <paragraph id="HC7E05C9E0289447DABFDDD43ADF8BA8D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Harold Rogers Prescription Drug Monitoring Program established under the Departments of Commerce, Justice, and State, the Judiciary, and Related Agencies Appropriations Act, 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/77">Public Law 107–77</external-xref>; 115 Stat. 748);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H63277532A33743038FD4B9B88004ADF6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the controlled substance monitoring program under section 399O of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/280g-3">42 U.S.C. 280g–3</external-xref>);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA6B3C1CF56384E9D903823B7C627BE91"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Prescription Drug Overdose: Prevention for States program of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4FC1C2713ECF4A38B95D7918591DAADB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Prescription Drug Overdose: Data-Driven Prevention Initiative of Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H67131C5371A04202969C0BC0A0B59C6E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Enhanced State Opioid Overdose Surveillance program of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCE017C446DB84CBB953599C2A4435675"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the opioid grant program under section 1003 of the 21st Century Cures Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/255">Public Law 114–255</external-xref>); and</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCDC7DDE97B5D4F4FB404663F14B5DAC2"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the State Opioid Response Grant program described under the heading <quote><header-in-text level="appropriations-small" style="OLC">Substance abuse treatment</header-in-text></quote> under the heading <quote><header-in-text level="appropriations-intermediate" style="OLC">Substance abuse and mental health services administration</header-in-text></quote> of title II of division H of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/141">Public Law 115–141</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD3332F1886FF471C9799562ADE848157"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the terms <term>dispenser</term> and <term>practitioner</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>).</text>
 </subsection></section><section commented="no" id="HC1065460257C43559E9B8B565EEBB06B"><enum>8.</enum><header>Interoperability of certified health information technology</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3001(c)(5) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300jj-11">42 U.S.C. 300jj–11(c)(5)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBD3289DBC1D8439FA2AC3EF65319657E" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H8A39EA8FB0DA4F34B04BE41F0049BC9E"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Interoperability</header><text>Beginning on January 1, 2021, the National Coordinator shall not certify electronic health records as health information technology that is in compliance with applicable certification criteria under this paragraph unless such technology is interoperable with the prescription drug monitoring programs of each State that, at the time of the request for such certification, has such a program.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section commented="no" id="HC38F9DFE511644D691E257EEE9DB2277"><enum>9.</enum><header>Studies related to overdose discharge and follow-up policies</header>
 <subsection commented="no" id="H04F058548D624706BB102611AF0B7B25"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text>Not later than January 1, 2021, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H29AF90D7768C4445B6156DE8AE80487F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct a study on the scope and circumstances of non-fatal opioid overdoses, the policies and procedures that States, health care systems, and first responders have implemented; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H7392534C618E44D295368E146BD814D3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in partnership with stakeholder organizations with subject matter expertise, establish guidelines for hospital procedures following non-fatal opioid overdose and the administration of overdose reversal medication.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1D8BAF0658434617ADBE6A71CAB1BC21"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study and development of quality measures under Medicare related to opioid abuse and substance use
 disorder</header><text>Section 1890A(e) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395aaa-1">42 U.S.C. 1395aaa–1(e)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HAC668910899F4C32BECD3A9B79BAF46E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">measures</header-in-text>.—The Administrator</quote> and inserting “<header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">measures</header-in-text>.—</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9537FCC5FB5A4921B1ED20C1B2AA8E40" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="HF9B10A14CD2D4CC6B26D3E2A286EC5E5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph><paragraph id="H48D243C8E4AB4DD6AE9B4AB2F7C22693"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H61E2D5C1D87048A797FF242048280FAE" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="HD61E2A4490E142579BCC249F887A6AEA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Study and development of quality measures related to opioid abuse and substance use disorder</header><text>Beginning not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this paragraph, the Administrator of the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Services shall study and through contracts develop, in coordination with appropriate subject matter organizations (such as the entity with a contract under section 1890), for use under this Act, quality measures related to standards of care for treating individuals with non-fatal opioid overdose, discharge procedures, and linkages to appropriate substance use disorder treatment and community support services.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H66DE96DDBD304492B582DA6B89EEF162"><enum>10.</enum><header>Medicaid opioid drug mapping tool</header>
 <subsection id="H2589EF873EBA4F589FC999C7C2848931"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall create an interactive opioid drug mapping tool, which shall be made publicly available on the internet website of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services, showing prescribing practices of providers that participate in State Medicaid programs and geographic comparisons, at the State, county, and ZIP code levels, of de-identified opioid prescription claims made under State Medicaid programs under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H3B1E02099F174344920E6007B2A9FB61"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Collection of data from States</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services may request from States such data as the Secretary determines necessary to create the opioid mapping tool described in subsection (a).</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H57340FFABB524899BCF0F8631C6B8988"><enum>11.</enum><header>National Academy of Medicine Study</header>
 <subsection id="HF7E239286E70498887F6A4ECE1F362AF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall enter into a contract with the National Academy of Medicine to carry out a study on the addition of coverage under the Medicare program under title XVIII of the Social Security Act of alternative treatment modalities (such as integrative medicine, including acupuncture and exercise therapy, neural stimulation, biofeedback, radiofrequency ablation, and trigger point injections) furnished to Medicare beneficiaries who suffer from acute or chronic lower back pain. Such study shall, pursuant to the contract under this paragraph, include an analysis of—</text>
 <paragraph id="HAFAA3C4FDF724EE59BB3F04677D72AC3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>scientific research on the short-term and long-term impact of the addition of such coverage on clinical efficacy for pain management of such beneficiaries;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7C128C5B3F42467B9ECF121FB2223C12"><enum>(2)</enum><text>whether the lack of Medicare coverage for alternative treatment modalities impacts the volume of opioids prescribed for beneficiaries; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDC322E22115D453F9AD1725639F347BC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the cost to the Medicare program of the addition of such coverage to treat pain and mitigate the progression of chronic pain, as weighed against the cost of opioid use disorder, overdose, readmission, subsequent surgeries, and utilization and expenditures under parts B and D of such title.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1B131020A6494A7C944A6C32C021C588"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, pursuant to the contract under subsection (a), the National Academy of Medicine shall submit to Congress a report on the study under subsection (a).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H25C76304F62C4BECB07DFEA311C8C113"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary.</text> </subsection></section><section id="HA9FAC0FC6BEB457387722F2498896200"><enum>12.</enum><header>Excise tax on opioid pain relievers</header> <subsection id="H9B2CD21C52F341958F246337C547B21E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter E of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/32">chapter 32</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text>
				<quoted-block act-name="" id="H8509213BD7BA456B8EC82A82BE4DF04A" style="OLC">
					<section id="H094AD685A5C54EACBBD1189A606C91A8"><enum>4192.</enum><header>Opioid pain relievers</header>
 <subsection id="H121E785791D045A7BCECFE46AC416D76"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is hereby imposed on the manufacturer or producer of any taxable active opioid a tax equal to the amount determined under subsection (b).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HC2ADDB05F2B3480BAFBABE3F333C054B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amount determined</header><text>The amount determined under this subsection with respect to a manufacturer or producer for a calendar year is 1 cent per milligram of taxable active opioid in the production or manufacturing quota determined for such manufacturer or producer for the calendar year under section 306 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/826">21 U.S.C. 826</external-xref>).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5DE3FDE85BBF44C2A96DCD92845AB203"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Taxable active opioid</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text> <paragraph id="HB8348C571CFD481090846D499A5F1439"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>taxable active opioid</term> means any controlled substance (as defined in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>), as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section) manufactured in the United States which is opium, an opiate, or any derivative thereof.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph id="HB719FD1F75A64B0292D0CB13A7434FCA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusions</header>
 <subparagraph id="HEB84CBA9EB75424195FCD113394592AD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Other ingredients</header><text>In the case of a product that includes a taxable active opioid and another ingredient, subsection (a) shall apply only to the portion of such product that is a taxable active opioid.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D8D1AC38A3F484F85E2DAC34EAFD855"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Drugs used in addiction treatment</header><text>The term <term>taxable active opioid</term> shall not include any controlled substance (as so defined) which is used exclusively for the treatment of opioid addiction as part of a medication-assisted treatment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H1CCAB7068C9D43F2B533270599B94106"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header>
 <paragraph id="HA2CBC00FD60F43BCB237C352D74B45D0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The heading of subchapter E of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/32">chapter 32</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subchapter" style="OLC">Medical devices</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subchapter" style="OLC">Other medical products</header-in-text></quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF1C596B436DD4D4094715B2DC569796E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The table of subchapters for chapter 32 of such Code is amended by striking the item relating to subchapter E and inserting the following new item:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4F9ABFBC436A4C9A82FF25BA19B1F7A2" style="OLC">
						<toc>
							<toc-entry bold="off" level="subchapter">Subchapter E. Other medical products</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5A9F82BEA881405ABA05A61CFEB7C0BF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The table of sections for subchapter E of chapter 32 of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H530D81C66AEF470C97E257ADA4097BC3" style="OLC">
						<toc>
							<toc-entry idref="H094AD685A5C54EACBBD1189A606C91A8" level="section">Sec. 4192. Opioid pain relievers.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6B2F5513603B485FBCFB362CD30CFB02"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to calendar years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HC921A1441BD444F39B7A68C83CF82010"><enum>13.</enum><header>Opioid consumer abuse reduction program</header>
 <subsection id="H4C3BA6E0E3DA452E9A3D7A183AA086BF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Opioid take-Back program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 302 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/822">21 U.S.C. 822</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H619D3F2BC3A4427CBDFC535F5C241FE3" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H75209CFE501E466A9096D9E7D63629D2"><enum>(h)</enum>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8B9BB580B8D043329496202580AABBEE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Attorney General shall establish a national take-back program for the safe and environmentally responsible disposal of controlled substances.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD84CF1DDE393431FA9B0E955770B5264" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In establishing the take-back program required under paragraph (1), the Attorney General—</text> <subparagraph id="HCD426BA4A14B4717AD512181079609E3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall consult with the Secretary and the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B9CDB73BE914DCEB73A4604E9CDCEB7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may coordinate with States, law enforcement agencies, water resource management agencies, manufacturers, practitioners, pharmacists, public health entities, transportation and incineration service contractors, and other entities and individuals, as appropriate.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H96E7893A19334B23AA954FB041F222B5" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The take-back program established under paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H49640569BECF43469B9B207A32796C94"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall—</text>
 <clause id="HE25F6D337CD14B31BB9A6E0421435692"><enum>(i)</enum><text>ensure appropriate geographic distribution so as to provide—</text> <subclause id="HDEE1E82689A045C89A904A7A7DF67FBF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>reasonably convenient and equitable access to permanent take-back locations, including not less than 1 disposal site for every 25,000 residents and not less than 1 physical disposal site per town, city, county, or other unit of local government, where possible; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H4DB6013F90EB421E8C0BE2CF86A3A21B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>periodic collection events and mail-back programs, including public notice of such events and programs, as a supplement to the permanent take-back locations described in subclause (I), particularly in areas in which the provision of access to such locations at the level described in that subclause is not possible;</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="HC94077DB60804BAC90407CDBB4533AC0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>establish a process for the accurate cataloguing and reporting of the quantities of controlled substances collected; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8941F345FEC94E68B19A4B68D0335F49"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>include a public awareness campaign and education of practitioners and pharmacists; and</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H629F5816CCFD45039F0CA44DF5C37F30"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may work in coordination with State and locally implemented public and private take-back programs.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB64EC4A336354166839EFB7DA4710259" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From time to time, beginning in the second calendar year that begins after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Secretary of the Treasury shall transfer from the general fund of the Treasury an amount equal to one-half of the total amount of taxes collected under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4192">section 4192</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to the Attorney General to carry out this subsection. Amounts transferred under this subparagraph shall remain available until expended.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA08D6D6C42654F9E8555A3808976F564"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Funding of substance abuse programs</header><text>From time to time, beginning in the second calendar year that begins after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury shall transfer from the general fund of the Treasury an amount equal to one-half of the total amount of taxes collected under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4192">section 4192</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as added by this Act, to the Director of the Center for Substance Abuse Treatment of the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration for programs of the Center, including the Block Grants for Prevention and Treatment of Substance Abuse program under subpart II of part B of title XIX of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300x-21">42 U.S.C. 300x–21</external-xref> et seq.) and Programs of Regional and National Significance. Amounts transferred under this subsection shall remain available until expended.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="HBE254CA9925A4E96AE1D866B78D9A8EA"><enum>14.</enum><header>GAO study</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study evaluating the various State laws, commercial insurance methods, and existing research on requirements that place limitations on opioid prescribing practices and provide analysis on best practices to address over-prescribing of opioids, while ensuring that individuals who need such opioids can access them safely. Such study shall provide recommendations, including with respect to—</text>
 <paragraph id="HFD63189F871941C6A5A403B8927FD451"><enum>(1)</enum><text>requiring non-opioid pain treatments to be front line therapies;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H072B04044E4C4C84A610D93D0EAC26A1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">limiting first-time opioid prescriptions to a patient for acute pain to a 72-hour supply; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC08185DD9F6F4B49940B1DF8332DB962"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">pain management treatment contracts between practitioners and patients that establish informed consent regarding the expectations, risks, long-term effects, and benefits of the course of opioid treatment, treatment goals, the potential for opioid misuse, abuse, or diversion, and requirements and responsibilities of patients, such as submitting to a urine drug screening.</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


