<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HD5AD4E7F0EF048DC8102D055F9F8F298" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5018 IH: Education and Workforce Innovation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5018</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180214">February 14, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000188">Mr. Kind</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To carry out pilot programs to improve skills and job training, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HE53D1D2D681946409B24A979D8969845" style="OLC">
 <section id="H3563621661FD4A8B8ABA2A49B77FB34D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Education and Workforce Innovation Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H092BFD77F0464F13AA488454F4D7B46E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Community Workforce Training Grants</header> <subsection id="H3D9392A73F874F7695474B24AEC98F5A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts available under subsection (f) to carry out this section, the Secretary of Education, in consultation with the Secretary of Labor and the advisory panel, shall carry out a pilot program to award grants to eligible entities to carry out programs that provide direct skills and job training for individuals to enter and advance in high-growth, emerging, and in-demand industries, such as skilled labor and trade industries.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H9FB734614D9646119EC3F317C472C634"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To receive a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit an application, at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary of Education may require.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF1FD7CDADEF74DEE94791EEB24547D44"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall use such grant to—</text> <paragraph id="H1D01C35BA5CF433C97DD911532C6E688"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and carry out a multi-year program to provide students enrolled in a school or institution described in subparagraphs (A) through (C) of subsection (g)(1) with education and training to prepare such students to enter and advance in high-growth, emerging, or in-demand industries by providing—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H947395AD9D894A89969E37BF6A7C86AA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>customized training that is valuable to such industries;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5EFCDD91F4A549E8B74EE7608B8E1317"><enum>(B)</enum><text>increased productivity and knowledge transfer;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDD08F130D2F4EDAAE2DAEE6C2D4EF81"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a stable and predictable pipeline to a high standard of employment (as determined by the Secretary of Labor in consultation with the advisory panel) upon graduation from the program;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45DBCBD0BB374E118B0A153E393D25BB"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a proven model of success, as determined by the Secretary of Labor in consultation with the advisory panel; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H84F3540628A945B9B0AC992E043E3751"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an opportunity for career advancement; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H06BBDB9E85BA412A8448CB7C6A39AF87"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">cover costs related to developing and carrying out the program, which may include—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H512BCF93BFE840249E7D1BB90E4DA040"><enum>(A)</enum><text>covering overhead costs;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B9DD941A4FC42AAA23E8061BD5D2B05"><enum>(B)</enum><text>improving program design;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDBA71F48FB7B4681912E33115DE26BC0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>expanding access to the program; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A593E8F0BD1407C883E3E5CDEC51C1D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>providing tuition subsidies for students enrolled, or desiring to enroll, in an institution described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (g)(1), if applicable, to participate in such program.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFCB9FF0B8FD94B0398144AFF524F12EA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Matching funds</header><text>An eligible entity that is awarded a grant under this section shall provide matching funds from non-Federal sources in an amount equal to not less than the Federal funds provided under the grant.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H92DB934BED124F7A9D8D6055FCCC58E8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Advisory panel</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the pilot program under this section, the Secretary of Education shall establish an advisory panel that is comprised of Federal education experts and private sector executives.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HDC57505630E64EC6A16ED0782186933E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Availability of funding</header><text>In each fiscal year not less than $50,000,000, shall be available from the amount appropriated for each such fiscal year for the Workforce Innovation Fund of the Department of Labor for the costs of carrying out this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HB55119B9551B4FC7942AC0C35B249347"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H5413F2C26EDD4DD4A128F46D372D131D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a private company involved in the manufacturing, production, or technology industries, in partnership with a—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE7263823D7D64DC7A05988B1D185D101"><enum>(A)</enum><text>junior or community college;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFF852B736764FD68066373BE2E38954"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">postsecondary vocational institution; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD460F338C9847D2AC041479A2E27EA2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>secondary school.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE94DE2A81B07480E9D20BF558EB1118B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Junior or community college</header><text>The term <term>junior or community college</term> has the meaning given the term in section 312(f) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1058">20 U.S.C. 1058(f)</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H50B7C97B8D9B427F95AA6141AB039ADC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Postsecondary vocational institution</header><text>The term <term>postsecondary vocational institution</term> has the meaning given the term in section 102(c) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002(c)</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0AA55EF473CC48AA84D5D800EBC4267F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secondary school</header><text>The term <term>secondary school</term> has the meaning given the term in section 9101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF495A4A5FBBA4FB3889EDB86C9CEDFC5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Skilled labor and trade industries</header><text>The term <term>skilled labor and trade industries</term> shall be defined by the Secretary of Labor.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB1EAF501839C42ABBE497F3A68697491"><enum>3.</enum><header>Financing a Skilled 21st Century Workforce Goal</header> <subsection id="HFA707FC84A4A45C182EFB4C71CA0EF5D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretaries of Education and the Treasury, jointly with the advisory panel, shall administer a pay-for-performance pilot program for 5 years to raise funds from qualified investors to cover the cost of a workforce training program that increases trade certifications or apprenticeships for unemployed individuals or dislocated workers, and that meets the requirements of subsection (b).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HC4C4DD49209B48E786F04A0BF3B3753F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The pay-for-performance pilot program carried out under subsection (a) shall require that—</text> <paragraph id="H45DFD8A7D27148C8894F2121E7F4F304"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretaries and the advisory panel establish the goals of increasing trade certifications or apprenticeships for unemployed individuals or dislocated workers, and other social and financial goals (such as reducing Federal, State, and local expenditures related to workforce training) for the program;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6ED1452FB66A4447901AD3D1A0133735"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a qualified investor enters into a pay-for-performance agreement with the Secretaries under which the qualified investor—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HB98CD7D86BFF4D779EA5CFB57E00DDB8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provides funds to a service provider selected by the Secretaries, the advisory panel, and the qualified investor to meet the goals established under paragraph (1); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCEED0E227D84E43ACC7A80BE5814733"><enum>(B)</enum><text>agrees to the repayment terms described in paragraph (4);</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8C949DF3C564A2491F0FAF883B4A9A7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the service provider uses such funds to carry out a workforce training program for unemployed adults or dislocated workers to meet such goals;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFF428AF70208465AAC65A558BCB296FB"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the Secretaries and the advisory panel determine that the workforce training program carried out by the service provider meets the goals established under paragraph (1), the Secretaries will repay the qualified investor the amount of funds provided by the qualified investor under paragraph (2) with financial returns; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0FCCC61A95F347C7B7E50DEBB14EFCB4"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretaries and the advisory panel assess the feasibility of expanding the pay-for-performance pilot program on a larger scale.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8AAAE8F724824554899101198C2CDE12"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated $75,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023 to carry out this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H77EFD0FAA87649F2B032C2BECE059EB1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act the following definitions apply:</text> <paragraph id="H54F3EC4E7BE44884A289089FB9C6A5F9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advisory panel</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>advisory panel</term> means a panel of business representatives selected by the Secretaries.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF49C6F5CE22741B182DE2766ECE94D4E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Dislocated worker; unemployed individual</header><text>The terms <term>dislocated worker</term> and <term>unemployed individual</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H65D76048D2824AB391F4E7987C4DD126"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Qualified investor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>qualified investor</term> has the meaning given such term in section 230.501(a) of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7C631A005BAE4C778554218FDE33EBE7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretaries</header><text>The term <term>Secretaries</term> means the Secretaries of Education and the Treasury.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H46DFB35E70D24EB6B722394B28BB00CB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Service provider</header><text>The term <term>service provider</term> means a nonprofit organization that carries out a workforce training program.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


