<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H6F9995CEA4194CE39ABD3DE5F81200D7" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5003 IH: To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to reinstate advance refunding bonds.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5003</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180213">February 13, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001059">Mr. Hultgren</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001189">Mr. Messer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000487">Mr. Royce of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001037">Mr. Capuano</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to reinstate advance refunding bonds.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H5B97D9876F254AC0B2651A526F2E1569" style="OLC">
		<section id="H19EA4F4CEAEB4B68AE1D68A0589E0331" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Treatment of advance refunding bonds</header>
 <subsection id="HE0863C215F9747CD8773DA530E9E47B3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/149">Section 149(d)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HEC8586AE22564DD5AE01D3F9F17C3603"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>to advance refund another bond</quote> and inserting <quote>as part of an issue described in paragraph (2), (3), or (4)</quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H19FEEF8F2AAF49C1AB7E08CBBE45AAF8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (2) and (3) as paragraphs (6) and (7), respectively; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H736EA647E64C425C9AAF7969D81B0B66"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (1) the following new paragraphs:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA0AE1DDBC37C4EFDAF5588D9225D9692" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H790F5D1643EA49718343B4A869DE39E1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certain private activity bonds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An issue is described in this paragraph if any bond (issued as part of such issue) is issued to advance refund a private activity bond (other than a qualified 501(c)(3) bond).</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="HC22774BE70BB4CFEB13BD65DF9C534D4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Other bonds</header>
 <subparagraph id="H38524B2B4C334443A0392F8C3FAAB892"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An issue is described in this paragraph if any bond (issued as part of such issue), hereinafter in this paragraph referred to as the <quote>refunding bond</quote>, is issued to advance refund a bond unless—</text>
 <clause id="H4C2707EFEA4447359B009129834B1F01"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the refunding bond is only—</text> <subclause id="H94C82F18E4774331BE32F5EA486A2195"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the 1st advance refunding of the original bond if the original bond is issued after 1985, or</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HC78811A1487545C7891FD4DE25A99C52"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the 1st or 2nd advance refunding of the original bond if the original bond was issued before 1986,</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="H1E64281EB3D94B7CA9299906D823218B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of refunded bonds issued before 1986, the refunded bond is redeemed not later than the earliest date on which such bond may be redeemed at par or at a premium of 3 percent or less,</text>
 </clause><clause id="HDA58AAB83D1E4641A9F7A0299BED0889"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the case of refunded bonds issued after 1985, the refunded bond is redeemed not later than the earliest date on which such bond may be redeemed,</text>
 </clause><clause id="HE29728098BB245DE83928FF80BCEEDE8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the initial temporary period under section 148(c) ends—</text> <subclause id="HBB2EAFBE4812437CB95BB0D1EDA474C8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>with respect to the proceeds of the refunding bond not later than 30 days after the date of issue of such bond, and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HD456EE1CAAEA4A009AB2E4EDF5FF6824"><enum>(II)</enum><text>with respect to the proceeds of the refunded bond on the date of issue of the refunding bond, and</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="HFED14F33EF7248F1BFF899ADA74F7A4A"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in the case of refunded bonds to which section 148(e) did not apply, on and after the date of issue of the refunding bond, the amount of proceeds of the refunded bond invested in higher yielding investments (as defined in section 148(b)) which are nonpurpose investments (as defined in section 148(f)(6)(A)) does not exceed—</text>
 <subclause id="HBA7B75549E384D5D90110E0BDDEBC3C0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the amount so invested as part of a reasonably required reserve or replacement fund or during an allowable temporary period, and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HABD485EDA7DD4E3CA1B0522272D72F00"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the amount which is equal to the lesser of 5 percent of the proceeds of the issue of which the refunded bond is a part or $100,000 (to the extent such amount is allocable to the refunded bond).</text>
									</subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD43FED9B41DC48D9BB60CC1B3327C17C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Special rules for redemptions</header>
 <clause id="H41DCDDD42C434057B014DA913B4112B0"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Issuer must redeem only if debt service savings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Clause (ii) and (iii) of subparagraph (A) shall apply only if the issuer may realize present value debt service savings (determined without regard to administrative expenses) in connection with the issue of which the refunding bond is a part.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H0E20CC70E30A4ABA8819059FB9049BB0"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Redemptions not required before 90th day</header><text>For purposes of clauses (ii) and (iii) of subparagraph (A), the earliest date referred to in such clauses shall not be earlier than the 90th day after the date of issuance of the refunding bond.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B64997709BE4CCC9C615A60D5B9D5DF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Abusive transactions prohibited</header><text>An issue is described in this paragraph if any bond (issued as part of such issue) is issued to advance refund another bond and a device is employed in connection with the issuance of such issue to obtain a material financial advantage (based on arbitrage) apart from savings attributable to lower interest rates.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA8607C14DD22488792DEA1E24C4B1F7B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Special rules for purposes of paragraph (3)</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (3), bonds issued before the date of the enactment of this subsection shall be taken into account under subparagraph (A)(i) thereof except—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H278DFDA92D3845B7ACAB1B4E83C6CC31"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a refunding which occurred before 1986 shall be treated as an advance refunding only if the refunding bond was issued more than 180 days before the redemption of the refunded bond, and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DAFDE0BB3A044B0854C310A4347574A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a bond issued before 1986, shall be treated as advance refunded no more than once before March 15, 1986.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44D6EACEACDC4DC5A8C7C78CEC3D4509"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 148(f)(4)(C) of such Code is amended by redesignating clauses (xiv) through (xvi) as clauses (xv) through (xvii) and by inserting after clause (xiii) the following new clause:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFBEE23E121CA4E14851DA087FAAF1E36" style="OLC">
 <clause id="H1DFE91AB5C2B4B44B4CD97A16099FAF6"><enum>(xiv)</enum><header>Determination of initial temporary period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subparagraph, the end of the initial temporary period shall be determined without regard to section 149(d)(3)(A)(iv).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HABFB0CDCD48D4F2AACB258F56C78F95B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to advance refunding bonds issued after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


