<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H41C8CB45F45D4919B875677837E35538" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5044 IH: Service-Disabled Veterans Small Business Continuation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5044</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180215">February 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000266">Mr. Chabot</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001301">Mr. Bergman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to clarify the treatment of certain surviving spouses under
			 the contracting goals and preferences of the Department of Veterans
			 Affairs.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H0D2D70E7B9214E51BF6F98D19EEE3C3A" style="OLC">
 <section id="H09B723C785014CE4B1A619FFD4449ECC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Service-Disabled Veterans Small Business Continuation Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H93FBE0DBC5074E3A82EC0BF1513993C6" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Technical amendment regarding treatment of certain surviving spouses under contracting goals and preferences of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Effective on the date specified in subsection (e) of section 1832 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/328">Public Law 114–328</external-xref>; 130 Stat. 2660), section 8127(k)(3) of title 38, United States Code, as amended by such section 1832, is further amended by inserting after the period at the end the following new sentence: <quote>A surviving spouse of such a veteran who is not covered by subparagraph (C)(i) of such section by reason of the disability rating of the veteran being less than 100 percent shall be treated as being so covered during the period beginning on the date of the death of the veteran and ending on the date that is three years after such death, the date on which the surviving spouse remarries, or the date on which the surviving spouse relinquishes an ownership interest in the small business concern, whichever occurs first.</quote>.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


