<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HBF105AE9E8474E2B99851627F7B28F2F" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5328 IH: Guam Land Return Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5328</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180319">March 19, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001245">Ms. Bordallo</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the return of surplus property, including Federal land, to the government of Guam, and
			 for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H775C0D55504E45638B803E79C4229AA6" style="OLC">
 <section id="HECA87212CBBB48E0BB2CE33B74C06007" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Guam Land Return Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H851AB352DB944B2ABC03F44E2599F6C9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Return of surplus property, including Federal land, to Guam</header> <subsection id="HD20A939C45E74A1BBBD5528EF1753BCC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator of General Services is authorized to transfer to the government of Guam all right, title, and interest of the United States in and to surplus property located on Guam by quitclaim deed and without reimbursement, to compensate for unreimbursed impact expenses claimed on behalf of Guam pursuant to section 104(e)(9) of the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1921c">48 U.S.C. 1921c(e)(9)</external-xref>). Such transfers of surplus property shall be in accordance with—</text>
 <paragraph id="H1941D80E03A249C189F9AA9D73207113"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subtitle I of title 40, United States Code;</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H1F47C5FF1C9E4323B3ADABF7EB3E2BC2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Public Law 103–339 (commonly known as the <quote>Guam Excess Lands Act</quote>); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H7B496FBE333D4E119107A4FC4872B36D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Public Law 106–504 (commonly known as the <quote>Guam Omnibus Opportunities Act</quote>), except paragraphs (1) and (2)(D) of section 1(b) of such Act.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HED8D365C504446339483AAE73EA96043"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Territorial notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall notify the Governor of Guam when any surplus property becomes available under this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA046E7F3176342178030E8F4DEB3B369"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Transfer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If within 90 days after receiving notification under subsection (b) the Governor notifies the Administrator that the territorial government intends to acquire the surplus property, the Administrator shall transfer such property pursuant to this section.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H636369DF8B444DA194603CE8FCCA58A3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Terms and conditions</header>
 <paragraph id="HAE09BDAEB90444A3B141A031DF795119"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements for transfer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Transfers of surplus property authorized by this section shall take place after—</text> <subparagraph id="H3700649638FD4186A60D396873B137DB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Administrator completes an appraisal determining the estimated fair-market value of the surplus property, the cost of which shall be paid for in accordance with section 571(b) of title 40, United States Code; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4E74BA9554C84A76AAFD9582C5220D65"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Governor submits to the Administrator and the Delegate to the House of Representatives from Guam a detailed plan for the future use of such surplus property and makes such plan available on a public government website.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H037A1CD1948D4A69B69EC3BFBC8EA2F5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Navigable airspace</header><text>The conveyance document for any surplus property that is real property transferred under this section located in a 6-mile radius of an airport shall contain a provision that requires a determination by the Federal Aviation Administration that no interference to air navigation exists in accordance with regulations set forth in subparts I and III of part A of subtitle VII of title 49, United States Code, in order for construction or alteration on the property to be permitted.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H70165F77B99046A4A335962EA3213806"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Severe contamination</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, the Administrator may choose not to transfer any surplus property under this section on which there is severe contamination, the remedy of which would require the United States to incur extraordinary costs.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H5DEB8463096140BF81A8AAC68612745B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>The fair-market value, appraised or otherwise estimated, of any surplus property transferred to the government of Guam under this section shall be used to supplement and not supplant other Federal funds provided to the government of Guam as compensation or reimbursement for costs or impact expenses incurred by that affected jurisdiction pursuant to—</text>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="HA3568DDEE83F41F6AE43A27B9AFB74D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>section 104(e)(6) of the Compact of Free Association Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1904">48 U.S.C. 1904(e)(6)</external-xref>);</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HAE9559BED207450BA090579DFAC3F2BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>section 104(e)(3) and section 104(e)(6) of the Compact of Free Association Amendments Act of 2003; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HAFA8652253DF4D55805E99544FBFC3A9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any other impact aid provided to the government of Guam under any other authority.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HF51C37FA6C9A49BC8BCA91776F434210"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Net-Negative land transfers</header><text>Land parcels (or the value thereof) included in the inventory under section (3) and transferred by the Secretary of Defense to the government of Guam shall not be counted—</text>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="HEC6F948E75024E8B8C927776E21B85D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>as compensation or reimbursement by the Federal Government for costs or impact expenses incurred by the territorial government; or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HDCFBEA953C344141947B7658183DF796"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for compensation by the Federal Government for unreimbursed impact expenses pursuant to subsection (a).</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF5E28CFDC1F04BC5B9D3ACFC8E580DE8"><enum>3.</enum><header>DOD net-negative inventory of Guam land parcels</header>
 <subsection id="H45C392A14531482584C44790CD5DE5D7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Net-Negative inventory of land parcels</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall maintain and update regularly an inventory of all land parcels located on Guam currently owned by the United States Government and administered by the Department of Defense which the Secretary expects to transfer to the territorial government, specifying for each parcel—</text>
 <paragraph id="HA113A9C2D30D4F28A402A3ECD94343DF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the approximate size of the parcel;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HA277ED4F651843C5B05EE049BBEF7DC7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an estimate of the fair market value of the parcel, if available or as practicable;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBD3E5720EE8547E0ACA94D904930BF7E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the branch of the armed forces with jurisdiction or operational control over the parcel;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H3984A6504841418CA06438F15C3F174C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the specific legal authority under which the Secretary will transfer the parcel to the territorial government; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H799C90B4B40C4A9CB0312202B11CFD0D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the date by which the Secretary expects to transfer the parcel to the territorial government, lease the parcel to the territorial government prior to final transfer, or otherwise designate the parcel as excess property or surplus property and then transfer to the territorial government.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD1562855959D42B894DE529194C817A7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Parcels required To be included</header>
 <paragraph id="HD43D06085A5A47E9B651A821BBCC0686"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Parcels included in 2017 Net Negative Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall include in the inventory under this section each of the following parcels, as described in the 2017 Net Negative Report:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H07ADE7E9849642EDB67EDFD68988A5F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Tanguisson Power Plant (5 acres), listed as Site 14 in the Report.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31A0649CA2544A288327C758BE9CBAEC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Harmon Substation Annex (9.9 acres), listed as Site 15 in the Report.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAFEE607438534DF9A190D479DF30873A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Piti Power Plant and Substation (15.5 acres), listed as Site 38 in the Report.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59C833050C10463EA910C0B10B69029E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Apra Heights Lot 403–1 (0.5 acres), listed as Site 55 in the Report.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBE44D169A77B42FF857C34A022CCB21A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Agana Power Plant and Substation (5.9 acres), listed as Site 54 in the Report.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74DBC4DB85744526BAF854E6FEC343ED"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The ACEORP Maui Tunnel-Tamuning Route 1 behind Old Telex (3.7 acres), listed as Site 23 in the Report.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDEFD1436F6049769B117C7347DA8E2F"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The Parcel South of Camp Covington, Parcel 7 (60.8 acres), listed as Site 49 in the Report.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07F98D43E6A7466AA882C836F2DC0B90"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The NCTS Beach Lot, adjacent to the Tanguisson Power Plant (13.3 acres), listed as Site 13 in the Report.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H396AD19C37604F8B8C02A3A2B62E966C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The Hoover Park Annex (also known as “Old USO Beach”; 6 acres), listed as Site 37 in the Report.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51C98BFED7634CD3B5E3F648BAAA78F9"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Parcel “C” Marbo Cave Annex (5 acres), listed as Site 12 in the Report.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F02A816E4FA4E0081A654876CF6E459"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other parcels</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to the parcels specified in paragraph (1), the Secretary shall include in the inventory under this section each of the following parcels:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H9B2177625C6F4FA686C9E558348C5B9D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Marbo school site (80 acres), currently under reversion to the Department of Education but expected to be transferred to the Department of the Navy (within Andersen South Annex).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8F7107B20694E4CA49815CD065546D2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Dandan property (159.12 acres), formerly the Apollo Tracking Station operated by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8AF848BDF75942EDA4CC2130454943F2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Urunao property (69.19 acres) at Andersen Air Force Base (Northwest Field), from the west side of Route 3A to the cliff line.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAAA8474B66D8414280BD06D4F03F9670"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Naval Water Treatment Plant (8.79 acres) and associated water and wastewater treatment utility systems at Naval Base Guam (Ordnance Annex/Naval Magazine).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H369F2DFAE672495F87F3BB3D823C992E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The following future photovoltaic sites along Route 1, currently under lease to the Guam Power Authority:</text>
 <clause id="H92836FC572294A64A364D9C264447036"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Harmon Annex (4 acres).</text> </clause><clause id="HE7733EBCCB104F82AA24B3087DF384AE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Harmon Booster Station (5.59 acres), listed as Site 16 in the 2017 Net Negative Report.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HEB02492895064DA89BBF955600F8A21C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The former Tumon Tank Farm (23.77 acres), listed as Site 17 in the 2017 Net Negative Report.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H366FDD40E69844C9A9134BBA808AF089"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>2017 Net Negative Report</term> means the report submitted by the Secretary of the Navy, on behalf of the Secretary of Defense, under section 2208 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/328">Public Law 114–328</external-xref>; 130 Stat. 2695) regarding the status of the implementation of the <quote>net negative</quote> policy regarding the total number of acres of the real property controlled by the Department of the Navy or the Department of Defense on Guam.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H69A7C1E376DF4D93911AAF217E4E96C9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Petition for placement of additional parcels in inventory</header>
 <paragraph id="H888D8C53C98848BCB314A001236C98C1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Mechanism for petition</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a formal mechanism under which the Governor of Guam may petition the Secretary to add parcels to the inventory maintained under this section.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD5B25FD91D3F457DB667ED13FA9074AE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Specification of public benefit uses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Governor shall specify in any petition under this subsection any public benefit uses proposed by the Governor for the parcel involved.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H133DF6B09211432AA7451D3175931F67"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exclusion of parcels</header><text>The Secretary shall not include in the inventory maintained under this section any parcel transferred to the government of Guam prior to the date of the enactment of this Act, without regard to whether or not the parcel is included in paragraph (1) or paragraph (2) of subsection (b).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H0667F374AF71451CBDEA43735DF6FEF0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Public notification</header><text>The Secretary shall publish and update on a public website of the Department of Defense the following information:</text>
 <paragraph id="H4E672332B5404785B35B37C07361AB0E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The inventory maintained under subsection (a), including the parcels required to be included in such inventory under subsection (b).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5C666D14DCEA4961A5F522AEB79D05B0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All petitions filed by the Governor under the mechanism established under subsection (c) (including any proposed public benefit use specified in any such petition).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8752513736D546848FD942FDBA7F1A1D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A description of each parcel of land transferred by the Secretary to the territorial government after January 20, 2011, including the following:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H00CE25DEFAC545A19895F49B4B17851C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The approximate size of the parcel.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7512926909649439366766CB71B494A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An estimate of the fair market value of the parcel, if available or as practicable.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE239672D07F544C5BE4464A678458EF0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The specific legal authority under which the Secretary transferred the parcel to the territorial government.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6EE3F4A58B4845E7AA52D027A461FDE6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The date the transfer of the parcel was completed.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H023E39C92B674117B62054B56E3E0826"><enum>4.</enum><header>Repeal of conditions on conveyance of certain lands by Guam</header> <subsection id="HCBE4E1C68634480C99485FC0E3F1C015"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 818(b)(2) of the Military Construction Authorization Act, 1981 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/96/418">Public Law 96–418</external-xref>; 94 Stat. 1782) is hereby repealed and shall have no force or effect.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HC0E0829E4D4849D68BEC6C3AAFF279DE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Execution of instruments</header><text>The Administrator and the Secretary shall execute all instruments necessary to implement this section.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="HE7D1E583A651461A9090EF93B4845D7D"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HA477C34A060E43AD9A0FE652919B7CEA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of General Services.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA24E3720A7534C729A992A7DA7617B88"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Governor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Governor</term> means the Governor of the territory of Guam.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H5154DD70275C4DEB8FF4DC511CCB4F55"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Defense.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H7DE9FF0D8BE44DA1A1BF58AB0A42A071"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Surplus property</header><text>The term <term>surplus property</term> has the meaning given that term in section 102 of title 40, United States Code.</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HDE9DACF0D1DC4B32B26A7A64A3078A4E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Territorial government</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>territorial government</term> means the government of Guam established under the Organic Act of Guam (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1421">48 U.S.C. 1421</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


