<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H7CF1A4E092294F5F9FBCE5D51EA87982" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5597 IH: Desert Tortoise Habitat Conservation Plan Expansion Act, Washington County, Utah</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5597</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180424">April 24, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001192">Mr. Stewart</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To provide for the expansion of the Desert Tortoise Habitat Conservation Plan, Washington County,
			 Utah.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="HA7F125FF691C41E8A507095A110AEBF0" style="OLC">
 <section id="HED3B30E97B834E7E99784571D85CE0B8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Desert Tortoise Habitat Conservation Plan Expansion Act, Washington County, Utah</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H14EF9FFBE13049E0BE8F943FF5A03D19"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
 <paragraph id="HE3151765F039407D8B45D8767B15E2C9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Beaver dam wash national conservation area</header><text>The term <quote>Beaver Dam Wash National Conservation Area</quote> means the Beaver Dam Wash National Conservation Area as established by the Omnibus Public Lands Management Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/11">Public Law 111–11</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAD4CF26D9F73404398258404BAD851F9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Desert tortoise habitat conservation plan</header><text>The term <quote>Desert Tortoise Habitat Conservation Plan, Washington County, Utah</quote> means the Washington County Habitat Conservation Plan signed February 23, 1996, by the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, Bureau of Land Management, the State of Utah, Washington County, Utah, and Ivins City, Utah.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H478D8C1705D841EEA6082738250A2007"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Red Cliffs National Conservation Area</header><text>The term <quote>Red Cliffs National Conservation Area</quote> means the Red Cliffs National Conservation Area as established by the Omnibus Public Lands Management Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/11">Public Law 111–11</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAB85D67CAD8F44438D738A640F37F32F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HBB0F6BDE38334587BB52F35ECC0712B0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Unit of local government</header><text>The term <quote>unit of local government</quote> means Washington County, St. George City, and other political subdivisions of the State of Utah, including municipalities of the State of Utah within the geographical boundaries of Washington County with authority over local planning and zoning and the Washington County Water Conservancy District.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF94BFF0421974EEB96CF0B293877CED8"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Utility</header><text>The term <quote>utility</quote> means existing or new sites, rights-of-way, permits, grants, infrastructure, edifices, facilities, and any other components that provide public services including, but not limited to, water, electricity, gas, sewage, and communications.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H87219C4F4EA54BC793F5468BFE497C6E"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Utility development protocols</header><text>The term <quote>utility development protocols</quote> means the Red Cliffs Desert Reserve Development Protocols for Projects agreement approved by Washington County, Bureau of Land Management, and United States Fish and Wildlife Service for the construction, operation, maintenance, and replacement of utilities within the Red Cliffs Desert Reserve and/or Incidental Take Areas dated August 1, 2006, as amended.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H2689E838B84641D2A9222D19929CF3A8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Amendment and renewal of the Desert Tortoise Habitat Conservation Plan, Washington County, Utah</header>
 <subsection id="HE37A1A365C6946F7829D38950D91930C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon receipt from Washington County, Utah, of a proposal to amend and renew the Desert Tortoise Habitat Conservation Plan, Washington County, Utah that includes an additional 6,865 acre desert tortoise reserve zone named the Red Cliffs Desert Reserve, Zone 6, as generally depicted on a map entitled <quote>Red Cliffs Desert Reserve, Zone 6</quote> and dated February 23, 2018, the Secretary shall, after coordination with units of local government and in accordance with the provisions of this Act and with applicable laws, approve such amendment and renew such plan and the permit under the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531</external-xref> et seq.) that was issued for such plan, for a period of 25 years.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H126F2E397BEC4F8193A14D2653867F68"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Management of Red Cliffs Desert Reserve, Zone 6</header><text>The Red Cliffs Desert Reserve, Zone 6 shall be managed by Washington County as part of and in conformity with the provisions of the Desert Tortoise Habitat Conservation Plan, Washington County, Utah.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HAB829BC4493A4DDF950DEC0A0A9B5432"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Management of Federal lands</header><text>The Secretary shall manage Federal lands within Zone 6 of the Desert Tortoise Habitat Conservation Plan, Washington County, Utah to enhance the natural values of such lands, including wildlife habitat, and recreational, cultural, educational, and scientific values of such lands.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H936B612BF66A46E29C7C3055FDC55CB2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Amendment of St. George Field Office Resource Management Plan</header>
 <paragraph id="H0895474D82B1434890E949B8FC14D96C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with units of local government including Washington County, shall amend the St. George Field Office Resource Management Plan to provide for management of Federal lands within the Red Cliffs Desert Reserve, Zone 6 area.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H204183E3B8A14166A59EA9924AABCC55"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amendment requirements</header><text>The amendment shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="H1408FCB043414CE3AB37E3050200C7F7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>management of species in accordance with the Desert Tortoise Habitat Conservation Plan, Washington County, Utah;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF482951A23FF4A4086D928CFFD03E284"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the utility development protocols as outlined for the Red Cliffs Desert Reserve and/or Incidental Take Areas dated August 1, 2006, as amended; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4DC3CC993372491584F1A86889275B14"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">management of recreation in conformance with the Desert Tortoise Habitat Conservation Plan, Washington County, Utah for other zones in the Red Cliffs Desert Reserve including rock climbing, organized events approved by the Washington County Habitat Conservation Advisory Committee, hiking, biking, horseback riding, and off-highway vehicle use on designated trails and roads.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1B63A961B91B427A9727460B404AD18E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Provision of mitigation credits</header><text>The Secretary shall manage the Red Cliffs Desert Reserve, Zone 6 as a land bank to provide mitigation credits for future disturbances of the Red Cliffs Desert Reserve, including utility disturbances and the construction of the Northern Transportation Corridor identified in section 5.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H9B2A44BA24034063A8CC87A950A449C1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Mitigation credits in renewed take permit</header><text>In the permit extended under subsection (a), the Secretary shall credit Washington County as follows:</text>
 <paragraph id="H52D3A31AAEDF42FFA66A62943A2E7048"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Washington County shall receive mitigation credit for the tortoises protected on non-Federal lands in Zone 6; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H93057F673CB6420C855061D11903AA58"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Washington County shall receive mitigation credit, in yearly installments, for those tortoises successfully translocated and surviving, based on survivorship and juvenile recruitment estimates as determined by the United States Fish and Wildlife Service.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HACCFCF11ECAF4717ADA6177A76A09776"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Adoption of amendment</header><text>The Secretary shall adopt the amendment to the St. George Field Office Resource Management Plan within one year after receipt of Washington County’s proposal to amend and renew the Habitat Conservation Plan including the Red Cliffs Desert Reserve, Zone 6.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H86FCEFAF77AA46E39E1BF720BB060177"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Habitat conservation plan not otherwise affected</header><text>Except as provided in this section, nothing in this Act otherwise limits, alters, modifies, or amends the Desert Tortoise Habitat Conservation Plan, Washington County, Utah.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H433488CF368B4CEC89E5F74980322EA0"><enum>4.</enum><header>Adjustment to resource management plans and conservation areas</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall amend the resource management plans for the Beaver Dam Wash National Conservation Area, the Red Cliffs National Conservation Area, and the amendment to the St. George Field Office Resource Management Plan—</text>
 <paragraph id="HD4BC084008544E65BD99CDC46A15974A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in accordance with section 202(c)(9) of the Federal Land Policy and Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1712">43 U.S.C. 1712(c)(9)</external-xref>);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6E9E21C32B4945DE81A8EAA417A9EE01"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in coordination and cooperation with units of local government in the State of Utah including Washington County, St. George City, and other political subdivisions, including municipalities of the State of Utah within the geographical boundaries of Washington County with authority over local planning and zoning, and the Washington County Water Conservancy District; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4491587729A44E2DA41F8F07CDE1DECD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>consistent with the provisions of this Act.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="HA1C38D0CF0B3490AB7E927C624D825C8"><enum>5.</enum><header>Red Cliffs National Conservation Area</header> <subsection id="HAA8F1873F523475783626DF8F9C0F0E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Boundaries and public access</header> <paragraph id="H65CDAE17219F44D2AAC724B534AD6E28"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Red Cliffs National Conservation Area shall consist of approximately 45,000 acres of public and non-Federal land in Washington County, Utah, identified on the Red Cliffs National Conservation Area Management Map dated February 23, 2018.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H61F0B72133724180849FC0FDC2C45096"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability of map</header><text>An updated map and legal description of the Red Cliffs National Conservation Area shall be on file and available for public inspection in the appropriate offices of the Bureau of Land Management.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE0B57059A731415E98BB2E3D3EDC2A7D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Preservation of Existing Utility Corridor</header><text>The Secretary shall recognize on federally managed lands a 150-foot-wide transportation utility corridor in each direction from the centerline of SR 18 through the Red Cliffs National Conservation Area.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE29A68D1819B4097976AE0497F02034D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Utility development protocols for habitat conservation plan</header><text>The Secretary shall adhere to the Utility Development Protocols dated August 1, 2006, as amended, within the Red Cliffs National Conservation Area and/or Incidental Take Area as the suitable mechanism for new and existing utility management within the Red Cliffs National Conservation Area.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE326C1DCBB7F4EDDA16AC8C8CD1F1F8C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Water rights associated with acquired land and interests for red cliffs national conservation area</header><text>The Secretary may not acquire any water rights in the Red Cliffs National Conservation Area or any water rights related to any land or interest in land in the Red Cliffs National Conservation Area.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H8D318285C0CF4300B7CF3AD88EC3EB44"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Northern transportation and utility corridor</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior shall grant to the State of Utah or to one or more units of local government a 300 foot wide right-of-way for the northern transportation and utility route pursuant to section 1977(b)(2)(A) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/11">Public Law 111–11</external-xref> identified on the Red Cliffs National Conservation Act Management Map dated February 23, 2018.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H5E65CA5BED79455EA2016050B839BF1D"><enum>6.</enum><header>Beaver Dam Wash National Conservation Area</header>
 <subsection id="HFEAF3E84963943898700BE86225B24B1"><enum>(a)</enum><text>Preservation of Existing Utility Corridor—The Secretary shall recognize on federally managed lands a 150-foot-wide transportation and utility corridor in each direction from the centerline of old US 91 through the Beaver Dam Wash National Conservation Area.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H2E6F247023AB49FFA4EE4E972E4A8F15"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Water rights associated with acquired land and interests for beaver dam wash national conservation
 area</header><text>The Secretary may not acquire any water rights in the Beaver Dam Wash National Conservation Area or any water rights related to any land or interest in land in the Beaver Dam Wash National Conservation Area.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H749F2AC290E140BC80E4894C951E2D31"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Utility development protocols</header><text>The Secretary shall adopt utility development protocols for the construction, operation, maintenance, and replacement of utilities within the Beaver Dam Wash National Conservation Area that are no more restrictive than the Red Cliffs Desert Reserve Utility Development Protocols dated August 1, 2006, as amended. The Beaver Dam Wash Utility Development Protocols shall comply with the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321</external-xref> et seq.), including the identification and consideration of potential impacts to fish and wildlife resources and habitat.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H63BCEF2A9D934FE0AEFE37228697BB64"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Preservation of Existing Utilities and Grazing Permits</header><text>Access to utilities and grazing permits and maintenance of utilities that are located in Beaver Dam National Wash National Conservation Area, shall be preserved.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


