<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB7478F4779104EFB8201EB03F220211F" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5291 IH: Offshore Wind Jobs and Opportunity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5291</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180314">March 14, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000465">Ms. Tsongas</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish an offshore wind career training grant program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H98BBA17EFF53484982946B3D8D3042A5" style="OLC">
 <section id="H80AFC53A406C4F389751DFEAD3F598B3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Offshore Wind Jobs and Opportunity Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H2A044C3EE3414060A1833102E15A5202" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Offshore Wind Career Training Grant Program</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1331">43 U.S.C. 1331</external-xref> et seq.) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCED51289F5EF49349E9BFC8223103D62" style="OLC">
				<section id="HE9802E5850C04975BA6FEAE028391571"><enum>33.</enum><header>Offshore Wind Career Training Grant Program</header>
 <subsection id="H6F63302CF1884E178E61369165C325E9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning 360 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary may award offshore wind career training grants to eligible entities for the purpose of developing, offering, or improving educational or career training programs that provide individuals in such programs skills that are useful for employment in the offshore wind industry.</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="HDF291E90A0B347978499498883A0FD91"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Allocation of grants</header>
 <paragraph id="H0907D7E0688641D19A8370A8C6395489"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Limitation on grant quantity and size</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity may not be awarded—</text> <subparagraph id="H016186E6AD8F41B39D67183A6C83463C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>more than one grant under this section for which the eligible entity is the lead applicant; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB11C3D79B5824A30B845C24B878D40A0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a grant under this section in excess of $1,000,000.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D6FE679C05B454A8B3C66AEB3B7DE06"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Allocation to community colleges</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less than 25 percent of the total amount awarded under this section for a fiscal year shall be awarded to eligible entities that are community colleges.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC97FD8996E2B40B88A5215C65F911C08"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Partnerships</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity seeking to receive a grant under this section may partner with one or more of the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HEC035BD609C24E8C82AE51D0700C5E98"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Another eligible entity (including an eligible entity that is a community college).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE7291A053CA24EE0BC2A445910654FB2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A State or local government.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB94C2E46714D4B209CF9EBEF3D298A86"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A nonprofit organization.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC79445532EA84D839B9A2721BAB49927"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of grant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity may use a grant awarded under this section for the following activities:</text>
 <paragraph id="H2F9AD402D68D4CF28ACA7859D5AD55D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Occupational skills training, including curriculum development, on-the-job training, and classroom training.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H37BDB3866F5A4B15BD82E456097F4F63"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Safety and health training.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9232CE80B7D94E89BF8AB9A2AC04D73E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The provision of basic skills, English as a second language, and job readiness training.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5886EFD4002F4B1CBBD65244E482C827"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Individual referral and tuition assistance for a community college training program or any training program leading to an industry-recognized certificate.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9C5367911D814028B955C344D3AF15D5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Internship programs in a field related to offshore wind energy.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HC2B03693BDAB4E48868C937678580637"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Customized training in conjunction with an existing registered apprenticeship program or labor-management partnership.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8A41DE464F5E4EEB83034235B6998192"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Incumbent worker and career ladder training and skill upgrading and retraining.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H03D36CA8AB9A4B90A089054B26E84698"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The implementation of transitional jobs strategies.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9B2B041EB9BB4D5983826744256E6009"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Curriculum development at the undergraduate and postgraduate levels.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H50F689CD958D43F5AF8363FEA5C05B78"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Development and support of offshore wind energy major, minor, or certificate programs.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF102A021013B46838A2A35D365305EE4"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Such other activities, as determined by the Secretary, to meet the purposes of this section.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9CACA8B74F584AD5B91A53711B6DEB70"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grant proposals</header> <paragraph id="H6FAA2E83EC854826816AF6FB9CE54C2D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Submission procedure for grant proposals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity seeking to receive a grant under this section shall submit a grant proposal to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBEAB9353396D40EDA6F7259E6D18305E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Content of grant proposals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A grant proposal submitted to the Secretary under this section shall include a detailed description of—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H98C6AF333F0846B48717E43FD95B5567"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the specific project for which the grant proposal is submitted, including the manner in which the grant will be used to develop, offer, or improve an educational or career training program that will provide individuals in such program skills that are useful for employment in the offshore wind industry;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C162358648648BC8A82867A03831B95"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any previous experience of the eligible entity in providing such educational or career training programs; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4F3F1A6BF06E4B72976DC35738A89ED7"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which such project will meet the educational or career training needs identified under subsection (i).</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H725F397AEA2D45039EB18AC0A27FC279"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Criteria for award of grants</header>
 <paragraph id="HDCAD4E0A86034CD38208D63307FF6714"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to appropriations, the Secretary shall award grants under this section based on an evaluation of—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H09D2359DA8804F6F8FF8AC7FBCA5B84F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the merits of the grant proposal;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA8437336FD7466D90421D8024F33B0D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the likely employment opportunities available to individuals who complete the educational or career training program that the eligible entity proposes to develop, offer, or improve;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H57ECA2D4DE47403EBD31FD2A1CD9A98A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>prior demand for such educational or career training programs in the community served by the eligible entity; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBACA93211B50421E9F66E00812025312"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the availability and capacity of existing educational or career training programs in the community to meet future demand for such programs.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FF7FF1BC1D6439281094473BAC8B77C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>Priority in awarding grants under this section shall be given to eligible entities that—</text> <subparagraph id="HA14F90355DAF4597BD228789D42D6CA6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are located in an economically distressed area;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4389D8D5DBCD473DAC8B4740ED6DECF2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">focus on individuals who are—</text> <clause id="HCC2CB03374CA4CBAB83D3F3E9EA9B616"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">displaced workers (particularly workers displaced from the offshore oil and gas, onshore fossil fuel, nuclear energy, or fishing industries);</text>
 </clause><clause id="H160AA99DE8204E5E94E8B77436984518"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">veterans, members of the reserve components of the Armed Forces, or former members of such reserve components;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H0903DA1B6344456ABEA7B9BBB6F00376"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>unemployed;</text> </clause><clause id="HE0F7FFA426F6464BAA25D9EE5BDF42B0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">seeking employment pathways out of poverty and into economic self-sufficiency;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC199CB8F7FD74BF58DB85881C5315C7F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>at-risk youth; or</text> </clause><clause id="H76D5F77B1A184366951C26D576EC6810"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">formerly incarcerated, ad­ju­di­ca­ted, nonviolent offenders; or</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H29749DE497BD4D01A16D8D60A0579091"><enum>(C)</enum><text>with respect to eligible entities that are institutions of higher education, have a high percentage of low-income or minority students.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H5F7ECD1CF5AB41AFA1ACFB8398C740D5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Geographic distribution</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, to the extent practicable, award grants under this section in a manner that provides for a reasonable geographic distribution, except that the Secretary shall not be required to award grants equally among different regions of the United States.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC0765EF8F34446E68BC2D687FB484D85"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Matching requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A grant awarded under this section may not be used to satisfy any non-Federal funds matching requirement under any other provision of law.</text>
					</subsection><subsection id="HA1085F7F090C471099B0A115A41C8FB3"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Grantee data collection</header>
 <paragraph id="H8FC1959727F4497AB2AE5167F7555DE8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A grantee, with respect to the educational or career training program for which the grantee received a grant under this section, shall collect and report to the Secretary on an annual basis the following:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H7880D564C3FF4D74BE1E6987ADEF8C8A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of participants in the educational or career training program.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45E51F40F07641078D36899A2C906EB6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The services received by such participants, including a description of training, education, and supportive services.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H198FD0B05CDF4484A9A39C54656C8BD4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The amount spent by the grantee per participant.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9ACFD6AC4E8C44FB950B54B3C36E7C09"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The rate of job placement of participants in the offshore wind industry or related fields.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H932C15F5C0054701A373BC295D45C207"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The rate of employment retention—</text> <clause id="H38CC1A9AEC3246BDAC04BC953A6C461F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the eligible entity is not an institution of higher education, 1 year after completion of the educational or career training program; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H0C74397A84CC423985841D8D5464CB47"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the eligible entity is an institution of higher education, 1 year after completion of the educational or career training program or 1 year after the participant is no longer enrolled in such institution of higher education, whichever is later.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H66B8AE067EFC4C3EAE946E6EF7CA7F46"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assistance from Secretary</header><text>The Secretary shall assist grantees in the collection of data under this subsection by making available, where practicable, low-cost means of tracking the labor market outcomes of participants and by providing standardized reporting forms, where appropriate.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1A8107CF67B44DECA73F27EA6792C374"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Identification of educational and career training needs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary, in consultation with the offshore wind industry, eligible entities, including eligible entities that are community colleges, State and local governments, labor organizations, and nonprofit organizations, shall identify the educational and career training needs of such industry, including needs related to manufacturing, operation, and maintenance activities relevant to the offshore wind industry.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5CE415091733496FA1A7D7677286F70C"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Guidelines</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 240 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="HB9BD489D67A940119AB457A341E6AF99"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promulgate guidelines for the submission of grant proposals under this section, including a list of the educational and career training needs identified under subsection (i); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8BC30B5D74814C268045106BC8ED08C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>publish and maintain such guidelines on a public website of the Secretary.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H42FE47CBD8594E4DA4ABFDD1D7D7EA54"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Reporting requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this section, and every 2 years thereafter, the Secretary shall submit a report to the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate on the grant program established by this section. The report shall include a description of the grantees and the activities for which grantees used a grant awarded under this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H46608BAFF82443258D4BFC854E291FA3"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated for purposes of this section $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2018 through 2021.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H91B594741C614EF59C50E9A95D2B2476"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HED8DCF8B40B64A3C8DA0F0EDFF245F32"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Community college</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>community college</quote> has the meaning given the term <quote>junior or community college</quote> in section 312(f) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1058">20 U.S.C. 1058(f)</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7D26C380D8D645D794AAE6B3E350E76A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>eligible entity</quote> means an entity that is—</text> <subparagraph id="H82387D4C7869478F8EF5D6F5D55FF42C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an institution of higher education, as such term is defined in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>)); or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74938215FF9147C6A1A50D55B5663020"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a labor organization.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB3AD0AB76A74EB5ABC57F77D26E1155"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Grantee</header><text>The term <quote>grantee</quote> means an eligible entity that has received a grant under this section.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBBAC25B1C0FB4197BED20EE4DA6D5729"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Lead applicant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>lead applicant</quote> means the eligible entity that is primarily responsible for the preparation, conduct, and administration of the project for which the grant was awarded.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA9BD771BB4CC473790177395A94E9955"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of the Interior, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, the Secretary of Education, and the Secretary of Labor.</text>
						</paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


