<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC59B3F56CAC14BAA83F3AABB258E654B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4858 IH: Clearing Local Impediments Makes Broadband Open to New Competition and Enhancements</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4858</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180119">January 19, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="M001180">Mr. McKinley</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To clarify section 224 of the Communications Act of 1934 as not limiting the ability of a State to adopt a one touch make ready policy for pole attachments, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD9BA9E0521524C8D845D99DA0AB04D09" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H178F4BC11AD640438C8612FE374553B2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Clearing Local Impediments Makes Broadband Open to New Competition and Enhancements</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CLIMB ONCE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD6C2F406A54E4C6AAC2E3D28F6E070F4"><enum>2.</enum><header>State adoption of one touch make ready policy for pole attachments</header> <subsection id="HD41D85E0880941C583BFEFF563A44F28"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>Nothing in section 224 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/224">47 U.S.C. 224</external-xref>) or the implementing rules of the Federal Communications Commission shall be construed to limit the ability of a State to adopt a one touch make ready policy with respect to pole attachments.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1FB0F74A3B2A47B5A1F44176C70360CD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Development of model policy</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commission shall publish recommendations on best practices, including a model policy, relating to the implementation of a one touch make ready policy by a State.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1FE8C203D793424A8C8DD3995F331E95"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text> In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H04CED4568A7748F2885669FED30010DA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Commission</quote> means the Federal Communications Commission.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="HC936BC2A72A943969D45A1D3ACA5E35B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>One touch make ready policy</header><text>The term <term>one touch make ready policy</term> means, with respect to the addition or modification of a pole attachment, regulations relating to the activity undertaken in order to prepare the pole, duct, conduit, or right-of-way for the addition of a new attachment including the ability of an attacher to perform all make ready work in a single trip to the pole and a requirement of the designation by a pole owner or utility of a list of at least two approved contractors for each pole, duct, conduit, or right-of-way to perform all such activity.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2446D59BAE9541AAAD4A8A1A58F6C1BE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Pole attachment; State; utility</header><text>The terms <term>pole attachment</term>, <term>State</term>, and <term>utility</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 224(a) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/224">47 U.S.C. 224(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill> 

