<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H0D037F090AB2494C8C71DBBA9F097CED" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5724 IH: Restoring Community Oversight of Sober Living Homes Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5724</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180509">May 9, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000409">Mr. Rohrabacher</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Fair Housing Act to clarify the applicability of that Act to recovery facilities, and
			 for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HCAC930022674490BB9FEC68DE4AB1D81" style="OLC">
 <section id="HF9DE4D7571544DCCB19D3CD0CFA6A080" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Restoring Community Oversight of Sober Living Homes Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H2D2BC32064AB4D1AB52E483E233481BF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Zoning and licensing of recovery facilities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 807 of the Fair Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3607">42 U.S.C. 3607</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF3E3804AD4D8488ABE900EC2FB359529" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="HF2B727C6FF314B0884955BD09A939B6A"><enum>(c)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this title or any other Federal law relating to protections for those with disabilities prohibits any State or local government from implementing laws, regulations, or ordinances that apply specifically to recovery facilities located in residentially zoned areas, including a law, regulation, or ordinance which prohibits recovery facilities in residentially zoned areas.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </section><section id="HD342365BCD3A4A81B4E1689EF6A67050"><enum>3.</enum><header>Fair Housing Act definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 802 of the Fair Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3602">42 U.S.C. 3602</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H0634EA58852B44649D23BC7E2324D34A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>, except that such term does not include any building, structure, or portion thereof that is located in a residentially zoned area and is used as a recovery facility</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H5C6592F5510A4CE0B9C022084B4062BF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H478DCA1EF2C9406A9718434005B70042" style="OLC"> <subsection commented="no" id="HD0614107674E42BF956C3951497D1B30"><enum>(p)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><quote>Recovery facility</quote> means a building, structure, or portion thereof that is occupied by a person who is handicapped due to drug addiction or alcoholism, and for which a condition of such occupancy of such building, structure, or portion thereof is that it remains free of controlled substances and alcohol.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="H95A8638A310C4BF8885945974540F8BA"><enum>4.</enum><header>Requirements for recovery facilities as a condition for certain Federal funding</header>
 <subsection id="H82A41562B21D402ABE97334D1832B3B8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A recovery facility in a residential zone may not receive direct or indirect payments or reimbursements or other remunerations from a Federal health care program unless—</text>
 <paragraph id="HCA302FB8B74D45958081B118ADE3B6C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the recovery facility is in compliance with State and local laws, regulations, or ordinances that apply within the zone where the recovery facility is located; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HACA3FCC871BC419BA3CD3D0286054385"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the local government with jurisdiction over the zone in which the recovery facility is located certifies to the Secretary of Health and Human Services that the recovery facility is in compliance with State and local laws, regulations, or ordinances that apply within the zone where the recovery facility is located.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF6F468AC90CF4869AB085B567279A624"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HC66EEFBBD16D4E87BE501FC47567F0F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal health care program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Federal health care program</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1128B(f) of the Social Security Act (42 U.S.C. 1320a7b(f)).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAA52F67BDE93413282A6715085445AE9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Recovery facility</header><text>The term <term>recovery facility</term> has the meaning given such term in section 802 of the Fair Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3602">42 U.S.C. 3602</external-xref>), as amended by section 3.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="HA8A8178B43F246F181C91352810FC9B1"><enum>5.</enum><header>Removing substance use disorder services as an essential health benefit</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1302(b)(1)(E) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18022">42 U.S.C. 18022(b)(1)(E)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and substance use disorder</quote>.</text>
 </section><section id="H39977F109EC54C178AF11BB357FBD252"><enum>6.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act, and the amendments made by this Act, shall take effect on the date that is 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


