<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H8AA200CA52D147AFB0BCA8BE9CC86A67" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5031 IH: To direct the Secretary of Energy to provide for prize competitions relating to climate and energy, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5031</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180215">February 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000563">Mr. Lipinski</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000464">Mr. Faso</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001111">Mr. Crist</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001107">Mr. Curbelo of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001202">Mrs. Murphy of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000435">Ms. Ros-Lehtinen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Energy to provide for prize competitions relating to climate and energy,
			 and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H7806B40D1ADC4E8089B3521576BA24D5" style="OLC">
 <section id="H856C0D07205D46F1A20C8D87C42662AD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Challenges &amp; Prizes for Climate Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF6792644B97246D3B3B6473F0BE39A8B" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Climate Solutions Challenges</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H95AFA6AA3A764673B742D729482BBD2E"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Energy shall establish a program to be known as <quote>Climate Solutions Challenges</quote> for carrying out prize competitions described under subsection (d) pursuant to section 24 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3719">15 U.S.C. 3719</external-xref>) relating to the climate and energy.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HDF7A489CBC4443A9B345081A461D9717"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prize committees</header>
 <paragraph id="H3D46543684D14F399D0662AA8368A743"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall assemble a prize committee with respect to each prize competition that shall define the scope and detail of, and provide the requirements for, the prize competitions under this section. Such committee shall be composed of—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD6F7B2871AAB42F59FABBBF5E0E0123E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>members from the Federal agency, department, or office that most appropriately corresponds with the topic of the prize competition, including—</text>
 <clause id="HE36D95A5ECC5429CB94320FC53F315DC"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to a prize competition under subsection (c)(4), the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration and the Director of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H9BE3216059CC49C898827FD446A084C3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to a prize competition under subsection (c)(5), the Director of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration and the Director of the National Technical Information Service; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B098ADD95CB4C579CFE61D974E479D7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>representatives of any other entities, as determined appropriate by the Secretary, including State and local governments and the private sector.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B7F32B11753449992D6D82A49729B13"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Defining topic areas</header><text>The prize committee may modify and define the scope of the prize areas described under subsection (c), so long as such modification is in accordance with descriptions in such subsection.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE6937499A9C04B05AE46E5BC259FD962"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Incentive for prize competition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The prize committee for each prize competition shall determine the incentive for the prize competition. In determining the incentive, the committee shall consider—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H8E6CD9AF2D1B485FBF56B43BCAFB5EAA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a cash prize;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA4A26A3EBC144EBADABC2B10D650155"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">access to Government facilities, such as through a lab-embedded entrepreneurship program of the Department of Energy, a cooperative research and development agreement, or other method;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA420F7464623471DA48B3B9C0D7002D5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>advance market commitments for technologies of use or promise to the Federal Government; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E8F3001370F4374A3D7A3CC88AC7AF1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other incentive provided for by law.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H29DDFEDACCEF46359E290CB584D73F8F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Judging criteria</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The prize committee for each prize competition shall establish judging criteria for the competition that shall include, at a minimum—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF50A86118B554CEFAA3BB2D9B72351F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">potential for the solution to become a commercial product or service or advance knowledge to further the public good;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22F231D05E2240D49061C79B193EED32"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consideration of how likely the solution is to lead to subsequent research, development, or manufacturing in the United States;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D14495CA5CB460C92F3F085FB4C3A0E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the degree to which the solution will lower the climate footprint of the United States; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1450FA43722544A09CA208A76B11B98A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the degree to which the solution will lower the global climate footprint.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H721C9023E24F411C9EA91CE22668037B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Consideration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out this section, the committee shall take into consideration the best practices provided for in the challenges and prizes toolkit made publicly available on December 15, 2016, by the General Services Administration.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8226333192094B5FB10405119D963935"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Definition of advance market commitment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <quote>advance market commitment</quote> means a commitment by the Federal Government to purchase a set number of units of a product from a private sector entity at an agreed-upon price, assuming pre-specified criteria are met.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE912C4F9388342F8B774CA2C821D89FE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prize competitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program, the Secretary shall provide for prize competitions, including at least one prize competition on each of the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H97BD43DA70944DC9B08E02484DAE829B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Carbon capture and beneficial use</header><text>Solutions to capture carbon directly from the atmosphere or from sources that would otherwise be emitted to the atmosphere, and convert it to a beneficial use that does not result in near-term re-release into the atmosphere, unless such re-release offsets the emission of additional carbon into the atmosphere, such that the net effect of the solution is to reduce the overall amount of carbon being emitted to the atmosphere.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H60CEA6EDA853454BB74BC9E63949662D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Energy efficiency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Solutions to achieve transformative increases in energy efficiency, defined as an increase in energy efficiency of 2 times or more over commonly-available technology without a proportional increase in cost.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA50907E26304444EA72371C6702C4E12"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Energy storage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Solutions to achieve implementation or grid integration of advanced energy storage technology.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H900C9B58979242F78213880B057FD07B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Climate resiliency</header><text>Solutions to provide new or improved approaches to mitigating or adapting to the effects of climate change (such as floods, drought, excessive heat and cold, and severe weather) in rural or urban areas.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC3E7568BF4364D68BEEBC88130A8FDEE"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Data analytics</header><text>Solutions to—</text> <subparagraph id="H84822F4101584866B213ECAB4B5ECB37"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide new or improved tools that use data to better model Earth’s climate at a global, regional, or local scale;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA723926C03A40EF9928BACF77261E71"><enum>(B)</enum><text>forecast climate-related phenomena (such as weather, seasonal trends, oceanic and atmospheric circulation); or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90DECB8C4BFD4C87B4BCC7A18726609D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide actionable information on the climate and related phenomena to government, industry, and members of the public.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H59FC7E5A8D6844E8B2B06BC588E4624E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Acceptance of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to such sums as may be appropriated or otherwise made available to the Secretary to award prizes under this section, the Secretary may accept funds from other Federal agencies, private sector entities, and State and local governments to award prizes under this section. The Secretary may not give any special consideration relating to the selection of awards under the prize competition to any private sector entity or individual in return for a donation to the Secretary or prize committee.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H010A1F0E6CE248038B910512DC33AC31"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 24(g)(3) of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3719">15 U.S.C. 3719(g)(3)</external-xref>), for a group to be eligible for an award under this section, at least one member of such group shall be a citizen or permanent resident of the United States.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5BB8519793B3419C9C621CEA90B04FA3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Completion of prize competitions</header><text>The prize competitions carried out under this section shall be completed not later than the date that is 5 years after the program is established under subsection (a).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5A1645E0279341FC8128AB320BDCEBBC"><enum>(g)</enum><header>GAO report</header><text>Not later than the date of completion under subsection (f), the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report on the impact and the effectiveness of the program carried out under this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H2AADEF59704146B1AA14EE678F359316"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $10,000,000 to carry out this Act, to remain available until expended.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


