<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HFBDB18B055D94F30B13E6267F5552CDA" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5075 IH: Ashanti Alert Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5075</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180220">February 20, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000477">Mr. Taylor</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001084">Mr. Cicilline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S000583">Mr. Smith of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To encourage, enhance, and integrate Ashanti Alert plans throughout the United States, and for
			 other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H1C18966E3CB840FB9BCB57DD232420AF" style="OLC">
 <section id="HAD8F9DD60BA54A9EB4EC5B8EB2478887" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ashanti Alert Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HABCCD153A13B4D08B3F34358AE95AD26"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
 <paragraph id="H1410140AB9044662B25560BD7B43D2FE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Missing adult</header><text>The term <term>missing adult</term> means an individual who—</text> <subparagraph id="H8303938CA60B4914A6AD493BDC5537E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is reported to, or identified by, a law enforcement agency as a missing person; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51B7FB7F24B0496A88413158A6CDA4E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>meets the requirements to be designated as a missing adult, as determined by the State in which the individual is reported or identified as a missing person.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C23D6EE3B694F75BC54B243E93E61D4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the 50 States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCBBE8F12F68849D7AE92F4069AE13AE3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Ashanti Alert</header><text>The term <term>Ashanti Alert</term> means an alert issued through the Ashanti Alert communications network, related to a missing adult.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H604E1774D4354D38A78709E998FEC3B8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Ashanti alert communications network</header>
 <subsection id="H4B898EFAAFDB4E3A9945D7162AD1F417"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall, subject to the availability of appropriations, establish a national communications network, to be known as the Ashanti Alert communications network, within the Department of Justice to provide assistance to regional and local search efforts for missing adults through the initiation, facilitation, and promotion of local elements of the network (referred to in this Act as <quote>Ashanti Alert plans</quote>), in coordination with States, units of local government, law enforcement agencies, and other concerned entities with expertise in providing services to adults.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5678CBE5F1DC45A58DE4E6BE9247699B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination with amber alert network</header><text>In establishing the Ashanti Alert communications network under subsection (a), the Attorney General shall ensure that, when feasible, the Ashanti Alert communications network is able to operate in coordination with the AMBER Alert communications network, established under subtitle A of title III of the PROTECT Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5791">42 U.S.C. 5791</external-xref> et seq.), to maximize the efficiency of both networks.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H37F62E215F074CD7B4B217D75B8084DE"><enum>4.</enum><header>Ashanti alert coordinator</header>
 <subsection id="HBF52878640E34EEF9D18B5FD83C46AD3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National coordinator within department of justice</header><text>The Attorney General shall designate an individual of the Department of Justice to act as the national coordinator of the Ashanti Alert communications network. The individual so designated shall be known as the Ashanti Alert Coordinator of the Department of Justice (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Coordinator</quote>).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H72203AD5BC374C07BD425782B08F96AD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties of the coordinator</header><text>In acting as the national coordinator of the Ashanti Alert communications network, the Coordinator shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H39C16C8807C3436A9E7D3EBA2AC4B29E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>work with States to encourage the development of additional Ashanti Alert plans in the network;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H8BAFDB7B5E754526B16F43A3679136E2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish voluntary guidelines for States to use in developing Ashanti Alert plans that will promote compatible and integrated Ashanti Alert plans throughout the United States, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H38D68127F6DF4ECF8FCC7CA13FCC73C5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a list of the resources necessary to establish an Ashanti Alert plan;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB820D541D1424544AA9000424021DB02"><enum>(B)</enum><text>criteria for evaluating whether a situation warrants issuing an Ashanti Alert, taking into consideration the need for the use of such Alerts to be limited in scope because the effectiveness of the Ashanti Alert communications network may be affected by overuse, including criteria to determine—</text>
 <clause id="H0AD1FC9499EA492098D44FE6C4EF19F4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>whether the mental capacity of an adult who is missing, and the circumstances of his or her disappearance, warrant the issuance of an Ashanti Alert; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB8E1EC1E213E406E98DCF53C27C42BB0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whether the individual who reports that an adult is missing is an appropriate and credible source on which to base the issuance of an Ashanti Alert;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC522308BB47424E892396703DACDFC4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of the appropriate uses of the Ashanti Alert name to readily identify the nature of search efforts for missing adults; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H531DBB66CF354D4795209E80F72531BC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>recommendations on how to protect the privacy, dignity, independence, and autonomy of any missing adult who may be the subject of an Ashanti Alert;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A3E6C7E88EE4F9AB7A989EF7FCF509C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>develop proposed protocols for efforts to recover missing adults and to reduce the number of adults who are reported missing, including protocols for procedures that are needed from the time of initial notification of a law enforcement agency that the adult is missing through the time of the return of the adult to family, guardian, or domicile, as appropriate, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H577395F155124820AF9FF8912E8EDD97"><enum>(A)</enum><text>public safety communications protocol;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H98DEEFFB74C24E07A68EE79C13FE5A60"><enum>(B)</enum><text>case management protocol;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54994BD1727D411286B2951AFA69C30B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>command center operations;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA18C86B3E1C4DE799365282F491C762"><enum>(D)</enum><text>reunification protocol; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50803545A21B4476A0E0E2E61E999109"><enum>(E)</enum><text>incident review, evaluation, debriefing, and public information procedures;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H537796F5A906498480B83AE50F1DAB5E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>work with States to ensure appropriate regional coordination of various elements of the network;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4E5FC7A413D747FF80C224259C1C0463"><enum>(5)</enum><text>establish an advisory group to assist States, units of local government, law enforcement agencies, and other entities involved in the Ashanti Alert communications network with initiating, facilitating, and promoting Ashanti Alert plans, which shall include—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HA2AF2303FAA14855993F1B10F0EBB5A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable, representation from the various geographic regions of the United States; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14A91E5BF04E46D39CAEEE4F242A0EC8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>members who are—</text> <clause id="H103BC76FA17447D59E4A5211F39B5FC4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>representatives of adult citizen advocacy groups, law enforcement agencies, and public safety communications;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H7AA6BC2E7057421D8671EA0D312520CB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>broadcasters, first responders, dispatchers, and radio station personnel; and</text> </clause><clause id="HF439F9B45E084AD78B537B0AAD3BEF38"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>representatives of any other individuals or organizations that the Coordinator determines are necessary to the success of the Ashanti Alert communications network; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0DDE9F713DCB4BAB994540B918A3DDE2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>act as the nationwide point of contact for—</text> <subparagraph id="H0DED0DE294054423A2F01E369391D4F6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the development of the network; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF74766EDB7804EB8B9CA0FB65C80B922"><enum>(B)</enum><text>regional coordination of alerts for missing adults through the network.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDCDDB4F7C5CC410589DA105BE2A93BAD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination</header> <paragraph id="H134B2DD0084C45DF98805D7A3C61A317"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coordination with other agencies</header><text>The Coordinator shall coordinate and consult with the Secretary of Transportation, the Federal Communications Commission, the Assistant Secretary for Aging of the Department of Health and Human Services, and other appropriate offices of the Department of Justice in carrying out activities under this Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H312FC82AF8444A368D9153B54F2135A5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State and local coordination</header><text>The Coordinator shall consult with local broadcasters and State and local law enforcement agencies in establishing minimum standards under section 5 and in carrying out other activities under this Act, as appropriate.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H59CD5D4626B0435F8361048676397E58"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Coordinator shall submit to Congress a report on the activities of the Coordinator and the effectiveness and status of the Ashanti Alert plans of each State that has established or is in the process of establishing such a plan. Each such report shall include—</text>
 <paragraph id="H043E319DA03A46C38977DD55BA1A7A71"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a list of States that have established Ashanti Alert plans;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE647975691484B6493088E6CBC5AF187"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a list of States that are in the process of establishing Ashanti Alert plans;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA432300800234B889CED649EFD02979A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for each State that has established such a plan, to the extent the data is available—</text> <subparagraph id="H5FD90AEE1DB6453686A6BB5955CBC9C9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of Ashanti Alerts issued;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BFE7BF1096C45B3B2F0B330F32D3F50"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of individuals located successfully;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5E3B3C553FC434A9883AC57DD4A37A8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the average period of time between the issuance of an Ashanti Alert and the location of the individual for whom such Alert was issued;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1191229C66D34ACC88D89C01412ACEB4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the State agency or authority issuing Ashanti Alerts, and the process by which Ashanti Alerts are disseminated;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6576848F10FB489A89260EFD3F07A88D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the cost of establishing and operating such a plan;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C9E5B195BE14E21B87EDB33511F03AC"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the criteria used by the State to determine whether to issue an Ashanti Alert; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32401E14D36446ACA250FCF693D180ED"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the extent to which missing individuals for whom Ashanti Alerts were issued crossed State lines;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5926292E13A4C2C8DB0AF3C8EB24660"><enum>(4)</enum><text>actions States have taken to protect the privacy and dignity of the individuals for whom Ashanti Alerts are issued;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H18A9303090C44DD49E1F344A53D4ABBE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>ways that States have facilitated and improved communication about missing individuals between families, caregivers, law enforcement officials, and other authorities; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0962109DF3CB4183AF4997EC614BAAE1"><enum>(6)</enum><text>any other information the Coordinator determines to be appropriate.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE1179E25ED1541C986CF8A0C8C9954B7"><enum>5.</enum><header>Minimum standards for issuance and dissemination of alerts through Ashanti alert communications network</header> <subsection id="HB830B79B3498440EB40CFFB4F76D9EB2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of minimum standards</header><text>Subject to subsection (b), the Coordinator shall establish minimum standards for—</text>
 <paragraph id="HBB085929238440C691C2A48C6F05DAAF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the issuance of alerts through the Ashanti Alert communications network; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H63F6711847E04308AAD2C0F4A7A40A57"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the extent of the dissemination of alerts issued through the network.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H94B1810A43A940758962F4943747F46B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitations</header>
 <paragraph id="HE03FE6AFDF8C4F42B1CA8E57A53B3C33"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Voluntary participation</header><text>The minimum standards established under subsection (a) of this section, and any other guidelines and programs established under section 4, shall be adoptable on a voluntary basis only.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2765523C70584B24ADF780E605FE902C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Dissemination of information</header><text>The minimum standards shall, to the maximum extent practicable (as determined by the Coordinator in consultation with State and local law enforcement agencies), provide that appropriate information relating to the special needs of a missing adult (including health care needs) are disseminated to the appropriate law enforcement, public health, and other public officials.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H47BE82159AE6484D9C766E0C8EE9F282"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Geographic areas</header><text>The minimum standards shall, to the maximum extent practicable (as determined by the Coordinator in consultation with State and local law enforcement agencies), provide that the dissemination of an alert through the Ashanti Alert communications network be limited to the geographic areas which the missing adult could reasonably reach, considering the missing adult’s circumstances and physical and mental condition, the modes of transportation available to the missing adult, and the circumstances of the disappearance.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFD9F8815D2184BB1B38A3BFADECAAFF1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Age requirements</header><text>The minimum standards shall not include any specific age requirement for an individual to be classified as a missing adult for purposes of the Ashanti Alert communications network. Age requirements for determinations of whether an individual is a missing adult shall be determined by each State, and may vary from State to State.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAD814C54630D4AF98EB3CC95A806ADBC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Privacy and civil liberties protections</header><text>The minimum standards shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H2FD8D1AE16BB43F58E8F767AC495F1DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure that alerts issued through the Ashanti Alert communications network comply with all applicable Federal, State, and local privacy laws and regulations; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD83F397263CB462FBE75A140A8AC88FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include standards that specifically provide for the protection of the civil liberties and sensitive medical information of missing adults.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E18689D85F04C249FE8168A09567F38"><enum>(6)</enum><header>State and local voluntary coordination</header><text>In carrying out the activities under subsection (a), the Coordinator may not interfere with the current system of voluntary coordination between local broadcasters and State and local law enforcement agencies for purposes of the Ashanti Alert communications network.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC59839F3D8274EFF8D11314C84A063BD"><enum>6.</enum><header>Training and other resources</header>
 <subsection id="HD0CBA538C13845589CEC02FAD63377E1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Training and educational programs</header><text>The Coordinator shall make available to States, units of local government, law enforcement agencies, and other concerned entities that are involved in initiating, facilitating, or promoting Ashanti Alert plans, including broadcasters, first responders, dispatchers, public safety communications personnel, and radio station personnel—</text>
 <paragraph id="H071BD4A93FC5447391302338B26DDAA4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>training and educational programs related to the Ashanti Alert communications network and the capabilities, limitations, and anticipated behaviors of missing adults, which shall be updated regularly to encourage the use of new tools, technologies, and resources in Ashanti Alert plans; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8975DA77257D4A54A5FCE97208268429"><enum>(2)</enum><text>informational materials, including brochures, videos, posters, and web sites to support and supplement such training and educational programs.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H5426B2BB8D974C7693235E2A07962B6A"><enum>7.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations for the Ashanti alert communications network</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Attorney General $500,000 to carry out the Ashanti Alert communications network as authorized under this Act.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


