<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H1F146CAAE6E340B8A1AD0504E52DC9CF" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5141 IH: United States-Israel Security Assistance Authorization Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5141</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180301">March 1, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000435">Ms. Ros-Lehtinen</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="D000610">Mr. Deutch</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To make improvements to certain defense and security assistance provisions and to authorize
			 assistance for Israel, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H7A5388350D074662A9F812B4A0040CF8" style="OLC">
		<section id="H489FE2AFC7064E0C97C55DA79D5FF509" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title and table of contents</header>
 <subsection id="H22CC72183B334E9083AD646E1343ADC7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United States-Israel Security Assistance Authorization Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H059762832979449E81F7CEA27AF430C9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
				<toc container-level="legis-body-container" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration">
					<toc-entry idref="H489FE2AFC7064E0C97C55DA79D5FF509" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title and table of contents.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HE34D03367D6B4C81A56E58A6906F1400" level="section">Sec. 2. Definition.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H8F99F93187B14FB8A4B4401CE99264FE" level="title">Title I—Security Assistance for Israel</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HEBE5908645984524AD2587B1E43B3404" level="section">Sec. 101. Findings.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HAE8D04510CFA4D7B8C4A81FCE70813F8" level="section">Sec. 102. Statement of policy.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HBCAE0DCDF38C436B840CD9CC3BA05864" level="section">Sec. 103. Assistance for Israel.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HEB9009D284824A1E8209A3281A98BADD" level="section">Sec. 104. Joint assessment of quantity of precision guided munitions for use by Israel.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H6E6A85895A834B2F9FC4DA00B2DAF02C" level="section">Sec. 105. Transfer of precision guided munitions to Israel.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H242E12610F7E4AE2B9FD304214A92FC4" level="section">Sec. 106. Modification of rapid acquisition and deployment procedures.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H277C7A4444464FE78E07CF9769276793" level="section">Sec. 107. Extension of War Reserves Stockpile authority.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HF1EE874FDD894B2DAEE2749B628704E1" level="section">Sec. 108. Eligibility of Israel for the strategic trade authorization exception to certain export
			 control licensing requirements.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H93A3F48255F349C0B24BDC04C2CAB025" level="section">Sec. 109. Extension of loan guarantees to Israel.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H4603BD969D704E19B8784097A74C0279" level="title">Title II—Enhanced Cooperation Between the United States and Israel</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HD584B36CB00F449595FBC85ED381B41A" level="section">Sec. 201. United States-Israel cybersecurity cooperation.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H6C11A8F63970457180AE6FCE3A3661C4" level="section">Sec. 202. United States-Israel space cooperation.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H74BFEDA641AC49119C50309F17BDB51B" level="section">Sec. 203. United States Agency for International Development—Israel enhanced cooperation.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H13155C95D59B4936BA2CB47EAE95D139" level="section">Sec. 204. Authority to enter into a cooperative project agreement with Israel to counter unmanned
			 aerial vehicles that threaten the United States or Israel.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H2A82EE1B73D340289A380710379C5C76" level="title">Title III—Ensuring Israel’s Qualitative Military Edge</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H11E0ADAF778B4F74805269385CA25C86" level="section">Sec. 301. Improved reporting on enhancing Israel’s qualtitative military edge and security posture.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H29753BD29894458CB3435FCF33004EE7" level="section">Sec. 302. Statement of policy.</toc-entry>
				</toc>
 </subsection></section><section id="HE34D03367D6B4C81A56E58A6906F1400"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> <paragraph id="H521DDDC36F2B4D349B03719CDE84DAF6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H00690D17E55D41CA9374DA9BCB539006"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Armed Services of the Senate.</text> </paragraph></section><title id="H8F99F93187B14FB8A4B4401CE99264FE"><enum>I</enum><header>Security Assistance for Israel</header> <section id="HEBE5908645984524AD2587B1E43B3404"><enum>101.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text>
 <paragraph id="H602EB6B51EE64E07A7389C9D6EEAA7D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In April 1998, the United States designated Israel as a <quote>major non-NATO ally</quote>.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H944BD0B86FBF4F999E188DF1E9A1832B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>On August 16, 2007, the United States and Israel signed a 10-year Memorandum of Understanding on United States military assistance to Israel, the total amount of military assistance over the course of this period would equal $30 billion.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF057615AFC434FE7A1D27B6F6E3BB237"><enum>(3)</enum><text>On July 27, 2012, the United States-Israel Enhanced Security Cooperation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/112/150">Public Law 112–150</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8601">22 U.S.C. 8601</external-xref> et seq.) declared it to be the policy of the United States <quote>to help the Government of Israel preserve its qualitative military edge amid rapid and uncertain regional political transformation</quote> and <quote>provide Israel defense articles and services, to include air refueling tankers, missile defense capabilities, and specialized munitions</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1946A377B2D34A7A921ABFCC82AB86EB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>On December 19, 2014, the President signed into law the United States-Israel Strategic Partnership Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/113/296">Public Law 113–296</external-xref>) which stated the sense of Congress that Israel is a major strategic partner of the United States and declared it to be the policy of the United States <quote>to continue to provide Israel with robust security assistance, including for the procurement of the Iron Dome Missile Defense System</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H72DF67C1F1D94922874937E28D145937"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Section 1679 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/92">Public Law 114–92</external-xref>; 129 Stat. 1135) authorized funds to be appropriated for Israeli cooperative missile defense program codevelopment and coproduction, including funds to be provided to the Government of Israel to procure the David’s Sling weapon system as well as the Arrow 3 Upper Tier Interceptor Program.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFDDC5B9649FB400798BF39F9B0AAF448"><enum>(6)</enum><text>On September 13, 2016, the House of Representatives passed, by a vote of 405 to 4, House Resolution 729, expressing support for the expeditious consideration and finalization of a new, robust, and long-term Memorandum of Understanding on military assistance to Israel between the United States Government and the Government of Israel.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H18317032A9AF495EBE564844EDDA4572"><enum>(7)</enum><text>House Resolution 729 provides that the House of Representatives—</text> <subparagraph id="HBCC9C3B1406B4C18AD0B207F995D0AB7"><enum>(A)</enum><text><quote>reaffirms that Israel is a major strategic partner of the United States</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F7863FF866F4DD2AEAFEC017750AB12"><enum>(B)</enum><text><quote>reaffirms that it is the policy and law of the United States to ensure that Israel maintains its qualitative military edge and has the capacity and capability to defend itself from all threats</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9DE648112F8471D9A206CDBBA5751C2"><enum>(C)</enum><text><quote>reaffirms United States support of a robust Israeli tiered missile defense program</quote>;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H081A8BCCC3464D6DB797CEE04E342BA3"><enum>(D)</enum><text><quote>supports continued discussions between the Government of the United States and the Government of Israel for a robust and long-term Memorandum of Understanding on United States military assistance to Israel</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A25DBEDF78E48369D0013EB6E4E26CD"><enum>(E)</enum><text><quote>urges the expeditious finalization of a new Memorandum of Understanding between the Government of the United States and the Government of Israel</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3CB897D9EA9E45B6915D81995AE34221"><enum>(F)</enum><text><quote>supports a robust and long-term Memorandum of Understanding negotiated between the United States and Israel regarding military assistance which increases the amount of aid from previous agreements and significantly enhances Israel’s military capabilities</quote>.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4DE61BCDAA1C4AD3A750E24DD70B6B6D"><enum>(8)</enum><text>On September 14, 2016, the United States and Israel signed a 10-year Memorandum of Understanding reaffirming the importance of continuing annual United States military assistance to Israel and cooperative missile defense programs in a way that enhances Israel’s security and strengthens the bilateral relationship between the two countries.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5824EBC64A984B20B741B7DCE73331CD"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The 2016 Memorandum of Understanding reflected United States support of Foreign Military Financing (FMF) grant assistance to Israel over the 10-year period beginning in fiscal year 2019 and ending in fiscal year 2028. Such FMF grant assistance would equal $3.3 billion annually, totaling $33 billion.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6B776BBE850240208F155C5E743C38CE"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The 2016 Memorandum of Understanding also reflected United States support for funding for cooperative programs to develop, produce, and procure missile, rocket and projectile defense capabilities over a 10-year period beginning in fiscal year 2019 and ending in fiscal year 2028 at a level of $500 million annually, totaling $5 billion.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HAE8D04510CFA4D7B8C4A81FCE70813F8"><enum>102.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It shall be the policy of the United States to provide assistance to the Government of Israel in order to support funding for cooperative programs to develop, produce, and procure missile, rocket, projectile, and other defense capabilities to help Israel meet its security needs and to help develop and enhance United States defense capabilities.</text>
 </section><section commented="no" id="HBCAE0DCDF38C436B840CD9CC3BA05864"><enum>103.</enum><header>Assistance for Israel</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 513(c) of the Security Assistance Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/106/280">Public Law 106–280</external-xref>; 114 Stat. 856) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="HAB8F5C7983234323AA6ACD6064829BEB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>2002 and 2003</quote> and inserting <quote>2019, 2020, 2021, 2022 and 2023</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H390B7F74B204495B81C2B614B24FB355"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>equal to—</quote> and all that follows and inserting <quote>not less than $3,300,000,000</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H438A42A1A498410D9FCDD699F8B16980"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>Funds authorized</quote> and all that follows through <quote>later.</quote> and inserting <quote>Funds authorized to be available for Israel under subsection (b)(1) and paragraph (1) of this subsection for fiscal years 2019, 2020, 2021, 2022, and 2023 shall be disbursed not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of an Act making appropriations for the Department of State, foreign operations, and related programs for the respective fiscal year, or October 31 of the respective fiscal year, whichever is later.</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></section><section id="HEB9009D284824A1E8209A3281A98BADD"><enum>104.</enum><header>Joint assessment of quantity of precision guided munitions for use by Israel</header>
 <subsection id="H6940B01D6F0D4B51B4D8CEDDA369C290"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President, acting through the Secretary of Defense, is authorized to conduct a joint assessment with the Government of Israel with respect to the matters described in subsection (b).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H6CF3C8D9CE9F4B4F9A1B26646EC5B16B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The matters described in this subsection are the following:</text> <paragraph id="HDC9D2D35AEE0410C9DBD342CF7D366ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The quantity and type of precision guided munitions that are necessary for Israel to combat Hezbollah in the event of a sustained armed confrontation between Israel and Hezbollah.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE00137E83AF641C1A5823B834EDF8F7C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The quantity and type of precision guided munitions that are necessary for Israel in the event of a sustained armed confrontation with other armed groups and terrorist organizations such as Hamas.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H062CE34DB8D64409842D3E5A2E16E009"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The resources the Government of Israel can plan to dedicate to acquire such precision guided munitions.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB4FFF9B30F3F4CF7BAA2BE2DFD796798"><enum>(4)</enum><text>United States planning to assist Israel to prepare for the sustained armed confrontations described in paragraphs (1) and (2) as well as the ability of the United States to resupply Israel in the event of such confrontations described in paragraphs (1) and (2), if any.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5A2FD03646BF4687B05F522ACE60A634"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header>
 <paragraph id="H6F978E42502148CBA7BD78C6B30BD61F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 15 days after the date on which the joint assessment authorized under subsection (a) is completed, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that contains the joint assessment.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H02059303B5AE420488778F0AE8E90272"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required under paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H6E6A85895A834B2F9FC4DA00B2DAF02C"><enum>105.</enum><header>Transfer of precision guided munitions to Israel</header>
 <subsection id="HE7380797F5F64817A2B991848A7FB8A2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 514 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2321h">22 U.S.C. 2321h</external-xref>), the President is authorized to—</text>
 <paragraph id="HAE0356916BDD4133B78D04B779CFEADB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>utilize the Special Defense Acquisition Fund to transfer precision guided munitions and related defense articles and services to reserve stocks for Israel; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0225EFD659FC4DF7803D48ECABB09B7A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>transfer such quantities of precision guided munitions from reserve stocks for Israel as necessary for legitimate self-defense and is otherwise consistent with the purposes and conditions for such transfers under the Arms Export Control Act.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBC35DCDD3F6848A296D50B8BA9B909BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>Except in the case of an emergency, not later than 5 days before making a transfer under subsection (a), the President shall certify to the appropriate congressional committees that the transfer of the precision guided munitions—</text>
 <paragraph id="HC1C6EFB96B054F9694333DE74524B6C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>does not affect the ability of the United States to maintain a sufficient supply of precision guided munitions; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3AC89DB974974585BD56E4FBB2A3E6AA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>does not harm the combat readiness of the United States or the ability of the United States to meet its commitment to allies for the transfer of such munitions.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H242E12610F7E4AE2B9FD304214A92FC4"><enum>106.</enum><header>Modification of rapid acquisition and deployment procedures</header>
				<subsection id="HCDC2BE2B568E408781113D5C2458A29D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement To establish procedures</header>
 <paragraph id="H9587D8EC7B8C42A38B423FB79C2D495C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 806(a) of the Bob Stump National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/2302">10 U.S.C. 2302</external-xref> note; 116 Stat. 2607) is amended—</text>
 <subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H077DCB3E3CE141C1A6F92EB970BC5D18"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(C), by striking <quote>; and</quote> at the end;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H498A88AE4AB74FFFA9C4D146CD2E1144"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H906D12C87E344709B8C68C7B79E18E4B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBCF5938562CF4C28803CDB88D544A184" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HD5127C10A9404ED398AD851D0E3ECE55"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">urgently needed to support production of precision guided munitions—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H07225004AA0546A4A1A32B76EF95FB3A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for United States counterterrorism missions; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H520C5415EDE94439AECD5C84C55662F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to assist an ally of the United States under direct missile threat from—</text>
 <clause id="HC7706B1D6E554417B9C188D2201F9EC0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an organization the Secretary of State has designated as a foreign terrorist organization pursuant to section 219 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189</external-xref>); or</text>
 </clause><clause id="HE6A315F9EB004319B3BB7E2986467FFE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a country the government of which the Secretary of State has determined, for purposes of section 6(j) of the Export Administration Act of 1979 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4605">50 U.S.C. 4605(j)</external-xref>) (as in effect pursuant to the International Emergency Economic Powers Act), section 620A of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2371">22 U.S.C. 2371</external-xref>), section 40 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2780">22 U.S.C. 2780</external-xref>), or any other provision of law, is a government that has repeatedly provided support for acts of international terrorism.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB81E6B53387443C8BE1CB2AFE5F3CB14"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prescription of procedures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall prescribe procedures for the rapid acquisition and deployment of supplies and associated support services for purposes described in paragraph (3) of section 806(a) of the Bob Stump National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2003, as added by paragraph (1) of this subsection, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HA38E792CDDFC474DB7F581DF9CB837CD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of amounts in Special Defense Acquisition Fund</header><text>Section 114(c)(3) of title 10, United States Code, is amended by inserting at the end before the period the following: <quote>or to assist an ally of the United States that is under direct missile threat, including from a terrorist organization supported by Iran, and such threat adversely affects the safety and security of such ally</quote>.</text>
				</subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H277C7A4444464FE78E07CF9769276793"><enum>107.</enum><header>Extension of War Reserves Stockpile authority</header>
 <subsection commented="no" id="HE7A55876C11547D08CCDF1C84B7A75CA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Department of Defense Appropriations Act, 2005</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (e) of section 12001 of the Department of Defense Appropriations Act, 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/287">Public Law 108–287</external-xref>; 118 Stat. 1011), as redesignated by section 105 of this Act, is amended by striking <quote>after September 30, 2018</quote> and inserting <quote>after September 30, 2023</quote>.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H95870E5D80774DC89B7DB76EC42BB062"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Foreign Assistance Act of 1961</header><text>Section 514(b)(2)(A) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2321h">22 U.S.C. 2321h(b)(2)(A)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>2013, 2014, 2015, 2016, 2017, and 2018</quote> and inserting <quote>2018, 2019, 2020, 2021, 2022, and 2023</quote>.</text>
				</subsection></section><section id="HF1EE874FDD894B2DAEE2749B628704E1"><enum>108.</enum><header>Eligibility of Israel for the strategic trade authorization exception to certain export control
			 licensing requirements</header>
 <subsection id="H95B8EFA957EF47ACBAC33E20A4DEF653"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="H4EF35BD07A994845919DC43B8030F943"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Israel has adopted high standards in the field of export controls.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC3490E207B444C829A802D8E1BA0891F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Israel has declared its unilateral adherence to the Missile Technology Control Regime, the Australia Group, and the Nuclear Suppliers Group.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0D3FD228BA2844B08C4340FFA91E06EE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Israel is a party to—</text> <subparagraph id="HE24B11C8088944FE9628351CB9A8563E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Protocol for the Prohibition of the Use in War of Asphyxiating, Poisonous or Other Gases, and of Bacteriological Methods of Warfare, signed at Geneva June 17, 1925; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50E435EC6FF9449EB2FDCD5B7369AF55"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Convention on the Physical Protection of Nuclear Material, adopted at Vienna on October 26, 1979.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H309DF48126E74D02AA5680D97CE2F6DC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Section 6(b) of the United States-Israel Strategic Partnership Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8603">22 U.S.C. 8603</external-xref> note) directs the President, consistent with the commitments of the United States under international agreements, to take steps so that Israel may be included in the list of countries eligible for the strategic trade authorization exception under section 740.20(c)(1) of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations, to the requirement for a license for the export, re-export, or in-country transfer of an item subject to controls under the Export Administration Regulations.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDEE84B860D944512BAEE3CA5DFC58FA6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>As of December 27, 2016, the last publication of the license exceptions country list, Israel had not been included in the list of countries eligible for the strategic trade authorization exception under section 740.20(c)(1) of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6EC361A18A864DEF9BCE73127A3371D1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report on eligibility for Strategic Trade Authorization exception</header>
 <paragraph id="H8435EEE1010E4A6ABF1820164A68A863"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HEBAFBC8AE67C428EB1EB3403E2359185"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describes the steps taken to include Israel in the list of countries eligible for the strategic trade authorization exception under section 740.20 (c) (1) of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations section, as required under 6(b) of the United States-Israel Strategic Partnership Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8603">22 U.S.C. 8603</external-xref> note); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54A6A65210924C71BBE4E92880776B2B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes the reasons as to why Israel has not yet been included in such list of countries eligible for the strategic trade authorization exception.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD8711D641A64C7C89AD0BF6C095A8BB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required under paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H93A3F48255F349C0B24BDC04C2CAB025"><enum>109.</enum><header>Extension of loan guarantees to Israel</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Chapter 5 of title I of the Emergency Wartime Supplemental Appropriations Act, 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/11">Public Law 108–11</external-xref>; 117 Stat. 576) is amended under the heading <quote>Loan Guarantees to Israel</quote>—</text>
 <paragraph id="H8B6284864C54463B9904E8D79A400798"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the matter preceding the first proviso, by striking <quote>September 30, 2019'</quote> and inserting <quote>September 30, 2023</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H07D929CD973A4CE098883A6D621A8A2D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the second proviso, by striking <quote>September 30, 2019</quote> and inserting <quote>September 30, 2023</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph></section></title><title id="H4603BD969D704E19B8784097A74C0279"><enum>II</enum><header>Enhanced Cooperation Between the United States and Israel</header>
			<section id="HD584B36CB00F449595FBC85ED381B41A"><enum>201.</enum><header>United States-Israel cybersecurity cooperation</header>
				<subsection id="HF46849834CF049A3B20BB220C6D152DD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant program</header>
 <paragraph id="H9556759D6BF34D97937463E9313EE8F1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary, in accordance with the agreement entitled the <quote>Agreement between the Government of the United States of America and the Government of the State of Israel on Cooperation in Science and Technology for Homeland Security Matters</quote>, dated May 29, 2008 (or successor agreement), and the requirements specified in paragraph (2), shall establish a grant program at the Department to support—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HFDDE31D32D5D46FB9D6FE6E26EAA8797"><enum>(A)</enum><text>cybersecurity research and development; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H839C22B9E2244319A918089F8736A04E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>demonstration and commercialization of cybersecurity technology.</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF78A9CCCA494991AD1CEE6238D67FAA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header>
 <subparagraph id="HDD621E6749434D9BB1CE79E7D1CA0D0C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, in carrying out a research, development, demonstration, or commercial application program or activity that is authorized under this section, the Secretary shall require cost sharing in accordance with this paragraph.</text>
						</subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27ACDDDB9ADB47639E3BFA5461CAEC75"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Research and development</header>
 <clause id="H73B67F1271E64B169F02A85A0913B097"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), the Secretary shall require not less than 50 percent of the cost of a research, development, demonstration, or commercial application program or activity described in subparagraph (A) to be provided by a non-Federal source.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H510CB1C704B246AA9743C4369E3F5388"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Reduction</header><text>The Secretary may reduce or eliminate, on a case-by-case basis, the percentage requirement specified in clause (i) if the Secretary determines that such reduction or elimination is necessary and appropriate.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB06C28FA7C9946ECA0FA65DA72CC2CBC"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Merit review</header><text>In carrying out a research, development, demonstration, or commercial application program or activity that is authorized under this section, awards shall be made only after an impartial review of the scientific and technical merit of the proposals for such awards has been carried out by or for the Department.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07FE6EF03EA2483D9A28C8F840DEDFAB"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Review processes</header><text>In carrying out a review under subparagraph (C), the Secretary may use merit review processes developed under section 302(14) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/182">6 U.S.C. 182(14)</external-xref>).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H377D077EB5724EE5A2EEA1C864ED8ACA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible applicants</header><text>An applicant shall be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection if the project of such applicant—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HCFC13384F3644F64BDECD37035CB546B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>addresses a requirement in the area of cybersecurity research or cybersecurity technology, as determined by the Secretary; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H525AF9588AB345168EFF4D772FD6961B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is a joint venture between—</text> <clause id="HD7AEDA82103247F983CB37AE0221F1C1"><enum>(i)</enum> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HF51DDB47D8C34F76BF5E6D8E14997763"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a for-profit business entity, academic institution, National Laboratory (as defined in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>)), or nonprofit entity in the United States; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H910D5F8C29C64B2A86C0BB48CC962528" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a for-profit business entity, academic institution, or nonprofit entity in Israel; or</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="HC4D09BB5AFE74C3488EB396BC8BE686B"><enum>(ii)</enum> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HBDF63C3C3B6D463592F2A820713F33E1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Federal Government; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HDD008466FCE74066B1070B1A135E870E" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the Government of Israel.</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A36F4E50CA148C581E4BC9E3F827600"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an applicant shall submit to the Secretary an application for such grant in accordance with procedures established by the Secretary, in consultation with the advisory board established under paragraph (5).</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H67939FC1E65C42618425E20DC05AD5B7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Advisory board</header>
 <subparagraph id="HBFDCBDE8B4E04F0D80854388338FEEE4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall establish an advisory board to—</text> <clause id="H07173074DC3C42EABAABB2D192EEB336"><enum>(i)</enum><text>monitor the method by which grants are awarded under this subsection; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF354A876FF9C4C2C82C0096BB0B5F3D7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide to the Secretary periodic performance reviews of actions taken to carry out this subsection.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H60CE1ED97CE84AA7BD568FAB81FCE179"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Composition</header><text>The advisory board established under subparagraph (A) shall be composed of three members, to be appointed by the Secretary, of whom—</text>
 <clause id="HF2E0A6882CD4490DA7D2261DCC9173ED"><enum>(i)</enum><text>one shall be a representative of the Federal Government;</text> </clause><clause id="H312557BED13A4D138D4BD613D904F8FD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>one shall be selected from a list of nominees provided by the United States-Israel Binational Science Foundation; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H01FB0DBB7ACE436ABED20D10A40132C8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>one shall be selected from a list of nominees provided by the United States-Israel Binational Industrial Research and Development Foundation.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD778DABF746E465D8240D85C421EA6E9"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Contributed funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary may accept or retain funds contributed by any person, government entity, or organization for purposes of carrying out this subsection. Such funds shall be available, subject to appropriation, without fiscal year limitation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD350CA01F8744122BCC6295BEF599062"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of completion of a project for which a grant is provided under this subsection, the grant recipient shall submit to the Secretary a report that contains—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H38DB3E0A03384203A61FC250DCCF7514"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of how the grant funds were used by the recipient; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B0F1583053F42568875A84FBEB3DC4E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an evaluation of the level of success of each project funded by the grant.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEFA964FD4DB49ADB64AA804128FD1F9"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Classification</header><text>Grants shall be awarded under this subsection only for projects that are considered to be unclassified by both the United States and Israel.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1A2AFA5736FA4A20BECC9DDCC9C9A612"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The grant program and the advisory board established under this section terminate on the date that is 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF0CD4279F6074AFF98316C2C41BB9559"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No additional funds authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No additional funds are authorized to carry out the requirements of this section. Such requirements shall be carried out using amounts otherwise authorized.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H12BE0E671C1D4A63B5A6FEE548251803"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section—</text> <paragraph id="HED9A502588ED4EE3A90D0088B052374C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>cybersecurity research</term> means research, including social science research, into ways to identify, protect against, detect, respond to, and recover from cybersecurity threats;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCB4019CFA61F4592A1F970A463A3821C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>cybersecurity technology</term> means technology intended to identify, protect against, detect, respond to, and recover from cybersecurity threats;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9E5F328C2D0548DDA1AD01768BFF002C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>cybersecurity threat</term> has the meaning given such term in section 102 of the Cybersecurity Information Sharing Act of 2015 (enacted as title I of the Cybersecurity Act of 2015 (division N of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/113">Public Law 114–113</external-xref>)));</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H37C742C5EEA84A339BBBA71E7AF44FC6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>Department</term> means the Department of Homeland Security; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HF98F89A999404FC3B53246DBD62D3C74"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H6C11A8F63970457180AE6FCE3A3661C4"><enum>202.</enum><header>United States-Israel space cooperation</header>
 <subsection id="HBF2157D5CBC941F38781F29463DDEB58"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Congress finds that—</text> <paragraph id="H9B27F4A1B0E64EF997F8F96237171AB7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">authorized in 1958, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) supports and coordinates United States Government research in aeronautics, human exploration and operations, science, and space technology;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE28364E4B764425C83836E0BDD76E072"><enum>(2)</enum><text>established in 1983, the Israel Space Agency (ISA) supports the growth of Israel’s space industry by supporting academic research, technological innovation, and educational activities;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3857742D0A48444B8201C10929BC9F8B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the mutual interest of the United States and Israel in space exploration affords both nations an opportunity to leverage their unique abilities to advance scientific discovery;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB257BB5CE3814A6581A3A13539F8C73B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in 1996, NASA and the ISA entered into their first agreement outlining areas of mutual cooperation, which remained in force until 2005;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3BB2E39B530240FCB5D5FF07D1E6A3B7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>since 1996, NASA and the ISA have successfully cooperated on many space programs supporting the Global Positioning System and research related to the sun, earth science, and the environment;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1E4BC5C0E7FB44F08107F0496DCE3855"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the bond between NASA and the ISA was permanently forged on February 1, 2003, with the loss of the crew of STS–107 including Israeli Astronaut Ilan Ramon;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1B117901164D426D91C96C8A7484D8A9"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the United States-Israel Strategic Partnership Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/113/296">Public Law 113–296</external-xref>) designated Israel as a Major Strategic Partner of the United States; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H72F73518D05E4CDA950F01D51BCC5349"><enum>(8)</enum><text>on October 13, 2015, the United States and Israel signed the Framework Agreement between the National Aeronautics and Space Administration of the United States of America and the Israel Space Agency for Cooperation in Aeronautics and the Exploration and Use of Airspace and Outer Space for Peaceful Purposes.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3BEB5713B9AC4FEA97809F6BB6FABBCD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Continuing cooperation</header><text>The Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration shall continue to work with the Israel Space Agency to identify and cooperatively pursue peaceful space exploration and science initiatives in areas of mutual interest, taking all appropriate measures to protect sensitive information, intellectual property, trade secrets, and economic interests of the United States.</text>
				</subsection></section><section id="H74BFEDA641AC49119C50309F17BDB51B"><enum>203.</enum><header>United States Agency for International Development—Israel enhanced cooperation</header>
 <subsection id="H445C5B76A35D4725A8A839BC6FAAD03A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It should be the policy of the United States Agency for International Development to cooperate with Israel in order to advance common goals across a wide variety of sectors, including energy, agriculture and food security, democracy, human rights and governance, economic growth and trade, education, environment, global health and water and sanitation.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H08BF08A261524B1CAEF94B3722185CDE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Memorandum of understanding</header><text>The Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development is authorized to enter into memoranda of understanding with Israel in order to advance common goals on energy, agriculture and food security, democracy, human rights and governance, economic growth and trade, education, environment, global health and water sanitation with a focus on strengthening mutual ties and cooperation with nations throughout the world.</text>
				</subsection></section><section id="H13155C95D59B4936BA2CB47EAE95D139"><enum>204.</enum><header>Authority to enter into a cooperative project agreement with Israel to counter unmanned aerial
			 vehicles that threaten the United States or Israel</header>
 <subsection id="H7AD44E2AB5F7440DBF2481DC99BB471E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="H902791ADD9D740F1A9CA7DFA7FD48F2A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On February 10, 2018, Iran launched an unmanned aerial vehicle (commonly known as a <quote>drone</quote>) from Syria that penetrated Israeli airspace.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBAD79FD7802C4F4490A1814D53240905"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Israeli officials noted that the unmanned aerial vehicle was in Israeli airspace for a minute and a half before being shot down by the Israeli air force.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H422ABC33ABE84920864B13DB30BAF581"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Senior Israeli officials stated that the unmanned aerial vehicle was an advanced piece of technology.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H45EEF04F6745478986FB668420694090"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It remains unclear whether the unmanned aerial vehicle was armed. Nonetheless, the launch, and sophistication of the unmanned aerial vehicle, highlight the threat Israel faces from unmanned aerial vehicles from Iranian forces active in Syria and from Hezbollah in Lebanon.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5B61C3AF9DFA4C8BB3104DD7C6F028F5"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States likewise faces the threat of unmanned aerial vehicles along the United States border and in areas of active hostilities, including unmanned aerial vehicles of the Islamic State of Iraq and Syria (ISIS) in Iraq and Syria and unmanned aerial vehicles manufactured of al-Qaeda in Afghanistan.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF9CE448ADA264BC7BD655EC536148BB0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text> <paragraph id="HF75FFC770CCC44A8AEE6B81E80FBD34F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">joint research and development to counter unmanned aerial vehicles will serve the national security interests of the United States and Israel;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7B1C19F166B34F7E827FE29593864C2C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Israel faces urgent and emerging threats from unmanned aerial vehicles and other unmanned aerial vehicles, launched from Lebanon by Hezbollah, from Syria by forces of Iran’s Revolutionary Guard Corps, or from others seeking to attack Israel; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7F48D0B3B88E4534AE9C5CC0049B6558"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the United States and Israel should continue to work together to defend against all threats to the safety, security, and national interests of both countries.</text>
					</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE5A1FDAA85E841A8BEBBE44BB1CD592B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authority To enter into agreement</header>
 <paragraph id="H4B94D29894D243F9B5533912B8D31681"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President is authorized to enter into a cooperative project agreement with Israel under the authority of section 27 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2767">22 U.S.C. 2767</external-xref>) to carry out research on and development, testing, evaluation, and joint production (including follow-on support) of defense articles and defense services to detect, track, and destroy unmanned aerial vehicles that threaten the United States or Israel.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3E54FB7356104767B5F98168E9E97FA0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable requirements</header><text>The cooperative project agreement described in paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H8E98DD77BD4048FA8261575A6ABA09B8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall provide that any activities carried out pursuant to the agreement are subject to—</text>
 <clause id="HEAB1BC157BC94574B908530DF45EC230"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the applicable requirements described in subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C) of section 27(b)(2) of the Arms Export Control Act; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB7F9DDF844A14B6A878D6F2FE0ADCC18"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other applicable requirements of the Arms Export Control Act with respect to the use, transfers, and security of such defense articles and defense services under that Act; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7B7E7B9129F84D4AA3B35C59D255F54F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall establish a framework to negotiate the rights to intellectual property developed under the agreement.</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H2A82EE1B73D340289A380710379C5C76"><enum>III</enum><header>Ensuring Israel’s Qualitative Military Edge</header>
 <section id="H11E0ADAF778B4F74805269385CA25C86"><enum>301.</enum><header>Improved reporting on enhancing Israel’s qualtitative military edge and security posture</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 36(h)(2) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2776">22 U.S.C. 2776(h)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2F98A05058C944739D513786062855E0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC882421F13BF49B7A57EE9B8A912211F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H0376DA5B9C9B4854A2B7A151782F406D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H063015B297474D709ED49CDED9F2F5A3" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H78FAEFBF1EC740C5B1635822F33F6093"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of—</text> <clause id="H1ED514600A594C0AB899482C4BCCD8BA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the ability of Israel to effectively defend itself against military threats from regional non-state actors;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HAAA31A0B701644B380DD459A185B5CD2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the risk that is posed by the sale or export of a subsequent unauthorized transfer or proliferation of the equipment for use against Israel;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HEF01284E0A414008B00D62D63DF86DDD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the range of cyber and asymmetric threats posed to Israel by state and non-state actors;</text> </clause><clause id="H4D5103669D7B4CDAB5956D495B1C6FD2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the range of threats posed to Israel by state and non-state actors through the use of unmanned vehicles and systems, through air, land or water; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H174BF20A06774859A178F4D10D93E3FC"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the effective countermeasures available to Israel to defend against the risks and threats described in clauses (ii) through (iv).</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H29753BD29894458CB3435FCF33004EE7"><enum>302.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States to ensure that Israel maintains its ability to counter and defeat any credible conventional military or emerging threat from any individual state or possible coalition of states or from non-state actors, while sustaining minimal damages and casualties, through the use of superior military means, possessed in sufficient quantity, including weapons, command, control, communication, intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance capabilities that in their technical characteristics are superior in capability to those of such other individual or possible coalition states or non-state actors.</text>
			</section></title></legis-body></bill>


