<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HFAB9FC290939403E9DF09EBDF8037E76" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4963 IH: Amy, Vicky, and Andy Child Pornography Victim Assistance Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4963</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180207">February 7, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001189">Mr. Messer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="U000031">Mr. Upton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000578">Mr. Reichert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000605">Mr. Perry</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001049">Mr. Clay</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to provide for assistance for victims of child pornography,
			 and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H1C2E5902D182479BAC9F5F7D47486B38" style="OLC">
 <section id="H40B76C1BE6C44F86A06F8F760E9EF5B0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Amy, Vicky, and Andy Child Pornography Victim Assistance Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H4BDF7E9B2BDC43ABA064CEC1F48215CF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H1A6B5207BB4A46769B5B29E1C2CAAC58"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The demand for child pornography harms children because it drives production, which involves severe and often irreparable child sexual abuse and exploitation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H86FC9D4F061F4BEF91B6FAA2ACD1BF3D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The harms caused by child pornography begin, but do not end, with child sex abuse because child pornography is a permanent record of that abuse and trafficking in those images compounds the harm to the child.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H41E0AEA26E944DE7B2C559A9FD07BB0B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In Paroline v. United States (2014), the Supreme Court recognized that <quote>every viewing of child pornography is a repetition of the victim’s abuse</quote>.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H29CFB11EC99D463581E12050EDF508C2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The American Professional Society on the Abuse of Children has stated that for victims of child pornography, <quote>the sexual abuse of the child, the memorialization of that abuse which becomes child pornography, and its subsequent distribution and viewing become psychologically intertwined and each compound the harm suffered by the child-victim</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H57A991A456834EB3B684A6777D09790B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Victims suffer continuing and grievous harm as a result of knowing that a large, indeterminate number of individuals have viewed and will in the future view images of their childhood sexual abuse. Harms of this sort are a major reason that child pornography is outlawed.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4A91FFE1037245BE9A11092870BD1BB2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The unlawful collective conduct of every individual who reproduces, distributes, or possesses the images of a victim’s childhood sexual abuse plays a part in sustaining and aggravating the harms to that individual victim. Multiple actors independently commit intentional crimes that combine to produce an indivisible injury to a victim.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB69B7BC559334FC79D093E08A12E4E3C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>It is the intent of Congress that victims of child pornography be fully compensated for all the harms resulting from every perpetrator who contributes to their anguish. Such an aggregate causation standard reflects the nature of child pornography and the unique ways that it actually harms victims.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="HBA368D935DCB4F1AB285B78F665AE254"><enum>3.</enum><header>Determining restitution</header>
 <subsection id="H76C6F8B3BA934B9FBCDB2622FE5C6029"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Determining restitution</header><text>Section 2259(b) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HCA7804DD579B4AE694D294CE1BC60A16"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H785A47DDEBBD4E888B8AF2EAA313B8F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The order</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the order</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40063286F6F9460A9DDD4B03EAD0816A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>as determined by the court pursuant to paragraph (2)</quote> after <quote>of the victim's losses</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2E0A7BC6C4642858837D29836A714CC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3);</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE003CD124B38419D9782D02D058648D0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (2) as paragraph (3); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBA8961E923054FE69037D0CB28271732"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (1) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDB407C3031DD494DA8634D7522DB4457" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H88622585C961413A9DE8E40C687BCF7A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Restitution for trafficking in child pornography</header><text>If the defendant was convicted for trafficking in child pornography, the order of restitution under this section shall direct the defendant to pay the victim (through the appropriate court mechanism) an amount of restitution determined by the court as follows:</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD7997EBE167A464FBBF391196D161000"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Determining the full amount of a victim’s losses</header><text>The court shall determine the full amount of the victim’s losses that were incurred or are reasonably projected to be incurred by the victim as a result of the trafficking in child pornography.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22296944E02E4D9CBFA4E46FD63717D1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Determining a restitution amount</header><text>After completing the determination required under subparagraph (A), the court shall enter an order of restitution against the defendant in favor of the victim in an amount which is between $3,000 and 1 percent of the full amount of the victim’s losses.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD922829785764DCA9EE9AA38E55185B7"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Termination of payment</header><text>A victim’s total aggregate recovery pursuant to this section shall not exceed the full amount of the victim's demonstrated losses. After the victim has received restitution in the full amount of the victim’s losses as measured by the greatest amount of such losses found in any case involving that victim that has resulted in a final restitution order under this section, the liability of each defendant who is or has been ordered to pay restitution for such losses to that victim shall be terminated. The court may direct the victim to provide information concerning the amount of restitution the victim has been paid in other cases for the same losses.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H864657B4522444A29B77A2AFB3915866"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional definitions</header><text>Section 2259(c) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H9CB06388A9954BFBA11B800BE4A453ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="USC">Definition</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="USC">Definitions</header-in-text></quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H67137D02B60244428897EB266DAC1646"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>For purposes</quote> and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H21C78B72A3C249EBBA1CB4BDD50CE6A0" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H1F1E93B2DD04463F80DBF6BADE1CBD1D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Victim</header><text>For purposes</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6F89774D30DF4424A0FC9A2A38E3020A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking <quote>under this chapter, including, in the case</quote> and inserting <quote>under this chapter. In the case</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H0CE1F81070924E6A852B5C386218E8B1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after <quote>or any other person appointed as suitable by the court,</quote> the following: <quote>may assume the crime victim’s rights under this section,</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC3D7D947428D4060AFD8BD95EB7D786D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by inserting before paragraph (4), as so designated, the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4E1924E77D4E4F279D1457AFE0E7DFC1" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H2FCA7D3B1E934DEF9721D360440A4CBB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Child pornography production</header><text>For purposes of this section and section 2259A, the term <term>child pornography production</term> means conduct proscribed by subsection (a) through (c) of section 2251, section 2252A(g) (in cases in which the series of felony violations involves at least one of the violations listed in this section), section 2260(a), or any offense under chapter 109A or chapter 117 that involved the production of child pornography, as defined in section 2256.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0793C4F1055D4798BDE2E52706711CD2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Full amount of the victim's losses</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>full amount of the victim's losses</term> includes any costs incurred, or reasonably projected to be incurred in the future, by the victim, and in the case of a trafficking in child pornography conviction, as a proximate result of all trafficking in child pornography offenses involving the same victim, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HA780153DE05A4B37A4C43F660B75C9A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>medical services relating to physical, psychiatric, or psychological care;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H840E8685DA4D415FBF92FE2372B82BB2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>physical and occupational therapy or rehabilitation;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A09EA24A3C6425DA307A978D2171497"><enum>(C)</enum><text>necessary transportation, temporary housing, and child care expenses;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC02E0E57719443D5BB0E8038E4563060"><enum>(D)</enum><text>lost income;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2589B40BAFD2400A9F8F11C97DB3273C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>attorneys’ fees, as well as other costs incurred; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0BF8F4D6C2D4278A2A22A98AED96B0B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>any other relevant losses incurred by the victim.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H476143C89C8247FE8CB8C0A64A5D9F9F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Trafficking in child pornography</header><text>For purposes of this section and section 2259A, the term <term>trafficking in child pornography</term> means conduct proscribed by section 2251(d), 2251A, 2252, 2252A, section 2252A(g) (in cases in which the series of felony violations exclusively involves violations listed in this section), or section 2260(b).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF0298F1A434D4FFEBB6F01A8C34AD6ED"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>Section 1593(b)(3) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>section 2259(b)(3)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 2259(c)(2)</quote>.</text> </subsection></section><section id="HA57B5C5342FE46B69555405DC1721E36"><enum>4.</enum><header>Defined monetary assistance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2259 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H03740053C045493CBF67E59BABE1A2A2" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="HC569DDE5C9A04ECB8EDEF33A1019FC8D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Defined monetary assistance</header>
					<paragraph id="HCCA8B48766E24D5EB41CFA1D6F7CDE74"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Defined monetary assistance made available at victim’s election</header>
 <subparagraph id="H096DB892E5C74D18AE0527A0B2F7D02B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Election to receive defined monetary assistance</header><text>Subject to paragraphs (2) and (3), if the defendant was convicted of child pornography production, the victim of child pornography production may choose to receive defined monetary assistance from the Child Pornography Victims’ Reserve established under section 1402(d)(6) of the Victims of Crime Act of 1984.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H539FDD05C0B6404E922EA6A7C43E8306"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Finding</header><text>To be eligible for defined monetary assistance under this subsection, a court shall determine whether the claimant is a victim of the defendant who was convicted of child pornography production.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C56959639E34D21B6B6FF91C2CEABF9"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Order</header><text>If a court determines that a claimant is a victim of child pornography production under subparagraph (B) and the claimant chooses to receive defined monetary assistance, the court shall order payment in accordance with subparagraph (D) to the victim from the Child Pornography Victims’ Reserve established under section 1402(d)(6) of the Victims of Crime Act of 1984.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD17E40FBAAC400F95EF1A64AC277FC0"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Amount of defined monetary assistance</header><text>The amount of defined monetary assistance payable under this subparagraph shall be equal to—</text> <clause id="H147B0AA53266432D933145FDCA49218B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for the first calendar year after the date of enactment of this subsection, $35,000; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H3E01232828C349779A6AA37CDF8995BC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for each calendar year after the year described in clause (i), $35,000 multiplied by the ratio (not less than one) of—</text>
 <subclause id="H8CB62908B71C4B11A0F880613BA99C23"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Consumer Price Index for all Urban Consumer (CPI–U, as published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics of the Department of Labor) for the calendar year preceding such calendar year; to</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H04986DD01BCE49988FE388F290AC3EDD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the CPI–U for the calendar year 2 years before the calendar year described in clause (i).</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H74B37ECD79EE4686B3586F4C8826B6A3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitations on defined monetary assistance</header> <subparagraph id="H860331EEBFB044AFAE4B6166D36F28F0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A victim may only obtain defined monetary assistance under this subsection once.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54EC84C152ED40FEA06932F43BCE8217"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Effect on recovery of other restitution</header><text>A victim who obtains defined monetary assistance under this subsection shall not be barred or limited from receiving restitution against any defendant for any offenses not covered by this section.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H047DDD0AC87F497D8A8E7A38B01CBE6A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Deduction</header><text>If a victim who received defined monetary assistance under this subsection subsequently seeks restitution under this section, the court shall deduct the amount the victim received in defined monetary assistance when determining the full amount of the victim’s losses.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF964ECA7D5354D78A85A58570AE40F22"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitations on eligibility</header><text>A victim who has collected payment of restitution pursuant to this section in an amount greater than the amount provided for under paragraph (1)(D) shall be ineligible to receive defined monetary assistance under this subsection.</text>
					</paragraph><paragraph id="H3C83A87BB2C64B5898229FAE2FEC0353"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Guardian ad litem</header>
 <subparagraph id="HCAC9DC46E24645C992A62C7A01C38F9A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In all cases alleging child pornography production, the court shall appoint a guardian ad litem, who shall be an attorney, for each identified victim of the child pornography production, pursuant to section 3509(h).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80FCFAC8368E417D84D58839F41539CA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Fees</header><text>A guardian ad litem appointed pursuant to this subsection may not charge, receive, or collect, without court approval for good cause shown, any fees or payment of expenses that in the aggregate exceed 10 percent of any defined monetary assistance payment made under this subsection.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC14F257D9410433EB064539AB4882071"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>Any guardian ad litem who violates subparagraph (B) shall be fined under this title, imprisoned for not more than one year, or both.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="H513BAD76AB664C66A36273E267E3C8D8"><enum>5.</enum><header>Assessments in child pornography cases</header>
 <subsection id="H0F500152B8FC4E67A47E59FB0EBC3524"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Assessments in child pornography cases</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/110">Chapter 110</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/18/2259">section 2259</external-xref> the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAF04C8FEEF9645B2B33D432E101A8569" style="USC">
					<section id="HE4CFEA13B5B04FC6B8FD581714AEAF99"><enum>2259A.</enum><header>Assessments in child pornography cases</header>
 <subsection id="HEDC8B5A0BB3F4FE996A7D4AB23EEA46A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In addition to any other criminal penalty, restitution, or special assessment authorized by law, the court shall assess—</text>
 <paragraph id="H45EECF01E7A64EBD8E422FE3827946C9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not more than $17,000 on any person convicted of an offense under section 2252(a)(4) or 2252A(a)(5);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HADAF61707DD14F068803353815EFAA5E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not more than $35,000 on any person convicted of any other offense for trafficking in child pornography; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE121CF81FD4F4C29AC3692CBDD5B926A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>not more than $50,000 on any person convicted of a child pornography production offense.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7664A14D82864A1E98E0DD05E82F48B0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual adjustment</header><text>The dollar amounts in subsection (a) shall be adjusted annually in conformity with the Consumer Price Index.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H0A35B0D81AC04B29975AD643A3A45169"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Factors considered</header><text>In determining the amount of the assessment under subsection (a), the court shall consider the factors set forth in sections 3553(a) and 3572.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H3703F2B9CB524257BC5DA9B7A9144B93"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Imposition and implementation</header>
 <paragraph id="H72AA8AED62BC4A8FA17D39003217FBE6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The provisions of subchapter C of chapter 227 (other than section 3571) and subchapter B of chapter 229 (relating to fines) apply to assessments under this section, except that paragraph (2) applies in lieu of any contrary provisions of law relating to fines or disbursement of money received from a defendant.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H81E32B0F1DB7417691477718AE39FCCD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effect on other penalties</header><text>Imposition of an assessment under this section does not relieve a defendant of, or entitle a defendant to reduce the amount of any other penalty by the amount of the assessment. Any money received from a defendant shall be disbursed so that each of the following obligations is paid in full in the following sequence:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H94C15E694EE0472EA8A5B0E20727B038"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A special assessment under section 3013.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4409FAC3D0194AC99703CC20C012402E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Restitution to victims of any child pornography production offense that the defendant committed.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H266A4FAC01B04D52BF2F12C0EE1D3CC8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An assessment under this section and restitution to victims of any trafficking in child pornography offenses.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3465103627DD4D7CB2ADCC1388EC4494"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Other orders under any other section of this title.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE98BD7521444B27A7154791107019B3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>All other fines, penalties, costs, and other payments required under the sentence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H89654E6AB4DD4CED9D4517DFEB07259C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Child pornography victims reserve</header><text>Section 1402(d) the Victims of Crime Act of 1984 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20101">34 U.S.C. 20101(d)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H49C38E63D9DE4D669492B40EC66902E7" style="USC">
					<paragraph id="H8A31E84D6FAB4FAFB37C2DB27C61F471" indent="up1"><enum>(6)</enum>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD7F3026CAC6A4ABEBBD52A393A64166D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Director may set aside up to $10,000,000 of the amounts remaining in the Fund in any fiscal year after distributing the amounts under paragraphs (2), (3), and (4), in a Child Pornography Victims Reserve, which may be used by the Attorney General for payments under section 2259(d) of title 18, United States Code.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF26D6262006D4C579E9157CD0CFEB3C5" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Amounts in the reserve may be carried over from fiscal year to fiscal year, but the total amount of the reserve shall not exceed $10,000,000. Notwithstanding subsection (c) and any limitation on Fund obligations in any future Act, unless the same should expressly refer to this section, any such amounts carried over shall not be subject to any limitation on obligations from amounts deposited to or available in the Fund.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H7C0DC7916C2748FC85D6E86491B984AF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Child pornography victims reserve</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/110">Chapter 110</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/18/2259A">section 2259A,</external-xref> as added by subsection (a), the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H852EC4D4144B4CD1B4EA43C778CA1CE9" style="USC">
					<section id="H5354087971C54D64B53782A48E47B29A"><enum>2259B.</enum><header>Child pornography victims reserve</header>
 <subsection id="H3461E7198F6C453E94A58E1DB725031C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Deposits into the reserve</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, there shall be deposited into the Child Pornography Victims Reserve established under section 1402(d)(6) of the Victims of Crime Act of 1984 all assessments collected under section 2259A and any gifts, bequests, or donations to the Child Pornography Victims Reserve from private entities or individuals.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H10717A56DFD8445EAFADCC6303CC7398"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Availability for defined monetary assistance</header><text>Amounts in the Child Pornography Victims Reserve shall be available for payment of defined monetary assistance pursuant to section 2259(d). If at any time the Child Pornography Victims Reserve has insufficient funds to make all of the payments ordered under section 2259(d), the Child Pornography Victims Reserve shall make such payments as it can satisfy in full from available funds. In determining the order in which such payments shall be made, the Child Pornography Victims Reserve shall make payments based on the date they were ordered, with the earliest-ordered payments made first.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H6DC5B82C9E034C74911510311DE61B26"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The Attorney General shall administer the Child Pornography Victims Reserve and shall issue guidelines and regulations to implement this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H8B6A9E273B7B4C3D9EC5F71518D8CF90"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that individuals who violate this chapter before this legislation is enacted, but who are sentenced after this legislation is enacted, shall be subject to the statutory scheme that was in effect at the time the offenses were committed.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H1D7FC14D8C144CAF9AA27429B0D57403"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/110">chapter 110</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/18/2259">section 2259</external-xref> the following:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H3F7A41A9633A4B1C91928B181F8E6CD9" style="USC">
					<toc>
						<toc-entry idref="HE4CFEA13B5B04FC6B8FD581714AEAF99" level="section">2259A. Assessments in child pornography cases.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="H5354087971C54D64B53782A48E47B29A" level="section">2259B. Child pornography victims reserve.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection></section><section id="H6C40AD0810A9418E8458619A943F8382"><enum>6.</enum><header>Child pornography victim’s right to evidence</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3509(m) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H821DCC7F7E374C3899EB89E5FA57713A" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HF785A9080F924C188E80205DBE3003B5"><enum>(3)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H13D9565D8DA849CC86D61CE60668DCB5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>In any criminal proceeding, a victim of trafficking in child pornography or child pornography production, as those terms are defined in section 2259(c), shall have access to any property or material that constitutes child pornography, as defined by section 2256, depicting the victim, for inspection, viewing, and examination at a Government facility, by the victim, his or her attorney, and any individual the victim may seek to qualify to furnish expert testimony.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8DAE965CACDE4652A977A438E04C0888" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A victim of trafficking in child pornography or child pornography production, as those terms are defined in section 2259(c), his or her attorney, and any individual the victim may seek to qualify to furnish expert testimony may not copy, photograph, duplicate, or otherwise reproduce any property or material that constitutes child pornography, as defined by section 2256 of this title, so long as the Government makes the property or material reasonably available to the victim, his or her attorney, and any individual the victim may seek to qualify to furnish expert testimony.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="H29546440A6F7428E87CA1A80A5ECAFF4"><enum>7.</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header>
 <subsection id="H5C584173A87A4862BC4498B11E5294DC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Expansion of civil remedies for satisfaction of an unpaid fine</header><text>Section 3613(c) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>an assessment imposed pursuant to section 2259A of this title,</quote> after <quote>pursuant to the provisions of subchapter C of chapter 227 of this title,</quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H998C0C9E99644C05A0B3657D4A7DD4F0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clarification of interstate or foreign commerce provision regarding certain activities pertaining to child pornography</header><text>Section 2252A (a)(2) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HC27DAAA4A51E470981B84D3842AD3B40"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text> <subparagraph id="H0CA0E871A5DA4AFDA9D9CDC2173603A0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>using any means or facility of interstate or foreign commerce</quote> and inserting <quote>has been</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37F348CB411B4F5AAE9354E163EAE71E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>using any means or facility of interstate or foreign commerce or</quote> after <quote>child pornography</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H65E5FA9F90854AA5A28145E0485D9844"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H112F467CD94840CD847E473D0FAE6E37"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>using any means or facility of interstate or foreign commerce</quote> and inserting <quote>has been</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBFBBA6F1A394A769C08B69777689336"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>using any means or facility of interstate or foreign commerce or</quote> after <quote>child pornography</quote>.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF88835BC0FF14076B1A3C860DB424B8E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clarification of the definition of <quote>sexually explicit conduct</quote></header><text>Section 2256(2) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H1BFE560CEEF14A93AE607527ACE5B29E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)(v)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H93182B8250384BB18F144A1523EBCC90"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>anus,</quote> before <quote>genitals</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A470B54A5104CA7AEEA72A8EE8A0172"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting a comma after <quote>genitals</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B11186C25994DBDB0AB47FC53B96C2B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)(iii)—</text> <subparagraph id="H3E94DE708E9247EF9DBFDAD302EDBF29"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>anus,</quote> before <quote>genitals</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H68D9F0FE2F8342B48437C2CCBFEA3444"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting a comma after <quote>genitals</quote>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC63643437EA54ECEB8E6E6467D18D789"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Clarification of the extent of the offense of coercion and enticement of a minor</header><text>Section 3559(e)(2)(A) of title 18, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>into prostitution</quote>.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H1A625949478140C49A0EAE2CD4BB4513"><enum>8.</enum><header>Report on implementation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 24 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall submit to Congress a report on the progress of the Department of Justice in implementing the amendments made by sections 3 through 5.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


