<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H92324C9D45E84200AF78B581968D013E" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5526 IH: Peter, Ellie, and Grayson Victims of Illegal Criminal Entry Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5526</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180417">April 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000601">Mr. Ratcliffe</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S000583">Mr. Smith of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001036">Mr. Hensarling</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000362">Mr. King of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000819">Mr. Walker</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001269">Mr. Barletta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000809">Mr. Womack</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000375">Mr. Arrington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000592">Mr. Rokita</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to provide for certain sentencing enhancements relating to
			 illegal reentry offenses, and to clarify the manner in which sentences for
			 such offenses are to be served, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H63B7E1EFFEF74797BFD42015CBEB3849" style="OLC">
 <section id="H0C66D9E43CF6484C87F970514631C3CB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Peter, Ellie, and Grayson Victims of Illegal Criminal Entry Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or as the <quote><short-title>VOICES Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HB0E4AF68D2E64AA8AE507D4BE8E9948B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Directives to the sentencing commission</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">Pursuant to its authority under section 994(p) of title 28, United States Code, and in accordance with this section, the United States Sentencing Commission shall review and amend—</text>
 <paragraph id="HCA206AD0AEA54A7797A74B19BBA84667"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">its guidelines and its policy statements applicable to persons convicted of an offense who are aliens who are not lawfully present in the United States, to provide that such unlawful presence be considered an aggravating factor for any Federal criminal offense; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H683D845419404FC5945DAC22637529E7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">its guidelines and its policy statements applicable to persons convicted of an offense under section 276 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1326">8 U.S.C. 1326</external-xref>) to provide that any criminal offense committed after such a person unlawfully reenters, attempts to reenter, or is found in the United States be considered an aggravating factor with regard to such offense under section 276.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H5AF48A00FEA448CEB19CE8C5974D721E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Service of a term of imprisonment for unlawful reentry</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3584 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA373A504BDBF47979C01894BD80BEF34" style="USC"> <subsection id="HACA6B3B580B04514A86F707FA2BE9A6A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Certain immigration offenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any defendant who is convicted of an offense under section 276 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1326">8 U.S.C. 1326</external-xref>)—</text>
 <paragraph id="H4336C00A72574D8C87AF24DAA0D265F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>if that defendant has committed any other offense while unlawfully present in the United States, the Federal term of imprisonment for the offense under such section 276 may not be concurrent with any State term of imprisonment for such other offense; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H61FA7155EBF24C3B8235F7E31DEAE65D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>no time served in a State facility or in any facility other than a facility administered by the Bureau of Prisons may be credited toward the service of the term of imprisonment for the offense under such section 276.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </section><section id="H7C66B306D64D4DCDAE5A86F66EE3EAA9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reentry of removed aliens</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 276(b) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1326">8 U.S.C. 1326(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H3C0D33C26F4343F28940339A5778175B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H64B3898145704A518FA2D5A977D3B021"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9702E5A9043943F39DA4C3F63BE0EFC5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (4) the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD22F7488B6EA43A3A32B429C45E20AAB" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H94B18702C60F4262AC3BC0E6FD721C51"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who, subsequent to removal and unlawful reentry, is determined by a criminal court of competent jurisdiction to have committed an act that resulted in injury to another person or persons, shall be fined under title 18, United States Code, and imprisoned for not less than 10 years and not more than 20 years; or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD92CA0F3F296425EB55F6E1037977798"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who, subsequent to removal and unlawful reentry, is determined by a criminal court of competent jurisdiction to have committed an act that resulted in the death of another person or persons, shall be fined under title 18, United States Code, and imprisoned for not less than 20 years and not more than 40 years.</text>
					</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


