<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H441B9EAF7FBD4252BFEBFB1CF478FAE7" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4953 IH: Advancing Innovation and Reinvigorating Widespread Access to Viable Electromagnetic Spectrum Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4953</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180206">February 6, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000567">Mr. Lance</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000482">Mr. Michael F. Doyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001284">Mrs. Brooks of Indiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000800">Mr. Welch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000798">Mr. Walberg</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To facilitate a national pipeline of spectrum for commercial use, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H120D8A55C3904BA4BDCED018781371C5" style="OLC">
 <section id="H0B2F527AE4114AC9BD2E3FA85D978048" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Advancing Innovation and Reinvigorating Widespread Access to Viable Electromagnetic Spectrum Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>AIRWAVES Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HE4633D6FCBBF412EAB9669BD90197F76" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the United States should strive to—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE329A8F2974646C98646013D99D39300"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">advance innovation with respect to, and investment in, wireless broadband Internet access;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H5DBAB51514EE40D29F251FDD7C09F585"><enum>(2)</enum><text>promote the benefits of connecting all individuals in the United States to quality wireless broadband Internet access, including those individuals in rural communities; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H522E35F075F1431C8B63C26BA9238EAD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>support comprehensive, technology-neutral spectrum policy that includes licensed, unlicensed, and shared use of spectrum bands.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H47784474878946E58174C33000EE3413"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act—</text> <paragraph id="H06E8AF39ADB042E09A9E2B0BE930CFDC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H7B54F58D38804A4BBD1A8A1580688A7F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0723A97FC1914445AB7869A2A45552DB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H563DEDD154E545519D291D85B1A9FA92"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other congressional committee with jurisdiction over a matter;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB32C796D9A6949309AFD8AB22532C342"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Communications Commission;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H21BB6910A31A411D909844761B58EADF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>eligible Federal entity</term> means an entity described in section 113(g)(1) of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration Organization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/923">47 U.S.C. 923(g)(1)</external-xref>);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9C91AA6CD562493298D350CBB8D6AA76"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>eligible frequency</term> means a frequency with respect to which the costs incurred by an eligible Federal entity in relocating from the frequency may be reimbursed from the Spectrum Relocation Fund;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HDCE017F3F0214B44A748D155D9E97010"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>Federal entity</term> has the meaning given the term in section 113(l) of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration Organization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/923">47 U.S.C. 923(l)</external-xref>);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2AA03281918241B8AE82A9507AAE945F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the term <term>NTIA</term> means the National Telecommunications and Information Administration;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H826B1FB5EA064166887FCABDD37D126F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the term <term>Spectrum Frontiers proceeding</term> means the Report and Order and Further Notice of Proposed Rulemaking in the matter of Use of Spectrum Bands Above 24 GHz for Mobile Radio Services, adopted by the Commission on July 14, 2016 (FCC 16–89);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H55D0BD05AB5B415285765A862C7306FF"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the term <term>Spectrum Relocation Fund</term> means the fund established under section 118 of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration Organization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/928">47 U.S.C. 928</external-xref>); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H661BE5763ACD45B6A84647E7EA8453D4"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the term <term>system of competitive bidding</term> means a system of competitive bidding conducted under section 309(j) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/309">47 U.S.C. 309(j)</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H753F0F601065421084EF8304CEB6E512"><enum>4.</enum><header>Spectrum Frontiers proceeding</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall complete the rule making to which the Spectrum Frontiers proceeding relates.</text>
		</section><section id="H473113436DD84A0A95B124A31D087546"><enum>5.</enum><header>Expanding access to commercial spectrum</header>
			<subsection id="HD8B9E004533047688F6D2CE2EF62309F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>FCC responsibilities</header>
 <paragraph id="HA7954499EA24424395F54BD338BE0F07"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission, in consultation with the NTIA, shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H5109B2AC31474D92BE19CD76EF4DB253"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than December 31, 2018, complete a system of competitive bidding to grant priority access licenses for the use of 70 megahertz of spectrum in the frequencies between 3550 megahertz and 3650 megahertz;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC31D87B4331E4A83BFC1D34DC196DC7E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than December 31, 2018, complete a system of competitive bidding for the use of spectrum in frequencies between—</text>
 <clause id="H59FB927E826F49A0A4A3192853D4A347"><enum>(i)</enum><text>24250 megahertz and 24450 megahertz;</text> </clause><clause id="H9553230A3DC340A1BE5431F0D09F87D5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">24750 megahertz and 25250 megahertz;</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H3DF1966A92384BD69FE78DA9F5C2DCE6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>27500 megahertz and 28350 megahertz, consistent with the spectrum sharing framework adopted for that frequency band as part of the Spectrum Frontiers proceeding;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF966175CAC5849A3AC59BBE2E6BBE73D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>37600 megahertz and 38600 megahertz;</text> </clause><clause id="HC17F5278E554434293410C01FAD2761A"><enum>(v)</enum><text>38600 megahertz and 40000 megahertz; and</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HE3B0A4E4876B4BF4B0ADC2B21550DA7F"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>47200 megahertz and 48200 megahertz; and</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4F9507B74964E799A44B34264722AA2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>not later than December 31, 2020, complete a system of competitive bidding for the use of spectrum in frequencies between—</text>
 <clause id="H9FE625D45EDF4C599C059028E37EC301"><enum>(i)</enum><text>31800 megahertz and 33400 megahertz;</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="HE41C9656329E4BD1B13E98B950429679"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>42000 megahertz and 42500 megahertz; and</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H14FDB2E7E53C40FE99CBDFA9A9E53C22"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>50400 megahertz and 52600 megahertz.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC846EEE2D3941B0A7DB4075D93E414B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements relating to 3550–3700 MHz band</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Consistent with the Commission's rules governing the Citizens Broadband Radio Service and the Report and Order and Second Further Notice of Proposed Rulemaking in the matter of Amendment of the Commission’s Rules with Regard to Commercial Operations in the 3550–3650 MHz Band, adopted by the Commission on April 17, 2015 (FCC 15–47)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF8062A7722A8485CADFA20F3E2D58D6F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>30 megahertz of spectrum in the frequencies between 3550 megahertz and 3650 megahertz shall be reserved for general authorized access use; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDEFE0CB1A25499FA26AA0E29B16E8B1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the frequencies between 3650 megahertz and 3700 megahertz shall be reserved for grandfathered wireless broadband licensees and general authorized access users.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEBD9C298425249F8B52CF9B4EEB5CA2E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Identifying frequencies between 7125 megahertz and 8400 megahertz To be utilized for unlicensed
			 purposes</header>
 <paragraph id="H45020BDD4A344401A64BEABC6041CD81"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the NTIA, in consultation with the Commission, shall identify any frequency between 7125 megahertz and 8400 megahertz with respect to which there is the potential for unlicensed use without causing harmful interference with incumbents.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HDBBBA0A5333D485B9FBB8C6E0596DCC0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule making</header><text>If the NTIA, in consultation with the Commission, makes an identification described in paragraph (1), the Commission shall consider initiating a rule making with respect to the unlicensed use described in that paragraph.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0B1E1EC00DA84B309848BC720055D626"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report on reallocation of certain incumbent Federal stations</header>
 <paragraph id="H01B5F424F66C415586B1A58D2CF292D2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than December 31, 2020, the NTIA, in consultation with the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report relating to the relocation of incumbent Federal stations authorized to use spectrum in the frequencies between 1300 megahertz and 1350 megahertz and between 1780 megahertz and 1830 megahertz in order to facilitate the reallocation of such spectrum from Federal to non-Federal use.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H50E682A3D2514CBCA8BC998489192679"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>The relocation described in paragraph (1) with respect to the frequencies between 1780 megahertz and 1830 megahertz shall take place not earlier than 2023.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8B0DE3B657164F86B4095657F8390BF8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Amendments to the Spectrum Pipeline Act of 2015</header><text>Section 1004 of the Spectrum Pipeline Act of 2015 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/921">47 U.S.C. 921</external-xref> note) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H4FAD8DBBB30F43209904709E2A45CF12"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>30 megahertz</quote> and inserting <quote>100 megahertz</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD84D1E7F070042208136A28D2BA2170B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(1)(B), by striking <quote>July 1, 2024</quote> and inserting <quote>July 1, 2023</quote>.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB8F1C621B68945FDA98E8F5567561CE7"><enum>6.</enum><header>Modernizing mid-band spectrum</header> <subsection id="H64D7EF19666E49CCA5E2331AD69E93B3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> <paragraph id="HFED1A8A09ED2414682DCD5BDD13BF64B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Spectrum identification</header><text>Not later than December 31, 2019, the Commission, in consultation with the NTIA, shall identify up to 500 megahertz of additional spectrum in the frequencies between 3700 megahertz and 4200 megahertz to make available for commercial licensed use.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9C07B89F2352422C8E1138C1CCFE6EA9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Spectrum auction</header><text>Not later than December 31, 2022, the Commission shall complete a system of competitive bidding for the use of spectrum identified under paragraph (1).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H454AE8B6F0E6476D9C06F0D3D4712247"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Rule making on the unlicensed use of the frequency band between 5925 megahertz and 7125 megahertz</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission, in consultation with the NTIA, shall issue a notice of proposed rule making with respect to creating opportunities for the unlicensed use of spectrum in the frequencies between 5925 and 7125 megahertz without causing harmful interference with any incumbents in that band.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="HCB6DDA60C1FC481A86EF487DA93A2787"><enum>7.</enum><header>Rural set-aside</header>
 <subsection id="H000088B8D78849F8B793ACC36B15BC6E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding section 309(j)(8) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/309">47 U.S.C. 309(j)(8)</external-xref>), the Commission shall allocate 10 percent of the proceeds from each system of competitive bidding conducted under this Act for the deployment of wireless infrastructure in areas that the Commission has determined are underserved or unserved with respect to wireless broadband Internet access service.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE2AFAA023A0F47ABBD476AE3A2E5DD97"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>No amounts allocated under subsection (a) may be combined with amounts that are used to fund any other program that is in existence on the date on which the allocation is made, including any program established under section 254 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/254">47 U.S.C. 254</external-xref>).</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H0553F84307814C58954C3D188CA711C3"><enum>8.</enum><header>Special rules</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">With respect to any frequency band described in this Act (in this section referred to as the <quote>covered band</quote>), if the relocation of an incumbent from the covered band to another equivalent frequency band is not possible, and if the Commission determines that no mitigation technology, alternative sharing approach, or incentives-based approach would reliably prevent harmful interference to incumbents in the covered band, the Commission—</text>
 <paragraph id="H9C85171DC2B748898E8F2CFDB2F7BB7D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall provide notification of that determination to the appropriate committees of Congress and the NTIA; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC4E22E1323BC45D2A50B1ABA21CCFCA5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may not proceed with any action, including relocating incumbents from the covered band or permitting new entrants into the covered band, that may result in the dislodging or harming of any incumbent in the covered band until the Commission can ensure that any such action will neither cause harmful interference with nor unreasonably constrain an incumbent in the covered band.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="HA0DE31B949B849609D3A2BE31B66848B"><enum>9.</enum><header>Commission study on enhancing the benefits of unlicensed spectrum for rural communities</header>
 <subsection id="H9B6E3245F28E4DBB8C688925863F8D13"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commission shall conduct, and submit to the appropriate committees of Congress the results of, a study regarding how unlicensed spectrum can be further utilized to assist in—</text>
 <paragraph id="H2BDE6C415EB849498F7FEDBAB2AA7E10"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the provision of healthcare in rural areas;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H2A884CF4E518488EBD7D372AD98FFA15"><enum>(2)</enum><text>distance learning; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H90D6AC17AECB4E9493AE33BFC8AB2F30"><enum>(3)</enum><text>facilitating innovations in agriculture.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H43BC179295684F99A96C3B1E3A1711C9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text>The results of the study submitted under subsection (a) shall include recommendations regarding—</text>
 <paragraph id="HDB20C970147F4AD3A30A87052F024CCD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>overcoming barriers to the use of unlicensed spectrum for the purposes described in that subsection; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAB10B1E2B26949DDA69C9CD1B2A56B8E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>how to further utilize unlicensed spectrum to meet the needs of rural communities with respect to broadband Internet access service.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H6069B5083F074160B9610EF371EC845E"><enum>10.</enum><header>GAO study on Spectrum Relocation Fund allocations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct, and submit to the appropriate committees of Congress the results of, a study to determine the efficiency with which amounts in the Spectrum Relocation Fund are transferred to eligible Federal entities that willingly relocate from eligible frequencies.</text>
		</section><section id="H49CC5D7BA04941DEA13EE3FFD52B9246"><enum>11.</enum><header>Rules of construction</header>
 <subsection id="H097AC14DDF8A43828CA5C3008E6705E2"><enum>(a)</enum><header> Frequency ranges</header><text>Any frequency range described in this Act shall be construed as including the upper and lower frequency in the frequency range.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H70F03DEEFBFC457CBC0C21EA1C199A81"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Assessment of electromagnetic spectrum reallocation</header><text>Nothing in this Act may be construed as affecting any requirement under section 156 of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration Organization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/921">47 U.S.C. 921</external-xref> note).</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


