<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB4A3A6CB22FB4501ACD64AB815DA0FCC" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4917 IH: IG Subpoena Authority Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4917</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180202">February 2, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000604">Mr. Russell</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Inspector General Act of 1978 to provide testimonial subpoena authority, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HA52ED46C8D6E4F4691CF19DD1D5030D1" style="OLC">
 <section id="H4E3DFFE583DC4921851BD67880D7ED82" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>IG Subpoena Authority Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HF959AAC81E4642BCB38124016BD68740"><enum>2.</enum><header>Additional authority provisions for Inspectors General</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Inspector General Act of 1978 (5 U.S.C. App.) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HC3FD65E0A7D64AC8BF4A16897471AD5E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting after section 6 the following new section:</text> <quoted-block id="H761AA6E40D654B07B7CB1917DE3B0C4D" style="OLC"> <section id="HB31D9BDC563B4A13B008F6A365B09251"><enum>6A.</enum><header>Additional authority</header> <subsection id="HBE1AB04449E94C7B97FB18DCA2859035"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Testimonial subpoena authority</header><text>In addition to the authority otherwise provided by this Act and in accordance with the requirements of this section, each Inspector General, in carrying out the provisions of this Act (or in the case of an Inspector General or Special Inspector General not established under this Act, the provisions of the authorizing statute), is authorized to require by subpoena the attendance and testimony of witnesses as necessary in the performance of the functions assigned to the Inspector General by this Act (or in the case of an Inspector General or Special Inspector General not established under this Act, the functions assigned by the authorizing statute), which in the case of contumacy or refusal to obey, such subpoena shall be enforceable by order of any appropriate United States district court. An Inspector General may not require by subpoena the attendance and testimony of any current Federal employees, but may use other authorized procedures.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE1E51F6E30E842F6B7A65383F57EAD0A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Nondelegation</header><text>The authority to issue a subpoena under subsection (a) may not be delegated.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H7C04E9115A98471A98AA44365D8D2F94"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Panel review before issuance</header> <paragraph id="HD73A47ABE16B4F1CACC634EBA8EC153B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Approval required</header> <subparagraph id="HCF5AE67AFC7E4C249F35DF9B550BCD75"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Request for approval by subpoena panel</header><text>Before the issuance of a subpoena described in subsection (a), an Inspector General shall submit a request for approval to issue a subpoena to a panel (in this section, referred to as the <quote>Subpoena Panel</quote>), which shall be comprised of three Inspectors General of the Council of the Inspectors General on Integrity and Efficiency, who shall be designated by the Inspector General serving as Chairperson of the Council.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H584E6ECEE6474C15978680EDACD32570"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Protection from disclosure</header><text>The information contained in the request submitted by an Inspector General under subparagraph (A) and the identification of a witness shall be protected from disclosure to the extent permitted by law. Any request for disclosure of such information shall be submitted to the Inspector General requesting the subpoena.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H24830BFF3CA2432C9005A4955433BF69"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Time to respond</header>
 <subparagraph id="H7CA523C58B264D349C096D931A358F1B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the Subpoena Panel shall approve or deny a request for approval to issue a subpoena not later than 10 days after the submission of such request.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5CF8A1C359EF4C30975121A3236B210A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional information for panel</header><text>If the Subpoena Panel determines that additional information is necessary to approve or deny such request, the Subpoena Panel shall request such information and shall approve or deny such request not later than 20 days after the submission of such request.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA47FF3CE54834A65AE35479E2617CA5C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Denial by panel</header><text>If a majority of the Subpoena Panel denies the approval of a subpoena, that subpoena may not be issued.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H54BC46C67E914C18A0462024B3F169F2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Notice to Attorney General</header>
 <paragraph id="H1BA5BB2B7F53422FA34616C97B6C93B9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Subpoena Panel approves a subpoena under subsection (c), the Inspector General shall notify the Attorney General that the Inspector General intends to issue the subpoena.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H58FF7AC54A5145CD94511F9E8498BCDD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Denial for interference with an ongoing investigation</header><text>Not later than 10 days after the date on which the Attorney General is notified pursuant to paragraph (1), the Attorney General may object to the issuance of the subpoena because the subpoena will interfere with an ongoing investigation and the subpoena may not be issued.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA9608E0BFA4045B3BEE5A12ADE5055C7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Issuance of subpoena approved</header><text>If the Attorney General does not object to the issuance of the subpoena during the 10-day period described in paragraph (2), the Inspector General may issue the subpoena.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4626FE8D7F7F4C80BA4F8C59D72A8947"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Chairperson of the Council of the Inspectors General on Integrity and Efficiency, in consultation with the Attorney General, shall prescribe regulations to carry out the purposes of this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H08739E6E9AE6486D97C7F2329457000F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Inspector General defined</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>Inspector General</term> includes each Inspector General established under this Act and each Inspector General or Special Inspector General not established under this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H2995F7963C38443F8D12C473D1887C99"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The provisions of this section shall not affect the exercise of authority by an Inspector General of testimonial subpoena authority established under another provision of law.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3FEBA5602F8F4BBEB83395B09B8D4881"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 5(a)—</text> <subparagraph id="HC7A5264BDB0345E7BD65D4EF5153A1ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (21)(B), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5515534A2DA04302B9C3B411C57FE5A4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (22), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A4BBECA45354B84A2D53E9CF985697D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H40070FC2F2CA4214AE994C80EF9E373C" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="HC69569087DA84C99B6F98B274512323A"><enum>(23)</enum><text>a description of the use of subpoenas for the attendance and testimony of certain witnesses authorized under section 6A.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H59CB87EE61B84E6B946D3ACDB9106D7C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 8G(g)(1), by inserting <quote>6A,</quote> before <quote>and 7</quote>.</text> </paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

