<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H124C251DE12745A496DCD819193E773A" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4892 IH: Collaborative Water and Soil Enhancement Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4892</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180129">January 29, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000455">Ms. Fudge</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Food Security Act of 1985 with respect to nutrient and soil health management and
			 source water protection, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H6D9E904A5D084693B44A0BCAAAE64621" style="OLC">
 <section id="H9CF98ABDFB7D45ED95A5047F6E9E9AFD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Collaborative Water and Soil Enhancement Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H3C556E75F77448029D3D04FED84DA7D0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Nutrient and soil health management</header> <subsection id="H31DEE0BA028C42F2B56DDF3FE1B4A994"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1244 of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3844">16 U.S.C. 3844</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H38E7B84677C34A2BA36E61D937706639" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="HBB1CA3B467474F1BB7BC308C8A6BCDF8"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Nutrient and soil health management</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the conservation stewardship program and the environmental quality incentives program, the Secretary shall enroll not less than 5 million acres annually, in watersheds where nutrient delivery to hypoxic zones is highest, to provide payments to producers for conservation activities or practices that promote nutrient and soil health management, as determined by the Secretary.</text>
					</subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HAD03BAE0883941D4B0AA6286A14B4882"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1242(e) of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3842">16 U.S.C. 3842(e)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBDF52702F9B543F7B8C31C779927502B" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="HC5E113294B4142B0A6841B81BD3D92F7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Certified crop advisors</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide a streamlined certification process under this subsection for third-party providers that have a 4R Nutrient Management Specialty Certification or a Sustainability Specialty Certification from the American Society of Agronomy.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection></section><section id="H0CAB257D4973435FB0E16A153A094B56"><enum>3.</enum><header>Source water protection through targeting of agriculture practices</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1244 of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3844">16 U.S.C. 3844</external-xref>), as amended by section 2, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAADBFC9927B94818A513775EC1CC7520" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="HBA84FF17F0D7433885D221A1C6DDC8B7"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Source water protection</header>
 <paragraph id="H8B9C6A496BCF44529109D7CBA49884CC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the conservation stewardship program and the environmental quality incentives program, the Secretary shall encourage practices that relate to water quality or water quantity that protect source waters for drinking water (including protecting against public health threats) while also benefitting agricultural producers.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H19274FD4DB3642B8AB1CA31FE3FFFD19"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Collaboration with drinking water utilities and increased incentives</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In encouraging practices under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H2D9DB2E7356F4AD8A7F9AEF99491B073"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">work collaboratively with community water systems and State technical committees established under section 1261 to identify, in each State, local priority areas for the protection of source waters for drinking water; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1BB336DBC062463AA8050947FC62BCA8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for practices that relate to water quality or water quantity that result in benefits that primarily occur outside of the land on which the practices are implemented, offer increased incentives and higher cost-share rates to producers than are otherwise statutorily authorized through the conservation stewardship program and the environmental quality incentives program.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8F8C6BF14D44DF08B56938EBDA6C2A8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reservation of funds and acres</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023, the Secretary shall use not less than 10 percent of any funds or acres available with respect to the conservation stewardship program and the environmental quality incentives program, in carrying out this subsection, to target the most effective practices for improving the quality or quantity of source water.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA1A9CDF467FA4BE69664966152B5B1A8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In carrying out this subsection, the Secretary shall give priority—</text> <subparagraph id="HD09EFBAEF6E84C97B9973240924D2012"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to practices determined by the Secretary, using the Conservation Practices Physical Effects matrix developed by the Secretary, to be the most effective; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D323644760C46449FFA04242C6B71AC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to practices implemented in local priority areas identified under paragraph (2)(A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section></legis-body></bill> 

