<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HB60E98E3508249FBA7E2AE6DB70C4340" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5796 IH: Responsible Education Achieves Care and Healthy Outcomes for Users’ Treatment Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5796</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180515">May 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001107">Mr. Curbelo of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Health and Human Services to provide grants for eligible entities to
			 provide technical assistance to outlier prescribers of opioids.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H0BF8754086B54D19BD482BF7B47B0263" style="OLC">
 <section id="H1F902E04D0704E2DB867862E6739AF94" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Responsible Education Achieves Care and Healthy Outcomes for Users’ Treatment Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>REACH OUT Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H75B8D9A14EF74111B0DAE820FE183EF5" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grants to provide technical assistance to outlier prescribers of opioids</header> <subsection id="H0319A708CD2E4BBFB131A35911E08ACE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall, through the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services, award grants, contracts, or cooperative agreements to eligible entities for the purposes described in subsection (b).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H4410C8805B664DBBA17B5909985EFE90"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Grants, contracts, and cooperative agreements awarded under subsection (a) shall be used to support eligible entities through technical assistance—</text>
 <paragraph id="H4AEBB7EF64FE42ADA2CDE15B14418CB2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to educate and provide outreach to outlier prescribers of opioids about best practices for prescribing opioids;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFE70305B644949FFA5BC44A1FF1D937C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to educate and provide outreach to outlier prescribers of opioids about non-opioid pain management therapies; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE43DFDF7FDFF47FCBE5FDCAFB1027BAB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to reduce the amount of opioid prescriptions prescribed by outlier prescribers of opioids.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H03BB90AC7F714D828742D4B33377355B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>Each eligible entity seeking to receive a grant, contract, or cooperative agreement under subsection (a) shall submit to the Secretary an application, at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H61894AFC0DB447DA98CCC037D2E6EC6D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Geographic distribution</header><text>In awarding grants, contracts, and cooperative agreements under this section, the Secretary shall prioritize establishing technical assistance resources in each State.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H6F22EA21DC834ED2AC2751A0F63BB740"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H0EAF0BC962744403969D43E6910064E8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <quote>eligible entity</quote> means—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H309A1009DAE043E0AE5B96FBAF51CFEF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an organization—</text> <clause id="H534F47DFC0174545BF02DB5DC37CAB49"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that has demonstrated experience providing technical assistance to health care professionals on a State or regional basis; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H3A5AD7A9D70248D89C90EAD68C51E916"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that has at least—</text> <subclause id="H811D6E1FC33846E1A5A583A8A113A4CD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>one individual who is a representative of consumers on its governing body; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HC84CB69F23F442F98DE572B57399E26B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>one individual who is a representative of health care providers on its governing body; or</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H38BA4AC6A39E4C01BE7A4FFA8CF96BCC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an entity that is a quality improvement entity with a contract under part B of title XI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320c">42 U.S.C. 1320c</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A62BABC56CB44F79D769BD6C3067316"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Outlier prescriber of opioids</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>outlier prescriber of opioids</quote> means a prescriber, identified by the Secretary of Health and Human Services (through use of prescriber information provided by prescriber National Provider Identifiers included pursuant to section 1860D–4(c)(4)(A) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-104">42 U.S.C. 1395w–104(c)(4)(A)</external-xref>) on claims for covered part D drugs for part D eligible individuals enrolled in prescription drug plans under part D of title XVIII of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-101">42 U.S.C. 1395w–101</external-xref> et seq.) and MA–PD plans under part C of such title (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-21">42 U.S.C. 1395w–21</external-xref> et seq.)) as prescribing, as compared to other prescribers in the specialty of the prescriber and geographic area, amounts of opioids in excess of a threshold (and other criteria) specified by the Secretary, after consultation with stakeholders.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE2A3C7D4B33844FA844C7214B7345686"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prescribers</header><text>The term <quote>prescriber</quote> means any health care professional, including a nurse practitioner or physician assistant, who is licensed to prescribe opioids by the State or territory in which such professional practices.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5CDC81A156B14B25A30F3C4DD48AF734"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of implementing this section, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall provide for the transfer from the Federal Supplementary Medical Insurance Trust Fund established under section 1841 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395t">42 U.S.C. 1395t</external-xref>) to the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services Program Management Account of $100,000,000 for fiscal year 2019. Amounts transferred under this subparagraph shall remain available until expended.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


