<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H69B0C7D342054051A8D253A21D1E046B" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5227 IH: Preventing Rogue and Foreign Actors From Evading Sanctions Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5227</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180308">March 8, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001187">Mr. Meadows</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="Z000017">Mr. Zeldin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a report and strategy with respect to virtual currencies and other related emerging
			 technologies being used to evade sanctions, finance terrorism, and launder
			 monetary instruments, and threaten United States national security, and
			 for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H9519377A269E4306900EBFA934AB769F" style="OLC">
 <section id="H967EC6AEF5EF41239505A6E8CFB2B368" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Preventing Rogue and Foreign Actors From Evading Sanctions Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H1CB01554C5784DE49A4EE9040FF05418"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report and strategy with respect to virtual currencies and other related emerging technologies</header> <subsection id="H33E338FE0F014F49A12FCB9639E11CEC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President, acting through the Secretary of Treasury and in consultation with the Attorney General, the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Homeland Security, the Director of National Intelligence, the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, and the appropriate Federal banking agencies and Federal functional regulators, shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H024FABDC27BA450AAAAE60E154121884"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that identifies and describes the potential uses of virtual currencies and other related emerging technologies by states, non-state actors, and foreign terrorist organizations to evade sanctions, finance terrorism, or launder monetary instruments, and threaten United States national security; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HADA2A3758F4E479C994E9C0FADBE41AC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and submit to the appropriate congressional committees a strategy to mitigate and prevent such illicit use of virtual currencies and other related emerging technologies.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H029CBF9148C2442E9081A019D79B2A2D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form; public availability</header>
 <paragraph id="H6339F68E849F4AE2B8488502D99CB10F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report and strategy required under subsection (a) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HEA0032DCF93E47ECB6AA3D4EDC54F864"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The unclassified portion of such report and strategy shall be made available to the public and posted on the internet website of the Department of Treasury—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HD27BF1326C1746E398605ADCAA357978"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in pre-compressed, easily downloadable versions that are made available in all appropriate formats; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E7B801994BD4F52BB6D7BE008320F64"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in machine-readable format, if applicable.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H670C3D7486FC4099BB84905E8AA88623"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sources of information</header><text>In preparing the report and strategy required under subsection (a), the President may utilize any credible publication, database, web-based resource, and any credible information compiled by any government agency, nongovernmental organization, or other entity that is made available to the President.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H0816AD2914B44253A5CFB922806641BB"><enum>3.</enum><header>Briefing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury shall brief the appropriate congressional committees on the implementation of the strategy required under section 2.</text>
 </section><section id="H73D38C2A97D84BB9B5648340EC824998"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HF5AAD4C0E6FD4286921440FBC586E9E6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H3534E2B9B4F74E87BCC948F1C86DD997"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Financial Services, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence, and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE8B446A43AA4057A9660BDAE2BB2304"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Select Committee on Intelligence, and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE28B46ED20AC450EA6B06A735F605025"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate Federal banking agencies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>appropriate Federal banking agencies</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813</external-xref>).</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H93A93512D0B64A06947C48FBD124A070"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Virtual currency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>virtual currency</quote> means a currency that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H69C1098588054AB9ADB31654F840140A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a digital representation of value that can be digitally traded;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF65F109D97B44414B971B3D1C31B351F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is used as a medium of exchange, unit of account, or store, of value; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HD876837FD1F047418850F0DFB3C92B97"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is not used to be a legal tender, whether or not denominated in legal tender.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D4A832AA348453DA603EDFBCD38A1CD"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federal functional regulator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Federal functional regulator</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 509 of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/6809">15 U.S.C. 6809</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC7CFA00AD8FC4820818D1573E3D42FB8"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Foreign terrorist organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>foreign terrorist organization</quote> means an organization that is designated as a foreign terrorist organization under section 219 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189</external-xref>).</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


