<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HF00D34B4E35F41A48D590FA712FC5599" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4832 IH: Restoring Economic Strength and Telecommunications Operations by Releasing Expected Dollars Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4832</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180118">January 18, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001096">Mr. Cramer</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Communications Act of 1934 to clarify that an eligible telecommunications carrier may
			 use high cost universal service support to aid in the restoration of
			 telecommunications capabilities in an area in which the President has
			 declared a major disaster or emergency and may elect to receive an advance
			 payment of such support.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HB54B1FE05B4B47FB96D86219D8AE5CBD" style="OLC">
 <section id="H57C5935FA170497ABFB220F3E28D3074" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Restoring Economic Strength and Telecommunications Operations by Releasing Expected Dollars Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>RESTORED Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="HD86F195AEC45444F825EB3BA58985380"><enum>2.</enum><header>Use of high cost universal service support following presidentially declared major disasters or
 emergencies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 254 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/254">47 U.S.C. 254</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE64544D3B613496892959C96C0901C13" style="OLC">
				<subsection id="H27FFDA1772474B8185D4B8843F860AE7"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Use of high cost universal service support following presidentially declared major disasters or
			 emergencies</header>
 <paragraph id="HF33E8466CB674C63B91D677029DDFEFE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Use of support</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered telecommunications carrier may use high cost support received with respect to a covered area to aid in the restoration of telecommunications capabilities in such area if such carrier—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H4098C1CB81D348F8A309259A0A8451C8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>repairs its network as rapidly and widely as possible to restore service; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H807F2CBF970343CF8293CC9562807780"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">uses such support for such restoration only in a covered area that is substantially unserved by facilities-based providers of residential fixed voice and broadband service that do not receive high cost support.</text>
						</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A447F3669A44979B0DDC8276C952A58"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Advance payments</header>
 <subparagraph id="H086A06B4BBAF41BD9BCE8257EA924C03"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If a covered telecommunications carrier makes an election described in subparagraph (B) with respect to a covered area, the Commission shall provide to such carrier in the form of a single advance payment the high cost support that, in the absence of such election, such carrier would have received with respect to such area over the number of months specified in such election.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF8E804787BE347B79EEA7C33DB460D98"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Election</header><text>The election described in this subparagraph is an election—</text> <clause id="HD8259536079A4CDD9964AE2F5B29C201"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by a covered telecommunications carrier to receive high cost support with respect to a covered area for a number of months specified in the election (not to exceed 7 months) in the form of a single advance payment; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H80B83BDA527A45C4910EB31A62FF4A5A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that is made not later than 30 days after the President has declared a major disaster or emergency under the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5121">42 U.S.C. 5121</external-xref> et seq.) with respect to such area.</text>
							</clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H81ED1120A3BE4C02BE9061410B3A6829"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header>
 <subparagraph id="H7464F9D5F69044D7B5E2688BD7B84F6E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Covered area</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered area</quote> means an area with respect to which the President has declared a major disaster or emergency under the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5121">42 U.S.C. 5121</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD66C17D87D8744A1A758F7002BF99895"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Covered telecommunications carrier</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered telecommunications carrier</quote> means an eligible telecommunications carrier designated under section 214(e) that receives high cost support with respect to a covered area.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0A2567C87DE4550B3D2C29DCBE6DFD2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>High cost support</header><text>The term <quote>high cost support</quote> means universal service support for high cost areas under subpart D of part 54 of title 47, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


