<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H7FDE9A3B01B04BFA92CC15912C0558EE" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5066 IH: State Assistance for Tropical Floriculture Research Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5066</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180216">February 16, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000571">Ms. Gabbard</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="H001050">Ms. Hanabusa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Agriculture to establish a grant program to make grants to State
			 departments of agriculture for the research and development of disease
			 resistant varieties of tropical flowers.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HF097C5A84ABF403FAD89786FBE5DC98D" style="OLC">
 <section id="H822B4E042BBA45D2B3AAF9BE95A49CAA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>State Assistance for Tropical Floriculture Research Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H0FB07E35113040CC950AE0992159D71D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H41764A6D4BC049D79A876AA01EE63932"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Tropical flowers contribute a natural and beautiful element to human environments, retain cultural, historic, and ceremonial significance to native peoples and others, and sustain an agricultural economy that employs thousands of Americans.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H643B92722FC548CAA494EC8EEDD1B230"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Given the value of tropical flowers, the public stands to benefit from scientific research that protects these flowers against diseases.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H4B8C1CACB0CB4316A9097E3944883C6A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Tropical floriculture research grant program</header>
			<subsection id="HFD71C4CB40CC476C9A9663A420F3A694"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program established</header>
 <paragraph id="HBBC74BA9B28846F2B89D4387F99D8DDC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture shall establish and carry out a grant program to make grants, on a competitive basis, to State departments of agriculture for the research and development of disease resistant varieties of tropical flowers.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFA878302F4544FDC9178B54546A20A4C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minimum amount of grant</header><text>A grant awarded under this subsection may not be less than $250,000 for a fiscal year.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7623BC4FE130413AAC82538F094AE27E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, a State department of agriculture shall submit an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary of Agriculture may require, including the State department of agriculture’s plan to research and develop disease resistant varieties of tropical flowers.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD7F18435EF6B43EF86B9B708A1269DC6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Temporary ineligibility for subsequent grants</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture shall determine a State department of agriculture to be ineligible to receive a grant payment under this section for a fiscal year if the Secretary determines that the State department of agriculture did not comply with the plan submitted under subsection (b).</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HE7B937E16DE8412BAC0D75AE5E9F3540"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Audit</header>
 <paragraph id="H72347E644DAD4D4A931CF7FB1B5704E3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Audit required</header><text>For each year in which a State department of agriculture receives a grant under this section, the State department of agriculture shall conduct an audit of the use of such grant funds.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H160EBD9BD2204B00A50039503DD502A0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Submission of audit</header><text>Not later than 30 days after an audit is completed pursuant to paragraph (1), the State department of agriculture shall submit such audit to the Secretary of Agriculture.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD31770FE16B54067B4C1F92749D4C84D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $10,000,000 for fiscal years 2018 through 2020.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


