<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H3ECBD01C4F4E4B6C94B64C54BE0E948C" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5119 IH: Partnerships for Progress and Prosperity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5119</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180227">February 27, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000454">Mr. Foster</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000577">Mr. Ryan of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000598">Mr. Polis</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Education to carry out a STEM grant program.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H485E3EAEECCD4F62A620D92AB70B449F" style="OLC">
 <section id="H074E19DDED754A11B66A6DC3434367A0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Partnerships for Progress and Prosperity Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>P3 Act</short-title></quote> .</text> </section><section id="H4BFAC7B5950D4FAAA1EDF0E7D05AF387"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HBB2DF6E0A6E24AEA8C95AB341349634F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As part of their Blueprint for Action researchers at Harvard Graduate School of Education and the Pathways to Prosperity Network recommend creating programs designed to <quote>combine work and academic learning in post-secondary career preparation</quote>. In a follow-up study to the original <quote>Pathways to Prosperity</quote> published by Harvard’s Graduate School of Education in 2011, the same researchers released <quote>A Blueprint for Action</quote> in June 2014.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H107A8E64AD7B4AF1ACB2223D5A39211E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Executive Office of Science and Technology Policy have explicitly stated a goal of strengthening America’s STEM workforce.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2F47BCABC93541569286CF9960DD2392"><enum>(3)</enum><text>According to a study by the Manufacturing Institute, a national survey of United States manufacturing executives found that 83 percent of American manufacturers reported a moderate or severe shortage of skilled workers.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H42104F32CA344816ACC8BA8D520E7807"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The American Enterprise Institute further states that, <quote>According to the U.S. Department of Labor, the percentage of manufacturing workers aged 55 to 64 and the share of workers older than 65 have both significantly increased since 2000. Moreover, they also report that the median age of the manufacturing workforce increased from 40.5 in 2000 to 44.1 in 2011. The Society of Manufacturing Engineers predicts that the shortfall of skilled factory workers could increase to 3 million jobs by 2015 due to the aging manufacturing workforce and the resulting retirements of older workers, at the same time that an anticipated manufacturing rebound will increase demand for skilled workers.</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H55D689BD14484EB2B15BA3ED12A08757"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The 2012 Program for International Student Assessment found the United States below the average score of participating countries in mathematics and science. Furthermore, the United States has dropped in the rankings for mathematics achievement from 25th in 2009 to 36th in 2012.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H525ACD784FB84E6EB2C4B9BC6535CE57"><enum>(6)</enum><text>NAE, along with other peer reviewed publications and studies from universities around the country have examined the benefits of partnerships between schools and outside organizations. <short-title>Partnerships for Progress and Prosperity Act</short-title> programs as well as experiential learning play an important role in training students for the jobs of the future.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H853A694E10C6437798D24ACA9CF8729C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Grant program</header>
 <subsection id="HFCFD82F84C744E2891818AD7AC3A225B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts appropriated under subsection (h), the Secretary of Education shall award grants to eligible entities to improve the education of students in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (in this section referred to as <quote>STEM</quote>) and prepare such students to pursue undergraduate and graduate degrees and careers in such fields.</text>
 </subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HB87B4F955E9A49CD93E0F7D9AC70C328"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To receive a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, which shall include a description of—</text>
 <paragraph id="H2EC12A61214645908D5C5D16E4948DED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the local, regional, or national employer in a STEM field with which the eligible entity will partner or collaborate to carry out activities under subsection (c)(2); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAAF5053553274F539AA2EB111EC67D76"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the activities the eligible entity will carry out under subsection (c)(2) with the grant.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC1F3A4C909ED4500B41FF55CB317CA9F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header> <paragraph id="HEA24D7631BD24329809AA5F59BADDA07"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Partnership or collaboration</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall carry out at least one of the activities described in paragraph (2) in partnership or collaboration with—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H7D7EAF3AAE724CC3AA7F5C56495073E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the local, regional, or national employer described in the agency’s application under subsection (b)(1); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0CDC698386C64A4BA110283D969BE586"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an institution of higher education, in the case of an eligible entity that is a local educational agency, or a local educational agency, in the case of an eligible entity that is an institution of higher education.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H88A4DDD9DAE443E5AE9353A38E3A2909"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>The activities referred to in paragraph (1) are as follows:</text> <subparagraph id="H7CDE724937A94AD1A18738E1D12A910A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Assist students in being placed in internships or apprenticeships with the employers with whom the eligible entity is partnering or collaborating under paragraph (1)(A).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1997DAD99F464981B97B2B5CC9A155A7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Develop the curriculum and metrics of STEM coursework.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD16FB75C258C4314A19F1B514145CCCE"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Carry out dual-credit courses that offer both secondary school credit and college credit, and incorporate STEM education and STEM workplace training.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89580EF3134C4708B213A365BD6182DF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Provide tutoring in STEM coursework and mentoring programs for academic advice and assistance in discussing future career opportunities in STEM fields.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51DA86ACBE1E4C3285E6C8881D7B895D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Enable students and their teachers to attend STEM events outside the classroom.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18CE0ABEDB2D46349F25E1BE207774A7"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Provide after-school and summer STEM programs for students.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7072D29968AA445F8945B4E7C60A0BEA"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Purchase education materials or equipment to facilitate STEM instruction.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1E416B85E04D45A285700FC08CCAE369"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Awarding of grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H1773B97F84BA471FB9112E8A3862F08B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>carry out a rigorous evaluation of each eligible entity’s application under subsection (b) being considered for a grant under this section to determine whether the eligible entity demonstrates a rationale based on high-quality research findings or positive evaluation that the activity proposed to be funded with the grant is likely to improve student outcomes or other relevant outcomes; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA8312822668B4160B096E5E1B930B58C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>give special consideration to eligible entities that—</text> <subparagraph id="H76BB200D747C4214981FD0C016CB39BF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promote in-classroom engagement between STEM professionals and students, creating co-teaching and guest-teaching opportunities;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA2755313F444880B590A88B17922B98"><enum>(B)</enum><text>use technology-based instructional materials and content;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF8E32A88CD14AB0ACA097269C328F22"><enum>(C)</enum><text>pair mentors and tutors with students struggling to meet curriculum benchmarks;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82D94D68E2164C61B74433388376535A"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of eligible entities that are local educational agencies, serve schools in which the majority of students are eligible to receive free or reduced price lunch under the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1751">42 U.S.C. 1751</external-xref> et seq.); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3FAA2D777C7C442C93F590B1DC07EFEC"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">propose to use the grant to target interventions for populations that are traditionally underrepresented in STEM fields, including women, minorities, and low-income students.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAD942114261C499F81447CC173893E68"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Matching requirement</header>
 <paragraph id="H72F8BD92418F495C81A53FB323BAB253"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall provide, from non-Federal sources, an amount equal to 50 percent of the grant. Such non-Federal contribution may be provided in cash or in kind.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H08640F17F4EA4CA99AEAAFEA457F3315"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Partnership authorized</header><text>An eligible entity may partner with a public and private entity that may assist the eligible entity in meeting the matching requirement under paragraph (1).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0349CC7AFB49493A86073BB3B8E0881A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may waive all or part of the matching requirement under paragraph (1) for an eligible entity if the entity demonstrates that such requirement would result in a serious financial hardship or a financial inability to carry out the goals of the grant.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD1CA9C58527547548F730C1F6E0CB30F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Grant funds provided to an eligible entity under this section shall be used to supplement, and not supplant, funds that would otherwise be used for activities authorized under this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF103AA2C436E41A3A12A1CB1D18F75CF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H4B65FE5EE5204DC9B396CFDF383FD4F8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a local educational agency or an institution of higher education.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB9BB8DA8A33443D48B41367C6CFB34A9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text>The terms <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>poverty line</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, <term>Secretary</term>, and <term>State</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H063EB565446D46FC8C55A134A4C27841"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5C902D7B5FA64E039F1D49B267E01F31"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Low-income student</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>low-income student</term> means a student whose family’s taxable income for the preceding year did not exceed 150 percent of the poverty line.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H2E8E3839FFA141B095EDF452764DB8B1"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this section for fiscal year 2018 and each succeeding fiscal year.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


