<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H07AA716816EE44E7A3257B3A632D59E0" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5428 IH: Stand with UK against Russia Violations Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5428</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180405">April 5, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="T000463">Mr. Turner</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To impose sanctions on certain persons responsible for the March 12, 2018, attack on Sergei and
			 Yulia Skripal, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H12EE11F159FB438B95ACDCBD6F0A344C" style="OLC">
 <section id="H073F6D909EA242D9B3341AA974A3DD32" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stand with UK against Russia Violations Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H5E87876B5F5D42B4903B15445D2FCD98"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H27E480740E68432E893B4A63A9C3A135"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On March 4, 2018, Sergei V. Skripal, and his daughter, Yulia Skripal, were found unconscious on a park bench in Salisbury, England.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB57DDFA5DF72456781D97F5DB4EE3BEC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">British Prime Minister Theresa May announced on March 12, 2018, that the poison used in the attack was Novichok, a military-grade nerve agent developed by Soviet scientists for use on North Atlantic Treaty Organization troops, and that Russia was responsible for the attack.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H375ECF499C1347139C27BAC47D8B9F9E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On March 15, 2018, the United Kingdom, France, and Germany issued a joint statement holding the Government of Russia responsible for the poisoning and characterizing the attack as <quote>an assault on UK sovereignty</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HB3CB977A40F34FA79585A3EFE425D10C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text> <paragraph id="H8EDFD370690E43A29CCF6BC6C4D3579A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The attempts of the Government of Russia to commit murders on British soil are unconscionable and violate international law.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD3595B85A72D406B8398B226BA76E231"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States stands in strong solidarity with the British government and its people as they respond to this violation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD61084510F874A5B87E2B57498DE2B98"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Russian aggression must be met with strength and resolve, including through sanctions to deter future Russian attacks on dissidents, expatriates, and democratic activists.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H94B5ED245CB6473BBCA34DACDF5D169C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions with respect to Russian persons responsible for March 12 attack</header>
 <subsection id="H26332077A5464C888F93B2176EFDA529"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall impose the sanctions described in <internal-xref idref="H7A3EC47C468448F68547C80F41FDAF4D" legis-path="4.(c)">subsection (c)</internal-xref> with respect to any person that the President determines—</text>
 <paragraph id="HCC08660FBFF54808A54D2C603DD670ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>knowingly engaged in, provided material support to, worked on behalf of, or acted as an agent or instrumentality of any person who perpetrated the attack against Sergei Skripal and Yulia Skripal on March 12, 2018; or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC1686DC6631946AC8CE3A315DAAA39AD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is an officer, employee, or agent of the Government of Russia and knowingly, on or after the date of the enactment of this Act, materially assisted, worked on behalf of, or acted as an agent or instrumentality of the Russian Government in the murder, attempted murder, or assault committed outside of Russia against any expatriate, dissident, or foreign national.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE2CB6BEB6AB04C50963B79F8CE2B69D0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Concurrent report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall submit to Congress a report, concurrent with the imposition of any sanction under subsection (a), that lists each person determined to have engaged in the conduct resulting in such sanction.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H7A3EC47C468448F68547C80F41FDAF4D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text>The sanctions described in this paragraph are the sanctions described in section 224(b) of the Countering America’s Adversaries Through Sanctions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/9524">22 U.S.C. 9524(b)</external-xref>).</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H5AF737CFDCCC4E849A02900897E0B90B"><enum>5.</enum><header>Prohibition on transactions relating to new Russian sovereign debt</header>
 <subsection id="H346A269E84C740E5B6CA68D78CEF0198"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the imposition of a sanction pursuant to <internal-xref idref="HC1686DC6631946AC8CE3A315DAAA39AD" legis-path="4.(a)(2)">section 4(a)(2)</internal-xref>, the President shall—</text> <paragraph id="HE144C6C896CD433FA7E306FD239D1A0E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>issue regulations prohibiting United States persons from engaging in transactions with, providing financing for, or in any other way dealing in Russian sovereign debt that is issued on or after the date that is 180 days after such date of imposition of sanctions; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC78C2C42480844B5A5661EC29DEBDEF3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>exercise all powers granted to the President by the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> 13 et seq.) to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of one or more of the financial institutions listed in <internal-xref idref="HFC5186DCE0904EBE9AE1E9138E506326" legis-path="5.(c)">subsection (c)</internal-xref> if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H606764EC72C7407FACC928DC04BB4C08"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Russian sovereign debt defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <term>Russian sovereign debt</term> means—</text> <paragraph id="HD632B0234EBC4501AF6E19AAD62863D2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>bonds issued by the Russian Central Bank, the Russian National Wealth Fund, the Russian Federal Treasury, or agents or affiliates of any such institution, with a maturity of more than 14 days;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7A01EB4060A341ECAF7D1A9F247FE238"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">new foreign exchange swap agreements with the Russian Central Bank, the Russian National Wealth Fund, or the Russian Federal Treasury, the duration of which agreement is longer than 14 days; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAC64AF56CEE0415288D98DE80D814C42"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any other financial instrument, the duration or maturity of which is more than 14 days, that—</text> <subparagraph id="HA315322BFF124343A7A10951BC349ADC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the President determines represents the sovereign debt of Russia; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9B289B2C1EE4879BAA275B57655343A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is issued by a bank listed in <internal-xref idref="HFC5186DCE0904EBE9AE1E9138E506326" legis-path="5.(c)">subsection (c)</internal-xref>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFC5186DCE0904EBE9AE1E9138E506326"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Russian financial institutions</header><text>The financial institutions listed in this subsection are the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H6327E525B6854542B2C9E822C7C34DE7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Sberbank.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9D729639EA3B48899D3058D840AAE323"><enum>(2)</enum><text>VTB Bank.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H191B0EB4380E43819D6B8D674D626972"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Gazprombank.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H7BDDAA4E7F2849C4AC2253831B5EA150"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Bank of Moscow.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H73667ADBC95047FC86CE12114AF34B3D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Rosselkhozbank.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H843774BBC4914C3497E9A1251EBBA495"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Promsvyazbank.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H853A5A93713644FAA8E76D8746FA8516"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Vnesheconombank.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7F843353E4D347F8BD5CA1DC94EF11F8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirement To promptly publish guidance</header><text>The President shall concurrently publish guidance on the implementation of the regulations issued pursuant to <internal-xref idref="H346A269E84C740E5B6CA68D78CEF0198" legis-path="5.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref>.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H56AFCAB77E9D49E1A8696A8A37E5B6AB"><enum>6.</enum><header>Implementation; penalties; termination</header>
 <subsection id="H1F1D5EFC5E7E472B84AFDF4B9B3823C3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may exercise all authorities provided to the President under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1702">50 U.S.C. 1702</external-xref> and 1704) to carry out this Act.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HDB445E10A03941D8A7CF862F67982528"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person that violates, attempts to violate, conspires to violate, or causes a violation of section 4 or 5, or any regulation, license, or order issued to carry out such sections, shall be subject to the penalties set forth in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) to the same extent as a person that commits an unlawful act described in subsection (a) of that section.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HC197ECF9ACFA480FBA068B1A0B4187DB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Termination</header>
 <paragraph id="HDB73F063D76D4DF7A7DC0286ABF8E5C9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President may terminate the application of a sanction under <internal-xref idref="H94B5ED245CB6473BBCA34DACDF5D169C" legis-path="4.">section 4</internal-xref> or <internal-xref idref="HC78C2C42480844B5A5661EC29DEBDEF3" legis-path="5.(a)(2)">section 5(a)(2)</internal-xref> if the President submits to Congress a determination that officers, employees, and agents of the Government of Russia no longer engage in the conduct described in <internal-xref idref="HC1686DC6631946AC8CE3A315DAAA39AD" legis-path="4.(a)(2)">section 4(a)(2)</internal-xref>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE95061AF4E6B449FAED3CDA8F3365AF5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may, on or after the date on which the President submits the determination described in <internal-xref idref="HDB73F063D76D4DF7A7DC0286ABF8E5C9" legis-path="6.(c)(1)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref>, waive the prohibition imposed pursuant to <internal-xref idref="HE144C6C896CD433FA7E306FD239D1A0E" legis-path="5.(a)(1)">section 5(a)(1)</internal-xref> with respect to Russian sovereign debt (as defined in such section) issued on or after such date if the President concurrently submits to Congress a notification that includes a justification of the basis for waiving such prohibition.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA2699BECB46845679B83AE5C3C772F00"><enum>7.</enum><header>United States person defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the term <term>United States person</term> means—</text> <paragraph id="HC20CBC342AB441C8B90C9388183E94D6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a United States citizen or an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence to the United States; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBED72977E8F64574822B34040F1B788E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an entity organized under the laws of the United States or of any jurisdiction within the United States, including a foreign branch of such an entity.</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


