<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HE94C45CE0E06412BA0599C3C9A66C44D" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4948 IH: National Fab Lab Network Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4948</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180206">February 6, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000454">Mr. Foster</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001184">Mr. Massie</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide a Federal charter to the Fab Foundation for the National Fab Lab Network, a national
			 network of local digital fabrication facilities providing universal access
			 to advanced manufacturing tools for learning skills, developing
			 inventions, creating businesses, and producing personalized products, and
			 for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H3D733E3107F44DCDBBE9A86EB3FC124E" style="OLC">
 <section id="HA66145C3C15C41A0BCA8C9CD0B04BB14" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Fab Lab Network Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H587B456928C1451EAFA663BF02E74C4F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H7ED07EF1803E427B86D518B39269B1FE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Scientific discoveries and technical innovations are critical to the economic and national security of the United States.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF427783756A547A091B3AE1B2370FEA7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Maintaining the leadership of the United States in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics will require a diverse population with the skills, interest, and access to tools required to advance these fields.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H438206D126454E538B9D764E8D10D77C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Just as earlier digital revolutions in communications and computation provided individuals with the Internet and personal computers, a digital revolution in fabrication will allow anyone to make almost anything, anywhere.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H77BB9AE5DE1C494EA96179E610DB004A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>These creations include communications devices, solar powered housing, consumer products, and new kinds of machines and tools for advanced manufacturing.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9776226F90DF4D3CADCE4C607FF23180"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Center for Bits and Atoms of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (CBA) has contributed significantly to the advancement of these goals through its work in creating and advancing digital fabrication facilities, or <quote>fab labs</quote> in the United States and abroad.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3A5F9DC484924BF38257DD4325369F3F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>MakerSpaces, TechShops, and other creative platforms also facilitate access to digital fabrication capabilities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3414F0D69EC84CBBA21570A8C442640B"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The fab labs of the Center for Bits and Atoms provide a model for a new kind of national laboratory that links local facilities for advanced manufacturing, providing universal access, and empowering communities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2335839A680C491E9B74BD94566325BF"><enum>(8)</enum><text>A coordinated national public-private partnership will be the most effective way to accelerate the provision of this universal infrastructure for learning skills, developing inventions, creating businesses, and producing personalized products.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H4B19A90C0DF746A78CFD217D186BEBFD"><enum>3.</enum><header>Federal charter for National Fab Lab network</header>
 <subsection id="H9D50BDC474F7404BB291B95168A4021E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part B of subtitle II of title 36, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new chapter:</text>
				<quoted-block id="H1D01ABF619B1425F8D4E4D0F5D63D0F4" style="USC">
					<chapter id="HD78AE6C7E818492882F9B0F4FC9FAB24"><enum>2501</enum><header>National Fab Lab Network</header>
						<toc>
							<toc-entry idref="HD78AE6C7E818492882F9B0F4FC9FAB24" level="chapter">CHAPTER 2501—National Fab Lab Network</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry level="section">Sec. </toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="H3CBD936150ED46088F67D4AAAB49040E" level="section">250101. Definitions.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="HF3F0D1B3E24C4AD889A51BAC1AEDB7D6" level="section">250102. Organization.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="H8A8198C37C2F47F5A83C10AD3BD319D4" level="section">250103. Purposes and goals.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="H3A868E21D90B41FA991C0B8E69CB7369" level="section">250104. Membership and organization.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="H667EE5B75DB646D48BF0348D8320749E" level="section">250105. Governing body.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="HAD09A49353F3413696C82FE7B1C49FC1" level="section">250106. Powers.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="HAAF4EE7A8A33449FACD6975721C884D2" level="section">250107. Restrictions.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="HEE1E0C33880740FB83A53CB7DE8AA66B" level="section">250108. Records and inspection.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="H0E6CD8CE85B94744B20F5B68624A37CA" level="section">250109. Duty to maintain tax exempt status.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="HD012DF3E8E254B55BF484E931FA9A0BD" level="section">250110. Liability for acts of officers and agents.</toc-entry>
							<toc-entry idref="H1E965139D71F41FC9D70C3EEC9F95835" level="section">250111. Annual report.</toc-entry></toc>
 <section id="H3CBD936150ED46088F67D4AAAB49040E"><enum>250101.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this chapter:</text> <paragraph id="H50DD2E32211944028D64BBFF153C7425"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Corporation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>corporation</term> means the National Fab Lab Network.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H223A7D324C994A4DB218D9C10C99B1AB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fab lab</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>fab lab</term> means a facility that is—</text> <subparagraph id="H1575ED8322A548F7B96B41C5807A444E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>equipped with a standard integrated suite of fabrication tools that can convert digital designs into functional physical things;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93351938C34E48D5961A7C00647C0785"><enum>(B)</enum><text>equipped with scanning tools to convert physical things into digital designs; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF40669FBE5374A7393890F0048A9B4A3"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">made accessible to the general public, allowing for necessary fees.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HF3F0D1B3E24C4AD889A51BAC1AEDB7D6"><enum>250102.</enum><header>Organization</header>
 <subsection id="H70B07A7B23624E0EB7F5A03C83B53663"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Redesignation</header><text>The Fab Foundation shall be known as the National Fab Lab Network.</text> </subsection><subsection id="HAFD6579E510A4776B45D42BD66D2A1C4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal charter</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The National Fab Lab Network is a federally chartered corporation.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H103D8633270D451C884BB051C5CD2F9A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Perpetual existence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise provided, the corporation shall have perpetual succession.</text> </subsection></section><section id="H8A8198C37C2F47F5A83C10AD3BD319D4"><enum>250103.</enum><header>Purposes and goals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes and goals of the corporation are as follows:</text>
 <paragraph id="H577EA2A56B6446BEAFCD24563844329C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To create a national network of connected local fab labs to empower individuals and communities in the United States.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8AAAA9D7ED3345269319F830B4927AB3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To foster the use of distributed digital fabrication tools to promote science, technology, engineering and math skills, increase invention and innovation, create businesses and jobs, and fulfill personal, professional, and community needs.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA5A9D019546D435889DA6610CCDB41A3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>To serve as a resource to assist stakeholders with the effective operation of fab labs.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HA393EBAE838D4C94879C3E6555846A64"><enum>(4)</enum><text>To provide a platform for education, research, and for catalyzing new methods in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics education.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H189C0C0E707843E9AFC198FEC59E56E6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>To create new ways of educating the workforce that will enable workers to compete in a 21st century global marketplace.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCCFC1953EB904D3596C1728938FA0557"><enum>(6)</enum><text>To seek to establish at least one fab lab per every 700,000 individuals in the United States in the first 10 years of its operation, corresponding to availability in all 435 Congressional districts and to provide guidelines for their sustainable operation.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H3A868E21D90B41FA991C0B8E69CB7369"><enum>250104.</enum><header>Membership and organization</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Except as provided in this chapter, eligibility for membership in the corporation and the rights and privileges of members are as provided in the constitution and bylaws of the corporation.</text>
 </section><section id="H667EE5B75DB646D48BF0348D8320749E"><enum>250105.</enum><header>Governing body</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Directors, officers, and other staff of the corporation, and their powers and duties are as provided in the bylaws of the corporation.</text>
 </section><section id="HAD09A49353F3413696C82FE7B1C49FC1"><enum>250106.</enum><header>Powers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The corporation may—</text> <paragraph id="HE5425C69CA734FEEBD690172B4F1BAF0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>coordinate the creation of a national network of local fab labs in the United States;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0785246BCAF244728926BB9C8ED1B795"><enum>(2)</enum><text>issue guidelines for the sustainable operation of fab labs;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HD6A2B19974C14873B2326048D4DA3EA2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>serve as a resource for organizations and communities seeking to create fab labs by providing information, assessing suitability, advising on the lab lifecycle, and maintaining descriptions of prospective and operating sites;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE3B1A9E1EBEB4CA8B2B16547E22C9926"><enum>(4)</enum><text>accept funds from private individuals, organizations, government agencies, or other organizations;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HAD6FD41F60984A69851EE99797E63EAE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>distribute funds to other nonprofit organizations to establish and operate fab labs as members of the corporation;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD21A545479A44177AB76138CF57C0073"><enum>(6)</enum><text>facilitate communication between other nonprofit organizations seeking to join the corporation with operational entities that can source and install fab labs, provide training, assist with operations, account for spending, and assess impact;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H73A249E861C946968DCD7AD374152842"><enum>(7)</enum><text>communicate the benefits available through membership in the corporation to communities and the public;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1166443B237644E8B04A001E791C0385"><enum>(8)</enum><text>facilitate and participate in synergistic programs, including workforce training, job creation, researching the broader impacts of such programs, and the production of civic infrastructure;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4112F87967EC4661BB34880230D32636"><enum>(9)</enum><text>amend a constitution and bylaws for the management of its property and the regulation of its affairs;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H88ADAF3191024CC7A04270F0FC875CBC"><enum>(10)</enum><text>choose directors, officers, trustees, managers, employees, and agents as the activities of the corporation require;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE8224552D1AC408091446671E8867014"><enum>(11)</enum><text>make contracts;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HDBCE4C0A638B430AB8EB9B8C85C9B118"><enum>(12)</enum><text>acquire, own, lease, encumber, and transfer property as necessary or convenient to carry out the purposes of the corporation;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H03C326B14FA747019B9A4E2C2567AE55"><enum>(13)</enum><text>borrow money, issue instruments of indebtedness, and secure its obligations by granting security interests in its property;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDEF9085C4530439D8A7086DF28D98C3F"><enum>(14)</enum><text>charge and collect membership dues and subscription fees; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H396DA4895F0C4B5EB4C42892355CE7FB"><enum>(15)</enum><text>sue and be sued.</text>
							</paragraph></section><section id="HAAF4EE7A8A33449FACD6975721C884D2"><enum>250107.</enum><header>Restrictions</header>
 <subsection id="HF371C567A3BF411BB5FE7A5E7EAE6E1A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Stock and dividends</header><text>The corporation may not issue securities of any kind or declare or pay a dividend.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H508F22B2A03B44929611F7B4F2FD3A78"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Distribution of income or assets</header><text>The income or assets of the corporation may not inure to the benefit of, or be distributed to, a director, officer, or member during the life of the charter of the corporation under this chapter. This subsection does not prevent the payment of reasonable compensation to an officer or reimbursement for actual necessary expenses in amounts approved by the board of directors.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H727FF29278B148CBA6AAAFF4DEDC5AED"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Loans</header><text>The corporation may not make a loan to a director, officer, or employee.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H96F3824E78754A88BF56320195C88408"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Claim of governmental approval or authority</header><text>The corporation may not claim congressional approval or the authority of the United States Government for any of its activities.</text>
							</subsection></section><section id="HEE1E0C33880740FB83A53CB7DE8AA66B"><enum>250108.</enum><header>Records and inspection</header>
 <subsection id="H4E27040908814EAC993FEF72566D5BC5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Records</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The corporation shall keep—</text> <paragraph id="HD86C93F73731475CAB87D2DE10FFA404"><enum>(1)</enum><text>correct and complete records of account;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE695F4494A4042E0AC7C7D38EBA2DAC8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>minutes of the proceedings of its members, board of directors, and committees having any of the authority of its board of directors; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H96D807D89A054C9F897260D335FB6218"><enum>(3)</enum><text>at its principal office, a record of the names and addresses of its members entitled to vote.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H62258DF944924E688CB6B4BAEE2E2FA6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inspections</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A member entitled to vote, or an agent or attorney of the member, may inspect the records of the corporation for any proper purpose, at any reasonable time.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H0E6CD8CE85B94744B20F5B68624A37CA"><enum>250109.</enum><header>Duty to maintain tax exempt status</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The corporation shall maintain its status as an organization exempt from taxation under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1">26 U.S.C. 1</external-xref> et seq.).</text>
 </section><section id="HD012DF3E8E254B55BF484E931FA9A0BD"><enum>250110.</enum><header>Liability for acts of officers and agents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The corporation is liable for the acts of its officers and agents acting within the scope of their authority.</text>
 </section><section id="H1E965139D71F41FC9D70C3EEC9F95835"><enum>250111.</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not less frequently than once each year, the corporation shall submit to Congress, including specifically to the <committee-name committee-id="SSCM00">Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate</committee-name> and the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives</committee-name>, a report on the activities of the corporation during the prior fiscal year. The report shall be submitted at the same time as the report of the audit required by section 10101 of this title. The report may not be printed as a public document.</text></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H43162CD44B16424C86637299CCD5337C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of chapters at the beginning of subtitle II of such title is amended by inserting after the item relating to chapter 2401 the following new item:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H389886BD974143C08374534087AF40D6" style="OLC">
					<table align-to-level="section" blank-lines-before="1" colsep="0" frame="none" line-rules="no-gen" rowsep="0" rule-weights="0.0.0.0.0.0" table-template-name="Flush/hang, 1 text, 1 num, bold hds" table-type="Leaderwork">
						<tgroup cols="2" rowsep="0"><colspec coldef="txt" colname="column1" colwidth="296.25pt" min-data-value="55"></colspec><colspec coldef="fig" colname="column2" colwidth="54.50pt" min-data-value="9"></colspec>
							<tbody>
								<row><entry align="left" colname="column1" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr">2501. National Fab Lab Network</entry><entry align="right" colname="column2" leader-modify="clr-ldr" rowsep="0"> 250101</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


