<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H21FFC161B77A4DBF83B44A367B96F330" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4784 IH: Affordable Care Act Outreach for the Uninsured, Transformative Recruitment, and Enrollment Action for Compassionate Healthcare Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4784</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180111">January 11, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Maxine Waters of California</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson of Indiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Danny K. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000627">Mrs. Demings</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000324">Mr. Hastings</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000248">Mr. Serrano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000486">Ms. Roybal-Allard</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001251">Mr. Butterfield</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000288">Mr. Ellison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000087">Mrs. Carolyn B. Maloney of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000580">Ms. Michelle Lujan Grisham of New Mexico</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000579">Mr. Lowenthal</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act to provide funding for American Health
			 Benefit Exchanges navigator programs and outreach and promotional
			 activities.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HEE25FB1FF8204364A89B4786D7F07AE8" style="OLC">
 <section id="H8FA95F5766944E73900A87BFD7E5BB6F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Affordable Care Act Outreach for the Uninsured, Transformative Recruitment, and Enrollment Action for Compassionate Healthcare Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ACA OUTREACH Act</short-title></quote>.</text>
		</section><section id="HE2F20981D3DA4EB79F178D86AD39A769"><enum>2.</enum><header>Funding American Health Benefit Exchanges navigator programs and outreach and promotional
			 activities</header>
 <subsection id="H9BB9E10785A74C1CB01ED252F43D0F90"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Funding for navigator program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1311(i) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18031">42 U.S.C. 18031(i)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35404C6617DF4D8AA5431B3A0EB15152" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H77010DDA9F324AEA9088FAD724197416"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Out of any funds in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, there is appropriated to the Secretary of Health and Human Services $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2018 through 2021 for navigator programs under this subsection.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HE74FDFCF6D86449D8455BF9A7CD940FB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal Exchanges outreach and promotional activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1321(c) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18041">42 U.S.C. 18041(c)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDAA5DA04ED094DCEBBE92FCAA19F0011" style="OLC">
					<paragraph id="H6F26C3D518B74BA38E7EE1029A2D926D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Outreach and promotional activities</header>
 <subparagraph id="HC89568C922CC491597CEC9CC3AB24470"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an Exchange established or operated by the Secretary pursuant to this subsection, the Secretary may carry out outreach and promotional activities as necessary and appropriate for the successful operation of such Exchange, including for purposes of informing potential enrollees in qualified health plans offered through the Exchange of the availability of coverage under such plans and financial assistance for coverage under such plans.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46AB76485D6F4655BED57F273C104008"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Diverse constituencies</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out any outreach and promotional activities under this paragraph in a manner that reaches diverse constituencies, including minority, rural, and underserved communities; people with disabilities; young adults; and individuals who are likely to be uninsured.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD231E71879514CAE8B0265601412908B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Out of any funds in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, there is appropriated to the Secretary of Health and Human Services $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2018 through 2021 to carry out this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD977921DA8C247FB9D54264A1E522F44"><enum>(c)</enum><header>State grants for State-Run Exchanges outreach and promotional activities</header><text>Section 1311 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18031">42 U.S.C. 18031</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H87DC23257C5C434B9DA5CCC29010D17A" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="HECB15B7CD0444268A0E89F76412FC2F5"><enum>(l)</enum><header>State-Run Exchanges outreach and promotional activities</header>
 <paragraph id="H3509684F3CAD4944B98305B70DEEC0FD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall carry out a grant program under which the Secretary awards grants to States that are electing States under section 1321(b) that have established Exchanges. Each such grant awarded to such a State that has established an Exchange shall be used by such Exchange for purposes of outreach and promotional activities as necessary and appropriate for the successful operation of the Exchange, including for purposes of informing potential enrollees in qualified health plans offered through the Exchange of the availability of coverage under such plans and financial assistance for coverage under such plans.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H0D0746CD941042EAAE711524B1EC44AB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligibility</header>
 <subparagraph id="H6C22ABC8DBDE4A68B4F00A920604D025"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for a grant under paragraph (1), a State described in such paragraph shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as specified by the Secretary. In establishing the process for States to apply for such grants, the Secretary shall ensure that applications are processed in a timely manner.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6925DC48DC8A44B58D2CA3FD1F4D1E1D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Diverse constituencies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for a grant under paragraph (1), a State described in such paragraph shall provide such assurances as are required by the Secretary to ensure that the Exchange established by such State carries out outreach and promotional activities under such grant in a manner that reaches diverse constituencies, including minority, rural, and underserved communities; people with disabilities; young adults; and individuals who are likely to be uninsured.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H00D1A88CC67942FB811560E9B5EC4267"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>Out of any funds in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, there is appropriated to the Secretary of Health and Human Services $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2018 through 2021 to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


