<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H6BDA87F1072A4B9CAB54915FF85B67DA" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4903 IH: Combating Opioid Misuse By Advancing Treatment Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4903</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180130">January 30, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff of Tennessee</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Comptroller General to conduct a study and submit a report to Congress on best
			 practices in use by Federal departments and agencies to reduce opioid
			 usage following medical procedures.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H967795B31C0144E68AF1225F1F922F30" style="OLC">
 <section id="H78D11EABA24740C1BDFD3ECA4B059F31" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Combating Opioid Misuse By Advancing Treatment Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>COMBAT Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H7EF0699BC1C84D13AD857D151BA57CE5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study on best practices in use by Federal Government to reduce opioid usage following medical procedures</header> <subsection id="H47C244E4805A46248E8E4385818CD9B9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Secretary of Defense, the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services, the Director of the National Institutes of Health, and the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, shall conduct a study on best practices in use by Federal departments and agencies to reduce opioid usage following a medical procedure that is conducted, funded, or otherwise supported by such departments and agencies.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H1EB21FEDA10942A59DEF8F22C9C674C9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Topics</header><text>The study required by subsection (a)—</text> <paragraph id="HDA13AA24AB3241CCAB3F0EC0320DD097"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE14586187C924483ACF62C1B159B4D01"><enum>(A)</enum><text>include analysis of the research that has been, and is being, conducted or supported on reducing opioid usage following medical procedures described in subsection (a);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5BDAA047C76E4D17968B951C992A90DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">disaggregate such analysis according to whether the medical procedure is a short-term medical procedure or a long-term medical procedure; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C9F4EDF7C304B2CAB9A3885705E19D4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>take into consideration—</text> <clause id="H02B1CD91406345BEB4CCF4CCD8691E90"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the costs associated with using the best practices described in subsection (a) relative to the costs of not using such best practices; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H2168434E68DD46F4A244610567AC5799"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the rates of addiction to opioids associated with using the best practices described in subsection (a) relative to the rates of addiction to opioids associated with not using such best practices; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H43432047A50348B8956CF96E55DF3E7E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall include analysis of—</text> <subparagraph id="HEE2F976F21AF4C5B8F57392E47EA4928"><enum>(A)</enum><text>gaps that have been identified by Federal officials with respect to the costs and rates described in clauses (i) and (ii) of paragraph (1)(C) relative to adult, young adult, and adolescent populations; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA494E55143F430BA5F12B06BAA066D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>justifications offered by such officials for such gaps.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9570FD03B55F48C88D392725B761D5B8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit to the appropriate committees of the Congress a report containing the results of the study conducted under subsection (a), including—</text>
 <paragraph id="HCB69F34D83F240D9B951D571897628A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a summary of the findings of the study;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE20FA38542924DDDABD01B6F44BC17B1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations based on the results of the study, including recommendations for such areas of research and legislative and administrative action as the Comptroller General determines appropriate; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAA509EED2AE74585B0A818B79932FBDA"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations on educating health care providers about the findings of the study.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD0EB0DCFB48743CCA1470B463B457E8E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text>
 <paragraph id="H97C82BF8D06243A8908F7FBC4D3ADF3D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>short-term medical procedure</term> means a medical procedure with a recovery time of less than 30 calendar days.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H5CD3360D398D47769B8126D52E531098"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>long-term medical procedure</term> means a medical procedure with a recovery time of 30 calendar days or more.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


