<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HD3ACA54A726C4B67A6D0724F0AB5CD5C" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5660 IH: Small Business Credit Card Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5660</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180427">April 27, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000480">Mrs. Lowey</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Truth in Lending Act to provide coverage under such Act for credit cards issued to
			 small businesses, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HBCF9571A887241D487C227FB5628A784" style="OLC">
		<section id="H3D23A2DF7F2E4A5098417B9989123577" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; Findings</header>
 <subsection id="H58982731168D4E5CAE065BA0A9EC87D2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Small Business Credit Card Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="HB984DAA1EE2A4496B94EBDAF9763EFC4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>The Congress finds as follows:</text>
 <paragraph id="H7592E85D17264D2FB539CE715E48787C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Economic growth has frequently been led by the creation of millions of new, small businesses.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB5891B4E5F2946C2AF1487A9B08B7ADD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Today, small business owners are severely limited in their ability to finance new business ventures because access to capital through traditional resources has been restricted.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3ED1A7E2A2AC4FCBAC12E9E3674BE7CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In 2017, 27 percent of small businesses surveyed cannot access adequate financing.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HCE8B1B9BC27C497A9CF663D1ABEDA308"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Small businesses are being pushed into using credit cards to meet capital needs.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB00A2A57DE0F4709BC3CEDD62498140D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>This use of credit cards is especially true for innovative and rapidly growing businesses which lack the assets necessary for a traditional loan.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA323103A84184F0EA722EBFD26765DE2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In 2017, 20 percent of small businesses say they were forced to reduce their number of employees as a result of inability to access financing.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4F8F0066DF534A4E83F56528A7BBD04C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>In 2017, 31 percent of the small businesses surveyed used credit cards to meet their capital needs.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HD3B67B9A147541DFB1F18444999DD01F"><enum>(8)</enum><text>In 1993, only 16 percent of small businesses used credit cards as a source of financing.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H82421157F8314E16A75335911E1417BB"><enum>(9)</enum><text>One-half of small businesses using a credit card carry a monthly balance, and one-quarter of small businesses carry a monthly balance in excess of $10,000.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFB2731534A474BC3A2DF69D9DB4F94C7"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The average interest rate charged on small business credit cards is 14.16 percent.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HBA3DDD5981F84CA5914C552F76940FF2"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Nearly one-in-three small businesses with credit cards have reported a worsening of terms, including increased interest rates, fees, and payment procedures, making it more difficult to expand operations or grow business.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF070E29730674421B03D54309134CDF9"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Small business credit cards contracts do not include consumer protections provided to individuals under the CARD Act.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HAAA67132C64E42269A167D95E06588ED"><enum>2.</enum><header>Extending credit card protections under the Truth in Lending Act to small businesses</header>
 <subsection id="H09349AF405634AE7B54D013C0C717FE5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of consumer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 103(i) of the Truth in Lending Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1602">15 U.S.C. 1602(i)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H96B610EA87EF4EAAA0D56251F9BF3394"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The adjective <quote>consumer</quote>, used with reference to a credit transaction, characterizes the transaction as one in which the party to whom credit is offered or extended is</quote> and inserting</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9BF9179532CA4D44B0F431C7C3F651E1" style="OLC">
 <text><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Consumer</header-in-text>.—</text><paragraph id="HFF057D3D1463416A901D4B32BC72ADE7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), the term <quote>consumer</quote>, when used as an adjective to describe or modify a credit transaction or credit plan, means a transaction or credit plan under which credit is offered or extended to</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H26BA2EC1081D49E1975E7BEBA7B10D54"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H19BE6EDDD3A04AB68F3E8F4F0234B4D6" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H65EC19AC5FDD4EED94E63508D5AF1723"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Small business included under certain circumstances</header> <subparagraph id="HDDC20D1E2C33423981297EBB322DEDC0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of any provision of this title relating to a credit card account under an open end credit plan, the term ‘consumer’ includes any qualified small business.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F3CCDED864B449E825975A1DC30CC74"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Qualified small business</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the term <quote>qualified small business</quote> means, with respect to any credit card account under an open end credit plan, any business concern having 50 or fewer employees, whether or not—</text>
 <clause id="HBFCB3266781B42659BF6E1631EC3C41B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the credit card account is in the name of an individual or a business entity; and</text> </clause><clause id="H809C6A627F4C423C87EFF5D6BF94B893"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any credit transaction involving such account is for business or personal purposes.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H58FB4C75607644CF9A3AEF6F1CC32B4A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exclusion of small business after <quote>opt out</quote> effective date</header><text>The term <quote>qualified small business</quote> shall not include any business concern described in subparagraph (A) after the effective date of any election under section 135(b) by the individual or business for which the credit card account referred to in such subparagraph has been established, so long as such election remains in effect.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC3AB89AE508240D196ED52BCDAF2D984"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amendments to exemptions</header><text>Section 104(1) of the Truth in Lending Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1603">15 U.S.C. 1603(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H27881A19708E46D89D0BA55CED63DBEE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>other than a credit transaction under an open end consumer credit plan in which the consumer is a qualified small business</quote> after <quote>agricultural purposes</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9908283B0C114668A2FE3FBD0F0734CE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>other than qualified small businesses</quote> after <quote>organizations</quote>.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5AF09640116744ACA3DFEFC541F2BBD9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Business credit card amendments</header><text>Section 135 of the Truth in Lending Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1645">15 U.S.C. 1645</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H2784D7D5DF344323A32262E2CBA15AEE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The exemption provided by</quote> and inserting <quote>(a) <header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">In general</header-in-text>.—The exemption provided by</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H93F900C8B8184ABAB28A311630EDFFDC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF35ACCBFF52D4DF9A347F9A3284C31E6" style="OLC">
						<subsection id="HECBBE024D202432982E555592753639D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualified small business opt out from coverage</header>
 <paragraph id="HA6F48B62DD23498282EDB7085E77E158"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice of coverage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The disclosures under section 127(a) before opening a credit card account under an open end credit plan for a qualified small business shall include a clear and conspicuous disclosure—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H7A82374A4A5B4DD6A737A1D7E5DB77EC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that the qualified small business is treated as a consumer under this title and is subject to the requirements of this title as a consumer;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H883B728B6115485AA6A34E86112F2C69"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that the business may elect, in accordance with this subsection, to be exempt, under section 104(1), from this title to the same extent as any business other than a qualified small business; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFC29978989BE4D969962BFE2B5812E20"><enum>(C)</enum><text>of the procedures for making the election and for subsequently revoking any such election.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B912BFC44D9483E8090825B1606009C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Election</header><text>The Board shall prescribe procedures for making an effective election under this subsection and for revoking any such election.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H092DD947C70C4878BEDAD511AF861B90"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prohibition on discrimination against qualified small business</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No creditor may—</text> <subparagraph id="H874FE9FD99024E0B94E8B1708A0B57FB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>discriminate against any business concern having 50 or fewer employees in connection with any credit card account of, or any application for a credit card account by such business, under an open end credit plan on any basis; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBE71654065A840579CE517A390DF50B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>require any qualified small business to make an election under this subsection as a condition for opening a credit card account, or for providing more advantageous terms for any credit card account, under an open end credit plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


