<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H7EE2A16FD07C46E3B687B495803D8AF7" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5488 IH: Remote Area Medical Charter Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5488</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180412">April 12, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000533">Mr. Duncan of Tennessee</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000582">Mr. Roe of Tennessee</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000616">Mr. DesJarlais</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 36, United States Code, to provide for a Federal charter for Remote Area Medical,
			 and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H5286C5330CA7418FBC0D07621CC0A6C3" style="OLC">
		<section id="H41E554667DFD4C2EAA0D9ED11432D51C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header>
 <text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Remote Area Medical Charter Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HC12CF8130AEA4828ACB4B94E19C268E6" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/36/1801">Chapter 1801</external-xref> of title 36, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3235447C0D454CB491B01F01256F51B8" style="USC">
				<chapter id="HC33181C203054A31ADE53449A484F3F7"><enum>1850</enum><header>REMOTE AREA MEDICAL</header>
					<toc container-level="chapter-container" idref="HC33181C203054A31ADE53449A484F3F7" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration">
						<toc-entry idref="H1281A02A29A247248B558CD75E43CCCC" level="section">185101. Organization.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="HE60A933B11A847D1B472B0036B78B75D" level="section">185102. Purposes.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="H7A6E14B948B04DDF893DD7E156F556BB" level="section">185103. Membership and chapters.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="HE00C13E696754E95AA1439B06A92E305" level="section">185104. Board of Directors.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="H0861928AC1074EECB171029EA92EC503" level="section">185105. Powers.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="H5930D52EFE8541CD859B6BA2B4946845" level="section">185106. Annual meeting.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="HC7302B1A0A144CA4B6088869AC628BD7" level="section">185107. Endowment fund.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="H4BB55D85D44446AB88F9484E225C0848" level="section">185108. Annual report and audit.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="HC7DB334AE09046769597C16566A74005" level="section">185109. Authority of the Comptroller General of the United States.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="H35A40D72C0264A569FF95B8840FB51F3" level="section">185110. Reservation of right to amend or repeal.</toc-entry>
						<toc-entry idref="H564768945545477E83852E2EB84E5D61" level="section">185111. Service of process.</toc-entry>
					</toc>
					<section id="H1281A02A29A247248B558CD75E43CCCC"><enum>185101.</enum><header>Organization</header>
 <subsection id="H40760B4EDC884D29A37EC2FA71A559ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal charter</header><text>Remote Area Medical (in this chapter, the <quote>corporation</quote>) is a Federally chartered corporation.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H87D8244B109D46EFAAA4AE94C937CDBF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Name</header><text>The name of the corporation is <quote>Remote Area Medical</quote> or <quote>RAM</quote>. The corporation may conduct its business and affairs, and otherwise hold itself out, as the <quote>Remote Area Medical</quote> in any jurisdiction.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5B9953EF864D4425AFC876117F819DBD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Perpetual existence</header><text>Except as otherwise provided, the corporation has perpetual existence.</text> </subsection></section><section id="HE60A933B11A847D1B472B0036B78B75D"><enum>185102.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of the corporation is—</text>
 <paragraph id="HAF8BB2046F4A44F0A127FA524F6E1281"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To prevent pain and alleviate suffering by providing free quality healthcare to those in need. The corporation will utilize mobile ground and airborne capabilities to provide free medical care and veterinary services to the needy.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCF3C195ED1D04808BC321BC5D7ED6143"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To organize and facilitate animal husbandry and wildlife conservation, to include the distribution of educational information and data.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF19FC323FC274FF583145DE1B791D2B8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>To organize and distribute education information and provide live educational and training programs for underprivileged youth and adults.</text>
						</paragraph></section><section id="H7A6E14B948B04DDF893DD7E156F556BB"><enum>185103.</enum><header>Membership and chapters</header>
 <subsection id="H200C7F0DE3274D2B88B3663C938191A8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>Membership in the corporation is open to all the people of the United States and its territories and possessions, or as provided in the bylaws.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H264B7F4A252340EF9247080EE98924FA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Affiliates</header>
 <paragraph id="H86D62063974248F6984320AC4EDA86C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The affiliates of the corporation are the local units of the corporation. The corporation shall prescribe policies and regulations related to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE25B7B2FB5CD457989672977FF9FFAAE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>granting charters to the affiliates and revoking those charters;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2AC9D728985540A28820FD12D58025DD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the territorial jurisdiction of the affiliates;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2875DE62856D468FBC63D9AE0DE7D7F9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the relationship of the affiliates to the corporation; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70550C68066749AD85DB21E7312F8000"><enum>(D)</enum><text>compliance by the affiliates with the policies and regulations of the corporation.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H25F892197D504C9DABD6A934AB1A6E42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The policies and regulations shall require that each affiliate adhere to the democratic principles of election specified in the bylaws in electing the governing body of the affiliate.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE00C13E696754E95AA1439B06A92E305"><enum>185104.</enum><header>Board of Directors</header>
						<subsection id="HC595CDD4FA034FAA8556EAEB5954BBF4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Board of Directors</header>
 <paragraph id="H1F143E7159C441E08ACDA32F642BE196"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board of Directors is the governing body of the corporation with all powers of governing and directing, and of overseeing the management of the business and affairs of, the corporation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H39A481F60E394B9F96FEDBAEA0A9ADCC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Number</header><text>The Board of Directors shall fix by resolution, from time to time, the number of members constituting the entire Board of Directors, provided that as of July 13, 2014, and thereafter, there shall be no fewer than twelve. There shall be 9 standing committees. Procedures to implement or amend the preceding sentence shall be provided in the bylaws.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0F51561073554304BCAAD79A540FFB09"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text>The Board of Directors shall be appointed or elected in the following manner:</text> <subparagraph id="H8139419370A14B9AAB927EE80886CDE7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>President</header> <clause id="HB0AAC351E58A44EBAC937D048469CA29"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board of Directors, in accordance with procedures provided in the bylaws, shall have Stan Brock serving as President of the Board for life or upon his resignation or removal from the Board.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HDB7BECFD18D4439C8B19114368355C5D"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>Vacancies as to the Presidency of the Board, whether resulting from the resignation, death, or removal by the Board, shall be filled as provided in the bylaws.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H64713DAD5A284D7F86ED42418FF70121"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The President shall be a member of the Board of Directors and, when present, shall preside at meetings of the Board of Directors and shall have such other duties and responsibilities as may be provided in the bylaws or a resolution of the Board of Directors.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD621DC8FA05740659C4E7F7A54ABFC82"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Other members</header>
 <clause id="HBC10E8F1EF2140D0B8FD5E4488CBDD21"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Officers of the Board of Directors other than the President shall be elected at the annual meeting of the corporation in accordance with such procedures as may be provided in the bylaws.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HE6E74038404F46DEA0D1AB0AC9E3D92E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>Vacancies in any such elected Board position and in any newly created Board position may be filled by a vote of the remaining members of the Board of Directors in accordance with such procedures as may be provided in the bylaws.</text>
									</clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB983626AF6894DAD947BD6F48130EB25"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Terms of office</header>
 <paragraph id="H0E3C369050124ED69405464947B6B691"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term of office of each member of the Board of Directors shall be 2 years, except that any member of the Board of Directors elected by the Board to fill a vacancy in a Board position arising before the expiration of its term may, as determined by the Board, serve for the remainder of that term or until the next meeting of the corporation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H65D2B054243F4E5E94446AA729F07F9E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Staggered terms</header><text>The terms of office of members of the Board of Directors (other than the President) shall be staggered. Elections of the Board of Directors shall take place in the winter quarterly meeting and each July at the annual meeting.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H22FC4BD76371425B924BF76134E714C7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Committees and officers</header><text>The Board—</text> <paragraph id="H2173B24F83E840F5A42972B7C184417F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may appoint, from its own members, an executive committee to exercise such powers of the Board when the Board is not in session as may be provided in the bylaws;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1386F36003C5412895A79E3B612AB30B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may appoint such other committees with such powers as may be provided in the bylaws or a resolution of the Board of Directors;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9C60462650BD465288A793F7A70D3FEC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall appoint such officers of the corporation, including a chief executive officer, with such duties, responsibilities, and terms of office as may be provided in the bylaws or a resolution of the Board of Directors; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H69B2AA8703984A1CB7E199481DD7612F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>may remove members of the Board of Directors (other than the President), officers, and employees under such procedures as may be provided in the bylaws or a resolution of the Board of Directors.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H26FAE531D21746CD894A6FC782C47E0D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Action without meeting</header><text>Any action required or permitted to be taken at any meeting of the Board of Directors or of any committee thereof may be taken without a meeting if 75 percent of the members of the Board or committee, as the case may be, consent thereto in writing, or by electronic transmission and the writing or electronic transmission is filed with the minutes of the next proceedings of the Board or committee, if ratified by a majority vote of the Board. Such filing shall be in paper form if the minutes are maintained in paper form and shall be in electronic form if the minutes are maintained in electronic form.</text>
						</subsection><subsection id="H849A6AA4377C4D1187014A6142885B82"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Voting by proxy</header>
 <paragraph id="H1DCAF9E8DFA04404A7677ACA3DC16041"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any member wishing to vote through proxy must notify the Secretary of the Board in writing more than 24 hours in advance of the Board meeting.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3DFD4A30F9694E0E8D3A6F64B3484EA0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Method</header><text>An e-mail constitutes a writing for proxy notification purposes.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6A115631B6DF4FF1AF55D60C217E5310"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Bylaws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board of Directors may—</text>
 <paragraph id="HA5EB24745CA242BB8BCEF8F6642C54EB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>at any time adopt bylaws; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB8FB740F9EFB45B592ABE2B41D741D0B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>amend these bylaws upon written notice provided at least 5 days in advance of any meeting convened for that purpose. Amendments may only be adopted on a majority vote of a quorum of the entire membership of the Board at the time the amendment is proposed.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0861928AC1074EECB171029EA92EC503"><enum>185105.</enum><header>Powers</header>
 <text display-inline="no-display-inline">The corporation may—</text> <paragraph id="HAA6F8CCE474D4AE9B26385AE90436533"><enum>(1)</enum><text>adopt policies and regulations;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAB38F2EB8E7745B0A8B393E3AE268060"><enum>(2)</enum><text>adopt, alter, and destroy a seal;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H29CD631C151843AF8EA2C7916342C5DB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>own and dispose of property to carry out the purposes of the corporation;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H51598836BCF646B2ABA97BA6B61DBAE8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>accept gifts, devises, and bequests of property to carry out the purposes of the corporation;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9F5E3203BD8043DA998092001ABD6D0C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>sue and be sued in courts of law and equity, State or Federal, within the jurisdiction of the United States; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HADF053B8C5C447E3927EFCA6860D1DBB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>do any other act necessary to carry out this chapter and promote the purposes of the corporation.</text> </paragraph></section><section id="H5930D52EFE8541CD859B6BA2B4946845"><enum>185106.</enum><header>Annual meeting</header> <subsection id="H6D13E6B51601487FB6C94EC1F0B32A3A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The annual meeting of the corporation is the annual meeting of Directors.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HC078D421417D4353AA0F98B96143533E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Time of meeting</header><text>The annual meeting shall be held during the month of July.</text> </subsection><subsection id="HC39EE777A7E3427FA1022168AD06727E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Place of meeting</header><text>The Board of Directors is authorized to determine that the annual meeting shall not be held at any place, but may instead be held solely by means of remote communication subject to such procedures as are provided in the bylaws.</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="HC7302B1A0A144CA4B6088869AC628BD7"><enum>185107.</enum><header>Endowment fund</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Any endowment fund of the corporation shall be kept and invested under the management and control of the Board of Directors.</text>
					</section><section id="H4BB55D85D44446AB88F9484E225C0848"><enum>185108.</enum><header>Annual report and audit</header>
 <subsection id="HE8A54714131E4DA9B5CB7A4A67C97CAB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Submission of report</header><text>As soon as practicable after the end of the corporation’s fiscal year, which may be changed from time to time by the Board of Directors, the corporation shall submit a report to Congress on the activities of the corporation during such fiscal year. The report may not be printed as a public document.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HB2B997DDECB7463181E6CF2592A0A9B9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Audit requirements</header><text>RAM shall comply with the audit requirements of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/36/10101">36 U.S.C. 10101</external-xref>.</text> </subsection></section><section id="HC7DB334AE09046769597C16566A74005"><enum>185109.</enum><header>Authority of the Comptroller General of the United States</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States is authorized to review the corporation’s involvement in any Federal program or activity the Government carries out under law.</text>
 </section><section id="H35A40D72C0264A569FF95B8840FB51F3"><enum>185110.</enum><header>Reservation of right to amend or repeal</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress reserves the right to amend or repeal the provisions of this chapter.</text> </section><section id="H564768945545477E83852E2EB84E5D61"><enum>185111.</enum><header>Service of process</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">As a condition to the exercise of any power or privilege granted by this chapter, the corporation shall file, with the secretary of state or other designated official of each State, the name and address of an agent in that State on whom legal process or demands against the corporation may be served.</text></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


