<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HC5520AFD489A49D9BED3E444636441BF" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5770 IH: Easy Medication Access and Treatment for Opioid Addiction Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5770</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180510">May 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000599">Mr. Ruiz</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Attorney General to amend certain regulations so that practitioners may administer
			 not more than 3 days’ medication to a person at one time when
			 administering narcotic drugs for the purpose of relieving acute withdrawal
			 symptoms.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H70E75F97AECB4DE6B70E5BE65AC80160" style="OLC">
 <section id="H5EB7C127700A4658A0B655CD40671BBC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Easy Medication Access and Treatment for Opioid Addiction Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Easy MAT for Opioid Addiction Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H34D0FE139CB8437BACEA1B7459C61E2A" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Administration of narcotic drugs for the purpose of relieving acute withdrawal symptoms</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall revise section 1306.07(b) of title 21, Code of Federal Regulations, so that practitioners are allowed to administer not more than a three-day supply of medication to one person or for one person's use at one time.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


