<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H752F88F2D31045F79645FF0FFFEB3DE7" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5520 IH: VA Medicinal Cannabis Research Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5520</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180416">April 16, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000799">Mr. Walz</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000582">Mr. Roe of Tennessee</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to use the authority of the Secretary to conduct and
			 support research on the efficacy and safety of medicinal cannabis, and for
			 other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H8B4FA7F922D9434798FABA5A3BDE018F" style="OLC">
 <section id="H48C50900E051409A8835689426E73B14" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>VA Medicinal Cannabis Research Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H33806A12667E4580B3FA97175305F129"><enum>2.</enum><header>Conduct of research into effects of cannabis on health outcomes of certain veterans</header> <subsection id="H1167CE6E19424C3F9908C36B5669846A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Research required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the responsibilities of the Secretary of Veterans Affairs under section 7303 of title 38, United States Code, the Secretary may conduct and support research relating to the efficacy and safety of forms of cannabis described in subsection (c) on the health outcomes of covered veterans diagnosed with chronic pain, post-traumatic stress disorder, and other conditions the Secretary determines appropriate.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA8C07AEFCE4E415BA277C833BEDAC9D7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Data preservation</header><text>Research conducted pursuant to subsection (a) shall include a mechanism to ensure the preservation of all data, including all data sets, collected or used for purposes of the research required by subsection (a) in a manner that will facilitate further research.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD598F79C1AA149479A1BCCB42A71FD79"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Forms of cannabis To be researched</header><text>The forms of cannabis described in this subsection are—</text> <paragraph id="H6DB52D47E95E44B7812D6B7A0239F385"><enum>(1)</enum><text>varying forms of cannabis, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H584B62B7DE8E420CACF64E618A44ABFC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>full plants and extracts;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9C343E965B942F4A9A7192C33F64D6F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least three different strains of cannabis with significant variants in phenotypic traits and various ratios of tet­ra­hy­dro­can­nab­i­nol and cannabidiol in chemical composition; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5ADD83CFF754DD68157408A240B0507"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other chemical analogs of tet­ra­hy­dro­can­nab­i­nol; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F96045A5B4F4031BAA6A62249BC8B27"><enum>(2)</enum><text>varying methods of cannabis delivery, including topical application, combustible and non-combustible inhalation, and ingestion.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1093C03A17249BE9608F1F7EBDC1AA1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="H55C88E9B36394CF8A68BEF9EAA2409F7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop a plan to implement this section and submit such plan to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0DACCA833DEF43CAA891C85AE992F8CC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>issue any requests for proposals the Secretary determines appropriate for such implementation.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H73D7BEE46571411391D98EBDD73A534E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the five-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit periodically, but not less frequently than annually, to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate reports on the implementation of this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H0BCABF5482944FCB984BEEC908C727DD"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Covered veteran defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered veteran</term> means a veteran who is enrolled in the patient enrollment system of the Department of Veterans Affairs under section 1705 of title 38, United States Code.</text>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


