<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H699AECDF6D444D7BB99E777D255AC58F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5553 IH: Loya-Sears Warrior Transition Assistance Reform Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5553</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180418">April 18, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="R000608">Ms. Rosen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to take certain steps to improve the Transition Assistance Program, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H060ACE6C34664B00872DEDAF31639DC3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H78118B3F15DE45949149CF142B484C52" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Loya-Sears Warrior Transition Assistance Reform Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H88FC3B90A4C74029A3D7580F876718CB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HCDEEC3264FCC40439A76B2739A41B322"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress affirms the importance of TAP in preparing members of the Armed Forces of the United States to rejoin civil society as productive citizens following their service.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF0A033D593B643DCBDB895F7B758E1F3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Despite considerable effort and investment in military transition assistance programs over many years, strong evidence exists that many veterans remain unprepared for transition and encounter significant challenges in living healthy and productive lives.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H29DB42ED916A4E168BD1DE512C72935D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Congress observes with concern the unacceptably high rates of suicide, unemployment, and homelessness that persist among America’s veteran population.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H21D289C8C15C49DE9D56C5ECA9639322"><enum>(4)</enum><text>While difficult to precisely establish the causal basis of this crisis, Congress is concerned that management controls should be improved to ensure the Department of Defense complies with current statutes regarding TAP attendance and participation, effective allocation of transition assistance resources, and effective measurement of TAP outcomes with timely feedback to the Department of Defense and its interagency partners in the Departments of Veterans Affairs and Labor.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H49366DA4D90C4381BF1133135B980449"><enum>3.</enum><header>Required actions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall provide an action plan to the congressional defense committees to accomplish the following with regards to all members of the regular and reserve components of the Armed Forces:</text> <paragraph id="H58AB99A4C6954A9582146441018FF0A8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Mandate initiation of TAP one year before separation from the Armed Forces.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H476D3248E4354723B1A30F610E52CABC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Standardize TAP curriculum across all military departments.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0A79428985254CF190A0334C2028B4BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Ensure unit and installation compliance with applicable statutes governing TAP program management and individual attendance.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3938222225984761A2DDBEF4F50DDC26"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Implementation, in consultation with the Secretaries of Veterans Affairs and Labor, of standardized performance metrics to measure TAP participation and outcome-based objective benchmarks in order to—</text> <subparagraph id="H464CF1BAB1034F62A684B44F540B8A39"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide feedback to stakeholders of each of the Departments of Defense, Veterans Affairs, and Labor;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H89DDB16FD94540DE89386E38690632C7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>improve program curriculum;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H555A09BF8BCC4A8580F9EA32C60B4645"><enum>(C)</enum><text>share best practices; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1ECF25E864EE4E32AB38CC74DF08319F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>facilitate effective oversight of TAP.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="H54AB40CEBCA34099868E4E458C354368"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report</header> <subsection id="H21292B0C013A4210AD6C40CFE50897ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the Secretaries of Veterans Affairs and Labor, shall provide a report to the congressional defense committees containing recommendations to improve the efficacy of TAP.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4370451CE7CD47DE8B93D807F464AE9E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report under this section shall include recommendations regarding the following:</text> <paragraph id="H00A6DA9978714025AD0211285815EC95"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Methods to improve and expand the duration and practical utility of the TAP curriculum in order to effectively prepare members of the Armed Forces to rejoin the civilian labor force.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA01849A042044C5B88A7C0119B61F24B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Ways to more effectively utilize national and local veterans service organizations to support veterans throughout transition.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5B1F90C68FA546588AE3A57BC3AC7682"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Proposed changes to law or policy to improve the ability of TAP to prepare members of the Armed Forces to rejoin civil society in productive manners.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H84541EAEEDDB4F30A97D7580AA7E9369"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H12327E2A65344FA7B902AF84D80B319D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>TAP</quote> means the Transition Assistance Program under sections 1142 and 1144 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFDB2C0EDEFCE440B9E473C161C87C52F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The terms <quote>military departments</quote> and <quote>congressional defense committees</quote> have the meaning given those terms in section 101 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

