<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H1B5F81A80E004B93A36BDF6A23608C7E" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5775 IH: Providing Reliable Options for Patients and Educational Resources Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5775</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180511">May 11, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000594">Mr. Paulsen</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000611">Mr. Poliquin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000188">Mr. Kind</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000588">Mr. Lamb</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to require Medicare Advantage plans and part D
			 prescription drug plans to include information on the risks associated
			 with opioids, coverage of certain nonopioid treatments used to treat pain,
			 and on the safe disposal of prescription drugs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H80930C859BED4E64B3A157356FA672DD" style="OLC">
 <section id="H130FE83446B94159935F908137F61715" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Providing Reliable Options for Patients and Educational Resources Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PROPER Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HC21F920D8E714E56AC69FE3C4B2B2E88" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requiring Medicare Advantage plans and part D prescription drug plans to include information on risks associated with opioids and coverage of nonpharmacological therapies and nonopioid medications or devices used to treat pain</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1860D–4(a)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-104">42 U.S.C. 1395w–104(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HEBC4F63F812D450FABA9812D349F0A91"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>, subject to subparagraph (C),</quote> before <quote>including</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE5454EECA2B64FEE9D795B80288CC2CA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by adding at the end the following new clause:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H78F9AC25CF8643DFB6A09C8C590BBCF8" style="OLC">
 <clause id="H6EA3011D470A4D6A96AE3CAB11514650"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For plan year 2021 and each subsequent plan year, subject to subparagraph (C), with respect to the treatment of pain—</text>
 <subclause id="H01D63A8CB8664CA68069BE0E51831AC5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the risks associated with prolonged opioid use; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="H33F38105178E42939DEEEE55F116E26B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>coverage of nonpharmacological therapies, devices, and nonopioid medications—</text>
 <item id="H82CB7271446E4EC99CD17019D3F513B5"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in the case of an MA–PD plan under part C, under such plan; and</text> </item><item id="H0FFE1D67F83346A9BD54B000ABD2472B"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in the case of a prescription drug plan, under such plan and under parts A and B.</text></item></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3739817D65E64CF2A1761886726AC1DF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB3F1C22860FB44588AFAE5DF022146F8" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H5C9669E0C3944D59A850E3F73657B0D2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Targeted provision of information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A PDP sponsor of a prescription drug plan may, in lieu of disclosing the information described in subparagraph (B)(vi) to each enrollee under the plan, disclose such information through mail or electronic communications to a subset of enrollees under the plan, such as enrollees who have been prescribed an opioid in the previous two-year period.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</paragraph></section><section id="HA3379C24A3B2491DB52A7C9818F4039F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Requiring Medicare Advantage plans and prescription drug plans to provide information on the safe
			 disposal of prescription drugs</header>
 <subsection id="HBA72099892BE432288EA67E03923367D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Medicare Advantage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1852 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-22">42 U.S.C. 1395w–22</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H512FC3B7DEC74C7D8FA666ED66D457FD" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H5550A7170B314D0BA90B410E5F2FDB55"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Provision of information relating to the safe disposal of certain prescription drugs</header>
 <paragraph id="H0BD9CE9A11E146279FA58F5E981E1C24"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an individual enrolled under an MA or MA–PD plan who is furnished an in-home health risk assessment on or after January 1, 2021, such plan shall ensure that such assessment includes information on the safe disposal of prescription drugs that are controlled substances that meets the criteria established under paragraph (2). Such information shall include information on drug takeback programs that meet such requirements determined appropriate by the Secretary and information on in-home disposal.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE28C03D5B61C46D7923D62994BB808BD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>The Secretary shall, through rulemaking, establish criteria the Secretary determines appropriate with respect to information provided to an individual to ensure that such information sufficiently educates such individual on the safe disposal of prescription drugs that are controlled substances.</text>
						</paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HCE4F3B316AE945C28BF5B7E178494C2D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prescription drug plans</header><text>Section 1860D–4(c)(2)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-104">42 U.S.C. 1395w–104(c)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H34995D80979746B189E7BD7D5717DA2F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>may include elements that promote</quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA6B0E1BF0F124802BFC265B88A9CBD7B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating clauses (i) through (iii) as subclauses (I) through (III) and adjusting the margins accordingly;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9BEB7DAAE55045729E67D7E4C9BA0E52"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting before subclause (I), as so redesignated, the following new clause:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H48425EDCADF04843B19286134A96E987" style="OLC"> <clause id="HBF7F25BDA2274D5ABA9168A9599CD6C2"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may include elements that promote—</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H696FB1CA21E247E88880D96B449186E2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subclause (III), as so redesignated, by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H94723A297325425AB5E6F2DC8E1B9E20"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new clause:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3340FAEBBD854181BDFFBCC681DE751D" style="OLC">
 <clause id="H01F2A7CA702244708AC02C0E73E96D18"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2021, shall provide for—</text> <subclause id="H2113EEE842CF4540BDC3D219FE81E535"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the provision of information to the enrollee on the safe disposal of prescription drugs that are controlled substances that meets the criteria established under section 1852(n)(2), including information on drug takeback programs that meet such requirements determined appropriate by the Secretary and information on in-home disposal; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H19409D7643CD4E32811E598AE11FE1EC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>cost-effective means by which an enrollee may so safely dispose of such drugs.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H6A96CF959CB64906915842AC339F4465" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Revising measures used under the Hospital Consumer Assessment of Healthcare Providers and Systems survey relating to pain management</header> <subsection id="H1817D340777445468A398D505AC49784"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Restriction on the use of pain questions in HCAHPS</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1886(b)(3)(B)(viii) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ww">42 U.S.C. 1395ww(b)(3)(B)(viii)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subclause:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H82A72F6A103447ED89920CCFBB604668" style="OLC">
 <subclause id="H8656478A7DBB4EC3A868AA5B71B2B92D" indent="up4"><enum>(XII)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a Hospital Consumer Assessment of Healthcare Providers and Systems survey (or a successor survey) conducted on or after January 1, 2019, such survey may not include questions about communication by hospital staff with an individual about such individual’s pain unless such questions take into account, as applicable, whether an individual experiencing pain was informed about risks associated with the use of opioids and about non-opioid alternatives for the treatment of pain.</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="H5F62054DC95946C6A0766910BC55653F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Restriction on use of pain questions in the hospital value-Based purchasing program for fiscal year
 2019</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1886(o)(2)(B) is amended by adding at the end the following new clause:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA31E2C40C75B40058CB05DB84F00B350" style="OLC"> <clause id="H410CDC5886F746A2AE37DF8CC049564C"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>For fiscal year 2019</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For value-based incentive payments made with respect to discharges occurring during fiscal year 2019, the Secretary shall ensure that measures selected under subparagraph (A) do not include a measure based on questions about communication by hospital staff with an individual about such individual’s pain included in the Hospital Consumer Assessment of Healthcare Providers and Systems survey.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


