<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H254B9C419FE848FA952A659ABD6D67A0" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5472 IH: Fairness to Pet Owners Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5472</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180411">April 11, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001092">Mr. Collins of New York</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To promote competition and help consumers save money by giving them the freedom to choose where
			 they buy prescription pet medications, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H97CE9E501F8847E4AA0D219F33BC1AB3" style="OLC">
 <section id="H6F38B6A764FC4C72AEBC094937607EC2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fairness to Pet Owners Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H10F696D49BDE4AFE818E646EC4AD3537"><enum>2.</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act shall only apply to medication for a domesticated household animal that the Federal Government bars consumers from purchasing without a prescription.</text>
 </section><section id="H9FAB014585474A3CA6EA1158D44E128A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Pet owner rights to copies of veterinary prescriptions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Federal Trade Commission shall promulgate rules in accordance with section 553 of title 5, United States Code, that include the following requirements with regard to a veterinary prescription:</text>
 <paragraph id="H356F47A794DF401CBACAC5BE606D74B0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A requirement that establishes the rights of pet owners prescribed an animal drug to receive a copy of the veterinary prescription, without having to request a copy.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HACA68A42E64B407A8EF934C1891AFDC0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Electronic option</header><text>The rights provided for in paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H8D2110597A464BB094731AEED7DB2A18"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may be satisfied by receipt of the prescription by electronic or other means; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC27C789B5A45482F9BEC552B7674D4CF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall include the right to have a copy of the prescription provided by electronic or other means consistent with applicable State law, if requested by a pharmacy or any other person designated to act on behalf of the pet owner.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H754B271B661743509D22200D24374B79"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Purchase, payment, and waiver</header><text>A requirement that the prescriber of an animal drug—</text> <subparagraph id="H4E7EF49C66094731BE49837E2EA41732"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may not—</text>
 <clause id="H7B1BBA06F17D4B998CFC7E611A525D65"><enum>(i)</enum><text>require purchase of the animal drug for which the veterinary prescription was written from the prescriber or from another person as a condition of providing a copy of the veterinary prescription or verifying such prescription under paragraph (1);</text>
 </clause><clause id="H6DDE1770B47846C69ECCD68DFD44360B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>require payment in addition to, or as part of, the fee for an examination and evaluation as a condition of providing a copy of the veterinary prescription or verifying such prescription under paragraph (1); or</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA6EBC550135A46E0B13C0A69EA79FEBF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>require the pet owner to sign a waiver or disclaim liability, or deliver to the pet owner a notice waiving or disclaiming liability of the prescriber for the accuracy of the veterinary prescription, as a condition of providing a copy of such prescription or verifying such prescription under paragraph (1); and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A54311E223B43C98F8EC57F8EFC49A1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may require payment of fees for an examination and evaluation before providing a veterinary prescription, but only if the prescriber requires immediate payment in the case of an examination that reveals no requirement for an animal drug.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HB3508B8619BB49F69E0337C8B9D49036"><enum>4.</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A violation of a rule prescribed pursuant to section 3 of this Act shall be treated as a violation of a rule defining an unfair or deceptive act or practice prescribed under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>). The Federal Trade Commission shall enforce this Act in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction as though all applicable terms and provisions of the Federal Trade Commission Act were incorporated into and made a part of this Act.</text>
 </section><section id="H0CA4F621E42249FE92C671172DD96388"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H1103E8AD1BB1440587DF2556F5E4B8D8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Animal drug</header><text>The term <quote>animal drug</quote> means a drug intended to be administered to an animal that may not be dispensed without a prescription.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3A6DF85D6FD84C5A8E99DF30E8FB2969"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Domesticated household animal</header><text>The term <quote>domesticated household animal</quote> means a companion animal permitted under applicable State and local law to be kept in a home for noncommercial purposes.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBBCEF2BF43DA4B5888B711F140467FB6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Pet owner</header><text>The term <quote>pet owner</quote> means the legal owner of a domesticated household animal or a person designated by such owner to present such animal to the prescriber for care.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBBC590C44D984A8A9D0D558EAC229248"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Prescriber</header><text>The term <quote>prescriber</quote> means a health care practitioner who is licensed to practice veterinary medicine or other person permitted under State law to issue prescriptions for animal drugs.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB2B81C2896D849039A76B31D2ECD6AFC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Veterinary prescription</header><text>The term <quote>veterinary prescription</quote>—</text> <subparagraph id="H9BC38361339E4E5CAB219A571E204004"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a written, oral, or electronic order from a prescriber authorizing the dispensing of an animal drug for use by a domesticated household animal and normally administered to the animal by its owner, issued in accordance with State and Federal law; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD55B570ABAB4B76884F34AC2855C5EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include an animal drug administered by the veterinarian in the course of providing acute care.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


