<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H41CF635EFAAC48B783C8D13B7931C486" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5366 IH: Safeguarding America’s Skies Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5366</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180321">March 21, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001053">Mrs. Hartzler</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001189">Mr. Austin Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001050">Ms. Hanabusa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to provide for certain authorized actions regarding
			 interdiction of unmanned aircraft, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HA21F7AEA713746B19E43E7AFF04B0F93" style="OLC">
 <section id="id75CFBA9B302241F1B88238DA4AFFD9FC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Safeguarding America’s Skies Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HF9CB73D330A64A9099D36C593DCAA693" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authorized actions regarding interdiction of unmanned aircraft</header> <subsection id="H0E34A62B6E8B44418E5E4789C7211B47"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In General</header><text>Chapter 1 of part I of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end of the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8AC24134E70F4C3F841F28F6B265E801" style="OLC">
					<section id="H08D186CE599643B6BCC3CD16AF90E033"><enum>28.</enum><header>Authorized actions regarding interdiction of unmanned aircraft</header>
 <subsection id="HB89CBE09110549F4B6DB996F54EF7004"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this title, except as described in paragraph (1), the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Attorney General may, for their respective departments, authorize officers, employees, and contractors of the department assigned with duties that include safety, security, or protection of personnel, facilities, or assets of the department, to take such actions described in subsection (b) that are necessary to mitigate the threat (as defined by the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary of Transportation) that an unauthorized UAV poses to the safety or security of a covered facility or asset. In taking such actions, the agency shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H50D7D1BBC54149DEA587A08B27A89844"><enum>(1)</enum><text>avoid any infringement of the privacy and civil rights of the people of the United States and the freedom of the press consistent with the First and Fourth Amendments, including with regard to the testing of any equipment and the interception or acquisition of communications;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7768E398DB85455489DF8013F1EDF42F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>limit the geographic reach and the duration of such actions to only those areas and timeframes that are reasonably necessary to address a reasonable threat; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB4A07EFD03424555A43924FD97848F02"><enum>(3)</enum><text>use reasonable care not to interfere with non-targeted manned or unmanned aircraft, communications, equipment, facilities, or services.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE8093EFFCC624022BFF4B7E2FEBC5BA2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Actions authorized</header>
 <paragraph id="H67B02568474D49D384097D296849C87B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Actions described</header><text>The actions described in this subsection are as follows:</text> <subparagraph id="H28D0A2A31353435DB6A722BC5732448F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Detect, identify, monitor, and track, without prior consent, a UAV, including by means of interception of or other access to wire, oral, electronic, or radio communications or signals transmitted to or by the UAV, to evaluate whether the UAV poses a reasonable threat to the safety or security of a covered facility or asset.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD4268766171486BAB41F20B9E58B403"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Warn the operator of the UAV, including by passive or active, and direct or indirect physical, electronic, radio, and electromagnetic means.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDC3C69679B345AE82A0F0DB94170AD3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Redirect, alter control, disable, disrupt, seize, or confiscate, without prior consent, a UAV that poses a reasonable threat as determined under subsection (a), including by intercepting, substituting, or disrupting wire, oral, electronic, or radio communications or signals transmitted to or by UAV.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H73CEB35B388643A4B1789A5BD186C032"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Use reasonable force to disable, disrupt, damage, or destroy a small unmanned aircraft, unmanned aircraft system, unmanned aircraft, or unmanned aircraft’s attached system, payload, or cargo that poses a reasonable threat to the safety or security of a covered facility or asset.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB51941E81914E1292D4175A2C13369E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Conduct research, testing, training on, or evaluation of any equipment, including any electronic equipment, to determine its capability and utility to enable.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE3B02B70C744EBB94F1893747A68286"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regulations and guidance</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security and the Attorney General, in coordination with the Secretary of Transportation, may make rules and shall issue guidance in their respective areas to carry out this section.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H24D03BB35F43426A8A13DA6DC37764AD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Avoidance of duplication</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security, the Attorney General, and the Secretary of Transportation shall coordinate and avoid duplication in the development of guidance under this paragraph or otherwise implementing this section.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H63D5BF2944364DF692276546049835AD"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Minimization of harmful interference</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security, the Attorney General, and the Secretary of Transportation shall also coordinate with the Federal Communications Commission and the National Telecommunications and Information Administration to ensure that all actions taken and guidance and rules made under this subsection minimize harmful interference to licensed and unlicensed communications, devices, and services authorized by the Federal Communications Commission.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5116D147F6C9465F95D4A770C054696F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Final rule regarding remote identification and tracking of UAVs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the effective date of this section the Secretary of Transportation shall issue a final rule requiring remote identification and tracking of UAVs, including UAVs for recreational use, to ensure that cooperative aircraft are identified.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0411B517393E424EA6331690466054DC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Forfeiture</header><text>Any UAV described in subsection (a) that is seized by the Federal agency is subject to forfeiture to the United States.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF7977F57EBF34EE6BFEDEF17F22A0904"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exemption from disclosure</header><text>Information pertaining to the technology, procedures, and protocols used to carry out this section, including any regulations or guidance issued to carry out this section, shall be exempt from disclosure under section 552(b)(3) of title 5 and exempt from disclosure under State and local law requiring the disclosure of information.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HBCD5A04EE02C4743AD592E59A01E9619"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Privacy protection</header><text>All actions taken and guidance and rules made under subsection (b)(2) shall ensure that—</text> <paragraph id="HE07C2D83510940B9850F60FA7E553AB2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the interception or acquisition of or access to communications to or from UAV under this section is conducted in a manner consistent with the Fourth Amendment to the Constitution and applicable provisions of Federal law;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H920831D14B93403998F4B8ABD45C6839"><enum>(2)</enum><text>communications are intercepted, acquired, or accessed only to the extent necessary to mitigate the reasonable threat that an unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft poses to the safety or security of a covered facility or asset;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6C7C2961F73A4637A5CDB742BF1081D0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>records of such communications are maintained only for as long as necessary and in no event for more than 180 days unless the Secretary of Homeland Security or the Attorney General reasonably determine that maintenance of such records—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H8AF807FBE63A465CBBA3CBD7DF0C4D38"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is necessary to support one or more safety or security functions of the Department of Homeland Security or the Department of Justice, respectively; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H345E6C1FF2194EE28A8457C72E2AA5A6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is required for a longer period to support a law enforcement agency or by any other applicable law or regulation; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE455DF22877944AC910C672BD256614E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>such communications are not disclosed outside the Department of Homeland Security or the Department of Justice unless the disclosure, subject to paragraph (a)(1) above—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H63E3A6F8C31C4367A5C240F751E8EAB2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>would fulfill a safety or security function of the Department of Homeland Security or the Department of Justice;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H56BEC9E422E84B36849264ACA2D351F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>would support the Department of Defense, a civilian law enforcement agency, or the enforcement activities of a regulatory agency of the Federal Government in connection with a criminal or civil investigation of, or any regulatory action with regard to, an action described in subsection (b)(1); or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41A4E8221BBF4E1F891FF9F6BBD32A49"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is otherwise required by law or regulation.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7DEC16026C234718BC279A723A3D3E4C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Scope of authority</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to provide the Secretary of Homeland Security or the Attorney General additional authorities beyond those described in (b)(1) without authorization by law.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H43440FDC27414FFDA0614E3A6E2E6CC1"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>The Attorney General and Secretary of Homeland Security, shall each submit to Congress, not later than one year after enactment, and each year thereafter, a report that shall include, at minimum—</text>
 <paragraph id="HC69824E11D194F4A826196DB47AB651A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of actions taken, guidance provided, and rules made pursuant to this section, including a summary of public comments submitted in relation to such guidance or rules;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7CE078139FA84001B83E748F4F200076"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of each Department’s efforts to address privacy, civil rights, and civil liberties issues implicated by the actions permitted by this section and other Federal and State government policies affecting UAVs;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD502433DA80646D19EE167C97D6FE3D7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the number of UAVs that have been subject to each of the actions taken under subsection (b)(2), broken out by action;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA5EA6392FBBD4773B9AC82A135F86806"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">actions taken by each Department to inform the public of covered facilities and assets authorized by this section;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0FD95C32CAEE4E3DAE0EE5F15D31557B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>implementation costs; or</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HF9726613B40943C3A6BD4F8732112DAF"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a description of any revisions to this section that may be desirable.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1D62984D9C844EBE8D58240B92156CAC"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H3F1ACFF28A45431D824CE8F0069D0020"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>cooperative aircraft</term> means aircraft that have an electronic means of identification aboard in operation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0E7F01EACC2943FD98DF0A6CA11EE1FF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>covered facility or asset</term> means any facility or asset that—</text> <subparagraph id="H87E9572AC169462EB5885D80ED5F9855"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is identified by the Secretary of Homeland Security or the Attorney General;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1BECCA8D29884590A0097D0C0F99492D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is located in the United States (including the territories and possessions of the United States): and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H090C96E6D318456F893F526FC6A2AA83"><enum>(C)</enum><text>relates to—</text> <clause id="HD512E04133B94D7EBDA2220E7DFD21AE"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the buildings and grounds leased, owned, or operated by or for the Federal Government, including Federal Facility protection operations;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA90364CD8B2D454285D4E70BB2047CA8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>authorized protective operations, including but not limited to the protection of Federal jurists, court officers, witnesses, and other persons;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF4AA14F01E314094AA47FACFDCD78A3D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>penal, detention, correctional, and judicial operations;</text> </clause><clause id="HA76EB0F0D6A443E0BF2349CC706B07FF"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>National Security Special Events, Special Event Assessment Ratings Events, or other mass gatherings or events that are reasonably assessed by the Department of Justice to be a potential target for terrorism or other criminal activity;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H71B71CC479A24E05B2476321928B0995"><enum>(v)</enum><text>active Federal law enforcement investigations;</text> </clause><clause id="HB3B5FF27F6064587A4A373DFD798C2BA"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>operations that counter terrorism, narcotics, and transnational criminal organizations;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1361FC565814495C8135D6330ED3E068"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>securing authorized vessels, whether moored or underway;</text> </clause><clause id="H2E5D95B97FE248898ACBD767C682C4BD"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>protection operations pursuant to section 3056;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H78B77BDEDB234AFB86A7D677A3EE4818"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>critical infrastructure;</text> </clause><clause id="HD7008FD3B6274B3891DCE28BF0E1E5DD"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Emergency Response Operations;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8B6C3D572A0C4ED8BA2ECA6543D3CEC8"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>National Disaster Areas if it is determined by the Secretary of Homeland Security that unauthorized access to the airspace would restrict recovery efforts;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HFDF74FB2A8074909982AF06AAE584E8C"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>Natural or Hazardous Disaster Areas if it is determined by the Secretary of Homeland Security that unauthorized access to the airspace would restrict recovery efforts; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HE7453D739FD8408EA972F6DEBA43795B"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>other areas identified by the President.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H860B11DC02CB49AFBFDCF25B47EBE3CE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>UAV</term> means a small unmanned aircraft, unmanned aircraft system, unmanned aircraft, or unmanned aircraft’s attached system, payload, or cargo.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H61A68758E6974574B3044B9C52D03BEE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The terms <term>unmanned aircraft</term>, <term>small unmanned aircraft</term>, and <term>unmanned aircraft system</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 331 of the FAA Modernization and Reform Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/112/95">Public Law 112–95</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/40101">49 U.S.C. 40101</external-xref> note).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCC91478F2A204710B284384C3BCDAB38"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The terms <term>intercept</term> and <term>wire, oral, electronic, or radio communications</term> have the meaning given those terms in section 2510.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H3AE45F7834B7453792F82ADF4605454E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The term <term>critical infrastructure</term> has the meaning given that term in section 2339D except that the Attorney General may, in his or her determination, amend the definition for purposes of this section in the issuance of any guidance or rules made under subsection (b)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H0727D7D9E71A446FBF29C6A4F638E2FD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for such chapter is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4E21EA1008A84E73B19C06B8D7714116" style="USC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">28. Authorized actions regarding interdiction of unmanned aircraft.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection><subsection id="H35FE89E44F7741A6BE02624872D0BBC9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H323E464C954340E587B00AD23756447D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 32, by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2C11A80E2B994FE88D00B8BB08137517" style="USC"> <subsection id="H25730F94B8B2440B9EC22C312113389A"><enum>(d)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall apply to any action lawfully taken under section 28.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD733D94B7FD440B4A8F20B8BE67540C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 1030, by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H863CC543E4B6411C84DC3577532B0CBD" style="USC"> <subsection id="H26E0CC53A1484017B4549463F23AF3C2"><enum>(k)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall apply to any action lawfully taken under section 28.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H290D3E3FE0CC4A4E87D310760E0235CE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 1362 by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5E1E7A902D294D84AA1BA90464949DDF" style="USC"> <quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="paragraph">Nothing in this section shall apply to any action lawfully taken under section 28.</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE842920E0A9749A9B178455E184C77C6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 1367, by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBA9F3A869E724562B2FEA966E9B5AAD6" style="USC">
 <subsection id="H0B667EFD683944349F811F6B56761669"><enum>(c)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall apply to any action lawfully taken under section 28.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph><paragraph id="H8E80F4415F1C4E1EB3386EC3791F5663"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in chapter 119—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE11B28A4CAFA4533B1F955AB08C684F8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H34A06D56478143629C0E949DE07B1C5A" style="USC"> <section id="HEF885091A2B4499184919759B788E468"><enum>2523.</enum><header>Exception for interdiction of unmanned aircraft</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this chapter shall apply in the case of any action lawfully taken under section 28.</text></section><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H69B92490D3DC4A999B3526ED2C22B1D2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the table of sections for such chapter, by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF9E667C113914E48AA38AEEBAB1AB2E3" style="USC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">2523. Exception for interdiction of unmanned aircraft.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">and</continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B1F548DABD34BCFBED4BB9A09DDC819"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in chapter 206—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H1E1F8CFBEE45490F81E795BF98C34075"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3732886BDE174A1B8F071E844C9D60C9" style="USC"> <section id="H2AFD01BA8ED9477F845C5E52996FD2BA"><enum>3128.</enum><header>Exception for interdiction of unmanned aircraft</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this chapter shall apply in the case of any action lawfully taken under section 28.</text></section><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2E3BE6F4BC545C581FDA7BE32D2AB7F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the table of sections for such chapter, by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0DE9B91575184F3D9DB5F551629F0FFD" style="USC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">3128. Exception for interdiction of unmanned aircraft.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

