<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H721B0F9CCB8A462EA1FF8FB82D575287" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5714 IH: Education for Disposal of Unused Opioids Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5714</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180509">May 9, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001273">Mrs. Black</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001038">Mr. Crowley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000599">Mr. Ruiz</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001067">Mr. Hudson</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to require Medicare Advantage plans offered under
			 part C of the Medicare program and prescription drug plans offered under
			 part D of such program to provide information relating to the safe
			 disposal of prescription drugs that are controlled substances to certain
			 individuals enrolled under such plans.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H85A7AAE9F09542E9AADF452474685EFA" style="OLC">
 <section id="HE0CA6FE0A5524C5FB0602653267641FF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Education for Disposal of Unused Opioids Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>EDU Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HE5BAE3084EB44C3ABF427651187EA06A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requiring Medicare Advantage plans and prescription drug plans to provide information on the safe disposal of prescription drugs</header> <subsection id="H2882279A574141A5893E63E318B0B939"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Medicare Advantage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1852 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-22">42 U.S.C. 1395w–22</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0EEB9D633AC44E6F95979CF5E431CE1E" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="HC2CE26B75EF84F92A4E860033423A225"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Provision of information relating to the safe disposal of certain prescription drugs</header>
 <paragraph id="H30CDBCD852B245BBBDFEE4AF4630CC62"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an individual enrolled under an MA or MA–PD plan who is furnished an in-home health risk assessment on or after January 1, 2021, such plan shall ensure that such assessment includes information on the safe disposal of prescription drugs that are controlled substances that meets the criteria established under paragraph (2). Such information shall include information on drug takeback programs that meet such requirements determined appropriate by the Secretary and information on in-home disposal.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0E5C688B57EB4AF5B4676FB56C72C345"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>The Secretary shall, through rulemaking, establish criteria the Secretary determines appropriate with respect to information provided to an individual to ensure that such information sufficiently educates such individual on the safe disposal of prescription drugs that are controlled substances.</text>
						</paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H75D7998EBD104C368D8CF793AD2BAB07"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prescription drug plans</header><text>Section 1860D–4(c)(2)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-104">42 U.S.C. 1395w–104(c)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HFCCC192CD2534978954FC2F13E140803"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>may include elements that promote</quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB9676EE210F0431F91AD75C15ACF28B0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating clauses (i) through (iii) as subclauses (I) through (III) and adjusting the margins accordingly;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H99EA9A0520C543E086FFAE06D7445977"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting before subclause (I), as so redesignated, the following new clause:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H44B44461A2764FF2B413CF5BD7C5FB06" style="OLC"> <clause id="HC2C866916B75459EAC85E80EFD9F5544"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may include elements that promote—</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAB9A2510F32243A6B8D0B22118451FD7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subclause (III), as so redesignated, by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE096CB5D3EC94B5795C522421C3A347D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new clause:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB6BC568D016942EAAEEC5F9C140D28DB" style="OLC">
 <clause id="H8645211DA48C4BC88034BC6E14CE0B48"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2021, shall provide for—</text> <subclause id="H8765B2E336C24C8CB22EAF449461999C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the provision of information to the enrollee on the safe disposal of prescription drugs that are controlled substances that meets the criteria established under section 1852(n)(2), including information on drug take­back programs that meet such requirements determined appropriate by the Secretary and information on in-home disposal; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HAA53A559E22A4B7896438FD6F3562666"><enum>(II)</enum><text>cost-effective means by which an enrollee may so safely dispose of such drugs.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

