<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H53485E0977ED4936A69B5BE660BBCDA6" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4780 IH: Transparency for Taxpayers Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4780</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180111">January 11, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001193">Mr. MacArthur</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000619">Mr. Rodney Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000563">Mr. Gibbs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000464">Mr. Faso</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001198">Mr. Marshall</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000580">Mr. Garrett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000609">Mr. Rutherford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney of West Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001187">Mr. Stivers</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of the Treasury to make available an online tax calculator to estimate the
			 change in an individual’s income tax liability with respect to the
			 amendments made by the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H82A361AF0F824761B0FB56190105BD20" style="OLC">
		<section id="HF445AFC2CB9349779367127B2F9C3F9F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; findings</header>
 <subsection id="HE8A578E6DF104FB985708BB626231160"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Transparency for Taxpayers Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="HD7CEC881A6604B53858DDD9C2E343DBF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds as follows:</text>
 <paragraph id="H61682178BC8D43F5A1EC296055BD334A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Most businesses have professional accountants to assess the immediate effects of the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H624820CFD33A4F90981372D95C2F4828"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Individuals have an immediate need to understand the impact that this legislation may have on them but don’t have the same resources as large businesses to do so.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8CDF4B7A129E4019A99F138BCEE5E36D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>It is necessary for the Internal Revenue Service to provide individuals with a tool to help aid them in assessing the effect tax reform will have on their personal finances.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA5B87F14AB4644C18E432DF9E2738AB5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Online tax calculator to determine change in tax liability expected by reason of the Tax Cuts and
			 Jobs Act</header>
 <subsection id="H3BA40CF26C9D472D806C42635AE35625"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than April 1, 2018, the Secretary of the Treasury shall make publicly available an online tool that allows taxpayers (other than corporations) to calculate the approximate change in the income tax liability of the taxpayer by reason of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref> (commonly known as the <quote>Tax Cuts and Jobs Act</quote>) by determining a simplified estimate of the taxpayer’s income tax liability that would be determined for the taxpayer’s taxable year beginning in 2017 if the amendments made by <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref> (commonly known as the <quote>Tax Cuts and Jobs Act</quote>) which apply for taxable years beginning in 2018, applied to taxable years beginning in 2017.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HF37797E8FD2F4D4B971536521EA7070F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Items taken into account in determining simplified estimates</header>
 <paragraph id="H5AD7387A5E0E4F9D8E756A13CFCDF3CB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of making simplified estimates of income tax liability under subsection (a), the online tool made available under such subsection shall take into account the following factors with respect to the taxpayer:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H145B985178D44A12A6FD017C16389F04"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The filing status and income of the taxpayer.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80DA7B2D2285400DB911EA759DB84033"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The number of qualifying children and other dependents of the taxpayer.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B842E5D9AB74291BF1575B319F18921"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The deductions allowable to the taxpayer for mortgage interest, charitable contributions, medical expenses, tuition, and State and local taxes.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB80C1C223DE840F191E56B633FCD17A1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Such other factors as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B5C0BF533D8407290831437E663D9FC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation on complexity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining the factors which are appropriate to take into account under paragraph (1)(D), the Secretary shall ensure that the online tool is as simple and quick to use for taxpayers as is reasonably possible.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE3DB26553F8D4DFEAC292DCD2FF44847"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Not applicable to business income</header><text>Except as otherwise determined to be feasible by the Secretary (and consistent with the requirement of paragraph (2)), the online tool made available under subsection (a) shall not apply with respect to income and deductions attributable to the conduct of any trade or business.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF264AF9A8782435AA0824E009898250E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Special rules</header>
 <paragraph id="HEE5A41F352E14C3D99612ECE34BB88BB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Publicity</header><text>The Secretary shall publicize the availability of the online tool made available under subsection (a). Such publicity shall include notices of such tool’s availability in connection with making available individual income tax return forms and instructions and by including a written notice of such tool’s availability with any income tax refund mailed to an individual.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H522D1B1672C94322837D0DB45172C4DE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disclaimer</header><text>The online tool made available under subsection (a), and the publicity of such tool under paragraph (1), shall make clear that such tool is designed to provide simplified estimates of the income tax liability of the taxpayer and that the taxpayer’s actual income tax liability may differ from the simplified estimates provided by the tool.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9E26DE858C6E4E46AF4C6C3648073995"><enum>(3)</enum><header>References to Secretary</header><text>For purposes of this section, the terms <quote>Secretary of the Treasury</quote> and <quote>Secretary</quote> each mean the Secretary of the Treasury or his designee.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

