<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H89BEC06A24F84598A5E1E9CC34C7A0E3" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5768 IH: Expanding Access to Diabetes Self-Management Training Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5768</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180510">May 10, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000585">Mr. Reed</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="D000197">Ms. DeGette</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to improve access to diabetes outpatient
			 self-management training services, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HE1230A4092024F6C85E57BEC09EFF8EC" style="OLC">
 <section id="HB6392BBF91B34FABB839413F1A193369" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Expanding Access to Diabetes Self-Management Training Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Expanding Access to DSMT Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H323A9A80265E43D596D4F998F828C2B2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improving access to diabetes outpatient self-management training services</header> <subsection id="HD8B1616C5E1C4E31B63C20C28F6CC0FE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1861(qq) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(qq)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H727A4FF346A949B48028D2B25E7CB0DE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H89C443D69A4D48CB9375B3293C1D1C4B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the Secretary determines appropriate</quote> and inserting <quote>specified in paragraph (3)</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7FD806E283BB480E95B87B1894BB80AD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or qualified nonphysician practitioner</quote> after <quote>only if the physician</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H516F9EB12E5C4A0BA3B3734912A904D2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(or other physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner furnishing items or services to such individual, in coordination with the physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner managing such individual’s diabetic condition)</quote> after <quote>managing the individual’s diabetic condition</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD887AE05777143B7B6691DD2F435A821"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(B), by striking <quote>paragraph</quote> and inserting <quote>subparagraph</quote>; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HAF761408E95549AAA040AAD0F2433F05"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H135638ADD7E34B05BA36E81657FED511" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="HF8109D3051164D1FA1916CE3A583FF68" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of paragraph (1), the times specified in this paragraph are the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H161A1F9F99774F5BAC742AB7796D87FA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An initial 10 hours of educational and training services described in paragraph (1), to remain available until used.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD9BBF52178D4399A02315E108A35E4F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Six additional hours (or a greater number of hours if determined appropriate by the Secretary) of such services during the year in which the individual exhausts the initial hours described in subparagraph (A), provided that the physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner who is managing the individual’s diabetic condition (or other physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner furnishing items or services to such individual, in coordination with the physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner managing such individual’s diabetic condition) certifies the medical necessity of such additional hours.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5FB5AD8E1D9A4C569384738D37763011"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Six additional hours (or a greater number of hours if determined appropriate by the Secretary) of such services per year for each year beginning after the year in which the individual exhausts the initial hours described in subparagraph (A), provided that the physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner who is managing the individual’s diabetic condition (or other physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner furnishing items or services to such individual, in coordination with the physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner managing such individual’s diabetic condition) certifies the medical necessity of such additional hours.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3814486227354844A0477D4A949E79C0"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For a year in which the individual has received additional hours described in subparagraph (B) or (C) and exhausted such hours, an additional number of hours determined appropriate by the physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner who is managing the individual’s diabetic condition (or other physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner furnishing items or services to such individual, in coordination with the physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner managing such individual’s diabetic condition), provided that the physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner who is managing the individual’s diabetic condition (or other physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner furnishing items or services to such individual, in coordination with the physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner managing such individual’s diabetic condition) certifies that—</text>
 <clause id="HA6A2CDB378714BC48C7490A2AAF823FB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>there has been a change in the individual’s diagnosis, medical condition, or treatment regimen;</text> </clause><clause id="HDFB20A450711490A8A7C17281E0E8A5D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the individual is not meeting appropriate clinical outcomes (as determined by such physician or qualified nonphysician practitioner) for such condition; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD04F996062784CA89CB6D3945983232B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the individual meets other criteria that necessitates such additional number of hours, as determined by the Secretary.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF90F4C41B24F41B9AFE19C28EAC8665E" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>qualified nonphysician practitioner</quote> means a physician assistant, nurse practitioner, or clinical nurse specialist (as defined in section 1861(aa)(5)).</text>
						</paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H29E96DA8CF644853ABF5BC85B47D4C22"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Medical nutrition therapy services</header><text>Section 1861(s)(2)(V) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(s)(2)(V)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H148B3B87BA0E4AD28BBB1513A3CE3DD6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking clause (i);</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDE601C22EEB04ABAA134B4CDBD40B65E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating clauses (ii) and (iii) as clauses (i) and (ii), respectively; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HA91957F61DB7443FB18ECFD32B7CA574"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in clause (ii), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>after consideration of</quote> and inserting <quote>consistent with</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H40122C80BFEA4813BA13353842D32108"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Cost-sharing</header><text>Section 1833 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HB5550B1F33B64CC482F59CCA1AD5732A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H99FE3BD406D54C35A611C7842EC8970A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and (BB)</quote> and inserting <quote>(BB)</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BB9EB6C2032437982110EF859775D55"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking the semicolon at the end and inserting <quote>, and (CC) with respect to diabetes outpatient self-management training services (as defined in section 1861(qq)), the amount paid shall be 100 percent of the lesser of the actual charge for the services or the amount determined under the fee schedule that applies to such services under this part;</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A9238EE77E441FFB6FF4B11D8F7D9F5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="HE7508E80E6B84FD78F8C234135E6757C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and (10)</quote> and inserting <quote>(10)</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD70BB30DC074B05A67D3E25CE2B5B84"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>1861(hhh)(1)).</quote> and inserting <quote>1861(hhh)(1)), and (11) such deductible shall not apply with respect to diabetes outpatient self-management training services (as defined in section 1861(qq)).</quote></text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HC85F69A1F0E34591B66943555667E7AE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Revision of manual</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall revise the Medicare Benefit Policy Manual to ensure that diabetes outpatient self-management training services (as defined in section 1861(qq) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(qq)</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (a)) may be furnished by an entity that is a hospital outpatient department at alternate, nonhospital sites (including community-based locations).</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HF69671924960454AACFF14AE4165F8A7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to items and services furnished on or after January 1, 2019.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H343B3D48CD2D41DB82A5C1BA339ACAC9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Virtual Diabetes Outpatient Self-Management Training Services Demonstration Program</header>
 <subsection id="HA472362F8DE54D5299218051F6BB2E55"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not later than January 1, 2019, the Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the “Secretary”) shall select an appropriate number of applicable beneficiaries to participate in a 2-year demonstration program to test the impact of furnishing diabetes outpatient self-management training services through a qualified online platform with respect to cost and clinical outcomes for such applicable beneficiaries. Under such program, diabetes outpatient self-management training services furnished through a qualified online platform to an applicable beneficiary shall be covered under title XVIII of the Social Security Act, and payment for such services shall be made in the same manner as payment is made under such title for such services furnished in an outpatient setting.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA7775B1719C149618DAF11FAAAAE7F58"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HB990AB9D4FF0413591FC52728E65FDEC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicable beneficiary</header><text>The term <quote>applicable beneficiary</quote> means an individual—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF308456D8A37490B819094CAEB481F2D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who is enrolled under part B of title XVIII of the Social Security Act;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88B3CEEDF3934A83A04112C561D30C3C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who has a diagnosis of diabetes; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD92D02E8A51416BAD59C6CDB8452B60"><enum>(C)</enum><text>who agrees to take part in the demonstration program described in subsection (a).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE4349FA06984073B5F832F5BF792510"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified online platform</header><text>The term <quote>qualified online platform</quote> means an online-based platform—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H52B037A8713A4790B764F5A32CFBEFEC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">designed to furnish educational and training services to an individual with diabetes to ensure therapy compliance with respect to the individual’s diabetic condition or to provide the individual with necessary skills and knowledge (including skills related to the self-administration of injectable drugs) to participate in the individual’s management of such condition; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E86F1155053469A987A9AAE0E3BEC19"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that meets the National Standards for Diabetes Self-Management Education and Support, as jointly published by the American Association of Diabetes Educators and the American Diabetes Association.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H33289D8C41444227925E9DAB448DEB56"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Diabetes self-management training services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>diabetes outpatient self-management training services</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 1861(qq) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(qq)</external-xref>) except that the requirement in paragraph (1) of such section with respect to such services being furnished in an outpatient setting shall not apply.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8E7F5A26E0BC444D9E688A7FA8626E29"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>The Secretary shall evaluate the demonstration program described in subsection (a) based on the following criteria:</text>
 <paragraph id="H0181261D3A7F481E912FCD21446588F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The improvement, if any, in health outcomes with respect to the diabetic conditions of applicable beneficiaries participating in such program as evidenced by—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H376732E5450B4312B9E0CD37941C89E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any improvement attributable to such program in the knowledge of such beneficiaries with respect to such conditions;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07E9D08E9E7342709E720959F1808BEE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any behavioral changes attributable to such program;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9D32B45402246C0B3CBB6A8C45CFC90"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any clinical outcome improvements attributable to such program;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4AAB898A46C14B81854500E7B54FB279"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any quality of life improvements attributable to such program; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02C685F253784019816D30C1DD474C3C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the overall satisfaction of such beneficiaries with such program.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CC23630E0974C448A7CDD3CFEC7A119"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Reductions, if any, in expenditures under title XVIII of the Social Security Act attributable to such program.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H77DC230AFAC348F5AAF4BF1DE8E92155"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Other criteria determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H24CC2FFFD583444191088A3E8AEB2AC6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the completion of the demonstration program described in subsection (a), the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report containing—</text>
 <paragraph id="HF0162E1048294D64B510443F411759D6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the results of the evaluation described in subsection (c);</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9E15400C4C8B49BC9CADF45B34D05E27"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an analysis of the demographic characteristics of applicable beneficiaries who participated in such program; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8B66C6AEF940450A80ABB7477AE9C56B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a recommendation on whether such program should be continued or expanded.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H36BD6743704844F4B4D17B48CA9B6717"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Waiver authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may waive such requirements of titles XI and XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1301">42 U.S.C. 1301</external-xref> et seq., 1395 et seq.) as may be necessary to carry out the provisions of this section.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H98E7319AE9B746C79FBA780471FD8B8B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authority To expand demonstration program</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (a), taking into account the evaluation described in subsection (c), the Secretary may, through rulemaking, expand the duration and the scope of the demonstration program described in subsection (a), to the extent determined appropriate by the Secretary, if—</text>
 <paragraph id="H19156FD508AD4CF281B57549B2F5736C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary determines that such expansion is expected to—</text> <subparagraph id="H440741E372DD4F1AA30669A63473FB04"><enum>(A)</enum><text>reduce spending under title XVIII of the Social Security Act without reducing quality of care; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC62219113014D5C85A4F80149199AA6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>improve the quality of care for individuals enrolled under part B of such title without increasing spending under such title;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1510279A9FDD45D591840737021939D3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Chief Actuary of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services certifies that such expansion would reduce (or would not result in any increase in) net program spending under such title; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC647153B986D493E95B936BE2FC54809"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Secretary determines that such expansion would not deny or limit the coverage or provision of benefits under such title for individuals enrolled under part B of such title.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


