<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H88CBAB509E854281A26117900D931713" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5716 IH: Commit to Opioid Medical Prescriber Accountability and Safety for Seniors Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5716</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180509">May 9, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000580">Mr. Roskam</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000557">Mr. Larson of Connecticut</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001284">Mrs. Brooks of Indiana</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000800">Mr. Welch</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to require the Secretary of Health and Human
			 Services to provide notifications under the Medicare program to outlier
			 prescribers of opioids.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H73B56360AFD14ADEB7CF589E3ED4EA3F" style="OLC">
 <section id="HB2FE4FB47FEA46DDB49AB10685786A5C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Commit to Opioid Medical Prescriber Accountability and Safety for Seniors Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>COMPASS Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H72FA47940185490BB21A2BC4E8ADBBCC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Medicare notifications to outlier prescribers of opioids</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1860D–4(c)(4) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-104">42 U.S.C. 1395w–104(c)(4)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
			<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2E17C2CD56644B6AAECA891F385054CE" style="OLC">
				<subparagraph id="H9E6E69A8390943409646D9B1144C3A5E"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Outlier prescriber notification</header>
 <clause id="H1A1B1F1C31674D27B12AAF283B324D12"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this subparagraph, the Secretary shall, in the case of a prescriber identified by the Secretary under clause (ii) to be an outlier prescriber of opioids, provide, subject to clause (iv), an annual notification to such prescriber that such prescriber has been so identified and that includes resources on proper prescribing methods and other information specified in accordance with clause (iii).</text>
					</clause><clause id="H54FD8C7F1B5C4A1598093BC1FEFF131C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Identification of outlier prescribers of opioids</header>
 <subclause id="HCB01222655CC44E6972D1815F1A56AC7"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, subject to subclause (III), using the valid prescriber National Provider Identifiers included pursuant to subparagraph (A) on claims for covered part D drugs for part D eligible individuals enrolled in prescription drug plans under this part or MA–PD plans under part C and based on the threshold established under subclause (II), conduct an analysis to identify prescribers that are outlier opioid prescribers for a period specified by the Secretary.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H60F739BCCFA847D0A27FAAAFE7D5D7D4"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Establishment of threshold</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subclause (I) and subject to subclause (III), the Secretary shall, after consultation with stakeholders, establish a threshold, based on prescriber specialty and geographic area, for identifying whether a prescriber in a specialty and geographic area is an outlier prescriber of opioids as compared to other prescribers of opioids within such specialty and area.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H2B6FA6BCBF314204B8DFAE068E7A0292"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may exclude the following individuals and prescribers from the analysis under this clause:</text>
 <item id="H64CA82D637D2497490437032652782FF"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>Individuals receiving hospice services.</text> </item><item id="HDF97C8F7414D4966AFC10429DD1C17C2"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>Individuals with a cancer diagnosis.</text>
 </item><item id="HFCAB5BF9D8FF4B779A8AFAAE964C25F2"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>Prescribers who are the subject of an investigation by the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services or the Office of Inspector General of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text>
 </item></subclause></clause><clause id="HA5594CEBA2A041D78A6D119ECA7C1591"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Contents of notification</header><text>The Secretary shall, based on input from stakeholders, specify the resources and other information to be included in notifications provided under clause (i).</text>
					</clause><clause id="H1891458C31E04889877C3E858AE0F944"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Modifications and expansions</header>
 <subclause id="H0053EBF48B5E49629D6C4DAF371DAC8A"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Frequency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning 5 years after the date of the enactment of this subparagraph, the Secretary may change the frequency of the notifications described in clause (i) based on stakeholder input.</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H7D001E4F987546C883E02B4DB6B414A6"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Expansion to other prescriptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may expand notifications under this subparagraph to include identifications and notifications with respect to concurrent prescriptions of covered Part D drugs used in combination with opioids that are considered to have adverse side effects when so used in such combination, as determined by the Secretary.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H85CCC563B2D549079ACD2759104E90BC"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Opioids defined</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <term>opioids</term> has such meaning as specified by the Secretary through program instruction or otherwise.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section></legis-body></bill> 

