<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H4647B0BC9EE947789E5B0D46426EA82E" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5480 IH: Women’s Entrepreneurship and Economic Empowerment Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5480</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180412">April 12, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000487">Mr. Royce of California</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000179">Mr. Engel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To improve programs and activities relating to women’s entrepreneurship and economic empowerment
			 that are carried out by the United States Agency for International
			 Development, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H73F05FF7EB514B8A958D064DF910C79B" style="OLC">
 <section id="H13B6B5EC977D442B81CA4514BE452915" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Women’s Entrepreneurship and Economic Empowerment Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H42697AE73D694F4799DC208F51D0D7BF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HFC1C8D2940904680BA693E3D8A7C3860"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Because women make up the majority of the world’s poor and gender inequalities prevail in incomes, wages, access to finance, ownership of assets, and control over the allocation of resources, women’s entrepreneurship and economic empowerment is important to achieve inclusive economic growth at all levels of society. Research shows that when women exert greater influence over household finances, economic outcomes for families improve, and childhood survival rates, food security, and educational attainment increase. Women also tend to place a greater emphasis on household savings which improves families’ financial resiliency.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8D28A940E7C74F41813C1B725E31A4F8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A 2016 report by the McKinsey Global Institute estimated that achieving global gender parity in economic activity could add as much as $28 trillion to annual global gross domestic product (GDP) by 2025.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H96DBCCCCCC28445E8051A38C1A14BEF0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Lack of access to financial services that address gender-specific constraints impedes women’s economic inclusion. More than one billion women around the world are currently left out of the formal financial system, which in turn causes many women to rely on informal means of saving and borrowing that are riskier and less reliable. Among other consequences, this hampers the success of women entrepreneurs, including those seeking to run or grow small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs). The International Finance Corporation has estimated that 70 percent of women-owned SMEs in the formal sector are unserved or underserved in terms of access to credit, amounting to a $285 billion credit gap.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H07AB3158899D4F8888B95AEC51961775"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Women’s economic empowerment is inextricably linked to a myriad of other women’s human rights that are essential to their ability to thrive as economic actors across the lifecycle. This includes, but is not limited to, living lives free of violence and exploitation, achieving the highest possible standard of health and well-being, enjoying full legal and human rights such as access to registration, identification, and citizenship documents, benefitting from formal and informal education, and equal protection of and access to land and property rights, access to fundamental labor rights, policies to address disproportionate care burdens, and business and management skills and leadership opportunities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB8701B4AC922421487F26E46F6C67A93"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Discriminatory legal and regulatory systems and banking practices are hurdles to women’s access to capital and assets, including land, machinery, production facilities, technology, and human resources. Often, these barriers are connected to a woman’s marital status, which can determine whether she is able to inherit land or own property in her name. These constraints contribute to women frequently running smaller businesses, with fewer employees and lower asset values.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5BEB0440E18D45F180372F9827B0BF92"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Savings groups primarily comprised of women are recognized as a vital entry point, especially for poor and very poor women, to formal financial services and there is a high demand for such groups to protect and grow their savings with formal financial institutions. Evidence shows that, once linked to a bank, the average savings per member increases between 40 to 100 percent and the average profit per member doubles. Key to these outcomes is investing in financial literacy, business leadership training, and mentorship.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H401EDABF631F44B69C0DEC8C78635E1A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>United States support for microenterprise and microfinance development programs, which seek to reduce poverty in low-income countries by giving small loans to small-scale entrepreneurs without collateral, have been a useful mechanism to help families weather economic shocks, but many microcredit borrowers largely remain in poverty. The vast majority of microcredit borrowers are women who would like to move up the economic ladder but are held back by binding constraints that create a <quote>missing middle</quote>—large numbers of microenterprises, a handful of large firms or conglomerates, and very few SMEs in between, which are critical to driving economic growth in developing countries.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HECFB1D3ECE55416EB4CC1392B188A877"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the World Bank, SMEs create 4 out of 5 new positions in emerging markets but about half of formal SMEs don’t have access to formal credit. The financing gap is even larger when micro and informal enterprises are taken into account. Overall, approximately 70 percent of all micro, small and medium-sized enterprises (MSMEs) in emerging markets lack access to credit.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H7E6A3B55B826473FA51BC0920DBAF62C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Actions to improve gender policies of the United States Agency for International Development</header>
 <subsection id="H07E2690A77DA40F78907BB0E2078DE35"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Development cooperation policy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be the development cooperation policy of the United States—</text> <paragraph id="HF8A0DDCBB1784E5EB609C641B70A580B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to reduce gender disparities in access to, control over, and benefit from economic, social, political, and cultural resources, wealth, opportunities, and services;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2C6879B83F6943E6B8792A4BC0CA9833"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to strive to eliminate gender-based violence and mitigate its harmful effects on individuals and communities through efforts to develop standards and capacity to reduce gender-based violence in the workplace and other places where women conduct work;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDE552B5F623344ABB560523075BE9BE1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to support activities that secure private property rights and land tenure for women in developing countries, including legal frameworks to give women equal rights to own, register, use, profit from, and inherit land and property, legal literacy to exercise these rights, and capacity of law enforcement and community leaders to enforce such rights; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAEFECB228B8F4E0EBA7E0802AE6DBFB8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to increase the capability of women and girls to realize their rights, determine their life outcomes, assume leadership roles, and influence decisionmaking in households, communities, and societies.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H17C84256365D4ACB9C03E3C1D33FDCAC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to advance the policy described in subsection (a), the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development shall ensure that—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE6E2B3533C1E4A8CA738F11C9B50A534"><enum>(1)</enum><text>strategies, projects, and activities of the Agency are shaped by a gender analysis and, when applicable, use standard indicators to provide one measure of success of such strategies, projects, and activities; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9697AC29D3EF47BD86E7228ADCFA6637"><enum>(2)</enum><text>gender equality and female empowerment is integrated throughout the Agency’s Program Cycle and related processes for purposes of strategic planning, project design and implementation, and monitoring and evaluation.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD7290DE536CA4143BE697102D57EFB43"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Gender analysis defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>gender analysis</term>—</text> <paragraph id="HFD6AD3551D1948E2BA1B53E4EF982A0A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>means a socio-economic analysis of available or gathered quantitative and qualitative information to identify, understand, and explain gaps between men and women which typically involves examining—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HC7C0EE6548284B5BA1E5344FCF292346"><enum>(A)</enum><text>differences in the status of women and men and their differential access to and control over assets, resources, opportunities, and services;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2A055D6E97674483B1D5D3D5FF1F028A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the influence of gender roles, structural barriers, and norms on the division of time between paid employment, unpaid work (including subsistence production and care for family members), and volunteer activities;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H06250D0BDA9743948A9E302C72625F10"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the influence of gender roles, structural barriers, and norms on leadership roles and decisionmaking; constraints, opportunities, and entry points for narrowing gender gaps and empowering women; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12D06650720C42AA80FF11F32DB21A4C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>potential differential impacts of development policies and programs on men and women, including unintended or negative consequences; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H04A35EB8E453400C872277D02EE3339B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes conclusions and recommendations to enable development policies and programs to narrow gender gaps and improve the lives of women and girls.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H76C771F63BF44FE58D21AFE532BDE2C8"><enum>4.</enum><header>Development assistance for micro, small and medium-sized enterprises</header>
 <subsection id="H6A61E41CD9ED465DAF8DE249B8FEE470"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings and policy</header><text>Section 251 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2211">22 U.S.C. 2211</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H2E5430EC9AD34178A05298ACB4A2BE7F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF907EAEE106A47BAB55AF60AE4CA4AD8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>microenterprise</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprise</quote>;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B5095912B83437CAF41D463B264A895"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and in the development</quote> and inserting <quote>, in the development</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDE2AEB546CD4C3A8DDA131575B8F583"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end before the period the following: <quote>, and in the economic empowerment of the poor, especially women</quote>;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H58245BC813DD4A8FA9C88035AB2BC983"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H0945CB9B87144B23A62438542E165FE1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>microenterprise</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprise</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA28809F117147A787B27BC89F4E0717"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end before the period the following: <quote>, particularly those enterprises owned, managed, and controlled by women</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H519333D989374B7CB96E487B96B322F7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>microenterprises</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprises</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H46F56BD7CC244CAAAF6092236FC55F3A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>microenterprise</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprise</quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H350EAE303FAC4DDA95278EC849C959BE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)—</text> <subparagraph id="H1FA3A62C6CB146D7A1EAA0B2A387BB2E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>should continue</quote> and inserting <quote>should continue and be expanded</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H87E77B99098942F290F5057EAFEC70FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>microenterprise and microfinance development assistance</quote> and inserting <quote>development assistance for micro, small and medium-sized enterprises</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9F4F14F9F944DCDB51978991E4D2157"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in paragraph (6)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HF3A4265479AE4D9BA895126408E909C5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>have been successful</quote> and inserting <quote>have had some success</quote>;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B12D54B2D1141DB81B90A0A913FF544"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>microenterprise programs</quote> and inserting <quote>development assistance for micro, small and medium-sized enterprises</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77EFE4916FCA4C50B6A5AE7ADE49CDD3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>, such as countries in Latin America</quote>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H95BFD6CF00514E3B9620E932900D8B0C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization; implementation; targeted assistance</header><text>Section 252 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2211a">22 U.S.C. 2211a</external-xref>) is amended as follows:</text>
 <paragraph id="H8B3F5CA172A546E6A4093A4C2F812E77"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="HE5B9C4DCADA243F385C06B94B879D2BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1)—</text>
 <clause id="HC59F23C2F4D64BEAA028A23606EFCB2D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>credit, savings, and other services</quote> and inserting <quote>credit, including the use of innovative credit scoring models, savings, financial technology, financial literacy, insurance, property rights, and other services</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H153A16C8D7D14C9DA7D11462E8CA8152"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>microfinance and microenterprise clients</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprise clients</quote>;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12911F8BCAF54D9A9DA49434F9B5BD66"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>microfinance and microenterprise clients</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprise clients, particularly those clients owned, managed, and controlled by women</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5DCCA9A8E2474D3D9196F635D781D333"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> <clause id="H97BA9360682E4A27BBC68C409C17694B"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>microenterprises</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprises</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HBFE6CAE620AB46D4A57E300214AD249B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>acquire United States goods and services,</quote> after <quote>United States markets,</quote>;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE3AFCE9A55F423CA2FF8DBDB1873F41"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text>
 <clause id="HC7FDA3EBE8E049DD92B5936C84289A1B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>microfinance and microenterprise institutions</quote> and inserting <quote>financial intermediaries</quote>;</text> </clause><clause id="H6DA140109888443BACB8DCBFB4F7D416"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>microfinance and microenterprise clients</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprises</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1AA30142577E4C70A4775057ABCAB932"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDCE66646F5B94E9091C0A86CED642E07"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)—</text>
 <clause id="HDAF06A466C1648C2BCF5CCC8ED2271F1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>microfinance and microenterprise clients and institutions</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprises, financial intermediaries, and capital markets</quote>; and</text> </clause><clause id="HB914DEBD0D7F497D8CE5EE69D2585A07"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the poor and very poor.</quote> and inserting <quote>the poor and very poor, especially women;</quote>; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3168B970358142EE8FE578F588A9BB9C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9343E00170114B418FD8FD3F91DB1761" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HEF7035845FCA4E45B0AF6025C0A89D78"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assistance for the purpose of promoting the economic empowerment of women, including through increased access to financial resources and improving property rights, inheritance rights, and other legal protections; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H15748AD8F4DE431B80DB6224FA56DA6D"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assistance for the purpose of scaling up evidence-based graduation approaches, which include targeting the very poor and households in ultra-poverty, consumption support, promotion of savings, skills training, and asset transfers.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F0ED171979B401C8939856E52EB0646"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="H596C622C6AA249DAAE8EC9D5A44AEDD9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1) to read as follows:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9432005695584A91AAA874172A666856" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="HFCE7A9139C33418E89F956FAF2B08EE2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be established within the Agency an office to support the Agency’s efforts to broaden and deepen local financial markets, expand access to appropriate financial products and services, and support the development of micro, small and medium-sized enterprises. The Office shall be headed by a Director who shall possess technical expertise and ability to offer leadership in the field of financial sector development.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D3009BB5F694BB4B3FD9B5F90E0FEAC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> <clause id="H1A6F9D9481B04F4B84F30A1767F189A9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text>
 <subclause commented="no" id="HCFD9525E786640E89227CE350E2F6F28"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">use of central funding mechanisms</header-in-text>.—</quote> and all that follows through <quote>In order to ensure</quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">use of central funding mechanisms</header-in-text>.—In order to ensure</quote>;</text> </subclause><subclause id="HF54FE09F5C424C4C922C4975C5BBE85E"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>the office shall</quote> and all that follows through <quote>and other practitioners</quote> and inserting <quote>the office shall provide coordination and support for field-implemented programs, including through targeted core support for micro, small and medium-sized enterprises and local financial markets</quote>; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HE5558B327C64456BB23C7AEBB80A698D"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking clause (ii);</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="H70873F7661DA44E39D8DC4C8B494472A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)—</text>
 <subclause id="HBF1A82691A8E4579BD9C40380F40761C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, particularly by protecting the use and funding of local organizations in countries in which the Agency invests,</quote> after <quote>and sustainability</quote>; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="H3BD85D4483C74040ACB7506B3DAFC1B0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, especially women</quote> after <quote>the poor and very poor</quote>; and</text> </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF00E5A04401844F3B0FE01C5495C48B7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H69D3AD6C8256411AA3C4441CBB9ED6C5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In subsection (c)—</text> <subparagraph id="H863568DCABF843E58F74EC01BE38E6A2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>all microenterprise resources</quote> and inserting <quote>all micro, small and medium-sized enterprise resources</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC399089D66640F3868B9CA6106819BD"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>clients who are</quote> and all that follows and inserting <quote>activities that reach the very poor, and 50 percent of all small and medium-sized enterprise resources shall be targeted to activities that reach enterprises owned, managed, and controlled by women.</quote>.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD761B4AA50C04EACAA27D3A4C896A9F0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Monitoring system</header><text>Section 253(b) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2211b">22 U.S.C. 2211b(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H4E3F33304C3C46008854B8E772CA87F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>, including goals on a gender disaggregated basis, such as improvements in employment, access to financial services, enterprise development, earnings and control over income, and property and land rights,</quote> after <quote>performance goals</quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9C72EA571AD846D389946C105A226365"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>include performance indicators</quote> and all that follows through <quote>the achievement</quote> and inserting <quote>incorporate Agency planning and reporting processes and indicators to measure or assess the achievement</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCC01A9F5D61D46A1AD2B2CBAE22DC0C7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (4).</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7AB4A87ED6A3491E9A6D25392AF80332"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Poverty measurement methods</header><text>Section 254 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2211c">22 U.S.C. 2211c</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE7CD21C25774D6B92F25A89BFB19ED5" style="OLC">
 <section id="HB3917A934BA8420A99963664D36D5E0F"><enum>254.</enum><header>Poverty measurement methods</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administrator of the Agency, in consultation with financial intermediaries and other appropriate organizations, should have in place at least one method for implementing partners to use to assess poverty levels of their current incoming or prospective clients.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H4BE8E073938F41B2934A791C3846DC5C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Additional authorities</header><text>Section 255 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2211d">22 U.S.C. 2211d</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H4FBAB1C356F544CAB205F799DD54267E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>assistance for microenterprise development assistance</quote> and inserting <quote>development assistance for micro, small and medium-sized enterprises</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDD76046C4335485580FE9288494D8F09"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and, to the extent applicable</quote> and all that follows and inserting a period.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HECBCF2BB54D1407290E39893F7792881"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Microenterprise development credits</header><text>Section 256 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2212">22 U.S.C. 2212</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H50A28121FC784C6C8D14DDFCB5151930"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the section heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">microenterprise development credits</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">development credits for micro, small and medium-sized enterprises</header-in-text></quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H284871745ECA4E0B9062AD1CF7895590"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE2C08632739441C38D1FC767C9AC9232"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>micro- and small enterprises</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprises</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H49E1B73B55F147528612BB71C7F100CF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>microenterprises</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprises</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C0D27FF646445379758152A2F3C3EB7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (b), in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>and other financial services</quote> after <quote>credit</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HEBE28D010DF9419CAF8723A3F49DB2EA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by striking <quote>microenterprise households</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprises and households</quote>; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H91B91F8DAA2A4AFBAAE2ACC6047D7EF7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by striking <quote>microfinance institutions</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>financial intermediaries</quote>.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3E713CE8FA14489FB8C1982CCFCE3A7D"><enum>(g)</enum><header>United States Microfinance Loan Facility</header><text>Section 257 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2213">22 U.S.C. 2213</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H3129E8CA4E0F4F899E4F21302998BC25"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the section heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">united states microfinance loan facility</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">united states micro, small and medium-sized enterprise loan facility</header-in-text></quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB0BF07771A1F4F42BB54D55707CE9173"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H85AA79BC26724912A1318EFD27A3C16A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>United States Microfinance Loan Facility</quote> and inserting <quote>United States Micro, Small and Medium-Sized Enterprise Loan Facility</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01F5DD1F7DB844888E0C0C6E59D540EC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>United States-supported microfinance institutions</quote> and inserting <quote>United States-supported financial intermediaries</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H02E06A57CE8E449E8BB9A2868A7D8E4C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>United States-supported microfinance institutions</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>United States-supported financial intermediaries</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HAFDE197CF15944A88F9C20D8422D33C6"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>microfinance institutions</quote> each place it appears and inserting “financial intermediaries”.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H821856553F884E6DBD3BA6F340695758"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Contents of report</header><text>Subsection (b) of section 258 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2214">22 U.S.C. 2214</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H293BFA4A65E248238A67D371AFA88CE1" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="HEA299698272B4C1DA5847C900545ED2A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent practicable, the report should contain the following:</text> <paragraph id="H4FEFF03225DF4C20B2951832935ED7FB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Information about assistance provided under section 252, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H8DF840497D9E49DFA94F573A1D5BE286"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amount of each grant or other form of assistance;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD77CD6B56C2D4E2C8BF0D55139A50BBB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the name of each intermediary and implementing institution receiving assistance;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H455BB6F1AA324DB5849D949C536C8CBF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the name of each country receiving assistance; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF3162920BA94BD9B05EDD78B6072534"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the methodology used to ensure compliance with the targeted assistance requirements in subsection (c) of such section.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H34E356A4C26848C883B8FD5485F5ACEC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The percentage of assistance provided under section 252 disaggregated by income level, including for the very poor, and gender.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H906DDFCAC15C42918E2425FD9D44A9AE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The estimated number of individuals that received assistance provided under section 252 disaggregated by income level, including for the very poor, and gender, and by type of assistance, including loans, training, and business development services.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE4CCB1C07D8A403AAA874A659BC1FE33"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The results of the monitoring system required under section 253.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H6204B0BFE65F4431BBC4AA5D39CAD277"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Information about any method in place to assess poverty levels under section 254.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H05489ABF0886408DAB32260B1B20E562"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Section 259 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2214a">22 U.S.C. 2214a</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HB5C01BFFFB394FD0984495EBD80D2D76"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>Committee on International Relations</quote> and inserting <quote>Committee on Foreign Affairs</quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA51C539514EA4581B43BAC216EF4E321"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>microenterprises</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprises</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HCDB6F835A7B54FF9896A2FEF09A8A48F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (6)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H3FFF62A4C49045AE8D4D3DB8BF7558F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (E), by striking <quote>microenterprise institution</quote> and inserting <quote>micro, small and medium-sized enterprise institution</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE7EA29EC354F416B92C469F8FC477167"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (F), by striking <quote>microenterprise institution</quote> and inserting <quote>financial intermediary</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H70B485AD59EE40C0966B56CB7BC1B051"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in paragraph (7) to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2674C1C79EBE44CDAAE26E7C68218139" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HD23C42264B084EEDB453BE1D057B20D0"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Micro, small and medium-sized enterprise institution</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>micro, small and medium-sized enterprise institution</term> means an entity that provides services, including finance, training, or business development services, for micro, small and medium-sized enterprises in foreign countries.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3E98DCA96F14477184BDCAC7343E3A2F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in paragraph (8) to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB4BC00E97463441BB887165992D5E185" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H60C8305EE3824D46B7CCDB134BFEEC94"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Financial intermediary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>financial intermediary</term> means the entity that acts as the intermediary between parties in a financial transaction, such as a bank, credit union, investment fund, a village savings and loan group, or an institution that provides financial services to a micro, small or medium-sized enterprise.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4B6BCB84DA4E4939A0931B9F5ADC039E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (9);</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HED94F039C2D4473C8125CB9C7F336A7F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (10) through (14) as paragraphs (9) through (13), respectively;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD63A2B271D9D4B53976614F03D7FA910"><enum>(8)</enum><text>in paragraph (9) (as redesignated), by striking <quote>of microenterprise development</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H2C025DB8416D48C3855F44B2DB1DC94D"><enum>(9)</enum><text>in paragraph (10) to read as follows:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1C13FCB51D3F4ECB9928571A1886BBD4" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H3738E09FA39E4BB492FF6F0AD0C3B4F6"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Practitioner institution</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>practitioner institution</term> means a not-for-profit entity, financial intermediary, telecommunications firm with a mobile money platform, a village and savings loan group, or any other entity that provides services authorized under section 252 that benefits micro, small and medium-sized enterprise clients.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H840E1CC57D244D5C9D59AEF3CC3EE593"><enum>(10)</enum><text>in paragraph (12) (as redesignated)—</text> <subparagraph id="H70F0704D51354BE69BFC4EA0BBFAA358"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">united states-supported microfinance institution</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">united states-supported financial intermediary</header-in-text></quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H762DE396643B456686F05A2DEE6B61DB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>United States-supported microfinance institution</quote> and inserting <quote>United States-supported financial intermediary</quote>;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BDB747134C24A30B4EB74277038DC3E"><enum>(11)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B) of paragraph (13) (as redesignated) to read as follows:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEAB235F451BB4E28A9AE55280D5F3855" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H4B8DECB502CE42C28EB63A3BCB655FDD"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">living below the International Poverty Line, as defined by the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International Development Association (collectively referred to as the <quote>World Bank</quote>).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5F6BEF51901549FA87A956E8A2F306F5"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title VI of chapter 2 of part I of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 is amended as follows:</text> <paragraph id="HF8256133693543759C5ABF09269E266A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the title heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">MICROENTERPRISE DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE FOR MICRO, SMALL AND MEDIUM–SIZED ENTERPRISES</header-in-text></quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA865C6E9295B41C79FDE182698779F36"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the heading for subtitle C, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">United States Microfinance Loan Facility</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">United States Micro, Small and Medium-Sized Microfinance Loan Facility</header-in-text></quote>.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HDB3AE9DA90504CA19F6120D7FA8A18A2"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report and briefing by United States Agency for International Development</header> <subsection id="HE3A67944E9394E3FB977806B335E2226"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development shall provide a briefing and submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on the implementation of this Act and the amendments made by this Act, including actions to improve the gender policies of the United States Agency for International Development pursuant to section 3.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD4450579FCFE4BCAA15B2C5E4FC69981"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The report required under paragraph (1) shall be posted and made available on a text-based, searchable, and publicly available internet website.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H6659C1E1B86D4750A17C99B0AAD5299E"><enum>6.</enum><header>Report by Comptroller General of the United States</header>
 <subsection id="HF0D75966206244DDA1C1A3B30D4BB742"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on development assistance for micro, small and medium-sized enterprises administered by the United States Agency for International Development.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H5D6116C3A3354043BC055E2A178C8017"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text>The report required under subsection (a) shall include an assessment of the following:</text> <paragraph id="H3DD3F31EA40D48A7A0B91B4F2855A947"><enum>(1)</enum><text>What is known about the impact of such development assistance on the economies of developing countries.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5A7B3A6192724F84A38F1E02982C4600"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The extent to which such development assistance is targeting women and the very poor, including what is known about how such development assistance benefits women.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF3BBFE02FABB4D708721541773288909"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The extent to which the United States Agency for International Development has developed a methodology used to ensure compliance with the targeted assistance requirement in section 252(c) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, as amended by section 4 of this Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H42BCB6606C5446D89934D51C8825B55A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The monitoring system requirements in section 253(b) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, as amended by section 4 of this Act, including the quality of such monitoring system.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body>
</bill>


