<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H659972A5CA804C8285EF70B642D084AB" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5248 IH: Sustainable Shark Fisheries and Trade Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5248</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180313">March 13, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Ted Lieu of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000255">Mr. Jones</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001049">Mr. Clay</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend and enhance the High Seas Driftnet Fishing Moratorium Protection Act to improve the
			 conservation of sharks.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H6079B96DC8D9429191E599710F9FCDDF" style="OLC">
 <section id="H3FB48CB467BD4F4196B85A55C6C0FAD7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Sustainable Shark Fisheries and Trade Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HDBCEAA0EBA604D6AB835EFC3A3A946C8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to establish a certification process to ensure that foreign nations engaging in shark trade into or through the United States conserve and manage populations of sharks in a manner that is comparable to regulatory programs in the United States and that effectively prohibits the practice of removing shark fins and discarding the carcass at sea.</text>
		</section><section id="H2F9627E457214DBC9DAA16B7005E3AF6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Shark conservation and trade fairness certification</header>
 <text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 610 of the High Seas Driftnet Fishing Moratorium Protection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1826k">16 U.S.C. 1826k</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HA2C08366A95841609D8D77DFEC42736F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="HCD84746782324A0DB2CE1AB6AD7A053C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon at the end;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A71174E6F74418E86DED3B18F59AEFE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H44554D3728634238BA76BCC5DF1ACB4C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB680BD4FD30B4FDBA8C9F9F5BFFBD6B2" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H950762D3EA8D4734941A8E494C661CC8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a nation if—</text> <subparagraph id="H01AF7E83FC7148C4AC5CFE8BD96B0C32"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that nation or any individual or entity has imported shark products into the United States or seeks to import shark products into the United States; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0380D4256A3345BDA70E0D5E6693CE37"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the nation has not sought and obtained, by not later than the effective date of subsection (g)(1), a certification from the Secretary under that subsection that the nation has in effect a regulatory program to provide for the conservation of sharks, including measures to prohibit removal of any of the fins of a shark (including the tail) and discarding the carcass of the shark at sea, that is comparable to that of the United States.</text>
							</subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8E3F9BCB439488AB87FADCB92B2D27A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b), in paragraphs (2) and (3), by striking <quote>subsection (a)</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>subsection (a)(1)</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB9151216B90A4026B9A20504E931773E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HC27C17184A244009803E68BE86EF27EC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>subsection (a)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (a)(1)</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H35B8B2BB988D466595B6F6588BC23386"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H1BD8AD4DEE164541951C45ABF1273827" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H64402184E21D485C9115DB46E5AB9F0F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Applicability to certain countries</header><text>This subsection does not apply to a nation identified under subsection (a)(3).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H58A071FF6F9B46DAACF80F5F1BFA6409"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H174CF98BC7FA4287B7BEAE4DBC567A7A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>or (g)</quote>after <quote>under subsection (c)</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53E8A0FDB2D4492DA156FA81637FC2B2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by inserting <quote>or (g)</quote> after <quote>under subsection (c)</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F5DDD2C428644FD8ADC23BAE1FDDA12"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H195FF6B3F1E14F31ADC00ABE9549D9FC" style="OLC"> <subsection id="HEE9BADDF1FDD435A89FFC12DDAAE7220"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Shark conservation and trade fairness certification</header> <paragraph id="HA26E5B9CCDB24FA2B965556AD36F09BE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition on importation</header> <subparagraph id="H217F7FF3CB2242A7A88C73CC5DDE7202"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), shark products shall not be imported into the United States unless the shark products are of a species of shark that were landed in a nation to which the Secretary has granted a certification or partial certification for such species under paragraph (2).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79FC87060B844F65BE97E9774D980BC9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply to shark products that are—</text> <clause id="H72F178B91E7E44698E20F9CA76A638E5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>traded, owned, held, or otherwise possessed by an employee or agent of a governmental agency for law enforcement purposes;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H86BC6081093E4E038A6DD04739CA74A2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>used for noncommercial subsistence purposes in accordance with Federal, State, tribal, or territorial law;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HB7F1C94FBCB74BDCA7B08D8F06BD8B4A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>used solely for display, education, conservation, or research purposes, by an accredited zoo, aquarium, museum, college, or university; or</text>
 </clause><clause id="H678322AA3A7D422195456A9DD8287CD4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>used by any other person under a State or Federal permit to conduct non-commercial scientific research.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H71023BBC10CF4BCB8981ED4B69BFF723"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certifications</header><text>Pursuant to the regulations promulgated under paragraphs (3) and (5), the Secretary—</text> <subparagraph id="HA29407F4CDA74C2CAE1FF15CC2E3915D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall grant a certification to any nation that has adopted and effectively enforces regulatory programs to provide for the conservation and management of sharks, and measures to prohibit shark finning, that are comparable to those of the United States; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD49E63D97BD24B08AC7C2F8407542D60"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may grant a partial certification for one or more specific species of shark to a nation if the Secretary determines that such nation—</text>
 <clause id="H12C568E3B00B4F73A351797461E5E44E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has adopted and effectively enforces regulatory programs that are comparable to the regulatory programs of the United States to provide for the conservation and management of such species imported into the United States or used to produce the shark products imported into the United States; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8EBC252CABDD4415B5884F584234A331"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has in effect an effective ban on shark finning, that is comparable to that of the United States.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FFF5EF79AC94759B2EAD5AF6C5B6FE4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Expiration; renewal</header><text>A certification or partial certification issued under this subsection—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H9E95044498A54B6B9DB2CB6A202268CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be effective for no more than three years after the date of issuance; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B1977E93C2C44A492D3D7AAC085555B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may be renewed in accordance with the provisions of this subsection relating to the initial issuance of the certification.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H465B032E675647CCA063CAD2216988F4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Certain determinations</header><text>The Secretary shall make a determination with respect to whether to renew under paragraph (3) or revoke pursuant to paragraph (5)(A)(ii) a certification or partial certification issued under this subsection, by not later than 180 days after the submission of the application for renewal or the petition for revocation, respectively.</text>
						</paragraph><paragraph id="H7C54DC85010C48A6A9BF2B23AA4D553B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Regulations</header>
 <subparagraph id="H34BA9037C64A4C46978925C2CBFEB1C8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of the Sustainable Shark Fisheries and Trade Act, the Secretary shall prescribe regulations under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, governing the submission, evaluation, revocation, and renewal of applications for certifications and partial certifications under paragraph (2).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H667FD75C73DC4035BE24FFC847409C76"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Content of regulations</header><text>Such regulations shall—</text> <clause id="H36B8C606F21E4C0BB204B4052C3F2868"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prescribe the content and format of applications and standards for information to be provided in such applications; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H39E4B086CE8148E7B76D1AA8B67890CA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>establish a process for petitioning the Secretary for revocation of the certification or partial certification of any nation, including standards for the information required to be provided to demonstrate that the nation no longer meets the criteria established under this paragraph for the certification.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCAF94D1C255043178A1BB5BF8703CC2E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Criteria for certification or partial certification</header><text>The regulations promulgated under subparagraph (A) shall establish criteria for determining whether a nation has and effectively enforces regulatory programs for the conservation and management of sharks, and measures to prohibit shark finning, that are comparable to those of the United States, including, at a minimum, a requirement that such programs—</text>
 <clause id="HEA25FF69B7164DA497E591178CEFB0C9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be consistent with the national standards for fishery conservation and management set forth in section 301(a) of the Magnuson-Stevens Conservation and Management Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1851">16 U.S.C. 1851(a)</external-xref>);</text>
 </clause><clause id="H5408B8D23CE648E4BA724C766B9E5345"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide for regularly updated management plans, scientifically established catch limits, and bycatch assessments and minimization;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H709FA877ED594B3EAF436AF09761BCEB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>include a program to prevent overfishing and to rebuild overfished stocks;</text> </clause><clause id="H548D377D14AE4ED5AEEE12F0F135E930"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>require reporting and data collection;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H869F413526114C849FD345F76073E947"><enum>(v)</enum><text>be consistent with the International Plan of Action for Conservation and Management of Sharks of the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H79394F6AA9294733AEA73A6503DBAA1C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>include a mechanism to ensure that, if the nation allows landings of sharks by foreign vessels that are not subject to such programs of such nation, only shark products that comply with such programs are exported to the United States.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2162D28CB3A84A69B39800C0273B3A5A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Publication; public comment</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HB7DC171576354877ACB2A9F5C8F2B11B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>publish in the Federal Register notice of applications, petitions, and decisions with respect to certifications, renewal of certifications, or revocation of certifications under this subsection; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1147F0246AF4EBB87FD62BDFC85E351"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide an opportunity for public comment with respect to such applications, petitions, and decisions.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H05F62860095E4FF3B6CEFC0FBB96AF8D"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Final agency action</header><text>A decision of the Secretary with respect to the issuance, renewal, or revocation of a certification or partial certification under this subsection, and a failure to make a determination required under paragraph (4), shall be considered a final agency action for the purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/7">chapter 7</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H76224BED96BF425697829D284F22BB8D"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall take effect on the earlier of—</text> <subparagraph id="HD13CD9C33B754702B0F15CC9A4F068CF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the date on which regulations are issued under paragraph (5); or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H933AD4E8828E44C399634DC7F5404F6D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the date that is 3 years after the date of the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Sustainable Shark Fisheries and Trade Act</short-title>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD0CA086567E4B41A19E1C1DC6AB3617"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text>
 <subparagraph id="HABA0386365C04191A2A657FB4BA414E1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Shark</header><text>The term <quote>shark</quote> means any species of the subclass Elasmobranchii.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC6F732888654A1AAB977F038CA325AB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Shark product</header><text>The term <quote>shark product</quote> means a live shark; a whole shark; the meat, skin, oil, fin (including a wing or tail), gill raker, cartilage, jaw, tooth, or liver of a shark; or any product containing meat, skin, oil, a fin (including a wing or tail), gill raker, cartilage, jaw, tooth, or liver derived from a shark.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C8E19D83A1B4370ABAE59BA40A7353D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Shark finning</header><text>The term <quote>shark finning</quote> means the removal of a shark’s fins, including the tail, and discarding the remaining carcass of the shark at sea.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HFEB66D46AA404A0A8E7AC7D7040211EE"><enum>4.</enum><header>Actions to strengthen international fishery management organizations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 608(a) of the High Seas Driftnet Fishing Moratorium Protection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1826i">16 U.S.C. 1826i(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="H53B85EA08A72484AB753644A999E52FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking subparagraph (F), and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H7F981A472943489E98345925C241D344" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H883698AE027D40288BC92009EDC0E86D"><enum>(F)</enum><text>to adopt shark conservation and management measures and measures to prevent shark finning, which are consistent with the International Plan of Action for Conservation and Management of Sharks of the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4E32C74075374CD7A865EC318BFC0A42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3), and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H9F98CB8704544E93A6FF0CB41A3DC75E" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H4B7EE551F4EE40AEB71AF3D476D2850B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>seeking to enter into international agreement that require measures for the conservation and management of sharks and measures to prevent shark finning, which are consistent with the International Plan of Action for Conservation and Management of Sharks of the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H7A6996B2FF5A421B9C9DA05CB02299CB"><enum>5.</enum><header>Inclusion of rays and skates in seafood traceability program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Commerce shall revise section 300.324 of title 50, Code of Federal Regulations, to include rays and skates in the species and species groups specified in subsection (a)(2) of that section.</text>
 </section><section id="HC691FC8699D6495E86C9609EDFE583F2"><enum>6.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall be construed to preempt any Federal or State law establishing additional or more stringent requirements than the requirements of subsection (g) of section 610 of the High Seas Driftnet Fishing Moratorium Protection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1826k">16 U.S.C. 1826k</external-xref>), as added by section 3.</text>
		</section></legis-body></bill>


