<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HC2CC4F70539A4B3CB30FDC6F29C365A0" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5345 IH: American Leadership in Space Technology and Advanced Rocketry Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5345</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180320">March 20, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001274">Mr. Brooks of Alabama</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S000583">Mr. Smith of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To designate the Marshall Space Flight Center of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration
			 to provide leadership for the U.S. rocket propulsion industrial base, and
			 for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H5E1323D10D6C4D5782D13C7CBBF5EE80" style="OLC">
 <section id="H6CF28299CBCD4F3BBD07673D4916D6CC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Leadership in Space Technology and Advanced Rocketry Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ALSTAR Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H3CDEA620C1164B6EB45892C5D1D487A8" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="HA978CC7F4036490DAD4BDB9508526838"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Rocket propulsion is an enabling technology for our Nation’s future prosperous way of life.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H6AE6503474FF4FB1B058E0A26AA1BB70"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Rocket propulsion technologies are critical to national security, intelligence gathering, communications, weather forecasting, navigation, communications, entertainment, land use, Earth observation, and scientific exploration.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8DFE030DC9D741B895E93420537E615D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The rocket propulsion industry is a source of high-quality jobs.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HFDDF1EFB481B4269BD45119722067114"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Multiple Federal agencies and companies are involved in rocket propulsion research, development, and manufacturing.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0E010B9E5B1542848E06DC40A58F5DFB"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Integration, coordination, and cooperation would strengthen the United States rocket propulsion industrial base.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H06E3CE8CC6F840E0AFEBF66057835E3E"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Erosion of the rocket propulsion industrial base would seriously impact national security, space exploration potential, and economic growth.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBE84726E442E487A90BFA35AF984C2FF"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Marshall Space Flight Center has decades of experience working with other Government agencies and industry partners to study and coordinate these capabilities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB81094A430F746A18A406FBEE2C7D12B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The Marshall Space Flight Center has made historic and unique contributions—</text> <subparagraph id="H54C911BEB5C24D3399FDC8556EE52EEE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by bringing stakeholders together to work on rocket propulsion industrial base sustainment;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36243F271E53406CA6E491F57AE378D6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>of technical expertise to key studies and review boards; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB8EDB1BAE86B4BE5A6DFB0F18C404A46"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by consistently participating in interagency working groups to address rocket propulsion issues.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H16AD4B2255824DA7A27F3AFE3BFC17DE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Rocket propulsion leadership</header>
 <subsection id="H58588D97BEA64CD2AF7538C2923FF32B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the Marshall Space Flight Center is the National Aeronautics and Space Administration’s lead center for rocket propulsion and is essential to sustaining and promoting U.S. leadership in rocket propulsion and developing the next generation of rocket propulsion capabilities.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HDA82D00F29924C76ADDA32C8BECD8537"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Leadership in rocket propulsion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Marshall Space Flight Center shall provide national leadership in rocket propulsion by—</text> <paragraph id="H1B555F2BEE9F453B903E7F4B4DED5592"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">contributing to interagency coordination for the preservation of critical national rocket propulsion capabilities;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H99BFF9DFB7474A6BBD58D7D1FF1B8F8C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>collaborating with industry, academia, and professional organizations to most effectively use national capabilities and resources;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0FADD0C4F0BF4207A242E035529EB07F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>monitoring public- and private-sector rocket propulsion activities to develop and promote a strong, healthy rocket propulsion industrial base;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9105F88E1F604FE5AD69B2827A893EEC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>facilitating technical solutions for existing and emerging rocket propulsion challenges;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB14AEDBB68584D2CBB4AF5E5166D3526"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supporting the development and refinement of rocket propulsion for small satellites;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCFAD23A78B354C679AD0ABBEAAC7DE8D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>evaluating and recommending, as appropriate, new rocket propulsion technologies for further development; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H79EF452E16C4464FB8EC3F4DC9E60F99"><enum>(7)</enum><text>providing information required by national decisionmakers so that policies and other instruments of the Government support the development and strengthening of the Nation’s rocket propulsion capabilities throughout the 21st century.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


