<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE02A30D7600C4474AC17A36746AF9F55" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5556 IH: Environmental Compliance Cost Transparency Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5556</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180418">April 18, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="A000374">Mr. Abraham</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000369">Mr. Amodei</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001290">Mr. Brat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001305">Mr. Budd</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000584">Mr. Gianforte</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000552">Mr. Gohmert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000255">Mr. Jones</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000362">Mr. King of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001177">Mr. McClintock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001180">Mr. McKinley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000588">Mr. Pearce</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001180">Mr. Schrader</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="Y000065">Mr. Yoho</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide for transparency and reporting related to direct and indirect costs incurred by the Bonneville Power Administration, the Western Area Power Administration, the Southwestern Power Administration, and the Southeastern Power Administration related to compliance with any Federal environmental laws impacting the conservation of fish and wildlife, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H6866746B0A3D41AF8CFCA5F8703F6B64" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H65C9FC2E167440489FE82AB70E8BD352" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Environmental Compliance Cost Transparency Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4DEE9B697EFC458E91C46A8D7B16A1B5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Transparency and reporting</header> <subsection id="HC687C51D0ACD4233B91953A19BC957C4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Information included in monthly billing to power customers</header><text>The Administrators of each of the Bonneville Power Administration, the Western Area Power Administration, the Southwestern Power Administration, and the Southeastern Power Administration shall include in monthly billings sent to each of their power customers information estimating and reporting the costs of the customer’s share of the direct and indirect costs that are incurred by the administration related to compliance with any Federal environmental laws impacting the conservation of fish and wildlife considered by the Administrator concerned, at that Administrator’s sole discretion after consultation with consumers, to be relevant.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9257D60C43244D3A84CD6CB7A9037D2E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Direct costs</header><text>Direct costs reported under this section shall include Federal agency obligations related to costs of studies; capital, operation, maintenance, and replacement costs; and staffing costs.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H4CB7AB80B5334F0E9CB9BA04BD62FCBD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Indirect costs</header><text>Indirect costs reported under this section shall include foregone generation and replacement power costs, including the net costs of any transmission.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7C25A58DE61941FA85250348F1FCAA3C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Commissioner of the Bureau of Reclamation and the head of any other affected Federal agency shall assist the Administrators with the identification of the costs.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H717C68BDE893449E97B9AD86828E10AF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text>No later than January 30 of each year, each of the Administrators referred to in subsection (a), in coordination with the Bureau of Reclamation and other affected Federal agencies, shall provide an annual report to the appropriate committees of the House of Representatives and the Senate that includes—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1D3A6CD905E140918E13F6F8E3D47822"><enum>(1)</enum><text>estimates of the total direct and indirect costs that are incurred by the administration related to compliance with any Federal environmental laws impacting the conservation of fish and wildlife considered by the Administrator concerned, at that Administrator’s sole discretion after consultation with consumers, to be relevant; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H541C93C023864A48B8ED6C88A2CD5AD5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the sources of replacement power.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


