<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H229E11B49ED041F9A549816CBF9167D8" key="H" public-private="public">
	<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5606 IH: Climate Change Education Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
		<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
		<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
		<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5606</legis-num>
		<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
		<action display="yes">
			<action-date date="20180424">April 24, 2018</action-date>
			<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001170">Ms. Shea-Porter</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001050">Ms. Hanabusa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001166">Mr. McNerney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000800">Mr. Welch</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
		</action>
		<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
		<official-title display="yes">To authorize the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration to establish a Climate Change
			 Education Program, and for other purposes.</official-title>
	</form>
	<legis-body id="H80C61A5F332A402A8E86C30A7FDB23CE" style="OLC">
 <section id="HE19A4CAC13A242888BDC515946DBD08E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Climate Change Education Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H1EDA2C83B9A5424D91C798239F3AAA9D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text>
 <paragraph id="H13DF1EBAADE04467ADE5E412149BB126"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The evidence for human-induced climate change is overwhelming and undeniable.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H2CB09699261F44A69C1ED1E04AB2183C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Atmospheric carbon can be significantly reduced through conservation, by shifting to renewable energy sources such as solar, wind, tidal, and geothermal, and by increasing the efficiency of buildings, including domiciles, and transportation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8B1A70A8A39447A1A5F5D0133BCA9B9C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Providing clear information about climate change, in a variety of forms, can remove the fear and the sense of helplessness, and encourage individuals and communities to take action.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2FB20448A4114259ACA3BEB1E30C5A52"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Implementation of measures that promote energy efficiency, conservation, and renewable energy will greatly reduce human impact on the environment.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3F4D9DA2A83D450992BBD9B33A2C86FA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Informing people of new technologies and programs as they become available will ensure maximum understanding and maximum effect of those measures.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF5196513038340DAA529621CD4CDFAEC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>More than 3,000,000 students graduate from high schools and colleges each year, armed with attitudes, skills, and knowledge about the climate that inform their actions.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD92BE2F544F54D7C938E0A64EA444ED9"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The effect on the climate, positive or negative, of each of those 3,000,000 students lasts beyond a lifetime.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H78BD0864F59740A383B89742428579B0"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Those students need to be prepared to implement changes in professional and personal practices, to support and help develop new technology and policy, and to address the coming social and economic challenges and opportunities arising from a changing climate.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA913148F7D374836BF0D95A0C2CEA9A1"><enum>(9)</enum><text>It has been demonstrated that the people of the United States overwhelmingly support teaching students about the causes, consequences, and potential solutions to climate change in all 50 States and more than 3,000 counties across the United States.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H585CC0AE2883404187C03E40066333D7"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Only 30 percent of middle school and 45 percent of high school science teachers understand the extent of the scientific consensus on climate change.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HEEEECD04021544FD84CCDB966EE960A6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HDDD5DDEF8EFF42E3A96A19FC5AA308CD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Climate change education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>climate change education</term> means informal and formal interdisciplinary learning at all age levels about—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H895E8FE63F634A7E8D3DC9249FD39DB6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">climate change, climate adaptation and mitigation, and climate resilience; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7E83BF1C0A9432D988758175862284E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effects of climate change, climate adaptation and mitigation, and climate resilience on the environmental, energy, social, and economic systems of the United States.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B172063831241DA9B31746F628551DF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Green collar job</header><text>The term <term>green collar job</term> means a job—</text> <subparagraph id="HA5C4F56B310341649807D900E0C4E01B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in a business that produces goods or provides services that benefit the environment or conserve natural resources; or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCCA5938EDA4F420087803EB8D46FAC46"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in which the duties of the worker involve making the production processes of the employer more environmentally friendly or use fewer natural resources.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF614C713A96240F582AA020C5EF945D5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Green economy</header><text>The term <term>green economy</term> means an economy that results in improved human well-being and social equity by significantly reducing environmental risks and ecological scarcities.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9C43F53B46EB405CAE55B770D0423DBB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H3A9EB3DAEFBA42A4B40AB98FF7595795"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Local educational agency; State educational agency</header><text>The terms <term>local educational agency</term> and <term>State educational agency</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBE26F69DA5584954AD7A0C15B175B40C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Nonprofit organization</header><text>The term <term>nonprofit organization</term> means an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from taxation under 501(a) of that Code.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="HD472D58A8D4D4ACE9C0BDB0E20B26CF0"><enum>4.</enum><header>Climate Change Education Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall establish a Climate Change Education Program to—</text>
 <paragraph id="H5904B662C4C54BB9AF5CC9B3706E82A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>increase the climate literacy of the United States by broadening the understanding of climate change, including possible long-term and short-term consequences and potential solutions;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8DDBEC25091A4E12AEBAFBF2B309FD8B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>apply the latest scientific and technological discoveries, including through the use of the scientific assets of the Administration, to provide formal and informal learning opportunities to individuals of all ages, including individuals of diverse cultural and linguistic backgrounds; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H293240F7CFE8479CA9AE675F7A4A7CE8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>emphasize actionable information to help people understand and promote implementation of new technologies, programs, and incentives related to climate change, climate adaptation and mitigation, and climate resilience.</text>
			</paragraph></section><section id="H7104AB0087CF4588931EEF9557A38725"><enum>5.</enum><header>Grant program</header>
 <subsection id="H2712F35443D64D00A8C8665A412F66DF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As part of the Climate Change Education Program established under section 4, the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall establish a program to make grants—</text>
 <paragraph id="HE5DBE96D6E224E6E84701C82A3E36B76"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to States to encourage and support plans and programs for kindergarten through grade 12 formal and informal climate change education—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H21FA19134F89449E92F76AF2A9DD7FF7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to ensure that students graduate from high school with high climate literacy, including—</text> <clause id="H474F1430C759461AA097055CDE963608"><enum>(i)</enum><text>relevant teacher training and professional development;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HDCF5B78BD3C34C8EBE1611FAADB1A926"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>science, technology, engineering, arts and design, and mathematics education; and</text> </clause><clause id="H2D19DCE9188745B79A0847FA9D74463E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>interdisciplinary studies; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC14E86031F2B43D4B44342F901AA4BB1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with a particular focus on programs that advance widespread State and local educational agency adoption of climate change education, including funding for State educational agencies in partnership with local educational agencies and local nonprofit organizations to—</text>
 <clause id="H2362FB0A04F24C888ADE4F3ABBE49315"><enum>(i)</enum><text>integrate key principles of climate change education into existing kindergarten through grade 12 State academic content standards, student academic achievement standards, or State curriculum frameworks;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1A5FC7B983224D83AD18174FCCD754B6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>create model State climate change curricula;</text> </clause><clause id="H9965EB950CF9498E9BF41F439AE91909"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>develop and implement State teacher training programs; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H4C1E5A360FC4415C8B5724565FB2BF2B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>support secondary school preparation or work-based experiences in green collar jobs;</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5B0DF9D243A457FA462E0278E844801"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to institutions of higher education to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HBBA747ED4BA44FF0A50C8EAFDCC7DF5C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improve the quality of and access to training, certification, and higher education for green collar jobs in the future green economy, such as green construction, design, technology, health, engineering, business, and policy studies, including sustainability science, and with a particular focus on programs that address restructuring institutional incentives and reducing institutional barriers to widespread faculty adoption of interdisciplinary teaching of climate change education; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE27C28D5F66649ED8106BED84AD15B37"><enum>(B)</enum><text>engage teams of faculty and students to develop applied climate research and deliver to local communities direct services related to local climate mitigation and adaptation issues, with a priority focus on communities impacted by climate change; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H75175371C8DE495FBA41AF1E8842773F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to professional associations for projects that build capacity at the State and national levels for continuing education by practicing professionals and the general public in green economy fields.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H76E099039DC64F5FA2E48A66F47A3984"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Climate Change Education Office</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be, within the Office of Education of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, a Climate Change Education Office to administer the grant program required by subsection (a).</text>
 </subsection></section><section id="H0A910D15D64242B1B14C69C97493E4C3"><enum>6.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall submit to Congress a report that evaluates the scientific merits, educational effectiveness, and broader effects of activities carried out under this Act.</text>
 </section><section id="H256CF1191F7D4D5CAD3345B66984DFB1"><enum>7.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration $20,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2024 to carry out this Act.</text>
		</section></legis-body>
</bill>


