<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H4442FA66972847E0A7A61E702B51ECCF" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5531 IH: Opioid Emergency Response Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5531</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180417">April 17, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001260">Mr. Buchanan</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001202">Mrs. Murphy of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for a comprehensive, multifaceted approach to preventing and treating opioid addiction.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HCA10E6D4923144919A9DEF1993AABFC7" style="OLC">
		<section id="H7F67FCAD5FED4B2DAEF68A9AA0E35526" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header>
 <subsection id="HC5E903CD9AA646C7A287BE6F266F0A81"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Opioid Emergency Response Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </subsection><subsection id="H0E0C77300ED2415B950A44CF9577AFE5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
				<toc container-level="legis-body-container" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration">
					<toc-entry idref="H7F67FCAD5FED4B2DAEF68A9AA0E35526" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H52177263644445D3BCB8470525B22C7B" level="section">Sec. 2. Alternatives to opioids prescribing.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H6CF44E2867FD4BD8BB725A8A5EDA8313" level="section">Sec. 3. Opioids and STOP Pain Initiative.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H5165C42B461549749299C7685BC2295B" level="section">Sec. 4. Veteran over-medication prevention.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HA1790C88E59344E5AFE8A0E0C6B150D8" level="section">Sec. 5. Amendment relating to the account for the State response to the opioid abuse crisis.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="HAB4DC9121A264210BE703EE52A21E6C8" level="section">Sec. 6. Mental health access improvement.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H2CC45CA39EE84E81A1A08B698F93A3A6" level="section">Sec. 7. Synthetics Trafficking and Overdose Prevention.</toc-entry>
					<toc-entry idref="H33540F855D894B6887E1E1F357DF0FFB" level="section">Sec. 8. Stop the Importation and Trafficking of Synthetic Analogues.</toc-entry>
				</toc>
			</subsection></section><section id="H52177263644445D3BCB8470525B22C7B" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Alternatives to opioids prescribing</header>
 <subsection id="H5969E158DDC74EAAA1120155920693F3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall carry out a 5-year demonstration project under which payment shall be made under the hospital outpatient prospective payment system under part B of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395j">42 U.S.C. 1395j</external-xref> et seq.) to participating hospitals for items and services furnished as alternatives to opioid medications to individuals enrolled under such part to treat conditions designated under subsection (c)(1) for purposes of evaluating the benefits of using, instead of opioid medications, such alternatives to treat in emergency departments such symptoms and conditions.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H4C8D3B8AF9A04FD28F9343ECFCCEB158"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Emergency departments</header>
 <paragraph id="HF1AE2BB467FE4228B437C9F3D2FB1091"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Selection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall select from hospitals with emergency departments voluntarily submitting applications under paragraph (4), not fewer than 30 hospitals with emergency departments, and not more than 50 hospitals with emergency departments, for participation in the demonstration project.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2C00682512114BAA809A1CF48685FC09"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Diversity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In selecting hospitals with emergency departments, the Secretary shall ensure such hospitals and emergency departments are diverse in geography and size.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFEA34180B5B94A45A0404A1C3E59A26D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Voluntary participation</header><text>Participation in the demonstration project under this section shall be on a voluntary basis.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H591DC9A742844F3F8C314EEE75B1865B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Applications</header> <subparagraph id="H0CC873B97442417E8AB2C96C258F3463"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To participate in the demonstration project, a hospital with an emergency department shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information (in addition to the written commitment described in subparagraph (B)) as specified by the Secretary. The Secretary shall take such measures as is necessary to make available such application form to potential participants no later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70AE043B8C34486CBF01F028174B68FD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Information required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each application submitted by a hospital under subparagraph (A) shall include a binding written commitment to participate in the demonstration project for the duration of the project signed by the Chief Executive Officer of the hospital, the physician medical director of the emergency department of the hospital, the nursing director of the emergency department of the hospital, and the pharmacy director of the emergency department of the hospital.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3AD016A98A9E4463A42B7C4AD9B687D6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Elements of demonstration project</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under the demonstration project, the following shall apply:</text> <paragraph id="HF93FF64B3DFB4B03A1CF98CDA49F3550"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall designate no fewer than five conditions or sets of symptoms that will be monitored during the demonstration project.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA73E90903C9C4B6DA5FB124F765E0848"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The performance during each year of the demonstration project, with respect to such conditions designated under paragraph (1), of all emergency departments of hospitals participating in the demonstration project will be measured against the performance of such emergency departments during a base year, which shall represent the most recent set of full year data available before the first date of the demonstration project.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6E96B92E40BB49F4BA491B3DD603703E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Secretary shall provide hospitals participating in the demonstration project with a description of clearly defined treatments that are considered alternatives to opioids to be applied for purposes of subsection (a).</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD52536DA142A423A9EB5FAD13F9453EA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Incentive payment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under the demonstration project, the Secretary shall create a payment structure under which hospitals participating in the demonstration project that increase the use of alternatives to opioids and decrease the use of opioids may receive a shared savings bonus in addition to what would otherwise be made for items and services furnished under subsection (a). The amount of such shared savings shall be based on the difference between readmission rates for individuals treated with an alternative to opioids at the emergency department of the participating hospital and the average rate of readmissions for individuals treated with opioids and discharged from a representative group of emergency departments of hospitals not participating in the demonstration project in the same region as the participating hospital over a period of five years.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HD69708C64E3D49E1861DDFFE11E72987"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing under this section shall prevent a health care provider from prescribing an opioid if an opioid is a medically necessary treatment.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="HA069D74D1503488EAA24F412B9DA0CE4"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header>
 <paragraph id="H5B778CE2629D42A5A060F000427B7D05"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that includes—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HC8F5CA63811E4BE2A4FA3158AFED7736"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the application form described in subsection (b)(4)(A) that is to be made available to potential participants; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H064984A7822349A3B674D14740271E31"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a progress report with respect to designating the conditions under subsection (c)(1) and establishing the description of clearly defined treatments described in subsection (c)(3).</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A3C50EADB1E4B8B91BEB9ABA01A5500"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Periodic demonstration reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning after the first year of the demonstration project and annually thereafter for each year of the demonstration project and not later than one year after the completion of the demonstration, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that includes the following data for each hospital participating under the demonstration project:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H27E448CECFCD4492B833D34F3CEC90B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each condition or set of symptom designated under subsection (c)(1), the number of individuals treated.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H85737527080749409E42F92B85A200ED"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each such condition, the number of individuals treated only with an alternative to opioids.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36FF641C53644FA0BCA6684917EB773F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each such condition, the number of individuals treated first with an alternative to opioids, followed by an opioid in the same visit.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37A50FFDBE3C466BAC086EC74AF83839"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each such condition, the number of individuals treated only with an opioid.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H546258A188554480BBE84148A0EDAB28"><enum>(E)</enum><text>With respect to each individual described in subparagraph (A) treated for such a condition or set of symptoms, whether or not the individual involved returned to the emergency department of the hospital or an emergency department of a different hospital for the same condition or symptoms.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDD5188116E344788079E2E0C611F32F"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The difference in cost between treating an individual with an alternative to opioid versus an opioid.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE447462045EF4552B37665DA7CAFEE11"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any additional information the Secretary determines necessary.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H6CF44E2867FD4BD8BB725A8A5EDA8313"><enum>3.</enum><header>Opioids and STOP Pain Initiative</header> <subsection id="HF36F45C2ACCD40B88F7F68244789B1BB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established an Opioids and STOP Pain Initiative, to be administered by the Director of the National Institutes of Health, in coordination with other agencies, as appropriate, which shall include efforts to support research on the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H94144EF91F9F4AD99FFAD0084B88FF61"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Section 108 of the Comprehensive Addiction and Recovery Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/284q-1">42 U.S.C. 284q–1</external-xref>), known as the STOP Pain Act, which directs the National Institutes of Health to intensify and coordinate fundamental, translational, and clinical research with respect to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H858847C7B2554C7E9DE8292FA5BDAE76"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the understanding of pain;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D30DE7F8D5D4993A5F4A8B36F96F5D4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the discovery and development of therapies for chronic pain; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HED92AB40F80B4C9C8120DEF367E882C2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the development of alternatives to opioids for effective pain treatments.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6132560C27D34E9CB1CA7E311FE26FE7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Developing improved options and evidence for medication-assisted treatment.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDDCC287C57D04E098EA6BBE0B9BCF8B5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Developing improved options and evidence for opioid overdose reversal treatments.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H4E94AC4216E848E7A3700B4DD353ED6A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Federal Pain Research Strategy, including research that focuses on—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H9D41FEAA5BFB44BEB05082DB5A6CC77D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>novel drugs, non-addictive, and non-pharmacological treatments for pain;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C209FDD2AB049C9A0BB15B1D99F9E08"><enum>(B)</enum><text>screening tools and outcome measure for assessments across the continuum of pain;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF35D0A2A8C147CDBE1ABCEB62B1C4F1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>national registries, datasets, and research networks;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H075601F502444636B83784A6EE004D0B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>effective models of care delivery for pain management; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46D6AB8768D44577ABD2C9032F4F4A67"><enum>(E)</enum><text>precision medicine methodology to prevent and treat pain.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3BC08EC0565940FBBF1E9A2A0492DAC1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The components of the Department of Health and Human Services five-point strategy to address the opioid crisis that states: <quote>Providing support for cutting edge research on pain and addiction</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB8C59A18E10049DAA7285BBD1CCA1967"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The pain therapy screening program established under subsection (c).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H90DC033B244045CA8ACD0632151C65B8"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Other elements that the Secretary of Health and Human Services may designate, in consultation with the Director of the National Institutes of Health.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H600F426AA52C48979D12A52E7D4B8F39"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Funding for the Opioids and STOP Pain Initiative</header>
 <paragraph id="H298927DC7A75480EAAD9461D9397CA46"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated, and there is appropriated, $500,000,000, to be used during the 5-fiscal-year period beginning in the fiscal year in which such funds are appropriated, to the National Institutes of Health Innovation Account to be used to administer the Opioids and STOP Pain Initiative established under subsection (a).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HD0945E3B2D284F61A3C462BC33EDED55"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Emergency spending</header>
 <subparagraph id="H67592EEF741C4B1A8C5C9265C783F61B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Amounts appropriated under paragraph (1) are designated as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 4(g) of the Statutory Pay-As-You-Go Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/933">2 U.S.C. 933(g)</external-xref>).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC9AF0EB41164A1AB8CB97095C53177A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Designation in the senate</header><text>In the Senate, amounts appropriated under subsection (a) are designated as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 403(a) of S. Con. Res. 13 (111th Congress), the concurrent resolution on the budget for fiscal year 2010.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H590A7FF6755547BEA78E59DCEBDBC2BF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Pain Therapy Screening Program</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1A631E936A96498DACF0FF069B154690"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall carry out through the National Institutes of Health a program to be known as the <quote>Pain Therapy Screening Program</quote> that focuses on the development of pain therapeutics.</text> </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE1690FF347BC4854819D2077D3D7AA36"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants under the program under paragraph (1) to eligible public and private nonprofit entities to support the development of new pre-clinical models for pain disorders, and the application of these models in drug, device, or other therapy screening.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HADAA9E8636614677BB2992E0DA4FF87B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Model</header><text>The program under this section shall be modeled after the Epilepsy Therapy Screening Program carried out by the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2D54649AABC04070B2A11B381E6340BE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Fees</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services may assess reasonable fees on private pharmaceutical or medical device industry entities that utilize the program under this section to screen proprietary molecular compounds and devices. Such fees shall be paid to the Foundation for the National Institutes of Health and transferred to the NIH Innovation Account to be used for the Opioids and STOP Pain Initiative established under subsection (a).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H417236ADB08C482DAF11D6C821690468"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>The Director of the National Institutes of Health shall determine the amount, and allocate, funds from the amount appropriated under subsection (b), to carry out this section.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4F8A6CD5D1214498B8EEEBC53D4B8834"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Funding provisions</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6D526E4F19644A6B887E3096C540B015"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Supplement not supplant</header><text>Amounts appropriated in this section (including the amendments made by this section) shall be used to supplement, not supplant, current funding for pain and opioid research at the National Institutes of Health.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB4FD84FF2E0F48D89AFE341E77938327"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Acceptance of donations</header><text>Notwithstanding section 1342 of title 31, United States Code, the Secretary of Health and Human Services may accept donations (including from the pharmaceutical and medical device industries) to be used to assist in carrying out programs and activities under this section (and the amendments made by this section). Such donations shall be paid to the Foundation for the National Institutes of Health and transferred to the NIH Innovation Account to be used for the Opioids and STOP Pain Initiative established under subsection (a).</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HB53D7B5FD3CC4BBBBD9532C297352805"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Inclusion of contribution amounts in basic research for purposes of research credit</header>
 <subparagraph id="HF57749E047904F4DAF4F9EF9CBF9C9AC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (6) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/41">section 41(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
						<quoted-block act-name="" id="H71EEA976F5E24918A4DADA004A2C1DF7" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="HE562D1ABA0C74A3A84EA16B09C0D759F"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Opioids and STOP Pain Initiative</header><text>The National Institutes of Health, if the payment is made in support of the Opioids and STOP Pain Initiative, as established by the Opioids and STOP Pain Initiative Act.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2831C7375EEB4A58AFB6AFD1A6373DC0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF137AF99F76C4D24ACA75A76B5F86B1B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of the law, the Director of the National Institutes of Health may use funds available under subsection (b) to enter into transactions (other than contracts, cooperative agreements, or grants) to carry out research identified pursuant to the Opioids and STOP Pain Initiative established under subsection (a).</text>
			</subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF46C481C071B4B2992148939CAA4D3D4"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports</header>
 <paragraph id="HB51C47617ABE44FABFF9FB3100AC336C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text>Not later than October 1 of each of fiscal years 2019 through 2026, the Director of the National Institutes of Health shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives, a report that includes—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H94D896335190419984029B9D14432435"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount obligated or expended in the fiscal year prior to the fiscal year in which the report is being submitted for each program or activity described in this section (or an amendment made by this section);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H69DA6048EAF24D849D83BC9A72C42D8A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of all such programs or activities carried out using funds provided under this section (or amendments); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B1FD92535FB4A48B998B0167EE76EF5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of how such programs or activities are advancing public health, including the impact on treating pain and addressing opioid misuse in the United States.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF05D7B341AAD448A987DCC4A34174551"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional reports</header><text>At the request of the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions or the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate, or the Committee on Energy and Commerce or the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives, the Director of the National Institutes of Health shall provide to the relevant committee an update in the form of testimony and additional reports concerning the allocation of funding under this section (or the amendments made by this section) or the description of the programs and activities carried out with such funding.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H5165C42B461549749299C7685BC2295B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Veteran over-medication prevention</header>
			<subsection id="H6770DDF6E14D4654B8586A15DCB44C73"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review required</header>
 <paragraph id="H46CAFC5E02374480825DB6BBE5148340"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall seek to enter into an agreement with the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine under which the National Academies shall conduct a review of the deaths of all covered veterans who died by suicide during the five-year period ending on the date of the enactment of this Act, regardless of whether information relating to such deaths has been reported by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H6D459E6C80BA4FFF9DE89C9E9334750C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The review required by paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H59DC811F855F4E6997493FA84CD85D24"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The total number of covered veterans who died by suicide during the five-year period ending on the date of the enactment of this Act.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1F79EE151424B6BAAB3749224A71736"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The total number of covered veterans who died by a violent death during such five-year period.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30447DA8FCD5426089538331D88FBBC6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The total number of covered veterans who died by an accidental death during such five-year period.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFAE6D362798C46D7A374AF7644E9F5BF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A description of each covered veteran described in subparagraphs (A) through (C), including age, gender, race, and ethnicity.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7B7A2DEB16B421FA7E1FF1477F64378"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A comprehensive list of prescribed medications and legal or illegal substances as annotated on toxicology reports of covered veterans described in subparagraphs (A) through (C), specifically listing any medications that carried a black box warning, were prescribed for off-label use, were psychotropic, or carried warnings that included suicidal ideation.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBAF1A9B9C3074C8A96009C590DA482F4"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A summary of medical diagnoses by physicians of the Department of Veterans Affairs or physicians providing services to covered veterans through programs of the Department that led to the prescribing of medications referred to in subparagraph (E) in cases of post-traumatic stress disorder, traumatic brain injury, military sexual trauma, and other anxiety and depressive disorders.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31BE274E1BA041D49160EF08F33E3859"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The number of instances in which a covered veteran described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) was concurrently on multiple medications prescribed by physicians of the Department or physicians providing services to veterans through programs of the Department to treat post-traumatic stress disorder, traumatic brain injury, military sexual trauma, other anxiety and depressive disorders, or instances of comorbidity.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43008C7567584194BD3B627070B7E1E5"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The number of covered veterans described in subparagraphs (A) through (C) who were not taking any medication prescribed by a physician of the Department or a physician providing services to veterans through a program of the Department.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8FF7608590854E69B4A898F21DFC4D99"><enum>(I)</enum><text>With respect to the treatment of post-traumatic stress disorder, traumatic brain injury, military sexual trauma, or other anxiety and depressive disorders, the percentage of covered veterans described in subparagraphs (A) through (C) who received a non-medication first-line treatment compared to the percentage of such veterans who received medication only.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H48FB4AD5F2ED48DC938E0EC07D76FC21"><enum>(J)</enum><text>With respect to the treatment of covered veterans described in subparagraphs (A) through (C) for post-traumatic stress disorder, traumatic brain injury, military sexual trauma, or other anxiety and depressive disorders, the number of instances in which a non-medication first-line treatment (such as cognitive behavioral therapy) was attempted and determined to be ineffective for such a veteran, which subsequently led to the prescribing of a medication referred to in subparagraph (E).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0BE587C2FD6744ADA1C427D481E87831"><enum>(K)</enum><text>A description and example of how the Department determines and continually updates the clinical practice guidelines governing the prescribing of medications.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5DBDA01745264F35AEC0FB2F27243DD9"><enum>(L)</enum><text>An analysis of the use by the Department, including protocols or practices at medical facilities of the Department, of systematically measuring pain scores during clinical encounters under the Pain as the 5th Vital Sign Toolkit of the Department and an evaluation of the relationship between the use of such measurements and the number of veterans concurrently on multiple medications prescribed by physicians of the Department.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE484D9586AD24ED687B3A76BE0330003"><enum>(M)</enum><text>A description of the efforts of the Department to maintain appropriate staffing levels for mental health professionals, such as mental health counselors, marriage and family therapists, and other appropriate counselors, including—</text>
 <clause id="H58A77A83B2DD4D7C9CC5C7A8EA4B34FF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a description of any impediments to carry out the education, training, and hiring of mental health counselors and marriage and family therapists under section 7302(a) of title 38, United States Code, and strategies for addressing those impediments;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H760B3A095A4E46AD9A125E577535E58D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a description of the objectives, goals, and timing of the Department with respect to increasing the representation of such counselors and therapists in the behavioral health workforce of the Department, including—</text>
 <subclause id="H5090E12592A24FA18F659E4C3B29D1A8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a review of eligibility criteria for such counselors and therapists and a comparison of such criteria to that of other behavioral health professions in the Department; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HEBB4A04A091149EA90DDE74A21391056"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an assessment of the participation of such counselors and therapists in the mental health professionals trainee program of the Department and any impediments to such participation;</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H49508927FDCC4504AB1D2C8C8C1BAB2A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an assessment of the development by the Department of hiring guidelines for mental health counselors, marriage and family therapists, and other appropriate counselors;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H5DF0E91E8DF74361A87FBE92884C53E4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a description of how the Department—</text> <subclause id="H3E727D562E444343AF928CC7EF57E11A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>identifies gaps in the supply of mental health professionals; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HB2C4EAECC3EB4951820F29BDD97BD876"><enum>(II)</enum><text>determines successful staffing ratios for mental health professionals of the Department;</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="H626E5F9162544BCCBA165F34BAFE2AE0"><enum>(v)</enum><text>a description of actions taken by the Secretary, in consultation with the Director of the Office of Personnel Management, to create an occupational series for mental health counselors and marriage and family therapists of the Department and a timeline for the creation of such an occupational series; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H43A4F4A32A0D46BB8C372EE29FA1C482"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>a description of actions taken by the Secretary to ensure that the national, regional, and local professional standards boards for mental health counselors and marriage and family therapists are comprised of only mental health counselors and marriage and family therapists and that the liaison from the Department to such boards is a mental health counselor or marriage and family therapist.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB0B8E0048B674CC39139017A65746028"><enum>(N)</enum><text>The percentage of covered veterans described in subparagraphs (A) through (C) with combat experience or trauma related to combat experience (including military sexual trauma, traumatic brain injury, and post-traumatic stress).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEB7265C337FC4FF4B62B1A3064FB5B71"><enum>(O)</enum><text>An identification of the medical facilities of the Department with markedly high prescription rates and suicide rates for veterans receiving treatment at those facilities.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA4223C7654B4AC7B3AD07568A4FFCA1"><enum>(P)</enum><text>An analysis, by State, of programs of the Department that collaborate with State Medicaid agencies and the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services, including the following:</text>
 <clause id="HFCCF71B2E46B4B85AEC19E04D39A2255"><enum>(i)</enum><text>An analysis of the sharing of prescription and behavioral health data for veterans.</text> </clause><clause id="H32B8485C49A744A8B726B1397C2F292F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An analysis of whether Department staff check with State prescription drug monitoring programs before prescribing medications to veterans.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC4DFD80E49B04F998E84F6A9082ECBF8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A description of the procedures of the Department for coordinating with prescribers outside of the Department to ensure that veterans are not overprescribed.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H191CE54A86B645659C39483F54ADCBC0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A description of actions that the Department takes when a veteran is determined to be overprescribed.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H235C3A33B0314136B84705CC2BD3B544"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>An analysis of the collaboration of medical centers of the Department with medical examiners’ offices or local jurisdictions to determine veteran mortality and cause of death.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBCF2875B7DE04DAB8E2B22D42D63AB87"><enum>(R)</enum><text>An identification and determination of a best practice model to collect and share veteran death certificate data between the Department of Veterans Affairs, the Department of Defense, States, and tribal entities.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B17D9ECA37242DE93A024545A40DF0B"><enum>(S)</enum><text>A description of how data relating to death certificates of veterans is collected, determined, and reported by the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66D29C92F2AC4618BBC59BC1400D0882"><enum>(T)</enum><text>An assessment of any patterns apparent to the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine based on the review conducted under paragraph (1).</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H047B0F4A345844719DAB619316867AD2"><enum>(U)</enum><text>Such recommendations for further action that would improve the safety and well-being of veterans as the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine determine appropriate.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CBD691992564D3885FCA75AE117BC74"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Compilation of data</header>
 <subparagraph id="H044158B95E704A66B2D252488A2EB676"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Form of compilation</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall ensure that data compiled under paragraph (2) is compiled in a manner that allows it to be analyzed across all data fields for purposes of informing and updating clinical practice guidelines of the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H328112946AEE47FB9238EF031769B4C6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Compilation of data regarding covered veterans</header><text>In compiling data under paragraph (2) regarding covered veterans described in subparagraphs (A) through (C) of such paragraph, data regarding veterans described in each such subparagraph shall be compiled separately and disaggregated by year.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE1CF1A9F8F1444590A4A2F65455CF90"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Completion of review and report</header><text>The agreement entered into under paragraph (1) shall require that the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine complete the review under such paragraph and submit to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs a report containing the results of the review not later than 180 days after entering into the agreement.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD8ED4AF7E0A74A1A885BFB0B8920AE84"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the completion by the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine of the review required under subsection (a), the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="HB441C9DB92D04E1F9AC1B7FAA8BF64DF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submit to the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on the results of the review; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9C9E9409085640B89A25A3254352E987"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make such report publicly available.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF35A134518B14347B034707A9CA7A092"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
 <paragraph id="H5DBDD1C3A3DB48AC901CB494659035E0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>black box warning</term> means a warning displayed on the label of a prescription drug that is designed to call attention to the serious or life-threatening risk of the prescription drug.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H40A12006B6924B4EB31D7D46C804E128"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>covered veteran</term> means a veteran who received hospital care or medical services furnished by the Department of Veterans Affairs during the five-year period preceding the death of the veteran.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBCAE2F0869AE4338A62910D6BCCCC27B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>first-line treatment</term> means a potential intervention that has been evaluated and assigned a high score within clinical practice guidelines.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4E8E4D1BFB6D41B4954C6EF46A2E08EE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the States, territories, and possessions of the United States, the District of Columbia, and the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA1790C88E59344E5AFE8A0E0C6B150D8"><enum>5.</enum><header>Amendment relating to the account for the State response to the opioid abuse crisis</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1003 of the 21st Century Cures Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/255">Public Law 114–255</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290ee-3">42 U.S.C. 290ee–3</external-xref> note) is amended in subsection (b)(3), by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
			<quoted-block id="H55E63758D7734DA18B3BDB9C5226115A" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="H9BCD1164FF764CA3BA1360AC8F4B10F9"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Appropriations after fiscal year 2018</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated, and there is appropriated, out of any monies in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, to the Account For the State Response to the Opioid Abuse Crisis $500,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
		</section><section id="HAB4DC9121A264210BE703EE52A21E6C8"><enum>6.</enum><header>Mental health access improvement</header>
			<subsection id="H3E6A3A4F8AF54CDE892833EB34BE1965"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Coverage of Services</header>
 <paragraph id="H2B73B15E0A49432FBD6DBBD8E3D3879B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1861(s)(2) of the <act-name parsable-cite="SSA">Social Security Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(s)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HAF50B7689A3441479008C619C60A590A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (FF), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon at the end;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4142803286074280AEDDB86094901D59"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (GG), by inserting <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon at the end; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE8723E69D22B40FF91A412621B9D1CF2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
						<quoted-block id="HF94C761607D84A2B9B7D931FA708B8B4" style="OLC">
 <subitem id="H4903CD6412BA498AA777981FFAA2F403" indent="up5"><enum>(HH)</enum><text>marriage and family therapist services (as defined in subsection (jjj)(1)) and mental health counselor services (as defined in subsection (jjj)(3));</text></subitem><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C73A219991A4B20813F00288BAB05BF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Section 1861 of the <act-name parsable-cite="SSA">Social Security Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block act-name="Social Security Act" id="HFECACD4770E34CBDB9702F21172BA90C" other-style="archaic" style="other"> <subsection id="H7A401C9CA9FB457AAE975B6BF96C7FCC"><enum>(jjj)</enum><header>Marriage and Family Therapist Services; Marriage and Family Therapist; Mental Health Counselor Services; Mental Health Counselor</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0F1FFA18E3B049E7AB5F49A3C96326F0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>marriage and family therapist services</term> means services performed by a marriage and family therapist (as defined in paragraph (2)) for the diagnosis and treatment of mental illnesses, which the marriage and family therapist is legally authorized to perform under State law (or the State regulatory mechanism provided by State law) of the State in which such services are performed, as would otherwise be covered if furnished by a physician or as an incident to a physician’s professional service, but only if no facility or other provider charges or is paid any amounts with respect to the furnishing of such services.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4F2943D56BD147CDA309472EDD63070E" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>marriage and family therapist</term> means an individual who—</text> <subparagraph id="H7EF8F5B6A01343F093DEEBCC9895E669"><enum>(A)</enum><text>possesses a master’s or doctoral degree which qualifies for licensure or certification as a marriage and family therapist pursuant to State law;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D83ECEADF8D4869A72C05D220E8FAAD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>after obtaining such degree has performed at least 2 years of clinical supervised experience in marriage and family therapy; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53E3BC76AF724714BF60BEBBC76EAABA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in the case of an individual performing services in a State that provides for licensure or certification of marriage and family therapists, is licensed or certified as a marriage and family therapist in such State.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H173888AE622C4DDA8B424A0D581E0B98" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>mental health counselor services</term> means services performed by a mental health counselor (as defined in paragraph (4)) for the diagnosis and treatment of mental illnesses which the mental health counselor is legally authorized to perform under State law (or the State regulatory mechanism provided by the State law) of the State in which such services are performed, as would otherwise be covered if furnished by a physician or as incident to a physician’s professional service, but only if no facility or other provider charges or is paid any amounts with respect to the furnishing of such services.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H34644813787D46E5A60C2647DB12649E" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>mental health counselor</term> means an individual who—</text> <subparagraph id="H16907706F27148D5B638C6E8C25D5A69"><enum>(A)</enum><text>possesses a master’s or doctor’s degree in mental health counseling or a related field;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB964223CE95F4C98835808CB3E8A6194"><enum>(B)</enum><text>after obtaining such a degree has performed at least 2 years of supervised mental health counselor practice; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE923359987604B3F87A74321CD6D94E1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in the case of an individual performing services in a State that provides for licensure or certification of mental health counselors or professional counselors, is licensed or certified as a mental health counselor or professional counselor in such State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBE327A47214C41B2894ABCF9ED0125C6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Provision for payment under part B</header><text>Section 1832(a)(2)(B) of the <act-name parsable-cite="SSA">Social Security Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395k">42 U.S.C. 1395k(a)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new clause:</text> <quoted-block act-name="Social Security Act" id="H0411A0182466477D9AEAAA4E8929EFA0" style="OLC"> <clause id="H7B4A3561DAC04A92ACF13E63DB9A9C27"><enum>(v)</enum><text>marriage and family therapist services (as defined in section 1861(jjj)(1)) and mental health counselor services (as defined in section 1861(jjj)(3));</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD7E9439955744A2E9249E7DBE4238D1C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Amount of payment</header><text>Section 1833(a)(1) of the <act-name parsable-cite="SSA">Social Security Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395">42 U.S.C. 1395</external-xref><added-phrase>l</added-phrase>(a)(1)) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H15AF40C814CA49F3B39BFE690BFADDE1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and (BB)</quote> and inserting <quote>(BB)</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72C6C63190E6400AA85C9D32E6E65320"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting before the semicolon at the end the following: <quote>, and (CC) with respect to marriage and family therapist services and mental health counselor services under section 1861(s)(2)(HH), the amounts paid shall be 80 percent of the lesser of the actual charge for the services or 75 percent of the amount determined for payment of a psychologist under subparagraph (L)</quote>.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5BB6EC5D7382441681D145F05B58BE87"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Exclusion of marriage and family therapist services and mental health counselor services from
 skilled nursing facility prospective payment system</header><text>Section 1888(e)(2)(A)(ii) of the <act-name parsable-cite="SSA">Social Security Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395yy">42 U.S.C. 1395yy(e)(2)(A)(ii)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>marriage and family therapist services (as defined in section 1861(jjj)(1)), mental health counselor services (as defined in section 1861(jjj)(3)),</quote> after <quote>qualified psychologist services,</quote>.</text>
				</paragraph><paragraph id="HDA2540CD0A1442BDB7AA2B9C39DF480B"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Inclusion of marriage and family therapists and mental health counselors as practitioners for
 assignment of claims</header><text>Section 1842(b)(18)(C) of the <act-name parsable-cite="SSA">Social Security Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395u">42 U.S.C. 1395u(b)(18)(C)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new clauses:</text> <quoted-block act-name="Social Security Act" id="H9AFADFD158A14452B05FCC95A8BA309F" style="OLC"> <clause id="H85D824B28110440FB718D8318AB3C877" indent="up2"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>A marriage and family therapist (as defined in section 1861(jjj)(2)).</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD0AE046C54664C2E9330E9C434A037CD" indent="up2"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>A mental health counselor (as defined in section 1861(jjj)(4)).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3B440C00672F4F9AAE263AD2F86AEE7C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coverage of certain mental health services provided in certain settings</header> <paragraph id="H6C94D9262EE1449BA08EB2A9FE85D5F7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Rural health clinics and federally qualified health centers</header><text>Section 1861(aa)(1)(B) of the <act-name parsable-cite="SSA">Social Security Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(aa)(1)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>or by a clinical social worker (as defined in subsection (hh)(1))</quote> and inserting <quote>, by a clinical social worker (as defined in subsection (hh)(1)), by a marriage and family therapist (as defined in subsection (jjj)(2)), or by a mental health counselor (as defined in subsection (jjj)(4))</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HAC58E67276C9450B9308C6493ADDF8BC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Hospice programs</header><text>Section 1861(dd)(2)(B)(i)(III) of the <act-name parsable-cite="SSA">Social Security Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(dd)(2)(B)(i)(III)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>, marriage and family therapist, or mental health counselor</quote> after <quote>social worker</quote>.</text> </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H14F5FAA7F2514FEB868A4D8F0F66DCA1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of marriage and family therapists and mental health counselors To develop discharge plans for post-Hospital services</header><text>Section 1861(ee)(2)(G) of the <act-name parsable-cite="SSA">Social Security Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(ee)(2)(G)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>, including a marriage and family therapist and a mental health counselor who meets qualification standards established by the Secretary</quote> before the period at the end.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="HA2237802370E408F8FA26BA918158C95"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to services furnished on or after January 1, 2019.</text>
			</subsection></section><section id="H2CC45CA39EE84E81A1A08B698F93A3A6" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>7.</enum><header>Synthetics Trafficking and Overdose Prevention</header>
 <subsection id="H208C14CA06E54783B72F151AD8D79C2F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Formal entry requirements—postal service as consignee</header><text>Subparagraph (B) of section 484(a)(2) of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1484">19 U.S.C. 1484(a)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6C51567EBA454534B45CAEBAFF63C4AD" style="OLC">
					<subparagraph id="H1F98406158AF4D23AFEE286F5B977A16" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum>
 <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H717C7F617B3D4CF28B0E758CAE73CAAC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>When an entry of merchandise is made under this section, the required documentation or information shall be filed or electronically transmitted—</text>
 <subclause id="H95E03DE7480B465D9D74361514468E89" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by the owner or purchaser of the merchandise; or</text> </subclause><subclause id="H2BD0B6D539804BB5968544D92832EEEE" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>when appropriately designated by the owner, purchaser, or consignee of the merchandise, by a person holding a valid license under section 641.</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="H4DF6FFBB6C934D0A84AF92A9C143035B" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Postmaster General shall be deemed the consignee for merchandise, as defined by section 498(c), imported through the mail, and the Postmaster General shall, at the Postmaster General's sole expense, designate a person holding a valid license under section 641 to file the required documentation or information or ensure that the owner or purchaser of the merchandise or a person holding a valid license under section 641 that is designated by the owner or purchaser files the required documentation or information.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H92B1E8A89D0B4A4F8614A40231F2CB0B" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>When a consignee declares on entry that he or she is the owner or purchaser of merchandise, U.S. Customs and Border Protection may, without liability, accept the declaration.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HD0FCC7DFBAB5478084B609095AC389F0" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>For the purposes of this Act, the importer of record must be one of the parties who is eligible to file the documentation or information required by this section.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H0556C9BFA5BE49A98B330879F3572144"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Informal entries</header><text>Section 498 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1498">19 U.S.C. 1498</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD7AF3FE614314919A80F9300D61D7AF3" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="H2702A394D7F741BB939CCF7173AA44F7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application to postal shipments</header>
 <paragraph id="H4D6046D3F31E4D0FAD4A2FB1F263D7CB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text> <subparagraph id="HFE86F9CC22194A0EA806774E51FC024F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Document</header><text>The term <term>document</term> means a piece of written, drawn, printed, or digital information, excluding objects of merchandise, that—</text>
 <clause id="H40337CBDE3BA4D8DA663A00EB611A72F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is conveyed in an envelope that is less than or equal to 165 millimeters in width, 245 millimeters in length, and 5 millimeters in depth; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HA276CF94B8754CF3B82467F58E8DBF2B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>weighs 100 grams or less when conveyed.</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9277BFA2205744579F7BAE6EB6146EB8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Merchandise</header><text>The term <term>merchandise</term> has the same meaning as that term is defined in section 401 but does not include a document.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H62CD4D0F1F27425AB690A59459559B78"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, for merchandise meeting the requirements of subsection (a), the Postmaster General shall comply with the entry requirements of section 484.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H774008463855494A9730FE857AC2BD28"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Any regulation issued pursuant to this subsection shall apply identical entry procedures for merchandise imported through the mail as are applied for merchandise imported via a private carrier.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="H9F39E341415E462195906C249468F869"><enum>(c)</enum><header>De minimis shipments</header><text>Section 321 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1321">19 U.S.C. 1321</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF2FDB03C4EBB45A39639E065C673DA26" style="OLC">
					<subsection id="HF6915E8D7C79460D8BC4F0F3D3914A6C"><enum>(c)</enum>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H13FF38D516DB4231BB059995AE6D44D1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>For imported articles that qualify for the administrative exemption under subsection (a)(2) and that arrive at international mail facilities in the United States, the Postmaster General shall be deemed the consignee for such articles that are considered merchandise, as the term is defined in section 498(c).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H193E622A6CCD45BF83C40B48C47CAE1C" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In addition to the parties that are authorized to comply with the entry requirements of sections 498 and 484, the Postmaster General, as a consignee, may, using reasonable care, enter such merchandise that qualifies for the administrative exemption under subsection (a)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HC57DD71594EE4B348C27DE662BD86785"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Customs fees</header>
 <paragraph id="HC3F79A20F8244D15BE3B8F9226366237"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (6) of section 13031(a) of the Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/58c">19 U.S.C. 58c(a)(6)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H98122DCC6CC943178CC8F34DCEF1872F" style="OLC">
						<paragraph id="H5353B3CBA2FE4D5090EBE629A5C67F82"><enum>(6)</enum>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC521148C6EED472FB92D1497DDE32B7E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For the arrival of shipments of merchandise (as the term is defined in section 498(c) of the Trade Act of 1930) or any other item that is valued at $2,000 or less (or such higher amount as the Secretary of the Treasury may set by regulation pursuant to section 498 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1498">19 U.S.C. 1498</external-xref>) and subject to adjustment under subsection (l)) arriving at an international mail facility:</text>
 <clause id="HA68B38473F304DF68DB936FD13CA85FF" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>$1 per individual airway bill or bill of lading (subject to adjustment under subsection (l)); or</text> </clause><clause id="H731187ED429A4404A295B625802A2AE5" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if such merchandise is formally entered, the fee provided for in paragraph (9), if applicable.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H473AB4BDDFA7447593D1B8B5AC59DBB0" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Notwithstanding section 451 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1451">19 U.S.C. 1451</external-xref>), the payment required by subparagraph (A) shall be the only payment required for reimbursement of U.S. Customs and Border Protection in connection with the processing of an individual airway bill or bill of lading in accordance with such subparagraph and for providing services at international mail facilities, except that U.S. Customs and Border Protection may require such facilities to cover expenses of the agency for adequate office space, equipment, furnishings, supplies, and security.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E887D2CF98749AC9D13FC73FF532DF9" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The payment required by subparagraphs (A) and (B) shall be paid on a quarterly basis by the Postmaster General in accordance with regulations prescribed by the Secretary of the Treasury. The payments shall be allocated as follows:</text>
 <clause id="H109040022E4D42DA996744E7EFE72594"><enum>(i)</enum><text>50 percent of the amount of payments received in this paragraph shall, in accordance with section 524 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1524">19 U.S.C. 1524</external-xref>), be deposited in the Customs User Fee Account and shall be used to directly reimburse each appropriation for the amount paid out of that appropriation for the costs incurred in providing services to international mail facilities. Amounts deposited in accordance with the preceding sentence shall be available until expended for the provision of customs services to international mail facilities.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF930E2AC93D349AE9B94355145B68F45"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Notwithstanding section 524 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1524">19 U.S.C. 1524</external-xref>), 50 percent of the amount of payments received under this paragraph shall be paid to the Secretary of the Treasury, which is in lieu of the payment of fees under paragraph (10).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H60A4DA4E1F0B4792834D30120453422E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Technical amendments</header><text>Paragraph (10) of section 13031(a) of the Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/58c">19 U.S.C. 58c(a)(10)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H872072490295419B8996B27B51CF140D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or</quote> in subparagraph (B);</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H836B524314FB439FA9A6B42A5FE530DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of subparagraph (C)(iii) and inserting a comma and <quote>or</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77B2C088728A48D3A1E0A31E3278E1BA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (C)(iii) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA68E117A689F400FB7DE64AA2BF44CB0" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HAFDB358C60754890866498268BE28762"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an international mail facility.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2CF0124EE92F4D4C89232EC1C477030B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in the undesignated material at the end by striking the period and inserting <quote>or referred to in subparagraph (D) see paragraph (6).</quote>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC41F266EA4A441B08F88929CB5468FE1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Mandatory advanced electronic information for postal shipments</header><text>Subparagraph (K) of section 343(a)(3) of the Trade Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/210">Public Law 107–210</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/2071">19 U.S.C. 2071</external-xref> note) is amended to read as follows:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6DCB8495B1B14585B6D2F6C61546A838" style="OLC">
 <subparagraph id="HB8062E2F98C14F7E86C686955896C9DE"><enum>(K)</enum><text>The Secretary shall require the Postmaster General to transmit or to ensure the transmission of the information required in paragraphs (1) and (2) to U.S. Customs and Border Protection for all shipments by the United States Postal Service which includes shipments that the United States Postal Service receives from foreign postal operators (shipments from foreign postal operators may be transported by private carriers). All regulations issued pursuant to this provision are required to impose the same information requirements on the United States Postal Service and private carriers.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection id="HC974304D95DD4086A230EFF977E8A6F1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Manifest penalties applied to the United States Postal Service</header>
 <paragraph id="HF1614CE9963646B99A05805E4AF84E75"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Penalties for violations of the arrival, reporting, entry, and clearance requirements</header><text>Section 436 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1436">19 U.S.C. 1436</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEFA4C50D895149EDA5BFBAC9DCB2711E" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="H38110F3906AC40C7AF3AC7691FA6CDD2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Civil penalties arising from violations for postal shipments</header><text>With respect to civil penalties provided for in subsections (b) and (d), the Postmaster General shall be liable for the penalty if the violation was caused by a foreign postal operator or the United States Postal Service.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1E4CC19DAAD443CB919C7B2C48D4355B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties for falsity or lack of manifest</header><text>Section 584 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1584">19 U.S.C. 1584</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA3FA06B888714707888A1DAA087CBF49" style="OLC">
 <subsection id="H90A5A7F4AE5146A7938A5C90CBC6C432"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Person directly or indirectly responsible shall include the Postmaster General</header><text>For purposes of subsection (a), the Postmaster General may be the person directly or indirectly responsible for a discrepancy if the discrepancy is the result of—</text>
 <paragraph id="HAE2F2F8FB325422EA43AF7640FD662B2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an omission by a foreign postal operator or the United States Postal Service; or</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HFF114D4933894249A99A0A71906878E9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>false information regarding the shipment that was provided to the carrier by a foreign postal operator or the United States Postal Service.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H09FB6681196C4D57BCD03BCBA55D5FF0"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Limitation on international postal arrangements</header>
				<paragraph id="HE576B8A8E1F043F79F5E6395D40FAE70"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Existing agreements</header>
 <subparagraph id="HA5D61C163FF9464ABF817BBB7330D16D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the event that any provision in this section is found to be in violation of obligations of the United States under the Universal Postal Union, the Secretary of State shall negotiate to amend the relevant provisions of the agreement so that the United States is no longer in violation of the agreement.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82BD782A8B57457C81CAF606B5645AD2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection may be construed to require or permit any delay in the implementation of this section.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F2F5615C81A4F5A991C65ECE308CDBF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Future agreements</header><text>The Secretary of State may not conclude any international postal arrangement pursuant to the authority set out in section 407 of title 39, United States Code, that is inconsistent with this section or any amendment made by this section.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5C600B95FDD041AC8BDBD34B82161BA0"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Application of other customs laws</header>
 <paragraph id="H7053463E893E42038508D6E035169F3C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">U.S. Customs and Border Protection shall ensure that all merchandise, as that term is defined in subsection (c) of section 498 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1498">19 U.S.C. 1498</external-xref>), imported to the United States through the mail shall be subject to the same import procedures, legal restrictions, and certifications as merchandise imported by private carriers.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCF52B616A5BD4D37B2FA8702B1AA2012"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall issue regulations pursuant to this section to ensure that merchandise imported through the mail is in accordance with Federal law.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD7C42857A97045CCA603F9227B662C34"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Cost recoupment</header><text>The Postmaster General shall ensure that all costs associated with complying with this section, as well as all penalties assessed against the Postmaster General, are charged directly to foreign shippers, foreign postal operators, or United States ultimate consignees.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H6D590925538744D5A6D1EDBF9EABF4A4"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Effective date; regulations</header>
 <paragraph id="H04597C8662544F0786F33BE7C1085B00"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section shall become effective upon the date of the enactment of this Act.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H1C05223B3DFE46D4A2CC95E2D389F339"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall prescribe all regulations required under this section.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H33540F855D894B6887E1E1F357DF0FFB"><enum>8.</enum><header>Stop the Importation and Trafficking of Synthetic Analogues</header>
 <subsection id="H3B9F603BB0CC4B18ABF855C1632AAFAF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of Schedule A</header><text>Section 202 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/812">21 U.S.C. 812</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H0E7A069A370748349FC596C2AAC5CCF2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>five schedules of controlled substances, to be known as schedules I, II, III, IV, and V</quote> and inserting <quote>six schedules of controlled substances, to be known as schedules I, II, III, IV, V, and A</quote>;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HB449BA65AEC140C7906D4B013B5E4ED8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H591E84001F83490E834EBA90F76F5D6F" style="OLC"> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE912CF4DB94D43D4B5CBC5807BC7E68E" indent="up1"><enum>(6)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Schedule A</header> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4F7DFB277867426F815FBAE8B59C330E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The drug or substance—</text>
 <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H78CCD3A839BF4016A1E9758C0A4D248D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2E8D89C04BF748B293DA157FBFDE8B19"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a chemical structure that is substantially similar to the chemical structure of a controlled substance in schedule I, II, III, IV, or V; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H540DC21E226347BB80DFDC51ABA57F59"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an actual or predicted stimulant, depressant, or hallucinogenic effect on the central nervous system that is substantially similar to or greater than the stimulant, depressant, or hallucinogenic effect on the central nervous system of a controlled substance in schedule I, II, III, IV, or V; and</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF802132F3EC94E78BCE05FE3DC3A1D31"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is not—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B52688266324119B1860AEBC9A57D11"><enum>(I)</enum><text>listed or otherwise included in any other schedule in this section or by regulation of the Attorney General; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEBDC82C7889A43BDAC45AD0EA3B3DC10"><enum>(II)</enum><text>with respect to a particular person, subject to an exemption that is in effect for investigational use, for that person, under section 505 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355</external-xref>) to the extent conduct with respect to such substance is pursuant to such exemption.</text>
 </subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC8A1A953C87E4D6E86C6D3D7C0F8BED2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Predicted stimulant, depressant, or hallucinogenic effect</header><text>For purpose of this paragraph, a predicted stimulant, depressant, or hallucinogenic effect on the central nervous system may be based on—</text>
 <clause id="H0AA3DBD45AFD4B42933AFA33138A5CB1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the chemical structure, structure activity relationships, binding receptor assays, or other relevant scientific information about the substance;</text>
								</clause><clause id="H1CB5A6B3B8C44B25B33A1F097A72DE4A"><enum>(ii)</enum>
 <subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD1052D38E30A4B7F9ADEF18E1A7FDF12"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the current or relative potential for abuse of the substance; and</text> </subclause><subclause id="HD68158A647CF4E55976DE2B3F13A7453" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the clandestine importation, manufacture, or distribution, or diversion from legitimate channels, of the substance; or</text>
 </subclause></clause><clause id="HB9D6B732687C4AEC91B5295B09D00C68"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the capacity of the substance to cause a state of dependence, including physical or psychological dependence that is similar to or greater than that of a controlled substance in schedule I, II, III, IV, or V.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1586299AB793423F9BBEE9B73D22DA09"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text> <subparagraph id="H1F004396402F49509EB2358F45D30173"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding schedule I, by striking <quote>IV, and V</quote> and inserting <quote>IV, V, and A</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61F7691188B64AA49C6B043839D3D474"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H439ED45572DA451988F9906238E7DA35" style="traditional"> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC94F0C0503CA4D61AB87C2D442527B11" section-type="undesignated-section"><enum></enum><header>Schedule A</header><text>(a) Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any of the following substances, as scheduled in accordance with section 201(k)(5):</text>
 <paragraph id="HCCF5ECD22CEE4C2A99AB94567203E02E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>4-fluoroisobutyryl fentanyl.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H1EF601DD2C4040AC91E9E2AF26110CDB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Valeryl fentanyl.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H237426925C9C49D1A4CC9233691CBA62"><enum>(3)</enum><text>4-methoxybutyryl fentanyl.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H687CC4A586854713B65094556AD30120"><enum>(4)</enum><text>4-methylphenethyl acetyl fentanyl.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC66E1BDD1DCA4F06B1DE9908E491AD3C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>3-furanyl fentanyl.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HA4910BB4797640FBB815EB140C6213DB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Ortho-fluorofentanyl.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H314FCE0E8F9A4E10ADC0A6F8FFEEDD2F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Tetrahydrofuranyl fentanyl.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H9144F77090C64CB0BC8CD751F16EC3AF"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Ocfentanil.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE0EF9925D82747AF8FC912E1415DB234"><enum>(9)</enum><text>4-fluorobutyryl fentanyl.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H224BCD76BB604CF1BF1BC5E9B7F6D63E"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Methoxyacetyl fentanyl.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD2B00EEF247447A5B72C5D6B841ED9A1"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Meta-fluorofentanyl.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HE033983F7FFD442191D74240651DC9DC"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Isobutyryl fentanyl.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7F5A2A7E4FC7426B9816C335E8D85B94"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Acryl fentanyl.</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H450E9F3AFEEC4A319FF8A28A47FE6F19"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Temporary and permanent scheduling of schedule A substances</header><text>Section 201 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/811">21 U.S.C. 811</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD1A7CF78C4A347D0BDDAC79FA63D0DF9" style="traditional">
					<subsection id="HE118E09FEAB7465EAB10EF5D82404D25"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Temporary and permanent scheduling of schedule A substances</header>
 <paragraph id="HF540209422D4408DA05EBEB8F55D945C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Attorney General may issue a temporary order adding a drug or substance to schedule A if the Attorney General finds that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H6704D12A17BB4C9CA3D5941AE095708C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the drug or other substance satisfies the criteria for being considered a schedule A substance; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4234D5671DFC486C89D9E2F025ABF92E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>adding such drug or substance to schedule A will assist in preventing abuse or misuse of the drug or other substance.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C488ED237534EC9B0C15ABC50A805FB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A temporary scheduling order issued under paragraph (1) shall not take effect until 30 days after the date of the publication by the Attorney General of a notice in the Federal Register of the intention to issue such order and the grounds upon which such order is to be issued. The temporary scheduling order shall expire not later than 5 years after the date it becomes effective, except that the Attorney General may, during the pendency of proceedings under paragraph (5), extend the temporary scheduling order for up to 180 days.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H46A6A4127F5F42BA8DB4ACB4DFD74168"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A temporary scheduling order issued under paragraph (1) shall be vacated upon the issuance of a permanent order issued under paragraph (5) with regard to the same substance, or upon the subsequent issuance of any scheduling order under this section.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE81D37F066D045EABB8AA7D64AF8397D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A temporary scheduling order issued under paragraph (1) shall not be subject to judicial review.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HB7F5FFAEC6FC40AB8F73A47F3505C0FD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Attorney General may, by rule, issue a permanent order adding a drug or other substance to schedule A if such drug or substance satisfies the criteria for being considered a schedule A substance. Such rulemaking may be commenced simultaneously with the issuance of the temporary scheduling order issued under paragraph (1) with regard to the same substance.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5A041FA337B6454A9975CA41825B5BFC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Before initiating proceedings under paragraph (1) or (5), the Attorney General shall transmit notice of an order proposed to be issued to the Secretary of Health and Human Services. In issuing an order under paragraph (1) or (5), the Attorney General shall take into consideration any comments submitted by the Secretary of Health and Human Services in response to a notice transmitted pursuant to this paragraph.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H55CDD1DA18D341A1B99459A399DFC5E3"><enum>(7)</enum><text>On the date of the publication of a notice in the Federal Register pursuant to paragraph (2), the Attorney General shall transmit the same notice to Congress. The temporary scheduling order shall take effect according to paragraph (2), except that the temporary scheduling order may be disapproved by Act of Congress within 180 days from the date of publication of the notice in the Federal Register.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
			</subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HEA4C8E81EDD8445495400BDAED5CF673"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalties</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="HE49E3273C98C43C1B08D84DCFD98F7EF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Controlled Substances Act</header><text>The Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/801">21 U.S.C. 801</external-xref> et seq.) is amended—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H5AD69AF0E771433485573C7F5A74A569"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 401(b)(1) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/841">21 U.S.C. 841(b)(1)</external-xref>), by adding at the end the following:</text>
						<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6191498EA6B6484DA1323EB8B9C8FE1A" style="OLC">
							<subparagraph id="HF46342FE9136451497B7026702DA2AC5" indent="up2"><enum>(F)</enum>
 <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H040A8748827E43248982104832BDA1A5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>In the case of any controlled substance in schedule A, such person shall be sentenced to a term of imprisonment of not more than 10 years and if death or serious bodily injury results from the use of such substance shall be sentenced to a term of imprisonment of not more than 15 years, a fine not to exceed the greater of that authorized in accordance with the provisions of title 18, United States Code, or $500,000 if the defendant is an individual or $2,500,000 if the defendant is other than an individual, or both.</text>
 </clause><clause id="H137FC755DEDB4CEAB0EEC099B8F81D27" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>If any person commits such a violation after a prior conviction for a felony drug offense has become final, such person shall be sentenced to a term of imprisonment of not more than 20 years and if death or serious bodily injury results from the use of such substance shall be sentenced to a term of imprisonment of not more than 30 years, a fine not to exceed the greater of twice that authorized in accordance with the provisions of title 18, United States Code, or $1,000,000 if the defendant is an individual or $5,000,000 if the defendant is other than an individual, or both.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC5C1F3787A734B458D2E519C5B1202B7" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Any sentence imposing a term of imprisonment under this subparagraph shall, in the absence of such a prior conviction, impose a term of supervised release of not less than 2 years in addition to such term of imprisonment and shall, if there was such a prior conviction, impose a term of supervised release of not less than 4 years in addition to such term of imprisonment.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1C0CB56C1A5D4A4D9854C23C1263C471"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 403(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/843">21 U.S.C. 843(a)</external-xref>)—</text> <clause commented="no" id="HE5A69135EDC042B98F3B1ABAD79FC8F7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (8), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="H5065590FA21E4703B8AC643E6203624A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (9), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="H4220989C72A24ABA9A69FA48582B620A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (9) the following:</text>
							<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4DC0F6B7CE3A40A7A99A5FA71A68D0F0" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="H3F7D61E7AEDB4CEAB6124FE27888F83A"><enum>(10)</enum><text>to export a substance in violation of the controlled substance laws of the country to which the substance is exported.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC9BB292090844B85943F8DB0007307A9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in section 404 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/844">21 U.S.C. 844</external-xref>), by inserting after subsection (a) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5E7711370FD24DFD94075BF7C73C7AEA" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H6B42A94FE4144A1C807CA89436109606"><enum>(b)</enum><text>A person shall not be subject to a criminal or civil penalty under this title or under any other Federal law solely for possession of a schedule A controlled substance.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H505EE2C7D2064B2D948CC646A1F60B0B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Controlled Substances Import and Export Act</header><text>Section 1010(b) of the Controlled Substances Import and Export Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/960">21 U.S.C. 960(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5C47CBBCB5FE43558DF5DE08A66C7775" style="OLC">
 <paragraph id="HC8E7FA9129284810A052BF172C80548F" indent="up1"><enum>(8)</enum><text>In the case of a violation under subsection (a) involving a controlled substance in schedule A, the person committing such violation shall be sentenced to a term of imprisonment of not more than 20 years and if death or serious bodily injury results from the use of such substance shall be sentenced to a term of imprisonment of not more than life, a fine not to exceed the greater of that authorized in accordance with the provisions of title 18, United States Code, or $1,000,000 if the defendant is an individual or $5,000,000 if the defendant is other than an individual, or both. If any person commits such a violation after a prior conviction for a felony drug offense has become final, such person shall be sentenced to a term of imprisonment of not more than 30 years and if death or serious bodily injury results from the use of such substance shall be sentenced to not more than life imprisonment, a fine not to exceed the greater of twice that authorized in accordance with the provisions of title 18, United States Code, or $2,000,000 if the defendant is an individual or $10,000,000 if the defendant is other than an individual, or both. Notwithstanding section 3583 of title 18, United States Code, any sentence imposing a term of imprisonment under this paragraph shall, in the absence of such a prior conviction, impose a term of supervised release of not less than 3 years in addition to such term of imprisonment and shall, if there was such a prior conviction, impose a term of supervised release of not less than 6 years in addition to such term of imprisonment. Notwithstanding the prior sentence, and notwithstanding any other provision of law, the court shall not place on probation or suspend the sentence of any person sentenced under the provisions of this paragraph which provide for a mandatory term of imprisonment if death or serious bodily injury results.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB162B68E7DE84C4085B92CB611A81D4D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>False labeling of schedule A controlled substances</header>
 <paragraph id="H0E49699C80A5468EB5D9339CB1DFC44D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 305 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/825">21 U.S.C. 825</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H65E81212CA564626ADC4521D83D56394" style="OLC">
						<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF7E40AFF05AD4D37A7D2117D9A1B13B7"><enum>(f)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">False labeling of schedule A controlled substances</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6DD8BE77D5F54CC3B2000525C3688325"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful to import, export, manufacture, distribute, dispense, or possess with intent to manufacture, distribute, or dispense, a schedule A substance or product containing a schedule A substance, unless the substance or product bears a label clearly identifying a schedule A substance or product containing a schedule A substance by the nomenclature used by the International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry (IUPAC).</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H12D141090A0C454EBC1BFE0B5E04C6FE"><enum>(2)</enum>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HCFD4583E16254DD3A4D036A34D7A9AC8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A product described in subparagraph (B) is exempt from the International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry nomenclature requirement of this subsection if such product is labeled in the manner required under the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA705294F417E446282F1F4B833C0B562" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A product is described in this subparagraph if the product—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H723F178BCB9541C2A3AEE2C373E93C00"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is the subject of an approved application as described in section 505(b) or (j) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act; or</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" id="HB83BDF9A62624C80B152CC6B3B65F121"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is exempt from the provisions of section 505 of such Act relating to new drugs because—</text> <subclause commented="no" id="HD37AAE89D7364928981CB15DC93D57BF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>it is intended solely for investigational use as described in section 505(i) of such Act; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H9D5816855C1D4ED6A4E7676B97F16283"><enum>(II)</enum><text>such product is being used exclusively for purposes of a clinical trial that is the subject of an effective investigational new drug application.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0E5BBE5AE9A94D02B8BB7D5B077BC78D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>Section 402 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/842">21 U.S.C. 842</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HE77E98FB78AC48788BD191C1F596871C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(16), by inserting <quote>or subsection (f)</quote> after <quote>subsection (e)</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5AF6F2400CF048A8BA82F8A645626D5A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(1)(D), by inserting <quote>or a schedule A substance</quote> after <quote>anabolic steroid</quote>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA05C74DFEE374E8BAEB2611E7DF9BB87"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Registration requirements for handlers of schedule A substances</header> <paragraph id="H61EB0068151349E9AFEED39DDF09D956"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Controlled Substances Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 303 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/823">21 U.S.C. 823</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA1A14C74965F4598AB1118005FFBFD79" style="OLC">
						<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5E733E0A1F3C46438307926696FBFC2C"><enum>(k)</enum>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4BADC55AA8944ED599443CC37DAA1ACB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall register an applicant to manufacture schedule A substances if—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H575266A5AB1644EC947B1AC782E13DC8" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the applicant demonstrates that the schedule A substances will be used for research, analytical, or industrial purposes approved by the Attorney General; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE52C5DFBCAB647C7BF26FD7B0A90E0DC" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Attorney General determines that such registration is consistent with the public interest and with the United States obligations under international treaties, conventions, or protocols in effect on the date of enactment of this subsection.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3F2F2F2459424103870A2BDC54BCF43A" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining the public interest under paragraph (1)(B), the Attorney General shall consider—</text> <subparagraph id="H31C38892235942D98274CBB7D948C817"><enum>(A)</enum><text>maintenance of effective controls against diversion of particular controlled substances and any controlled substance in schedule A compounded therefrom into other than legitimate medical, scientific, research, or industrial channels, by limiting the importation and bulk manufacture of such controlled substances to a number of establishments which can produce an adequate and uninterrupted supply of these substances under adequately competitive conditions for legitimate medical, scientific, research, and industrial purposes;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CD0866000D14BA790DF67D7ADE2126C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>compliance with applicable State and local law;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF67236D134D7434BA4DEC33E527ED848"><enum>(C)</enum><text>promotion of technical advances in the art of manufacturing substances described in subparagraph (A) and the development of new substances;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64B70006E35F4A9CBF1B281E4F4EABB3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>prior conviction record of applicant under Federal and State laws relating to the manufacture, distribution, or dispensing of substances described in paragraph (A);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HBA7D15E536DC4548BA73532A9EE150BC"><enum>(E)</enum><text>past experience in the manufacture of controlled substances, and the existence in the establishment of effective control against diversion; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE3978EF8012548FC962FEC967F5B70AE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>such other factors as may be relevant to and consistent with the public health and safety.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C0487A829D14A40A7BCCB4BD9E84E6D" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>If an applicant is registered to manufacture controlled substances in schedule I or II under subsection (a), the applicant shall not be required to apply for a separate registration under this subsection.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB333A2D9FE084DB8A85997991D186D6B"><enum>(l)</enum>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H862FAE038E984A83A4B74B9D88967324"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall register an applicant to distribute schedule A substances—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFEDDE0A642624B28A7C37123F04F4063" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>if the applicant demonstrates that the schedule A substances will be used for research, analytical, or industrial purposes approved by the Attorney General; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1C7BF08AC3DF4310942A3E9088F1E2A2" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">unless the Attorney General determines that the issuance of such registration is inconsistent with the public interest.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8006432D51C94909BF9D0094D310CA74" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining the public interest under paragraph (1)(B), the Attorney General shall consider—</text> <subparagraph id="H8FDAF25DE4E343F79684612E26EEDA27"><enum>(A)</enum><text>maintenance of effective control against diversion of particular controlled substances into other than legitimate medical, scientific, and industrial channels;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H979CB4830DC14EA48444C541615865A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>compliance with applicable State and local law;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB8CCC6663F6F4C18992422F27F8CF572"><enum>(C)</enum><text>prior conviction record of applicant under Federal or State laws relating to the manufacture, distribution, or dispensing of substances described in subparagraph (A);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A4A76B3A8E84B509C20972813C4687F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>past experience in the distribution of controlled substances; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E266216CAB24F4180A1D81AFB59B684"><enum>(E)</enum><text>such other factors as may be relevant to and consistent with the public health and safety.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CA9915BC50149A788A7D89780380A64" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>If an applicant is registered to distribute a controlled substance in schedule I or II under subsection (b), the applicant shall not be required to apply for a separate registration under this subsection.</text>
							</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HC97664710C664DE08DAE1648DF6FD3B1"><enum>(m)</enum>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H3CB029420266478D970D60C904635A00"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Not later than 90 days after the date on which a substance is placed in schedule A, any practitioner who was engaged in research on the substance before the placement of the substance in schedule A and any manufacturer or distributor who was handling the substance before the placement of the substance in schedule A shall register with the Attorney General.</text>
							</paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H3457C87DB2C446FAB0FCE04E3E24B5F0" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum>
 <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H2378092A626642BFA59C682EC6B99FF1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Not later than 60 days after the date on which the Attorney General receives an application for registration to conduct research on a schedule A substance, the Attorney General shall—</text>
 <clause commented="no" id="H9C1D3D35112F423DADACACF183EE57F3" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>grant, or initiate proceedings under section 304(c) to deny, the application; or</text> </clause><clause commented="no" id="HE1C44D08C3604A29AD1B7E1C2E991C84" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>request supplemental information from the applicant.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H05CC727A7B50426BA8C78B011A431AD1" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which the Attorney General receives supplemental information requested under subparagraph (A)(ii) in connection with an application described in subparagraph (A), the Attorney General shall grant or deny the application.</text>
								</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD5AE19808146481A8741A3ACB041ACB6"><enum>(n)</enum>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HEB042002E1234D1CAC002F1216A5968C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall register a scientific investigator or a qualified research institution to conduct research with controlled substances in schedule A in accordance with this subsection. In evaluating applications for such registration, the Attorney General shall apply the criteria set forth in subsection (f) of this section that apply to practitioners seeking a registration to conduct research with a schedule I controlled substance, except that the applicant shall not be required to submit a research protocol.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H4DB5F58F7E104B38BA0F464BAA16E123" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the applicant is not currently registered under subsection (f) to conduct research with a schedule I controlled substance, the Attorney General shall refer the application to the Secretary, who shall determine whether the applicant will be engaged in bona fide research and is qualified to conduct such research.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF500132470814694A688AC41B9920597" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the applicant is currently registered under subsection (f) to conduct research with a schedule I controlled substance, the applicant will be considered qualified to conduct research with controlled substances in schedule A and the Attorney General shall modify the applicant's registration to include schedule A controlled substances in accordance with this paragraph. The applicant shall notify the Attorney General of his intent to conduct research with a controlled substance in schedule A. Upon receiving such notification, the Attorney General shall modify the practitioner’s existing registration to authorize research with schedule A controlled substances, unless the Attorney General determines that the registration modification would be inconsistent with the public interest based on the criteria of subsection (f).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8DC2F55E8D0F44FEBA541E2EC02522C0" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Registrations issued under this subsection to a qualified research institution will apply to all agents and employees of that institution acting within the scope of their professional practice.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H900600613882415FB2A660E89B78945A" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At least thirty days prior to conducting any research with a controlled substance in schedule A, the registrant shall provide the Attorney General with written notification of the following:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H1C96428665E1428AA1E1F032E3841706"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The name of and drug code for each substance.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H417AFA899B63410487AC6865D209151C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The name of each individual with access to each substance.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H869F032B1E64481E8A2128891BB1B714"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The amount of each substance.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF26380FFCD4F4F6D84B32BF14E63D122"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Other similar information the Attorney General may require.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H23392912101D46B2A8F10027F12D1F88" indent="up1"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The quantity of a schedule A controlled substance possessed by a person registered under this subsection shall be appropriate for the research being conducted, subject to the additional limitations set forth in this paragraph. To reduce the risk of diversion, the Attorney General may establish limitations on the quantity of schedule A controlled substances that may be manufactured or possessed for purposes of research under this subsection and shall publish such limitations on the website of the Drug Enforcement Administration. A person registered under this subsection may, based on legitimate research needs, apply to the Attorney General to manufacture or possess an amount greater than that so specified by the Attorney General. The Attorney General shall specify the manner in which such applications shall be submitted. The Attorney General shall act on an application filed under this subparagraph within 30 days of receipt of such application. If the Attorney General fails to act within 30 days, the registrant shall be allowed to manufacture and possess up to the amount requested. The Attorney General shall have the authority to reverse the increase for cause.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HFD22493C4A2741AEA4685314D69B3D6A" indent="up1"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall by regulation specify the manner in which applications for registration under this subsection shall be submitted.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H2D528D65035745C5BF556810BE004A5D" indent="up1"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Registrants authorized under this subsection may manufacture and possess schedule A controlled substances up to the approved amounts only for use in their own research setting or institution. Manufacturing for use in any other setting or institution shall require a manufacturer’s registration under section 303(a).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8CC7D52569B8410386F5B7B805BF590C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Controlled Substances Import and Export Act</header><text>Section 1008 of the Controlled Substances Import and Export Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/958">21 U.S.C. 958</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
					<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H71A2F891623C425DA01DE46F654AFA7C" style="OLC">
						<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H456724D1D57E498FB2D30FA75585CAEB"><enum>(j)</enum>
 <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H702601B616554287989C1BDF30AD6667"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall register an applicant to import or export a schedule A substance if—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H217E6A261DC646F18F126302727BB088" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the applicant demonstrates that the schedule A substances will be used for research, analytical, or industrial purposes approved by the Attorney General; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H39A44BADDAB2454FBA7E2EE93DED91F8" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Attorney General determines that such registration is consistent with the public interest and with the United States obligations under international treaties, conventions, or protocols in effect on the date of enactment of this subsection.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H43509505AD294BEFB6020E7E909B4A55" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining the public interest under paragraph (1)(B), the Attorney General shall consider the factors described in subparagraphs (A) through (F) of section 303(k)(2).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCDA63339FD3C41A6A778E2D06F2A0181" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>If an applicant is registered to import or export a controlled substance in schedule I or II under subsection (a), the applicant shall not be required to apply for a separate registration under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H13DB7D186AD147A580EFD429DEB35EBE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Additional conforming amendments</header>
 <paragraph commented="no" id="HD55EB9427F95447B8BE7F6B788A1BC8C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Controlled Substances Act</header><text>The Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/801">21 U.S.C. 801</external-xref> et seq.) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H6BA803C48B024B109584AECFD926C286"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 303(c) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/823">21 U.S.C. 823(c)</external-xref>)—</text>
 <clause id="H5F955E96F5594ED68FE3B988078487D0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>subsections (a) and (b)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (a), (b), (k), or (l)</quote>; and</text> </clause><clause id="HB3CEA93895984610BB81C498CC393423"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70EEBE368687403B955C4A90F2010F50"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 306 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/826">21 U.S.C. 826</external-xref>)—</text> <clause id="H3A9487B53F634B8DA8C231E927E93E13"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (a), in the first sentence, by striking <quote>schedules I and II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedules I, II, and A</quote>;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HFAECD243EFCB4B90A426E4093C3663FF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (b), in the second sentence, by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>;</text> </clause><clause id="HD3317B18BCFC4448B847ED3CC05385E5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subsection (c), in the first sentence, by striking <quote>schedules I and II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedules I, II, and A</quote>;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H1071F24C39694DF4A38CB16902AFD0F0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subsection (d), in the first sentence, by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>;</text> </clause><clause id="H3FF22D8E51E640AB84EB000404E3B6FE"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in subsection (e), in the first sentence, by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF349354B92CE4C5BA416ED8BED00DCB1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>in subsection (f), in the first sentence, by striking <quote>schedules I and II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedules I, II, and A</quote>;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99191AE992DB4C9997C99F8EF89E169F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in section 308(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/828">21 U.S.C. 828(a)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD325ED250C984C41A8F2C8BE34845F31"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in section 402(b) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/842">21 U.S.C. 842(b)</external-xref>), in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5CF403B930C54F4DB0641928DDCF8C44"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in section 403(a)(1) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/843">21 U.S.C. 843(a)(1)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H398D288B72F943EBBF142002DCEE817F"><enum>(F)</enum><text>in section 511(f) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/881">21 U.S.C. 881(f)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H3D8482AAD96A4408A519D89EBE036A70"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Controlled Substances Import Export Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Controlled Substances Import and Export Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/951">21 U.S.C. 951</external-xref> et seq.) is amended—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H626FF67F93C34EA5A99844B0200E9C17"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 1002(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/952">21 U.S.C. 952(a)</external-xref>)—</text> <clause id="H6A11EC4F107B426F8549B719F3AD28A1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H81D90BA775D24E2A92066F17FE820BCD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC5DD8803CAE433E8F08C62AACE72BED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 1003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/953">21 U.S.C. 953</external-xref>)—</text>
 <clause id="H587F39B7722A4A67A6C43276E20BE8BF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (c), in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>; and</text> </clause><clause id="H9D60BC06BD9941A4AE3F17DAC583F925"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (d), by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9EFF7C7F05C24F1C8D151142B833B5B8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in section 1004(1) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/954">21 U.S.C. 954(1)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>schedule I</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I or A</quote>;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75DA5129C5174B5E873883C6CD41F886"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in section 1005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/955">21 U.S.C. 955</external-xref>), by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFBED73A53B7A4182BEDA0C7662C11AD6"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 1009(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/959">21 U.S.C. 959(a)</external-xref>), by striking <quote>schedule I or II</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I, II, or A</quote>.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1F1C738477B041F79173AC16703852D3"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Controlled substance analogues</header><text>Section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HB0A6B4EFA4CA406D86E48F539F0E6680"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking <quote>or V</quote> and inserting <quote>V, or A</quote>;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H298596D63061429D9F42DA6534A7A68A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (14)—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HE44C6659FC9C4FA59D41A3F0DCF2795E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>schedule I(c) and</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I(c), schedule A, and</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H888499D219D24115BDFD08839B325E10"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>schedule I(c),</quote> and inserting <quote>schedule I(c) and schedule A,</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0D2021011AE485AA60FFB7BF7814639"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (32)(A), by striking <quote>(32)(A)</quote> and all that follows through clause (iii) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H739DBB12DDC949439943F44191C7BBEC" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H4BA3486399D14806BB306F6A311DFFBC" indent="up1"><enum>(32)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HDC76ACF7F0B941F697406A49B7257E84"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (C), the term <term>controlled substance analogue</term> means a substance whose chemical structure is substantially similar to the chemical structure of a controlled substance in schedule I or II—</text>
 <clause id="H81F37BF8570940A59767BB781784909A" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>which has a stimulant, depressant, or hallucinogenic effect on the central nervous system that is substantially similar to or greater than the stimulant, depressant, or hallucinogenic effect on the central nervous system of a controlled substance in schedule I or II; or</text>
 </clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF1F7B308B83C4EC38053CBBBEFFEF502" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with respect to a particular person, which such person represents or intends to have a stimulant, depressant, or hallucinogenic effect on the central nervous system that is substantially similar to or greater than the stimulant, depressant, or hallucinogenic effect on the central nervous system of a controlled substance in schedule I or II.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HC32799CF28AE4370AC6AA92D6FE1A67F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Amendment to the sentencing guidelines</header><text>Section 2D1.1 of the Federal Sentencing Guidelines is amended, in Application Note 6 (Analogues and Controlled Substances Not Referenced in this Guideline) of the Commentary, by striking <quote>In determining the most closely related controlled substance, the court shall, to the extent practicable, consider the following:</quote> and inserting the following:</text>
				<quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H525AFE862E74405D98E72DC88FDC1226" style="OLC">
 <text>In determining the most closely related controlled substance and the applicable guideline or drug equivalence, the court shall—</text><subparagraph id="HE133130F50D44697887BEC727C63311C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>if Attorney General has provided guidance on the appropriate sentencing equivalency or ratio to a controlled substance that is referenced in the guidelines through publication in the Federal Register (whether such guidance is included in or separate from any notice of proposed temporary or permanent scheduling of such substance under section 201 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/811">21 U.S.C. 811</external-xref>)), apply any such sentencing equivalency or ratio; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59337DAED43E4BECB3E6D604DB11BA7C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the absence of guidance with respect to a substance or group of substances as described in paragraph (A), use equivalencies for the following structural classes of substances as if they were included on the Drug Equivalency Tables:</text>
						<table align-to-level="section" blank-lines-before="1" colsep="1" frame="topbot" line-rules="hor-ver" rowsep="0" rule-weights="4.4.4.0.0.0" table-template-name="Generic: 2 text, even cols" table-type=""><tgroup cols="2" grid-typeface="1.1" rowsep="0" thead-tbody-ldg-size="10.10.12"><colspec coldef="txt" colname="column1" colwidth="148pts" min-data-value="130" rowsep="0"></colspec><colspec coldef="txt-no-ldr" colname="column2" colwidth="177pts" min-data-value="155" rowsep="0"></colspec><thead><row><entry align="center" colname="column1" morerows="0" namest="column1" rowsep="1">Drug Class</entry><entry align="center" colname="column2" morerows="0" namest="column2" rowsep="1">Marihuana Equivalency of 1 gm<linebreak></linebreak> of subject substance</entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" leader-modify="force-ldr" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">Synthetic Opioids</entry><entry align="left" colname="column2" leader-modify="clr-ldr" rowsep="0">1 gm = 10 kg</entry></row><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" leader-modify="force-ldr" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">Synthetic Cannabinoids</entry><entry align="left" colname="column2" leader-modify="clr-ldr" rowsep="0">1 gm = 167 gm</entry></row><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" leader-modify="force-ldr" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">Synthetic Cathinones</entry><entry align="left" colname="column2" leader-modify="clr-ldr" rowsep="0">1 gm = 380 gm</entry></row><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" leader-modify="force-ldr" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">Tryptamine</entry><entry align="left" colname="column2" leader-modify="clr-ldr" rowsep="0">1 gm = 80 gm</entry></row><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" leader-modify="force-ldr" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">Phenethylamines</entry><entry align="left" colname="column2" leader-modify="clr-ldr" rowsep="0">1 gm = 2.5 kg</entry></row><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" leader-modify="force-ldr" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">Piperazines</entry><entry align="left" colname="column2" leader-modify="clr-ldr" rowsep="0">1 gm = 2 kg</entry></row><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" leader-modify="force-ldr" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">Benzofurans</entry><entry align="left" colname="column2" leader-modify="clr-ldr" rowsep="0">1 gm = 500 gm</entry></row><row><entry colname="column1" leader-modify="clr-ldr" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-clr" stub-hierarchy="1">Arylcyclohexylamines <linebreak></linebreak> (PCP-like substances)</entry><entry align="left" colname="column2" leader-modify="clr-ldr" rowsep="0"><linebreak></linebreak>1 gm = 1 kg</entry></row><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" leader-modify="force-ldr" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">Methylphenidate analogs</entry><entry align="left" colname="column2" leader-modify="clr-ldr" rowsep="0">1 gm = 100 gm</entry></row><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" leader-modify="force-ldr" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">Benzodiazepines</entry><entry align="left" colname="column2" leader-modify="clr-ldr" rowsep="0">1 <quote>unit</quote> (as defined in Note (F) to the Drug Quantity Table in 2D1.1) = 0.0625 gm</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>
					</subparagraph><quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="paragraph">In the case of a substance for which paragraphs (A) and (B) above are not applicable, the court
			 shall determine an equivalency or ratio by considering the following
			 factors, to the extent practicable:</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </subsection><subsection id="HB1328CC8D4974049AF91E90F0DBD5EDF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section, or the amendments made by this section, may be construed to limit—</text> <paragraph id="H8E15D4A04B52492C91F89A93DFDEF805"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the prosecution of offenses involving controlled substance analogues under the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/801">21 U.S.C. 801</external-xref> et seq.); or</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9353CB599BDB4EAF9CC09BAEF665F230"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the authority of the Attorney General to temporarily or permanently schedule, reschedule, or decontrol controlled substances under provisions of section 201 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/811">21 U.S.C. 811</external-xref>) that are in effect on the day before the date of enactment of this Act.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9239303F06E2454980183C41CD45EA53"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Study by Comptroller General</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall complete a study and submit a report to the Committees on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and of the Senate regarding the costs associated with the amendments made by subsection (c), including—</text>
 <paragraph id="H5C6E1C39B54F455A8C6F7FAF73CABE7B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the annual amounts expended by Federal agencies in carrying out the amendments;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H98A7CEB34C8C4FCB92451D423E333497"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the costs associated with arrests, trials, convictions, imprisonment, or imposition of other sanctions in accordance with the amendments; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HDD66346AAD174EE9B27D23B26842DB1A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the impact (including the fiscal impact) of the amendments on existing correctional facilities and the likelihood that those amendments will create a need for additional capacity for housing prisoners.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


