<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0AA85AAE661248BD869B2A877DFE5AB7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5035 IH: Hezbollah Kingpin Designation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5035</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180215">February 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001305">Mr. Budd</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="Z000017">Mr. Zeldin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the President to determine whether Hezbollah should be designated as a significant foreign narcotics trafficker or a transnational criminal organization, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6A09361F2CB24DD5A8B3E882D168AE10" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3B1ED0DE0BB9490EA5DCEFD64BFDFFB0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hezbollah Kingpin Designation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4F3325DE55B14BEC8753D34B8A5EEF34"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H668EF535C06B4F07B38C3A6088768202"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Since 2010, Lebanese-based Hezbollah has been linked with South American drug trafficking organizations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H69170460B117464EAB94E834324A1BC9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Drug Enforcement Administration’s <quote>Project Cassandra</quote> has identified Hezbollah as a major supplier of cocaine into the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDFF549C1D47F44F9BDE6329B22E23C23"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On January 11, 2018, Attorney General Jeff Sessions announced the creation of the Hezbollah Financing and Narcoterrorism Team to investigate individuals and networks providing support to Hezbollah’s narcoterrorist activities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H92A86E76C7FA407687A33D6A05FFD6AE"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Michael Braun testified before the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives, on June 8, 2016, that <quote>hundreds of tons of cocaine, over [a] 15-year period and move massive amounts of currency, hundreds of, millions, perhaps billions of dollars in currency around the world in the most sophisticated money laundering scheme that we have ever witnessed</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDFBC560922A644EEA4186711E452A70C"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2011, the Drug Enforcement Administration indicted Ayman Saied Joumaa, a Lebanese-Colombian dual national, for using a global network of companies operating out of Latin America, West Africa, and Lebanon to launder as much as $200,000,000 a month in drug proceeds for Mexican and Colombian cartels.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD0D54125E47848D7A30C80DB38660013"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The House of Representatives passed H.R. 3329, the Hezbollah International Financing Prevention Act, on October 25, 2017, to provide additional resources to enforcement agencies to counter Hezbollah’s other criminal enterprises including money laundering.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H8B1E4309A7E247CBB9607AFC22263170"><enum>3.</enum><header>Designations required</header> 
<subsection id="H7A8021E00EC540C187832D79485AC920" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Kingpin designation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall, in accordance with the requirements for additional determinations under section 804(h)(1) of the Intelligence Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/1903">21 U.S.C. 1903(h)(1)</external-xref>), determine whether Hezbollah is a <quote>significant foreign narcotics trafficker</quote>, as such term is defined for purposes of such section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H7CAEBEAB9005494C9B073DBED9BB8307"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transnational criminal organization designation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall submit to Congress a determination whether to designate Hezbollah as a <quote>transnational criminal organization</quote>, as such term is defined for purposes of the list of specially designated nationals and blocked persons maintained by the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury.</text> </subsection> </section> 
<section id="H3C50D81E296B4555BD1CB69FA29A5B23" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Asset report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury shall issue a report to the Committees on Financial Services and Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committees on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs and Foreign Relations of the Senate containing an estimate of the total assets under direct or indirect control by Hezbollah-linked leaders of political parties or movements who are located in the United States.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

