<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H63F001819D8048AABBC42ACFB0FC245A" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5032 IH: Toll Credit Marketplace Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-02-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5032</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180215">February 15, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000563">Mr. Lipinski</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a pilot toll credit marketplace program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H153B3D519DD54CFB93AE1E417BC7A934" style="OLC">
 <section id="HCBF6F09CFB774EB8AA1060834837F31E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Toll Credit Marketplace Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H3BB4DDBD725245B98AA8E581A1B12462" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Toll credit marketplace pilot program</header> <subsection id="HD7B671F0A05B4E9D99F641104E18AD33"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
 <paragraph id="H5159D344C6CF4ED68FDB805805326E79"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Pilot program</header><text>The term <term>pilot program</term> means the toll credit marketplace pilot program established under subsection (b).</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H5E34FF1613E94A97B3A2090B7BE7FAB7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Transportation.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H08F26F1E255B42F48D4F52BACA1EBAE7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of title 23, United States Code.</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HFBB320D2B17F4A008810698137F6696B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Toll credit</header><text>The term <term>toll credit</term> means the credit that can be used toward the non-Federal share requirement under section 120(i) of title 23, United States Code.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H250E61014AAE4FC18D7E2F729858D18D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Toll credit marketplace</header><text>The term <term>toll credit marketplace</term> means a market in which toll credits can be purchased and sold by States participating in the pilot program.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF442E5F98CA84DEBB07B2F31B51EE94B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish and implement a pilot program to develop a toll credit marketplace for States to buy and sell toll credits.</text>
 </subsection><subsection id="H37A03D2E465C41EB95834BDC19031282"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of the pilot program are—</text> <paragraph id="HDECF2D73C8FC40FD83B8D3A33F65AA49"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to identify whether a monetary value can be assigned to toll credits;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1A20573B61C54369A6E3E4D76D0A81AC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to identify the discounted rate of toll credits for cash;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H96610DA754174009BCB4331A609F610B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to determine if the purchase of toll credits by States provides the purchasing State budget flexibility to deal with funding issues, including off-system needs, transit systems with high operating costs, or cash flow issues; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA2A8C7DA26394D07902EA94BBE1FEC84"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to test the feasibility of expanding the toll credit market to allow all States to participate on a permanent basis.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5B93D212E7AE419D9256F4D3DACB9484"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Administration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the pilot program, the Secretary—</text> <paragraph id="H7BC68B87334345D68DD3532FE6D2C2E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall establish procedures for a toll credit marketplace;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H18E7C0303C324A4489C23B23E6A99783"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall establish an online platform that allows participating States to offer and bid on toll credit purchases;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9C51B21402284F5E9D5BA206929C14B2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, shall provide notice to States that the Federal Highway Administration is requesting participants for the pilot program;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD89BF1FB335E41C1AD304F0D7E96E3E4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>shall allow to participate in the pilot program—</text> <subparagraph id="H777D3E73D2A64BD4BF9704B415317514"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State that maintains a toll credit balance accumulated before the date of enactment of this Act;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6ED781310BF240E9AEDC4408723CFF09"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State that does not maintain infrastructure for the collection of toll credits; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13C72BFC93AA470AB319F1111C8F9DB2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a State that has not accumulated a toll credit balance; and</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H71D111D3D21449C39EFB1D92C65F7795"><enum>(5)</enum><text>shall not allow a State to purchase or sell toll credits in an amount that is less than 10 percent of the value of the toll credit value if applied as a non-Federal share requirement under section 120(i)(1) of title 23, United States Code.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3B76CD00F27D414B9AD858D62A0B2F66"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header>
 <paragraph id="H61A2BCFE7B9045B98F80779D6CD04147"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after notice of the pilot program is provided to the States under subsection (d)(3), the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report on the progress of the toll credit marketplace.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H5B819D713696466195CC4433D42A78B3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State report</header><text>Not later than 30 days after a purchase or sale in the toll credit marketplace under the pilot program—</text>
 <subparagraph id="HC4CA2F9898CC4AE59C8B251E96B9F817"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State selling toll credits shall provide to the Secretary information on the transaction, including—</text>
 <clause id="H0946F2DF3B5A4CF8A76EEA2BF9C3FB23"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the amount of cash received;</text> </clause><clause id="HD71A45750ABA46DE9ACDD6FFDFE4FC98"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the value of toll credits sold;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H33707E22DB2840CFB86DEBADDD30E310"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the intended use of the cash; and</text> </clause><clause id="H7BC2C3E3DD9147DEA0CC1CEA2DC78D05"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the remaining toll credit balance of the State; and</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BA988AEBCB94462A02B6C88917322FF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State purchasing toll credits shall provide to the Secretary information on—</text> <clause id="H8A9B6686216F4F9E8B37F6A46369D849"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the value of toll credits purchased;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HFB50B02ADF054049A54083DE524E0A8D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the anticipated use of the toll credits; and</text> </clause><clause id="H8947F1E7F9354AC5AE1CEB79709907EA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>plans for maintenance of effort for spending on Federal-aid highway projects.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3CBDB4FF91446619354CCE19F1F2405"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after notice of the pilot program is provided to the States under subsection (d)(3) and each year thereafter that the pilot program is in effect, the Secretary shall—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H64AD1BC124DF4D118B5A3940CE25642A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report that—</text>
 <clause id="HDB68FAD0807A471DB48643BD0C46F7DD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>evaluates whether a toll credit marketplace is viable;</text> </clause><clause id="HCA059DC6E5874C7C926AF020B4C483E6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>describes the buying and selling activities of the toll credit marketplace;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H7C94CD23CF2F4F01867D1B66436576E2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>determines the monetary value of toll credits;</text> </clause><clause id="HCCDBEAE1EEEE4249A35C845D40AC5F32"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evaluates whether the pilot program could be expanded to more States or all States; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H72559F9B77D8471AB9FAF1D7015DC187"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides updated information on the toll credit balance accumulated by each State; and</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H144F96BFF4FD48CA974B1A2C5DD1CBDB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>make the report under subparagraph (A) publicly available on the website of the Secretary.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H00776B05214648F9A93E4776E658DD0E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (i)(2), a State participating in the toll credit marketplace shall be subject to section 120(i)(2) of title 23, United States Code.</text>
			</subsection><subsection id="H4A5D36E125E54688A05F848557235469"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Use of funds received for the sale</header>
 <paragraph id="HF0BA4BF117EC41E4971825B8967320C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State that receives funds from the sale of a toll credit may use the funds only for a project eligible for assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/23/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of title 23, United States Code, or <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HE64751437E2A41F2B4488DED2686D1BB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>Before expending any funds received in exchange for a toll credit, the State shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HFA67C1C6A93F419FB4F906E630B7B25D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide to the Secretary a certification that the funds will be used as described in paragraph (1); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H509A413E57C14D9BA810C76321FBBF88"><enum>(B)</enum><text>receive approval from the Secretary under paragraph (3).</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4CF6840842EB4ADE9E552D779D395149"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Approval</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the receipt of a certification under paragraph (2), the Secretary shall send a notice of decision to the State that—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H107867E0FBF549DFAF4D53DE41327B47"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">approves the certification; or</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1AB165896173445AAA96096801A0CCC8"><enum>(B)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HCABDC6188C534A19AF7156BCEDCF86FA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>disapproves the certification; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="HF0257A17C38845D5A4BA6613A209B4B0" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes an explanation of the grounds for disapproval and recommendations for addressing the deficiencies.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HAE7FEC346D5249988828E40D6F0EFDEF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Appeal</header><text>If the Secretary disapproves the certification under paragraph (3)(B)—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HBDED88F322BB481DACDE447F6F1772E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than 30 days after a State receives a notice of decision disapproving the certification, the State may ask the Secretary to reconsider the decision; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0050E1D6C98146F2B8D23C014E86F62F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than 60 days after the Secretary receives a request to reconsider under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall review the request and make a determination.</text>
					</subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8B50B6FA29144070BD50DDA23D30DF8B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Metropolitan planning organization and local government toll credit allocation</header>
 <paragraph id="HF843D40837B641F89CFB4C68DF3275D5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Purchase of toll credits</header><text>On request of a metropolitan planning organization or local government in the State, and with a timely payment of the amount of the toll credits, a State may purchase toll credits under this section on behalf of the metropolitan planning organization or local government.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HBFB8D1DFB53E40E482CA494DDD0A27B6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Allocation of toll credits</header><text>On approval of the relevant metropolitan planning organization or local government, a State may allocate toll credits purchased by the State for use by the metropolitan planning organization or local government.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3C0901AC53AF44ADA535ED202B6D527E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Limitation on use of Federal funds for the purchase of toll credits</header>
 <paragraph id="H4C2E44AAC9CC404597810DA63C12A439"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Limitation on Federal funds</header><text>A State, metropolitan planning organization, or local government may not use Federal funds to purchase toll credits on the toll credit marketplace.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HC725354F76FA446FB7862EF5741CC6E9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of toll credits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State may use toll credits purchased under this section to meet not more than 10 percent of the non-Federal share requirement for any funds made available to carry out <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/23/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of title 23, United States Code, or <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code, for each fiscal year.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2CC241BEA59D45F5B6D9A6B8B4C30C00"><enum>(j)</enum><header>GAO report</header><text>After the end of the first year during which the toll credit marketplace is in operation, the Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text>
 <paragraph id="H5D97E4D51E7E4CEE98D415092D9A3AAF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct a study on the performance of the toll credit marketplace; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H6A350FD7CE624289A0A9F8C19582D22F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to Congress a report that includes—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H8AF5495DDCB14BCA88BE023EC8EB0020"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a determination as to whether the pilot program is successful; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A4A34A6A8924DEF89D6DC5A9030A6BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any recommendations on how to improve the pilot program.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4DFCFE058F5E47F2BC7A99F7417CDFAD"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The pilot program shall terminate on September 30, 2020.</text> </subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

