<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H0E12958286E9414AA15DAF6A77A91C78" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4829 IH: Artificial Intelligence Job Opportunities and Background Summary Act of 2018</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-01-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4829</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180118">January 18, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001201">Mr. Mitchell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001105">Mrs. Comstock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001069">Mr. Courtney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To promote a 21st century artificial intelligence workforce.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="HDB00ADC2B9CA4A4A824FE98DBD7B9FB8" style="OLC">
 <section id="H286B5FB4EA28491CAB05E6771E643EFA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Artificial Intelligence Job Opportunities and Background Summary Act of 2018</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>AI JOBS Act of 2018</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HE95AB9FB311540C08DE1A15075FE9A66"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that technology can improve the lives of individuals, but can also disrupt jobs, and for this reason, innovation should be encouraged while training and retraining American workers for our 21st century economy.</text>
		</section><section id="H932CEBAA8BB746AA9D0D07284EB57E6C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report on artificial intelligence</header>
 <subsection id="H5612F327A5FE4AD78D189920995E99C4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor, in collaboration with the individuals and entities described in subsection (b), shall prepare and submit to the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, a report on artificial intelligence and its impact on the workforce, which shall include the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H913EA297DEFC43E3A40730C0C6C5DE11"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Outline the specific data, and the availability of such data, necessary to properly analyze the impact and growth of artificial intelligence.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HD4F344C7C3864CE7B103B7C3BEA480C2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Identification of industries that are projected to have the most growth in artificial intelligence use, and whether the technology will result in the enhancement of workers’ capabilities or their replacement.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HEA2862C58F6F473091EA9DA6CB1120E9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Analysis of the expertise and education (including computer science literacy) needed to develop, operate, or work alongside artificial intelligence over the next two decades, as compared to the levels of such expertise and education among the workforce as of the date of enactment of this Act.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9226C6245B30491ABBBA3DCC489AB130"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Analysis of which demographics (including ethnic, gender, economic, age, and regional) may experience expanded career opportunities, and which such demographics may be vulnerable to career displacement, due to artificial intelligence.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H8A2F010241A1404AA6E74D3B5746BC2E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Any recommendations to alleviate workforce displacement, prepare future workforce members for the artificial-intelligence economy, and any other relevant observations or recommendations within the field of artificial intelligence.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4686D60B24324A338EADC10097768CC1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In preparing the report under subsection (a), the Secretary of Labor shall collaborate, through a series of public meetings, roundtables or other methods, with—</text>
 <paragraph id="H9B16D07D24404D1CB4C5CAF500473B7E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>local educational agencies, institutions of higher education (including community colleges), workforce-training organizations, and National Laboratories;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HA44135EC894144EB917BE492E5F177CC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a broad range of industrial stakeholders in the technology and manufacturing sectors, including companies (large and small), think tanks, and industry organizations; and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H0DCD6F2FCD474059AFE1C47B94730830"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of Commerce, the Director of the Bureau of the Census, and the heads of any other Federal agency the Secretary of Labor determines appropriate.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H088968EDB7AA4B73A3A53898E956C294"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H32C9154651904F30B2A9CD0FE28B27AC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence</term> means systems that—</text>
 <subparagraph commented="no" id="HE4344B1C2322464893669F3200C57080"><enum>(A)</enum><text>think like humans (including cognitive architectures and neural networks);</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB13964EF947E404484C53531C79965F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>act like humans (such as passing the Turing test using natural language processing, knowledge representation, automated reasoning, and learning);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H20D63CF81272480786A6FCCBD69C32A6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>think rationally (such as logic solvers, inference, and optimization);</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HFF1D328A530E4054998E2D19220F14F5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>act rationally (such as intelligent software agents and embodied robots that achieve goals via perception, planning, reasoning, learning, communicating, decision-making, and acting); or</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HECC50F5C3DD24DBB8D4C5D3F7CE08E95"><enum>(E)</enum><text>automate or replicate intelligent behavior.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CCB43934B44417AA7D9DC3C3089BD2B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Community college</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>community college</term> has the meaning given the term <term>junior or community college</term> in section 312(f) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1058">20 U.S.C. 1058(f)</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H9D289835206D43BC895166B7965C28D8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H7EA4FA2D05EF4CEF83545B3C01EA01BE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Local educational agency</header><text>The term <term>local educational agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


