<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H91155D1AA6EC4B3CACF7B2837460A500" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5256 IH: To direct the Attorney General to acquire data, for each calendar year, about sexual offenses, including rape, that occur aboard any mode of transportation over which the Federal Government exercises jurisdiction.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5256</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180313">March 13, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001087">Mr. Crawford</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Attorney General to acquire data, for each calendar year, about sexual offenses,
			 including rape, that occur aboard any mode of transportation over which
			 the Federal Government exercises jurisdiction.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H3EA318142EE242BA9A706C2E40263005" style="OLC">
		<section id="HC4CBCD1514994D8EAD55830E9C9F3D79" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Statistics relating to sexual offenses that occur aboard any mode of transportation over which the
 Federal Government exercises jurisdiction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Under the authority of section 534 of title 28, United States Code, the Attorney General shall acquire data, for each calendar year, about sexual offenses, including rape, that occur aboard any mode of transportation over which the Federal Government exercises jurisdiction (including aircraft, any vessel of the United States or which travels in interstate or foreign commerce or within the admiralty and maritime jurisdiction of the United States, any vehicle used or designed for flight or navigation in space, and any vehicle which travels via any facility of interstate or foreign commerce), disaggregated by—</text>
 <paragraph id="H7E88D09C29C5481F84576B5E7046323F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the mode of transportation aboard which the offense was committed; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HBADBE8FB70CC44C19AFD588B50F57992"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the location of the commission of the offense.</text>
			</paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


