<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="H098B63EEEF2140FDA943F0120B8255B8" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5718 IH: Perioperative Reduction of Opioids Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5718</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180509">May 9, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001195">Mr. Smith of Missouri</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="H001038">Mr. Higgins of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such
			 provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for a technical expert panel to provide recommendations on reducing opioid use in the
			 surgical setting and on best practices for pain management, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H736AC4C4638B4985B78DE2CCB0E6B593" style="OLC">
 <section id="H10E46125FBB44AFCA54DE3C4A496D16A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Perioperative Reduction of Opioids Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PRO Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HCC68265FA5264938A397A84C5782F432" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Technical expert panel on reducing surgical setting opioid use; data collection on perioperative opioid use</header> <subsection id="H99922D9D249841408774B8DCC747855F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Technical expert panel on reducing surgical setting opioid use</header> <paragraph id="HBFADBB6E20B149649D91B6E96478F774"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall convene a technical expert panel, including medical and surgical specialty societies, to provide recommendations on reducing opioid use in the inpatient and outpatient surgical settings and on best practices for pain management, including with respect to the following:</text>
 <subparagraph id="H50AC29F8C7E244DEAE13911C8C1D9691"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Approaches that limit patient exposure to opioids during the perioperative period, including pre-surgical and post-surgical injections.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H060097D9C6804FB89EE824C81AABA205"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Shared decisionmaking with patients and families on pain management, including recommendations for the development of an evaluation and management code for purposes of payment under the Medicare program under title XVIII of the Social Security Act that would account for time spent on shared decisionmaking.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32135E30A1B04AD1A1096BE97F9062D5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Education on the safe use, storage, and disposal of opioids.</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9402C01DA0E24DEEA69694F5C0495B1E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Prevention of opioid misuse and abuse after discharge.</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3DB868ABF2F94EF1B8AD8B2A8146956C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Development of a clinical algorithm to treat opiate tolerant patients and reduce reliance on opiates for acute pain during the perioperative period.</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD21B4152D274BE4BB36D079647FF1B6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress and make public a report containing the recommendations developed under paragraph (1) and recommendations for broader implementation of pain management protocols that limit the use of opioids in the perioperative setting and upon discharge from such setting.</text>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H12D9462F61464BE49378CA75E5ED9419"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Data collection on perioperative opioid use</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit to Congress a report that contains the following:</text>
 <paragraph id="H747ECFB01FFA4B3FA79A74F57FB61CB1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The diagnosis-related group codes identified by the Secretary as having the highest volume of surgeries.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H04245D18739C4449814054FF42633E73"><enum>(2)</enum><text>With respect to each of such diagnosis-related group codes so identified, a determination by the Secretary of the data that is both available and reported on opioid use following such surgeries, such as with respect to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H56148B77BECD40ADA9930EC152EEF6E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">surgical volumes, practices, and opioid prescribing patterns;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1697A8BBFBE47AEAC498B44BC943F4D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>opioid consumption, including—</text>
 <clause id="H2274ACB64BB3458A98BF3B2F6001E5BC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>perioperative days of therapy;</text> </clause><clause id="H0F4E6551CAB04EAB9D6400BA58D16678"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>average daily dose at hospital, including high dosage greater than 90 milligram morphine equivalent;</text>
 </clause><clause id="HCFC778A9807949F3B8C1D4F9D6DA20C9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>post-discharge prescriptions and other combination drugs that are used before intervention and after intervention;</text>
 </clause><clause id="H8C61F1E98EC2441883E1F492956F9345"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>quantity and duration of opioid prescription at discharge; and</text> </clause><clause id="H699039A2B935441AB391DD95DAED681B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>quantity consumed and number of refills;</text>
 </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF6415485B6FB452AB2178DB825BFB362"><enum>(C)</enum><text>regional anesthesia and analgesia practices, including pre-surgical and post-surgical injections;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H737F6F63A36D46F789F089A136C5B0F2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>naloxone reversal;</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E6A48E6E5B5424A930C6FA087C7DFE7"><enum>(E)</enum><text>post-operative respiratory failure;</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H501051F1DFDD4FF4B80450CB65D39441"><enum>(F)</enum><text>information about storage and disposal; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70E57C827A9A431EAE850B8A8C3AA2D6"><enum>(G)</enum><text>such other information as the Secretary may specify.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6680593AF23E4F66A55FCBC83DFC97A9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations for improving data collection on perioperative opioid use, including an analysis to identify barriers to collecting, reporting, and analyzing the data described in paragraph (2), including barriers related to technological availability.</text>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


