<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB9FD37AD656F40208355510B1DC4AEFB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5508 IH: End the Cyprus Arms Embargo Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5508</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180413">April 13, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001084">Mr. Cicilline</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001111">Mr. Crist</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000610">Mr. Deutch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000087">Mrs. Carolyn B. Maloney of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000034">Mr. Pallone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000580">Mr. Roskam</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000435">Ms. Ros-Lehtinen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To repeal the prohibition on transfer of articles on the United States Munitions List to the Republic of Cyprus.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HB77EF27BC8C24A77B2023ED1B84B8C2F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF2640F7E10E8427CBD3C723420072FAF" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>End the Cyprus Arms Embargo Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H125C124D076144EEA0443A044476BBE1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD45873B32FD74E16BF82617B5B547479"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Republic of Cyprus is a vital strategic partner to the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H522B2972032F4811BBCF02FA75EF29BD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Republic of Cyprus is a critical member of the Global Coalition to Counter the Islamic State in Iraq and the Levant.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5798F25EFEAA43E98B731D6FAEDBACF5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The United States cooperates closely with the Republic of Cyprus through information sharing agreements.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H749AB0D7469241F8808BD79138A8B29A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>High-level United States officials have assisted the Republic of Cyprus with crafting that nation’s national security strategy.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD9033B6FC11A4A81A7EBEAAFD7EBFB84"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The United States provides training to Cypriot officials in areas such as cybersecurity, counterterrorism, and explosive ordinance disposal and stockpile management.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4AE007CD7538463BB5456DF44D453C48"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Republic of Cyprus is a valued member of the Proliferation Security Initiative to combat the trafficking of weapons of mass destruction.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9C65A7B6332B4271A5972A234D764EF0"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The Republic of Cyprus continues to work closely with the United Nations and regional partners in Europe to combat terrorism through law enforcement, counter violent extremism programs, and through financial mechanisms.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E6E5E296F5242E7A21B1AAA0E731335"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The United States and the Republic of Cyprus maintain strong bilateral economic relations, particularly in sectors such as energy, financial services, and logistics.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDEA7B593742440DDB0952B260314F437"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The energy exploration in the Republic of Cyprus’s Exclusive Economic Zone and territorial waters includes the participation of United States companies and furthers United States interests by providing a potential alternative to Russian gas for United States allies and partners. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4D6BACEE62F74D72A29F023F38DF2D7E"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Energy exploration in the Eastern Mediterranean must be safeguarded against threats posed by terrorist and extremist groups such as Hezbollah and others. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE540A38E5FBB4BD78D2E00FD156284BD"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Despite robust economic and security relations with the United States, the Republic of Cyprus has been subject to a United States embargo prohibiting the export of defense articles and services since 1987.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0BD6E9421D1949009CDE1AE9640C7195"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The 1987 arms embargo was designed to restrict United States arms sales and transfer to both the Republic of Cyprus and the occupied part of Cyprus to avoid hindering reunification efforts. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H863830F3298943DAA4D3647B8B7B7DD1"><enum>(13)</enum><text>At least 30,000 Turkish troops are stationed in the occupied part of Cyprus with weapons procured from the United States through mainland Turkey.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4B61A1D0A95D4E00B05B381CA04237E0"><enum>(14)</enum><text>The inability of the United States to provide defense articles and services to the Republic of Cyprus has forced Cyprus to obtain these items from countries which pose challenges to United States interests around the world.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFEFB8FED0F9C4F4FB219333DC0D55CE2"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The security of partners in the Eastern Mediterranean region is critical to the security of the United States and Europe.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HD24279FACFF64FA2BEAFD93DFC2B9C27"><enum>3.</enum><header>Repeal of prohibition on transfer of articles on the United States Munitions List to the Republic of Cyprus</header> <subsection id="HCF70CB9F2C614F0FB36C3980C5347CA4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 620C of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2373">22 U.S.C. 2373</external-xref>) is amended by striking subsection (e).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7852372887D7426B82BB5E7F7671C24A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Other provisions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The following provisions shall have no force or effect:</text> <paragraph id="H1CFC9DF76B564D04A9B4B42A18C81AFE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Paragraph (r) of section 126.1 of title 22, Code of Federal Regulations (relating to prohibited exports, imports, and sales to or from Cyprus).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3467C1203A42401B81975767EB407375"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Public Notice 1738 of December 18, 1992 (57 Fed. Reg. 60265; relating to policy governing munitions export licenses to Cyprus).</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

