<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA540B27806D44EAC904B40709C995EDC" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5887 IH: Building Innovation Growth through Data for Intellectual Property Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-05-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5887</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180521">May 21, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000266">Mr. Chabot</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Leahy-Smith America Invents Act to extend the period during which the Under Secretary
			 of Commerce for Intellectual Property and Director of the United States
			 Patent and Trademark Office may set or adjust certain fees, and for other
			 purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H9DE10535449E4E8C96A3123B2B4E0615" style="OLC">
 <section id="H5AB578B587884BF68C786FD12C251211" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Building Innovation Growth through Data for Intellectual Property Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>BIG Data for IP Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="H8EF4BEEE075F4ADDBD0D9B910FE82B32"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act—</text>
 <paragraph id="H0FADF670B66F4359BA4E853E11E22D66"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>advanced data science analytics</term> means techniques, such as artificial intelligence, machine learning, and other methods of analyzing large data sets, that are used to make policy recommendations;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H71FF329216CF4D028BE59176C72D85D6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>Director</term> means the Under Secretary of Commerce for Intellectual Property and Director of the Office;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="HFE9B4EF03AD74E6A856DA8D18E22E9E1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>Office</term> means the United States Patent and Trademark Office;</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H621714361052490490A9073E0230BAEF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>PPAC</term> means the Patent Public Advisory Committee of the Office; and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H89EC49A885BF4CCF82B407FC65F9BAFE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>TPAC</term> means the Trademark Public Advisory Committee of the Office.</text>
 </paragraph></section><section id="H9D084C3823424DA9A5C23A7180A0151F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="HFA1EA86C0BE445CAA021B549B6A412B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Section 10(a) of the Leahy-Smith America Invents Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/35/41">35 U.S.C. 41</external-xref> note) grants the Director the authority to <quote>set or adjust by rule any fee established, authorized, or charged under title 35, United States Code, or the Trademark Act of 1946. … to recover the aggregate estimated costs to the Office for processing, activities, services, and materials relating to patents (in the case of patent fees) and trademarks (in the case of trademark fees), including administrative costs of the Office</quote>.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H1FD8A521747847199F2AEBB34E53EE4C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Office has worked with PPAC, TPAC, and the public to engage in a fee-setting process that is transparent, as envisioned by the Leahy-Smith America Invents Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/112/29">Public Law 112–29</external-xref>; 125 Stat. 284).</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HF52D95DD240D4F5CBBF9DA2ED72D6E71"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Since 2011, the Office has used this fee-setting authority to implement a sustainable funding model with an operating reserve, which allows the Office to invest in long-term projects, including crucial infrastructure upgrades that are necessary for a 21st century intellectual property office, regardless of whether there are temporary fluctuations in patent or trademark filings.</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H39298C31FA084C71B56CF34FAFF0AABB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The infrastructure upgrades described in paragraph (3) include the use of advanced data science analytics, which will help to—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H0F15FA5A755148AAA57D9B40F42C557B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improve productivity and quality with respect to the issuance of patents and trademarks; and</text> </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D1EF1C00AB546EB8E4ACD25CBD17FCF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure—</text>
 <clause id="HBAB2660A7C9E438786F6D313067C4B6D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the consistent application of laws by nearly 9,000 patent examiners and trademark examining attorneys; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H23A21DF329A547179C80EA29EAF019BB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the certainty and strength of federally granted rights that are foundational to the economy of the United States.</text>
 </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H16984E7397DE412FAA5052981DC29EC6"><enum>4.</enum><header>Extension of sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 10(i)(2) of the Leahy-Smith America Invents Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/35/41">35 U.S.C. 41</external-xref> note) is amended by striking <quote>the 7-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act</quote> and inserting <quote>the 8-year period beginning on the date of enactment of the BIG Data for IP Act</quote>.</text> </section><section id="HAAF0DA4976D6475486FBE2EE0CB38D2A"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director shall submit to Congress a report that includes—</text>
 <paragraph id="H270A3D4F94664AF5BF711E9C0FD4E20A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the status of the capabilities of the information technology systems of the Office with respect to—</text> <subparagraph id="HDA8A77B8DAB24EC1814F656E0CD9C8DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the examination of patents and trademarks; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC16AD240C2B4964B4224A41FE78A2CD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>proceedings conducted before the—</text> <clause id="H3C75764398A44578B353A64B3D0313F3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Patent Trial and Appeal Board of the Office; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H450B23B50B5B42F4A4783901C008E8AC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Trademark Trial and Appeal Board of the Office;</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0DB037E7DFA4A63A03FCFF43D6397F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a 5-year plan for further modernization of the information technology systems described in paragraph (1); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="HCBBD697220EB4A8EACCD055DCD42D228"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an accounting of the use by the Office of advanced data science analytics, including from commercially available sources, to improve the patent and trademark examination process where appropriate, including—</text>
 <subparagraph id="H7EAABA03D5C042B195D2F06CDE633CC6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of how the Office uses advanced data science analytics with respect to the examination of patents and trademarks to—</text>
 <clause id="H7B679440638340D6BBB52742A0679816"><enum>(i)</enum><text>improve consistency;</text> </clause><clause id="H7B35D82AA9D840FBA540A271740563DF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>detect common sources of error; and</text>
 </clause><clause id="H9E989353A5524F2CA6DEA2D5F3A2B8E3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>improve productivity;</text> </clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02DAC34E7D984EE8912125470F48DC7C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a 5-year plan for further development of advanced data science analytics for the uses described in subparagraph (A); and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF2D5EF447B204B649BFCCF6F79CD33F2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of how the findings made as a result of the uses of advanced data science analytics under subparagraph (A) shall be made available to the public on a regular basis.</text>
				</subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill>


