<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3CF8372B55C94D8085B7097C443036E7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5490 IH: Handgun Purchaser Licensing Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-04-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5490</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20180412">April 12, 2018</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000293">Ms. Esty of Connecticut</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide for a grant program for handgun licensing programs, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H7139256CEB474EF59CF61636D8037A55" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H88150C68FD7D473CAF3384BFC9C9368B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Handgun Purchaser Licensing Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H55C2E527C72C42ACA28394432841E71C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds as follows:</text>
<paragraph id="H8D0D135BC8CA4453B4FABE2052A6DB55"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In 2013, more than 33,000 Americans were killed by guns and almost 90 percent of the firearms used in these deaths were handguns.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H22D826491C1B42AC868D1BAC992ACC0B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Recently published research by top national experts, notably on Missouri and Connecticut handgun purchaser licensing laws, have estimated that Missouri’s repeal of its handgun purchaser licensing law led to a 25-percent increase in firearm homicide rates while Connecticut’s adoption of its handgun purchaser licensing law led to a 40-percent decrease in firearm homicide rates.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HED44BCF3D5EF4B478894096E25A4F759"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In States which have had effective handgun purchaser licensing laws for decades, such as Connecticut, Massachusetts, New Jersey, and New York, the vast majority of guns traced to crimes originated in other States, which supports the need for handgun purchaser licensing laws in every State.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HEAF19F8C94204E259CBF271218B6413B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act—</text>
<paragraph id="HF077BA04BFF44C44AAA54728631F6209"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the terms <term>Attorney General</term> and <term>handgun</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 921(a) of title 18, United States Code; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H58FE019699AE4BEE9FA41A75BDFA81DE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>Indian tribe</term> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/450b">25 U.S.C. 450b</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="HA17053E813C44C93BBF360A922FAC8C7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Grant program authorized for handgun licensing</header>
<subsection id="HAAD8EB5581254DCF9E946627454609E2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General is authorized to award grants to States, units of local government, and Indian tribes for the development, implementation, and evaluation of handgun purchaser licensing requirements.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3FC217D4F225457581609F4CB7A3CB66"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>From the amounts appropriated to carry out this Act and not later than 90 days after such amounts are appropriated, the Attorney General shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible applicants whose applications are approved under subsection (c) to assist such applicants in implementing and improving handgun purchaser licensing programs.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H1E99D46250FF43ACB4C4AF0362BEDF19"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this Act, a State, unit of local government, or Indian tribe shall submit to the Attorney General an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Attorney General may require, including—</text> <paragraph id="H10253CFB178A49568B79FA2C55905443"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the law that the applicant has enacted to require a license for any purchase of a handgun including a description of any exemptions to such law; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF4CC37C97D4C4F7D9DC550789A08F116"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of how the applicant will use the grant to carry out or improve its handgun purchaser licensing program.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6893749F8FB945A482204C5418BEAA52"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligibility requirements</header><text>To be eligible for a grant under this Act, an applicant shall have in effect handgun purchaser licensing laws that—</text>
<paragraph id="HACEF0CDE46B14D00B8E399B8CCCCF9C0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>require—</text> <subparagraph id="H0F62F1FB857C474996E67239C420CAB0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an individual applying for a handgun license or permit to be at least 21 years old and be a national or lawful permanent resident of the United States;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF3829AB1545841FD9DE2BF69B2B17EBF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an individual described in subparagraph (A) to apply for the handgun purchaser license or permit at a law enforcement agency in the State in which the individual resides;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAF1584D590F34A1F9ECF02FAF3DCD51F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an individual who is issued a handgun license or permit to reapply for the handgun purchaser license or permit after a period not longer than 5 years;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF8C01287C3374898823C98D493ACCE10"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an individual described in subparagraph (A) to submit to a background investigation, and a criminal history check, in connection with the application, as established by the State;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0470F8FBADC04A31AC077D2BA88D4FD6"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an individual described in subparagraph (A) to submit fingerprints and photographs in connection with the application for the license or permit; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H23BC64A659BE4CC596EB62391EE66A20"><enum>(F)</enum><text>an individual described in subparagraph (A) to provide—</text> <clause id="HD0AF048C10AA4BED8E046E8412A97EE4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>proof that the individual is legally present and lawfully resides in the United States, including a birth certificate, or valid passport; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HB8E4338F7512483F9D09F93239FDD2AF"><enum>(ii)</enum>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4444DA606B5142A9AB98D7FCD0FBE609"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the case of a lawful permanent resident, the alien registration number and 90-day proof of residency; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H4B36A0B1F3324E7DBD985FD6C336667F" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of a naturalized citizen, proof of citizenship; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H97D632C013244BB793BEDB3A8A6E018F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prohibit an individual who is prohibited from possessing a firearm under section 922(g) of title 18, United States Code, from receiving a license or permit.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H039B886AD9F848A2B4BC15AC56943E51"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of Funds</header><text>A grantee under this Act shall use such grant to improve handgun purchaser licensing programs of that grantee.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H38FB63DFF4574EAC8D1EA6841A090EFA"><enum>5.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Attorney General such sums as may be necessary to carry out this Act.</text></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

