<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" bill-type="olc" dms-id="HA6438D3FCEE84940A34B78D1A305F6D5" key="H" public-private="public"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5324 IH: Supporting Teachers and Safe Students Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2018-03-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">115th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5324</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20180319">March 19, 2018</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve school safety and mental health services, and for other purposes.</official-title></form>
	<legis-body id="H961673617A324A209537148A635E18CD" style="OLC">
 <section commented="no" id="H53F37578B1C945129C477FDBED0570E9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supporting Teachers and Safe Students Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section><section id="HE3EEBC57030042E0B03D7CAEE28F8293"><enum>2.</enum><header>Violence prevention and mental health support</header> <subsection id="H5EF127B320644AD7833B6306AAA4F4E1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>State uses of funds</header><text>Section 2101(c)(4)(B) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6611">20 U.S.C. 6611(c)(4)(B)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HBF1D1429E0404899B764DD623D9FA63F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating clause (xxi) as clause (xxiv); and</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H13E5550E6BD24E96948F90692305826D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (xx) the following:</text>
					<quoted-block id="H61A29709FA294C46BDDA9D1783F2E988" style="OLC">
 <clause id="H9DD4B646E264491CA94DDFF85663A166"><enum>(xxi)</enum><text>Supporting efforts to increase the professional development that is evidence-based (to the extent the State, in consultation with local educational agencies in the State, determines that such evidence is reasonably available) for teachers, principals, school leaders, and other school personnel in mental health awareness, violence prevention, crisis response, de-escalation and anger management techniques, positive behavioral interventions and supports, bullying and harassment prevention, and other similar programs designed to reduce and prevent school violence.</text>
 </clause><clause id="HC3CDB091DB40452D8F4E781C9B3316A4"><enum>(xxii)</enum><text>Assisting local educational agencies in—</text> <subclause id="HEF87D55B80714778B03578FADF6BE4D8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>developing and implementing professional development that is evidence-based (to the extent the State, in consultation with local educational agencies in the State, determines that such evidence is reasonably available) on violence prevention programs and emergency response and notification systems; and</text>
 </subclause><subclause id="HD4B98E0760CE4B319A710D8B0766DB3A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>improving school climate.</text> </subclause></clause><clause id="H7F434B1307FF4E1F93FA9C383EB5F360"><enum>(xxiii)</enum><text>Developing agreements between local educational agencies, law enforcement agencies, and health agencies, including nonprofit, public, and private mental health agencies and institutions, to improve coordination of services and to identify, respond to, and prevent threats to the safety of students and school personnel.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
 </paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE4FB062753914DEBA233130C349AD618"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Local uses of funds</header><text>Section 2103(b)(3) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6613">20 U.S.C. 6613(b)(3)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
 <paragraph id="HAC0BE26E17EB4CB9BE2FE1B0888CD9FB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I)—</text> <subparagraph id="H89E9660BD25D4D14B48BF8B4E311FCFF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by inserting <quote>, including mental health services,</quote> after <quote>services</quote>; and</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0887135305324BF4AB11A9902107A613"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking <quote>and public or private mental health organizations</quote> and inserting <quote>, public or private mental health organizations, and local law enforcement agencies, to improve the coordination of services and to identify, respond to, and prevent threats to the safety of students and school personnel</quote>;</text>
 </subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H76427B4313CE414EA218EBCDCFE87F5A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (O), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text> </paragraph><paragraph id="H5063593195D546F5BB5269E99A552396"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (P) as subparagraph (R); and</text>
 </paragraph><paragraph id="H68C818268AA74727810657D9FA78C943"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (O) the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HE40867A466B34A2BB1EDB2E29E802531" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H24DB345CFA4341678DDCE110B33F9655"><enum>(P)</enum><text>reducing the ratio of students to counselors to improve the ability of schools to address the needs of students through the recruiting and hiring of school-based mental health services providers, as defined in section 4102(6);</text>
 </subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6FA98581064F4D349D3C754C90E3036C"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>developing and implementing professional development that is evidence-based (to the extent the State, in consultation with local educational agencies in the State, determines that such evidence is reasonably available) for teachers, specialized instructional support personnel, principals, school leaders, and other school personnel in violence prevention, mental health awareness, threat de-escalation methods, and positive behavioral interventions and supports, and supporting bullying and harassment prevention programs, and other similar programs designed to reduce and prevent school violence and improve the school climate for all students; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block>
				</paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


