<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="25147">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;House Hearing, 115 Congress&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;From the U.S. Government Publishing Office&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         H.A.S.C. No. 115-31&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                        CONSEQUENCES AND CONTEXT&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                       FOR RUSSIA'S VIOLATIONS OF&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                             THE INF TREATY&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               __________&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                             JOINT HEARING&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               before the&lt;/info&gt;
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON STRATEGIC FORCES&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                                 of the
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;committee_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES&lt;/committee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                          meeting jointly with
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON TERRORISM, NONPROLIFERATION, AND TRADE&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                                 of the
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <committeeComposition>
    &lt;comitteeM_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON FOREIGN AFFAIRS&lt;/comitteeM_name&gt;
    &lt;Chairman&gt;
        &lt;Cname&gt;                          Serial No. 115-57&lt;/Cname&gt;
        &lt;Clocation&gt;                          Serial No. 115-57&lt;/Clocation&gt;
    &lt;/Chairman&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;ViceChair&gt;
        &lt;Cname&gt;ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS&lt;/Cname&gt;
        &lt;Clocation&gt;ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS&lt;/Clocation&gt;
    &lt;/ViceChair&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;FIRST SESSION&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;FIRST SESSION&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;HEARING HELD&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;HEARING HELD&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;MARCH 30&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; 2017&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;WASHINGTON : 2017&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;WASHINGTON : 2017&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt; For sale by the Superintendent of Documents&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; U.S. Government Publishing Office&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Internet:bookstore.gpo.gov. Phone:toll free (866)512-1800;DC area (202)512-1800&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;Internet:bookstore.gpo.gov. Phone:toll free (866)512-1800;DC area (202)512-1800&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Fax:(202) 512-2104 Mail:Stop IDCC&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;DC 20402-001&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
</committeeComposition>
    <committeeComposition>
    &lt;comitteeM_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES&lt;/comitteeM_name&gt;
</committeeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON STRATEGIC FORCES&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                     MIKE ROGERS, Alabama, Chairman
TRENT FRANKS, Arizona, Vice Chair    JIM COOPER, Tennessee
DOUG LAMBORN, Colorado               SUSAN A. DAVIS, California
DUNCAN HUNTER, California            RICK LARSEN, Washington
MO BROOKS, Alabama                   JOHN GARAMENDI, California
JIM BRIDENSTINE, Oklahoma            BETO O'ROURKE, Texas
MICHAEL R. TURNER, Ohio              DONALD NORCROSS, New Jersey
MIKE COFFMAN, Colorado               COLLEEN HANABUSA, Hawaii
BRADLEY BYRNE, Alabama               RO KHANNA, California
SAM GRAVES, Missouri
                         Tim Morrison, Counsel
                         Leonor Tomero, Counsel
                           Mike Gancio, Clerk
                                 ------                                
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON FOREIGN AFFAIRS&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                 EDWARD R. ROYCE, California, Chairman
CHRISTOPHER H. SMITH, New Jersey     ELIOT L. ENGEL, New York
ILEANA ROS-LEHTINEN, Florida         BRAD SHERMAN, California
DANA ROHRABACHER, California         GREGORY W. MEEKS, New York
STEVE CHABOT, Ohio                   ALBIO SIRES, New Jersey
JOE WILSON, South Carolina           GERALD E. CONNOLLY, Virginia
MICHAEL T. McCAUL, Texas             THEODORE E. DEUTCH, Florida
TED POE, Texas                       KAREN BASS, California
DARRELL E. ISSA, California          WILLIAM R. KEATING, Massachusetts
TOM MARINO, Pennsylvania             DAVID N. CICILLINE, Rhode Island
JEFF DUNCAN, South Carolina          AMI BERA, California
MO BROOKS, Alabama                   LOIS FRANKEL, Florida
PAUL COOK, California                TULSI GABBARD, Hawaii
SCOTT PERRY, Pennsylvania            JOAQUIN CASTRO, Texas
RON DeSANTIS, Florida                ROBIN L. KELLY, Illinois
MARK MEADOWS, North Carolina         BRENDAN F. BOYLE, Pennsylvania
TED S. YOHO, Florida                 DINA TITUS, Nevada
ADAM KINZINGER, Illinois             NORMA J. TORRES, California
LEE M. ZELDIN, New York              BRADLEY SCOTT SCHNEIDER, Illinois
DANIEL M. DONOVAN, Jr., New York     THOMAS R. SUOZZI, New York
F. JAMES SENSENBRENNER, Jr.,         ADRIANO ESPAILLAT, New York
    Wisconsin                        TED LIEU, California
ANN WAGNER, Missouri
BRIAN J. MAST, Florida
FRANCIS ROONEY, Florida
BRIAN K. FITZPATRICK, Pennsylvania
THOMAS A. GARRETT, Jr., Virginia
     Amy Porter, Chief of Staff      Thomas Sheehy, Staff Director
               Jason Steinbaum, Democratic Staff Director
                                 ------                                
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;Subcommittee on Terrorism, Nonproliferation, and Trade&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;Chairman&gt;
        &lt;Cname&gt;                        TED POE&lt;/Cname&gt;
        &lt;Clocation&gt; Chairman&lt;/Clocation&gt;
    &lt;/Chairman&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;JOE WILSON&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; South Carolina&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;WILLIAM R. KEATING&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Massachusetts&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;ViceChair&gt;
        &lt;Cname&gt;DARRELL E. ISSA&lt;/Cname&gt;
        &lt;Clocation&gt; California&lt;/Clocation&gt;
    &lt;/ViceChair&gt;
    &lt;ViceChair&gt;
        &lt;Cname&gt;LOIS FRANKEL&lt;/Cname&gt;
        &lt;Clocation&gt; Florida&lt;/Clocation&gt;
    &lt;/ViceChair&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;PAUL COOK&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; California&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;BRENDAN F. BOYLE&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Pennsylvania&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;SCOTT PERRY&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Pennsylvania&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;DINA TITUS&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Nevada&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;LEE M. ZELDIN&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; New York&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;NORMA J. TORRES&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; California&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;BRIAN J. MAST&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Florida&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;BRADLEY SCOTT SCHNEIDER&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Illinois&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;THOMAS A. GARRETT&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Virginia&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <Directory>
    &lt;table-of-content&gt;C O N T E N T S&lt;/table-of-content&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS&lt;/Speakers&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Subcommittee on Strategic Forces, Committee on Armed Services..     1&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Hon Mike Rogers&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative from Alabama Chairman&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;witnesses&gt;WITNESSES&lt;/witnesses&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Hon Frank A Rose&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Former Assistant Secretary of State for Arms Control Verification&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Hon Robert M Scher&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Former Assistant Secretary of Defense for Strategy Plans&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Jon Brook Wolfsthal&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Former Senior Director for Arms Control and Nonproliferation National Security Council&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;APPENDIX&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;Prepared Statements:&lt;/Speakers&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;Subcommittee on Terrorism, Nonproliferation, and Trade,&lt;/Speakers&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;Hon Jim Cooper&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative from Tennessee Ranking Member&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;Committee on Armed Services Documents Submitted for the Record: Letter to Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff Dempsey Joint Chiefs of Staff  report Witness Responses to Questions Asked During the Hearing: There were no Questions submitted during the hearing Questions Submitted by Members Post Hearing: Mr Cooper Mr Rogers CONSEQUENCES AND CONTEXT FOR RUSSIA'S VIOLATIONS OF THE INF TREATY  House of Representatives&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Subcommittee on Strategic Forces Meeting Jointly with the Committee on Foreign Affairs&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;ALABAMA, CHAIRMAN, SUBCOMMITTEE ON STRATEGIC FORCES, COMMITTEE 
                       ON ARMED SERVICES
    Mr. Rogers. This joint hearing will come to order. Since we 
were called away for votes at a bad time, we have agreed to 
dispense with opening statements from the members and go 
directly to our witnesses. We want to thank our witnesses for 
being here and taking the time to not only attend, but to 
prepare. We know it takes a lot of time and energy, and it is a 
great help to us, so thank you very much.
    We have a distinguished panel with us today. The Honorable 
Frank Rose, former Assistant Secretary of State for Arms 
Control, Verification, and Compliance; the Honorable Bob Scher, 
Former Assistant Secretary of Defense for Strategy, Plans, and 
Capabilities; and Jon Wolfsthal, did I say that right?
    Mr. Wolfsthal. Excellent, sir.
    Mr. Rogers. Former Senior Director of Arms Control and 
Nonproliferation, National Security Council.
    We will start with Mr. Rose. You are recognized for an 
opening statement.
    The prepared statement of Mr. Rogers can be found in the 
Appendix on page 33.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;     STATE FOR ARMS CONTROL, VERIFICATION, AND COMPLIANCE, 
                      DEPARTMENT OF STATE
    Mr. Rose. Great. Chairman Rogers, Chairman Poe, Ranking 
Member Cooper, Ranking Member Keating, members of the 
committee, it is a pleasure to appear before you today to 
discuss how the United States and its allies should respond to 
Russia's violation of its obligations under the Intermediate 
Nuclear Forces, or INF, Treaty. As I outlined in my prepared 
statement, I believe it is highly unlikely that Russia will 
return to compliance with its obligations under the treaty for 
a variety of political and military reasons. Specifically, I 
believe that Russia no longer views the Euro-Atlantic security 
architecture put in place in the late 1980s and early 1990s as 
in its interest, and it is slowly but surely trying to, I would 
say, dismantle that architecture, and the INF Treaty violation 
is a symptom of that.
    Therefore, a strong but proportional response is required 
by the United States and its allies to effectively deal with 
Russia's violation. I would recommend that the United States 
and its allies adopt a, quote, ``countervailing strategy'' in 
response to Russia's violation that seeks to enhance deterrence 
by holding critical Russian assets at risk. That response 
should also include limited defensive measures to deny Russia 
significant military benefit from the deployment of the new 
ground launch cruise missile. This approach would include 
several elements.
    First, I think it is important that the United States 
remain focused on maintaining the unity of our alliance, both 
in Asia and in Europe. The INF Treaty is not simply a bilateral 
treaty between the U.S. and Russia, but it goes to the heart of 
Euro-Atlantic security. So as we develop our response options, 
I think it is imperative we do that in a way that maximizes 
coordination with allies. And, furthermore, as we look at 
military response options, I think it is important that we find 
ways to include the allies.
    Secondly, I think the United States needs to place the 
blame for the demise on the INF Treaty squarely with Russia. It 
is Russia who has cheated on the treaty and got caught. We need 
to be careful, though, that we don't unilaterally withdraw and 
give Russia a victory. My predecessor in the Bush 
administration, Steve Rademaker, in testimony before this 
committee in July of 2014, made the same point. We don't want 
to give the Russians a gift.
    Third, I think it is very important that the United States 
continue to fund the nuclear modernization program, 
specifically the new air-launch cruise missile, the long-range 
standoff system, or LRSO. This will improve our ability to hold 
critical Russian targets at risk.
    Fourth, I think the United States should develop a 
conventional variant of the LRSO. Again, this conventional 
variant of the LRSO will further allow us to hold critical 
Russian targets at risk.
    Fifth, I think we should facilitate allied acquisition of 
air- and sea-launch conventional strike capabilities, 
particularly the joint air and surface standoff missile, or 
JASSM, and we should also consider selling the Tomahawk sea-
launch cruise missile to interested allies.
    Sixth, I think it is critical that we remind Russia that 
NATO North Atlantic Treaty Organization remains a nuclear 
alliance, and implement all of the key nuclear recommendations 
from NATO's Warsaw Summit of July 2016.
    And, finally, the United States and NATO should deploy 
limited cruise missile defenses to protect key alliance assets 
in the event of a conflict with Russia. While I support the 
deployment of limited cruise missiles, I would caution against 
moving forward with the deployment of a larger set of mission 
defense capabilities aimed against Russia, especially Russia's 
strategic deterrent. Such an approach would be extremely 
expensive and technologically challenging.
    In conclusion, Mr. Chairman, the INF Treaty has served the 
security interests of the United States and our allies for 
almost 30 years. It is not just a bilateral treaty between the 
U.S. and Russia, but goes to the heart of European security. 
However, it is clear to me that Russia is not coming back into 
compliance, or unlikely to do; therefore, a strong but 
proportional response is required. Those response options 
should be implemented in a way that maintains alliance unity, 
and places the blame for the demise of the treaty squarely 
where it belongs, with Russia.
    Thank you very much.
    The prepared statement of Mr. Rose can be found in the 
Appendix on page 40.
    Mr. Rogers. Thank you very much.
    Mr. Scher, you are recognized for your opening statement.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;OF DEFENSE FOR STRATEGY, PLANS, AND CAPABILITIES, DEPARTMENT OF 
                            DEFENSE
    Mr. Scher. Thank you. Chairman Rogers, Chairman Poe, 
Ranking Member Cooper, Ranking Member Keating, distinguished 
members, thank you for inviting me to testify today. As I am 
sure you all know, my testimony represents my personal views 
only, and not those of the previous administration. And I will 
try to touch on just the key highlights of my written 
testimony, which I know will be put into the record, in this 
opening statement to keep lots of time for questions and 
answers.
    Russia's violation of the INF Treaty and its deployment of 
the violating system must be considered within the context of 
Russia's overall aggressive behavior. Given this, any approach 
to Russia's violation needs to be considered within a complete 
context of a strategy towards Russia. Having said that, within 
this context, I believe it will be very difficult, if not 
impossible, to bring Russia back into compliance, but I also 
believe that right now, it remains in our best interests to try 
to get Russia to return. Having the INF Treaty in force 
enhances strategic stability, and continuing to be seen by our 
allies as working diligently with Russia is important.
    The centerpiece of any policy must be approaching this with 
all levers of national power and using these to demonstrate 
that we will not allow the Russians to benefit from their 
violation. As such, the administration should consider taking 
some combination of military actions along with diplomatic and 
economic actions to show Russia it will not achieve the 
advantages it seeks by deploying this system. And further, I 
would argue that U.S. government policies should be oriented 
towards demonstrating to Russia that they are actually going to 
be worse off militarily and diplomatically if they continue to 
field this system. Certain actions clearly need to be taken or 
are already being taken and should be built upon. We need to 
better protect our forces and our allies directly from these 
missiles, and I believe that there should be consideration of 
increasing those capabilities, especially in the area of cruise 
missile defense. The United States and its allies must look to 
field systems into and around the region that can hold at risk 
key targets inside of Russia, including, but not limited to, 
the violating systems.
    The U.S. and NATO should continue to improve the readiness 
and presence of their conventional and nuclear forces. As the 
United States and NATO allies step up pressure, other actions 
should be considered in any review. When considering these 
options, however, we must realize that any policy has to strike 
the difficult balance between demonstrating to Russia that it 
cannot take its aggressive actions and expect that there will 
be no response, against ensuring that any actions taken to 
increase overall strategic stability--sorry--that any actions 
will increase strategic stability, not reduce it.
    Some examples of military actions I described in my 
testimony that could be considered are: increasing deployments 
of SSGNs cruise missile submarines in and around Europe to 
increase strike capacity of U.S. assets in the region; fielding 
unilaterally and in conjunction with NATO allies broader and 
more sophisticated rocket artillery systems on the territory of 
our eastern allies; speeding up the deployment of the LRSO and 
quickly developing a conventional cruise missile variant; 
transitioning the Air Force program office overseeing LRSO 
development into a joint program office; and considering how to 
develop or how we might field a ground-launch cruise missile 
similar to the one Russia has apparently deployed. While 
consideration of this option is not a violation of the INF 
Treaty, clearly, many would see this as the most escalatory of 
the options.
    Critical to any coordinated political, economic, and 
military set of actions that we take is that they are developed 
and carried out in coordination with our allies. Our alliance 
structure is key to our strength, and it is a comparative 
advantage we have over Russia. However, we also cannot afford 
to let NATO drift into paralysis, and must make it clear to our 
allies that inaction is unacceptable.
    I appreciate the attention that these subcommittees have 
paid to this important issue. I appreciate the chance to 
testify in front of you, and look forward to answering any 
questions you may have.
    The prepared statement of Mr. Scher can be found in the 
Appendix on page 49.
    Mr. Rogers. Thank you very much for that statement.
    Mr. Wolfsthal, you are recognized for 5 minutes.
&lt;/option&gt;
</Directory>
</Hearing>
