<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="32259">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;115th Congress }                            Printed for the use of the                       &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt; 2nd Session   }      Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;======================================================================&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	                     A Truly Inclusive Society:&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	                Encouraging the Ability in Disability&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         SEPTEMBER 24, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                           Briefing of the&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         Washington: 2019&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;      Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  234 Ford House Office Building                                               &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   Washington, DC 20515&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      202-225-1901&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      csce@mail.house.gov&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      http://www.csce.gov&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         @HelsinkiComm&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            Legislative Branch Commissioners&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;              HOUSE				SENATE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;CHRISTOPHER H. SMITH, New Jersey 	ROGER WICKER, Mississippi,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Co-Chairman			  Chairman&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ALCEE L. HASTINGS, Florida		BENJAMIN L. CARDIN. Maryland&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ROBERT B. ADERHOLT, Alabama		JOHN BOOZMAN, Arkansas&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;MICHAEL C. BURGESS, Texas		CORY GARDNER, Colorado&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;STEVE COHEN, Tennessee			MARCO RUBIO, Florida&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;RICHARD HUDSON, North Carolina		JEANNE SHAHEEN, New Hampshire&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;RANDY HULTGREN, Illinois		THOM TILLIS, North Carolina&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;SHEILA JACKSON LEE, Texas		TOM UDALL, New Mexico&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;GWEN MOORE, Wisconsin			SHELDON WHITEHOUSE, Rhode Island&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;               Executive Branch Commissioners&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                    DEPARTMENT OF STATE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  DEPARTMENT OF COMMERCE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                            [II]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ABOUT THE ORGANIZATION FOR SECURITY AND COOPERATION IN EUROPE  &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Helsinki process, formally titled the Conference on Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe, traces its origin to the signing of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Helsinki Final Act in Finland on August 1, 1975, by the leaders of 33 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European countries, the United States and Canada. As of January 1, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;1995, the Helsinki process was renamed the Organization for Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE). The membership of the OSCE has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;expanded to 56 participating States, reflecting the breakup of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Soviet Union, Czechoslovakia, and Yugoslavia.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The OSCE Secretariat is in Vienna, Austria, where weekly meetings &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the participating States' permanent representatives are held. In &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;addition, specialized seminars and meetings are convened in various &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;locations. Periodic consultations are held among Senior Officials, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Ministers and Heads of State or Government.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Although the OSCE continues to engage in standard setting in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fields of military security, economic and environmental cooperation, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and human rights and humanitarian concerns, the Organization is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;primarily focused on initiatives designed to prevent, manage and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resolve conflict within and among the participating States. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Organization deploys numerous missions and field activities located in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Southeastern and Eastern Europe, the Caucasus, and Central Asia. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;website of the OSCE is: &amp;lt;www.osce.org&amp;gt;.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ABOUT THE COMMISSION ON SECURITY AND COOPERATION IN EUROPE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, also known as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Helsinki Commission, is a U.S. Government agency created in 1976 to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;monitor and encourage compliance by the participating States with their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;OSCE commitments, with a particular emphasis on human rights.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission consists of nine members from the United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Senate, nine members from the House of Representatives, and one member &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;each from the Departments of State, Defense and Commerce. The positions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Chair and Co-Chair rotate between the Senate and House every two &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years, when a new Congress convenes. A professional staff assists the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commissioners in their work.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In fulfilling its mandate, the Commission gathers and disseminates &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relevant information to the U.S. Congress and the public by convening &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hearings, issuing reports that reflect the views of Members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission and/or its staff, and providing details about the activities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the Helsinki process and developments in OSCE participating States.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission also contributes to the formulation and execution of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.S. policy regarding the OSCE, including through Member and staff &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participation on U.S. Delegations to OSCE meetings. Members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission have regular contact with parliamentarians, government &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;officials, representatives of non-governmental organizations, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;private individuals from participating States. The website of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission is: &amp;lt;www.csce.gov&amp;gt;.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                        A Truly Inclusive Society:&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 Encouraging the Ability in Disability&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                           September 24, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                                                 Page&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              PARTICIPANTS&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Allison Hollabaugh Parker, General Counsel, Commission for Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe  .......................................     1&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Sara Hart Weir, President and CEO, National Down Syndrome Society..2&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Kayla McKeon, Manager of Grassroots Advocacy, National Down &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Syndrome Society.......................................................4&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Sheryl Lazarus, Director, The TIES Center......................6&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    John Cronin, Entrepreneur with Down Syndrome and Co-Founder of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;John's Crazy Socks.....................................................8&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mark Cronin, Co-Founder and President of John's Crazy Socks........9&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                     A Truly Inclusive Society:&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  Encouraging the Ability in Disability&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              ----------                              &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                           September 24, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The briefing was held at 3:30 p.m. in Room 2220, Rayburn House &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Office Building, Washington, DC, Allison Hollabaugh Parker, General &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Counsel, Commission for Security and Cooperation in Europe, presiding.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Panelists present: Allison Hollabaugh Parker, General Counsel, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission for Security and Cooperation in Europe; Sara Hart Weir, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;President and CEO, National Down Syndrome Society; Kayla McKeon, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Manager of Grassroots Advocacy, National Down Syndrome Society; Dr. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Sheryl Lazarus, Director, The TIES Center; John Cronin, Entrepreneur &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with Down Syndrome and Co-Founder of John's Crazy Socks; and Mark &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Cronin, Co-Founder and President of John's Crazy Socks.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Good afternoon. My name is Allison Hollabaugh Parker. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;am general counsel at the Helsinki Commission, also known as the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, and it's my pleasure &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to welcome you this afternoon to our briefing on creating ``A Truly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Inclusive Society: Encouraging the Ability in Disability.''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    As you may know, 57 million Americans are living with disabilities, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;400,000 of them with Down syndrome. Almost three decades ago, President &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Bush signed into law the Americans With Disabilities Act (ADA). This &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;provided individuals with disabilities access to the same employment &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opportunities and benefits available to people without disabilities, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;encouraged employers to make reasonable accommodations, required state &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and local governments to make all services and programs available to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals with disabilities, prohibited places of public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;accommodation from discriminating against individuals with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities, and directed businesses to make reasonable modifications &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;when serving individuals with disabilities.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In so doing, the ADA has broken down many barriers blocking the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;full participation of individuals with disabilities in their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;communities, in the economy, and across the United States, in every &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sphere in which they would like to participate. While the United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has an exemplary system of integration, empowerment, and protection, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals with intellectual disabilities, like Down syndrome, have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;recommended numerous further improvements to U.S. law in order to fully &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;realize the goals of the Americans With Disabilities Act.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    This briefing will explore best practices developed federally and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;locally in the United States to empower and integrate individuals with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;intellectual disabilities. We'll also discuss changes that will enable &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals with disabilities to reach their full potential. The law on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this subject is a work in process and I look forward to hearing from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our five panelists this afternoon, the first of whom is Sarah Hart &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Weir. She is the president and CEO of the National Down Syndrome &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Society (NDSS), which is the largest nonprofit in the United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;dedicated to advocating for people with Down syndrome and their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;families. As president, she oversees the organization's mission, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;vision, and administration. Ms. Weir works each day to ensure people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with Down syndrome are represented at every table where critical &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;decisions are made, whether it's the White House, the U.S. Congress, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the United Nations, or in state capitols across the country. Ms. Weir &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has a Bachelor of Arts in psychology and political leadership from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Westminster College and a Master of Science in public policy and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;management from Carnegie Mellon University's Heinz College.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Weir.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Weir. Good afternoon. My name is Sarah Hart Weir and I'm the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;president and CEO of the world's largest Down syndrome advocacy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organization, the National Down Syndrome Society.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I have had the opportunity to work with people with Down syndrome &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for almost 20 years and was inspired to get involved in this amazing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;community from my best friend, Kasey, who happens to have Down syndrome &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and lives in Kansas.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    On behalf of NDSS, the leading human rights organization for all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals with Down syndrome, it's an honor to sit at this table &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;today to present to the Helsinki Commission with Dr. Lazarus, one of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our favorite NDSS #DSWORKS&amp;#4; employment partners, Mark and John Cronin &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from John's Crazy Socks, and, of course, my esteemed colleague Kayla &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;McKeon.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    At NDSS, we believe if you're not at the table you're on the menu. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I personally want to thank the Helsinki Commission for today's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;imperative discussion and lending a critical voice to a population &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that, even in our great nation, the United States of America, and still &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in 2018 is far more discriminated against than any other community.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Today's topic, ``A Truly Inclusive Society: Encouraging the Ability &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Disability,'' is something we live and breathe at the National Down &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Syndrome Society as we strive to achieve equality for all Americans &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with Down syndrome in the United States.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Our great nation's first motto, ``E Pluribus Unum,'' is embedded in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;every fabric of our country's rich history. The phrase is used on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;currency, the seal of the president, vice president, the U.S. Congress, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the U.S. House, the U.S. Senate, and on the seal of our Supreme Court. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;It is cemented in our country's rich history, culture, and values. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness comes from the Latin phrase &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;``out of many, one.'' From this belief springs a unifying purpose for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our Nation: equality. Unfortunately, in the United States and around &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the world, people with Down syndrome and other disabilities are not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;treated as one.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    At NDSS, we believe no matter your differences or your abilities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you should have a fair shot at the American dream. And we work hard &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;each and every day to ensure America's motto is upheld for people with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Down syndrome and that ``one'' truly means one.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    At NDSS, a fourth of our staff have Down syndrome and work across &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all of our programs and departments. Not a single decision within our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organization is made without their input and the input of our self-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;advocates.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    At NDSS, our programs--including our National Advocacy and Policy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Center here in Washington, DC, our #DSWORKS&amp;#4; employment program, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our health promotion and resources program--each of these programs are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;dedicated to advancing proactive policies and providing invaluable &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resources on issues across the lifespan, from birth to old age, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;across five key critical pillars: health care and research, education, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;employment, community integration, and economic self-sufficiency.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Next year, we will celebrate NDSS's 40th anniversary. During this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time, one of the most important advancements for individuals with Down &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;syndrome has been an increased access to advancements in health care. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;This result has led to a dramatic increase in the life expectancy for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people with Down syndrome. In 1983, it was 25. Today it's well into the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;60s. And this is a result of early detection of co-occurring &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conditions, like congenital heart defects, quality dental care and, of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;course, inclusion.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    From its origins in 1979, NDSS has been involved in so many Federal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and state advocacy efforts as well as judicial efforts that have helped &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals with disabilities become more included in society: The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;passage of IDEA that guarantees students with disabilities the right to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be educated alongside their peers in their neighborhood school; the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Americans With Disabilities Act, or ADA, that prohibits discrimination &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;against individuals with disabilities in all areas of public life and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the subsequent Olmstead Supreme Court decision that requires public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;agencies to provide services in the most integrated settings; of course &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the shutdown of Willowbrook in New York, which was brought to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;forefront of the public's conscientiousness to shut down institutions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;across the country; and something we at NDSS are extremely proud of, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the landmark passage of the Stephen Beck Jr. Achieving a Better Life &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Experience Act, best known as the ABLE Act, which allows individuals &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with disabilities to save their own money for the future.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    These accomplishments and milestones were vital to ensure &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals with disabilities have access and adequate supports to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;basic liberties those without disabilities enjoy: education, community &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;integration, housing, employment, and savings.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Despite these significant advancements, we have a long way to go. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;People with Down syndrome are still held back and confined to laws that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;were put into place when we were still institutionalizing people with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities, the life expectancy was very, very low and a time when &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;perceptions of people with Down syndrome were not even realized.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Still, today, individuals with disabilities still do not have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;access to marriage equality. Individuals with disabilities cannot &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;maintain their vital benefits while working, despite--and you'll hear &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from Kayla and John--being ready, willing, and able to work. Though we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fought for IDEA, many students do not have the access to inclusive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;education to which they are entitled to and is the basis of life in our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;schools each and every day.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Many cannot choose where they want to live and housing options are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;extremely low. And many are still not economically self-sufficient, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;despite ABLE accounts being open to qualifying individuals across the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Nation.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Outrageously, many are still getting paid way below the minimum &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wage. We still have Section 14(c) of the Fair Labor Standards Act, a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;law that was put in place in 1938, where businesses can apply for wage &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;certificates from the Department of Labor to pay individuals with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities way below the Federal minimum wage, sometimes as low as 30 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cents an hour. Something we at NDSS are advocating very aggressively &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for is the passage of the TIME Act led by Congressman Greg Harper. Last &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;year, NDSS launched our campaign to end #LawSyndrome, to draw attention &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to these issues and to advocate for change.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Down syndrome does not hold Kayla, John or any of our friends and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;loved ones with Down syndrome back. It's truly these antiquated laws &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that are preventing individuals with Down syndrome from reaching their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;full potential. And we at NDSS will not stop until every single &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;American with Down syndrome has the same rights as every other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;American.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    One of my proudest accomplishments at NDSS is ensuring individuals &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with Down syndrome are not even--not just part of our incredible team &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and wonderful organization, but they are at every table where key &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;decisions about their future are made. When you have a seat at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;table, you have a say in those decisions and how they are made. When &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it's your table, you make the decisions. This is how we end &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;#LawSyndrome.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'm honored to introduce--and I know Allison will as well and let &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Kayla follow--my colleague, who has not only earned a seat at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;table, she owns the table and she owns Capitol Hill.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you, Allison, and the members of the Helsinki Commission and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;staff for making today possible.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. And thank you, Ms. Weir, for the long and hard work of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;NDSS to ensure that we continue to move forward in the United States in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the advancement of human and civil rights for individuals with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;intellectual disabilities.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'd like to next introduce Kayla McKeon.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Am I saying that correctly?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. McKeon. Yes.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. She is the first registered lobbyist in the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States with Down syndrome and she's a member of the Down Syndrome &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Society's Self-Advocate Advisory Board where she serves as manager of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;grassroots advocacy. Prior to joining the NDSS team, she worked for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Congressman John Katko from New York. Ms. McKeon is also a Special &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Olympics athlete and a Special Olympics congress member. In 2011, she &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;competed in the Special Olympic World Games in Athens, Greece, winning &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a silver and a bronze medal.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Kayla.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. McKeon. And thank you, Allison.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And good afternoon. And to echo Sarah's words, thank you to Allison &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and the Helsinki Commission for letting me speak today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My name is Kayla McKeon and I am the manager of grassroots advocacy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at the National Down Syndrome Society and I am the first registered &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;lobbyist who just happens to have Down syndrome.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Down syndrome doesn't define me and it definitely does not stop me. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;What limits me and my fellow advocates and friends with Down syndrome--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as Sarah mentioned, #LawSyndrome is a series of very old and antiquated &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;laws that were passed when I would not have lived past my adolescence &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;or even my childhood, and even if I did, I would not have left the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hospital with my parents because people with Down syndrome were still &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;being institutionalized. These laws were put in place when the social &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;acceptance of individuals with disabilities was at an all-time low.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I was lucky in my upbringing in Syracuse, New York. When I was 18 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;months old, my parents involved me in an early education program. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;progressed through school alongside my classmates and graduated at 18 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as soon as inclusive education became possible. I was always in an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inclusive setting. I won't deny there were bumps and stumbling blocks &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;along the way, but my parents always thought it was best for me to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;included with my classmates and placed in settings that challenged me &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to reach my highest potential. And there were times when they pushed &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;me, but it was only because they knew I could succeed.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I earned awards in 8th and 9th grades--character, commitment and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;courage--as well as in English and math. My final grade for algebra was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the 90s. I got a 93 in a math regent's exam. So if you are familiar, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you know how tough that was. [Laughter.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Later, an agency known as Vocational and Educational Services for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Individuals with Disabilities, or VESID, and my high school had set up &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a program to take an office technology program. It was a 6-month &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;certificate program for adults. They arranged it where I could do it--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;go through it twice. I passed the program, earned a certificate and, as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a result, I am very fast on the keyboard. I was even the commencement &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;speaker.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I also attended Onondaga Community College taking some noncredit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;courses. But I thought to myself, does it make sense I'm doing all the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;work without earning any credits? But I like the classes, so I began &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;taking one class per semester for credit. I can happily say I am now &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;more than halfway to earning my Associate's degree. I started back in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;August. I love taking classes with my peers. Many of my classmates are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a little bit younger than me, but so what?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I started advocating a number of years ago. I started advocating on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;laws about the differently abled by going to elementary schools, going &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to middle schools, colleges, and the schools of nursing. I try to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;motivate them to do the best that they can do. My message to kids is to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;persevere. I am who I am today partly because I was included with my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;peers throughout my childhood.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    One day in Syracuse, I met John Katko at a baseball game. He was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;running for the U.S. House of Representatives. He handed me his &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;business card, so I handed him mine. He called me later and said if he &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was elected he wanted me to come and intern for him. When he won, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;became an intern in the Syracuse office. I represented him at different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;events and did office work. In June of last year, he asked me to go &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with him to a disability conference in Washington. We didn't realize at &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that time it was with the National Down Syndrome Society. It was there &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at the end of the meeting that Sarah Hart Weir, our president and CEO &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of NDSS, offered me the job of manager of grassroots advocacy. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;started last October.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    With my position as the first registered lobbyist with Down &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;syndrome, I go to Capitol Hill and speak to many members of Congress &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and their staff on issues that are very important to me. I helped lobby &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to pass the original ABLE Act as a volunteer for NDSS and now the ABLE &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to Work Act and the ABLE Financial Planning Act as a lobbyist. These &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;laws allow me and my friends, the differently abled, to have savings &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;accounts and meaningful employment without giving up our benefits.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We are now tirelessly working on ending #LawSyndrome. Down syndrome &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;doesn't stop us, it never stops us. And there are some old, antiquated &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;laws that hold us back. One example is the 80-year-old provision with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Fair Labor Standards Act, known as Section 14(c) that Sarah had &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mentioned. People like me are still getting paid cents an hour while &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;other individuals performing the same task that are paid at least &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;minimum wage. These issues segregate us from the rest of society. We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are still viewed as ``less than.''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Society is ready to move past these laws. When will the government &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;keep up? [Laughter.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We still have a long way to go for individuals with Down syndrome &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to be fully included in society. To me, having Down syndrome is who I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;am, but it has never stopped me from achieving my own hopes, dreams and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;passions. What I want for my life and all individuals with disabilities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is for us to be treated just like everyone else, an opportunity to live &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the American dream.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you. [Applause.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Thank you, Kayla. I have no doubt that you will achieve &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all that you set your heart and your mind to do.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. McKeon. Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Next we have Dr. Sheryl Lazarus. She is the director of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the TIES Center at which she conducts research and provides technical &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;assistance on educational change that will support the integration of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all students into inclusive learning settings. She addresses barriers &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to inclusion and works to build consensus and capacity among &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;practitioners and policymakers for sustainable inclusion. Dr. Lazarus &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has published more than 200 articles and reports, including on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;instruction and assessment of students with disabilities and English &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;learners with disabilities.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Please welcome Dr. Sheryl Lazarus.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Lazarus. Thank you. I would like to thank the Helsinki &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission for the opportunity to talk with you today. I'm the director &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of TIES Center. TIES is funded by the U.S. Department of Education and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is the national technical assistance center on inclusive practices and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;policies. Its purpose is to create sustainable changes to educational &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;systems so that students with the most significant cognitive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities can fully engage in the same instructional and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;noninstructional activities as their general education peers, while &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;being instructed in ways that meet their individual needs.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Expectations for students with disabilities in the United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;historically have been low, but several laws have encouraged a more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inclusive educational system. Beginning in 1975, Public Law 94-142 set &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a precedent for inclusive education with its least-restrictive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;environment clause. The Individuals With Disabilities Education Act of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;1997, which is often referred to as IDEA, says that students with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities have the right to learn the general curriculum based on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the same standards as their peers who do not have disabilities.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The most recent reauthorization of IDEA, as well as the 2015 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reauthorization of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act, also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;known as the Every Student Succeeds Act, or ESSA, states that education &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;must be designed to promote progress in the general education &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;curriculum.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    IDEA also mandates that students with disabilities be provided with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a free and appropriate public education which includes both special &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;education and related services, and that students are to be educated in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the least-restrictive environment. This creates a legal presumption &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that the general education setting is the default unless the child &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cannot be educated satisfactorily there, even after the necessary &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;support is provided.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    These laws and others provide the underpinnings of inclusive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;education in the United States, but the real heroes are the individuals &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with disabilities, their families, and advocates. They have exercised &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their rights, and sometimes had to push, shove, and hold the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;educational system to what the law required, though they must consider &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;themselves fortunate to be in a country in which individuals with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities and their families have the legal right to disagree with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;schools and the government.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Next, I'll discuss two critical components that support sustainable &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inclusion for all students. The first is raising expectations. It's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;important to note that students with the most significant cognitive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities are very diverse. For example, more students with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;significant cognitive disabilities can read than you might think. Two-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thirds are readers. Unfortunately, in the past, students with the most &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;significant cognitive disabilities often were only taught functional &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;skills such as how to care for themselves.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The curriculum started to change in the early 2000s when &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;accountability for academic performance for students with disabilities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was strengthened. As teachers introduced content similar to what peers &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;were learning, students with the most significant cognitive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities surprised us with what they could do. We heard over and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;over, who knew that these students could learn to read and do math and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;social studies and science?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    A second critical component that supports inclusion is what we call &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;communicative competence. Most students with the most significant &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cognitive disabilities communicate verbally just like everyone else. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;However, a few students communicate in other ways or show minimal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;response to stimuli. Students who lack a consistent mode of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;communication are often served in segregated educational settings &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because many teachers feel unprepared to support them. A key to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;successful inclusion and better outcomes is getting a communications &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;system in place, ideally by kindergarten or the early primary grades.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Here is an example which illustrates how a commitment to building &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;communicative competence helps enable students to thrive in inclusive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;contexts. Jaimar Fish is a middle school student in Danville, Kentucky. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;He has multiple disabilities. He did not have a consistent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;communication system. He gets along well with other students, but it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was difficult for him to develop relationships with them because he &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;could not communicate. His educational team addressed his &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;communications needs by first figuring out what he enjoyed and might &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want to communicate about. Then they gave him what we refer to as an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;augmentative and alternative communication device. In his case, this is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a simple motion-detection switch. It is activated by his smallest &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;movements and translates these movements into verbal language. Now &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Jaimar can respond to questions during math, reading, and other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;classes, talk with his friends about his likes and dislikes, and is one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the group.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In addition to raising expectations and communicative competence, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there are many other components of successful inclusion, such as high-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;quality, accessible instructional resources and providing training and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;professional development to all teachers so that they can confidently &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;instruct students with the most significant cognitive disabilities in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inclusive settings. Please see my written statement for additional &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;details.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Research has shown us the path to successfully educating all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;students, including those with the most significant cognitive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities. And the United States has taken some steps in that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;direction, but we need to have the commitment to make sustainable &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inclusion happen for all students. To improve outcomes for kids, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;behavior of adults needs to change. There needs to be shared &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;responsibility across educators for all students with all students &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;being held to high expectations. Together, we can create a future that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;supports the learning of all students in inclusive settings, which will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;lead to a future with communities where all individuals are valued &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;members.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Thank you, Dr. Lazarus. Thank you for the very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;practical suggestions that you've both developed and shared with us &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Next, we have John Lee Cronin. John is a 22-year-old man full of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;life and aspirations, who also happens to have Down syndrome. His love &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of colorful and fun socks and desire to perform meaningful work &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inspired him to found a new business, John's Crazy Socks. John is the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;chief happiness officer of John's Crazy Socks. John is a graduate of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Huntington High School and a Special Olympics athlete.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    John.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. J. Cronin. Good afternoon. My name is John Cronin and I am the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;co-founder and chief happiness officer of John's Crazy Socks. I come &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;here to stand up for people with Down syndrome and all people with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different abilities.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I have Down syndrome and Down syndrome never held me back. I am 22 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years old and I work hard every day to show the world that people with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Down syndrome are ready, willing, and able to work. Give us a chance &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and we can be successful.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    You may have heard about John's Crazy Socks. We have a mission to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;spread happiness. We have a good story, but we are a good business, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;too. We offer 2,300 different socks. We have shipped our socks to every &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;state and 80 different countries. This year, we will ship over 170,000 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;orders and earn over $6 million. I may be cute, but I run a serious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;business.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I started this business with my dad, Mark. It was my idea and I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;came up with the name. My dad--my dad--believed in me and he gave me a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;chance. I love my dad. I work hard every day. I love my business. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;let me tell you why I started John's Crazy Socks.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In the fall of 2016, I began my last year of school and needed to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;decide what I would do. When school ended, I had received a good &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;education at Huntington High School. I was healthy and ready to go. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;looked around, but I saw few choices and opportunities. I knew I could &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do more. I wanted a good job just like my brothers, Patrick and Jamie. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I decided to create my own--my own job. I told my dad that I wanted--I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wanted to go into business with him. I came up with the idea to sell &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;crazy socks because I had always worn and loved colorful and fun socks. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;We opened John's Crazy Socks in December 2016. We were entrepreneurs &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and we took a chance.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now everyone wears my socks, even the movie stars, prime ministers &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and presidents. We have created 35 jobs and 18 of my colleagues have a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different ability. We make films that have been seen over 4 million &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;times. We have raised over $135,000 for our charity partners. We are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;making John's Crazy Socks a success, and we owe it to our colleagues. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can be in my own business because I had a great teacher. I want to do a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shout-out to Dr. Erica Murphy-Jesson and Patricia Klee, my speech &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;teacher. I can lead my own business because I played Special Olympic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sports. I can lead my own business because my dad gave me a chance.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I want you to know what people like me can do. Give us a chance and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;watch what we can do. [Applause.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Thank you, John. I'm so glad that you took that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;business risk and had the courage to create your own opportunity &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because it is changing the world.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. J. Cronin. Thank you so much.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Next we have Mark X. Cronin, who is the co-founder of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;John's Crazy Socks along with John. He serves as the business's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;president and developed the social enterprise model for the business. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Mark spent much of his earlier career in the health care field leading &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;management and technology firms seeking to improve health care to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;poor and strengthen doctor-patient relations. He's also led political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;campaigns, published numerous short stories, and taught school.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mark.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. M. Cronin. Good afternoon. My name is Mark X. Cronin. As you've &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;heard, I'm John's father and partner in our business, John's Crazy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Socks.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We are here today to share some best practices, or at least our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;practices, of working with people with differing abilities. And what we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do in our business is simple: We want to show what's possible, we want &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to show what people with differing abilities can do if given a chance.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In John's Crazy Socks, we have built a social enterprise, so we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have a social mission and a business mission and they're indivisible. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Our social mission shows the world what people with differing abilities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can do and we give back by supporting and raising money for our charity &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;partners, like the National Down Syndrome Society. But we can only &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;succeed if we run a rigorous business. We compete with some of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;world's largest and best companies--Amazon, Walmart, Target--and we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;must match or beat what they do. For us to do good, we have to do well.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And that's why we hire people with differing abilities. Doing so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;serves our social mission, but it also serves our business mission. To &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;succeed, we have to provide great service. We do same-day shipping. We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;make sure our customers are happy. And we hire people with differing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;abilities because they help us run that great business. We do not hire &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;out of charity or altruism; we hire because it is good business.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    John told you that we have been fortunate enough to create 35 jobs &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with 18 held by people with differing abilities. Our starting pay is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;$12 an hour, $1 more than the New York State minimum wage. Our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;colleagues do not do minimum work, so we do not offer minimum pay.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Too often, people with differing abilities are not offered jobs or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they can only find work in sheltered workshops. They might be offered &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;positions out of pity or charity. Our business demonstrates that people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with differing abilities are just like the rest of us. They want &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;meaningful work where they can make a contribution and receive fair &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pay. After all, that's how we got started.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    When John was finishing school, healthy and ready to go, he did not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;see many choices and the entrepreneur in him said great, I'll create my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;own job. What does it take to hire people with differing abilities? We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;simply need to focus on what people can do, not what they cannot do. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Match the skills of the worker to the job.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We operate a pick-and-pack warehouse. Our warehouse workers--we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;call them sock wranglers--those with differing abilities and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;neurotypicals all pass a test to prove they can do the job. No charity, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just real work.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We have no government support. We have no special programs. Yes, we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;make accommodations for our differently abled, but we also make &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;accommodations for our neurotypical employees. We have created a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;unified workplace where people of differing abilities work side-by-side &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;neurotypical employees. And everyone benefits. We have better &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;productivity, better morale, better retention.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And yet, we're talking about best practices. Small accommodations &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can make a difference. We make sure everyone has an email address and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;knows how to use email, even if they're not working with a computer. We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;give everyone a business card as a symbol of their professionalism and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we watch as they give that out proudly to family and friends. We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;schedule regular social events outside of the office for all of our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;staff, like attending a chamber of commerce dinner. Having a job gives &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our employees standing in the community. And these are small &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;initiatives, but they have a big impact on our differently abled &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;population.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We have learned that hiring the differently abled gives us a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;competitive advantage. The United States and other industrialized &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nations are now facing shortages of workers, and yet we have this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;great, untapped, natural resource in the differently abled. Employers &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;will learn that those with differing abilities are an asset, not a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;liability, and the employers who learn this lesson the fastest will be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at an advantage and have greater success.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Our governments need to change, too. We need to see the differently &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;abled as full-fledged citizens, people able to contribute, not helpless &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;beings who need pity. We need laws that guarantee the same rights, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;including the same wages, as the neurotypical population. Here in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States, the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938--which is anything &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;but fair--allows employers to pay people with disabilities less than a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;minimum wage. Just because you can pay people less does not make it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;right. And it may make you some extra money, but it will leave you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;morally bankrupt. We are working with the National Down Syndrome &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Society to support passage of the TIME Act to afford all people a fair &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and minimum wage in the U.S. and elsewhere.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We have benefit programs that limit the ability of the disabled to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;work. Many of our colleagues who are differently abled can only work &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;part time. Why? Because if they work too many hours they will lose &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their Medicaid and they cannot afford to do so. Take Aliya, one of our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;colleagues who has a form of autism and works as a sock wrangler. Aliya &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;does a great job and would love to work 40 hours a week, but cannot &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because she cannot afford to lose her Medicaid. Don't we all want Aliya &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to work full time? Then why have laws that limit how much she can work?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And my son, John--he does not receive benefits yet; however, when &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;he needs those benefits in the future, he will need to choose between &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;his benefits and the equity in the company he created. Do we want to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prevent people from engaging in entrepreneurship?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    It is time to decouple the poor from the disabled in our means-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tested programs so that people with differing abilities can work full &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time and maximize their contributions to society. We want to encourage &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people to work and to pay taxes, so let's remove the disincentives.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In the end, our message is simple: It is good business to hire &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people with differing abilities. John created his own future when he &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;created John's Crazy Socks. We need more businesses that offer a future &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of meaningful work to all people. Employers here in the U.S. and around &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the world will come to learn that people with differing abilities make &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;great employees.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    John and I, we're a couple of simple guys from Long Island. We're a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;couple of knuckleheads selling socks. [Laughter.] We have no special &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;training. We have no special talents. If we can do this, anyone can. No &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;more excuses. Let's show the world what's possible.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. J. Cronin. I love you, dad.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Thank you, Mark. Thank you for your vision and creating &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a very successful business and social enterprise model for the rest of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;us to take note of and follow.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    You mentioned in your statement that the minimum wage floor does &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not apply to individuals with intellectual disabilities at this point. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And there is a bill that's been introduced called the TIME Act that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;will address that issue. Will that bill also address the issue of part-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time work, which you also mentioned, meaning individuals with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;intellectual disabilities who do not have the option to work full time &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and keep their benefits? Or will that be addressed by different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;legislation?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And, Sarah, please feel free to jump in.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. M. Cronin. Well, I mean, Sarah's more of the expert than me. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;The TIME Act will only prevent employers from paying people less than &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;minimum wage. To change that issue about the limits on what people can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;work, the ABLE Act changes some of that on the margin, but that's a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fundamental change that would have to--we would have to change the way &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we provide health insurance to working people who are disabled.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And the reason it's critical, Medicaid covers more than what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;traditional health insurance pays. So even if you have traditional &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;health insurance, there are some benefits that are crucial to many &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people with disabilities that they can only get through Medicaid.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But, Sarah, you know, you're the expert on this.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Weir. Sure. It's actually one of the main reasons we launched &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our Law Syndrome campaign last October. And Mark pointed this out in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;his testimony and it's exactly what we're trying to achieve with the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;work we do at the National Down Syndrome Society, and that's, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;essentially, we need to decouple the poor from the disabled in these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;means-tested programs.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We still have very obsolete income and asset limitations that exist &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as far back as the 1960s and 1970s that prevent individuals with Down &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;syndrome and other disabilities from keeping what they can earn and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;what they can save. ABLE was a huge step forward and it doesn't solve &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all of our issues, but it created a financial tool, a 529A or a 529 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ABLE account to allow individuals with disabilities to save their money &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in an ABLE account without putting benefits in jeopardy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, really, our focus on the employment side is to address the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;archaic, outdated income limitations. And we really feel at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;National Down Syndrome Society and with the partnership of businesses, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;like John's Crazy Socks, $800 billion corporations like Voya Financial, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from Main Street to Wall Street, the way to do that is to essentially &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;eliminate the ability to pay people with disabilities far below minimum &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wage. The TIME Act is one example. We know that there are other efforts &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;here on the Senate side to introduce new legislation to address this. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And then we're exploring opportunities to address this administratively &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with the administration and look at ways to make sure that no new 14(c) &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;certificate holders are created in a time when the supply and demand &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for sheltered workshops are the lowest it's been in, you know, recent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;decades.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So there's multiple ways to do this. But from an equality and a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;human rights perspective, I think there's nothing more discriminatory &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;than a 1938 provision that tells somebody who was born with Down &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;syndrome that you're far less valued in an employment setting than &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;anybody else.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Thank you. We'll have to probably take the additional &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bills up in the next Congress because we're coming to the end of this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Congress. But it sounds like there's some great work still to be done.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I wanted to ask John, what is a typical day like for you at John's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Crazy Socks?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. J. Cronin. When I get at work, I do--I handle all the--I do &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;videos. I do a bunch of videos, like I tell you new ones and call it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;John's networking. We're doing--we're doing ``Mad Science,'' a ``Mad &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Science'' show. [Inaudible.] And we're doing ``Cooking Up Happiness.'' &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I'm doing it with a guest with differing abilities on ``Cooking Up &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Happiness.''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. M. Cronin. So it's videos that you do.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. J. Cronin. I do a--there's a video. I do a--I'm pulling--I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pulling sock records. I help pick out socks, every order. And after &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that, I'm doing a video order or a video of that, and I write personal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;notes, personal videos, all that. I'm doing a big engagement right now. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I'm just having fun.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And my--and mostly I like making home deliveries. If fun things are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;going on--and I--[inaudible]--candy, and thinking of it is something &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sweet.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Thank you, John. It sounds like you have a very busy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;day doing public relations, merchandising and shipping for the socks.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And do you typically work part time, full time, does it vary from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;week to week depending on how busy things are?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. J. Cronin. Actually, I'm going to tell you I have work when I--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;when I--I'm an entrepreneur, me and my dad. When we get up, we get in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the office around 9. And some nights--some nights, around 6, 7 at &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;night. We work--me and my dad work long hours. And I tell you that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because we're going two more years. We're going on vacation in two more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years. We're entrepreneurs. [Laughter.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. M. Cronin. So we work hard, huh?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. J. Cronin. We work very hard and so it's very appreciated.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. M. Cronin. But you like it?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. J. Cronin. But, yes, I like it. [Laughter.] Yes.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Thank you, John.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Kayla, I had a question for you. You mentioned in your testimony &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that ``I am who I am today in large part because I was included with my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;peers throughout my childhood.''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. McKeon. Correct.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. And I'm wondering, what are your best memories of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inclusion during your childhood? And what are also your memories of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;times when you wish you had been included more in your childhood?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. McKeon. You're making me think . . . It's been a while. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;remember being in a classroom with a special education teacher and I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;didn't have a one-on-one yet. But I will probably get a one-on-one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;after I--sorry to say this--but I went into the woods. I was--I behaved &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;like I shouldn't when I was little. And so I have this bad memory, but &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it was part to get a one-on-one that helped me gain independence, it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;helped me build the skills I needed to get up to where everybody else &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And back then, I was in high school and I still had this one-on-one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who had to hold my hand in the hallways. I said, um, no, thank you, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we're going backward, I don't want to backpedal, I'm independent and I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can cross a hallway on my own. Well, they thought I needed that extra &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;help where I did not need it, but I needed the help in the classroom &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;where they were able to break down the instructions, make it easier for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;me to learn. And doing things more hands-on helped me greatly. So I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not saying it was a bad memory, but it helped get that one-on-one that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I needed to propel me to work harder.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And one of my one-on-ones was Ms. Powers who helped me to be more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;independent and got me into a club in school that I really enjoyed. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;again, it helped with the independence.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Sounds like you had the extra support when you needed &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it, but also the freedom to say I can stand on my own two feet now, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thank you, when you didn't need it. So I'm glad to hear that.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Lazarus, I wanted to dig deeper into how teachers can be better &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prepared to instruct students with the most significant cognitive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities when they're trying to create an inclusive setting and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;student may need quite a bit of extra support.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Lazarus. What we've found is that the students, they understand &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;each other. They want to work together, they want to be friends, they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want to be colleagues. But it's often the adults who can get in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;way. And teachers all, I truly believe, every single teacher out there &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wants what is best for students. And they also want what they--they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want to feel like they are successful as teachers. And when they lack &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the skills to instruct some of their students, then they start &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thinking, well, maybe this isn't a good fit for this child.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So what we really need is to create schools where all teachers have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the confidence that they can successfully instruct all students. And so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to get this, it involves teacher prep programs where all educators have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the opportunity to instruct, learn how to instruct the widest range of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;students, the development of instructional materials and resources that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are easy to use and can be used with students across the range of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;students.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We also need to think about administrators and how they might &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;support inclusion and the importance of all people in the school taking &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;responsibility for the learning of all students. Too often we have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;silos that the special educator does this and the general educator does &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that, and if we can combine where everyone in the school cares about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all students, then we will have much better places.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Thank you, Dr. Lazarus.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Before we run out of time, I want to make sure that we leave some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time for any questions from the audience or online as the case may be.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'll give you a moment to think while I follow up with Dr. Lazarus.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    How does being included in regular classrooms with peers without &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities help prepare students for better quality outcomes for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;adult life? Why is this a key goal?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Lazarus. The early inclusion supports later inclusion. Early &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;segregation almost ensures that there will be segregation later in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;life. That's so important to think about, what do we want in our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;communities, in our country? And when we think about our schools are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;preparing our future corporate leaders, our future civic leaders, our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;faith leaders, and if those individuals are comfortable with--familiar &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with--individuals who have a wide variety of characteristics, whether &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it be ethnic diversity, English learners or individuals with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;significant cognitive disabilities, we are creating communities that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;value all individuals. And I just see inclusion right from the get-go &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as being a really important part of that.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. M. Cronin. If I could add to that--you know, at a personal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;level and in our business. So John is the youngest of three sons. John &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;benefited from his older brothers leading him and taking care of him. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;But his older brothers benefited from John and they are better people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because of it. And in our workplace--so we have this unified workplace. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;We see minor miracles every day with our differently abled. But our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;neurotypical staff, they're better off, they're happier. And that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;diversity that we bring benefits the business. So everyone--it's not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that inclusion doesn't just benefit the differently abled, it benefits &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;everybody.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Lazarus. And I totally agree with Mark. That is just so, so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;true.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Weir. Well, and I echo both what Dr. Lazarus and Mark said. But &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I think it comes down to the treatment of people with disabilities. It &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;should be no different than anyone else. The way and the reason we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fight for inclusion for students with Down syndrome is so they have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;access to the general curriculum, they have access to a great &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;education. And the expectation when they graduate from high school or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;college needs to be employment, just like everyone else.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. We have run out of time, unless there's a burning &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;question from the audience.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And if not, I will thank the panelists for bringing us both &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tangible examples as well as the challenges of creating a truly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inclusive society. I am so encouraged by the success that you are, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Kayla, the success that you are, John, and the success that you are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;encouraging amongst your peers and urging others in your life to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;achieve by changing laws that are holding you back. And so I thank you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for being here today. Thank you for your insights.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I hope that everyone in the audience will join me in thanking &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;them. [Applause.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. McKeon. And thank you for having all of us. We very much &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;appreciate it.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Parker. Our pleasure.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    [Whereupon, at 4:36 p.m., the briefing ended.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                            A P P E N D I X &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    =======================================================================&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Good afternoon. My name is Sara Hart Weir, and I am the President &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and CEO of the world's largest Down syndrome advocacy organization--the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;National Down Syndrome Society (NDSS).&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    On behalf of NDSS, the leading human rights organization for all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals with Down syndrome, it is an honor to sit at this table &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;(today) to present to the Helsinki Commission with Dr. Lazarus, one of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our favorite NDSS #DSWORKS&amp;#4; partners, Mark and John Cronin, from John's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Crazy Socks and of course, my esteemed colleague, Kayla McKeon.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    At NDSS, we believe if you're not at the table, you're on the menu. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I, personally, want to thank the Helsinki Commission, for today's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;imperative discussion and lending a critical voice to a population, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;even in our great nation, the United States of America, and still in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;2018, that is far more discriminated against more than any other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;community.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Today's topic--``A TRULY INCLUSIVE SOCIETY: ENCOURAGING THE ABILITY &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;IN DISABILITY'' is something we live and breathe at the National Down &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Syndrome Society--as we strive to achieve equality for all Americans &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with Down syndrome in the U.S.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Our great nation's first mottos--``E Pluribus Unum''--is embedded &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in almost every fabric of our country's rich history. The phrase is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;used on our currency, the seal of the President, Vice President, United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States Congress, of the United States House of Representatives, of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States Senate and on the seal of the United States Supreme &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Court. It is cemented in our country's rich history, culture and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;values--life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness--e pluribus unum &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;comes from the Latin phrase meaning ``OUT of many, ONE.''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    From this belief, springs a unifying purpose for our nation. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Equality. Unfortunately, in the United States, and around the world &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people with Down syndrome and other disabilities are not treated as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;one.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    At NDSS, we believe no matter your differences or abilities you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;should have a fair shot at the American Dream--and we work hard each &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and every day to ensure America's motto is upheld for people with Down &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;syndrome and that ONE truly means ONE.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    At NDSS, \1/4\ of our staff have Down syndrome and work across all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of our programs and departments. Not a single decision within our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organization is made without the input of our self-advocates. At NDSS, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our programs, including:&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt;  our National Advocacy and Public Policy Center&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt;  our #DSWORKS&amp;#4; Employment Program--our Health Promotion &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Resources Program&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    These programs are dedicated to advancing proactive policies and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;providing invaluable resources on issues across the lifespan, from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;birth to old age, across five critical pillars: healthcare and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;research, education, employment, community integration and economic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;self-sufficiency.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Next year, we will celebrate NDSS' 40th anniversary. During this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time, one of the most important advancements for individuals with Down &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;syndrome has been an increased access to and advancements in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;healthcare. The result is a dramatic increase in life expectancy of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals with Down syndrome from 25 years old in 1983, \1\ to about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;60 years old today \2\--all a result of early detection of co-occurring &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conditions like congenital heart defects, quality dental care and of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;course, inclusion.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;---------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;\1\  https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4445685/&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;\2\  https://academic.oup.com/eurpub/article/17/2/221/435114&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;---------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    From its origins in 1979, NDSS has been involved in so many federal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and state advocacy as well as judicial efforts that have helped &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals with all disabilities become more included in society:&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt;  The Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (Public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Law 101-476), or ``IDEA'' that guarantees students with disabilities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their right to be educated alongside their peers in their neighborhood &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;school;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt;  The Americans with Disabilities Act (Public Law 101-336), &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;or ``ADA,'' that prohibits discrimination against individuals with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities in all areas of public life and the subsequent Olmstead &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Supreme Court decision that requires public agencies to provide &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;services in the most integrated settings possible;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt;  The shutdown of the Willowbrook Institution in New York &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that was brought to the forefront of the public's conscious; and&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt;  The landmark passage of the Stephen Beck Jr., Achieving a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Better Life Experience Act (Public Law 113-295), best known as the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;``ABLE Act,'' that allows individuals with disabilities to save money &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;without it affecting their benefits.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    These accomplishments and milestones were vital to ensure &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals with disabilities have access and adequate supports to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;basic liberties those without disabilities enjoy--education, community &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;integration, housing, employment and savings.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Despite these significant advancements, we have a long way to go. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;People with Down syndrome are still held back and confined to laws that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;were put in place as long ago as the 1930's--a time where the life &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;expectancy rate was very, very low, a time when we were still &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;institutionalizing people with Down syndrome and perceptions of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people with Down syndrome were not even realized.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Today:&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt;  Individuals with disabilities still do not have access to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;marriage equality&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt;  Individuals with disabilities cannot maintain their vital &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;benefits while working, despite being ready, willing and able to work&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt;  Though we fought for IDEA, many students still do not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have access to the inclusive education to which they are entitled and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is the basis of a life of inclusion&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt;  Many cannot choose where they want to live as housing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;options for individuals with Intellectual and Developmental &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Disabilities especially are extremely limited&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    &amp;lt;bullet&amp;gt;  Many are still not economically self-sufficient despite &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ABLE accounts being open to qualifying individuals across the nation&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Outrageously, many are still not getting paid the minimum wage that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all other Americans are entitled to. Under Section 14(c) of the Fair &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Labor Standards Act (of 1938), businesses can obtain a special wage &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;certificate from the Department of Labor to pay individuals with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities below minimum wage, sometimes as little as thirty cents an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hour--the only group of people it is still legal to pay below minimum &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wage. For purposes of conscious, inclusion and equality, this is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;unacceptable.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Last year, NDSS launched our campaign to end #LawSyndrome to draw &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;attention to these issues and advocate for change. Down syndrome &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;doesn't hold anyone back but rather these antiquated laws prevent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals from fulfilling their potential. We will not stop until &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;every single American with Down syndrome has the same rights as every &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;other American.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    One of my proudest accomplishments at NDSS is ensuring that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals with Down syndrome are not only part of our incredible team &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and organization, but they are at every table where key decisions about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their future are made. When you have a seat at the table, you have a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;say in the decisions that are made and when it's your table, you make &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the decisions--this is how we end #LawSyndrome. I am honored to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;introduce my colleague who has not only earned a seat the table--she &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;owns the table and Capitol Hill.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Good afternoon, everyone. To echo Sara's words, thank you to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Allison and the Helsinki Commission for inviting me to speak.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My name is Kayla McKeon and I am the Manager of Grassroots Advocacy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at the National Down Syndrome Society. I am the first registered &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;lobbyist who just happens to have Down syndrome. Down syndrome doesn't &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;define me, Kayla, and it definitely does not stop me. What limits me &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and my fellow advocates and friends with Down syndrome and other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disabilities across our great country is Law Syndrome.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    As Sara mentioned, Law Syndrome is a series of VERY old laws that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;were passed when I wouldn't have lived past my adolescence or even my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;childhood, and if I did, I would not have left the hospital with my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;parents because people with Down syndrome were still being &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;institutionalized. These laws were put in place when the social &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;acceptance of individuals with disabilities was at an all-time low.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I was lucky in my upbringing in Syracuse, New York. When I was 18 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;months old, my parents enrolled me in an early education program. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;progressed through school alongside my classmates and graduated at age &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;18. As soon as inclusive education became possible, I was always in an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inclusive setting. I won't deny there were bumps and stumbling blocks &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;along the way, but my parents always thought it was best for me to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;included with my classmates and placed in settings that challenged me &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to reach my highest potential. There were times when they pushed me, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;but it was always because they knew I could succeed.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I earned awards in eighth and ninth grade for character, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;commitment, courage, English and math. My final grade for algebra was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the 90's and I got a 93 on my math regents' exam. If you are from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;New York, you know how tough that was.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Later, an agency known as Vocational &amp;amp; Educational Services for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Individuals with Disabilities, or VESID, and my high school set up a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;program for me to take an office technology program. It was a six-month &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;certification program for adults. They arranged the program for me to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;go through it twice. I passed the program, earned the certificate and, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as a result, I am pretty fast on a keyboard. I was even the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;commencement speaker.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I also attended Onondaga Community College taking some non-credit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;courses, but I thought to myself, it doesn't make sense that I'm doing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all the work without earning any credits! But I liked the classes, so I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;began taking one course per semester for credit. I can happily say I am &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;now more than halfway to earning my associate's degree. I start back up &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;later this month. I love taking classes with my peers. Many of my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;classmates are a little bit younger than me now, but so what! I started &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;advocating a number of years ago. I started educating others who are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;differently abled by going to elementary schools, then moved on to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;middle schools, colleges and the school of nursing. I try to motivate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;them to do the best that they can do. My message to kids in school is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to persevere. I am who I am today in large part because I was included &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with my peers throughout my childhood.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    One day in Syracuse, I met John Katko at a baseball game. He was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;running for the U.S. House of Representatives. He handed me his &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;business card so I handed him mine. He called me later and said if he &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was elected he wanted me to come and work for him. When he won, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;became an intern in his Syracuse office. I represented him at different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;events and did office work. In June of last year, he asked me to go &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with him to a disability conference in Washington. We didn't realize at &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the time it was with the National Down Syndrome Society. It was there &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at the end of the meeting that Sara Hart Weir, our President and CEO of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;NDSS, offered me the job of Manager of Grassroots Advocacy. I started &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;last October.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    With my position as the first registered lobbyist with Down &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;syndrome, I go to Capitol Hill and speak to many Members of Congress &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and their staff on issues that are important to me. I helped lobby to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pass the original ABLE Act as a volunteer for NDSS and now the ABLE to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Work Act and the ABLE Financial Planning Act as a lobbyist. These laws &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;allow me and my friends who are differently-abled to have savings &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;accounts and meaningful employment without giving up our benefits.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We are now tirelessly working on ending #LawSyndrome. Down syndrome &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;doesn't stop us. It never stopped us. It is just some old, antiquated &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;laws that hold us back. One example is the 80-year-old provision within &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Fair Labor Standards Act known as Section 14(c) that Sara &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mentioned. People like me are still getting paid cents an hour, while &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;other individuals performing the same tasks are paid at least minimum &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wage. These issues segregate us from the rest of society. They show we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are still viewed as ``less than.'' Society is ready to move past these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;laws. When will the government catch up?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We have a long way to go for individuals with Down syndrome to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fully included in society. To me, having Down syndrome is who I am but &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it has never stopped me for achieving my own hopes, dreams and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;passions. What I want for my life and all individuals with disabilities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is for us all to be treated just like everyone else. I want to live the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;American Dream.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Good afternoon. My name is John Cronin, and I am the co-founder and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Chief Happiness Officer of John's Crazy Socks. I come here to stand up &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for people with Down syndrome and all people with differing abilities.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I have Down syndrome and Down syndrome never holds me back. I am &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;22-years old and work hard every day to show the world that people with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Down syndrome are ready, willing and able to work. Give us a chance and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we can be successful.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    You may have heard about John's Crazy Socks. We have a mission to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;spread happiness. We have a good story, but we are a good business too. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;We offer 2,300 different socks. We have shipped our socks to every &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;state and 80 different countries. This year we will ship over 170,000 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;orders and earn over $6 million. I may be cute, but I run a serious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;business.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I started this business with my dad, Mark. It was my idea and I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;came up with the name. My Dad believed in me and gave me a chance. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;love my Dad. I work hard every day. I love my business.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Let me tell you why I started John's Crazy Socks. In the fall of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;2016, I began my last year of school. I needed to decide what I would &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do when school ended. I had received a good education at Huntington &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;High School. I was healthy and ready to go. I looked around but saw few &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;choices and opportunities. I knew I could do more. I wanted a good job &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just like my brothers Patrick and Jamie.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I decided to create my own job. I told my dad that I wanted to go &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;into business with him. I came up with the idea to sell crazy socks &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because I had always worn and loved colorful and fun socks. We opened &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;John's Crazy Socks in December 2016. We were entrepreneurs and we took &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a chance. Now, everyone wears my socks, even movie stars, Prime &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Ministers and Presidents.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We have created 35 jobs and 18 of my colleagues have a differing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ability. We make videos that have been seen over 4 million times. We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have raised over $150,000 for our charity partners. We are making &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;John's Crazy Socks a success and we owe it to our colleagues.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I can lead my own business because I had great teachers. I want to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shout out to Dr. Erica Murphy-Jessen and Patricia Klee, my speech &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;teacher. I can lead my own business because I played Special Olympics &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sports. I can lead my own business because my Dad gave me a chance.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I want you to know what people like me can do. Give us a chance and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;watch what we can do.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Good afternoon. My name is Mark X. Cronin and I am John's father &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and partner in John's Crazy Socks. We work to show what is possible, we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;work to show what people with a differing ability can do if given a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;chance.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In John's Crazy Socks, we have built a social enterprise; we have a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;social and a business mission and they are indivisible. Our social &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mission shows the world what people with a differing ability can do and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we give back by supporting and raising money for our charity partners. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;But we can only succeed if we run a rigorous business. We compete with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;some of the largest and best companies in the world--Amazon, Wal-mart &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Target--and we must match or beat what they offer. To do good, we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have to do well.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Hiring people with differing abilities serves our social mission, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;but it also serves our business mission. To succeed, we must provide &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;great service, so we do same day shipping and that makes our customers &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;happy. We hire people with differing abilities because they help us &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fulfill our mission. We do not hire people out of charity or altruism. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;We hire because it is good for business.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    John told you that we have been fortunate enough to create 35 jobs &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with 18 held by people with differing abilities. Our starting pay is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;$12 per hour, $1 more than the New York State minimum wage. Our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;colleagues do not do minimum work, so we do not offer minimum pay. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sad reality is that we could pay less, much less, and many of our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;workers and their families would still welcome the job because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;meaningful work is so scarce. But that would be wrong. Taking advantage &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of vulnerable workers may put money in the bank, but it would be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;morally bankrupt.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Too often, people with differing abilities are not offered jobs or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they can only find work in sheltered workshops. They might be offered &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;positions out of pity or charity. Our business demonstrates that people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with differing abilities are just like the rest of us: they want &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;meaningful work where they can make a contribution and receive fair &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pay.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    What does it take to hire people with differing abilities? We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;simply need to focus on what people can do, not what they cannot do. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Match the skills of the worker to the job. We operate a pick and pack &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;warehouse. Our warehouse workers--those with differing abilities and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;neuro-typical--all pass a test to prove they can do the job. No &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;charity, just real work.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We have no government support and no special programs. Yes, we make &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;accommodations for our differing abled, but we also make accommodations &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for our neuro-typical employees. We have created a unified workplace &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;where people of differing abilities work side-by-side with neuro-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;typical employees. And everyone benefits. We have better productivity, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;better morale and better retention.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And yet small accommodations can make a big difference. We make &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sure everyone has an email address and knows how to use email. We give &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;everyone a business card as a symbol of their professionalism and watch &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as they proudly give them out to family and friends. And we schedule &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regular social events outside the office for all of our staff like &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;attending a Chamber of Commerce dinner. Having a job gives our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;employees standing it the community. These are small initiatives, but &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they have a big impact on our differing abled population.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We have learned that hiring the differently abled gives us a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;competitive advantage. The United States and other nations are now &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;facing shortages of workers, and yet we have a great untapped natural &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resource in the differently abled. Employers will learn that those with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;differing abilities are an asset, not a liability. And the employers &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who learn this lesson the fastest, will be at an advantage and find &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;greater success.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Our governments need to make changes too. We need to see the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;differently abled as full-fledged citizens, people able to contribute, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not helpless beings who need pity. We need laws that guarantee the same &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rights--including the same wages--as the neuro-typical population. Here &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the U.S., the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 allows employers to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pay the people with disabilities less than a minimum wage. We are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;working with the National Down Syndrome Society to support passage of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the TIME Act to afford all people a fair, minimum wage.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In the U.S. and elsewhere, we have benefits programs that limit the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ability of the disabled to work. Our colleagues with disabilities work &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;part-time. Why? Because if they work too many hours, they will lose &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their Medicaid and they cannot afford to do so. Take Aliya, who has a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;form of autism and works as a Sock Wrangler. Aliya does a great job and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would love to work 40 hours per week but cannot because she cannot &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;afford to lose her Medicaid. Don't we all want Aliya to work full-time? &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Then why have laws that limit how much she can work?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And my son John, he does not receive benefits yet. However, when he &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;needs those benefits in the future, he will need to choose between his &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;benefits and equity in the company that he has created. Do we want to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prevent people from engaging in entrepreneurship?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    It is time to decouple the poor from the disabled in our means-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tested programs so that people with differing abilities can work full-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time and maximize their contributions to society. We want to encourage &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people to work and to pay taxes, so let's remove the disincentives to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;work.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In the end, our message is simple. It is good business to hire &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people with differing abilities. John created his own future when he &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;created John's Crazy Socks. We need more businesses that offer a future &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of meaningful work to all people. Employers here in the U.S. and around &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the world will come to learn that people with differing abilities make &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;great employees.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    John and I are a couple of simple guys from Long Island, a couple &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of knuckleheads selling socks. We have no special training and no &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;special talents. If we can do this, anyone can. No more excuses. Let's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;show the world what is possible.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                    [all]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            This is an official publication of the Commission on&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                    Security and Cooperation in Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  This publication is intended to document&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  developments and trends in participating&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  States of the Organization for Security&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                     and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE).&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;           All Commission publications may be freely reproduced,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            in any form, with appropriate credit. The Commission&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            encourages the widest possible dissemination of its&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               publications.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      www.csce.gov       @HelsinkiComm&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 The Commission's Web site provides access&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 to the latest press releases and reports,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                as well as hearings and briefings. Using the&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;         Commission's electronic subscription service, readers are&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            able to receive press releases, articles, and other&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          materials by topic or countries of particular interest.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                          Please subscribe today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;&amp;lt;/pre&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
</intro>
</Hearing>
