<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="30829">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;115th Congress }                            Printed for the use of the             &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;2nd Session    }      Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe                       &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;======================================================================&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	        Transatlantic Relations in Flux&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                           July 18, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                           Briefing of the&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         Washington: 2019&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;      Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  234 Ford House Office Building                                               &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   Washington, DC 20515&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      202-225-1901&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   csce@mail.house.gov&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   http://www.csce.gov&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                     @HelsinkiComm&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            Legislative Branch Commissioners&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;              HOUSE				SENATE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;CHRISTOPHER H. SMITH, New Jersey 	ROGER WICKER, Mississippi,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Co-Chairman			  Chairman&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ALCEE L. HASTINGS, Florida		BENJAMIN L. CARDIN. Maryland&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ROBERT B. ADERHOLT, Alabama		JOHN BOOZMAN, Arkansas&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;MICHAEL C. BURGESS, Texas		CORY GARDNER, Colorado&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;STEVE COHEN, Tennessee			MARCO RUBIO, Florida&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;RICHARD HUDSON, North Carolina		JEANNE SHAHEEN, New Hampshire&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;RANDY HULTGREN, Illinois		THOM TILLIS, North Carolina&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;SHEILA JACKSON LEE, Texas		TOM UDALL, New Mexico&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;GWEN MOORE, Wisconsin			SHELDON WHITEHOUSE, Rhode Island&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;               Executive Branch Commissioners&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                    DEPARTMENT OF STATE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  DEPARTMENT OF COMMERCE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                            [II]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ABOUT THE ORGANIZATION FOR SECURITY AND COOPERATION IN EUROPE               &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;The Helsinki process, formally titled the Conference on Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe, traces its origin to the signing of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Helsinki Final Act in Finland on August 1, 1975, by the leaders of 33 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European countries, the United States and Canada. As of January 1, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;1995, the Helsinki process was renamed the Organization for Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe [OSCE]. The membership of the OSCE has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;expanded to 56 participating States, reflecting the breakup of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Soviet Union, Czechoslovakia, and Yugoslavia.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The OSCE Secretariat is in Vienna, Austria, where weekly meetings &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the participating States' permanent representatives are held. In &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;addition, specialized seminars and meetings are convened in various &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;locations. Periodic consultations are held among Senior Officials, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Ministers and Heads of State or Government.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Although the OSCE continues to engage in standard setting in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fields of military security, economic and environmental cooperation, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and human rights and humanitarian concerns, the Organization is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;primarily focused on initiatives designed to prevent, manage and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resolve conflict within and among the participating States. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Organization deploys numerous missions and field activities located in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Southeastern and Eastern Europe, the Caucasus, and Central Asia. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;website of the OSCE is: &amp;lt;www.osce.org&amp;gt;.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ABOUT THE COMMISSION ON SECURITY AND COOPERATION IN EUROPE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, also known as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Helsinki Commission, is a U.S. Government agency created in 1976 to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;monitor and encourage compliance by the participating States with their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;OSCE commitments, with a particular emphasis on human rights.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission consists of nine members from the United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Senate, nine members from the House of Representatives, and one member &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;each from the Departments of State, Defense and Commerce. The positions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Chair and Co-Chair rotate between the Senate and House every two &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years, when a new Congress convenes. A professional staff assists the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commissioners in their work.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In fulfilling its mandate, the Commission gathers and disseminates &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relevant information to the U.S. Congress and the public by convening &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hearings, issuing reports that reflect the views of Members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission and/or its staff, and providing details about the activities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the Helsinki process and developments in OSCE participating States.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission also contributes to the formulation and execution of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.S. policy regarding the OSCE, including through Member and staff &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participation on U.S. Delegations to OSCE meetings. Members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission have regular contact with parliamentarians, government &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;officials, representatives of non-governmental organizations, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;private individuals from participating States. The website of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission is: &amp;lt;www.csce.gov&amp;gt;.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;			       [III]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                    Transatlantic Relations in Flux&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                             July 18, 2018                             &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                                                                               Page&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               PARTICIPANTS&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Dr. Mischa E. Thompson, Senior Policy Advisor, Commission on Security and Cooperation&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in Europe  ..................................................................................... 1&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;MEP Claude Moraes (UK), Chair, European Parliament Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Home Affairs, Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats ............................. 2&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;MEP Michal Boni (Poland), European People&amp;#65533;s Party .............................................. 3&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;MEP Nathalie Griesbeck (France), Chair, European Parliament Special Committee on Terrorism,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Alliance of Liberals and Democrats ............................................................. 4                          &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                 (iv)&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                Transatlantic Relations in Flux&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              ----------                              &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                             July 18, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The briefing was held at 10:00 a.m. in Room 216, Hart Senate Office &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Building, Washington, DC, Dr. Mischa E. Thompson, Senior Policy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Advisor, Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, presiding.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Panelists present: Dr. Mischa E. Thompson, Senior Policy Advisor, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe; MEP Claude Moraes &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;(UK), Chair, European Parliament Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Home Affairs, Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats; MEP &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Michal Boni (Poland), European People's Party; and MEP Nathalie &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Griesbeck (France), Chair, European Parliament Special Committee on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Terrorism, Alliance of Liberals and Democrats.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Thompson. Good morning. My name is Dr. Mischa Thompson, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;welcome to ``Transatlantic Relations in Flux,'' a briefing on the U.S.-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;EU relationship hosted by the U.S. Commission on Security and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Cooperation in Europe, also known as the Helsinki Commission. For those &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of who you may not know, the Helsinki Commission is an independent U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Government agency focused on human rights, economics, and security in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the 57 North American and European countries that make up the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe, or the OSCE. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;commission is bicameral and bipartisan, and comprised of members of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Congress and the executive branch, including our U.S. State Department. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;More on our commission can be found at www.csce.gov. You can also find &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;us on Facebook and on Twitter at @HelsinkiComm.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We are so fortunate today to be joined by three members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;delegation from the European Parliament's Civil Liberties, Justice, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Home Affairs Committee, visiting Washington, DC to attend the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Transatlantic Policy Network's acclaimed Transatlantic Week. We thank &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Jorn Fleck and his team for helping to facilitate today's briefing, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are only sorry that they cannot be with us today as they are also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;currently hosting an event. We also thank Antoine Rippel and Holger &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Benzig for helping us to arrange today's event so quickly.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think today's event couldn't be more timely, in that it's simply &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;taking place on the heels of our president's European travel and ahead &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of meetings planned for July 25th with the head of the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission, Jean-Claude Juncker, who will travel to Washington, DC to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;meet with our president. You can find the bios of today's panelists, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who are all members of the European Parliament, or MEPs, in the blue &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;folders and online. Given that we have about an hour, I will begin by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;asking a few questions, after which we will have time for questions and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;discussion from the audience, including those with us online. Given &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that we are also taping this briefing, I ask everyone to please speak &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;directly into their microphones. And for those of you here on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;panel, you will need to press the red button to talk.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And with that, I will begin by introducing you. To my right we have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;member of the European Parliament Claude Moraes of the United Kingdom, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who's also chair of the European Parliament Committee on Civil &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Liberties, Justice, and Home Affairs, and a member of the Progressive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Alliance of Socialists and Democrats. To my left we have MEP Michal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Boni of Poland, a member of the Civil Liberties and Constitutional &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Affairs Committees, as well as vice chair of the EU-Moldova &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Parliamentary Association Committee, and member of the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;People's Party. Further to my left we have MEP Nathalie Griesbeck of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;France, chair of the European Parliament's Special Committee on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Terrorism and member of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And so with that, I will actually turn to MEP Moraes and just ask &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;if you can start by telling us why you're here in Washington right now, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;what is the purpose of your delegation's visit, who are you meeting &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with, and what is it you hope to accomplish.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Moraes. Okay, thank you very much, Mischa, and thank you to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Helsinki Commission for this kind invitation. I should remind people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also that you in the Helsinki Commission have regularly come to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Brussels, to the European Parliament. So this is a vehicle for really &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;good cooperation between the European Parliament and the institutions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;here between you and Congress. So it's great to be here.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Maybe first to say that a lot of interesting things happened in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Helsinki. And maybe one of the best things was the creation of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Helsinki Commission. And one of the reasons we're here is to do what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was in the founding principles and the signature in 1975, which is to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;strengthen relationships between the European Union and the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States. Within that very abstract statement lies a program for us which &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is very specific and very focused. And it represents the difference &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;between perhaps what would have been a 1975 program, when many of you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would not have been born--some would--and that would be the advances in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;what cooperation means.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So, our specific thematic issues include data transfers both in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;commercial and security areas. Privacy Shield, for example, the success &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Safe Harbor, the whole issue of the CLOUD Act and how it coalesces &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with the Umbrella Agreement, these very major international agreements &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in data transfers--the wider area, as my colleague Nathalie Griesbeck &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;will talk about, the whole area of security cooperation and data &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transfers to make our two continents safer from terrorist attacks. So &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the issue of counterterrorism cooperation, and cybersecurity, which has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;taken on an extraordinarily new vista, which is now not just about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;protecting our critical infrastructure but also protecting our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;democracy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We've seen the Cambridge Analytica crisis. And it's about ensuring &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that we protect our democracies, our elections from interference, as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we've seen from Russia, and to ensure that in order to do that we are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cooperating, and we understand what the issues are. So these are some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the issues that our committee in particular will be and have been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;discussing with our counterparts and their detailed passenger name &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;records, actual international agreements. So we're highly focused and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we're regular in visiting. And we hope to make progress in all of these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;areas.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Thompson. Now, we titled this briefing ``Transatlantic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Relations in Flux.'' And there's been a lot of recent focus, rightly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;so, on the flux, or all of the changes that have been taking place in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the U.S. approach to relations with Europe. However, I'd like to take a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;step back today and think about where it is we would ideally like to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;see the transatlantic relationship. So if we were to look into the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;future in a decade or two, where is it we would actually like for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transatlantic relations to be? And are we currently on the path to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;getting there? And I'll actually turn to MEP Boni to ask your thoughts &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on where it is you would ideally see the transatlantic relationship in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;10 years.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Boni. First of all, thank you very much for the invitation. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was a student in 1975 when the Helsinki conference occurred. And after &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that, it was kind of an opening in some countries. In 1976, in my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;country, the committee for defending workers was established. And as a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;student, I was involved in dissemination and propagation of the first &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;underground newspapers--it was the beginning of our fight for freedom. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;So, from that time to today, when the Helsinki Commission in Warsaw, in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Poland, is very active defending democracy and freedom, I see the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Helsinki idea, the Helsinki Commission as one of the important &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;movements in defending democracy all over the world.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And of course, we need transatlantic relations if we want to have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and to develop the opportunity to defend the liberal democracy which, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hope, is the core of Western values. And I think also the transatlantic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;values. So this is one key point. Second, I think that this is a chance &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to establish the future of transatlantic competitive advantages, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;especially in the digital field. And we need to work on it. And also, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this is a possibility in transatlantic relations to create positive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reference points for global development in many areas. Global &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;development means economic development, but it also means ensuring that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;democracy is functioning. It's one of the key issues.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And of course, when I'm looking at that time frame I need to define &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;some obstacles. It is difficult to develop future-oriented cooperation &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;when we are starting trade wars as it was in the 19th century--not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;20th, 19th century. It is difficult to develop policy, to develop &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;policy protection and create a good global reference point for privacy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;protection when we are starting to consider how many threats and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;concerns the CLOUD Act, passed in the U.S., is bringing. It is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;difficult to take common responsibility for global development when the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.S. authorities decide to withdraw the signature from the Paris &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Agreement, so it means that there is no possibility to cooperate for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;saving the globe against the environmental collapse.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And it is difficult to build a common defense strategy in a time in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which the EU is taking a new responsibility for defense, when EU &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;partners are humiliated by the president of the United States, as it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was last week in the NATO summit in Brussels. And it is difficult to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;develop transatlantic relations without political stability, rather &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with strong uncertainty. We need to come back to the path of stability &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of those relations. But there are problems not only on the U.S. side. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;There are also many problems on our European side.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'm from Poland, and I'm living in a country in which the ruling &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;party is undermining the democracy, the freedoms, and also the rule of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;law and the independence of the judicial system. Now we are fighting &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for the Supreme Court and keeping the Supreme Court independent. It's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not so easy to say that we will win this battle. The same situation is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in Hungary. One month ago, Hungary approved legislation which is full &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of punishment for people who are ready to support and to help refugees. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;The same situation is growing in Slovakia, where an independent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;journalist was killed some months ago. The same situation is growing in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Czech Republic and in Romania, and some countries. Also in Italy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So, there is a big problem on both sides of the transatlantic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;geography model. And I think that if we want, in the perspective of 10 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years, to develop and to make many solutions much more advanced in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;digital realm, in the economic realm--we need now to start and to fight &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for democracy, freedoms, and the rule of law on both sides of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Atlantic.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Thompson. Before we go any deeper into your comments, I would &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;like to turn to MEP Griesbeck, and ask where do you see things in 10 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years? Do you agree with MEP Boni's assessment in terms of what the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ideal relationship should be and what some of the obstacles are in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;getting there?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Griesbeck. Yes. First of all, thank you very much, Mischa, for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organizing this meeting. Sorry for my bad English, because I am French &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and it's--I did not--my studies in United States. But I like very much. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I was an international visitor at the 20th century. It's a long time &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;before. [Laughs.] But it was a very marvelous time for me. And I like &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very much to come. Today I come to United States in this prestigious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Congress and with the delegation. And it's for me a great pleasure.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I am with Mr. Michael Speiser, he is the chief administrator for a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different committee in the European Parliament. It's also an honor for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;me to speak today to the Helsinki Commission. That reminds us of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;name of the city of the summit Helsinki 2 days ago between your &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;president and Mr. Putin. And it's a strange situation, because for me &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Helsinki Commission is an institution that has been created in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;order to announce consideration of human rights in the formulation of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.S. foreign policymaking, and to support democratic change in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries of the former Soviet bloc.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    One, the principles standing at the creation of the commission have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;lost nothing of their importance today. They are the expression of our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shared values, as Michal Boni said just before. And it's very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;important. And principles that our countries follow, and without which &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our democracies could not exist. The respect for freedom, equality, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;civil liberties, rule of law, and democracy are values upon which our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;societies are built. And it's, for me, to answer to your question, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;work to do for the 10 years in front of us. But it is work from the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;human dimension, the Helsinki Commission also monitors developments &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regarding the security dimensions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And its activities in recent years have been included in hearings &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on combating terrorism. Terrorist organizations violate the basic human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rights of people, such as the right to life and physical and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;psychological integrity. As chair of the Special Committee Against &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Terrorism, the fight against terrorists, these common positions are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very important. Currently we are experiencing some tensions in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relationship between our countries, as my colleagues said. For example, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also, it was not mentioned in our trade relations, at the same time, to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our regret, the U.S. has decided to disengage from U.N. efforts such as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.N. human rights, UNESCO, and Paris Agreement on climate change.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Despite this, speaking here today as the chair of the Special &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Committee on Terrorism, I would like to stress that the U.S. is one of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our most important partners in the fight against terrorism. I went &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;yesterday to the terrorist training center. And we have a very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;interesting meeting with the intelligence services, with the FBI, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we have to work together in the fight against terrorism because it's a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;global threat--it's a world, global threat. And we need to be together &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to fight against these bad things. And it was very, very interesting to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;speak with your intelligence services, because they are extraordinarily &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;well organized.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I want to say this today, we are guided by the shared concern for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the security of our citizens and face the same threats. Some of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;recent attempted terrorist attacks in the EU have been thwarted thanks &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to information received from U.S. intelligence services. And without it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would be most difficult to fight against them. And the cooperation in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this field has increased very much in recent years to mutual benefit. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;The Committee of Foreign Affairs of the European Parliament recently &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;adopted its report on EU-U.S. relations, according to which the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union and the United States building on the strong foundation &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of shared values and principles should use all available channels of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;communication in order to strengthen the transatlantic relationship.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The U.S. Congress and the European Parliament should, with regard &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to this, use the full potential of the cooperation to preserve the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;democratic, liberal, and multilateral order, and to promote stability &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and continuity in the 10 years on the continents and in the world, even &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;if the winds are sometimes bad. I don't know if this situation is able &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to explain something in my bad English, but in French it's something &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very clear as the winds are sometimes bad. And we are in this sequence &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;today since several months. Even in the European Union, not only here &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;or there.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    These efforts are even more needed as we face new challenges in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;multipolar world. I can only agree with these conclusions. I would like &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to use this opportunity to express my hopes that our cooperation in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;areas in defense of peace, freedom, and democracy will continue for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;world stability.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you. And excuse me for my bad English, but you seem to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understand.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Thompson. Thank you so much. I will say, your English is so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;much better than my French. [Laughter.] So thank you. We appreciate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    There were a number of issues that were just raised in terms of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;where we would see ourselves in the next 10 years on both sides of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Atlantic. I think what obstacles we would have to address--everything &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from the CLOUD Act to where the U.S. stands on a number of U.N. bodies &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regarding the Human Rights Council, as well some other multilateral &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;agreements including climate change, and then, of course, our recent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;comments made at the NATO summit.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But before we actually turn things over to the audience, I will say &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;one of the things that we didn't hear about just yet is actually Brexit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and where we would--[laughs]--see ourselves in the next 10 years. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;since we are lucky enough to have someone from the U.K. on the panel--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and I apologize, I know you must get this question all the time--but &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just given what we see in the next months where----&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Moraes. So I got the boring first question and then I get the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Brexit question. Thanks, Mischa, very much. [Laughter.] My colleagues &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;get all the really cerebral, sophisticated questions. I get what are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you doing here and tell us about Brexit. [Laughter.] Thank you very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;much. I'll see how I can make this really imaginative as well. So let's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;see how I can weave this into something interesting. Yes. Anyway, what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do you want to know about Brexit? We're leaving. [Laughter.] So, yes, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;OK, moving on.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Thompson. [Laughs.] I'll ask you two questions. So what does &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that mean for the U.K. in 10 years, what does it mean for the EU in 10 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years? And then I'll even say, most recently, what will it mean for the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Parliament next year?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Moraes. Yes, like I said, we're leaving. [Laughter.] So--well, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you never know. [Laughs.] Oh, that's being recorded.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Well, yes, it's a bit of a mess. And one of the reasons it's a mess &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is because, first of all, the European Union is a good thing, as people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are learning. And the process of leaving, as always happens when one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;leaves, is you start to understand what the good things are about your &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;partner and how you might miss them. Well, that's certainly what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;happened between me and my partner. And we're still together, so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;everything's fine. I'm just making that very personal.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But the issue about Brexit in terms of the issues that Nathalie and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Michal have been discussing are actually quite serious ones. If you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think about, for example, the issues at stake, if you look at security, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for example, it was always thought that we could just walk into Brexit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and there would be an easy kind of accommodation between what is a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;major economy, the United Kingdom, a major security asset country like &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the United Kingdom, with some of the most mature intelligence and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;defense assets anywhere in the world, and the European Union. And that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would be easy to do. Remember, the United Kingdom is part of Five Eyes &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with the United States, just to give you one aspect which is also of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;interest to my colleagues here.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And we see that this is not the case. And it's not the case because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the European Union is a very sophisticated and added-value concept, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which has both benefited Europe and it's benefited the United States. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Why? Because what has happened over that period is that the security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;aspect has become a more complicated and important issue. For example, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;data has led it. So when you deal with terrorists, very often you're &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not dealing with terrorists through hot pursuit and enforcement and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;machines. You're dealing with it through information, data. Europol, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;one of the most successful agencies anywhere in the world--it's a very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;small agency but it's a huge added value--is not an enforcement agency. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;It's an intelligence agency. But it's so successful because it takes &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;its intelligence capacity very seriously and it's good at it. And it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shares its information very well and it has the correct priorities.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, the United Kingdom, through Brexit, will want to share in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol afterwards. But because of the legal constraints, the U.K. will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be a third country. That will be tough. Now, that also has an impact on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the United States. Why? Because the U.K. is in Five Eyes. And it's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;difficult to divide what is happening in the European Union from what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is happening in intelligence sharing generally, because these are not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;divisions that people can make very easily. So Brexit has all sorts of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;difficult and unintended consequences because the European Union's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;development has happened in such a way to impinge on the real needs and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;values of the transatlantic relationship.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    What Britain got from the European Union was a magnification of its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;role and its relationship with the United States, not a diminution. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I think people are realizing that now. It's a less-special relationship &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;when you're on your own because you don't have the added value, you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;don't have the economies of scale. So, what we had in our intelligence &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;services and our defense assets, and so on, don't have the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;magnification by not being in the European Union. So, the other thing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is the simple question of a security treaty with the EU legal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;constraints on our access to databases. We'll need adequacy agreements &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and so on.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So the European Union, as you may have gathered from what I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;saying, is a good thing. But it's a good thing for the United States. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And the United States is a good thing for us. What will constrain &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that--and Brexit has thrown everything into sharp relief--is an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understanding that the relationship must be nurtured. And that means &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that the United States is much more than who might be president today. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;It is a long-lasting relationship where the fundamentals need to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nurtured.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So today, when we look at the issues that Nathalie has raised, one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the things that we have to get very much right are the big issues of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;safety, how we keep our people safe, counter terrorism, and then the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;big issue of how that has managed to impinge on the areas of commercial &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transfers of data. Because data is data, but it can be transferred for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;many reasons.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And there are two big reasons--one is security. So, when we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;travel--and I want to mention this in the context of Brexit because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it's to illustrate how important these areas are for this generation. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And there are many young people here, so this is the future. And this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is the difference between 1975 and today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The qualitative difference is that the future will be about massive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;data transfers both within domestic countries--there won't be the high &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;streets that we have been used to; everything will be online--but &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;between countries there will be massive commercial transfers. But if &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there are security exemptions and so on to these transfers, of course &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we have to sort out what they have to be. And then we have to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understand security data transfers to ensure that we are keeping people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;safe. Of course, we have to ensure that our privacy is protected when &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that happens--hence, the Umbrella Agreement, hence all of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;international agreements that we have between us.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, you mentioned Brexit. Of course, when a country leaves two &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;things happen, when a big country leaves, particularly. One is, we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;realize the importance of many of these things. Passenger name records &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was an agreement which the United Kingdom was very much leading and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wanted. And of course, no doubt will keep involved in. But many other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;agreements, perhaps not. So, when you look at the headlines--there are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;headlines and then there are the realities of what it means to leave &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;such a unique and extraordinary association as the European Union. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;There's nothing like it in the world. It is quite a unique association &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of countries. And I think the security aspect of that was very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;underestimated. And at some point, there will be an impact on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States because of that.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We'll see how the Brexit story goes. The Brexit story is not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;finished. As you're all keen students of politics, you will be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;watching. You probably know more about it than I do. I've been here in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Washington without wi-fi. You probably have access to wi-fi. But I'd &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;like to know a bit more about what happened in the last hour, for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;example. It's an hour-by-hour story--our Brexit story. So let's see &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;what's happened so far. But there are only negatives for the U.K. of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Brexit, because we are the ones who are leaving. Getting a deal not in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the conventional sense. We are leaving, and the terms are with the 27. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And I think this was the big, big, big problem about the idea, that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there would be some kind of equal negotiation, which was never to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the case.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I think, as far as the United States is concerned, the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States wanted the U.K. to stay within the European Union. I think that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was a cross-party sense and analysis, if we remember the history of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Brexit. Whether you were a Democrat, whether you were a Republican, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;whether you were independent, you tended to think that it would be a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;good thing if the United Kingdom stayed within the EU. And I think &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people would tend to think that still. I don't think there are many &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people who think that's not a good idea. I think there is one person &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who thinks it's a good idea. But I think the broad swath of opinion is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;probably not the case. And I think there's plenty of evidence now to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;show that.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    There are people who like Brexit, by the way. You may have noticed &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I'm not one of them. So does that answer your question about Brexit? &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Good.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Thompson. So--and I think we could easily take all of today's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time to discuss Brexit. But we won't. [Laughs.] I have a number of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;questions I do want to raise with the panel. But just given the time, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do want to turn to our audience, and also just let people know that we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are still expecting Senator Wicker. He had a conflict and is coming &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from another meeting. So with that, we have a microphone that is going &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;around. If you're interested in asking a question, please raise your &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hand. Please introduce yourself.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Hi. My name is Elias Passis [ph]. I work in Senator &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Duckworth's office.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I had a question regarding here in our Congress, there are a number &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of bills addressing beneficial ownership, illicit economies, and tax &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;evasion. But with so many of the top earners in the world having stakes &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in economies across the transatlantic and elsewhere, I was wondering &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;what kind of structures any of you have considered or see as being &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;beneficial in making sure that illicit economies are something that we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can address?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Boni. Thank you very much. First, I would like to address and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;add something about Brexit. Could we imagine the situation that in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;perspective of 3 years the delegation of the European Parliament will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;go to London and will discuss with the U.K. Parliament the Privacy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Shield, as we are now discussing with the U.S.? Because it will--of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;course, I hope that the U.K. will keep the solutions which were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;approved in the European Union, but it's not so clear? So, Brexit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;creates many, many new challenges. And I think it will not be so good &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for our common future.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Coming back to some economic issues, I think that there is a big &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opportunity to create--when we are talking about data protection and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;personal data protection--to create the global reference point when we, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union and U.S., also we are working with Japan and South Korea &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on some agreements on proper conditions for data flows. If we will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;create this reference point, I think it will be easier to discuss also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with China and with Russia on those issues. So we need to make it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;together.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Second, when we are talking about artificial intelligence, the U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is much more advanced. But in the European Union we have started the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;work on it. This is the first step in investment, 1.5 billion euro. But &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on the other hand, we are discussing the ethical aspects of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;functioning of artificial intelligence. We are discussing the future &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;labor markets. We are discussing what interactions between humans and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;artificial intelligence will look like in the future. It requires some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;changes in education that require some new skills and solutions in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;area of attitudes and competencies.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So, we need to be much more adaptable, if we will make it together, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the European Union and the United States, I think that we will go &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;forward. And when we are looking at China's program to be the first, to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be the leader in 2025 in the area of artificial intelligence, I think, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;unfortunately without those considerations for ethical issues--I think &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it will be much stronger, it will be better for creating the strategy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for artificial intelligence, which will be human-centered, because this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is very important.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    When we are talking about cybersecurity, in the European Union we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are now working on cybersecurity act. What does it mean? That we are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;working on certification schemes and the model of shared responsibility &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;between states, the companies or institutions responsible for critical &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;infrastructure, but also all companies, including small and medium &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;companies, and individuals, because this is some kind of cybersecurity &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hygiene which is needed also for us as individuals. If we make them &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;together, and if standards important for certification schemes become &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;common in the European Union and in the United States, both sides will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;benefit. On the one hand we will be much more secure, on the other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hand, we will create our economic advances in that area.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So if I'm considering many, many issues, I think that there are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;common goals. And we need to go in this way, especially also when we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;will back commonly--the U.S. and European Union--to the track of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Paris Agreement, because this is an opportunity for us as humans to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;live in a better world. But on the other hand, this is an opportunity &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for businesses, yes? For a new model of development.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So the list is very long. And I think that beyond the linguistic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;problem, as it was presented yesterday by President Trump--beyond many &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tensions existing now, I think that we need to have this list and we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;need to start cooperation because the future belongs to us.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Moraes. May I say one thing about what Michal said that's very, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very important that he raised just now? It is that to underestimate the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relationship between the European Union and the United States is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;perilous. He gave such an excellent example of artificial intelligence &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and the movements in that field that would expand in China. China will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do it. China will do all of these things. But they will do them in a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different way. And they will do them in a way which will have a set of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different values. European Union values on security, on commercial &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transfer are different. There will be liberal democratic values &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;underpinning them. And this is critical. And that's why Brexit's bad &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;too, because you want to stay within this area of values. This creates &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;better business, it creates better security, better counterterrorism, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because it's underpinned by values.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, of course, there's a spectrum to that always. But China will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do this. Other countries may go down different paths, but you really &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;underestimate this to everyone's peril. And I think artificial &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;intelligence and robotics are very good examples. And that's why the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union is cooperating with South Korea and Japan. And it's why &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the United States does as well. So this relationship is so critical for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that reason. And that's why we are more emotional about Brexit, because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it should be within this incredibly important values arc, which should &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;never be underestimated. And in the current context, it's why we feel &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the way we do about the relationship with the United States and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Griesbeck. [Through interpreter.] Well, just to add to what my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;two colleagues just said, I'm totally in agreement with them. And let &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;me tell you that they are both coming from a different political angle &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;than myself. They are from two different parties, and I'm from a third &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;party. But on these--on these big lines, we basically have very similar &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;views and a very similar approach. And we are in Europe with half a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;billion--500 million people--over there. And the United States, you are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;something like 300 million. And there's on the one hand the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Union and the United States, and on the other hand there's China.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And what distinguishes us from China is the set of values and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;principles that guide us. And despite the small differences between us &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and the United States, there's a dividing line between us and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States on the one hand and China on the other hand. We have an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ethical structure on which we are elaborating and on which we are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;developing. And, yes, to answer your question on tax evasion, for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;example, obviously we are doing similar--we are doing similar efforts. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;But we are doing them on values and the rule of law and on principles. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And fine for China that they are developing, but they are developing on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a very different basis. And from a--and starting--setting off from a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different set of rules. So just to tell you that here we are, very much &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on the same page and very much in agreement, the three of us.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    [Speaks in English.] Excellent, Michael. He is from Germany. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[Laughter.] Excellent.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Speiser. One wouldn't believe that, huh? [Laughter.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Hi. I'm Erika Schlager from the Helsinki Commission &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;staff.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    First of all, I'd like to thank you for the excellent presentations &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that you've made this morning. The transatlantic relationship has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;really been built on a comprehensive concept of security, one that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;includes democracy and human rights. So I was particularly interested, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and welcomed the comments that we heard this morning, about the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;challenges at present regarding the rule of law and independence of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;judiciary. Now, you may know that members of Congress from both sides &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the aisle, particularly in the Senate, have spoken to some of these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;issues, have written to the president and to the secretary of state &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about the importance of democracy and human rights in U.S. foreign &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;policy. My question for you is, do you have suggestions on how Congress &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can constructively engage and reinforce democracy and human rights in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the region at this juncture?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Boni. Thank you very much for this question. And I want to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thank to the representatives of Congress and the Senate, because the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;activity of those two chambers and the activity of many American &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;institutions, the judges' associations and so on, is very high.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And it's very important in Poland, when we have this kind of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;international support for keeping the independence of the judiciary &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;system, for example, because it means that it is not only a topic for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;political internal battles, but that this is something more, yes? And I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think it's very important for this part of society who is fighting for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;those values.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I think that because this is an ongoing story, so if you will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be involved all the time and comment, and send some information, some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;suggestions, organize some pressure in a positive sense, I think that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it will be very, very useful for all of us in Poland because one of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;dimensions of the populistic model of the governing is to polarize &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;society. So we have two societies in our country. This part of society &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who is involved in activities of the ruling party--this is some kind of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious community, my view is that it is not the civil society. This &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is the religious community, without any critical thinking about some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;solutions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But on the other hand, we have people who are fighting for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;democracy, who want to keep the independence of the judiciary system. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;They are attacked very often. We have no public media. Public media is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;TV propaganda, and so on and so on. So your voice is very, very, very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;important. And I want to just--to add just one point. When we start in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the autumn in Poland and next year when we have many elections--local &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and regional elections this year, elections to the European Parliament &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;next year, and the election to the Polish Parliament next year, and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;presidential election in 2020.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And we are organizing some kind--which is WWW, in Polish. But it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;means volunteers for free elections--for fair elections. Because we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want to avoid the situation in which there will be some, delicately &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;speaking, misunderstandings--[laughs]--with results of the elections. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And I think if the civil society, Helsinki Commission, some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;representatives of Congress and Senate will be involved in keeping the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fair elections, the [patron ?] of this action is--[inaudible]. So I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think it's also visible to our American colleagues that this is one of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the key person fighting for freedom in this part of Europe. So be with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;us and be in touch together.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Thompson. As we're waiting for the microphone to get to our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;next question, I did want to raise a question about the demographic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;change that we're seeing in Europe. And, again, is this is one of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;other issues that we should be focusing on? A number of people noted &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that the team in France, for example, that brought home the World Cup &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was quite diverse. And so there have been questions of whether or not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there's a way to capitalize on increasing diversity in Europe. And I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;actually just really pleased, again, to have you here today, because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you've been leading on the blue card initiative for Europe, that's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;looking at Europe's changing work force. And I was hoping you could &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;talk a little bit about where things are with that and if there's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;anything specifically relevant to this high skilled effort that can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also be utilized with the newer migrant and refugee populations that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we're seeing in Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Moraes. It's interesting that you're talking about the legal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;channels for coming to the European Union. So interestingly, nobody &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wants the blue card, which kind of tells you where that is. It tells &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you where the United States is at the moment and tells you where the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union is.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But what is happening in the world is that Western countries, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;liberal democracies that we're talking about, are under relative &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;migration pressure. Mr. Boni talked about climate change, we talk about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;refugee hot spots, Syria, Libya, what proceeded it, Iran, Iraq, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Afghanistan, the refugee crises of that period. Although, in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Mediterranean the numbers are, in fact, falling. But the numbers that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are coming are heavily politicized, as you well know when you watch the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;news.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So there's migration pressure, but at the same time--and I don't &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;know exactly the demographics in the United States--but at the same &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time in the European Union there's a very heavily aging, ethnically &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;white population. So you have even in countries like Italy, Spain with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relatively high density, you still have aging populations and the need &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for work in particular sectors. So you've got this conundrum. But &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;migration is not a simple thing, particularly in European societies, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;post-colonial societies. Ethnicity, identity, race is a huge issue when &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you have powers that literally were colonial powers, and still are. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Some European Union countries still have colonies. And so the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;psychology of this is extremely important.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Each European Union country has had a different relationship with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;immigration. And immigration has been shaped in relation to those &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries. So that's the underlying tension below all of this. Those &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries without those colonial pasts, those who have had fewer &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;colonies--Germany, for example--have a different immigration passage. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Those countries that have few migrants and have been accession &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries in 2004, like Poland and Hungary, have had a different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;migration passage. But France and the United Kingdom, colonial powers, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their migration history is shaped by that. And then, of course, their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;constitutions have shaped it. So in France the republican notion, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;everyone is French. The United Kingdom, everyone is kind of British. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[Laughs.] Sort of. So this is a complicated thing.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Then this makes it difficult for the European Union to then have a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;migration policy, because you're dealing with the very, very difficult &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;issues of sovereignty, identity, of citizenship, which are very, very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;defined. However, the European Union has an external border. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union needs to have the integrity of the external border and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the freedom of movement within. And that's the big paradox. So this has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been tested very heavily in recent years. And to have a settlement--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because we talk about human rights, liberal democracies--it has been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tested heavily. And the first thing, to be positive, many good things &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have happened. Many countries have stepped up to the plate, have tried &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to do the right thing. Germany being a good example, Sweden, and other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries trying to do the right thing. Many other countries have been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;doing good things, but they're not being identified as doing so, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because the whole issue has been caricaturized.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So this is a very big subject, as you can see from how I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;describing it. But it should not be simplified. The big issues now that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we have to deal with are that we have to have a managed migration &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;policy for the European Union without us descending into populism and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;moving to a situation where the fear of migration dictates how &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governments are elected. And in my view--because I shouldn't have a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;view on the United States, you should have a view on the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States--but once leaders pursue the notion of fear of migration rather &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;than management of migration, then you are descending into the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;situation we had in the 1920s, fear of invasion, fear of an enemy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rather than understanding that you should manage migration for the good &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of everyone, for a win-win situation. And, second, understanding what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;migration means. There are certain push factors and certain pull &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;factors. And the population should really be truthfully told what they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are and why people are moving and what their migration needs are.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We haven't reached this point yet. And certainly the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Union, there's been a shock to that. So today for example, the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Union doesn't have much of a legal migration policy because that's in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;retreat. But that doesn't mean we don't have the capacity to do it. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union has managed to do many things. And by the way, I would &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;say about the European Union, people talk about the end of the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Union in many phases all the time. And it always is resilient. It &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;always comes back and has a solution. And I'm very optimistic that even &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in this very difficult area, we will find solutions, we will manage &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;things, because we're talking about sophisticated countries that can do &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this. And there are political, progressive forces that can try and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ensure that we get a good solution, but it won't be easy. And I'm glad &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I'm getting older and it's all up to you. No, it's not, you're &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;American. But the younger generation will have to grapple with this.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Climate change, climate change refugees, I have to say that much of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the movement--as we saw when we were in Lebanon recently--developing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries have the overwhelming majority of refugees, not Europe or the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States. That's the reality. But if you say to somebody in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union or the United States that's the case, it's meaningless &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;if they switch on Fox News and everyone's telling them that they're &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;being invaded by Mexicans and there needs to be a wall. So it's the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;same in the European Union. If Salvini in Italy is telling them that, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;look, we need to do this because he's under pressure. What's more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;difficult is if somebody in another country, where there's virtually no &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;migration, tells them that they're being invaded--so Hungary, for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;example. And that's the big problem. This is a huge issue for us. But &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we can manage this.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Why do we know we can manage it? Because history has been here--we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have been here before. And we need to learn the lessons of history. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I think this is a profound issue. It's a management issue. It's an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organizational issue. And by the way, when we talk about the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transatlantic relationship, there's some symmetry here between the two.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Can I just say this one final thing on migration? It's quite &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;interesting, but a few years ago--both in the United States and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union--people said that migration was a non-issue. I remember &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that. It was about 22, 23 years ago. Secondary migration was the only &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thing. Everyone said immigration doesn't exist anymore as an issue in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the United States. But all that existed in the United States as it was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;becoming more ethnically diverse. But immigration was not an issue. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Refugees were not an issue for the United States.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Funnily enough, it's a big issue today, and it's the same in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union. And there are many, many factors determining that, but &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we have to get through this. And the other thing is that it's a global &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;issue, not an issue for the Western liberal democracies. We are caught &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in it because we don't want those people to come. And yet, we need some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of them to do the work that no one else wants to do. And then as Mischa &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;said, we need some of the skilled ones to do the more skilled work that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we want them to do. So in my country, the National Health Service would &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;collapse tomorrow without the migrant labor that we have, or the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union free movement that we need. So this is the big paradox &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of migration. But it's probably the biggest single challenge that we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have in the European Union, which almost like dwarfs the economy which &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;seems to be ticking along nicely.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And just a final point, the countries that complain most about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;migration have got the highest economic growth in the European Union &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;today. That's just a really interesting point to mention.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Griesbeck. May I say a few words about the blue card and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conclusion from our President Claude Moraes?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    [Continues through interpreter.] Just to add to what Claude said, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on the blue card, Claude Moraes, our president, used to be the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rapporteur on this file. And he was in charge of this file. And I want &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to congratulate him for the great work that he has put into it, and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;progress that had been made. A blue card would have been one way of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opening routes for migrants--legal routes for migrants to come to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe. And that would have been a good thing. Now it is because of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reluctance of some member states and their hypocrisy, in a way, that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this dossier has not seen the light yet, or at least not seen the light &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the way that it should be.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Blue card would have been also an important issue because we are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;actually facing here two major problems in Europe. One is the problem &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of migration. And this problem of migration can basically cause us harm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and bring down Europe if we are not able to provide for the good--for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the good replies to it. And the blue card, in a way, would have been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;one way of a good response to that. And on the other hand, that was the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;question of Mischa from the start, the demographic development and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;demographic change of Europe. If you look at Europe in a couple of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years from now it will be a continent of gray hair, like myself. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And as paradox as it might sound, so on this one hand this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;migration issue, and at the same time we need something in terms of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;migration if we don't want to become the continent of gray hair. So &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that is a very big issue. And these are the two challenges that we are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;currently facing.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Thompson. Okay. So we're going to do a really quick lighting &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;round to see if we can end in 5 minutes. And--[laughs]--and so with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that we'll take the two questions here.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Dan Stoller from Bloomberg.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Just a quick question. With the growing political tension between &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the U.S. and the EU, and the EU's appetite for more data transfer pacts &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with Japan and South Korea, do you think there will be more data &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transfer agreements with other nations outside of the U.S. going &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;forward? Is there a larger appetite for that?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. I'm Robert Hand. I'm a colleague of Mischa's at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Helsinki Commission. And my portfolio is the Western Balkans, which is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a region where the United States and the European Union has had to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;coordinate policies. In fact, at many of our previous hearings and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;briefings we have often had an EU official or even a member of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Parliament come to talk about policy responses to the Balkans.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    If I were to present U.S. policy in its more simplistic form, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;say it's to follow the European lead, to support Europe in its approach &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to the Western Balkans, how would you react? How confident are you in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe's ability to lead in the Balkans, particularly given the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;problems with European leadership in the 1990s? And what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;recommendations would you make for U.S. engagement with Europe in that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;region that is knocking on the EU door right now?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Thompson. So, and I'll say the last question I want to add to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the lightning round--and I apologize because I'm going to have to cut &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you off--is that there's been a lot of talk about security issues &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;emanating from both Russia and China. Yet, there are a number of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European countries, as well as our country, that are currently doing a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;lot of business with China in particular, and also looking to do more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;business with both in the future. And so I think the question emanating &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from that is whether or not there's a scenario where both China and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Russia can actually become more credible partners on security with the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And so, with that, I will quickly turn to the panel for 1-minute &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;answers on these three questions that were just posed.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Moraes. Just on the Bloomberg colleague's question about the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;adequacy agreements and the relationships--I mean, our committee will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be going to South Korea in October, and we've just been to Japan. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our role is on the adequacy agreement in relation to the trade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;agreement. So the answer is absolutely yes, we're seeing adequacy with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these countries. I met with the South Korean equivalent of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;information commissioner body a couple of weeks ago. And the point is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that they are extremely keen. When we meet them, they're extremely keen &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to seek this kind of equivalency, because they understand the need for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;kind of frictionless data transfers. So they're building relationships &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for the future, not just for the trade agreement. And they understand &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;exactly what is happening in the European Union. I know this is fast, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;but understand we're modernizing our data protection laws, and again, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you've got liberal economic space. But you've got rules which are now &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tried and tested. And I think that's been really good.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Why are we doing it? We are doing the adequacy part. It's not just &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about privacy, it's also the commercial side. So absolutely yes, this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is an exciting area. And I think yes, the U.S. should be aware of that, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that we are doing that. And it's successful because we concluded the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Japan trade agreement just recently. And we're quite excited to be part &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of that. I don't know, Mr. Boni might--and, of course, he had mentioned &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;artificial intelligence, robotics, and so on. All of these areas--for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;example, Japan is hugely interested in that. So, the answer is yes.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Boni. I know we are sort of the beginning of conversation &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;negotiations with Singapore on data flows. There are many companies &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;installed in Singapore. So I think it will be very, very important from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the economic point of view. And also, we are talking about Canada, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because it should be also recognized. And after that, we need to make &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;an order of the--[inaudible].&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    This year in May, in the European summit in Sofia, we focused on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;establishing the strategy for the Balkans country's development. And I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think it was very, very important. It was multidimensional, focused on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;many areas related to political issues, to fight against corruption, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;but also to support and to help those countries in the problems of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;depopulation, because it's a real challenge for those countries. We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have discussed also about digital issues and making some special &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;agreements and also using European money in the new infrastructure, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;making the accessibility to the internet much more open and for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;everybody.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And Serbia is the one country for which the commission said, okay, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;2025 could be the year in which it this country will be a member of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union. And what is important is solving the problem of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;name of Macedonia, is I think it's also opened the further steps. My &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;personal view is that now for the European Union, from a political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;point of view, Balkan countries are much more important than the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;eastern partnership. But of course, the eastern partnership is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;crucial--Ukraine, Moldova, and Georgia having the association &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;agreement, some distance to go for Armenia and Azerbaijan. Of course, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there are many problems with Belarus. But I think that Balkan countries &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are the main focus.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Thompson. And MEP Griesbeck, just on whether Russia and China &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can be credible counterterrorism and security partners for the U.S. and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;EU.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    MEP Griesbeck. [Through interpreter.] Right. To answer the question &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the gentleman on the Balkans, I don't know what was really behind &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this question, if there's intention or if there is the thought behind &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;whether the Balkans should join the European Union, yes or no. Let me &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;answer the following--I know coming from a centrist, center political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;movement, being a member of the liberal group, I know that I'm a bit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;isolated here with my position. But here's the following look at &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Turkey. We opened accession discussions with Turkey and see where that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has led us today. It was President Bush in 2004 who basically &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;encouraged us to integrate Turkey into the European Union. And now &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relations with Turkey are rather deteriorating than improving. We have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very, very, very difficult relations with Turkey. Look at the terrorist &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;financing problems, look at the refugee problems. We have struck a deal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with them that cost us 6 billion euros. And yet, this deal is subject &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to permanent blackmailing. So in case we wouldn't deliver, they would &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;send more and more refugees.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And this is to say I was always one of those who voted against &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Turkey's accession to the European Union. And in the same way, I'm also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opposing the idea of integrating more Western Balkan countries into the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;EU. They should benefit from a very advanced and privileged &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;partnership, but for the time being they should not be members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;EU. Why? Because the European Union is much more than just an economic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;platform. It's a political entity. It's an entity of shared values and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ideas. And we are currently in a phase where we first need to deepen &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our integration with the member states that we have before we can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;basically go for further enlargement of the European Union. If we would &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;go on and just enlarge the European Union, we would just run around &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;like a duck without a head. And we first need to basically make our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;minds up where we want to go with this European Union that we are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;currently having before we ask more members to join us. And I know this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is not a very popular position. And I know I'm not in the majority &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there with my views, but I wanted to share them with you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Thompson. Well, thank you all very much for such an amazing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;panel, following such a long trip from Europe, I'm certain with very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;little sleep. We know that officials on both sides were taking notes on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;everything that you said in preparation for the July 25th meeting that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;will take place between Presidents Trump and Juncker. And so, with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that, we thank everyone else.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Senator Wicker sends his apologies. He actually got tied up with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Senate business. And so, we're hoping that there might be another &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opportunity for the delegation to connect with him, and with that, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thank all of you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you. [Applause.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    [Whereupon, at 11:18 a.m., the briefing was adjourned.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                          [all]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            This is an official publication of the Commission on&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                    Security and Cooperation in Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  This publication is intended to document&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  developments and trends in participating&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  States of the Organization for Security&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                     and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE).&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;           All Commission publications may be freely reproduced,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            in any form, with appropriate credit. The Commission&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            encourages the widest possible dissemination of its&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               publications.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      www.csce.gov       @HelsinkiComm&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 The Commission's Web site provides access&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 to the latest press releases and reports,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                as well as hearings and briefings. Using the&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;         Commission's electronic subscription service, readers are&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            able to receive press releases, articles, and other&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          materials by topic or countries of particular interest.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                          Please subscribe today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;&amp;lt;/pre&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
</intro>
</Hearing>
