<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="28980">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;Doc-title&gt;POLICY PRIORITIES AT THE DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND THE ADMINISTRATION'S FISCAL YEAR 2019 BUDGET PROPOSAL&lt;/Doc-title&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;           ADMINISTRATION'S FISCAL YEAR 2019 BUDGET PROPOSAL
=======================================================================
                           OVERSIGHT HEARING
                               before the
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;committee_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES&lt;/committee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                     U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             SECOND SESSION
                               __________
                        Thursday, March 15, 2018
                               __________
                           Serial No. 115-40
                               __________
       Printed for the use of the Committee on Natural Resources
        Available via the World Wide Web: http://www.govinfo.gov
                                   or
          Committee address: http://naturalresources.house.gov
                       _________ 
            U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
29-980 PDF          WASHINGTON : 2018                
&lt;/option&gt;
</intro>
    <committeeComposition>
    &lt;comitteeM_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON NATURAL RESOURCES&lt;/comitteeM_name&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;ROB BISHOP&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Chairman&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;RAUL M. GRIJALVA&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Ranking Democratic Member&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Don Young&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; AK&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Grace F. Napolitano&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; CA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Chairman Emeritus&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;Chairman Emeritus&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Madeleine Z. Bordallo&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; GU&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Louie Gohmert&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; TX&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Jim Costa&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; CA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Vice Chairman&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;Vice Chairman&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Gregorio Kilili Camacho Sablan&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; &lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Doug Lamborn&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; CO&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;CNMI&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;CNMI&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Robert J. Wittman&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; VA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Niki Tsongas&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; MA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Tom McClintock&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; CA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Jared Huffman&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; CA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Stevan Pearce&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; NM&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Vice Ranking Member&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;Vice Ranking Member&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Glenn Thompson&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; PA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Alan S. Lowenthal&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; CA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Paul A. Gosar&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; AZ&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Donald S. Beyer&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; VA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Raul R. Labrador&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; ID&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Ruben Gallego&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; AZ&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Scott R. Tipton&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; CO&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Colleen Hanabusa&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; HI&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Doug LaMalfa&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; CA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Nanette Diaz Barragan&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; CA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Jeff Denham&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; CA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Darren Soto&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; FL&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Paul Cook&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; CA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;A. Donald McEachin&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; VA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Bruce Westerman&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; AR&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Anthony G. Brown&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; MD&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Garret Graves&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; LA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Wm. Lacy Clay&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; MO&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Jody B. Hice&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; GA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Jimmy Gomez&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; CA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Aumua Amata Coleman Radewagen&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; AS&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Vacancy&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;Vacancy&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Daniel Webster&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; FL&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Jack Bergman&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; MI&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Liz Cheney&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; WY&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Mike Johnson&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; LA&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Jenniffer Gonzalez-Colon&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; PR&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Greg Gianforte&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; MT&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;John R. Curtis&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; UT&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Cody Stewart&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Chief of Staff&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Lisa Pittman&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Chief Counsel&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;David Watkins&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Democratic Staff Director&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
</committeeComposition>
    <Directory>
    &lt;table-of-content&gt;CONTENTS&lt;/table-of-content&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;   Hearing held on Thursday&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;March&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Members&gt;Statement of Members:&lt;/Members&gt;
    &lt;Speaker&gt;Hon Rob Bishop&lt;/Speaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative in Congress from the State of Utah Prepared statement of&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Speaker&gt;Hon Raul M Grijalva&lt;/Speaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative in Congress from the State of Arizona Prepared statement of&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;witnesses&gt;Statement of Witnesses:&lt;/witnesses&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Hon Jared Huffman&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative in Congress from the State of California Prepared statement of&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Hon Ryan Zinke&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Secretary US Department of the Interior&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;submittedMaterial&gt;Additional Materials Submitted for the Record:&lt;/submittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;List of documents submitted for the record retained in the Committee's official files Submissions for the Record by Rep Grijalva Alliance for Retired Americans&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;American Society on Aging Statement for the Record AMVETS&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;Submission for the Record by Rep Huffman California Natural Resources Agency&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Rep Pelosi and Senators McConnell and Schumer&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;Submission for the Record by Rep McClintock Zinke&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Letter to Chairman Bishop dated October&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;OVERSIGHT HEARING ON POLICY PRIORITIES AT THE DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR AND THE ADMINISTRATION'S FISCAL YEAR  BUDGET PROPOSAL  Thursday&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;US House of Representatives Committee on Natural Resources Washington DC&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;The Committee met&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;at : am in&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;room&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Hon Rob Bishop [Chairman of the Committee] presiding&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;Present: Representatives Bishop&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Gohmert Lamborn&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;Wittman&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Pearce Thompson&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;LaMalfa&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Graves Hice&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;GonzalezColon&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Curtis; Grijalva Bordallo&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;Sablan&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Huffman Lowenthal&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;Hanabusa&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Soto McEachin&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;The Chairman We are happy to welcome all of you here for this hearing that deals with the Department of the Interior and their Fiscal Year  budget The Committee on Natural Resources will come to order Under Committee Rule (f)&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;any oral opening statements at&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;hearings are limited to the Chairman&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;the Ranking Minority&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;Member&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;and the Vice Chair This will also allow us to hear&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;from witnesses sooner Therefore&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;I am going to ask unanimous&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;SubmittedMaterial&gt;consent that all other Members' opening statements be made part of the hearing record if they are submitted to the Subcommittee on Federal Lands Clerk by : pm today I appreciate that I am going to submit most of my opening statementwell&lt;/SubmittedMaterial&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;the bulk of my opening statementto the&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                     FROM THE STATE OF UTAH
    The Chairman. Secretary, we appreciate having you here. 
Thank you, as well to those who are joining you. We appreciate 
that opportunity. We want to welcome you back to the Committee, 
Mr. Secretary.
    I do have some praise I want to give to what you have done 
so far, as you have repositioned the Department into looking at 
what your core statutory functions are, and new evidence that 
the greatest concern is how you actually impact people.
    For too long we have had people coming back here addressing 
us dealing with special interest groups, as opposed to simply 
people. We like the way you looked at some of the burdensome 
regulations that you inherited from the prior administration.
    We will be talking about two elements that I think are 
extremely significant. I think some of your proposals have 
instituted a new degree of federalism never heard before, which 
is very refreshing around this place.
    And also, you have some new initiatives that deal with the 
backlog. I hope you will be talking to that. It is one of the 
things we will be talking about, not just today but in the 
coming few weeks at the same time.
    It is a significant issue.
    With that, I will submit the rest of my statement for the 
record.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Rob Bishop, Chairman, Committee on 
                           Natural Resources
    Welcome back to the Committee, Mr. Secretary. We are pleased to 
have you here to testify on the Administration's Fiscal Year 2019 
budget and its policy priorities for the Department of the Interior.
    Let me start by offering my praise for your work on many fronts to 
improve land and resource management functions of the Department. Over 
the past year, you have worked proactively to reposition the Department 
as an ally and advocate to the people it serves, and to restore its 
core statutory functions.
    The Administration has also prioritized greater American energy 
abundance and security, and you have positioned the Department as a 
chief contributor in this endeavor. In doing so, you have acted to 
address many overly burdensome regulations initiated under the prior 
administration that resulted in hindered American energy development on 
Federal lands, lost revenues and fewer opportunities for western 
communities.
    Additionally, the Department has used its existing authorities to 
promote the responsible development of our vast onshore and offshore 
energy resources, including the Department's proposed National OCS Oil 
and Gas Leasing Program.
    Whether they know it or not, many of my Democratic colleagues have 
become ardent supporters of federalism because of this plan. Imagine 
that: Political leaders wanting to decide if and how energy resources 
are developed in their states and not be dictated to from Washington. 
Unfortunately, their rush to defend local voices is only a priority 
when it benefits their own interests.
    The Administration and the Department have also demonstrated a 
commitment to greater stewardship of public lands. You clearly realize 
the importance of conserving and maintaining lands and resources 
already under Federal control and have prioritized addressing our 
massive maintenance backlog as part of this effort. You have also taken 
on a broader reorganization of the Department to improve agency 
bureaucracy, elevate local input, and more effectively and efficiently 
serve communities and taxpayers.
    The Administration's Fiscal Year 2019 budget reflects a commitment 
to these priorities and several others. The Administration's nearly 
$800 million budget investment in energy related programs demonstrates 
your commitment to an ``All of the Above'' energy strategy to promote 
both onshore and offshore development.
    The budget request includes innovative solutions to tackle the 
maintenance backlog, including a Public Lands Infrastructure Fund, 
which has garnered bipartisan support. Some have criticized your 
proposal for its reliance on oil and gas revenues as its funding 
mechanism. Ironically, many of these same special interest groups have 
led the charge for permanent reauthorization of the Land and Water 
Conservation Fund, a program that is almost entirely funded by oil and 
gas development on Federal lands.
    Political posturing from a small group of fringe special interests 
shouldn't be allowed to detract a proposal viewed by most Members as a 
thoughtful and creative legislative proposal. I appreciate your 
commitment to this issue and look forward to advancing a solution 
during this Congress.
    As mentioned, the Department has also outlined an ambitious plan 
for reorganization, a concept I wholeheartedly support. The Committee 
looks forward to continuing to work with you on this important 
initiative, and views the related $17.5 million request within your 
budget as a down payment in this endeavor.
    Mr. Secretary, you and your staff conducted significant outreach to 
Congress, governors, local communities and interested stakeholders on 
this proposal. This sort of local engagement is important in all 
decisions your Department makes and we hope this outreach will continue 
as you formalize next steps in the process.
    The President's budget also makes tough choices, balancing fiscal 
realities while prioritizing scarce resources. Overall, it reflects a 
commitment to restore public access to public lands, improve resource 
management and solutions that promote both conservation and economic 
prosperity.
    This Committee is dedicated to advancing shared goals and working 
to provide any additional tools and authorities necessary to achieve 
them. I look forward to your testimony and the engagement of our 
Members.
                                 ______
    The Chairman. I will now turn to Mr. Grijalva for his 
opening statement.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;               CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF ARIZONA
    Mr. Grijalva. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, and let me join the 
Chairman in welcoming you, Mr. Secretary, to the Committee. We 
are glad that you are here to discuss the Trump 
administration's spending priorities for the Department, and an 
opportunity for this Committee to exercise its oversight 
responsibilities.
    And right now it seems a good time to exercise those 
oversight responsibilities. Recently, we have seen several 
reports of questionable spending at your Department. These 
reports have raised significant questions about your 
stewardship of taxpayer dollars. I believe the public deserves 
a detailed accounting of these questionable expenses, 
particularly now that you are proposing enormous budget cuts 
across your Department.
    For example, just last week, it was revealed that taxpayers 
are on the hook for more than $138,000 to replace some doors in 
your personal office. This, understandably, reminds the public 
of the $31,000 dining set that was recently ordered by another 
cabinet secretary's office. In your case, your Department has 
said that the office's redecorating expenses are 
``reasonable.'' I hope you will provide some detailed answers 
today explaining why spending $138,000 for office doors is a 
reasonable expense for the public to bear.
    Going down the list of questionable spending, last month, 
taxpayers paid for your travel 1 mile outside Pennsylvania's 
18th Congressional District 2 weeks before a competitive 
special election where you appeared in a photo-op with the 
Republican candidate in that race holding an over-sized 
ceremonial check for abandoned mine cleanup. As you know, these 
grants are routine, and you could have gone to over 1,000 
abandoned mine sites in over 25 states to announce the issuance 
of grants for that cleanup. So, the question for the Committee, 
should you choose to answer that one, is why this particular 
site?
    In October, we saw reports that taxpayers paid for several 
trips where you attended political fundraisers, including 
events at a ski resort in Montana and an upscale Alaskan steak 
house. These trips create the appearance that taxpayers are 
financing partisan political work. Taxpayer-funded trips to 
Santa Barbara and Montana, where you own homes, have similarly 
been called into question.
    In fact, there have been enough questions about your 
taxpayer-funded travels that both the Office of Special Counsel 
and the Interior's Inspector General have opened 
investigations. This questionable spending is even more 
troubling, given the fact that you are simultaneously proposing 
significant funding cuts for important programs serving the 
American people.
    Let me give you some of these enormous cuts in areas such 
as the construction of rural water projects which deliver 
drinking water to rural and tribal communities without potable, 
reliable drinking water; cuts to core climate research and 
science programs at USGS; cuts to renewable energy programs; 
and a 90 percent cut for land acquisition under the popular, 
bipartisan Land and Water Conservation Fund.
    Americans expect our Federal agencies to responsibly manage 
taxpayers' money. The reports of your spending signal to the 
public that maybe we are not meeting that critical standard.
    While the Majority does not seem bothered by reports of 
ethical lapses and conflicts of interest at the Department, my 
Democratic colleagues and I have sent dozens of oversight 
requests seeking information about these matters. 
Unfortunately, you have not seen fit to respond to any of them.
    Last year I, along with other Members, sent two letters 
asking about the decision of the Office of Surface Mining, 
Reclamation, and Enforcement to halt the NAS study on the 
severe health impacts suffered by people who live near 
mountaintop removal coal mines. The rationale provided does not 
withstand scrutiny, and cancellation would result in the waste 
of approximately $400,000 in taxpayer dollars. Yet, there has 
been no response. This is a public health issue and I 
understand it is not a coal industry priority, but it is a 
public health issue to the American people.
    I also requested justification for your review of national 
monuments, but you did not respond, and it was not until the 
Washington Post leaked a copy of the final report that the 
public got a chance to see what it was and get an explanation 
as to why some monuments were included and some were not.
    Last month, I requested information about another secret 
plan that BLM has been working on to steamroll the rights of 
Americans to an open government and an open process. The policy 
changes in the secret report are almost as disturbing as the 
process in which it was generated. The comment period was 
announced via press release, and comments were entered through 
a Google form. Your agency omitted contrary opinions and 
handpicked a selection of anonymous supportive comments. By any 
measure, that is really far from transparent.
    You have an opportunity today to address these and other 
concerns to all my colleagues on the Committee, and I sincerely 
hope that you will.
    Mr. Chairman, I yield back.
    The Chairman. Otherwise, everything OK?
    Mr. Grijalva. Everything is good.
    The Chairman. Good, good.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Raul M. Grijalva, Ranking Member, 
                     Committee on Natural Resources
    Thank you, Mr. Chairman, and welcome back to the Committee, Mr. 
Secretary. I'm glad you're here to discuss the Trump administration's 
spending priorities for the Department of the Interior, and I thank you 
for being here so we can exercise our oversight responsibilities.
    I'm sorry to say, Mr. Secretary, that right now seems to be a good 
time to exercise our oversight responsibilities. Recently, we've seen 
several reports of questionable spending at your Department. These 
reports have raised significant questions about your stewardship of 
taxpayer dollars, and the public deserves a detailed accounting of 
these questionable expenses, particularly now that you're proposing 
enormous budget cuts across your Department.
    For example, just last week, it was revealed that taxpayers are on 
the hook for more than $138,000 to replace some doors in your personal 
office. This understandably reminds the public of the $31,000 dining 
set that was recently ordered for another cabinet secretary's office. 
In your case, your Department has said your office's redecorating 
expenses are ``reasonable.'' I hope you'll provide some detailed 
answers today explaining why spending so much for your office's doors 
is a reasonable expense for the public to bear.
    Going down the list of questionable spending, last month, taxpayers 
paid for you to travel 1 mile outside Pennsylvania's 18th Congressional 
District 2 weeks before a competitive special election, where you 
appeared in a photo-op with the Republican candidate in that race 
holding an over-sized ceremonial check for abandoned mine cleanup. The 
grants you were announcing are routine and you could have gone to over 
a thousand abandoned mine sites for a photo-op. You will need to 
explain to the Committee how you chose that one.
    In October, we saw reports that taxpayers paid for several trips 
where you attended political fundraisers, including events at a ski 
resort in Montana and an upscale Alaskan steak house. These trips 
create the appearance that taxpayers are financing your partisan 
political work. Taxpayer-funded trips to Santa Barbara and Montana, 
where you own homes, have similarly been called into question.
    In fact, there have been enough questions about your taxpayer-
funded travels that both the Office of Special Counsel and Interior's 
Inspector General have opened investigations. This questionable 
spending is even more troubling given the fact that you're 
simultaneously proposing significant funding cuts for important 
programs serving the American people.
    To take just a few examples, you've proposed enormous cuts: for the 
construction of rural water projects, which deliver drinking water to 
rural and tribal communities without reliable drinking water; to core 
climate research and science programs at USGS; for renewable energy 
programs; and a 90 percent cut for land acquisition under the popular, 
bipartisan Land and Water Conservation Fund.
    Americans expect our Federal agencies to responsibly manage 
taxpayers' money. The reports of your spending signal to the public 
that you are not meeting this critical standard.
    While the Majority has not seemed bothered by reports of ethical 
lapses and conflicts of interest at the Department, my Democratic 
colleagues and I have sent dozens of oversight requests seeking 
information about these matters. Unfortunately, you have not seen fit 
to respond.
    For example: Last year, I sent two letters asking about the 
decision of the Office of Surface Mining Reclamation and Enforcement to 
halt an NAS study on the severe health impacts suffered by people who 
live near mountaintop removal coal mines. The rationale provided does 
not withstand scrutiny, and cancellation would result in the waste of 
approximately $400,000 in taxpayer dollars. Yet, there has been no 
response.
    I also requested a justification for your ``review'' of national 
monuments, but you did not respond and it wasn't until the Washington 
Post leaked a copy of the final report did the public get any 
explanation as to why some monuments were included and some were not.
    Last month, I requested information about another secret plan that 
BLM has been working on to steamroll the rights of Americans to an open 
government. The policy changes in the secret report are almost as 
disturbing as the process in which it was generated--the comment period 
was announced via press release and comments were entered through a 
Google form. Your Agency omitted contrary opinions and handpicked a 
selection of anonymous supportive comments. By any measure, this is far 
from transparent.
    You have an opportunity today to address these and other concerns, 
and I hope you will.
    Thank you, I yield back.
                                 ______
    The Chairman. We want to welcome the witnesses that are 
here today.
    First of all, the Honorable Ryan--do I have to say 
honorable all the time here--the Honorable Ryan Zinke, who is 
Secretary of the Department of the Interior.
    He is accompanied by Olivia Barton Ferriter--we appreciate 
you--who is the Deputy Assistant Secretary for Budget, Finance, 
Performance, and Acquisition--long title, but is here to answer 
specific questions on details of the budget, as well as Ms. 
Denise Flanagan, who is the Director of the Office of Budget 
within the Department of the Interior.
    [Pause.]
    The Chairman. Apparently there is another statement from 
the Democrat side. We do allow the Vice Chairs. We are going to 
waive that on our side.
    Mr. Huffman, apparently you want to make a statement.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;             CONGRESS FROM THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA
    Mr. Huffman. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, and welcome to 
Secretary Zinke and our witnesses.
    We are here to examine the President's Fiscal Year 2019 
budget request for the Department of the Interior, a budget 
that many of us find deeply disappointing. It is not just the 
huge cuts that would hamstring critically important programs 
like western drought funding, climate research, endangered 
species conservation, and land acquisition through the Land and 
Water Conservation Fund (LWCF).
    This is a budget that places the exploitation of our public 
lands above any other uses. It undermines national parks and 
cuts land and water conservation. It turns back the clock on 
our Federal Government's role to a time before Teddy Roosevelt, 
John Muir, and Gifford Pinchot.
    This is a budget that prioritizes the profit that oil, gas, 
and coal companies can dig, drill, and otherwise wring out of 
our public lands, with no consideration of future generations 
or the long-term impacts to health and the environment. We are 
producing more oil and natural gas today than ever before, and 
now we have so much that we export millions of barrels of crude 
and billions of cubic feet of gas overseas every day, and yet, 
according to the priorities in this President's budget, the 
Interior Department still isn't doing enough favors for oil and 
gas companies.
    Every year, average global temperatures get hotter. The 
Arctic ice cap gets smaller, storms get stronger, and droughts 
get more severe. Yet, according to the priorities in this 
budget, the Interior Department had been previously thinking 
and doing too much to combat global climate change.
    In over 3,600 pages of budget documents from your 
Department, the phrases ``climate change,'' ``climate impact,'' 
``climate science,'' and ``climate resilience'' are used a 
grand total of 31 times combined, with 21 of those times being 
references to programs that are being slashed or eliminated.
    The new DOI strategic plan eliminates all references to 
climate change, but makes sure that the first three words in 
the new departmental vision statement are to ``promote energy 
dominance.'' That is the kind of vision that leads to opening 
both the Atlantic and Pacific coasts to unwanted offshore 
drilling.
    It is the kind of vision that leads to stacking a royalty 
collection advisory committee with oil, gas, and coal 
executives, which, unsurprisingly, led to recommendations to 
give those industries huge discounts and rip off the American 
taxpayers for the use of their lands and waters.
    That is the kind of vision that leads to a cynical proposal 
to pay for maintenance in our national parks through vastly 
expanded drilling and mining. You want to fix that leaky roof 
at the visitor center? Fine, let's drill a few more oil wells.
    We should not have to drill our parks in order to save 
them, especially not when the President is continuing to 
celebrate the enormous budget holes that he and this Republican 
Congress just created with their tax cuts.
    The more you look at this budget, the more offensively 
misplaced priorities you see. The budget proposes drastic cuts 
to programs that have helped the United States to lead the 
international fight against wildlife trafficking, replacing 
these proven efforts with an ill-conceived International 
Wildlife Conservation Council to carry out the wishes of trophy 
hunters and the NRA.
    And now it has gotten worse. Following a lawsuit by the NRA 
and others, unfortunately, Mr. Secretary, your Department has 
reopened the door for more elephant tusks and lion hides to be 
imported into the United States, lifting the ban on these big 
game trophies on a case-by-case basis. President Trump, who 
will never be mistaken for a conservationist, rightly described 
these trophy hunts as a horror show for elephants.
    And while the Department is rolling back protections, 
ironically, China is stepping up its work on international 
wildlife conservation. So, just when our years of pressure and 
leadership are starting to work in the world community, we are 
abdicating our leadership role.
    This decision to allow elephant trophies to be imported 
reflects an administration under the undue influence of the 
NRA. And we have seen reports that taxpayers recently paid for 
you to stay at the Four Seasons Resort in Dallas to attend a 
conference organized by the NRA, where you also reportedly met 
with several campaign donors.
    I am reminded, too, of the decision by political appointees 
in your Department to muzzle the National Park Service's 
concerns about the provisions of the NRA-backed silencer bill.
    The bottom line is we see a budget here that should uphold 
strong environmental protections for air, water, wildlife, and 
natural places, areas where we have been a world leader. But 
instead, this budget would dismantle those things. In so many 
ways right now, this great agency is mired in chaos, cronyism, 
and at least the appearance of corruption. That, and the 
upside-down budget priorities surely have TR rolling in his 
grave.
    With that, I yield back.
    The Chairman. Thank you.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;   Prepared Statement of the Hon. Jared Huffman, a Representative in 
                 Congress from the State of California
    Thank you, Mr. Chairman. And welcome back to the Natural Resources 
Committee, Secretary Zinke.
    We're here to examine the President's Fiscal Year 2019 budget 
request for the Department of the Interior, a budget that is deeply 
disappointing. It's not just the huge cuts that would hamstring 
critically important programs, like western drought funding, climate 
research, endangered species conservation, and land acquisition through 
the Land and Water Conservation Fund.
    This is a budget that places the exploitation of our public lands 
above any other uses. It undermines national parks and cuts land and 
water conservation, and it turns back the clock on the Federal 
Government's role to a time before Teddy Roosevelt, John Muir, and 
Gifford Pinchot.
    This is a budget that prioritizes the profit that oil, gas, and 
coal companies can dig, drill, or otherwise wring out of our public 
lands, with no consideration of future generations or the long-term 
impacts to health and the environment. We are producing more oil and 
natural gas than ever before in our Nation's history, and we now have 
so much that we export millions of barrels of crude and billions of 
cubic feet of gas overseas every day, yet according to the priorities 
in this President's budget, the Interior Department still isn't doing 
enough favors for the oil and gas companies.
    Every year, average global temperatures get hotter, the Arctic ice 
cap gets smaller, storms get stronger, and droughts get more severe, 
yet according to the priorities in this President's budget, the 
Interior Department had been previously thinking and doing too much to 
combat climate change.
    In over 3,600 pages of budget documents from your Department, the 
phrases ``climate change,'' ``climate impact,'' ``climate science,'' 
and ``climate resilience'' are used a grand total of 31 times combined, 
with 21 of them being references to programs being slashed or 
eliminated.
    The new DOI strategic plan eliminates all references to climate 
change, but makes sure that the first three words in the new 
Departmental vision statement are to ``promote energy dominance.'' 
That's the kind of vision that leads to opening both the Atlantic and 
Pacific coasts to unwanted offshore drilling.
    That's the kind of vision that leads to stacking a royalty 
collection advisory committee with oil, gas, and coal executives, 
which--unsurprisingly--led to recommendations to give those industries 
huge discounts and rip off the American taxpayers for the use of their 
lands and waters.
    That's the kind of vision that leads to a cynical proposal to pay 
for maintenance in our National Parks through vastly expanded drilling 
and mining. You want to fix the leaky roof in that visitors center? 
Fine, hope you don't mind the seismic testing outside the front gate.
    We should not have to drill our parks in order to save them. 
Especially not when the President is continuing to celebrate the 
enormous budget holes that he and this Republican Congress created with 
their tax cut scam.
    The more you look at this budget, the more offensively misplaced 
priorities you see. This budget proposes drastic cuts to programs that 
have helped the United States lead the international fight against 
wildlife trafficking, replacing those proven efforts with an ill-
conceived ``International Wildlife Conservation Council'' to carry out 
the wishes of trophy hunters and the NRA.
    And now it's gotten worse: following a lawsuit by the NRA and 
others, your Department has re-opened the door for more elephant tusks 
and lion hides to be imported into the United States, lifting the ban 
on these big game trophies on a case-by-case basis. President Trump--
who will never be mistaken for a wildlife conservationist--rightly 
described these trophy hunts as a ``horror show'' for elephants.
    And while the Interior Department is rolling back protections, 
China is stepping up its work on international wildlife conservation.
    The decision to allow for elephant trophies to be imported into our 
country reflects an Administration under the undue influence of the 
NRA. We've seen reports that taxpayers recently paid for you to stay at 
the Four Seasons Resort in Dallas to attend a conference organized by 
the NRA, where you also reportedly met with several campaign donors.
    I am reminded, too, of the decision by political appointees in your 
Department to sideline the National Park Service's concerns about 
provisions of the NRA-backed Silencer Bill that would prohibit the Park 
Service from regulating hunting and fishing within park boundaries.
    This is a sad state of affairs. The Interior Department budget 
should uphold our strong environmental protections for air, water, 
wildlife, and natural places. These are areas where we have been a 
world leader.
    This budget would instead dismantle that conservation legacy bit by 
bit, rewarding extractive industry while ignoring our responsibilities 
to our children and grandchildren.
    I have a lot of questions about this budget's misplaced priorities 
that I hope we'll have time for, but for now I look forward to hearing 
the Secretary's testimony, and I yield back.
                                 ______
    The Chairman. Mr. Gohmert, we will waive your statement so 
we can get back to questions, we can hear speeches all the 
time. We will waive your speech, going forward with that. 
Whether you want to waive it or not, you just waived it.
    Mr. Zinke, let me turn the time over to you. You understand 
how the system works. You have to turn the microphone on. You 
have 5 minutes for the opening presentation, and then we will 
launch right into questions for you, if that is OK.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                  THE INTERIOR, WASHINGTON, DC
    Secretary Zinke. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, Ranking Member, 
and Committee members, for the opportunity to offer my support 
for President Trump's Fiscal Year 2019 budget for the 
Department of the Interior. With your permission, I would like 
to submit my entire statement for the record.
    The President has been very clear about his priorities, and 
he has spent the first year in office keeping his promises he 
has made to the American people. And he is keeping his 
promises. The budget is a major step toward keeping another 
promise: rebuilding our infrastructure.
    Our proposal is the largest investment in our public lands 
infrastructure in the history of this Nation. Our public lands 
are recognized as our greatest treasures, but they have 
suffered serious neglect from our Nation's leaders from both 
parties over the past.
    Interior's deferred maintenance budget backlog is $16 
billion; $11.5 billion of that can be found in our beloved 
national parks. This includes everything from roads, bridges, 
tunnels, visitor centers, and restrooms. It is no way to treat 
our national treasures. At the Grand Canyon alone, for example, 
a water pipe has broke 80 times since 2010. It has forced 
emergency rationing and has cost millions of dollars to fix 
over and over.
    The President's budget proposes legislation for new public 
lands infrastructure to address the deferred maintenance 
problem. This legislation is a top priority. It is a 
legislation based on all energy, not oil and gas, as our policy 
is clear. We are American energy first, all types of energy, 
and not just oil and gas.
    The fund will provide up to $18 billion over 10 years for 
maintenance improvements in our national parks, wildlife 
refuges, and Bureau of Education, in that I am responsible for 
the education of 48,000 American Indian Natives, and they 
deserve a world-class education, too. This budget also includes 
$1.3 billion for construction and repairs.
    Infrastructure is not an expense, it is an investment. Our 
budget does just that, it invests in our Nation's treasures. 
Our public lands should be for the benefit and enjoyment of the 
people, as what is expressed in the Roosevelt Arch at the 
Yellowstone National Park.
    In 2006, we had 330 million visitors through our parks, and 
spent an estimated $18.4 billion in local gateway regions, 
nationwide. The economic support of the recreational industry 
is at $887 billion and employs approximately 7.6 million 
Americans. All Americans should have the opportunity to enjoy 
our national parks, but without a significant investment in 
infrastructure to go along with a record-setting amount of 
visitors we have on a yearly basis, we are simply loving our 
parks to death.
    Along with being a great steward of our public lands, 
again, I am the champion of our Indian Nations, and I take that 
responsibility seriously, in that it provides $634 million to 
address our backlog of 150 Bureau of Indian Education schools 
in 23 states.
    We see a great opportunity also to reorganize the 
Department for the next 100 years, and have the same courage 
Roosevelt did 100 years ago to bring this Nation on a path of 
our public lands. As a retired Navy SEAL, I think you will look 
at the front lines. Our front lines are too short and the 
authority in Washington to make decisions about our public 
lands in the field has oftentimes been wrong.
    This budget includes $18 million to begin shifting 
resources to the front line, where they belong, and establish 
unified regional boundaries in Interior's bureaus. This 
reorganization will also enable us to achieve our mission of 
stewardship.
    Our organization is based on science. It is based on 
watersheds, wildlife corridors, ecosystems to manage our public 
lands and waters according to the best science, best practices, 
longest term, greatest good. That is the American conservation 
ethic.
    This budget also recognizes that American strength relies 
on American energy. Under President Trump we are pursuing and 
reaching American energy dominance. And yes, I am proud to say 
that America produced 10.6 million barrels a day. For the first 
time in 60 years we are an exporter of liquid natural gas. I 
wish there was a battery. But until we get a battery, we are 
going to produce energy here at home. President Trump's tax 
cuts and smart regulation are helping to grow the American 
economy. We are growing the economy and American energy 
dominance is a part of that growth.
    All told, our budget request for Fiscal Year 2019 is $11.7 
billion, with a proposed transfer--the Department of Defense 
for the Palau contract, or compact. It raised it to $11.8 
billion.
    This budget clearly lays out a top priority of this 
Administration of energy, conservation, reorganization, and 
rebuilding our park system, our national wildlife system, and 
our Indian education opportunities.
    With that, I am happy to take your questions.
&lt;/option&gt;
</Directory>
</Hearing>
