<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="28996">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         [H.A.S.C. No. 115-73]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                HEARING&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                   ON&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                          FOR FISCAL YEAR 2019&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                  AND&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;              OVERSIGHT OF PREVIOUSLY AUTHORIZED PROGRAMS&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               BEFORE THE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;committee_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES&lt;/committee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             SECOND SESSION
                               __________
&lt;/option&gt;
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON EMERGING THREATS AND CAPABILITIES HEARING&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                                   ON
                     EVOLUTION, TRANSFORMATION, AND
                       SUSTAINMENT: A REVIEW AND
                   ASSESSMENT OF THE FISCAL YEAR 2019
                    BUDGET REQUEST FOR U.S. SPECIAL
                     OPERATIONS FORCES AND COMMAND
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                           FEBRUARY 15, 2018
                                ______
                     U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE 
28-996                    WASHINGTON : 2018                 
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON EMERGING THREATS AND CAPABILITIES&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                ELISE M. STEFANIK, New York, Chairwoman
BILL SHUSTER, Pennsylvania           JAMES R. LANGEVIN, Rhode Island
BRAD R. WENSTRUP, Ohio               RICK LARSEN, Washington
RALPH LEE ABRAHAM, Louisiana         JIM COOPER, Tennessee
LIZ CHENEY, Wyoming, Vice Chair      JACKIE SPEIER, California
JOE WILSON, South Carolina           MARC A. VEASEY, Texas
FRANK A. LoBIONDO, New Jersey        TULSI GABBARD, Hawaii
DOUG LAMBORN, Colorado               BETO O'ROURKE, Texas
AUSTIN SCOTT, Georgia                STEPHANIE N. MURPHY, Florida
JODY B. HICE, Georgia
                Pete Villano, Professional Staff Member
              Lindsay Kavanaugh, Professional Staff Member
                          Neve Schadler, Clerk
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <Directory>
    &lt;table-of-content&gt;C O N T E N T S&lt;/table-of-content&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS&lt;/Speakers&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;Hon James R Langevin&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative from Rhode Island Ranking Member&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Hon Elise M Stefanik&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative from New York Chairwoman&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;witnesses&gt;WITNESSES&lt;/witnesses&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;GEN Raymond A Thomas&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;USA Commander&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Owen West&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Assistant Secretary of Defense for Special Operations/LowIntensity Conflict US Department of Defense&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;APPENDIX&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;Prepared Statements:&lt;/Speakers&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;Hon Elise M Thomas Stefanik&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;GEN Raymond A West Owen&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
</Directory>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;Subcommittee on Emerging Threats and Capabilities,&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;Chairman&gt;
        &lt;Cname&gt;                       Washington&lt;/Cname&gt;
        &lt;Clocation&gt; 2018.&lt;/Clocation&gt;
    &lt;/Chairman&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;The subcommittee met&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; in &lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;ViceChair&gt;
        &lt;Cname&gt;room 2212&lt;/Cname&gt;
        &lt;Clocation&gt; Hon. Elise M. &lt;/Clocation&gt;
    &lt;/ViceChair&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Stefanik (chairwoman of the subcommittee) presiding.&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;Stefanik (chairwoman of the subcommittee) presiding.&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;FROM NEW YORK, CHAIRWOMAN, SUBCOMMITTEE ON EMERGING THREATS AND 
                          CAPABILITIES
    Ms. Stefanik. The subcommittee will come to order. I am 
pleased to welcome everyone to this important hearing entitled, 
``Evolution, Transformation, and Sustainment: A Review of the 
Fiscal Year 2019 Budget Request for U.S. Special Operations 
Forces and Command.'' The fiscal year 2019 budget request for 
U.S. Special Operations Command [SOCOM] totals more than $13.6 
billion, an approximate 10 percent increase, and the largest 
request ever submitted. It also seeks additional personnel 
authorizations, putting the total size of the force above 
71,000, the largest ever envisioned. While I am pleased to see 
continued fiscal support for special operations forces [SOF], 
it is deeply troubling to see continued dependency on overseas 
continued [contingency] operations funding [OCO]. This problem 
is most acute in the operations and maintenance accounts, where 
OCO is an alarming 33 percent.
    One year ago, before this very committee, General Thomas 
wisely noted that such dependency has created a force that is, 
quote, ``largely a facade,'' unquote. Unfortunately, we find 
ourselves in the same place today, if not worse. Working 
together, we must commit to remedy this imbalance. And I look 
forward to talking about concrete ways in which this committee 
can help, while you continue to help yourselves. This 10 
percent budget increase also reminds us that we must work to 
ensure we are not choosing quantity over quality, and that 
special operations forces remain balanced across the entirety 
of the joint operating force and the military services, who 
are, themselves, experiencing near existential readiness 
crises.
    The recently released National Defense Strategy [NDS] 
indeed places special operations forces central to efforts 
across the full spectrum of non-state and state threats. Rising 
and asymmetric challenges posed by Russia and China and the 
potential for contingencies on the Korean Peninsula impair our 
ongoing efforts in Afghanistan, Iraq, Syria, Yemen, and 
Somalia. All this while SOF also maintains a presence in some 
80 additional countries today. Now, more than ever, we run the 
risk of overextending our SOF forces, who are central to our 
national defense.
    Of particular concern, we see the fight in Syria changing. 
More and more, our forces are engaging Russian and Syrian 
regime proxies, as most recently seen in the aggressive 
fighting in Deir al-Zour. The defeat of ISIS [Islamic State of 
Iraq and Syria] now reveals the fingerprints of the larger 
geopolitical fight we are engaged in, putting at risk current 
authorities, frameworks, and partnerships, and not to mention 
the considerable risk to our forces on the ground in an already 
clouded and fractured battlefield.
    I look forward to hearing from both of our witnesses today 
how our special operations forces are postured to support the 
new National Defense Strategy, while also continuing forward as 
the main line of effort in our current efforts across the 
globe.
    A large part of this subcommittee charge is looking far 
ahead to consider what's next. In doing so, I see many 
challenges, but also great opportunities in emerging 
technologies such as AI [artificial intelligence], quantum 
computing, nanotechnology, synthetic biology, the Internet of 
Things, and many others that will provide a significant 
battlefield advantage for special operations forces and the 
broader joint force. We must ensure that we are doing 
everything we can to push the technological edge and maintain a 
battlefield advantage. Rest assured, our near-peer adversaries 
are already aggressively exploring these technologies, which 
present both economic and national security challenges for our 
Nation. To this end, I am somewhat disappointed that SOCOM's 
budget request decreases research and development [R&amp;amp;D] funding 
for a second year in a row. I look forward to hearing the 
rationale for this, and taking any necessary steps to ensure we 
do not lose our technological and battlefield advantages.
    Needless to say, there is a lot of ground to cover today. I 
would like to welcome both of our witnesses, Mr. Owen West, the 
Assistant Secretary of Defense for Special Operations and Low-
Intensity Conflict [SO/LIC], and General Tony Thomas, Commander 
of U.S. Special Operations Command. Since this is Mr. West's 
first appearance before the House Armed Services Committee, let 
me congratulate you on your confirmation as Assistant Secretary 
of Defense for Special Operations, and we look forward to 
working with you. I would also like now to recognize my friend 
and the ranking member, Jim Langevin, from Rhode Island, for 
any opening comments he would like to make.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Appendix on page 25.]
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;RHODE ISLAND, RANKING MEMBER, SUBCOMMITTEE ON EMERGING THREATS 
                        AND CAPABILITIES
    Mr. Langevin. Thank you, Madam Chair. And thank you, 
Secretary West. I want to welcome you before the committee. And 
General Thomas, I want to thank you both for appearing before 
us today and for your service to our Nation. It is great to 
have you back, General. Last year in my opening statement on 
the U.S. Special Operations Command budget request, I 
highlighted the ever-increasing demand for reliance on special 
operations forces by combatant commanders, as the chair has 
also referenced in her opening statement. Today, that demand 
and reliance has not decreased. In fact, under the new National 
Defense Strategy it will likely increase with the focus on 
inter-state competition with gray zone conflicts below the 
level of armed conflict. Our special operators have a myriad of 
critical skill sets that can be employed across the full 
spectrum of conflict, yet we must be prudent about how the 
force is employed, or we risk breaking the tip of the spear. 
After 17 years, the global counterterrorism fight is by no 
means over. At the same time, we must be prepared for future 
activities and conflicts in which potential adversaries have 
made gains in technologies like robotics and biotechnology, and 
have new capabilities aimed at achieving information dominance.
    The fiscal year 2019 budget request for USSOCOM is $13.6 
billion, just 2 percent of the overall Department of Defense 
[DOD] request. Reflected in the request are more robust 
investments for enhancing SOF operations throughout the 
information environment, including enhanced cyber and network 
resiliency capabilities. As a result of section 1637 of the 
National Defense Authorization Act [NDAA] for FY [fiscal year] 
2018, the Secretary of Defense has directed USSOCOM to 
establish a centralized capability for military information 
support operations, global messaging, and counter-messaging. 
The FY 2019 request includes $18 million to that end.
    This hearing provides us with an opportunity to understand 
how USSOCOM will fulfill its roles and responsibilities under 
section 1637 to better enable an enhanced approach to maximize 
effects from the tactical to strategic levels, while 
contributing to a whole-of-government effort. As in years past, 
much of the USSOCOM funding request, particularly in the 
operations and maintenance accounts, remains part of the 
overseas contingency operations. However, many of these 
activities and programs are enduring, which means their 
classification remains a serious concern for me. Baseline 
funding is crucial to provide USSOCOM stability for programming 
and, reflected properly, it would enable us to better 
understand defense spending in the current and the out-years.
    In addition to a dialogue about the demands on our force, 
readiness for current and future contingencies, and associated 
resource requests, there are several legislative and policy 
issues at hand to discuss. This includes implementation of 
section 922 of the NDAA regarding the role and responsibilities 
of your office, Secretary West. And I look forward to hearing 
your vision and efforts for implementing reforms intended to 
empower your position to effectively conduct internal oversight 
and advocacy.
    SOF are engaged in operational activities globally under 
legislative authorities carefully overseen by the committee. 
Section 1209 of the FY 2015 NDAA authorizes the Department to 
provide assistance to vetted Syrian opposition forces. SOF 
continue to advise and assist in the fight against ISIL 
[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant] in Syria, where we have 
seen remarkable progress. A transition to stability operations 
has begun in many areas. So with 1209 set to expire on December 
31, 2018, I would like to ask our witnesses their perspective 
on an extension of that authority, and how would continued 
training and assistance be scoped if, in fact, an extension is 
granted? In closing, I, again, want to thank our witnesses for 
being here today, and express my gratitude to the men and women 
of our Armed Forces around the globe. I know you have 
extraordinary responsibilities and burdens on your shoulders. 
The Nation is grateful for the work that you do and for your 
service. With that, Madam Chair, I yield back.
    Ms. Stefanik. Thank you, Jim. And I want to take this 
moment to remind our members that immediately following the 
open hearing, the committee will reconvene right next door in 
2216 for a closed, classified roundtable discussion with both 
of our witnesses. Before we begin, I also want to remind our 
witnesses that your full written statements will be submitted 
for the record. And we ask that you summarize those statements 
in 5 minutes or less for your opening statements. Secretary 
West, we will begin with you, and I look forward to your 
opening statement.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt; SPECIAL OPERATIONS/LOW-INTENSITY CONFLICT, U.S. DEPARTMENT OF 
                            DEFENSE
    Secretary West. Thank you, Chairwoman. Chairwoman, Ranking 
Member, and distinguished members of this committee, I am 
honored to appear before you as the Assistant Secretary of 
Defense of Special Operations/Low-Intensity Conflict. In my 
short time on the job, I have been most impressed by the level 
of commitment demonstrated by my staff and their U.S. Special 
Operations Command teammates. There exists a relentless but 
thoughtful focus on warfighting, which is unsurprising in an 
enterprise led by Secretary Mattis. I am pleased to share this 
opportunity with one such warfighter. From 2001 to 2013, 
General Tony Thomas deployed every year to combat. He is a 
reflection of the force he leads, from his deployment cycle to 
the intellectual creativity and competitive drive he shares 
with his fellow operators.
    I mentioned competitiveness because we have a new National 
Defense Strategy that clarifies my priorities, none bigger than 
helping General Thomas steadily build competitive advantage 
across the vast spectrum of warfare special operations calls 
home. The NDS calls for a new era, where we compete in what 
Secretary Mattis calls the contact layer, the daily clash of 
national will that occurs short of armed conflict, where your 
special operations forces are today building relationships and 
reducing the enemy. The task is to remain unpredictable but 
expansive, pushing the competitive boundaries in ways our 
enemies do not expect. To sustain this expansion, we must be 
fiscally hawkish, reducing asymmetry by adopting a focus on 
return on investment.
    Overhead costs increase as you move from tooth to tail. In 
business, we call this upstream inflation. For example, 
$500,000 in Washington, DC, can buy you a think-tank report, 
whereas $500,000 deployed in the field with a captain as a 
chief investment officer can be leveraged into a force of 
highly trained indigenous allies.
    Secretary Mattis' business reform efforts seek to make the 
force more lethal, and resource allocation that prioritizes the 
operating forces is the next logical step. The 127 Echo program 
is an example of best practices investing. I would like to 
thank Congress for continuing to support 127e, which has grown 
from a pilot program to a $100 million lever that has had a 
direct impact in steadily clawing back territory lost to ISIS 
to name a single impact point.
    Likewise, section 1202 is an example of Congress' forward-
leaning investment to counter unconventional threats. I see 
these authorities as part of Congress' strong and continued 
investment in SOF. My commitment to you is to focus on returns. 
USSOCOM amounts to roughly 1.9 percent of the DOD budget, which 
enables a global presence in 90 countries. This capital 
expenditure fuels the current fight, but it must also result in 
long-term competitive advantage.
    The most important capital investment is human. Everyone on 
this committee is well aware of the demand inelasticity for 
SOF. We simply lack the supply to satisfy all customers. 
General Thomas has already taken the first step in sustainment 
by addressing dwell time, and a second step by conducting a 
comprehensive prioritization review. That leaves mission set.
    As Secretary Mattis indicated in late December, our 
conventional force is capable right now of assuming some of 
these missions. I say that leaves mission set because our other 
option is growing the force. Our 2019 budget request does 
include modest end strength increases for SOF across each of 
the services, but the growth rate has slowed precipitously. SOF 
cannot be quickly grown. Today, we face a natural resource that 
is fully tapped by traditional service recruiting. Only 30 
percent of high schoolers are qualified for military service. 
We must, therefore, explore unconventional techniques and new 
pools to recruit men and women who have the right stuff.
    Today's battlefield has challenged the traditional 
definition of a combatant. Successfully operating in the global 
contact layer demands that we build a diverse force. The SOF 
entry standards are high, but America has always encouraged its 
pioneers. We need more candidates without military histories, 
we need more cultural diversity, we need more women.
    SOF tryouts are life-altering experiences. The reward is 
joining an elite team, where the commitment to each other is as 
strong as the commitment to country. That human element is the 
key element in SOCOM. General Thomas runs a global risk-reward 
venture, and human failure is inevitable. When mistakes are 
made, one of my principal responsibilities is to ensure 
transparency and provide you the necessary and appropriate 
information. We owe it to the families, the Department [of 
Defense], Congress, and the American people to complete 
investigations with thoroughness, diligence, and timeliness.
    We will take all steps necessary to protect our greatest 
asset, those men and women who have volunteered several times 
over to earn the title of special operators. Their fervent 
defense of our beloved Nation makes us all proud. I will never 
lose sight of that.
    I want to end on section 922. I view Congress as a natural 
partner. During my confirmation hearing, I promised to remain 
close to Congress because of that natural partnership. There 
should be no surprises. The Department is reviewing the 
implementation of 922. General Thomas and I are partners in 
this effort. We will move together to implement it. Our goal is 
to make SOCOM a more efficient enterprise that supports the 
National Defense Strategy and the Secretary of Defense. Thank 
you, and I look forward to your questions.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;the Appendix on page 27.]
    Ms. Stefanik. Thank you, Secretary West. General Thomas.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                   SPECIAL OPERATIONS COMMAND
    General Thomas. Chairwoman Stefanik, Representative 
Langevin, and distinguished members of the committee, I am 
honored to appear before you to provide an update on the 
posture of United States Special Operations Command and our 
superb special operations forces. I am pleased to share the 
table with our new Assistant Secretary for Special Operations, 
Owen West. Working closely with Secretary West, we are 
embracing section 922 as the natural evolution of SOCOM's 
service-like responsibilities that Congress envisioned when you 
created us 31 years ago.
    Let me summarize the posture of SOCOM and your special 
operations forces. We continue to have outsized effects around 
the globe, defeating our enemies, training, equipping, and 
enabling our friends and allies, rapidly transforming the 
organization to be prepared for all future threats, and caring 
for our fallen, wounded, and ill, and their families. Your 
special operations forces are doing phenomenal work. Since I 
last appeared before this committee, SOCOM's primary focus has 
continued to be on the defeat of ISIS and al-Qaida and their 
affiliates. Special operations forces played an integral role 
as part of the joint force in the destruction of ISIS's 
physical caliphate in Syria and Iraq.
    In coordination with allied and host nation partners, 
special operations forces continue to confront ISIS and al-
Qaida wherever they sought sanctuary: in Afghanistan, Yemen, 
Libya, Somalia, the trans-Sahel, Lake Chad basin, the Maghreb, 
and even as far off as the Philippines. In addition to our 
historic efforts to confront violent extremism, SOCOM continues 
to enhance our role as part of the joint force in assuring 
allies and improving their capabilities in the face of 
aggressive regional hegemons, reinforcing host nation and law 
enforcement efforts in the Western Hemisphere in defense of our 
national boundaries, and preparing for contingency operations.
    Our successes are directly attributable to recruiting and 
training amazing Americans, outfitting them with the best 
equipment and training in the world, and empowering them with 
the requisite authorities to defeat our adversaries. Our people 
continue to be the decisive advantage. Congress' support 
continues to be key in our efforts in the form of necessary 
resources and specific authorities. With title 10, section 127 
Echo, Congress allowed special operations forces to support 
vetted foreign forces against terrorist groups. It is a 
powerful authority directly responsible for neutralizing 
hundreds of enemy leaders and fighters.
    Section 1209 of the 2015 NDAA allowed special operations 
forces to train and equip a 50,000-plus person force of vetted, 
Kurdish, and Arab Syrians to remove ISIS from 98 percent of the 
territory they once held in Syria. 1209 played a decisive role 
in the military defeat of ISIS's physical caliphate.
    In this year's NDAA, you provided us section 1202, an 
authority special operations forces will employ to support 
friends and dissuade aggression by strategic competitors. We 
think it will provide us a distinct operational advantage, and 
thank you for this important irregular warfare authority. 
Congress has continued to provide us with all the resourcing we 
need to do our job. As you two mentioned in your preamble and 
Secretary West mentioned in his, in fiscal year 2017, our 
budget was $11.8 billion. Our projected budget for fiscal year 
2018 is $12.3 billion; and fiscal year 2019 is projected to be 
$13.6 billion. At 1.9 percent of the total DOD budget, with 
roughly matching sister service contributions, special 
operations forces provide unique and highly effective 
capabilities and extraordinary return on investment across the 
full spectrum of conflict.
    Defeating our enemies, defending the homeland, deterring 
adversaries, supporting allies, and fostering innovation, SOCOM 
operates at a fast, but manageable pace.
    Since I last appeared, SOCOM service components effectively 
reduced the deployment tempo of our personnel, with the 
majority under the Secretary of Defense-directed deployment-to-
dwell ratio of 1:2. Our people and our formations are better 
than they have ever been, thriving under pressure, executing 
the toughest missions, and achieving success.
    Success, however, has carried a high price. In the past 10 
months, we suffered the loss of 20 special operations personnel 
from our formation in combat, with 144 wounded and injured. I 
will close recounting the words of one of our Gold Star mothers 
at the funeral of her son, Green Beret Staff Sergeant Aaron 
Rhett Butler from the 19th Special Forces Group, a National 
Guard noncommissioned officer killed in Afghanistan this past 
August. Aaron was a four-time Utah State wrestling champion in 
high school, and the seventh of eight children. In the midst of 
her grief, Mrs. Butler looked me straight in the eye and said, 
``Stay on this. Finish it.'' Her resolve resonated with me, and 
reflects the extraordinary support we enjoy from our service 
member families. I know it resonates with this committee as 
well.
    SOCOM and our special operations forces are relentlessly 
focused on winning our current fights and preparing for all 
future threats facing our Nation. Again, thank you for your 
trust and support for this command and our special operations 
forces.
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
</Hearing>
