<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="24670">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      AT WHAT COST? EXAMINING THE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         SOCIAL COST OF CARBON&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;=======================================================================&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                             JOINT HEARING&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               BEFORE THE&lt;/info&gt;
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON ENVIRONMENT &amp;amp;&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON OVERSIGHT&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;committee_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON SCIENCE, SPACE, AND TECHNOLOGY&lt;/committee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
                           FEBRUARY 28, 2017
                               __________
                           Serial No. 115-05
                               __________
 Printed for the use of the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology
       Available via the World Wide Web: http://science.house.gov
                                   ______
                         U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE 
24-670 PDF                     WASHINGTON : 2017 
-----------------------------------------------------------------------
  For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing 
  Office Internet: bookstore.gpo.gov Phone: toll free (866) 512-1800; 
         DC area (202) 512-1800 Fax: (202) 512-2104 Mail: Stop IDCC, 
                          Washington, DC 20402-0001
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <committeeComposition>
    &lt;comitteeM_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON SCIENCE, SPACE, AND TECHNOLOGY&lt;/comitteeM_name&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;HON. LAMAR S. SMITH&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Chair&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;FRANK D. LUCAS&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Oklahoma&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;EDDIE BERNICE JOHNSON&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Texas&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;DANA ROHRABACHER&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; California&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;ZOE LOFGREN&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; California&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;MO BROOKS&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Alabama&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;DANIEL LIPINSKI&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Illinois&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;RANDY HULTGREN&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Illinois&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;SUZANNE BONAMICI&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Oregon&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;BILL POSEY&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Florida&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;ALAN GRAYSON&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Florida&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;THOMAS MASSIE&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Kentucky&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;AMI BERA&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; California&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;JIM BRIDENSTINE&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Oklahoma&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;ELIZABETH H. ESTY&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Connecticut&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;RANDY K. WEBER&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Texas&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;MARC A. VEASEY&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Texas&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;STEPHEN KNIGHT&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; California&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;DONALD S. BEYER&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Virginia&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;BRIAN BABIN&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Texas&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;JACKY ROSEN&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Nevada&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;BARBARA COMSTOCK&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Virginia&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;JERRY MCNERNEY&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; California&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;GARY PALMER&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Alabama&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;ED PERLMUTTER&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Colorado&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;BARRY LOUDERMILK&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Georgia&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;PAUL TONKO&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; New York&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;RALPH LEE ABRAHAM&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Louisiana&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;BILL FOSTER&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Illinois&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;DRAIN LaHOOD&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Illinois&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;MARK TAKANO&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; California&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;DANIEL WEBSTER&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Florida&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;COLLEEN HANABUSA&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Hawaii&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;JIM BANKS&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Indiana&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;CHARLIE CRIST&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Florida&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;ANDY BIGGS&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Arizona&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;ROGER W. MARSHALL&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Kansas&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;NEAL P. DUNN&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Florida&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;CLAY HIGGINS&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Louisiana&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;overview&gt;Subcommittee on Environment&lt;/overview&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                    HON. ANDY BIGGS, Arizona, Chair
DANA ROHRABACHER, California         SUZANNE BONAMICI, Oregon, Ranking 
BILL POSEY, Florida                      Member
MO BROOKS, Alabama                   COLLEEN HANABUSA, Hawaii
DANIEL WEBSTER, Florida              CHARLIE CRIST, Florida
BRIAN BABIN, Texas                   EDDIE BERNICE JOHNSON, Texas
GARY PALMER, Alabama
BARRY LOUDERMILK, Georgia
JIM BANKS, Indiana
CLAY HIGGINS, Louisiana
LAMAR S. SMITH, Texas
                                 ------                                
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Subcommittee on Oversight&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                   HON. DRAIN LaHOOD, Illinois, Chair
BILL POSEY, Florida                  DONALD S. BEYER, Jr., Virginia, 
THOMAS MASSIE, Kentucky                  Ranking Member
GARY PALMER, Alabama                 JERRY MCNERNEY, California
ROGER W. MARSHALL, Kansas            ED PERLMUTTER, Colorado
CLAY HIGGINS, Louisiana              EDDIE BERNICE JOHNSON, Texas
LAMAR S. SMITH, Texas
&lt;/option&gt;
</committeeComposition>
    <Directory>
    &lt;table-of-content&gt;C O N T E N T S&lt;/table-of-content&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt; February &lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Witness List Hearing Charter Opening Statements&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;  Representative Andy Biggs&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Chairman Subcommittee on Environment Committee on Science&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;  Representative Suzanne Bonamic&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Ranking Member&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
</Directory>
    <Directory>
    &lt;table-of-content&gt;Subcommittee on Environment, Committee on Science, Space, and&lt;/table-of-content&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt; Technology&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;US House of Representatives Written Statement&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;  Representative Darin LaHood&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Chairman Subcommittee on Oversight Committee on Science&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;  Representative Donald S Beyer&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Jr Ranking Member&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
</Directory>
    <Directory>
    &lt;table-of-content&gt;Subcommittee on Oversight, Committee on Science, Space, and&lt;/table-of-content&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt; Technology&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;US House of Representatives Written Statement&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;  Representative Lamar S Smith&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Chairman Committee on Science Space&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;witnesses&gt;Witnesses:&lt;/witnesses&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Dr Ted Gayer&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;PhD Vice President and Director of Economic Studies and Joseph A Pechman Senior Fellow at Brookings Institution Oral Statement Written Statement&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Dr Kevin Dayaratna&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;PhD Senior Statistician and Research Programmer Center for Data Analysis&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Dr Michael Greenstone&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;PhD Milton Friedman Professor in Economics the College&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Dr Patrick Michaels&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;PhD Director Center for the Study of Science&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Appendix I: Answers to Post-Hearing Questions&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Dr. Kevin Dayaratna, PhD, Senior Statistician and Research 
  Programmer, Center for Data Analysis, Institute for Economic 
  Freedom and Opportunity at The Heritage Foundation.............   124
Dr. Michael Greenstone, PhD, Milton Friedman Professor in 
  Economics, the College, and the Harris School; Director of the 
  interdisciplinary Energy Policy Institute at the University of 
  Chicago and the Energy &amp;amp; Environment Lab at the University of 
  Chicago Urban Labs.............................................   127
            Appendix II: Additional Material for the Record
Statement submitted by Representative Eddie Bernice Johnson, 
  Ranking Member, Committee on Science, Space, and Technology, 
  U.S. House of Representatives..................................   134
Document submitted by Representative Darin LaHood, Chairman, 
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Subcommittee on Oversight, Committee on Science, Space, and&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;  Technology, U.S. House of Representatives......................   136
                      AT WHAT COST? EXAMINING THE
                         SOCIAL COST OF CARBON
                              ----------                              
                       TUESDAY, FEBRUARY 28, 2017
                  House of Representatives,
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Subcommittee on Environment and&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Subcommittee on Oversight,&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;               Committee on Science, Space, and Technology,
                                                   Washington, D.C.
    The Subcommittees met, pursuant to call, at 10:07 a.m., in 
Room 2318, Rayburn House Office Building, Hon. Andy Biggs 
[Chairman of the Subcommittee on Environment] presiding.
    Chairman Biggs. Good morning. The Subcommittees on 
Environment and Oversight will come to order.
    Without objection, the Chair is authorized to declare 
recesses of the Subcommittee at any time.
    Welcome to today's hearing entitled ``At What Cost? 
Examining the Social Cost of Carbon.'' I recognize myself for 
five minutes for an opening statement.
    Welcome to today's joint subcommittee hearing entitled ``At 
What Cost? Examining the Social Cost of Carbon.'' Today, we 
will examine the previous Administration's determination of the 
social cost of carbon, or SCC, and explore why the calculated 
value is flawed.
    Energy is the bedrock of our society, and yet the SCC 
estimate of the previous Administration has killed jobs, 
limited innovation, and resulted in higher energy costs for 
American families, all in exchange for benefits that are 
negligible at best and nonexistent at worst.
    The Obama Administration's Interagency Working Group, which 
ultimately established an enormously high SCC of $37 per ton of 
CO&amp;lt;INF&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/INF&amp;gt; emitted into the atmosphere, relied on an 
outdated economic model and failed to take into account the 
White House's own Office of Management and Budget, or OMB, 
guidelines for cost-benefit analysis. Quite simply, the working 
group used numbers that got them the results they wanted in 
order to advance some of the most expensive and expansive 
regulations ever written. In pushing forward this political 
agenda, the working group acted irresponsibly. It also allowed 
the previous Administration to implement stringent and costly 
regulations without a scientific basis.
    As we will learn today, the SCC working group ignored two 
major OMB recommendations for federal agency rulemaking. First, 
it failed to use a seven percent discount rate, and instead 
relied on rates of 2.5 percent, three percent, and five 
percent. and, second, it ignored the guideline to report cost-
benefit analysis from a domestic perspective. If nothing else 
is taken away from what will be a very technical hearing, I 
hope it will be these two very basic flaws.
    The low long-term discount rate established by the previous 
Administration fundamentally disregards the notion that the 
American economy is resilient and can respond to potential 
future threats with technological development and innovation. 
As to the flaw of the previous Administration's decision to 
focus on CO&amp;lt;INF&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/INF&amp;gt; emissions from a global perspective, 
this approach leaves the United States footing the bill for 
costly regulations that are based on benefits conferred to 
other countries. It is simply not right for Americans to be 
bearing the brunt of costs when the majority of benefits will 
be conferred away from home.
    By ignoring OMB guidelines, the current SCC models leave 
critical components out of the discussion. If the OMB 
guidelines would have been followed, the social cost of carbon 
would have been significantly lower.
    The previous Administration disregarded scientific 
integrity by overestimating climate change resulting from 
greenhouse gas emissions. In order to push an expensive 
regulatory agenda, the Administration inflated the SCC to 
justify costly regulations in response to the allegedly 
terrible damage CO&amp;lt;INF&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/INF&amp;gt; emissions will cause in the 
future.
    The SCC is nothing but a one-sided manipulation of 
parameters to fit the policy-driven agendas of the previous 
Administration. These alarmist tactics need to stop. Today's 
hearing is intended to uncover the real truth and deception 
behind the SCC.
    America's strength emanates from our resilience and 
flexibility. Attempts to justify government regulations over 
industry innovations hinders growth and development. I look 
forward to working with the Trump Administration to renew faith 
in American ingenuity and technological development.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;    Chairman Biggs. I now recognize the Ranking member of the 
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;statement.
    Ms. Bonamici. Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman, and thank 
you to our witnesses for being here today.
    The social cost of carbon is a metric used to value the 
damage caused by emitting 1 ton of carbon dioxide into the 
atmosphere in a year. It provides a consistent value for all 
federal agencies to use for their cost-benefit analysis on 
regulatory efforts that reduce carbon dioxide emissions.
    There are some people who criticize this metric, but the 
Government Accountability Office and independent peer review by 
the National Academy of Sciences have validated it many times. 
Additionally, federal courts have upheld that the methodology 
used to develop the social cost of carbon is based on robust 
science and sound economic analysis. It is critical that 
updates to the social cost of carbon metric are based on the 
best available science and updated economic analysis based on 
peer-reviewed literature.
    The Government Accountability Office has found that the 
methodology used to develop the social cost of carbon was based 
on peer-reviewed academic literature and took steps to 
incorporate new information as it became available. This 
process also provided ample opportunity for public comment on 
both the social cost of carbon and the regulations that use the 
metric in their cost-benefit analysis.
    Some people suggest that regulations to reduce the 
emissions of carbon dioxide and other pollutants are 
unnecessary because climate change does not exist or human 
activity does not contribute to it, but simply ignoring a fact 
does not make it less true. The climate is warming, and we need 
to work now to limit the consequences for future generations. 
Our children and grandchildren should not inherit an 
environment that degrades their health and harms their future 
economy.
    Economic growth and reducing carbon pollution are not in 
conflict with one another. Clean energy development allows us 
to continue powering our communities in ways that avoid long-
term negative consequences on future generations. It also gives 
us the opportunity to bring new living-wage jobs into 
communities. In fact, the American Wind Energy Association 
found that the wind energy sector accounts for 3,000 jobs 
throughout my home State of Oregon alone. In addition to 
boosting Oregon's economy, wind energy generation avoided more 
than 1 million tons of statewide carbon dioxide emissions in 
2015, and many of the wind energy jobs are in rural areas where 
jobs are needed.
    The social cost of carbon is not a product of a single 
President, a single scientific study, or a single legal action. 
It is rooted in overwhelming scientific consensus on climate 
change, an effort spanning 30 years from both the executive and 
judicial branches of the Federal Government. These factors, 
coupled with a transparent development process and strong 
economic analysis, form the basis of this metric that has been 
used in at least 79 federal regulations, including fuel economy 
standards for vehicles, energy efficiency measures for home 
appliances, and regulations such as the Clean Power Plan. This 
metric was not invented to serve a political agenda but in fact 
was developed to meet a legal mandate to justify, in simple 
terms of dollars and cents, how the Federal Government's 
actions will affect Americans today and our children and 
grandchildren tomorrow.
    I look forward to hearing how we may best continue to use 
the social cost of carbon in support of policies that protect 
our environment.
    With that, I would like to again thank the witnesses for 
being here today, and I yield back the balance of my time.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;    Chairman Biggs. Thank you, Ms. Bonamici.
    I now recognize the Chairman of the Subcommittee on 
Oversight, Mr. LaHood, for his opening statement.
    Mr. LaHood. Thank you, Chairman Biggs, and happy to be part 
of this hearing today with you, today's hearing titled ``At 
What Cost? Examining the Social Cost of Carbon,'' and happy to 
have the witnesses here today as we examine the previous 
Administration's social cost of carbon and the shortfalls in 
application of this flawed process.
    There is significant evidence that the previous 
Administration manipulated the social cost of carbon 
calculation to reflect significant benefits to enacting what 
were ultimately job-killing regulations and policies across a 
wide spectrum of issues. The social cost of carbon is a flawed 
tool used by the Obama Administration to justify a green agenda 
when, in reality, the prior Administration was seeking to 
offset its costly regulations with far-reaching implications 
that burden our industries and nation.
    Unsurprisingly, the previous Administration ignored 
specific guidelines set forth by the Office of Management and 
Budget, OMB, and used the social cost of carbon as a vehicle to 
tout the economic benefits of the new environmental 
regulations. This is troubling and to me is not being honest 
with the taxpayers.
    Critics take issue primarily with two aspects of the social 
cost of carbon methodology, specifically, the discount rate 
used and the domestic versus global benefits claimed. Both 
issues I look forward to discussing in more detail with our 
panel of esteemed witnesses today.
    I, too, take issue with the methodology but also the lack 
of transparency with the use and development of the social cost 
of carbon. Three statistical integrated assessment economic 
models were used to develop the social cost of carbon: the 
FUND, the DICE, and the PAGE. Experts have concluded these 
three models are flawed and possess too many uncertainties to 
be the foundation of the benefit analysis of environmental 
regulations. If one were to change the assumptions these models 
are based on, the result will drastically differ, demonstrating 
malleability in the social cost of carbon calculation.
    Because of these realities, last year, I was pleased to be 
an original cosponsor of H.R. 5668, the Transparency and 
Honesty in Energy Regulation Act, or THERA, introduced by my 
friend and colleague Evan Jenkins of West Virginia. This 
legislation is aimed at prohibiting the Department of Energy 
and the Environmental Protection Agency from considering the 
social cost of carbon as part of any cost-benefit analysis 
unless specifically authorized by law. If signed into law, the 
DOE and the EPA would no longer rely on manipulated and 
fabricated economic benefits to justify or support new job-
killing environmental regulations. I look forward to working 
with Congressman Jenkins again on this issue this Congress.
    It appears that the social cost of carbon is nothing but a 
political tool lacking scientific integrity and transparency 
conceived and utilized by an Administration pushing a green 
agenda to the detriment of the American taxpayers. Perhaps a 
better measurement of the social cost of carbon is not the net 
damages that result from a one-metric-ton increase in carbon 
dioxide emissions in a given year but the damage inflicted on 
domestic industries, including manufacturers in my district 
like Caterpillar, by the environmental regulations justified by 
this flawed calculation.
    I would like to thank our witnesses for being here today to 
discuss this important matter. In addition, I look forward 
working with the Trump Administration to reverse the damage 
caused by the Obama Administration as it relates to this issue.
    With that, I yield back to the Chair.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;    Chairman Biggs. Thank you, Mr. LaHood.
    I now recognize the Ranking Member of the Subcommittee on 
Oversight, Mr. Beyer, for his opening statement.
    Mr. Beyer. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, and thank you, all the 
witnesses, for being here.
    You know, the social cost of carbon is a complex metric 
which our witness Dr. Greenstone has described as the most 
important number you've never heard of. Assessing and 
addressing the impact of climate change on current and future 
generations is critical. It seems already that in just the 
first few minutes of this hearing we see a dramatic difference 
between the short-term emphasis on job creation, which is 
important, and a long-term emphasis on protecting our planet.
    The social cost of carbon permits the government to help 
quantify the future economic damages as a result of carbon 
pollution that contributes to climate change and global 
warming. This metric didn't materialize out of thin and dirty 
air. It took a federal judge to mandate its use during the Bush 
Administration based on a law passed when Ronald Reagan was 
President.
    In 2009, the Obama Administration convened an interagency 
effort to formalize a consistent value for it. This was not a 
political tool. This was an attempt to protect our environment.
    We'll hear today that this development process was 
transparent, it was open to public comment, it's been validated 
over the years, and, much like our climate, it's not static and 
it changes over time in response to updated inputs. And 
although its use has been challenged in the courts recently, 
the courts have upheld the methodology used to obtain this 
estimate as proper based on real science and appropriate 
economic models.
    As a Minnesota administrative law judge determined last 
April, the preponderance of evidence supports the fact that 
federal social cost of carbon is reasonable and the best 
available measure to determine the environmental cost of 
CO&amp;lt;INF&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/INF&amp;gt;. I'm pretty certain we won't hear any of that 
today from the majority members and their witnesses. Instead, 
we'll hear the same arguments made against climate regulations 
that we've heard before. And sadly, those anti-science 
arguments both ignore the abundant scientific evidence that 
shows that climate change exists, that fossil fuel production 
is its main contributor, and will also admonish virtually any 
responsible regulatory mechanism to help protect our nation's 
citizens from the environmental, economic, and public health 
harm that results from climate change's global impacts.
    These individuals will argue already that social cost of 
carbon is outdated, inaccurate, and not a proper regulatory 
mechanism for addressing climate change. We've heard these 
arguments before. In fact, in 1982 the tobacco company R.J. 
Reynolds produced internal talking points about the social cost 
of smoking when Congressman Henry Waxman was holding hearings 
regarding the harm to the public's health from cigarette 
smoking. At the time, Representative Waxman said the annual 
smoking-related cost in lost productivity was $25.8 billion and 
$13.6 billion in annual medical costs. R.J. Reynolds said, 
quote, that ``attempts to establish a dollar value of so-called 
cost of smoking are ill-founded and unreliable,'' end quote.
    More than one decade later, in 1994, the tobacco company 
Philip Morris was producing glossy brochures to combat the 
growing evidence revolving around the harm of cigarette 
smoking. One was titled, quote, ``Debunking the Social Cost of 
Smoking,'' and an internal memo from Philip Morris said simply, 
``Philip Morris does not believe that smoking has been shown to 
pose any social cost on society.''
    So we're going to hear similar arguments today on the 
social cost of carbon emissions from fossil fuels, their impact 
on climate change. These arguments resonate loudly with the new 
Trump Administration, but they contradict the economic analysis 
and scientific evidence that supports the use of social cost of 
carbon.
    In a much-publicized recent memo, Dr.--or Thomas Pyle, the 
head of Trump's Department of Energy transition team, stated, 
quote, ``If the social cost of carbon were subjected to the 
latest science, it would certainly be much lower than what the 
Obama Administration has been using,'' end quote. And he 
suggested ending the use of it in federal rulemaking. The memo 
went on to describe plans to withdraw from the Paris Climate 
Agreement, eliminate the Clean Power Plan, increase federal oil 
and natural gas leasing, lift the moratorium on coal leasing--
in other words, more and more and more fossil fuels at greater 
cost to the environment.
    Mr. Chairman, climate change is real. Scientific evidence 
across the world, we think we are the only country in the world 
that doesn't--that has any internal disagreement about climate 
change. And as members of the Science Committee, we should be 
leading the fight to protect our nation against its impacts, 
and I hope my colleagues will be persuaded by the weight of 
evidence. The evidence becomes ever clearer with every passing 
day. And we will work together to promote policies that protect 
our future generations.
    Mr. Chair, I yield back.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;    Chairman Biggs. Thank you, Mr. Beyer.
    I now recognize the Chairman of the Full Committee, Mr. 
Smith, for his opening statement. Chairman Smith.
    Chairman Smith. Thank you, Chairman Biggs. And 
congratulations on becoming the Chairman of the Environment 
Subcommittee. I look forward to helping you restrain the EPA's 
out-of-control regulatory agenda.
    The EPA, along with other federal agencies, often bases 
their regulations on models and science not familiar to most 
Americans. Americans are led to believe that the EPA's 
regulations are based on the best science available. 
Unfortunately, this committee has discovered that that is not 
the case.
    The EPA's track record does not inspire trust. For example, 
the EPA routinely relies on nondisclosed scientific studies to 
justify its regulations, but how can Americans believe an 
agency that isn't being open and honest?
    Another little-known component of environmental regulations 
is the social cost of carbon. The EPA attempts to put a price 
on a ton of carbon emitted into the atmosphere. This term is in 
many of the EPA's regulations. However, like many of the 
Agency's determinations, it is often based on a one-sided 
political agenda.
    Many factors contribute to the value of the social cost of 
carbon. While multiple models are used to determine a value for 
carbon, the ones frequently used in regulations assume only a 
worst-case scenario for climate change impacts. Similar to 
climate models, which predict worst-case scenarios and are 
repeatedly proved wrong, the social cost of carbon used by 
federal agencies is also flawed.
    The federal government should not include faulty 
calculations to justify costly regulations. Examples would be 
the Clean Power Plan and standards used by the Department of 
Energy. Instead, it should eliminate the use of the social cost 
of carbon until a credible value can be calculated.
    Rushing to use unreliable calculations, such as the social 
cost of carbon, to justify a regulation is irresponsible and 
misleading. For instance, the EPA's Clean Power Plan would cost 
billions of dollars every year in return for a minimal benefit 
on the environment. In fact, the regulation would reduce global 
temperatures by only 0.03 degrees Celsius and limit sea level 
rise by only the width of three sheets of paper.
    One of the many components used to justify this rule is the 
social cost of carbon. This flawed value desperately attempts 
to justify the Agency's alarmist reasoning for support of the 
Clean Power Plan and other climate regulations. Agencies should 
rely on sound science, not flawed data. The fact that different 
models for the social cost of carbon exist and all have 
different values is a testament to how uncertain the science 
behind the value really is. For example, the social cost of 
carbon ranges from negative values to $37 per ton, which is the 
estimate used by government agencies under the Obama 
Administration. Before the EPA includes this value in 
rulemakings, the Agency should reassess how it is determined.
    Americans deserve credible science, not regulations based 
on data that is suspect and calculated to justify the EPA's 
climate agenda. Sound science and actual data should lead the 
way, not politically calculated social costs.
    Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I'll yield back.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;    Chairman Biggs. Thank you, Chairman Smith.
    Let me introduce our witnesses. Our first witness today is 
Dr. Ted Gayer, Vice President and Director of Economic Studies 
and Joseph A. Pechman Senior Fellow at the Brookings Institute. 
Dr. Gayer received his bachelor's degree in mathematics and 
economics from Emory, and his master's degree and Ph.D. in 
economics from Duke University.
    Our next witness is Dr. Kevin Dayaratna, Senior 
Statistician and Research Programmer at the Heritage 
Foundation's Institute for Economic Freedom and Opportunities 
Center for Data Analysis. Dr. Dayaratna received his bachelor's 
degree in applied mathematics and mathematical physics from the 
University of California at Berkeley, his master's degrees in 
mathematical statistics and business management from the 
University of Maryland, and his Ph.D. in mathematical 
statistics from the University of Maryland.
    Our third witness today is Dr. Michael Greenstone, Milton 
Friedman Professor in Economics, the College, and the Harris 
School; Director of the Interdisciplinary Energy Policy 
Institute at the University of Chicago; and Director of the 
Energy and Environment Lab at University of Chicago Urban Labs. 
Dr. Greenstone received his bachelor's degree in economics at 
Swarthmore College and his Ph.D. in economics from Princeton.
    Our final witness today will be Dr. Patrick Michaels, 
Director of the Center for the Study of Science at the Cato 
Institute and contributing author to United Nations' 
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, which was awarded 
the Nobel Peace Prize. Dr. Michaels received his bachelor's and 
master's degrees in biological sciences and plant ecology from 
the University of Chicago and his Ph.D. in ecological 
climatology from the University of Wisconsin at Madison.
    I now recognize Dr. Gayer for five minutes to present his 
testimony.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;        VICE PRESIDENT AND DIRECTOR OF ECONOMIC STUDIES
              AND JOSEPH A. PECHMAN SENIOR FELLOW
                    AT BROOKINGS INSTITUTION
    Dr. Gayer. Chairs Biggs, LaHood, and Smith; and Ranking 
Members Bonamici and Beyer; and members of the subcommittees, I 
appreciate the opportunity to appear here today to discuss the 
social cost of carbon.
    The social cost of carbon is a dollar estimate of the 
damages caused by a 1-ton increase in greenhouse gas emissions 
in a given year. It is a conceptually valid and important 
consideration when devising policies and treaties to address 
climate change, yet estimating the value of the social cost of 
carbon is an enormously complex and uncertain exercise.
    In 2009, the Obama Administration established an 
Interagency Working Group to develop a range of estimates for 
the social cost of carbon subsequently used by agencies to 
evaluate federal regulations. My focus is on the specific 
question of whether the social cost of carbon should account 
for the global or the domestic harm of a ton of greenhouse gas.
    In a world in which the United States and all the other 
major emitters of greenhouse gases adopted a coordinated set of 
policies to address climate change, then a global measure would 
be appropriate since greenhouse gases contribute to damages 
around the world no matter where they occur.
    But we don't live in such a world. Instead, in the United 
States we have opted for a suite of regulatory policies ranging 
from subsidizing lower carbon energy sources; mandating energy 
efficiency levels in buildings, vehicles, and household 
appliances; requiring transportation fuels to contain minimum 
volumes of different renewable fuels, and restricting emissions 
from electric utilities.
    Given the diversity of regulations directed at climate 
change, it is useful and important for the agencies to 
coordinate on a single measure of climate benefits. But the 
question is whether they should report and consider the 
benefits to U.S. citizens or to the world. The Interagency 
Working Group opted for a global measure.
    I believe the exclusive focus on a global measure runs 
counter to standard benefit cost practice in which only the 
benefits within the political jurisdiction bearing the cost of 
the policy are considers. It also seems at odds with the 
express intent of longstanding Executive orders and of 
authorizing statutes. For example, the main regulatory guidance 
document that has been in place for 20 years is Executive Order 
12866, which makes clear that the appropriate reference point 
for analyzing federal regulatory policy--policies is the U.S. 
citizenry, not the world.
    Similarly, when enacting the Clean Air Act, Congress stated 
that its purpose was to, quote, ``protect and enhance the 
quality of the nation's air resources so as to promote the 
public health and welfare and productive capacity of its 
population,'' end quote, which again suggests a focus on 
domestic benefits.
    The global measure is 4 to 14 times greater than the 
estimated domestic measure, which is significant. For example, 
for its proposed regulations for existing power plants, the EPA 
estimated climate benefits amounting to $30 billion in 2030. 
However, the estimated domestic climate benefits would have 
only amounted to $2 to $7 billion, which is less than EPA's 
estimated compliance cost for the rule.
    I believe that adopting a global measure for the benefits 
of a domestic policy would be justified if U.S. actions led to 
complete reciprocity from other countries. The question is 
whether efforts by the United States to regulate greenhouse 
gases might spur reciprocity by other countries to do so as 
well, generating domestic benefits that are 4 to 14 times as 
great as the direct domestic benefits to the U.S.-only policy. 
This is doubtful since the agency regulations taken under 
existing U.S. laws such as the Clean Air Act are not tantamount 
to treaty commitments that can establish a formal basis for 
other countries matching the efforts undertaken domestically.
    By using the global social cost of carbon, the agencies are 
claiming that their rules provide benefits that in fact largely 
accrue to foreign citizens. Of course, many Americans are 
altruistic and care about the welfare of people beyond our 
borders, but foreign aid decisions should be made openly and 
not hidden in an obscure metric used in domestic rulemaking.
    A global measure of the social cost of carbon is 
appropriate if the intent is to use it to support the 
development of a global system of reducing greenhouse gases, 
such as through a worldwide carbon tax. I favor a carbon tax 
for the United States that replaces regulations and relies on 
border tax adjustments to incentivize other major emitters to 
follow suit. But absent such an approach, for domestic agencies 
considering domestic regulations in which the costs are 
incurred domestically, a global measure deviates from standard 
practice and requires more scrutiny and justification than it 
has received to date. At the very least, agencies should report 
the expected domestic benefits and only separately and 
transparently report the expected foreign benefits of their 
actions informed by concrete evidence of reciprocity expected 
from other countries.
    Thank you.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;    Chairman Biggs. Thank you, Dr. Gayer.
    I now recognize Dr. Dayaratna for five minutes to present 
his testimony.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;          SENIOR STATISTICIAN AND RESEARCH PROGRAMMER,
                   CENTER FOR DATA ANALYSIS,
                 INSTITUTE FOR ECONOMIC FREEDOM
           AND OPPORTUNITY AT THE HERITAGE FOUNDATION
    Dr. Dayaratna. Chairman Biggs, Ranking Member Bonamici, and 
other Members of the Subcommittees, thank you for the 
opportunity to testify about the social cost of carbon.
    My name is Kevin Dayaratna. I'm the Senior Statistician and 
Research Programmer at the Heritage Foundation. The views I 
express in this testimony are my own and should not be 
construed as representing any official position of the Heritage 
Foundation.
    One of the primary metrics that the previous Administration 
had used to justify agenda regarding energy policy--justify 
regulatory--its regulatory agenda regarding energy policy is 
the social cost of carbon, which is defined as the economic 
damages associated with a metric ton of carbon dioxide 
emissions summed across a particular time horizon.
    There are three primary statistical models that the Obama 
Administration's Interagency Working Group had used to estimate 
the SCC, the DC. model, the FUND model, and the PAGE model. My 
colleagues and I have used the DC. and FUND models, testing 
their sensitivity to a variety of important assumptions. Our 
work, published both at Heritage, as well as in the peer-
reviewed literature, as repeatedly illustrated that while these 
models might be interesting for academic exercises, they can be 
readily manipulated by regulators and bureaucrats.
    In particular, as with any statistical model, they are 
dependent on various assumptions. I'd like to discuss three 
assumptions regularly manipulated to achieve predetermined 
outcomes: the choice of a discount rate, a time horizon, and 
the specification of an equilibrium climate sensitivity 
distribution.
    The first easily manipulated assumption is the discount 
rate. In this type of cost-benefit analysis, the discount rate 
should reflect the rate of return on generally achievable 
alternative investments. The IWG had run these models using 
2.5, 3, and five percent discount rates despite the fact that 
OMB guidance in circular A-4 had specifically stipulated that a 
seven percent discount rate be used as well.
    At Heritage, we re-estimated these models using a seven 
percent discount rate and noticed drastic reductions to the 
SCC. In 2020, for example, according to our recent analysis of 
the DC. model published in the peer-reviewed journal Climate 
Change Economics, under a three percent discount rate, the SCC 
is estimated to cost $37.79 per ton, while under a seven 
percent discount rate, it is estimated to be $5.87, an 84 
percent reduction. The higher estimates previously found by the 
IWG can enable policymakers to justify unnecessary regulations 
and taxes on the economy.
    The second easily manipulated assumption is the 
specification of a time horizon. It is close to impossible to 
forecast what the economy will look like decades into the 
future. Foolishly, these models attempt to make projections not 
decades but rather three centuries into the future. In my work 
at Heritage, I have changed the time horizon to a significantly 
shorter but still unrealistic time horizon of 150 years into 
the future. With the DC. model, we find that these results 
plummet by 25 percent in some instances.
    The third readily manipulated variable is the model's 
equilibrium climate sensitivity, or ECS, distribution, 
quantifying the Earth's temperature response to a doubling of 
carbon dioxide concentration. My colleague Dr. Pat Michaels 
will go into this in more detail, but the IWG used an ECS 
distribution that was published ten years ago in the journal 
Science. Since then, a number of newer ECS distributions have 
been published suggesting lower probabilities of extreme global 
warming.
    Using the more up-to-date ECS distributions generate 
significantly lower estimates of the SCC. In our peer-reviewed 
work, we found that, as a result of updating the ECS 
distributions, the results drop by as much as 197 percent under 
some circumstances. Inflated estimates of climate sensitivity 
drive up the SCC, which can become manifested in unnecessary 
regulations.
    Finally, the unexplored issue here is are there any 
benefits associated with carbon dioxide emissions? The answer 
is surprisingly yes. The FUND model actually allows for 
negative SCC, meaning a positive outcome. In fact, under some 
assumptions, there are actual substantial probabilities of 
negative SCC, meaning increased CO&amp;lt;INF&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/INF&amp;gt; fertilization, 
leading to increased agriculture and forestry yields.
    Moreover, if one were to take the IWG's interpretation of 
these models seriously and implement the associated 
regulations, there would be significant damage to the economy. 
In particular, our analysis finds that by 2035 the country 
would experience an average employment shortfall of 400,000 
lost jobs, a marked increase in electricity prices, and an 
aggregate $2.5 trillion loss in GDP.
    Our analysis using the model for the assessment of 
greenhouse gas-induced climate change has found that these 
devastating impacts would be accompanied by insignificant 
changes and less than 2/10 of a degree Celsius in temperature 
mitigation and less than 2 centimeters of sea level rise 
reduction.
    In conclusion, the SCC is a broken tool for regulatory 
policy and taking it seriously would provide significant harm 
and little environmental benefit.
    Thank you for your attention, and I look forward to your 
questions.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;    Chairman Biggs. Thank you, Dr. Dayaratna.
    I now recognize Dr. Greenstone for five minutes to present 
his testimony.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;            MILTON FRIEDMAN PROFESSOR IN ECONOMICS,
              THE COLLEGE, AND THE HARRIS SCHOOL;
               DIRECTOR OF THE INTERDISCIPLINARY
      ENERGY POLICY INSTITUTE AT THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO
                AND THE ENERGY &amp;amp; ENVIRONMENT LAB
            AT THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO URBAN LABS
    Dr. Greenstone. Thank you, Chairmen Biggs and LaHood, 
Ranking Members Bonamici and Beyer, and Members of the 
Subcommittees, for inviting me to speak today.
    My name is Michael Greenstone, and I'm the Milton Friedman 
Professor in Economics and Director of the Energy Policy 
Institute at the University of Chicago.
    The social cost of carbon is a monetized value of the 
damages from the release of an additional ton of 
CO&amp;lt;INF&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/INF&amp;gt;. This means that it can be used to determine the 
benefits of regulations that reduce CO&amp;lt;INF&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/INF&amp;gt; emissions. 
Indeed, these benefits can then be compared to the costs that 
regulations impose to determine whether the regulation is 
beneficial or not.
    In 2009, while working in the Obama Administration, Cass 
Sunstein and I convened and co-led an Interagency Working Group 
to determine a government-wide value for the social cost of 
carbon. Ultimately, the Interagency Working Group determined a 
central estimate of $21 per metric ton. That estimate has since 
been revised to reflect scientific advances and is now about 
$36.
    The approach has been judged valid. Last August, the 
Federal Court of Appeals rejected a legal challenge to the 
metric. Further, the General Accounting Office has said that 
the working group's processes and methods reflected key 
principles that ensured its credibility: It used consensus-
based decision-making, relied largely on existing academic 
literature and models; and disclosed limitations and 
incorporated new information by considering public comments and 
revising the estimates as updated research became available.
    Indeed, the social cost of carbon's credibility is 
underscored by the fact that it has been adopted by the 
governments of California, Illinois, Minnesota, Maine, New 
York, and Washington State, not to mention Canada and Mexico.
    Before concluding my testimony today, I would like to 
address two frequent critiques of the social cost of carbon. 
One such critique is that the real discount rates used--2.5, 3, 
and 5 percent--are too low. Why is a discount rate so 
important? If we choose a discount rate that is too low, then 
we're going to pay too much for mitigation efforts today. If 
instead we choose one that's too high, then we will impose 
higher climate damages on our children and grandchildren than 
we intend.
    Economic theory tells us that we'll be best off if the 
discount rate is equal to the market interest rate from 
investments that match the structure of payoffs that climate 
mitigation provides. If we thought climate damages were likely 
to be imposed consistently and predictably over time, then it 
would be appropriate to set a discount rate equal to something 
like the average return for the stock market. That's about 5.3 
percent over the last 50 years.
    But, on the other hand, if we think climate damages could 
be unpredictable and that tail risk points towards major 
losses, then markets, markets themselves, tell us to use a 
lower discount rate. Consider the case of gold. Its average 
return is only about three percent, yet people hold it as an 
investment. Why is that? The reason is that it pays off 
dramatically during infrequent episodes of economic distress. 
For example, during the Great Recession, gold outperformed the 
stock market by 67 percent.
    When one considers the possibility of large temperature 
changes for given increases in emissions, great sea level rise 
in relatively short periods of time, the possibility of 
physical tipping points or human responses to these changes 
that include mass migration, then the case for using a low 
discount rate to determine the social cost of carbon appears 
strong.
    In addition to this conceptual reason to prefer low 
discount rates, the decline in global interest rates, so 
another market-based reason, since the mid-1980s provides 
another reason. The three percent real discount rate that has 
been a cornerstone of regulatory analysis since 2003 draws its 
justification from the fact that it was roughly equal to the 
real rate of return on long-term government debt at that time.
    However, the world has changed. Rates are now much lower 
and indeed the comparable rate is now probably below two 
percent. Put another way, capital markets are trying to tell us 
to use discount rates that are lower than those currently being 
used to determine the social cost of carbon.
    A second criticism of the social cost of carbon is that it 
reflects global costs from emissions, but the United States 
should only be concerned with domestic damages. However, this 
criticism misses an important point that the goal of policy is 
to maximize net benefits to Americans and that recognizing 
foreign damages is likely to increase net benefits.
    Why is this the case? It's because each ton of CO&amp;lt;INF&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/INF&amp;gt; 
emitted outside the United States inflicts damages on us. Thus, 
we benefit when China, India, the European Union, and others 
reduce their emissions. It absolutely strains credibility to 
assume that these countries' emissions cuts would be as large 
as if we reverted to a social cost of carbon based only on 
domestic damages.
    In many respects, the Paris Climate Agreement, where nearly 
200 countries agreed to take action on carbon emissions, is a 
validation of the importance of treating climate change is a 
global problem.
    To summarize, society needs to balance the cost to our 
economy of mitigating climate change with the coming climate 
damages. Wishing that we did not face this tradeoff will not 
make it go away. Ultimately, we will be better off if a social 
cost of carbon based on sound science, economics, and law, 
continues to serve as a lynchpin of regulatory policy. Thank 
you.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;    Chairman Biggs. Thank you, Dr. Greenstone.
    I'll now recognize Dr. Michaels for five minutes to present 
his testimony.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;        CENTER FOR THE STUDY OF SCIENCE, CATO INSTITUTE;
             CONTRIBUTING AUTHOR TO UNITED NATIONS
           INTERGOVERNMENTAL PANEL ON CLIMATE CHANGE
                    (NOBEL PEACE PRIZE 2007)
    Dr. Michaels. May we have the first image? Thank you.
    [Slide.]
    Dr. Michaels. Mr. Chairman, Ranking Members, Members of the 
Subcommittees, thank you for inviting my testimony on 
scientific problems relating to the current calculation of the 
social cost of carbon or SCC. I am Patrick J. Michaels, 
Director of the Center for the Study of Science at the Cato 
Institute. Prior to that, I was a Research Professor of 
Environmental Sciences at University of Virginia for 30 years.
    A year-and-a-half ago I testified to the Committee on 
Natural Resources that the Obama Administration's calculations 
of the SCC were in contravention of a large and growing body of 
scientific literature--next image----
    [Slide.]
    --demonstrating that the sensitivity of temperature to 
human emission of carbon dioxide is not nearly as large as was 
previously thought. And more important, the chance of a high-
end warming has greatly diminished. Since then, the evidence 
has grown stronger.
    Climate sensitivity is the amount of net warming one gets 
for doubling atmospheric carbon dioxide. It also roughly 
approximates the forecast for surface warming for the 21st 
century. The Obama Administration used a sensitivity 
specification by Roe and Baker, which is the top line there, 
that had a mean sensitivity of 3.0 degrees C and a 5 to 95 
percent confidence limit of 1.7 to 7.14 degrees C, a very large 
number.
    Beginning in 2011, all this work down here, a growing body 
of the scientific literature has yielded 32 new estimates of 
the sensitivity generated by more than 50 researchers from 
around the world with a mean sensitivity of 2 degrees C and a 5 
to 95 percent confidence limit of 1.1 to 3.5 degrees C.
    The large distributions of warming--next image--
    [Slide.]
    --used in Roe and Baker resulted in large part because of 
extremely wide range of estimates of the cooling effects of 
sulfate aerosols, another human emission. These were 
dramatically narrowed by researchers Nick Lewis and Judith 
Curry of Georgia Tech, which greatly reduced the sensitivity, 
as you can see here, and the spread around that sensitivity.
    As my colleague Kevin Dayaratna has shown, the newer more 
reality-based estimates result in a dramatic lowering of the 
SCC. Next image.
    [Slide.]
    Let's now have a look at how well those climate models that 
were used to calculate the previous Administration's SCC are 
doing. This illustration is a further update of an analysis 
initially presented in the testimony of John Christy in 2015 
with data that ended in 2014. The uptick in observed warming at 
the end of the record is an apparent improvement between the 
models and reality. But it is not. Instead, it is the 2015/2016 
El Nino.
    Next image.
    [Slide.]
    And that spread is likely to widen again in recent years, 
as you can see from surface temperatures here that they have 
dropped back down very close to their previous El Nino value.
    [Slide.]
    Next is a chart of predicted trends and tropical 
temperatures measured vertically. This is where the largest 
integrated warming on Earth is forecast to occur. The green 
line on the left is reality, which is--generally shows two to 
three times less warming than has been predicted. At the top of 
the active weather zone around here, the forecast is 
approximately seven times less than--or seven times more than 
is what is being observed. To deny this reality is to deny 
science.
    It is the vertical temperature distribution that largely 
determines daily weather. If this is forecast incorrectly, then 
any subsidiary forecast of surface weather regimes are of 
little to no value. To deny that is to deny science.
    There is another systematic error on the previous 
calculations of the SCC. We live on a planet that is becoming 
greener because of the direct--next image----
    [Slide.]
    --physiological effects of increasing carbon dioxide on 
plant photosynthesis. A massive survey of the scientific 
literature by Dr. Craig Idso shows this caused a $3.2 trillion 
increment in agricultural output from 1961 through 2011. My 
colleague Mr. Dayaratna has shown that a more realistic 
sensitivity in carbon dioxide fertilization can result in a 
negative SCC or a net external benefit from the production of 
carbon dioxide.
    In closing, I provide you this image of the greening of our 
luke-warming home planet, as taken by NASA satellites. Where 
there are dots, the changes are statistically significant. Note 
that the greatest increases, the ones in pink, are in the 
margins of the world's deserts and the tropical rainforest, 
places we all feared for. To acknowledge this is to affirm 
reality.
    Thank you very much for inviting my testimony.
&lt;/option&gt;
</Directory>
</Hearing>
