<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="33312">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;Doc-title&gt;MARKUP OF COMMITTEE RESOLUTION 115-21&lt;/Doc-title&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;=======================================================================
                                 MARKUP
                               BEFORE THE
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;committee_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON HOUSE&lt;/committee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                             ADMINISTRATION
                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             SECOND SESSION
                               __________
                           SEPTEMBER 26, 2018
                               __________
      Printed for the use of the Committee on House Administration
                       Available on the Internet:
         http://www.govinfo.gov/committee/house-administration        
                              _________ 
                U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
 33-312                  WASHINGTON : 2018            
                   Committee on House Administration              
                  GREGG HARPER, Mississippi, Chairman
RODNEY DAVIS, Illinois, Vice         ROBERT A. BRADY, Pennsylvania,
    Chairman                           Ranking Member
BARBARA COMSTOCK, Virginia           ZOE LOFGREN, California
MARK WALKER, North Carolina          JAMIE RASKIN, Maryland
ADRIAN SMITH, Nebraska
BARRY LOUDERMILK, Georgia
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;Doc-title&gt;MARKUP OF COMMITTEE RESOLUTION 115-21&lt;/Doc-title&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="1" speaker=""&gt;The Committee met, pursuant to call, at 11:00 a.m., in Room 
1310, Longworth House Office Building, Hon. Gregg Harper 
[Chairman of the Committee] presiding.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;hearing-info paraId="2" speaker=""&gt;Present: Representatives Harper, Davis, Walker, Smith, 
Loudermilk, and Brady.&lt;/hearing-info&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="3" speaker=""&gt;    Staff Present: Sean Moran, Staff Director; Kim Betz, Deputy 
Staff Director/Policy and Oversight; Steven Wall, Deputy 
General Counsel; Dan Jarrell, Legislative Clerk; Elizabeth 
Joseph, Professional Staff; Courtney Parella, Communications 
Director; Jamie Fleet, Minority Staff Director; Khalil Abboud, 
Minority Deputy Staff Director; and Eddie Flaherty, Minority 
Chief Clerk.
&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="3" speaker=""&gt;    The Chairman. I now call to order the Committee on House &lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="4" speaker=""&gt;Staff Present: Sean Moran, Staff Director; Kim Betz, Deputy 
Staff Director/Policy and Oversight; Steven Wall, Deputy 
General Counsel; Dan Jarrell, Legislative Clerk; Elizabeth 
Joseph, Professional Staff; Courtney Parella, Communications 
Director; Jamie Fleet, Minority Staff Director; Khalil Abboud, 
Minority Deputy Staff Director; and Eddie Flaherty, Minority 
Chief Clerk.
Administration. For purposes of today's Committee meeting, a 
quorum is present, so we may proceed. The meeting record will 
remain open for 5 legislative days so that Members may submit 
any materials they wish to be included therein.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="5" speaker=""&gt;There is one item on the docket today, and that is 
Committee Resolution 115-21, adopting the recommended standards 
and processes submitted by the House officers in response to 
Committee Resolutions 115-13 through 18.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="6" speaker=""&gt;As you all recall, this past April the Committee adopted a 
package of resolutions, Committee Resolutions 115-13 through 
115-18, to strengthen the oversight of shared administrative 
employees.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="7" speaker=""&gt;The resolution set forth policies and the Committee 
identified as essential to ensuring that risks posed to the 
House by the practice of sharing employees were sufficiently 
mitigated.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="8" speaker=""&gt;The resolutions directed the House Chief Administrative 
Officer, the House Sergeant-at-Arms, and the Clerk of the House 
to report back to the Committee within 30 days on the plans to 
implement these policies.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="9" speaker=""&gt;While each House officer met the deadline, the Committee 
allowed for extra time to address concerns more thoroughly. The 
Committee received revised standards and processes from the 
Chief Administrative Officer on September 14, 2018.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="10" speaker=""&gt;Last night the Committee received an additional letter from 
the CAO, a copy of which you all have been provided. I ask 
unanimous consent that the letter be entered into the record, 
and without objection, so entered.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="11" speaker=""&gt;    [The information follows:]
&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="11" speaker=""&gt;    The Chairman. The Committee is prepared to adopt today &lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="12" speaker=""&gt;[The information follows:]
those revised standards and processes, as well as the 
recommendations previously submitted by the House Sergeant-at-
Arms and the Clerk of the House.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="13" speaker=""&gt;    I would now like to recognize the Ranking Member, Mr. 
Brady, for the purpose of providing an opening statement.
&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;speaker&gt;Mr. Brady&lt;/speaker&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="14" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Thank you for calling
this meeting.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="15" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;Mr. Chairman, unless the Committee meets in a lame duck, 
this is likely to be the last time we will be sitting together 
at this dais, and I want you to know it has been an absolute 
pleasure to work with you.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="16" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;You have been a total class act the entire time as you have 
been Chairman. And the few things, very, very few things I will 
miss is to be working with you, not being here.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="17" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;I have said many times before I would like to thank you for 
your bipartisan work, working together, and making it a 
pleasure to work on this Committee.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="18" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;We have worked on shared employees issues for years, and 
today represents another step in trying to find the balance 
between letting Members run their offices with broad discretion 
and working to make sure that all our rules and regulations are 
followed and enforced.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="19" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;I would like to also thank Mr. Davis for having meetings 
with me and my staff and many other meetings.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="20" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;I believe this might be your baby. You really worked on 
this and cared for it and now it is coming to fruition.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="21" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;So while I am certain the next Congress will continue to 
wrestle with these issues, hopefully it will be a little easier 
because of the work we do here today.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="22" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;I want to thank the shared employees who gave us feedback 
for this proposal. I know it is not everything you wanted, but 
hopefully it represents a compromise document that helps 
improve how our House operations. I support the resolution 
before us and urge my colleagues to do the same.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="23" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;    And before I yield back the balance of my time, Mr. 
Chairman, I want to give you a hug.
&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="23" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;    The Chairman. You know, they usually only write or do news &lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="24" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;    And before I yield back the balance of my time, Mr. 
Chairman, I want to give you a hug.
stories on the fussing and fighting.
&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;speaker&gt;Mr. Brady&lt;/speaker&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="25" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt; That is why they are never here.
&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;speaker&gt;The Chairman. I know&lt;/speaker&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="26" speaker="The Chairman. I know"&gt; I know. But what I want to say is, I
want to echo those sentiments. And I am going to miss working 
with you, but I hope that we can maintain this friendship past 
Congress.
&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;speaker&gt;Mr. Brady&lt;/speaker&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="27" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt; I hope so.
&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="27" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;    The Chairman. And would love to come up to Philadelphia for &lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="28" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt; I hope so.
some sightseeing and hang out with you Mr. Brady. There is a 
Philadelphia, Mississippi, isn't there?
&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;speaker&gt;The Chairman. There is&lt;/speaker&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="29" speaker="The Chairman. There is"&gt; It is in my district, as a matter
of fact. And it is a great place. Mississippi Band of Choctaw 
Indians is located in Philadelphia. And also the Williams 
Brothers Grocery is there, and that is the family of Archie 
Manning's wife, Olivia. So, I mean, you would almost have to go 
to Williams Brothers to check it out.
&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;speaker&gt;Mr. Brady&lt;/speaker&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="30" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt; Thank you.
&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="30" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;    The Chairman. And I just want to thank you, not just for &lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="31" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;Thank you.
the way we have worked together for these 10 years, but your 
friendship. And if this is our last hearing, I will always 
remember the special hug, and I appreciate that. Thank you.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="32" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;I would ask if any other Member of the Committee wishes to 
be recognized for the purpose of providing an opening 
statement.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="33" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;I now call up and lay before the Committee, Committee 
Resolution 115-21, to adopt the recommended standards and 
processes submitted by the House officers in response to the 
directives laid out in Committee Resolutions 115-13 through 
115-18. Without objection, the first reading of the resolution 
is dispensed with and the resolution is considered read and 
open for amendment.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="34" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;    [The resolution follows:]
&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="34" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;    The Chairman. Is there any debate? Are there any Members &lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="35" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;[The resolution follows:]
who want to offer an amendment to the resolution?&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="36" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;If not, I move the Committee adopt the resolution. The 
question is on the motion.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="37" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;All those in favor, signify by saying aye.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="38" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;Opposed, say nay.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="39" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;In the opinion of the Chair, the ayes have it.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="40" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;Without objection, the motion to reconsider is laid upon 
the table. I ask unanimous consent that the staff be allowed to 
make necessary technical and conforming changes to the bills 
ordered reported today subject to the approval of the minority. 
Hearing no objection, so ordered.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="41" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;I would like to now take a moment before we adjourn because 
this may be one of the last business meetings this Committee 
holds this year. I want to thank every person, every Member on 
this Committee, majority and minority.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="42" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;I have been on the Committee on House Administration since 
I started in January of 2009 with Mr. Brady as the Chairman, 
and it has been a great Committee to be on. We have worked 
together almost always in a bipartisan method and manner.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="43" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;And in the times that we didn't agree, I just want to 
compliment Mr. Brady because it was never, the differences that 
we had were never personal. They may have been on policy or 
issues. But I think Congress works better this way.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="44" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;And I thank each of you for your service on this Committee, 
and I wish everyone well as we go through the rest of this 
year.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
    &lt;paragraph paraId="45" speaker="Mr. Brady"&gt;And now, without objection, this markup is adjourned.&lt;/paragraph&gt;
</intro>
</Hearing>
