<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="33110">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;115th Congress }                            Printed for the use of the             &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;2nd Session    }      Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe                       &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;======================================================================&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	            A New Approach to Europe?  U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	           Interests, Nationalist Movements&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	               and the European Union&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                          November 1, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                           Briefing of the&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         Washington: 2019&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;      Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  234 Ford House Office Building                                               &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   Washington, DC 20515&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      202-225-1901&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      csce@mail.house.gov&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      http://www.csce.gov&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         @HelsinkiComm&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            Legislative Branch Commissioners&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;              HOUSE				SENATE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;CHRISTOPHER H. SMITH, New Jersey 	ROGER WICKER, Mississippi,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Co-Chairman			  Chairman&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ALCEE L. HASTINGS, Florida		BENJAMIN L. CARDIN. Maryland&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ROBERT B. ADERHOLT, Alabama		JOHN BOOZMAN, Arkansas&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;MICHAEL C. BURGESS, Texas		CORY GARDNER, Colorado&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;STEVE COHEN, Tennessee			MARCO RUBIO, Florida&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;RICHARD HUDSON, North Carolina		JEANNE SHAHEEN, New Hampshire&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;RANDY HULTGREN, Illinois		THOM TILLIS, North Carolina&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;SHEILA JACKSON LEE, Texas		TOM UDALL, New Mexico&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;GWEN MOORE, Wisconsin			SHELDON WHITEHOUSE, Rhode Island&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;               Executive Branch Commissioners&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                    DEPARTMENT OF STATE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  DEPARTMENT OF COMMERCE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                            [II]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Helsinki process, formally titled the Conference on Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe, traces its origin to the signing of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Helsinki Final Act in Finland on August 1, 1975, by the leaders of 33 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European countries, the United States and Canada. As of January 1, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;1995, the Helsinki process was renamed the Organization for Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE). The membership of the OSCE has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;expanded to 56 participating States, reflecting the breakup of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Soviet Union, Czechoslovakia, and Yugoslavia.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The OSCE Secretariat is in Vienna, Austria, where weekly meetings &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the participating States' permanent representatives are held. In &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;addition, specialized seminars and meetings are convened in various &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;locations. Periodic consultations are held among Senior Officials, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Ministers and Heads of State or Government.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Although the OSCE continues to engage in standard setting in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fields of military security, economic and environmental cooperation, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and human rights and humanitarian concerns, the Organization is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;primarily focused on initiatives designed to prevent, manage and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resolve conflict within and among the participating States. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Organization deploys numerous missions and field activities located in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Southeastern and Eastern Europe, the Caucasus, and Central Asia. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;website of the OSCE is: &amp;lt;www.osce.org&amp;gt;.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, also known as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Helsinki Commission, is a U.S. Government agency created in 1976 to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;monitor and encourage compliance by the participating States with their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;OSCE commitments, with a particular emphasis on human rights.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission consists of nine members from the United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Senate, nine members from the House of Representatives, and one member &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;each from the Departments of State, Defense and Commerce. The positions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Chair and Co-Chair rotate between the Senate and House every two &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years, when a new Congress convenes. A professional staff assists the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commissioners in their work.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In fulfilling its mandate, the Commission gathers and disseminates &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relevant information to the U.S. Congress and the public by convening &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hearings, issuing reports that reflect the views of Members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission and/or its staff, and providing details about the activities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the Helsinki process and developments in OSCE participating States.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission also contributes to the formulation and execution of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.S. policy regarding the OSCE, including through Member and staff &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participation on U.S. Delegations to OSCE meetings. Members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission have regular contact with parliamentarians, government &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;officials, representatives of non-governmental organizations, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;private individuals from participating States. The website of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission is: &amp;lt;www.csce.gov&amp;gt;.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;             A New Approach to Europe? U.S.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;           Interests, Nationalist Movements, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                and the European Union&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                            November 1, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                  				Page&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              PARTICIPANTS&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Kyle Parker, Chief of Staff, Commission for Security and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Cooperation in Europe						    1&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Alex Tiersky, Senior Policy Advisor, Commission for Security and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Cooperation in Europe						    2&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Ted R. Bromund, Senior Research Fellow in Anglo-American &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Relations, Margaret Thatcher Center for Freedom, The Heritage &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Foundation							    3&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Paul Coyer, Research Professor, The Institute of World Politics&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;								    7&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Jeffrey Rathke, President, American Institute for Contemporary &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;German Studies, Johns Hopkins University			   10&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;A New Approach to Europe? U.S. Interests, Nationalist Movements,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                        and the European Union&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              ----------                              &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                            November 1, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The briefing was held at 10:00 a.m. in Room 562, Dirksen Senate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Office Building, Washington, DC, Alex Tiersky, Senior Policy Advisor, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission for Security and Cooperation in Europe, presiding.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Panelists present: Kyle Parker, Chief of Staff, Commission for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Security and Cooperation in Europe; Alex Tiersky, Senior Policy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Advisor, Commission for Security and Cooperation in Europe; Dr. Ted R. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Bromund, Senior Research Fellow in Anglo-American Relations, Margaret &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Thatcher Center for Freedom, The Heritage Foundation; Dr. Paul Coyer, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Research Professor, The Institute of World Politics; and Jeffrey &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Rathke, President, American Institute for Contemporary German Studies, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Johns Hopkins University.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Parker. Good morning, everyone. My name is Kyle Parker. I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with the U.S. Helsinki Commission. I'd like to welcome you all today to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our briefing, ``A New Approach to Europe.''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Here at the Helsinki Commission we have the luxury of looking a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;little further ahead, going a little deeper on some of the questions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that occupy the minds of the legislative branch as well as general &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;national security questions that are confronting the United States. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;one of the things, of course, in the past year or two is--there's a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tension in transatlantic relations. Something has clearly changed.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think it's fair enough to say that the relationship is in flux, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;maybe even strained. Look at many things that characterize this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;moment--the populist movements, the strong euro-skeptic threat in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe, Brexit, fairly robust pro-NATO sentiment, real concern in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;east about Moscow's intentions, concerns on Europe's southern flank &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with immigration, and a number of policy questions that surround that.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    At the same time, I think it's fair to say that a lot remains the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;same, in that the United States' national security goal post-war, of a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe that's whole, free, and at peace, remains. And so there's a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;question of how will we use the institutions that we participate in--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;namely NATO and the OSCE--to advance those goals in this context? And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;where does that place us vis-a-vis the EU, which, of course, we are not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;members of.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So in our discussion today we have a solid panel who will bring &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;divergent viewpoints to this and hopefully raise some provocative &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;questions. I'd just like to lay out three questions we should shed some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;light on. And the first one is the question of patriotism, national &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;identity. How much does the lack of what we here in the United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would consider not simply a benign but a positive, even essential, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;flag-waving patriotism--how much does the lack of that in Europe &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;contribute to the unwillingness of populaces in many of the countries &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to spend what is necessary to defend their own state, and meet its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;obvious defense needs, and also to meet their collective security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;obligations?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So in that sense is NATO necessarily pitted against the EU? Can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;NATO be aggrandized--or should NATO be aggrandized at the EU's expense, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from our perspective? Our attention, understanding the moment we're in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and thinking, Well, there's broad overlap between these organizations--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;let's shore up NATO and let the chips fall where they may on the EU? So &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that would be my first question.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I also would be interested in this--to what extent is the burden--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it's obvious in our own domestic debate that the burden-sharing is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;politically important. And our current leadership has made it even more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;important and really highlighted it. But on a tactical and technical &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;level how critical is it from our perspective? I think from the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;perspectives of the states themselves it's obvious, to be able to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;defend yourself. But from our perspective, how important is it that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these targets are met, and met in the frame that we'd like to see them &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;met?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And finally, let's imagine we arrive at the high-class problem &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;where Germany spends 2 percent or more on national defense. If we were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to see that, would we not have other problems in what might look like &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;German militarization? And the fact that, with German politics in flux, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we're not going to see that happen under a Chancellor Merkel. What sort &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of leadership would we see that happen under in Germany? And what sorts &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of unanticipated effects might that cause politically in neighboring &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;states--Poland, and France, and other places?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Those are the questions I have. And without any further delay, I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;looking forward to everyone's presentation, and will turn this over to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;my colleague Alex to moderate our discussion.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Thank you, Kyle. Let me add my welcome to everybody &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;here. I see a very healthy audience that we have, which I take is an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;excellent sign of interest in this set of topics, and certainly in our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;distinguished colleagues who have joined us on the panel to have this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conversation.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Kyle, thank you for your intellectual leadership in laying out some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the questions that we anticipate discussing today. I would only add &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that the commission has a track record of kind of big thinking on a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;number of these issues, and certainly an engagement policy-wise on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;issues ranging from the security framework of Europe, to include, for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;instance, this briefing.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In the folders that you may have picked up, there's a resolution &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that was introduced by our chairman, Senator Wicker, joined by our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;senior Democratic Senator, Ben Cardin, and two other of our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;commissioners, Senators Tillis and Shaheen, who are the leaders of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Senate NATO Observers Group. They introduced together a resolution in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;advance of the most recent NATO summit talking about exactly these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;issues of transatlantic relationship and United States interests.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would also point out that not very long ago we had an event &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;featuring members of the European Parliament to talk about some of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these questions. They were here trying to assess continued United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States interest in their institution and collaboration across the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Atlantic. So this, I think, fits well within the breadth of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;coverage that the Helsinki Commission devotes to these questions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So, without further ado, my role here principally is that of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;traffic cop. And what I would suggest that we do is, I will introduce &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our speakers. I'll ask them for some opening comments, in the order you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;see them to my left. And, dear audience, I will turn to you for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;questions. I will assume that you will be jotting down those questions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you will have when the time comes, after I take the moderator's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prerogative to push our panelists a little bit in areas in which they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;may agree and in areas in which they disagree.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Let me very quickly introduce the speakers I have been lauding. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;First, to my left, will be our first presenter, Dr. Ted Bromund. He is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the senior research fellow in Anglo-American relations at the Margaret &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Thatcher Center for Freedom of the Heritage Foundation. To say he &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;writes prolifically would be an understatement. He previously served as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;associate director of international security studies at Yale. And we've &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;asked him to offer us a broad-strokes overview of United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relations with Europe in a historical context, as well as thinking hard &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about what the European Union's role is as a security provider in its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;own region today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Our second presenter will be Dr. Paul Coyer of the Institute of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;World Politics. He'll be offering his thoughts on the nature of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nationalism in Europe today, that's been alluded to already, and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;implications of some of these trends on transatlantic relations. Dr. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Coyer, who is a historian, is a contributor to Forbes magazine and a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;contributing editor of Providence, a journal of Christianity and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;American foreign policy. Of course, we're always also happy to welcome &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;back a former Hill staffer.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Last, we will hear from Jeff Rathke, who serves as president of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;American Institute for Contemporary German Studies at the Johns Hopkins &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;University. Jeff, congratulations, again, on that still relatively &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;recent appointment. I think they selected a terrific candidate. Prior &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to joining the institute, Jeff was the senior fellow and deputy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;director of the Europe program at the Center for Strategic and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;International Studies (CSIS). He joined CSIS in 2015 from an extremely &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;distinguished career at the Department of State, where he served as a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;foreign service officer for 24 years. And in that distinguished career, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;he was primarily dedicated to U.S. relations with Europe, including &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;stints at NATO headquarters.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So three very different backgrounds to assess this set of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;questions. I'm looking forward to their presentations. Ted, please &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;start us off.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Bromund. Thanks very much. Real pleasure to be here. And I want &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to start off by thanking Alex Tiersky and Kyle Parker for conceiving of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and organizing this briefing. It's an important subject, because U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;policy toward Europe has changed fundamentally since 1945, and in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;particular since 1989. But in my view, the shifts in U.S. policy have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not been well considered or well understood, in part because most of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the relevant scholars, policymakers, and funding derive from a single &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;perspective--that of the European Union.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So in my view, the U.S. does not need a new policy toward Europe. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;It already has a new policy toward Europe. And it's had a new policy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;toward Europe since the end of the cold war. It needs to return to its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;former policy, from which it has thoughtlessly strayed. Inevitably, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this briefing, like any discussion of Europe, raises the question of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;populism. I'm not entirely sure what is meant by the term populism, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;except that it is obviously used to describe parties, movements, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;beliefs that the speaker dislikes. It is a negative term.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    At the level of politics, what is happening is that in many &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European nations--except for Britain, interestingly--established &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;parties on the left in particular, but also on the right, are losing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;votes to new parties which are often described as populist or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nationalist. It's important to understand why this is happening. I've &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been struck over the past several years by the relatively uncurious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;approach that's been taken toward the rise of the new parties and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;decline of the old ones. The phenomena, in my view, is condemned more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;often than it is analyzed.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Sometimes the explanation that's offered is that it's all the fault &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the Russians. I have been a vehement opponent of the Russian regime, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and a great many pieces on it published, but in my view blaming the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Russians is so simplistic an explanation that it barely merits a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rebuttal. It should be obvious that when large numbers of people vote &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for new parties, they are doing so because the old parties do not meet &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their needs. If lots of people did not vote for the new parties, there &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would be no rise of populism to worry about. It should be equally &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;obvious that the old consensus and the analytic and policy support for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it from the U.S. are equally faulty. After all, if that consensus had &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been genuinely satisfactory, it would be now receiving more support &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from the European publics.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    One problem is the relative narrowness of the political consensus &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in Europe. You don't have to go very far on the left, or especially on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the right, before you fall outside the European political consensus. In &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these circumstances, anyone who disagrees with a substantial part of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that consensus is going to have to look for a new party to vote for. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And given that support for the European Union and for ever-deeper &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;integration are a core part of the elite European political consensus, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it's inevitable that a good deal of the rebellion against it is going &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to be associated with nationalism.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, nationalism is a dirty word in Europe. That's because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nationalism has been tarred by association with Nazism. Precisely why &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Adolf Hitler, who was a racist imperialist, is now regarded as a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nationalist, while the nationalists in Poland, France, and Britain who &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resisted Hitler and fought to restore or save their political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;independence are treated as the heroes of Europe's anti-nationalist &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rebirth is an interesting question. But the broader fact is this: Every &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;single stable democracy in the world--every one of them--grew out of a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;national state and was fortified by a sense of nationalism. Without &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nationalism, there is no political community, and without political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;community there can be no democracy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    This is not an original idea on my part. Philosophers from Adam &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Smith to John Stuart Mill regarded what I have just said as an absolute &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;commonplace. Historians of almost every European nation--I'm thinking &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of my first advisor at Yale, Linda Colley, who wrote about Britain, to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the distinguished historian of France, Eugene Weber--have pointed out &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the importance of a felt sense of national identity to the making of a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;political nation--all of these historians have also pointed out &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;something else. National identity is not inherent. Babies are not born &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;French or Polish. National identity is learned and constructed. In &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;other words, you do not just--in Eugene Weber's phrase--make peasants &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;into Frenchmen once. You have to do it every generation.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And you have to do it with immigrants, too. Too many in Europe &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;believe that Europe can rest forever on the nation-making achievements &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of past generations, or even that it should degrade those achievements &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;by denigrating nationalism for the sake of a shallowly rooted &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europeanism. This is a fundamental error. Nations are not made forever. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And if they are not being continuously remade, they are being &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;destroyed.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would not, myself, say that nationalism is a good thing. Like any &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;kind of group identity, it offends against God's truth that we are all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individuals. Nor would I say that all nationalism in Europe will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;necessarily be for the best. You cannot spend 70 years equating &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nationalism with illiberalism and Adolf Hitler and then be shocked that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the belief that you have demonized is represented at times by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;illiberals. Europe has made its bed and it's going to have to lie in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it. If liberals do not own nationalism, it will inevitably become the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;property of illiberals.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But I would say that nationalism is a necessary thing, and that if &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you don't have it or if you try to repress it, its space will be filled &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;by other kinds of group identities that are fundamentally incompatible &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with democracy. In other words, I regard nationalism as an important &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and necessary force. I disagree with those who argue that nationalism &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was responsible for Europe's fall. I agree, instead, with Adam Smith; &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe rose because it was divided into competing units. Nationalism as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the cause of Europe's rise, not Europe's fall.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So part of the reason for the rise of populism in Europe is that a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;narrow and anti-national elite political consensus left no space for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nationalism. Nationalism has therefore made its own space. But this is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;only part of what's going on. Another part are specific policy errors &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that Europe has made and that the U.S. has, especially since the end of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the cold war, indulged and supported. If we go back to the immediate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;post-1945 years, we will see that the U.S. approach to stabilizing and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;democratizing Europe, or at least Western Europe, rested heavily on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;belief that democracy cannot exist without reasonably high and steady &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;levels of economic growth. At the least, there can be no Great &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Depressions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thus, all of the U.S. initiatives in post-war Europe--from the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Bank for Reconstruction and Development--we now call it the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;World Bank--to the IMF, to the Marshall Plan, to the GATT--it's now the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;World Trade Organization--and, yes, even NATO--were fundamentally &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economic. This belief drew on a diagnosis about the causes of the rise &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the Nazis and the origins of the Second World War, which was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fundamentally liberal. The resulting, largely liberal, strategy was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;well informed and extremely successful.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    If I had to sum up that post-1945 U.S. strategy, it was to make &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economic changes to preserve the political order. What do we do now? We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do precisely the opposite. The apple of the EU's eye is the euro, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which, as the Obama administration agreed during the euro crisis, must &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be preserved at all costs. The EU therefore pushes the forces of change &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;away from its economic system and into the political systems of its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;member nations--such as Greece and now Italy. And the U.S. supports the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;EU in this error. We now prioritize economics over politics. After &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;1945, we did precisely the reverse.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The EU likes to boast that the European economic model is different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from that of the United States. By this, the EU means that the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;model is low growth. And the EU regards that as a good thing, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regardless of how much youth unemployment it leads to in Spain. But it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is worse than that. With the EU's approach to Brexit and, for example, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;its impending copyright law, the EU has reached the stage where it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;simply tries to chain the other guy down or make as much money as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;possible by suing him. In other words, the EU does not just back a low-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;growth model, it has abandoned its hopes of becoming a leading digital &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;online power and is now much more interested in trying to insulate its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;low-growth model by reducing growth elsewhere.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Of course, I would be the first to admit that Europe's growth &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;problem is not all the EU's fault. All over Europe, and indeed in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States, national policies mirror and exacerbate the EU's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;policies. But virtually everyone recognizes that, just as the EU &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;claims, the EU and European economic models value social protection &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;over growth. But at some point--and we are well past that point--Europe &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;needs to emphasize growth, for the same reason that it needed growth &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;after 1945. Democracies cannot tolerate persistently high levels of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;unemployment. It is a sure bet that voting publics will react to low &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;growth and high unemployment somehow, likely by blaming the parties in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;power and voting for new ones.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The first major error we have made is, therefore, economic. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;second major error we and Europe have made is to neglect security. More &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;specifically, the U.S. has sought to outsource the responsibility for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European security to the Europeans and the EU. This is the culmination &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of a long-held American wish, one expressed almost as vehemently by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;President Eisenhower as was it was by Presidents Obama or Trump. But no &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;matter how long or how vehemently we wish for this, it will not work &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because the Europeans and, in particular the EU, lack the willingness &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to provide for their own security. I regret this, but I see no point in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;kidding ourselves.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The threats to European security today come from two quarters: &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Russia and the Mediterranean. The European response to the Russian &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;invasion and dismemberment of Ukraine has been a set of modest and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;largely symbolic sanctions and, except for the NATO member states that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;border on Russia, no meaningful increases in defense spending at all. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;In other words, an absolute and complete failure to respond in any &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;significant way whatsoever. In the Mediterranean, Chancellor Merkel, in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;line with Germany's dual role as America's worst ally and Europe's most &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;selfish power, adopted a cataclysmically irresponsible open borders &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;policy, a policy which rested on no consultations at all and which &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;embodied nothing more than a politically foolhardy sense of guilt.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But the problem is deeper than that. Americans are remarkably &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;gullible in their acceptance of the belief that the EU is our friend &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and are equally and remarkably unwilling to overlook repeated EU &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;statements that it views the U.S. as a rival. As EU President Donald &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Tusk put it in early 2017, quote, ``It must be made crystal clear that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the disintegration of the EU will not lead to the restoration of some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mythical, full sovereignty of its member states, but to their real and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;factual dependence on the great superpowers: the United States, Russia &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and China. Only together can we be fully independent.'' Close quote.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The point of this is, indeed, crystal clear. President Tusk classes &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the United States with Russia and China. I suggest we take him at his &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;word and treat him with as much consideration as he treats us. It is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time for us to recognize that the EU is an open and declared enemy to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the role that the U.S. assumed in Europe after 1945. At the EU level, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the fundamental problem, the reason why the EU takes this approach, is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that for the EU everything is political. The point of EU defense &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;initiatives is not to improve Europe's defenses. It is to reduce the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;defense sovereignty of EU's nation-states, and to diminish NATO in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;general, and particularly the American role in the defense of Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The point of the euro is not to make the European economies work &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;better. It is a political instrument for European unity. The point of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;having an EU foreign policy, or a border force, is not to do these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;things better. It is to elevate Brussels and reduce the role of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nation-states of Europe. This strategy has been remarkably successful &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on its own terms, but it neglects one key point. Strategy, security, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the economy, the border, foreign policy--all of these things are issues &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with realities of their own. By treating them merely as political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;instruments for the greatness of the European Union, the EU shows it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prefers a show of greatness to the reality of achievement in any of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these areas.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    At the level of national politics, the rise of populism is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;therefore not surprising. If you are an established political party in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a democratic political system that offers little meaningful choice, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would suggest that an approach which combines low growth, low levels of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;job creation, high levels of unskilled migration, increasing levels of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;supranational control, a rejection of the assimilative force of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;national identity, and lashings of deeply felt guilt are unlikely to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;increase your vote share with the public. If you want to provoke people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;into voting against you, however, all of these things make up an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;excellent strategy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    That is the path that Europe has followed. And it is the path that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the U.S. has endorsed and enabled. This path is a foolhardy one. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;problem is that we are now so far down it that backing out will be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;extremely difficult. In too many European countries, there are too few &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;credible voices outside the consensus who can lead a move away from it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and move back to a path of sovereign national democracies, a restored &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;balance between social protection and economic growth, and a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transatlantic security alliance that rests on controlled borders and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;credible deterrence against the Russians. But that is the right path &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for us to follow, nonetheless.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Ted, thanks for that. You put a lot on the plate--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;questions of the proper understanding of nationalism, the role of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;growth. You've tied together economics and the strategic plane to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;politics in a very compelling way.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Let me immediately pass the floor to Paul for his remarks.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Coyer. Thank you. I'm going to address the issue of nationalism &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and national identity as well. I'm going to leave out much of what Ted &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;said--actually, I have a chapter coming out in a publication from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;National Defense University Press next month. That's coming out of a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conference at which I gave a keynote in August. So I agree with Ted's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;take on that.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ted and I are both historians, so I want to take a bit of a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;historical perspective to start with. This is November 2018. Can any of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you remember 100 years ago what happened? [audience comment] Not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Versailles, the armistice. So you were on the right track. In 10 days, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we will be observing the hundredth anniversary of the ending of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;First World War, a war which has been blamed, to a large degree, on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;passions of nationalism, just as the war that followed that would be. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And today, we see debate over the virtues and vices of national &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;identity, national sovereignty, and the nation-state vis-a-vis growth &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and the importance of supranational institutions and more global &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governance that is strikingly similar, in many ways, to that which &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;occurred in the aftermath of the Great War.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Brexit vote, the election of Donald Trump here in the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States, and the surge of what has been referred to in a pejorative &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;manner as populist and nationalist movements throughout the West are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;only the opening salvos of what I am convinced will be a mammoth &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;struggle over ideas regarding national identity versus cosmopolitanism, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;more local national governments versus transnational government &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;institutions, the importance of identity in general, and the impact &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that those ideas will have on the shape of the international order.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    It is conflicting attitudes toward these ideas, more than anything &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;else, that in my view is the cause of the disconnect that we see &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;currently between President Trump and many Western European leaders. A &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;group of European scholars have argued in an essay last year regarding &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the EU that the originally envisioned European integration project has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;become overtaken by a secularizing, progressive ideological agenda, at &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;odds with the project envisioned by many of the EU's founders, which &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;vision was more grounded in Europe's Christian and classical cultural &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;roots, and which gave room to distinctive national and regional &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;identities. According to these scholars, the project was conceived and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;initiated in a very different cultural ecology than that which exists &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;among Europe's ruling class today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    They point to Christianity and Europe's classical heritage as being &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the foundation of European culture, arguing that as that cultural &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;foundation has eroded, quote, ``the loss of that cultural horizon in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the process of European integration after the Second World War can be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;explained by the secularization of European societies and by the turn &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;away from classical values in favor of the technocratic, progressive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;agenda of scientifically informed societal management.'' One of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;things that Alex didn't mention from my bio is that I'm an associate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;professor at the French Army's version of West Point. And I get a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;first-hand view in France of this struggle within Europe and among &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;themselves over these sorts of values.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    To a large degree, the scholars I just referenced that wrote that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;paper last year blame this cultural shift I've described, and they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;described, and the divergence of attitude between the EU's ruling &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;elites and vast swaths of European citizenry toward fundamental issues &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;such as tradition and the importance of national identity and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sovereignty for the position within which the EU finds itself today, in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which the foundations of political and popular support for the EU &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;project and European integration are increasingly shaky. Along with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these authors, I believe that a renewed emphasis on the importance of a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;healthy nationalism does not require a retreat from European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;integration, so long as that integration is reconceived to be more in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;line with the vision of its founders, rather than reflective of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;progressive agenda that has come to dominate it.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The United States certainly needs a strong, unified, reliable, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prosperous, and democratic partner on the other side of the Atlantic. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And European integration can play a key role in ensuring that that type &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of partnership exists and continues to exist, so long as the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;project gives more space to such issues as tradition, identity, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;national sovereignty. Unless it does so, the bases of its popular &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;support will continue to be threatened, and the disconnect between the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;EU's elites and vast swaths of European citizenry over these issues is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;going to increasingly threaten the future of the whole political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;project.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In the context of highly contested visions during the 1980s of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;form that should be taken by the emerging European Union at the time, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;then-British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher warned European leaders &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;against their current course in her famous speech in September 1988 in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Bruges. She said, quote, ``To try to suppress nationhood and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;concentrate power at the center of a European conglomerate would be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;highly damaging and would jeopardize the objectives we seek to achieve. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe will be stronger precisely because it has France as France, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Spain as Spain, Britain as Britain, each with its own customs, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;traditions, and identity. It would be folly to try to fit them into &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;some sort of identikit European personality.''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    ``Indeed, it is ironic,'' she went on, ``that just when those &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries such as the Soviet Union, which have tried to run everything &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from the center, are learning that success depends on dispersing power &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and decisions away from the center, there are some in the community who &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;seem to want to move in the opposite direction. We have not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;successfully rolled back the frontiers of the state in Britain, only to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;see them re-imposed at a European level with a European super-state &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;exercising a new dominance from Brussels. Certainly we want to see a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe more united and with a greater sense of common purpose. But it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;must be in a way that preserves the different traditions, parliamentary &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;powers, and sense of national pride in one's own country; for these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have been the source of Europe's vitality through the centuries.''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    That vision that Prime Minister Thatcher gave of European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;integration, rather than one in which the principle of solidarity is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;given only lip service, decisionmaking authority becomes increasingly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;distant from and unaccountable to the European grassroots, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;attachment to traditional sovereignty and national identity are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disdained, is one that would address the concerns of those within &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe who have been leading the charge against the EU as it is now &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;constructed and conceived, and would strengthen the space of popular &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;support among Europe's citizenry.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    It would also help with the geopolitical challenge posed by Russia, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in my view. Like Ted, I have written quite a bit on Russia for Forbes &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and other publications. I have had my share of troll attacks. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Russians have selected me; I will not fly Aeroflot anytime soon. But &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;like Ted, I have to say that it is absurd, I think, to put it bluntly, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to blame everything that's happening in Europe, the rise of what are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;called populist and nationalist parties, on Russia. However, Vladimir &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Putin has quite shrewdly played upon the sense among large portions of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the West that its leaders no longer share their appreciation of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;importance of faith, family, tradition, and national identity. He has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;played on this theme in order to increase his soft power appeal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;throughout major segments of the West, while at the same time to create &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a positive brand for Russia, whose reputation has, to put it mildly, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;taken quite a hit in the past few years, and which has been therefore &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in desperate need of rebranding.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Kremlin's skillful propaganda in this regard, which has been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;interwoven with its propaganda regarding the West turning hostile to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;its Christian civilizational roots, the implication, of course, being &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that Russia remains traditional and Christian, has found broad &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resonance within Europe and much of the rest of the world, despite the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;obvious fact that Vladimir Putin is hardly a paragon of Christian &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;virtue, nor an exemplar of ethical Christian leadership.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Early in President Trump's presidency, Guy Verhofstadt, the EU &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Parliament's Brexit negotiator and former Belgian prime minister, gave &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a speech in London in which he said that Europe faces a threat from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Donald Trump. EU leaders also uniformly speak about how national &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;identity is also a threat, using pejorative language and portraying it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as a uniformly dark and fascist force.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Many Europeans, however, see national identity, sovereignty, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tradition as a moral good, and are therefore much more in line with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;President Trump's thinking in this area than they are with the take of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the EU leaders, that see supranational institutions and the diminution &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of national identity and national loyalties as necessary for peace and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prosperity in Europe. Increasingly, the United States and many of our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Western allies are being led by those to which the late Samuel &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Huntington, in his 2004 essay, ``Dead Souls,'' a phrase borrowed from a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Sir Walter Scott poem of the same name, referred to as a, quote &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;``denationalized elite who have forgotten the mystic cords of memory, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;while the American people have not.'' He was referring to the American &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;context when he wrote this.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The deep divide within Europe on the issues of tradition, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sovereignty, and national identity and what constitutes Europe's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;historic cultural values is one reason why these issues need much more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reflective and nuanced attention than, for the most part, they have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been receiving from EU's ruling class. The restoration of a sense of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;solidarity between these leaders in the West and our citizenry is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;necessary to the future of liberal democracy. Unless this large gap in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;perceptions between European elites and much of the European citizenry &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is addressed, not only will it continue to see the disintegration of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the political bases of support for the European project, but the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Kremlin will continue to have an open opportunity to continue to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;increase its influence and standing within our own political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;constituencies, to the detriment of us all.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The value and importance of transatlantic ties is not in question, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;despite some of President Trump's rhetoric that has caused heartburn. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Whether U.S.-European relations are headed off a cliff, as some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;suppose, depends upon which Europe one is talking about: the Europe &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;envisioned and espoused by European leaders of today in which a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;centralized authority, increasingly divorced from much of the people it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governs in terms of its governing philosophy and aspirations, or the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;traditional Europe we see arising in opposition to the EU's leaders, in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which European cooperation is to be based upon sovereign, independent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nation-states cooperating because it is in their national interest to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do so.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    A similar debate over all these issues--one that reflects starkly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;differing worldviews--is taking place both within Europe and here in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the United States. And it is the outcome of this debate on both sides &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the Atlantic that will determine the nature and shape of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transatlantic relationship going forward.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Thanks, Paul. I take away a number of things from your &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;presentation. Your description of a European integration that, while it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has its challenges, in your view, need not necessarily be in retreat. A &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;united Europe can play a key role as a partner to the United States, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;but under specific circumstances and not based on an identikit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;strategy. I also take away your description of Putin being able to play &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on the differences between the elites and the citizenships--the elites &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who--you referenced Samuel Huntington's ``Dead Souls.''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Let me pass over now to Jeff Rathke for his views before I engage &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you all in responding to some of those points.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thanks.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Rathke. Thanks, Alex. Thanks also Kyle Parker, and to everyone &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;associated with the Helsinki Commission. And I want to recognize at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;start the important work that the commission does, and my appreciation &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for the invitation. I also want to thank those who are here, who made &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the effort to come in person, but also those who are watching online.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'm speaking today on the one hand as president of the American &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Institute for Contemporary German Studies, but also as someone who &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;served as a diplomat for a long time in Republican and Democratic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;administrations and worked mainly on U.S. relations with Europe--both &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;political relations as well as defense and security.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So an important question brings us here today--whether the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States needs a new approach to Europe. I have to say, I've heard &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relatively little about what the new approach should be thus far, so I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want to try to contribute a bit to that. It is unquestionably true that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the international landscape in security terms, in economic terms, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in political terms has been changing for quite a few years.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The United States and its allies face a revanchist Russia that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;attempts to alter borders by force in Europe, and also seeks to exploit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the social and political vulnerabilities in our societies, to weaken &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our cohesion, and to undermine our democracies. I would agree with both &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the previous speakers that Russia does not create those &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;vulnerabilities. It does seek to exploit them, sometimes with success. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And so that is something we need to be vigilant about, even as we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;recognize that the divisions they exploit are largely of our own making &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and not of Russia's creation.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Beyond Russia, we have the challenge from China expanding its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;international influence and its ability to project economic, political, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and military power not only in the Asia-Pacific but also in Europe, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which is a challenge to the international order. Proliferation of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nuclear and missile technology in North Korea and Iran is a pressing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;concern. And international terrorism is an important threat. These &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;geopolitical factors, I believe, are correctly diagnosed in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;administration's national security strategy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, turning more particularly to Europe, which is the topic of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;discussion today, there has been a rise--regardless of how you want to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;characterize it--of nationalist or of anti-establishment political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;forces inside Europe over many years. And it has spread over time &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;across much of the European continent. This is altering the internal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;politics in European countries. It's affecting the dynamics within the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union. And it's affecting the relations among European states. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Brexit is one example, perhaps the most prominent. But there are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;others.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So the question for this panel, as I understand it, concerns U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;policy toward Europe. Now, for seven decades the U.S. has had a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;remarkably consistent approach to Europe, I would argue, promoting a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;stronger and more integrated Europe so that it can play the role of a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;partner to the United States in transatlantic security, in shaping the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;global economy, and in responding to international foreign policy and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;security challenges.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, that's not to say we haven't had disagreements with Europe on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;many issues over the decades. There have been some quite serious ones. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;But on just about any major international problem that the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States has to confront and has tried to confront--whether by Republican &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;or Democratic administrations--the United States has inevitably sought &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the partnership and support of European countries in that endeavor. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;That's true of military operations, such as the wars in Iraq and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Afghanistan, the fight to eliminate the so-called Islamic State, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;intervention in Libya, and the wars in the Balkans, if you go back &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;farther.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    When it comes to the economic relationship, the ties across the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Atlantic are the most intense and important trade and investment &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relationship in the world. One trillion dollars annually in two-way &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;trade, 5 trillion [dollars] in mutual investments. The U.S. and Europe &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have sought over the years to reduce tariff and non-tariff barriers, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because they realize that the potential gains to the transatlantic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economy are enormous given the breadth of our relationship. Now, those &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;negotiations have not always succeeded. And there's certainly much more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to be done.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The United States also works together with Europe to fight &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;proliferation, to counter terrorism, to advance democracy and human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rights, and to promote international norms and standards that favor &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;freedom and the rule of law.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, sometimes there is an element of nostalgia that comes with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;discussion of the transatlantic relationship. I think both previous &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;speakers have tried to avoid that, and I appreciate that, because, you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;know, while the U.S. security alliance with Europe brought about what I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would argue is the most monumental success of the late 20th century--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the triumph of democracy and liberty in the standoff with the Soviet &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;empire--sentimentality is not a guide for the policy choices that we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;face today and for the future.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So another way of formulating the question might be this: Do the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;changes in the international environment in recent years mean that the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transatlantic instincts that leaders of both parties have cultivated &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;since the end of the Second World War are no longer valid? I would &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;contend that the logic behind those instincts is as compelling as ever. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;When you look across the Atlantic, the United States finds the largest &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;collection of economically advanced, militarily capable, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;politically like-minded countries, that are prepared to take political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;risks and stand with the United States in confronting a challenge. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European countries and institutions like NATO and the European Union &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are our partners of first resort. And it is clear that the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States benefits from and should seek partnership with Europe, unless we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;choose to deliberately do things alone, which is a choice.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, getting to the policy differences that we have with some of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our European friends and partners, those could be reasonably be raised &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as an objection. The Nord Stream II gas pipeline is one example. But I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;believe that an effective foreign policy for the United States is one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that seeks to establish priorities that are achievable within the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resources that we have available to us. And if we look at the world &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;through a lens of great power competition, as I believe this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;administration does, in which there are five crucial challenges--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Russia, China, North Korea, Iran, and international terrorism--U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;success in meeting any of those challenges will be greatly enhanced by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;partnership with Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Economically, it is hard to see the European Union as a greater &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;challenge than China, for example, and to portray the European Union as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a foe is, frankly, absurd. The United States and the EU together &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;account for 46 percent of global GDP. Our influence is enormous &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;together on global economic issues. Alone, the United States is 24 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;percent of global GDP, and necessarily wields less influence in trying &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to shape the future of the global economy than we would in partnership &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would remind you that the majority of U.S. foreign investment is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in Europe. Fifty-eight percent of our foreign investment is in Europe. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And Europe is the largest source of foreign investment in this country. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Sixty-nine percent of foreign investment in the U.S. comes from Europe. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;So I think it is not particularly helpful to U.S. policy formulation to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;demonize the countries that share the most with us in terms of their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economic models, their democratic values, and their willingness to take &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;actions beyond their own borders to achieve common goals.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, it's a separate question whether the changing politics inside &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe means that these partners should be somehow less attractive. If &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you look at European foreign policy, which is a complicated mix of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;national policies and policies coordinated at the EU level, let's look &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at European Union sanctions on Russia, for example. Those were adopted &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as an EU policy by consensus. And they have held since Russia's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;invasion of Ukraine in 2014. Now, if we raise the question of whether &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we would have a more effective European response if it were not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;coordinated at the European Union level, I think the answer is obvious.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And it becomes even more obvious now when you look at the number of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries that want the European Union to end its sanctions on Russia, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because they don't want to make that economic sacrifice anymore. Is it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the United States' interest to have effective sanctions against &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Russia or not? If the answer is yes, and I believe it is, then working &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with the European Union is the way to accomplish that. Working with not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;only leaders of the European Union--that is, the European Commission &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and the European Council--but with the leaders of European Union member &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;states. I think previous speakers have both pointed out that the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;national leaders remain important. And I would argue that they remain &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the most important factors in European decisionmaking, especially on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;crucial foreign policy issues. There is no Europe that is driven--in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;crucial foreign policy issues--by faceless bureaucrats in Brussels or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;by the European Parliament. It is the engagement and the priority-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;setting of the national leaders in the European Union that are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ultimately decisive.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I would say that we see the European Union is able to act in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;unison, despite the sometimes fractious politics within Europe. Let's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;look at one example, which is the retaliatory tariffs that the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Union imposed on the United States after the United States imposed &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;national-security-based tariffs on imports of steel and aluminum from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the European Union. Now, it's a separate question whether there's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;really a national security basis for those kinds of sanctions, but I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think it belies the suggestion that Europe is not able to act together &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;when it sees its interests at stake.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But there are other cases where the European Union has failed to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reach consensus on taking unified action. One example in recent years &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was the European Union being unable to agree on a resolution that was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;up at the United Nations that criticized China's human rights record. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Now, that resolution was torpedoed by Greece. Greece, which has been a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;recipient of a significant amount of Chinese investment since the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European and global financial crisis in 2008 and 2009. So China's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;growing economic stake in Europe, and China's promotion of arrangements &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;like the 16+1, raised major concerns in Europe, as I think they do for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the United States, that China will try to use its economic influence to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;divide Europe and prevent the European Union from achieving common and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;critical positions on matters of concern to Beijing.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    There's also a rising concern in many European countries about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;investment by China in Europe--and from other countries, not just &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;China, investment in strategically significant industries. Currently, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that's a national competency. It is the responsibility of EU member &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;states to have their own national standards. But this has led to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;proposals for an EU-wide investment screening framework. It's currently &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;under discussion, and has not been concluded. But if the United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sees China's economic model and its predatory capitalist approach, its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;theft of intellectual property, and its attempt to use its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;infrastructure investment to gain political influence, it seems to me &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;obvious that the United States has an interest in a robust and unified &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European response, rather than piecemeal national efforts that will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;allow countries to be picked off one by one.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, you could also look at this as a situation that the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States could seek to exploit for its own national benefit. In that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sense, the question would be: Is anti-establishment or populist or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nationalist politics an opportunity for the United States or a threat? &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Does the rise of populism and its stress on sovereignty present new &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opportunities to promote U.S. interests more effectively? In other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;words, is there a silver lining in that cloud?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would start by looking, again, at the EU sanctions on Russia. In &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;international economic diplomacy, the EU has had much more at stake in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;its relationship with Russia. And it has made much greater sacrifices, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;frankly, than the United States has economically in trying to impose &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;costs on Russia for its invasion of Ukraine.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, it's a separate question whether there could have been other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;responses. For example, the Obama administration was unwilling to sell &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;lethal arms to Ukraine. That's a policy that's been reversed by the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Trump administration. I think that's a topic that's worthy of debate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and discussion, especially critical discussion with our European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;friends and allies. But it's clear that the Europeans have made greater &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economic sacrifices in trying to constrain Russia in its revanchist &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;project in Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And regardless of what you think of the Joint Comprehensive Plan of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Action (JCPOA), it is also true that European Union countries were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;willing to impose substantial costs on their own firms in order to try &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to bring Iran to the negotiating table. Again, that's separate from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;discussing the merits of the JCPOA, which is perhaps worthy to do, but &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I don't think it's really the topic of this panel. But the point is, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe is able to act when we forge common cause on crucial issues, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that benefits, in my view, the United States.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And more broadly, I think the benefit to the United States in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;populist contagion is chimerical. We can seek it, but we're never &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;really going to find it. It is precisely the nationalist governments in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe that exhibit the greatest sympathy for Vladimir Putin's Russia. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;If you look at Italy, Italian Interior Minister Matteo Salvini, who's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the leader of the far-right Lega Party, which now has the highest &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;proportion of public support--according to opinion polls--recently &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;visited Moscow. He is vocal in his opposition to sanctions on Russia. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Hungarian President Victor Orban has called for lifting sanctions, as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have the Czech Republic and Greece. Austria is sympathetic. And by the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;way, the right-wing FPO, which is part of the ruling coalition in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Vienna, even concluded a cooperation agreement with the United Russia &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;party of President Putin.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Poland is the one exception to that trend. It is a nationalist-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;oriented government that remains tough on Russia. But it's the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;exception. There is a high degree of correlation between nationalist &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governments in Europe and pro-Russian sentiment. So if Russia is one of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our top geopolitical competitors, one of the top two challenges we face &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;if you take the hierarchy of the administration, why should the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States be encouraging Moscow's best friends? I don't see it.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, I think there's a legitimate criticism of European leaders. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;There has been a lack of sufficient creativity and political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;willingness on the part of many European countries, and at the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Union level, to play a stronger international role, and to be proactive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in trying to find issues around which the United States and Europe can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;coalesce. So I don't mean to try to suggest that they don't bear a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;share of responsibility for finding the substantive elements of a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;future-oriented agenda between the United States and Europe. But I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think our focus today is on U.S. policy toward Europe, which is why &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I've directed my remarks there.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would conclude by saying that when you get to burden sharing, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which, Kyle, you mentioned at the very start, I think we need to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;clear about what we seek from burden sharing. There is a focus on 2 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;percent of spending, but I think Ted Bromund also raised the question &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about what role burden sharing plays. I heard--you can correct me if I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;misunderstood--a criticism of the U.S. that it has tried to outsource &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the security relationship to Europeans and to the European Union. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think there's a tension, though, between whether we want Europeans to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bear their share of the security responsibility for transatlantic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;security, for our shared security--whether we want them to do that or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think we should have European countries bearing their share of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the security burden. They have not done as much as they should have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;over the years. I think the way to get there is through persistent, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;effective diplomacy that takes American policy desires and finds ways &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to promote those in ways that build European support, not just of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governments but of publics as well, for this common security agenda.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So I would just end by saying I think rather than being an open and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;declared enemy of U.S. objectives in Europe, as Ted Bromund put it in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;talking about the European Union, I would say the Europeans are our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;closest allies, our most effective partners when you look at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;challenges we face in the world. And we need to focus on ways to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;collaborate with them, rather than to demonize them and to try to stoke &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;animosity across the Atlantic.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you very much.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Thanks, Jeff.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I see in these three excellent presentations really an opportunity &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for a classic debate to break out, but I'm going to try to manage this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as a conversation rather than a debate format. Let me ask a couple of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;kind of framing questions before I go back to the audience, because--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I'm sure there's a lot that the audience would like to jump in on here. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Clearly some different perspectives were expressed on the level of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;leadership in the European Union currently and U.S. policy, and where &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it should be going.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But let me start with asking Ted, perhaps, to respond to Jeff's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;last point, which is the tension between Europeans bearing their fair &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;share for providing security in their own region, as opposed to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tension that we have with the outsourcing debate. If you could--and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we've got a number of things on the table, so I'll ask your responses &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to be relatively brief, in the 2-minute range.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Bromund. That's a really excellent question. Let me start off &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;by saying that in my view the point of increased European spending on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;defense is not primarily to acquire additional military capabilities. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Those are, of course, desirable and they are necessary. But that is not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the main point. The main point of increased European defense spending &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is to reinforce the American political consensus in favor of a strong &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;American contribution to European defense. It has been an argument for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;generations that the political consensus in the U.S. in favor of NATO &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is not sustainable unless the Europeans pay a fair share and are seen &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;by the American people to pay a fair share. So I am opposed to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;outsourcing security to the Europeans or to the European Union and I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want them to pay a fair share precisely because that is the only way to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ensure that we also play a role over the long run.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Let me explain what I mean specifically by ``outsourcing'' with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;some historical examples. In the 1990s, after the end of the cold war, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we did everything we could under two administrations to try to leave &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Balkan wars to the Europeans. We eventually were forced to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;intervene. I'm very glad that we did. But we delayed, and delayed, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;delayed. After the cold war, reductions in U.S. forces in Europe were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;certainly necessary and warranted. But they went much too far. We took &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;over 90 percent of our forces and, under the Obama administration, all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of our armor out of Europe. There was excessive U.S. disinvestment in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European security. When you take a look at crises on the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;border, in my view, we have tried and tried and tried to leave it to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Europeans, only in the end to belatedly have to get involved. Libya &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is the classic example here.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So I am unhappy with the U.S. approach that doesn't take a strong &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;leadership position on security issues in and around Europe, that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;outsources. But I am equally unhappy with a European underspend &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;approach, precisely because it reinforces our desire--which we have had &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;since the Eisenhower administration--to try to leave all these things &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to the Europeans. These are not contradictory factors. They are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;complementary problems. And they can only be solved by addressing both &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of them together.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Let me shift gears on a question to Paul and go back &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to something that was present in your presentation. You described the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;potential for a healthy nationalism.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think, Ted, if I jotted this down correctly, you used the phrase &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;``nationalism is necessary'' and it's become a ``dirty word'' in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would love for the two of you, but let's start with Paul, to help &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;us understand where the line is between a healthy nationalism and a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;potentially unhealthy nationalism. I think this gets to one of Kyle's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;framing points about Germany. Are we concerned about a nationalism that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would develop in a manner that would be contrary to peace and security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on the European continent and, therefore, to the United States' &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;interests?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Paul, I'd like for you to take a crack at that and maybe Jeff &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;after. Thanks.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Coyer. Sure. This is a good question. And just to reinforce, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;yes, I do believe there are healthy and unhealthy nationalisms.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    One of the things that I disagree with in the rhetoric that we hear &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;coming out of EU leaders uniformly is that nationalism is always seen &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the pejorative and they don't recognize the fact that there is a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;healthy form of nationalism. As Ted alluded to, it was in the context &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the modern nation-state that we developed modern democratic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governance and representative governance, human rights protections, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that sort of thing, the rule of law. Liah Greenfield of Boston &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;University and many other academics have written about this, that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;without the modern nation-state we would not have democracy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Getting to your question of where to draw the line, I don't think &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it is exactly a fine line, but there's a long debate that we don't have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time to get into now over creedal nationalism, which we see in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States, where we are defined by a creed that came out of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Declaration of Independence and the Constitution, as opposed to an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ethnic nationalism that you see prominently in places like Russia. It &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;isn't just ethnic there, it's more cultural; but there's an ethnic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;component to it, with the Russian world being a big, supposedly unified &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;culture in the post-Soviet space.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I have Serbian friends. The Serbs constantly get criticized, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sometimes justifiably when you look at their history, for an ethnic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Serb nationalism that is a bit virulent. So when you do have a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nationalism that, in my view, is defined by an ethnicity more than &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;anything else, that's particularly where you need to double down on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;democracy promotion and the rule of law and transparency, that sort of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thing.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Philosophically speaking, a healthy nationalism, in my view, is one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that appreciates one's own traditions and culture while also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;appreciating those of other people. There's a point that's made by a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;friend of mine, Yoram Hazony, an Israeli scholar that just came out &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with a book called ``The Virtues of Nationalism,'' a title that tells &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you where he's coming from. And one of the things that he says is that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we should try to inculcate a type of nationalism that is characterized &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;by humility in our own national distinctiveness, a pride in it, but not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;an overweening pride; a sense of our own distinctiveness that also is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tempered by humility, knowing that we are not the be-all and end-all of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cultural achievement.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    When you can look at other cultures--my wife, for instance, is a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Venezuelan. I've lived much of my life overseas. When you look at other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cultures and can appreciate their distinctiveness and where they might &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have some aspects of their culture that are superior to your own, that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can provide a limiting effect on a tendency toward an overweening &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pride.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I mean--this could be the topic of a whole daylong discussion, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;obviously. The chapter that I told you about that I wrote on this issue &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;approaches nationalism specifically from an ethical point of view. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that was only 20 pages long, and that could easily have been 2[00] or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;300. So I'll end my brief remarks there.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. We appreciate the executive summary.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you. [Laughter.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Jeff, over to you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Rathke. Thanks. So I wanted to touch on a couple of things.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    First, I think it's important to remember that support for NATO in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the United States is at an all-time high. On the one hand, that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;suggests a commitment by the American public to the transatlantic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;security alliance. I think it's also worth noting at the same time that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there is a divergence, an increasing divergence, in the views of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people, based on their political affiliations in the United States, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;toward NATO. I think, while there has been a dramatic rise among &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;independents and supporters of the Democratic Party in their support &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for NATO, among Republicans it has declined, which I think is certainly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regrettable. I think it's probably a function of the administration's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;harping on the 2 percent target. But nevertheless, taken as a whole, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;American public support for NATO is increasing.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would also highlight that if you look at public support for the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union across EU member states, you find that in many of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries whose governments are most critical of Brussels, you actually &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have the highest level of public support for their membership in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union. So I think it's a more complicated issue than is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sometimes presented in the media, as far as publics being frustrated &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with Brussels and questioning the value of the European Union.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But I wanted to come back to the question you asked about Germany, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and which Kyle also mentioned at the start, and Germany's role. Kyle, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the way you put it is: If Germany spent 2 percent on defense, would we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have a problem in Europe? I would go back to the always-quotable Radek &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Sikorski, former minister and defense minister of Poland, who said &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;quite a few years ago that he fears German weakness more than he fears &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;German strength. And I think that is still the case. Germany needs to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do more in the defense realm. Germany acknowledges it, but the progress &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has been very, very slow, slower than anyone, I think, would like. But &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I don't think there's any real objection to Germany increasing its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;commitment to the transatlantic alliance. Instead, I think there's just &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;frustration that it hasn't been going as fast as people would like.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    That has deeper roots within the German public, among the political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;parties. And as much as we might like to see it go faster, I'm not sure &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it's going to speed up even with a change in the Christian Democratic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Union leadership, frankly, because it brings up questions of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;complicated coalition politics--what government can be formed if there &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ever is a change of government, and what political coalition will move &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Germany faster toward that goal.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Colleagues and friends in the audience, I think I've &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;stood between you and the panel for long enough now. I would love to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;take some questions from the audience and keep my own in abeyance for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;now.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I see a hand in the back on the right. Please identify yourself, if &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you could.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Hi. My name is Ben. I'm an intern with Congressman &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Cohen.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My question was, I understand the point that you were making on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European technocratic authenticity separate from the people who can be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;difficult to support, but what is the ideal format for the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Union that has this sovereign diversity of strength that you see? Is it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a U.N.-style secretariat? Does it continue to have a transnational &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;parliament? Does it focus more on the Council and backroom deals? I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not quite seeing how it maintains the sovereignty of strength and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;continues to include the people, if you have thoughts on that.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Thanks. Let me add to that. If we find a different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;institutional framework for the European Union, I would like Ted and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Paul both to respond to this because it also gets to, I think, Jeff's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;advocacy of the EU as a partner of first resort, I think was his word, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on challenges internationally. If we find a different kind of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governance structure that's more responsive to the public, as you've &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;described, do we lose a kind of a partnership with the EU, and on what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;areas? How would that cooperation look under a different kind of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governance structure, as well?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Coyer. I can start and then we can move over to Ted, I guess.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think one place I would start would be the European Commission, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which people in Europe don't feel is responsive to them. That needs to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;change.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    To answer the issue that Alex raised just now, I don't think a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;change in governing structure, however you look at it or redefine it or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reshape it, necessarily means a reduction in American partnering &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;capacity with Europe. I think that you can certainly do it in such a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;way where we continue that strong relationship.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I completely agree with much of what Jeff said, that we need &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that transatlantic relationship. I not only teach in France, I did my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Ph.D. in Britain, travel there a lot, and of course we need that.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, specifics how to structure it are harder to define and that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would take some more careful thought. I would just start with the EC &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because that's the obvious target. That's the one that people point to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the most as being unaccountable.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Bromund. I'll pick up on that just quickly. I appreciate the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;question and I appreciate that it's a very serious one. I'm a little &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reluctant as an American to sort of sit here dispensing my purported &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wisdom about the way the EU should be organized, which, frankly, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;whatever I say will have absolutely no impact on what they do. So with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all respect to what is clearly a very serious question, I'm not sure &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that this is something where American input is going to be very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;usefully offered.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My personal instinct--and I emphasize personal--is that the way for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sovereign democratic nations to cooperate is through the traditional &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mechanisms of interstate diplomacy. You can call that backroom deals &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for the European Council if you care to, I would call it diplomacy. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Probably Woodrow Wilson would also have called it backroom deals. But I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;remain very supportive of that basic mode of operation, if only because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I think diplomacy is the way that civilized nations do business and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;diplomacy is traditionally done by sovereign nation states.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    On the question of European partnership, well, let's look at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;five big challenges. I agree there are rising concerns, but the EU has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;played, and European nations in general have played, a largely &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;negligible role in concerns about China. And in my view, they will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;continue to play a largely negligible role.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Europe does, of course, have a role in combating terrorism. I'm not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sure that European efforts in the North African Sahel regions have been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;particularly successful.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Europe is a nonfactor on North Korea, simply does not matter in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;North Korean issue.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And we come to Russia. Jeff mentioned the sacrifices that Europeans &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and the EU have made vis-a-vis Russian sanctions. Of course, there have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been more economic losses due to sanctions in Europe than there have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been in the United States because they trade more with Russia--or did &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;trade more with Russia--than we do. But the Russians have invaded and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;occupied a nation in Europe and we are sitting here saying, oh, the EU &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has done wonderful things because it has imposed really some fairly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;limited and not always effective sanctions on the Russians and we are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;busy patting them on the back for this tremendous achievement. This is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not a tremendous achievement.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Jeff passed over Nord Stream 2 fairly quickly. In the midst of all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of this supposedly brilliant sanctioning achievement, Germany is busy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;totally on its own backing and constructing a gas pipeline to Russia, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which is absolutely going to have an infinitely greater restorative &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;effect on the Russian economy than all the EU sanctions have had a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;negative effect.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I am stunned by the paucity of the EU's and the Europeans' ambition &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in this regard. And I'm stunned by our willingness to give them credit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for doing well when in response to a Russian invasion of a European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nation they have done so little. Let's not pitch our ambitions here too &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;low. If the EU and the Europeans want to play a serious security role &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in their own continent, the invasion of a European nation needs to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;met with more than a few economic sanctions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Sure, Jeff, please.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Rathke. Thanks. I'll respond to that point. I did not use the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;words ``wonderful'' or ``tremendous achievement.'' I said that the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union's sanctions have made a greater economic impact than the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States' economic sanctions. And you're right, it's because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europeans previously did trade more with Russia. That's a function of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;geography, it's a function of Russia being a natural resource exporter. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;There's not exactly a value judgment behind that, I think.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think the fact is that, confronted with the invasion and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;occupation of a European country, there has been a relatively &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;consistent European response. It could have been done more in other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;areas, I agree with you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But I think we also have to be honest about what the scope was for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nonmilitary action in response to the invasion of Ukraine. That is, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think, a different and broader topic to discuss.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I wanted to come back to the question about what's the right &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;structure. Like Ted, I wouldn't want to prescribe, but I would &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;highlight, for example, counterterrorism, which is clearly an issue of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;concern for the United States as well as for European governments and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for Europe collectively. And if you look at the response since the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;attacks in Paris and in Brussels, for example, you see a greater role &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;being played by European institutions in information sharing, things &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;like passenger name recognition and so forth. On the European level, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;greater responsibility Europe-wide for things that contribute to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fight against terrorism and law enforcement.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    It seems to me that that benefits the United States because the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;more the Europeans are coordinated among themselves and sharing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;information, the easier it is for the United States to work with them &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rather than to work with 28 individual member States. So I think that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;suggests another area of benefit to the United States that we haven't &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;talked about before.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    With respect to China and whether the EU will play a significant &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;role, I think one of the interesting things this administration is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;doing is to partner with the European Union and Japan to try to address &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;what they refer to as global economic issues, which is really about how &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to deal with China's growing international economic role. So I think &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that is an indication of readiness to engage with this U.S. Government. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And I think that's a welcome thing. The greater collection of countries &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that are interested in open economies, the better for the U.S.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Thanks, Jeff.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'd like to take another few questions from the audience if I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;could. I see a lot of hands. Great. Let me start in the corner, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;standing up.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Hi. My name is Erika Schlager. I'm with the Helsinki &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission staff. Thank you for this extremely interesting program this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;morning.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I want to preface my question with a little comment on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;definitional issue that was at the start of this panel, how we're &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;describing various political parties today. And I certainly agree that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the terminology that we have available doesn't seem to be as helpful as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we might like.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So extremist, populist, even left, right aren't necessarily very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;informative anymore and there may be a quick consideration of whether &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;certain parties or political actors have fascist tendencies. I would &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;like to hear more people discussing whether they have communist-era &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tendencies, whether some of the policies and practices echo somewhat &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the 1945 to 1948 practices that we saw and the takeover of communism in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Central Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    That said, I am now going to use the word ``nationalism'' since we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sort of concluded our discussion there. And it seems to me that we're &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sort of talking about two levels here: U.S. policy toward what's going &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on in specific individual EU countries and then the U.S. policy toward &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the EU itself. And with respect to the nationalist voices--caveated use &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of that word--but with respect to the nationalist voices or parties or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nonstandard parties that are emerging, it seems to me that one of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;challenges or one of the problems that we face is that those &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nationalist parties and voices also tend to be the ones advancing anti-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;human rights policies and anti-democratic policies. And I'm thinking &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about the extreme centralization that's taking place in Hungary, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rise in anti-Semitism and historical revisionism, stripping religions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of their religious status, the purging of the supreme court in Poland &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and the reintroduction of the Soviet-era feature of lay judges and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;end of the finality of legal decisions and the end of legal certainty.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So are there nationalist voices that are also pro-democracy and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pro-human rights? Because it seems to me, if you can't get those two &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;things to go together, it's going to be hard for us to be neutral or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;supportive of a different kind of nationalism. Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Please.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Bromund. Well, I'll gladly take a crack at that one. It &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;probably should have been obvious from our remarks, but I'll just spell &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it out here. I am rather skeptical about the value of a lot of these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;populist movements, however one sort of cares to classify them--not all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of them, but most of them. And I largely agree with Jeff's comment &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that, although not all populist or nationalist movements in Europe are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;associated with the Russians, there is more of an alignment there than &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;one might care to see.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But I don't think we can necessarily stop there. If our answer to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these populist or nationalist movements is to say ``We reject them &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;completely, we need to go back to the old system,'' we're, therefore, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;left with a problem. Where did these movements come from in the first &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;place? They came from the old system. So, obviously, something was not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;satisfactory in the previous setup and simply condemning the new &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;developments without trying to sort of fix or revive or change the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;older system is probably not going to get very far. It's going to put &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;us right back where we are today or maybe even a worse place.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    That really is the point of my argument, that we need to think &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about economic growth in Europe. I don't see how you have stable &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Christian Democratic or Social Democratic parties without reasonable &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;levels of growth. I don't see how you have them without more awareness &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Europe's cultural and, largely, Christian past, to take Paul's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;point. And I don't think you can have them without a meaningful &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;approach to national security, which includes strong and reasonable &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;border controls. If you don't have those things, I think you're going &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to be pushed in some undesirable or different--frequently undesirable--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;direction.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But you put your finger really on the core of the problem. We are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;where we are in Europe because of a series of policies and events that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have happened over the last 70 years, many of which, in my view, were a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mistake. And we are now in a position where the routes out of that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;series of errors are frequently very unattractive for precisely the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reasons that you and Jeff and indeed Paul and also I set out.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So how do we go forward? Do we simply approve of every populist or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nationalist movement that appears in Europe? I simply don't propose to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do any such thing. But can we have policies which make it clear that we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prioritize growth over stability? I think we can. I believe we should.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Should we have a strong deterrent policy toward the Russians? I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;believe that's absolutely necessary. Should we back firm European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;border controls? I think politically in Europe that is an absolute &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;necessity right now. If we don't back sensible things that are somewhat &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different from the immediate past consensus, we will simply get more of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these movements, some of which are going to do things that we are going &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to find extremely distasteful.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Paul?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Coyer. I would just agree with that. And I would just add to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that, I think a void in the national aspirations of many Europeans has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been created in the manner which I have described and Ted has spoken to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as well. And when you don't fill the void with something that's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;healthy, it's going to be filled with something that's unhealthy. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that's why I think we need to take an active role in defining and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shaping a healthy sort of nationalism that includes human rights &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;protections.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Indeed, as I mentioned earlier, modern conceptions of human rights, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;modern democratic governance, the rule of law, all that arose in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;context of a modern nation-state. So it is not mutually exclusive. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;don't see nationalism as being something that's in contradiction to all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;those aspirations and those things that we need. So I think that we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;need to be actively involved in shaping a healthy form of nationalism &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and defining that so that these sorts of issues are addressed.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I also agree with you, and as Ted also said, there is a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;negative tendency on the part of not all, but some of these movements &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;within Europe to be too sympathetic to Putin and to Russia. This is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;another reason we need to be heavily involved. I think I made this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;point in my initial statement as well--the more the EU leaders double &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;down on their blanket condemnation of national identity and tradition &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and that sort of thing, the more it plays into the hands of Putin and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;gives rise to some of these negative actors.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Jeff, I'm actually going to beg your forgiveness and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ask you to hold your comments because we're getting close to the end of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our time here today and I saw a number of questions in the audience. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;really would like to give folks a chance to participate.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So what I propose is a kind of a lightning round where I take as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;many questions as I can and our panelists do their best to take what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they can and respond and offer any final remarks at this point.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So I see in the front row here and then in the back and then in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;far back, one, two, three. Am I missing anybody else? Okay, four, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;great. We'll do four at once.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Should I skip the identification, or is that still &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;important?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. No, it's important for the transcript.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Short, please. Yes. Per Bergstrom [sp], Senator &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Murray's office. These are mostly my thoughts.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Merkel seems to be getting out while the going is still good. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with her out of the picture, it seems that only Macron in France is a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;major European head of state that seems to be willing to speak for the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European project. How do you think this affects the dynamics we've been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;talking about today?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Great. Do me a favor and hand the microphone straight &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;back.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Mark Toner, Helsinki Commission, the State Department's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;senior adviser.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My question is pretty basic and simple, which is, soft power &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;diplomacy. This is my view--but we've let the transatlantic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relationship atrophy, and by that I mean we had this distinct &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relationship with the post-war generation of Europeans that understood &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and appreciated America's role. And that relationship between Europe &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and America, I don't think the new generation has that appreciation.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We talk about working within multilateral settings with the EU and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at NATO, but I think that relationship doesn't filter down to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;publics both in America, despite Jeff's quoting strong support for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;NATO, but certainly in most European populations. So how do we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;revitalize that?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Great. And then one here and then in the far back, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;please.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Hi. I'm Andrew Myslik with Congressman Larson's office, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also speaking from my views.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I am curious, to go on a NATO stretch here, how much stock and how &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;should we define 2 percent of GDP as well as the 20 percent threshold &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;contained within that, specifically given that a lot of European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nations in the east, should NATO have to move heavy weaponry such as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.S. tanks rapidly east, could not actually support a lot of that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;infrastructure in their trains and their bridges. So there has been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this debate and an ongoing debate in NATO regarding how 2 percent GDP &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;should be defined.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And then also, we in the U.S. like to say that we are spending all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this and carrying all this burden--and we certainly are carrying a very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;large burden, we spend upwards of 3\1/2\ percent--I'm not sure of it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;exactly--but a lot of that is spent out of NATO areas. So are we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;actually carrying a sufficient burden in NATO as well?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Great, thanks for that. And I will commend to you the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transcript of a briefing we did with General Ben Hodges just after he &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;retired as U.S. Army commander in Europe on precisely that subject.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Paul, please.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Paul Massaro with the Helsinki Commission.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    A few years ago, it looked like the next big step in transatlantic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relations would be an EU-U.S. free trade agreement. That appears to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;totally off the table now and outside of the discussion. To what extent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;should free trade be part of the U.S. approach to Europe?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. Great, thanks. And very succinct, thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Here's what I propose. Let's start in the opposite order that we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;did the panel, so we'll go to Jeff and then in this direction, for your &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;final thoughts.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thanks.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Rathke. Okay. I will be quick. So, Paul, to your question, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think there should certainly be the ambition to work on, whether it is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tariffs or nontariff barriers or the kind of global structural issues, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the economy, the United States and Europe need to be working together. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Whether that has to lead to a free trade agreement--tariffs, on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;average, are relatively low in the United States and in Europe already, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;so there is some gain to be realized there. But as we saw with the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership (TTIP), both in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States and even more crucially in Europe, there was a lot of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public opposition, so you've got to figure out where you can make &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;progress and focus energy there, I think, as the first order of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;business.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    On the 2 percent, 20 percent question, 2 percent has always, for a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;long time, been something the United States wanted NATO to adopt. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it predated the Trump administration. I think the difference now is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there is a singular focus on that one number, which does not always &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bring countries along to increase their contributions. I think 20 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;percent matters more because that's actual investment in real military &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;capabilities, that is 20 percent of spending on R&amp;amp;D and procurement of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;equipment.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think we need to define what capabilities we want Europeans to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have and then hold them to those commitments. We need to measure &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;outputs rather than inputs. And if we measure only inputs, you can have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;an inefficient defense establishment in country A that spends 2 percent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and accomplishes much less than a country B that spends it efficiently.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    As for the future of the European project, Angela Merkel is going &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to remain chancellor of Germany. She's not going to run for her party &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;leadership, but she, depending on how that turns out, she could remain &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;chancellor until 2021. Now, she's weakened by the recent political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;developments, so whether Germany is going to play an active role will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;depend a lot on how this succession takes place. But it leaves France &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as really the country that's putting out ideas that others have to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;react to. But without support of other major European players, it's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hard to move those forward.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    One last comment because it's been discussed a little bit--growth &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rates. It is true that, on average, over the last 10 years, the U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economy has grown faster than Europe, but the gap is actually not as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;dramatic as it might seem. There have been years where Europe's growth &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rate was higher than that of the United States. And then there have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been years where it's been the opposite, especially during the Greek &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;financial crisis in the 2013, 2014, 2015 period.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But I think it would be a mistake to write off Europe's economic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;model as one that is ineffective and that fails to deliver. Despite its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;problems and complications there are still a lot of places across &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe where the economy is growing and where unemployment is falling.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Coyer. I'll be similarly quick. On the 2 percent issue, Ben &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Hodges spoke about this I think in January when he was here, that I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think it's wise to look at that not just in a purely strict way, but &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also look in other ways that countries may contribute to our mutual &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;defense that may not count toward the 2 percent. I think it's smart to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;consider that because there is a lot that other countries do. He raised &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the issue of Germany, which is many times criticized and has been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;perennially on this issue, that they give more than is counted toward &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their actual number.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    On the issue of French leadership of the EU, Macron right now has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very, very, very low approval ratings. I've forgotten what they are, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;but they're really bad--15 to 20 percent, something like that. So &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;whether he sticks around very much longer is an issue as well.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    As I believe I mentioned in my opening statement as well, one of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the key issues that will determine how the EU thrives or whether it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;withers away is whether or not the ruling class in Europe can rethink &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their approach to governance and speak to the clearly expressed &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;aspirations of many of the European citizenry we see in these movements &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that are EU skeptic movements that are arising.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    About popular support on both sides of the Atlantic for the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transatlantic relationship, that's a very, very good point. And that's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;something that I try to address in my speaking and my writing. That's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;actually one of the reasons why I, about 4 years ago with several &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;friends, started this journal called ``Providence: A Journal of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Christianity and American Foreign Policy,'' because on the U.S. side of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Atlantic, as you know, evangelicals and Catholics are a big voting &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bloc. Many times, especially evangelicals, they're not that well &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;informed. They have kind of a kneejerk sense of what America's national &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;identity is and what its role in the world should be, but it's not well &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thought out. So one of the reasons why we started this journal was to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;educate that critical voting bloc in the United States. And we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;specifically, in the area of transatlantic relations, are trying to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;address it from a normative and moral perspective, as well, which is a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;language that crowd gets as to why it's so important in terms of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;democracy promotion, which leads to human flourishing and freedom and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thriving, which, again, is language that evangelicals and Catholics &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;get.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    That's just one aspect of the American voting bloc. The populace as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a whole needs to be educated on this. Same thing in Europe, but a very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;good question.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Bromund. Let me take a stab at doing all four of them really &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;quickly. U.S.-EU free trade, the United States Trade Representative has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;announced the intention to negotiate a trade agreement with the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union as well as the United Kingdom and Japan, so that is back &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on the table in some shape or form. The fundamental problem with TTIP, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in my view, was that it was an effort at regulatory harmonization to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European levels. It was not a tariff-cutting, preeminently, exercise.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In my view, a regulatory tie-up between the U.S. and the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Union would do considerable long-term damage to the competitiveness of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;both of our economies, although it would be very convenient for large &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;companies today who would dictate the terms of that regulatory tie-up. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;So unless we take a fundamentally different approach than we did during &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;TTIP, I remain somewhat skeptical about this approach.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    On 2 percent, with all due respect to General Hodges and his &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;national service, I think he is doing an enormous disservice by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;promoting this line that infrastructure spending is a replacement for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tanks. No amount of German autobahns or improved railways to the east &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are going to deter the Russians. You do not deter people with empty &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;railcars and highways with nothing on them. It takes actual military &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;capabilities.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    All of this argument about infrastructure and logistics, I do not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;underrate the importance of logistics, but it all comes down to being &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;an excuse to allow places to spend money on things that are not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;actually contributors to genuine deterrent power. And that is all it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is. So it is a fundamental disservice to increased genuine European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;defense spending.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Third, soft power. I'm tempted to be flip and say the way to get &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the old relationship back is to have World War III because, I mean, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;World War II was what did it. We're not going to get that back and we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shouldn't run around wishing for it to return, in some respects, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because it would mean an absolute cataclysm.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I don't think there is a really easy or even a very convincing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;long-run answer to the correct problem that you are articulating. I am &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;clearly a Euro skeptic and quite a firm one, but I am certainly not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;anti-European nations and I am not anti-European unless you narrowly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mean anti-European Union by that stricture.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I don't think that there is a lot of anti-Europeanism in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;American public. I do think that there is a significant element of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;anti-Americanism in Europe. I wouldn't say it's a predominant element, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;but it is there, it is a real factor and TTIP proved it, among other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;things. The single most useful thing that could happen would be for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European political leaders to stop making excuses for anti-Americanism, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;full stop.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Finally, Merkel, Macron--the last time I checked, Macron was at 27 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;percent, so I guess he's doing a little better, but it's still &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;terrible. Macron, in a way, is a symptom of the problem we've been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;talking about, right? He is another populist leader. He happens to be a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;somewhat more attractive one in some respects, but where are the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;traditional parties of France, the traditional post-Gaullist settlement &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;parties of France at least? Macron, in some ways, is a rebellion &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;against those parties because they were seen to be, well, failing. So &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for many reasons he is as much a symptom of the problem as he is any &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sort of potential cure for it.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    That really highlights sort of the core problem here, that one can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be very critical, and I am, of Chancellor Merkel or other European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;political leaders in big nations. But it's not very clear who the next &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;appealing person is. One can be critical of Theresa May in Great &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Britain, and I am quite critical. Would you prefer Jeremy Corbyn from a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transatlantic point of view? Well, I would not. Would you prefer the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;French nationalists to Macron? Well, I probably would not prefer them. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And that's the problem that we've run into, that the political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;consensus now is so shallow, commands so little loyalty, but yet is so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all-encompassing that when you look outside of it, many of the options &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are not very appealing; but when you look inside it, it's obvious that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the options are not very appealing either. And that's a very bad place &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to be in.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Let me close on the mundane question of growth rates, which Jeff &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has returned to. We all prioritize growth too little, including in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States. We are marginally better than Europe, but we, too, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prioritize stability excessively and growth too little. The Europeans &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are on sort of one extreme of that tendency, but we ourselves are no &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;paragon of virtue in this regard.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I will simply close and reiterate what I said at the start. After &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;World War II, we came to the understanding that you don't have stable &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;democratic political systems unless you have reasonably high and stable &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;levels of economic growth. Social protection is important, but it must &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be balanced with growth. Everywhere in the developed world, we give too &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;much attention to protection and too little attention to growth. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that is a rejection of the lesson that we learned the hard way by 1945.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Tiersky. With that invocation of World War II, let me thank our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;panelists for informing the Helsinki Commission and our broader &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;community here in Congress and around Washington and our Facebook feed.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think we've seen today the evidence of why it's important to air &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;both our agreements and our disagreements, particularly at times of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;significant change. One key point I take away from this is that, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regardless of its form, I think all of the panelists have agreed that a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transatlantic partnership that is strong is crucial, even if we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disagree on how to get there.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Colleagues, panelists, we appreciate your contributions to our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reflection on this set of issues and in particular for staying a few &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;minutes extra to undertake responses to the excellent questions we got &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from our audience here. Thank you very much for your time. [Applause.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    [Whereupon, at 11:43 a.m., the briefing ended.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                          [all]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            This is an official publication of the Commission on&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                    Security and Cooperation in Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  This publication is intended to document&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  developments and trends in participating&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  States of the Organization for Security&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                     and Cooperation in Europe [OSCE].&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;           All Commission publications may be freely reproduced,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            in any form, with appropriate credit. The Commission&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            encourages the widest possible dissemination of its&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               publications.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      www.csce.gov       @HelsinkiComm&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 The Commission's Web site provides access&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 to the latest press releases and reports,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                as well as hearings and briefings. Using the&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;         Commission's electronic subscription service, readers are&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            able to receive press releases, articles, and other&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          materials by topic or countries of particular interest.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                          Please subscribe today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;&amp;lt;/pre&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
</intro>
</Hearing>
