<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="25872">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                        [H.A.S.C. No. 115-50]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                HEARING&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                   ON&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                          FOR FISCAL YEAR 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                  AND&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;              OVERSIGHT OF PREVIOUSLY AUTHORIZED PROGRAMS&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               BEFORE THE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;committee_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES&lt;/committee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
&lt;/option&gt;
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON SEAPOWER AND PROJECTION FORCES HEARING&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                                   ON
                   DEPARTMENT OF THE AIR FORCE FISCAL
                      YEAR 2018 BUDGET REQUEST FOR
                     SEAPOWER AND PROJECTION FORCES
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                              MAY 25, 2017
                                  ______
                         U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE 
25-872                         WASHINGTON : 2018 
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON SEAPOWER AND PROJECTION FORCES&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                 ROBERT J. WITTMAN, Virginia, Chairman
K. MICHAEL CONAWAY, Texas            JOE COURTNEY, Connecticut
VICKY HARTZLER, Missouri             SUSAN A. DAVIS, California
BRADLEY BYRNE, Alabama, Vice Chair   JAMES R. LANGEVIN, Rhode Island
SCOTT DesJARLAIS, Tennessee          MADELEINE Z. BORDALLO, Guam
MIKE GALLAGHER, Wisconsin            JOHN GARAMENDI, California
DUNCAN HUNTER, California            DONALD NORCROSS, New Jersey
PAUL COOK, California                SETH MOULTON, Massachusetts
JIM BRIDENSTINE, Oklahoma            COLLEEN HANABUSA, Hawaii
STEPHEN KNIGHT, California           A. DONALD McEACHIN, Virginia
RALPH LEE ABRAHAM, Louisiana
                Bruce Johnson, Professional Staff Member
              Phil MacNaughton, Professional Staff Member
                          Jodi Brignola, Clerk
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <Directory>
    &lt;table-of-content&gt;C O N T E N T S&lt;/table-of-content&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS&lt;/Speakers&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;Hon Joe Courtney&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative from Connecticut Ranking Member&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Hon Robert J Wittman&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative from Virginia Chairman&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;witnesses&gt;WITNESSES&lt;/witnesses&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Lt Gen Arnold W Bunch&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Jr USAF&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;APPENDIX&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;Prepared Statements:&lt;/Speakers&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;Lt Gen Arnold W Bunch&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Jr joint with Lt Gen Jerry D Harris and Maj Gen Scott A Vander Hamm Wittman&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
</Directory>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;Subcommittee on Seapower and Projection Forces,&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;Chairman&gt;
        &lt;Cname&gt;                            Washington&lt;/Cname&gt;
        &lt;Clocation&gt; 2017.&lt;/Clocation&gt;
    &lt;/Chairman&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;The subcommittee met&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; in &lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;ViceChair&gt;
        &lt;Cname&gt;room 2212&lt;/Cname&gt;
        &lt;Clocation&gt; Hon. Robert J. &lt;/Clocation&gt;
    &lt;/ViceChair&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Wittman (chairman of the subcommittee) presiding.&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt;Wittman (chairman of the subcommittee) presiding.&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;     FROM VIRGINIA, CHAIRMAN, SUBCOMMITTEE ON SEAPOWER AND 
                       PROJECTION FORCES
    Mr. Wittman. We will call to order the Subcommittee on 
Seapower and Projection Forces.
    And I want to thank all of the witnesses for joining us 
today.
    And thank you, for the members joining us for an early 
morning start.
    So today the subcommittee convenes to receive testimony on 
the fiscal year 2018 Air Force budget request regarding bomber, 
tanker, and airlift acquisition programs. The distinguished 
panel of Air Force leaders testifying before us today are: 
Lieutenant General Arnold W. Bunch, Jr., U.S. Air Force 
Military Deputy, Office of the Assistant Secretary of the Air 
Force for Acquisition; Lieutenant General Jerry D. Harris, 
United States Air Force Deputy Chief of Staff for Strategic 
Plans and Requirements; and Major General Scott A. Vander Hamm, 
United States Air Force Assistant Deputy Chief of Staff for 
Operations.
    Gentlemen, thank you for being with us today.
    The fiscal year 2018 budget request for projection forces 
continues to modernize and recapitalize critical Air Force 
weapon systems. I am pleased to see significantly increased 
investment in the B-21 long-range strike bomber and steady 
investment in procuring KC-46A tankers. The budget also 
continues to take solid steps to modernize the legacy Guard and 
Reserve C-130H tactical airlift fleet and recapitalize the 
high-visibility Presidential aircraft.
    That said, I continue to be concerned about the ability of 
our military to properly provide for our Nation's defense given 
the damage that sequestration may have had on our fiscal year 
2018 budget deliberations. Throughout the year in this past 
year in testimony to Congress, the Air Force senior leadership 
indicated the Air Force is one of the busiest, smallest, 
oldest, and least ready fleets in our history. It is my firm 
conviction, in light of the higher-end threats posed by China, 
Russia, Iran, and North Korea, that we provide the Air Force 
the resources it needs to fully support and, if possible, 
accelerate critical recapitalization programs.
    With regard to bombers, I fully support the critical B-21 
bomber program and am pleased to see that we are moving forward 
on this new platform, which is needed for projecting power over 
long distances and into denied environments. I look forward to 
assessing in better detail the classified portion of the B-21 
program to ensure progress on design and to assess proposed 
risk mitigation strategies.
    With regard to tankers, I am concerned that the KC-46A 
program continues to suffer delays. Even after overcoming 
initial setbacks, it is now facing a highly compressed test and 
certification schedule that has almost zero room for error. I 
look forward to hearing your thoughts on this program and 
whether or not the first 18 aircraft will be delivered in time 
to meet the adjusted October 2018 contract deadline.
    With regard to recapitalizing the Presidential aircraft, I 
want to ensure that the President has the capability to carry 
out the requirements of the office and that the American 
people, whose taxes fund these aircraft, do not have to pay one 
dime more than necessary.
    Lastly, I am concerned that this budget fails to provide 
the necessary resources to procure needed avionics upgrades. 
These upgrades will ensure that the entire fleet of tankers, 
airlifters, and bombers are able to operate safely in 
compliance with the FAA [Federal Aviation Administration]-
mandated next-gen [generation] air traffic management standards 
by January 1, 2020. The civilian aviation sector is rapidly 
moving towards compliance, and I am concerned that our military 
aircraft could be shut out of airspace they need for transit 
and training.
    While I am pleased that the Air Force's fiscal year 2018 
budget request makes up some lost ground over last year, I am 
concerned that the proposed budget directs the Air Force to 
make false choices between capability, capacity, and safety, 
when the undeniable reality is that our military needs all of 
the above. I firmly believe that what this subcommittee and the 
rest of Congress does about national defense and military 
readiness will be a defining issue.
    We need a strong Air Force equipped with the most capable 
aircraft that enable our men and women to carry out their 
missions effectively and safely. To do this we need leadership 
in national security. We need an unambiguous declaration that 
our national security is our preeminent responsibility.
    Once again, I want to thank our witnesses for participating 
in our hearing this afternoon, and I look forward to discussing 
these important topics.
    Obviously my clock is different than yours. The hearing is 
this morning.
    With that, I turn to my good friend and colleague, the 
ranking member of the subcommittee, Joe Courtney.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Appendix on page 27.]
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;   CONNECTICUT, RANKING MEMBER, SUBCOMMITTEE ON SEAPOWER AND 
                       PROJECTION FORCES
    Mr. Courtney. Thank you, Mr. Chairman, and thank you for 
holding this hearing on the 2018 Air Force budget request for 
the projection forces programs within our jurisdiction.
    And thank you, to all the witnesses, again for being here 
today.
    The tankers, bombers, and airlift programs that fall under 
the projection forces side of our panel's oversight serve as 
the backbone of our Nation's ability to bring and sustain the 
power that preserves our Nation's interests around the world. 
As we know all too well, however, these important aircraft all 
share the common enemy of age.
    The tankers and bombers in service today are largely legacy 
aircraft. These aircraft in most cases are much older than the 
airmen and women who fly and service them.
    That is why it will be critical that we ensure that the 
2018 budget properly invests in the refueling, mobility, 
maritime patrol, and long-range strike programs under our 
purview. Among other things, the budget continues to reflect 
the high strategic priority placed on two critical 
recapitalization programs: the KC-46A Pegasus tanker and the B-
21 long-range strike bomber. Both of these programs are vital 
to ensuring that our Nation can continue to support operations 
around the world and respond when needed.
    Another continued area of concern for me and this 
subcommittee is the modernization of our C-130H fleet. Back 
home in Connecticut the Flying Yankees of the 103rd Airlift 
Wing have largely completed their transition to the new C-130H 
flying mission. Half of their aircraft recently deployed 
overseas on their first combat mission, which was a capstone to 
years of effort to stand the unit up stemming from the 2005 
BRAC [base realignment and closure].
    As we all well know, the C-130H fleet is an aging one in 
need of modernization. This panel led the efforts in the 2015 
NDAA [National Defense Authorization Act] to unlock the 
avionics modernization program needed to upgrade these aircraft 
with the assistance, again, of some of the witnesses here this 
morning, to meet international airspace restrictions by 2020.
    A second phase of the program is focused on additional 
cockpit and technology upgrades. We have heard testimony about 
the progress made on both of these increments of the avionics 
modernization program and would appreciate any updates on how 
the 2018 budget supports these efforts.
    Along these lines, Congress has invested substantial 
resources into other C-130H modernization initiatives, such as 
upgraded engines and propellers. It is my understanding that 
funding provided in 2016 and 2017 is currently on hold pending 
the results of operational testing being conducted right now. 
Given the strong interest that we have in ensuring that the C-
130H remains relevant into the future, I would appreciate an 
update on this testing and the way ahead.
    Finally, over the last year Congress has made meaningful 
and bipartisan progress in limiting the impact of sequestration 
and Budget Control Act. While mitigating the across-the-board 
cuts in 2016 and 2017 with the 2-year budget deal was 
important, the fact remains that our Air Force, like the 
military at large, remains handcuffed by sequestration in 2018 
and beyond because that 2-year deal obviously has expired.
    World events will continue to further demonstrate just how 
important it is for all of us on this committee and colleagues 
on both sides of our aisle to come together to make the 
compromises needed to protect our security and support the 
needs of our Nation.
    I look forward to hearing from our witnesses and our 
colleagues on the subcommittee, Mr. Chairman, and I yield back.
    Mr. Wittman. Thank you, Mr. Courtney.
    Major General Vander Hamm, Lieutenant General Bunch, 
Lieutenant General Harris, I understand that you all are going 
to be providing a single combined statement so I will turn it 
over to you for presentation of that statement.
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
</Hearing>
