<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="30027">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;115th Congress }                            Printed for the use of the             &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;2nd Session    }      Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe                       &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;======================================================================&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	                     Democracy Deferred: The State&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	                    of Elections and Fundamental&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	                       Freedoms in Azerbaijan&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              May 9, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                           Briefing of the&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         Washington: 2019&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;      Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  234 Ford House Office Building                                               &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   Washington, DC 20515&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      202-225-1901&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      csce@mail.house.gov&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      http://www.csce.gov&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         @HelsinkiComm&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            Legislative Branch Commissioners&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;              HOUSE				SENATE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;CHRISTOPHER H. SMITH, New Jersey 	ROGER WICKER, Mississippi,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Co-Chairman			  Chairman&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ALCEE L. HASTINGS, Florida		BENJAMIN L. CARDIN. Maryland&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ROBERT B. ADERHOLT, Alabama		JOHN BOOZMAN, Arkansas&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;MICHAEL C. BURGESS, Texas		CORY GARDNER, Colorado&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;STEVE COHEN, Tennessee			MARCO RUBIO, Florida&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;RICHARD HUDSON, North Carolina		JEANNE SHAHEEN, New Hampshire&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;RANDY HULTGREN, Illinois		THOM TILLIS, North Carolina&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;SHEILA JACKSON LEE, Texas		TOM UDALL, New Mexico&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;GWEN MOORE, Wisconsin			SHELDON WHITEHOUSE, Rhode Island&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;               Executive Branch Commissioners&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                    DEPARTMENT OF STATE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  DEPARTMENT OF COMMERCE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                            [II]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Helsinki process, formally titled the Conference on Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe, traces its origin to the signing of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Helsinki Final Act in Finland on August 1, 1975, by the leaders of 33 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European countries, the United States and Canada. As of January 1, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;1995, the Helsinki process was renamed the Organization for Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE). The membership of the OSCE has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;expanded to 56 participating States, reflecting the breakup of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Soviet Union, Czechoslovakia, and Yugoslavia.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The OSCE Secretariat is in Vienna, Austria, where weekly meetings &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the participating States' permanent representatives are held. In &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;addition, specialized seminars and meetings are convened in various &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;locations. Periodic consultations are held among Senior Officials, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Ministers and Heads of State or Government.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Although the OSCE continues to engage in standard setting in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fields of military security, economic and environmental cooperation, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and human rights and humanitarian concerns, the Organization is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;primarily focused on initiatives designed to prevent, manage and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resolve conflict within and among the participating States. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Organization deploys numerous missions and field activities located in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Southeastern and Eastern Europe, the Caucasus, and Central Asia. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;website of the OSCE is: &amp;lt;www.osce.org&amp;gt;.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, also known as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Helsinki Commission, is a U.S. Government agency created in 1976 to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;monitor and encourage compliance by the participating States with their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;OSCE commitments, with a particular emphasis on human rights.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission consists of nine members from the United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Senate, nine members from the House of Representatives, and one member &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;each from the Departments of State, Defense and Commerce. The positions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Chair and Co-Chair rotate between the Senate and House every two &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years, when a new Congress convenes. A professional staff assists the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commissioners in their work.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In fulfilling its mandate, the Commission gathers and disseminates &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relevant information to the U.S. Congress and the public by convening &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hearings, issuing reports that reflect the views of Members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission and/or its staff, and providing details about the activities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the Helsinki process and developments in OSCE participating States.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission also contributes to the formulation and execution of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.S. policy regarding the OSCE, including through Member and staff &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participation on U.S. Delegations to OSCE meetings. Members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission have regular contact with parliamentarians, government &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;officials, representatives of non-governmental organizations, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;private individuals from participating States. The website of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission is: &amp;lt;www.csce.gov&amp;gt;.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Democracy Deferred: The State of Elections and&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                Fundamental Freedoms in Azerbaijan&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              May 9, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                  				Page&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              PARTICIPANTS&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Everett Price, Policy Advisor, Commission on Security and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Cooperation in Europe                                               1&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Audrey L. Altstadt, Professor of History, University of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Massachusetts-Amherst                                               3&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Maran Turner, Executive Director, Freedom Now                   6&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Emin Milli, Director, Meydan TV                                 9&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;           Democracy Deferred: The State of Elections and&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  Fundamental Freedoms in Azerbaijan&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              ----------                              &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              May 9, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The briefing was held at 10:32 a.m. in Room SVC 215, Capitol &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Visitor Center, Washington, DC, Everett Price, Policy Advisor, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, presiding.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Panelists present: Everett Price, Policy Advisor, Commission on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Security and Cooperation in Europe; Dr. Audrey L. Altstadt, Professor &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of History, University of Massachusetts-Amherst; Maran Turner, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Executive Director, Freedom Now; and Emin Milli, Director, Meydan TV.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. Good morning, everyone. I'll let people take a second to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;get seated. On behalf of our Chairman, Senator Roger Wicker, and Co-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Chairman, Congressman Chris Smith, I want to welcome you to this U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Helsinki Commission briefing titled ``Democracy Deferred: The State of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Elections and Fundamental Freedoms in Azerbaijan.'' I'm grateful for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;your presence with us this morning and extend my appreciation to all of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;those who are tuning in from around the world via our Facebook Live &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;stream.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My name is Everett Price. I am the commission's policy advisor &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;responsible for the Southern Caucasus region. The commission is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;convening this briefing this morning to assess the state of democracy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and human rights in Azerbaijan today. As a participating State of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe, Azerbaijan, like &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the United States and over 50 other nations, has freely undertaken &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;robust commitments in the fields of democratic principles and basic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rights. Our commission is charged with monitoring the implementation of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these commitments across Europe and Eurasia and informing American &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;foreign policy toward the OSCE and its member States.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Regrettably, the actions of the Azerbaijani Government have given &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;us cause for concern in recent years. At the start of his second decade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in power, President Ilham Aliyev in 2013 tightened his regime's grip on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;national institutions, the political opposition, and independent press. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Our commissioners closely followed these developments and drew &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;attention to them. In December 2015, then-Commission Chairman &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Congressman Chris Smith introduced the Azerbaijan Democracy Act which, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;among other things, sought to impose strict travel bans and asset &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;freezes on Azerbaijan's leadership until the government released &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;political prisoners, ceased its harassment of the media and civil &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;society, and demonstrated progress toward free, fair, and transparent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;elections.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Since the introduction of the Azerbaijan Democracy Act, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government has freed some political prisoners. But it has continued, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and in some ways escalated, its clampdown on political activists and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the press. What's more, the country has not held a single free and fair &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;election. Quite to the contrary, President Aliyev staged a popular &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;referendum in September 2016 that extended presidential terms from 5 to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;7 years and empowered himself to appoint his wife as vice president, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;unilaterally placing her at the top of the line of succession. Amidst &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;widespread harassment of journalists and anti-referendum campaigners, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the government reported that the sweeping constitutional changes were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;approved with around 90 percent of the vote.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    2017 brought more worrying developments. Having, over the years, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shuttered, co-opted, or otherwise censored all independent print, TV, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and radio media, the government took the next step by blocking &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;virtually all the country's major online sources of independent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reporting, including Meydan TV, whose director is here with us this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;morning. There were also disturbing claims that the government has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resorted to kidnapping independent journalists abroad. In September of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;last year, Congressman Smith and Congressman McGovern responded to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these events by introducing a successor bill to the Azerbaijan &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Democracy Act, House Resolution 537. H. Res. 537 calls on the U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;administration to pursue targeted human rights and religious freedom &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sanctions against Azerbaijani authorities.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Just last month, President Aliyev was re-elected to a 7-year term &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with more than 86 percent of the vote. The government fulfilled its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;commitment to invite the OSCE to observe the election and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;observation mission conducted its work freely. Unfortunately, however, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the international observers had a bleak story to tell. The OSCE's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;preliminary conclusions described a vote that ``lacked genuine &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;competition'' amidst a ``restrictive political environment and legal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;framework that curtails fundamental rights and freedoms.''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Azerbaijan is an important partner for the United States in a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sensitive and critical region. Our examination of Azerbaijan's human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rights record is born out of this recognition. The United States holds &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;its friends to a higher standard in the interest of fostering stable &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and enduring partnerships that are rooted in core values. As Azerbaijan &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prepares to mark 100 years of independence on May 28, it has the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opportunity to open a new century by renewing its respect for the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fundamental freedoms and dignity of its people. Our expert panel today &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;will help us to take stock of this moment in Azerbaijani history, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the steps that are needed to begin charting a new path. With us today &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are distinguished experts in Azerbaijan in different aspects of this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;situation that we're examining.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    First, we'll begin with Audrey Altstadt, a professor of history at &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the University of Massachusetts-Amherst. She is the author of numerous &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;articles, op-ed essays, and three books, most recently ``Frustrated &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Democracy in Post-Soviet Azerbaijan,'' published by the Woodrow Wilson &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Center Press and Columbia University Press just last year in 2017. She &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is chair of the George F. Kennan Institute Advisory Council and has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been a consultant to The Freedom House, Radio Liberty, U.S. Departments &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of State and Justice, other U.S. Government agencies, and the U.S. Army &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;War College. She earned a doctorate from the University of Chicago and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;an honorary doctorate from Khazar University in Baku, Azerbaijan.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Altstadt will help us with an overview of the situation facing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;democracy and elections in Azerbaijan. And then we'll move on to our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;other panelists who will discuss the situation regarding political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prisoners as well as media freedom in the country. And without further &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ado, I will turn it over to Dr. Altstadt. Thank you for being here.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Altstadt. Thank you. I want to thank Everett and I want to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thank the commission for the opportunity to be here and make these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;comments.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Azerbaijan's political profile in both law and practice continues &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to move away from democratic norms, as exemplified in its recent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;presidential election of April 11. The turn away from democracy has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been apparent throughout most of the post-Soviet period, but has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;changed noticeably under Ilham Aliyev's presidency, since 2003. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Although we often hear about the crackdown of 2014, I think that the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pattern that it refers to actually began after the 2012 elections to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the national assembly, because in that election the major opposition &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;parties were sidelined, and the ruling party and its supporters gained &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a substantial majority in the national assembly. That control of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;legislature was instrumental in centralizing control in the executive.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The tightening of controls in Azerbaijani politics is readily &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;measurable in the electoral process. And so I'll begin briefly by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mentioning a few points that come up with the recent OSCE ODIHR &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;monitoring reports concerning the April 11 election. Those of you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;familiar with the OSCE process--probably most of you in this room--know &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that there are several reports for each election: a needs assessment &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;report, an interim report prior to election day, a preliminary post-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;election report, and the final report. The last time I checked, which &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was last night, that was not yet up on the website. The election &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;itself, as previously, was marked by ballot box stuffing, carousel &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;voting, irregularities in polling stations and in counting. At the end &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the day, the election campaign was deemed to have been not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;competitive. None of the candidates offered significant alternative &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;views or criticism of current policies, or of the incumbent.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    One of the strengths of the OSCE ODIHR reports--which I've used &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;over the years and read every one with respect to Azerbaijan--is that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they not only examine the applicable laws and the events of the actual &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;day of voting, but they also examine the laws and the structures, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;media environment, and the role of authorities prior to the election &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;day, as well as other times. I want to draw attention to just a couple &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of points here. This is by no means an exhaustive list. First is the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;timing of the election in April 11. This was in and of itself an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;anomaly, because in the past, elections have been held in the fall, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;usually October or November. And indeed, this election also was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;originally scheduled for October. It was moved to April 11 only in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;February.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The reason for the abrupt change has been a subject of lots of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;speculation, most vocally, I suppose, the undercutting of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opposition. But the opposition has been so significantly sidelined by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;previous policies and practices that that doesn't seem like a real &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;major reason to make such a sudden change. There was also discussion &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about Ilham having serious illness and needing to undergo medical &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;treatment. I don't know whether any of these things are true, but I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;will return to this point at the end.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The second point in my thinking really has to do with how it is the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;election got moved in the first place. And this is related to another &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;aspect of the OSCE ODIHR reporting, which is the larger, complex legal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and constitutional issues, some of which Everett just talked about in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;his introduction--the constitutional amendments, more than 100 of them, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which were rushed through in the summer of 2016, which then &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;concentrated more power in the hands of the president.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    A third aspect is the concentration of power in the ruling party in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the national assembly. The ability to make changes in law and in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conditions that allow for the ruling elite is really significant. First &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of all, with respect to elections, it means that YAP, the Yeni &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaycan Partiyasi, the ruling party, not only controls a third of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the election commission, its other supporters control more than that. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Therefore, it also controls all the lower level commissions. And it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;chairs all the commissions at all levels. Many of the opposition &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;parties and opposition parliamentarians--used loosely in this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;instance--who are deputies of the national assembly are in fact nominal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opposition. But they are actually regime supporters. This lock on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;national assembly is what allows the assembly to introduce bills, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;debate them, and then implement them as if they were in fact a product &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of independent, elected action by an elected body, rather than a diktat &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the regime. And this process is a charade.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    A fourth point is the general environment in which the election &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;took place. Constraints on the media, which others will talk about, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public demonstrations, which are constrained and sometimes quashed with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the use of violence by the police. There is intimidation of potential &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participants, and sometimes just physically blocking access to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;demonstrations by closing streets or by closing subway stations. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these are significant because they are an important measure of civil &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;society participation, which is essential in a democratic system. In &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the same way that many of the opposition parties are not really in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opposition, many of the so-called NGOs are actually GONGOs, or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government-organized nongovernmental organizations. These are also a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fiction.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And finally, one of the things which concerns me the most is the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;specific targeting of the younger generation, people that are 40 and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;under, those who have been shaped to the least degree by Soviet &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;education and Soviet expectations.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    There is a wider situation here, which is an important context for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understanding political life, governance, and other issues in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan. In Azerbaijan we are seeing democracy in form but not in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;substance. The regime uses the terminology of democracy, but in fact it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;establishes a system which it controls and shapes for the regime's own &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;benefit. This is really the opposite of a democracy. And yet, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regime and its representatives insist that the form is the substance. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;There are supporters who make this argument. There are those who have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been persuaded by gifts or lobbying from Azerbaijan. But there are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;groups that are not fooled. And the OSCE is one of those. The Venice &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission has not been fooled. The European Court of Human Rights has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not been fooled.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The numerous rulings which the court has made against cases brought &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from Azerbaijan have been ignored in Baku. And even though the regime &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;talks about conforming to its principles and of the Council of Europe, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in fact when it comes right down to the actions, they violate these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regularly. Late last fall, the Council of Europe finally stood up to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the pressures of the regime and voted to potentially expel Azerbaijan &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from its membership in a multistep process that it is beginning. This &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;infringement process would first begin with loss of voting rights. If &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it should take place, and if they should ultimately get to a point of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;expelling Azerbaijan or getting close to expulsion, this would be an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;enormous embarrassment for the regime. And the Aliyev regime certainly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;does not like to be embarrassed.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And this, in my mind, brings us back to the reason which I believe &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is a crucial reason for having moved the elections in the first place, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and that has to do with the case of Ilgar Mammadov. And, again, my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;colleagues will talk more about this, but the European Court for Human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Rights ruled that his 2013 conviction was, in fact, politically &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;motivated and ordered that he be released. But he was not. The warnings &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;were ignored. And in November 2017, there was a Council of Europe &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;deadline which passed, not surprisingly that the regime, again, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ignored. And then that's when the Council of Europe threatened to take &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these infringement steps.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Perhaps it is only coincidental that a few weeks later Azerbaijani &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;law was changed to allow the president to move the date of elections, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as long as they were within 60 days--or, more than 60 days from the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;date of setting. It was then about a month and a half after that that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the elections were, in fact, rescheduled. I don't believe in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;coincidences, so I suspect that this is in fact a way to move the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;election to beat this multistep process by the Council of Europe and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;then, before they could take an action, release Ilgar Mammadov--too &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;late for him to be a contender in the Presidential election, but in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time to stop this action against Azerbaijan.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    There is a notion that Azerbaijan is a good partner for the West &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and for the United States with respect to energy cooperation, military, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and business opportunities. I'm well familiar with this explanation, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and also the plea that Westerners should be fair and talk about the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;advances that this regime has in fact made in terms of rebuilding the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;infrastructure, finding housing for internally displaced persons &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;(IDPs), improving the poverty rate in the country. I do acknowledge &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that. And I do, indeed, want to be fair. And to be further fair, I also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want to point out that many of these infrastructural improvements were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;made in such a way that the companies that in fact carried them out are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;owned directly or indirectly by the first family and other oligarchs, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;allegedly, in conjunction with international reporting, which has taken &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;place and discovered ownership of these various companies.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So in other words, the picture is indeed complex. I want to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;acknowledge that. I want to point out that we are talking about that. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And in Azerbaijan, there really are stark differences between, let's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;say, those who have these opportunities to make money through tourism &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and construction, who have the ability to gain immense private wealth &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;while some IDPs are still living in train cars. There are people whose &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;children go to schools in Baku that are underfunded. They have to pay &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;teachers just to get the grades the students earn, much less better &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;grades. And then there are other people who, of course, send their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;children to school abroad, where they can live in condos in London or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;New York and go to private schools. So the gap between the rich and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;poor, the haves and the have-nots, is very stark here.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The underlying argument that Azerbaijan is a good partner in some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ways is not the argument I'm making. I'm making quite the opposite &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;argument. I'm making the argument instead that the key function of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government is to protect the individual, regardless of the individual's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;views or beliefs. And I think, speaking as a historian, that one thing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we learn from the 20th century is that systems that repress individual &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;human rights and human beings ultimately may look like they're good &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;partners, but in the end make poor partners because they are ultimately &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;untrustworthy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. Thank you very much for that insightful overview. That &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;helps set the stage for the rest of our conversation.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Next, I'd like to turn to Maran Turner. She's the founding &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;executive director of Freedom Now, a U.S.-based organization that works &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to eliminate politically motivated detention worldwide. Among its &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;efforts is the individual representation of prisoners of conscience, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;working with pro bono counsel and NGO partners to provide legal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;assistance and targeted advocacy initiatives intended to secure the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;release of those arbitrarily detained. Freedom Now has worked &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;extensively in Eurasia, and since 2010 has maintained active cases and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;projects in Azerbaijan. The rest of her bio is available in your &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;folders.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So, Maran, thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Turner. Thank you, Everett. And my thanks to the Helsinki &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission and to all of you. I'm delighted to see a room that has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;quite filled out. I know all of us here maintain a keen eye on what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;happens in Azerbaijan. And it's important to see such interest from you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all as well.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Subject to my bio, as Everett just read, I'm going to speak about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the situation pertaining to political prisoners in Azerbaijan, which is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;an ongoing and destabilizing trend that's ripped apart families and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ripped apart the strong networks of civil society. As small as it was, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it was a great hope for the future of that country. And as my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;colleague, Audrey, has spoken about, President Aliyev has really &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;meticulously consolidated power around his family and a small cabal of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;loyal allies. And this is really what's provided the framework for the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sheer scale of politically motivated imprisonment. It's what has made &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it possible to keep him insulated from criticism and from political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;threat. And true to the authoritarian's playbook, Aliyev and his close &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;associates do this by maintaining a strict hold and exploiting primary &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;institutions like the judiciary, law enforcement, and the media.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But it's the law enforcement and the judiciary that's been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;especially busy, since commencing a crackdown that began in earnest &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;around 2011-2013. This intensified, quite famously, in 2014, when civil &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;society was quite decapitated in the country, and the leaders of a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;dozen civil society organizations were arrested. This was after the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government had implemented a series of NGO laws which, at the time, we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;suspected where they were going with that. But there was optimism late &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in 2015 and 2016, when about a dozen of these individuals had been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;released. And these were people that a lot of us paid close attention &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to, because they were people--journalists, lawyers, and human rights &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;defenders--who we had worked with over the years, who had been bringing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;us cases of other political prisoners. And all of a sudden, they were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in jail.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    It meant a lot to us to advocate for their release. And we were all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very heartened when we saw them released. But we were not operating &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;under an illusion that change was coming. And in fact, the revolving &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;door carried on. More arrests came. And many people actually were not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;released and stayed in prison, and still are. Today, there's around 140 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to 160 political prisoners. This is actually more than the number that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was reported in 2014, at the height of the crackdown. The people in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prison are lawyers, journalists, activists, politicians. Since that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time, since a number of them have been released, they've gone into &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;exile. Even before those arrests, there were a number of people working &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the country as journalists and human rights defenders who saw the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;writing on the wall and escaped.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Some came to the West. For the most part, they have been able to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;continue their advocacy from abroad. But as many can tell you, Emin as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;well, their family members have suffered on their behalf at home. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Others went to neighboring Georgia. There are obvious drawbacks to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;activists. Even though they've been able to carry on their advocacy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from abroad, they are not on the ground. And the government has been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;able and has done their level best to paint them as traitors who've &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;escaped the country to go join outside forces.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    One particularly egregious example I want to speak about, which &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Audrey touched on as well, is the case of Ilgar Mammadov. He's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;important for a couple reasons. One, he has been in jail since 2013, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;when he wrote a blog post dispelling a narrative that the government &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;had been putting out and promoting with respect to a demonstration that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;had turned destructive. He was sentenced for essentially fomenting mass &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disorder and was imprisoned--and put in prison for 7 years. And he's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;still there. I don't think any of us expected this. There was a lot of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;international and local attention on his case in 2013, in 2014. When &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the other arrests came in 2014, Ilgar Mammadov's case continued to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on every short list I saw that was going to the State Department and to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the European Union calling for his release.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    As Audrey mentioned, he actually was subject to two European Court &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;decisions, one with respect to the denial of his pre-trial release, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;then also with respect to the government's failure to provide him with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a fair trial. And what was notable on both those cases is that the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Court found a violation of Article 18, which is essentially &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;political motivations on the part of the government. Again, Ilgar is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;still in prison. And, again, as Audrey mentioned, the infringement &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;proceedings have been taken up by the European Court at the request of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Council of Ministers. Suspension or expulsion is possible. A few &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years ago, I don't think any of us in the international human rights &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;community wanted that. We continued to maintain that having Azerbaijan &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the Council of Europe, subject to the jurisdiction of the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Court, was critical. That being surrounded by discussions and a spirit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of rule of law and democratic principles could only fare well in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;long term.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Unfortunately, now I don't know that there's many that continue to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hold that position. Reports have come out in recent years--most &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;recently from the Parliamentary Assembly and the Council of Europe--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that detail a level of corruption that is staggering and beyond, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think, even what people working inside the Council of Europe were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;already aware of. It seems now that rather than what people thought &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would be a democratizing impact, has actually been the opposite. That &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in fact, having Azerbaijan inside the Council of Europe unfortunately &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has been a corrupting force. To put this in context, Ilgar's petition &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;or application at the European Court is actually just one of 2,000. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;There are 2,000 cases pending at the European Court against Azerbaijan. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Last year the court decided 26 cases, found human rights violations of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;24 of them--violations related to rights to freedom from arbitrary &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;detention, right to fair trial, and right to freedom of assembly and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;association.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I want to touch on a couple of things before I close. Among the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cases that don't get enough attention, frankly, are the religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;freedom cases. This issue has been made quite murky by the Azerbaijan &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Government which declares these individuals as extremists and under the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;influence of Iran. And while there are no doubt some radicals in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;country, Iran has gained influence inside as well, and the Azerbaijani &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Government is secular, 60 percent of the prisoners of conscience on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these lists are those who have been put in prison because of their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;independent practice of Islam, and their association with outspoken &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;clerics that has been used as an impetus to imprison them.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The U.S. Commission on International Religious Freedom has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;designated Azerbaijan as a tier two country, indicating that violations &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of religious freedom are systematic and ongoing. Best example of this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is the so-called Nardaran raid in 2015, where a number of individuals &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;associated with a group called the Muslim Unity Movement were arrested. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;They were charged with inciting violence. Their leaders have been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;horrifically treated and tortured. In fact, just last week there were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reports of new beatings. This group has been well known to civil &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;society in the country. In fact, they're not known for religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;advocacy or even particularly political. They're actually more known &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for protesting the government's treatment and policies toward them, as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;well as their calls for a better social support system. If there's a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;lesson that we've learned in the war on terror, it's that branding &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;innocent people, especially community leaders, as terrorists can lead &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to radicalization within the country. And while their pleas might fall &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on deaf ears in Baku, I can tell you that Tehran is all ears.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The final trend I want to touch on is Azerbaijan's transnational &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;activities. As more and more dissidents have fled, the government's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tentacles have spread out in search of them. Those in exile in the U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Europe, as I mentioned, have mostly been left alone. Their family &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;members have not. They're harassed. They're threatened. They're &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;detained. And in neighboring Georgia there's been sufficient evidence &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that the Azerbaijani authorities have acted in that country almost as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;though it's their backyard. We, along with a couple of other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organizations, did a trip to Georgia last summer, where we documented &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;systematic instances of people being followed, surveilled, and directly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;threatened.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The most egregious, of course, is the May abduction of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;journalist Afgan Mukharli, who was convicted, after being kidnapped, of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;illegal border crossing and having 10,000 euros on him, which is an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;illegal amount. Exactly 10,000. Not 9,000, not 11,000, but the exact &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;amount of 10,000. He got 7 years. His wife, no longer feeling safe in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Georgia, fled the country for another country in Europe. The Georgians &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are still ostensibly carrying out that investigation. As last I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understood it, the Azerbaijanis were still denying them access to Afgan &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;himself so that they could question him.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So to close, it's time for a new strategy on Azerbaijan. Since the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time I've been working on the country, this regime has gotten more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;emboldened and more calculating. They've also become impervious to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;outside pressure, but at the same time more concerned with cultivating &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a sophisticated image. But this is an authoritarian kleptocracy. And a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;seat in the elite circles in Washington and London should not come so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cheaply. Until they actually start to meet the standards that they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;profess to adhere to, they should be shunned. Until they stop their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;systematic campaign against civil society and address the impunity &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;within their law enforcement ranks, they should be turned away.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    It's time to start naming and shaming. It's not Azerbaijan that's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;committing human rights violations. It's people inside the government &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that are committing human rights violations. These are ministers. These &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are prosecutors. These are judges. These are police officers. And it's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time to hold them to account or call on the authorities in Baku to hold &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;them to account. This means we have to start talking more stick and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;less carrot. And that includes Global Magnitsky.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'll leave it at that.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. Thank you very much, Maran.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now I'd like to turn to Emin Milli, managing director of Meydan TV, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;independent online media for Azerbaijan. Meydan TV has been launched &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from Berlin in 2013. It is reaching weekly around 10 percent of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;entire population in Azerbaijan. From 2002 to 2004, Milli was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;coordinator of the Friedrich Ebert Foundation. And prior to that, he &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was a coordinator of the International Republican Institute in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan. Milli was sentenced in 2009 for 2\1/2\ years for his &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;critical views about the government of Azerbaijan and spent about 17 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;months in jail. He has a master's degree in state, society, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;development from the University of London School of Oriental and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;African Studies. We're grateful that he's here with us from across the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Atlantic.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you, Emin. Please go ahead.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Milli. Thank you very much for invitations. Thank you for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;coming. I really would like to apologize that what I will talk about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;now is not exactly the speech of a media manager, but more of a citizen &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Azerbaijan.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    On behalf of Ilgar Mammadov, who has been a candidate in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;presidential elections but was jailed and wasn't given this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opportunity. On behalf of Giyas and Bayram, who just wrote graffiti on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the monument of Heydar Aliyev, father of the current president, and got &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just for this 10 years in jail, and have been tortured. On behalf of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the 2-years-old niece of Ordukhan, who is the most efficient and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;greatest political activist who lives abroad now, who organized a lot &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of protests in front of embassies of Azerbaijan abroad. And for this, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;12 members of his family--his brothers, sisters, and even 2-years-old &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;niece, Siljan [ph]--were detained. They were threatened. And the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government used this as a weapon to silence him.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    On behalf of Tural Aliyev, Ordukhan's 19-year-old nephew, who was a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;student at Baku State University and who was arrested just a week ago, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;again to target Ordukhan personally. On behalf of Ilkin Rustamzadeh, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who is now for years in jail just for organizing peaceful protest &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;against the crimes committed in the army of Azerbaijan against soldiers &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Azerbaijan by the government of Azerbaijan. I will try to speak &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;briefly on behalf of all these people, and millions of others who are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;silenced, who live in fear, who are robbed by their own government.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    One hundred years ago, Azerbaijan created the first democratic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;republic in the Muslim world. This is the heritage of 10 million people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;living today in Azerbaijan. Unfortunately, 100 years later we feel &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ashamed. We're feeling the shame that now in the Caucasus, we're the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;only country that didn't manage to get rid of the criminal and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;dictator, who usurped the power. And I accuse Ilham Aliyev of all the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;crimes, all the detailed reporting that Audrey Altstadt and Maran &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Turner just presented to you, all these crimes of falsifying elections, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;torturing people, kidnapping people of Azerbaijan from other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries--like Afgan Mukharli, investigative journalist who was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;publishing his investigations about Aliyev and his businesses in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Georgia at Meydan TV.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    All these crimes of torturing people in prisons of Azerbaijan, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;going after their relatives when they speak out against the regime &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;abroad, stealing of billions and tens of billions of dollars that came &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to Azerbaijan within last two decades from selling oil and gas--all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these crimes, these are not abstract crimes. These are very specific &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;crimes. And the person who leads this gang--because I cannot call it a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government--is Aliyev. You know, there has never been, since Aliyev &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;came to power, any sort of legitimate elections. These are not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;elections.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    When Vaclav Havel wrote in his essays, and in ``The Power of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Powerless,'' but also in other essays, that certain concepts that you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are using, like democracy, or parliament, or freedom of assembly, rule &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of law--these concepts that are born in the West, and they have been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;developed and have certain meanings--when they're applied in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;authoritarian countries, like Azerbaijan today, they lose any meaning. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;So if we talk about elections, I cannot talk about elections in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan because elections do not exist in Azerbaijan as you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understand it here.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    This is very important for when we analyze. All these election &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;observation missions, they lose their meaning because there is nothing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to analyze. There is no legitimate process that is going on in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan. So today I stand here and, again, on behalf of people of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan, accuse Ilham Aliyev for stealing 2.5 billion U.S. dollars &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and allocating this in British offshore bank accounts, and using this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;money not just against people of Azerbaijan, but against Europe, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union, and against the U.S. What have they been doing with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this money? And this is just 2.5 billion dollars.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    This money has been put in these accounts by companies linked to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Aliyev's family, linked to the International Bank of Azerbaijan, linked &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to ministries of Azerbaijan. This was a top story in The Guardian and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Organized Crime and Corruption Reporting Project, OCCRP, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;investigated this. There is evidence from just 2012 till 2014, 2.5 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;billion U.S. dollars--just think about this. Three million dollars on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;average per day has been channeled from Azerbaijan to British offshore &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bank accounts to bribe European politicians, American politicians, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;journalists, the expert community.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    When such American and European politicians talk about Aliyev as a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;friend or an ally--because there are such American politicians and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European politicians who talk about Aliyev as an ally--you have to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think about this. What Aliyev and his family have been doing now for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;decades is destroying and committing crimes not just against the people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Azerbaijan. They have been committing crimes against the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States of America, against European Union member States. The Council of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe, in fact, just published a report--it's more than 200 pages--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which exactly detailed how they have been spending these tens of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;millions and hundreds of millions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    They are bribing European politicians. Not just any politicians. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Luca Volonte, who has been accused now of receiving more than 2 million &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;euros from our government, he wasn't just any politician. He was leader &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the faction of the European People's Party in the Parliamentary &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Assembly of the Council of Europe. Another case, CNN producer Eckart &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Sager. If you watch CNN, what CNN is doing? They are promoting this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;dictatorship. They are promoting this money, which is also coming from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these offshore bank accounts. This money has been robbed from the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people of Azerbaijan.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    There has been a call to investigate how the Aliyev regime has also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;corrupted members of the EU Parliament. And I think it's time that the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.S. Congress investigates if and how Aliyev regime corrupts &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;politicians, journalists, media, and the expert community in the U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Two former U.S. ambassadors are now on the payroll of the Aliyev &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regime. It's a shame. If I was an American, I would feel ashamed. It's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not just about Azerbaijan. Aliyev became a symbol of corruption. It's a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;global symbol of corruption. Someone who commits crimes against his own &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people. Someone who is very effective.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Azerbaijan's a small country. For a small country, Aliyev is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;extremely effective in helping to spread narratives like Kremlin &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;propaganda spreads around the world. What does Kremlin propaganda say? &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;That the West is corrupt. It's in decadence. It's corrupting. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Everything is relative. We have corruption. They have corruption. What &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do you want from us, right? This is exactly word for word what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijani state propaganda says every day to 10 million people in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan and around the world. It's not just the 10 million people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;living in Azerbaijan. Azerbaijanis are spread around the world.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So Aliyev is not a friend. He is an enemy. In my view, it is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;extremely important to talk about sanctions against Aliyev, because he &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is on the top of this criminal pyramid. He became a symbol. It became &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fashionable today to be a dictator, to be authoritarian. You know this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;here in the U.S. You know in Europe. Journalists are not just killed in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan anymore. They are killed in Europe. They're attacked in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.S. And if you think, conservatives or Democrats, that just focusing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on the U.S. will save the U.S., well, I have bad news for you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The very reason that the frontlines of freedom of expression, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;democracy, freedom at large are not in this post-Soviet space anymore &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;but, in Hungary, in Poland, in the U.S., in Britain, in France, is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because for two decades European and American politicians thought that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the best way to deal with people like Aliyev is to avoid escalation. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Every time when some media outlet has been shut down, some politician &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has been killed, a political activist has been jailed, what was the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reaction? Statements of `we're deeply concerned,' accepting the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reality, signing more contracts, more business, energy issues, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;security issues.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    All this backfired, because you have to understand, leaders like &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Aliyev, they have this gangster mentality. Aliyev doesn't say anything &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bad about Russia or Putin. He himself and his entire propaganda use &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very tough language against Europe and against the U.S. They shut down &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Radio Liberty in Azerbaijan. Even Putin didn't shut down Radio Liberty &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in Moscow. He thinks that these are weak leaders. They cannot do &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;anything to him. He can bribe American and European politicians into &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;accepting his way of life.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    It's not just his way of life. This is the way of life and thinking &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;supported by all dictators around the world. And this is coming to your &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;home. This is in the U.S. now. This is in Europe now. If you are Le Pen &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and if you are supported by another dictatorship, you can go to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bank and take millions to fund your campaign. Now, show me the bank &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;where you can go if you want to become president of Russia, if you want &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to become president of Uzbekistan, if you want to become a president of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;any other dictatorship--to fight against a dictatorship. Is there any &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bank you can go and take so much money?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So dictators became, like Aliyev, again, much more creative. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;entire global civil society infrastructure of supporting freedom--we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have to accept it--became more outdated. I really would like to thank &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the U.S. Helsinki Commission, Chris Smith personally, many congressmen &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and people in the U.S. Government and in Europe, who understand this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and try to put, for example, Azerbaijani officials on the sanction list &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and who try to put Russian officials who violate human rights in Russia &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on the sanction list.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But unfortunately, this is not mainstream political decisionmaking. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;You know, much more needs to happen. So, again, I would like really to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;repeat that it is extremely important to personally put Ilham Aliyev on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this sanctions list to show, for example, not just to Azerbaijan, not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just to send a message around the world, but also to send a message &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;here in the U.S., at this difficult time, to show people in the U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and around the world, what the U.S. is really about. That it's about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;values. It's about democracy. It's about human rights. And if you stop &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;promoting this abroad, you will have these problems at home.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you very much. [Applause.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. Thank you very much. Thank you very much, Emin, for your &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;powerful words and testimony, as you said, on behalf of people in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I want to take just a few moments in my prerogative as the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;moderator to ask a couple questions before turning over the floor to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the audience for your questions as well. First, I'd like to address the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;question of the opposition, which some of you touched on. Obviously, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the opposition that participates within the parliament, as you said, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Audrey, is not a legitimate one or a credible one. But there are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;genuine opposition movements that exist in Azerbaijan. And all of you, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I think, discussed how many of them have fled the country and now exist &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the diaspora.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Could you--from each of your perspectives--address what are the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;main opposition groups and what is the state of them now? And to what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;extent and how are they constrained and controlled by the government?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Altstadt. Okay. Well, one of the most potentially significant &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is the REAL Alternative--REAL, with which Ilgar Mammadov is associated. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I'm saying that it is potentially influential because all the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organizations that function or try to function inside of Azerbaijan are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very sharply constrained in ways that my colleagues have both mentioned &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in terms of direct attacks on them or pressure on their families in and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;outside the country. One of the distinguishing features of REAL is that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it tends to be a younger generation. It's that generation of people 40 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and under who have not been as significantly shaped by Soviet system &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;expectations, education, and so on, as the older generation had been.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think that Aliyev and his group are, I believe, especially &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fearful of the younger group because there are lots of groups of young &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;activists who are involved in all of the assorted color revolutions, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;so-called, starting with Georgia, which took place right next door when &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;he first came to the presidency in 2003. And I think that that probably &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;felt to him like the shot across the bow. I think that's potentially &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;one of the most significant ones.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. Sorry, could you also address the opposition's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participation or non-participation in the election? Was that a decision &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that was taken by the opposition? Were they constrained by the timing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the election as well? I know you talked about it a little bit, but I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was wondering if you could expand on it.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Altstadt. Because the major opposition parties are the older &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;parties with the older leadership, they've been effectively &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;marginalized. Their offices that used to be downtown are now out in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;little rust-bucket suburbs and so on. They don't have the resources, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they don't have the means to maintain a regular network. So for them, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;having a long time to prepare to contest elections, such as they are, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is really essential for them. And so rather than try to scramble and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;put together with their minimal resources, their small networks, and so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on something relatively last minute, I think that was a key reason why &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they decided to boycott.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Another reason, of course, as Emin mentioned, you really can't talk &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about elections in the way that we understand them in a Western &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;country. And the opposition still understands this. The Milli Shura, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the national council, has said these kinds of things. And so there's a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sense of `what's the point?' If we can't get out there and make our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;points, make our arguments, get ourselves into the public eye, then the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;next-best strategy is probably a boycott. And if they were not already &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;so weakened and so constrained, there might have been other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;possibilities for them.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Of course, the additional problem, I suspect, is that lots of them &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are potentially discouraged. They've been fighting this fight for a lot &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of decades and they don't have any opportunity to move forward. So I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think these components go into their thinking.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. Emin, want to say a few words on that?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Milli. Yes. Regarding the opposition, well, again, it depends &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;how you define opposition. There is no opposition in a sense that you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understand opposition here in the U.S., because there is no condition. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Opposition in the U.S. is a part of a system. It's part of how this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;country is run. This is not the case in Azerbaijan. Aliyev has created &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;such a system that opposition is branded 24/7 on the entire pro-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government TV as enemies of the people, enemies of the state, all the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;time. These are people who are killed, jailed, tortured, forced into &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;exile, travel ban is imposed on them. So you cannot talk about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opposition.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    You have a group of citizens--various groups, individuals--who are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not giving up the fight inside of the country and outside of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;country. And I am actually optimistic about the prospects of change in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan, because REAL is one of the political groups who potentially &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has power to lead the change when the situation is right. So there are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a lot of very educated, very talented experts, and politicians. This is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;another argument that kills everything that the government propagates &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inside and outside of the country, that there is no one except Aliyev &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who can run the country. This is just a lie.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    There are also, you know, quite experienced, again, expert &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;community inside and outside of Azerbaijan. There is a new phenomenon &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of bloggers and activists abroad. As Maran explained, many people had &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to flee. For example, Ordukhan is one of the most effective &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;communicators and political activists who lives in the Netherlands. He &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;communicates, alone, with 1 million people every week. Some of his &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;videos get hundreds, thousands of views. He is not alone. There are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;several other bloggers like him. If Meydan TV communicates every week &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with 1 million people, people like Ordukhan alone communicate with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hundreds, thousands, and up to 1 million and sometimes more than 1 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;million people inside of Azerbaijan.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    This has never been the case before. And I ask myself a question: &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;If people of Azerbaijan are so happy about this development and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;stability as Aliyev and his propaganda states, then why would people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;watch Ordukhan or Meydan TV or other bloggers who basically expose &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;corruption, expose how the government and its officials treat ordinary &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;citizens, the people's social problems, what people are facing. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reason why Meydan TV is popular is because we are just showing how &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people are living their everyday lives. That is the most popular &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;content we have.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But when we show who is really vice president, the wife of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;current president, Mehriba Aliyeva, just one video gets 1.5 million &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;views, which is 15 percent of the entire population of Azerbaijan. When &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we showed a video of Ilham Aliyev's old and rotten team, 1 month ago we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;published such a video, it had 800,000 views, which is 8 percent of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;population. And by the way, I think president and his team watched it, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because recently Aliyev actually did appoint five younger and more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;educated ministers.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So my point is, there is genuine movement inside and outside of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan. And Azerbaijan doesn't live in a vacuum. I told you about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the history, heritage of this country. And despite all the attacks, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organizing against people inside and outside of Azerbaijan, this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;movement is growing. It has never faded away. And the people are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;gathering their courage and have no doubt, there are millions of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;unhappy people in Azerbaijan who are waiting for the moment to show up &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the street and get rid of Aliyev. So this will happen. It's a matter &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of time.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And in my view, policymakers here in U.S. and in Europe, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Union, they shouldn't sit and do nothing and just get &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;surprised when things change in Armenia, or get surprised when &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;everything changes in Ukraine, or get surprised when things change in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Georgia, or in other dictatorships. They must start believing in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;values on which United States of America is based, what made America &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;great. You really have to believe in this. And you have to integrate it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in your policies abroad as well, in regard to dictators like Aliyev as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;well.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. And Emin, could you also address the state of access to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;information inside of Azerbaijan? I know your outlet has been blocked &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;by the government. Does it remain blocked? What other outlets are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;blocked? What's the state of independent media within Azerbaijan?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Milli. Well, the government monopolizes the entire TV, this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;classical TV infrastructure in Azerbaijan. They like to make &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;statements. This is Aliyev's take at every Davos, at every forum that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there is internet freedom in Azerbaijan. We have to understand that, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Ordukhan can say later what is internet freedom. Even from the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Netherlands--and the government tries to stop him in that by attacking &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;his relatives and people who speak up on the internet. They are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;arresting and torturing people who write Facebook statuses. They &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;blocked Meydan TV's website, Radio Liberty Azerbaijan Service website, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Tehran TV website, Azadliq newspaper website, and many others. They are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;trying to block the information. They are not succeeding. They don't &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understand it. They have even shut down the entire internet.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And this is my message to policymakers here in D.C., and also to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the government of Azerbaijan. All of you have to understand. In last 5 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years--Meydan TV is a great example--they have been threatening me &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;personally with this. They have been jailing my relatives. They have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;kidnapped our journalists. They blocked our website. They attacked us &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in every possible way. But every year, we just doubled our audience. So &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these repressions have never worked, and they will not work. So the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;only problem we actually have to grow and reach 60-70 percent of people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in Azerbaijan is not Aliyev's repressions, it's our lack of resources.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My entire thinking now is can we actually create more resources so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we can hire more journalists within and outside of Azerbaijan, citizen &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;journalists--we have a huge network of citizen journalists. People in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;every corner of Azerbaijan feeding--sending us videos. The people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;became journalists, you know, because they jailed, killed, stopped, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;silenced so many journalists. So the citizens became journalists. It's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;even more powerful than any media could ever imagine.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So they are trying, of course, to stop access to information. But &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the thing is, this is the problem for dictatorships, the more they try &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to close the free space, the more hunger for freedom they create, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the more people are interested in having more freedom and working for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this and sacrificing for this. So this is what they tried. But they are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;failing. And I think the policymakers here have to understand these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;trends. They shouldn't be behind the trends. You know, they should be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on top of those trends.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. And, Maran, could you discuss a little bit more about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the restrictions that NGOs face, and religious organizations, as you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mentioned in your testimony?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Turner. Sure. Well, as many of you in the room are probably &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;aware--and I touched on in my opening remarks--there was a series of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;NGO laws that were passed a few years ago. This was not unique to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan. This was a wave that we were seeing across the region. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;laws of these types have actually been in various countries, like India &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and China, for a long time. But what we saw was a real enthusiasm, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;particularly in Eurasia and especially in Azerbaijan. And they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;essentially implemented a series of laws that required organizations to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;register with the ministry of justice, and then also required them to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;register any grants they received. And what NGOs found when they tried &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to comply with these requirements, was that they couldn't get &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;registered, that in fact there would be lots of delays, or the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;registration would be lost, et cetera.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So many of them were just, frankly, not able to register. And then &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;even in some cases where they had registered, and even tried to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;register grants they were receiving, it didn't matter. These laws were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;passed with a real purpose in mind, and it was to really go after the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;leaders of civil society organizations. The cases that were brought &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;against these individuals, bizarrely, were actually combined in one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;large case, I believe it had the same case number. And in the same &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;case, they went after international organizations like Radio Free &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe and, I think, Open Society, and a few others. And the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prosecutions, as well, were just identical--completely identical. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;exact same allegations, which included abuse of office and illegal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;entrepreneurship. And these were also levied against Khadija &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Ismayilova, for example, who was with Radio Free Europe. But she wasn't &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;running the office. So it was just a bizarre allegation against her. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And it showed that they really weren't trying that hard.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    These laws are still in force. And this is why so many people had &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fled the country and are working from outside of the country. And this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is, frankly, why Tbilisi, I think, has really come to the forefront of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Azerbaijani authorities. I mean, I think that they have been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;seeking dissidents out in Georgia for a long time and harassing people. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;But in recent years, because so many people have been using it as a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;base and the authorities weren't able to get their hands on them in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Baku, they just walked straight across the border and went to Tbilisi. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;So they're moving further afield. As Emin astutely pointed out, this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has greatly frustrated civil society. But it hasn't ridden the regime &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of them. They are still working. And again, as Emin said, there's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;plenty of journalists still working inside the country. It's a very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;encouraging sign to see how many people are still in that fight, and I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hope that continues. And I know that they've got a lot of support from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the individuals in exile.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And the situation's probably even more dim for their religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;groups. There are so many laws that the government has passed that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;really allow them to harass just innocent people practicing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;independently of the state. And they use those laws to put people in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prison, not just leaders that are organizing but also just &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;practitioners and people that are particularly associated with clerics &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that are outspoken. And as I said, they're generally not political. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;This is usually much more social. Azerbaijan has followed that trend, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;where once upon a time it was generally just fabricated charges like &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;drug charges, hooliganism, and whatnot. In recent years they've really &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;started to, in some ways, follow the path of rule of law, ironically--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which is to say instead of just making stuff up, pass some laws that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are just Byzantine and almost impossible to dissect and understand, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;then just apply them, across the board and with little attention to how &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they're actually applying those laws.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. Thank you. I'd like to give the audience an opportunity &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to ask questions. Edwin here will pass around the microphone to anybody &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who's interested. I think we have a hand here in the back. If you'll &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wait for the microphone just for a second, because that way the folks &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on Facebook Live can hear as well.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. My name is Abdullah Skarov [ph]. Just a few days ago, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;former U.S. Ambassador Richard Kauzlarich expressed his concern on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;social network and shared an article from the Israeli newspaper &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Haaretz. And I think the title of the article speaks for itself. It &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;says how Israeli Jewish lobby groups in Capitol Hill are used by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijani Government as a secret weapon. And considering two sorts of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Israel--oil is coming from Azerbaijan and multibillion dollar huge arms &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;deals with Israel, and most recent escalating conflict with Iran, many &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijani people believe this kind of inconsistent calls for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sanctions or hearings, at best, are lip service or, worse, it's used &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;after every big impact--thing like elections or huge oil contracts--to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;put the pressure--to buildup a pressure on the government to extract &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;concessions. So what's your take on this?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. Well, I would say from the U.S. Helsinki Commission's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;perspective, I think I laid out in my opening remarks the consistency &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of our focus in light of the developments in Azerbaijan. Obviously, we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;respond to developments, we monitor commitments, and we highlight &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;concerns where they exist. And that's been our practice, especially &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;since the crackdown that began around 2013 and 2014. And we're here &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;having this hearing in order to continue doing so.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Just one small additional. Emin Milli mentioned about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;corruption. There's multibillion-dollar corruption and violence. There &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are federal officials, local officials. Where this money's going? This &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;multibillion dollars is usually siphoned out of the country. And in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this case, it's reflected on arms deals, so are these arms deals with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Israel. So the money is not staying in Azerbaijan. Nobody talks about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these Jewish lobby groups in D.C. No one talks about where this money &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;goes. They just inconsistently point fingers at the Azerbaijani &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Government.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    These sanction calls have been on the floor before. Where did it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;end up? They are not consistent. They go nowhere. It is just coming &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;after elections, these hearings, these talks, good, it's closed. And, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;again, another oil contract. Some talks here and it's closed. And my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thought is, where this is going. Are you consistent with your sorts of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opinions on these human rights issues? Many people believe democracy in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan is sacrificed. It's not a priority for U.S., as they are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just used as a tool.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Milli. So I think everything Abdullah [sp] said is legitimate. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And this is unfortunately the reality of global politics today, and not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just in regard to Azerbaijan.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But I want to make just one point, which is very important for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;audience here and audience back in Azerbaijan who are watching us live. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;In my view, it is, first of all, for the people of Azerbaijan, for the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;citizens of Azerbaijan to change the situation in Azerbaijan, to change &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the government, to keep the president and all these corrupt officials &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in Azerbaijan accountable. So this is first of all a mission of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people in Azerbaijan.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And everyone in Azerbaijan should understand this. Because unless &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we care about our own problem and we actually show the world by showing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;up, 1 million people on the streets, and demanding freedom and justice &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in Azerbaijan, why should the Israeli lobby care? Why should U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;congressmen care? Why should the U.S. Government care? Of course, I'd &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;make the argument that they should care, but to be honest with you--and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I think everyone in Azerbaijan should be honest with himself or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;herself--that it is, first of all, our problem. Unless we change, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;unless we show courage and show criminals who are unfortunately &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;occupying our government their place in history, this will not change &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;much, unfortunately.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Altstadt. We hear a lot about the U.S. Government does or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;doesn't do that, or a government does or doesn't do that. Government-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to-government relations do matter. But it is also important to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;recognize that there are groups and factions within governments and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;within societies in and out of government that are really working to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;support dictatorships. And there are those that are fighting against &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;those dictatorships, and they're trying to promote democracy and human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rights in whatever ways that they're able to do that. And so in a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sense, this case we're looking at today happens to be Azerbaijan, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because we all work on Azerbaijan and that's our focal point.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But in the same way that dictators learn from one another across &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;international borders, the human rights community and the pro-democracy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;community supports each other and they learn from each other as well. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;The lines are not only inside of individual countries, although they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are and they must be, but there's really a much more international, a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;global division between people who favor dictatorships and favor &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;supporting dictatorships by saying, oh, we can work with these people--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which sounds chillingly like the 1930s.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And then there's the other faction that says, no, we don't accept &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all of that. We're interested in the ideals of democracy and human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rights, even though countries that support those may do so imperfectly. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And so the real question is, which side are you going to be on?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. I think we have a question up here in front.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. My name is Ordukhan Teymurkhan. As Emin Milli said, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;am a political activist and video blogger in Azerbaijan, but I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;abroad. And as he told you, my family is regularly, in the last 3 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years, getting terrorized--I would say terrorized by the Azerbaijani &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Government. And as Emin Milli said, the accusations are going on Aliyev &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;himself, Ilham, because I know a hundred percent all the orders are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;given by himself. And I would say thank you very much for Helsinki &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission that you are organizing these kind of discussions about the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;corruption and dictatorship of Aliyev.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But at the same time, some European countries and even the U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Government is playing double games. For example, about the sanctions--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;everybody knows that Aliyev, himself and his family is corrupt hundred &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;percent, because even in The Guardian 2 weeks ago, in the newspaper &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they put that the two daughters of Aliyev, Leyla and Arzu, invested 110 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;million euros in Dubai for one palm island. They both want an island, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and on one island, more than 20 houses. Why? Why can't the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries and the U.S. Government put sanctions on these corrupt &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;families? And they have to start from Aliyev, Aliyev himself, and then &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the other ministers and judges, as he said. And even they didn't say &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;anything about when Ilham Aliyev appointed his wife as a vice &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;president. And the European--in the countries, in the Western &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries, democratic countries said nothing about these things.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And the elections--in one hand, in European countries we say we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;support democracy and human rights and we support only the humanity. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And the elections in Azerbaijan, after the elections, everybody knew &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that he got 68 percent of votes. Can you imagine? And in one country &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;even--no one is getting this kind of percentage in the elections. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in Venezuela, Europe--the U.S. Government didn't support the elections &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because the same happened in Venezuela as in Azerbaijan. And one day &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Aliyev comes and says, okay, the elections will be in April. And after &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the elections, the U.S. Government, even Trump, the President of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.S., he sends a letter, congratulates Aliyev and says we are going to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;walk with you together, Mr. Aliyev. Why? Why not with Venezuela and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with Aliyev as well?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I am very disappointed I couldn't speak as a speaker. As Emin said, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;1 million people watch me in Azerbaijan and if there are four or five &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people, who can change the country in Azerbaijan, I am one of them. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;may be exaggerating. I could speak and tell my people that we have to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do it ourselves, but the democratic countries like the U.S. and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European countries have to give us, the Azerbaijani people, support--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not the dictator Aliyev, because of oil and money.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'm sorry for my long speech.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. Well, thank you for coming, and glad we have this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opportunity to open the floor to the audience and to that sort of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participation and to hear voices from the Azeri community.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think there is a lot of interest here in sanctions. I was going &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to leave a question about sanctions more toward the end, but given the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;previous two questions I think it is fitting to discuss it now. There's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been discussion of Global Magnitsky. Obviously, Global Magnitsky has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;provisions for travel bans and asset freezes for egregious human rights &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;violations and also for levels of high corruption in the government.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I was wondering if the panel would perhaps like to talk about if &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there are ongoing efforts to pursue sanctions by the NGO community &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;since NGOs have the ability to provide leads and information and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;evidence to the Department of State and to our Treasury Department. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also what obstacles they believe stand in the way to the application of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sanctions against Azerbaijan?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Turner. I guess I'm the first to use the term Global Magnitsky, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;so I should speak. In short, the answer to your question is yes, there &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;certainly are conversations among organizations here in Washington--and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not just Washington. The U.S. is not the only country to pass Global &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Magnitsky legislation. A number of others have as well, including the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United Kingdom, and there have been some recent extensions of that. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there have been quite a lot of discussions in both these countries &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about how they should be used, and there's a lot of coordination, which &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is important.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would say, sadly, the main obstacle is the fact that it's new and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there's a certain amount of discomfort, I think, in the administration &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of maybe using them too liberally, and within that limited appetite &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there's a lot of people in a lot of countries that are all vying to put &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their names on a Global Magnitsky list. But certainly some names have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been furnished to the State Department and to the Treasury Department, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and there have been moves to try to promote within the administration &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to consider them closely, and they're primarily, I would say, police &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;chiefs and people who've been directly accused of torture, but not just &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;them. I mean, there's wider consideration of people within the various &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;apparatus of government that is ongoing and systematically persecuting &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;civil society. So, yes.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. Are there any other questions from the audience?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Here in the front.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Thank you very much for this opportunity. I would like &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;us to focus on government, not on opposition, but I'm going to ask this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;question because I'm curious. Emin Milli said that the majority of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijani people are silenced, and he's right. This is the case. But &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;when asking the question about opposition parties and movements near &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the outset, you mentioned Republican Alternative but you didn't mention &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;others, especially Popular Front of Azerbaijan.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, to be clear, I'm not being supportive of Popular Front of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan. But today this is the single political party who organizes &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;demonstrations every month, and at least several thousand people come &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to those demonstrations, knowing that they are going to be subject to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;face recognition [technology]. Now, liking posts is good. Watching &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;videos is also good. But to come to demonstrations in person, it needs &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;more courage, right?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So, going back to the issue you've discussed, I think that if we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are going to support the Azerbaijani people, we shouldn't try to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;silence political parties, people who are more active, who struggle in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan. Because when you mention Republican Alternative but don't &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;even mention Popular Front of Azerbaijan--which does, I believe, more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;now than others--that sounds to me like silencing the real struggle of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Azerbaijani people.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Altstadt. I suspect you and I both remember a time when the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Popular Front was secretly meeting in the offices of the Academy of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Science and the university, and they were the pioneers in the anti-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Soviet movement back in the late 1980s and the early 1990s. And if you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;go back and look at some of the programs which they first articulated, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;what is striking and was always striking to me about the things that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they wrote was that they really understood what democracy was about. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;They really understood the concepts.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I think part of the reason was that these were largely &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;historians and other intellectuals who had studied the First Republic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and its leadership and its ideals. And they really had a good &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understanding of what this meant. They understand it wasn't simple. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;They understood that democracy is a struggle. Maybe we should treat it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as a verb rather than as a noun. And I have great respect for that and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for their tradition, and also the other parties that grew out of it and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the National Council, which now includes many of those more traditional &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;parties.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My point is that right at the moment, those parties have been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;effectively marginalized, that they've been pushed out of their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;offices. Their publications and their leadership have been constrained. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Ali Karimli hasn't been allowed to leave Azerbaijan in over a decade. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And all of these things, I think, have made it much more difficult for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;them to move ahead with agenda items that they now have. The----&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. Sorry, could you say who Ali Karimli is.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Altstadt. Oh, I'm sorry. Yes, Ali Karimli has been the head of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Azerbaijan Popular Front Party since the loss of Elchibey &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Rachmadli. And so these are an important cohort.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I don't want to offend them or you, but they haven't changed &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their methods in a long time. And I don't think they're appealing in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;modern ways to a new group. That's why the younger generation's so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;important. That's why social media's so important, because it's this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;younger generation that needs to take up that baton and move forward.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In the early 1990s, people who were my teachers in Azerbaijan in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the 1980s stuck their necks out. They stepped outside of their comfort &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;zones. They got into doing political activism that was exceedingly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;dangerous for people who remembered Stalinism and remembered the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;midnight knock at the door.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Within a year, the next generation, people who then were in their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;30s, guys who were considered to be the young radicals like Isa Gambar, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who was the founder of the Muavat Party, and Etibar Mammadov, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Independence Party. These guys looked at the generation who were then &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in their 50s, who have now mostly passed away, and thought that they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;were much too conservative. They just weren't radical enough. They &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;needed to go on and be more critical and do more of these kinds of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;things. And those people are now in their 50s and 60s and the next &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;generation is coming along and saying you need to be more radical, you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;need to use different methods, and so on.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And so no disrespect to anybody intended--and these people were all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;my friends--so I don't want to offend them for personal and other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reasons--but when I'm asked about the activism for the future of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan opposition--and agreeing that an opposition that we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understand in a Western country doesn't truly exist in Azerbaijan--I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think of that next generation that's pushing the boundaries and pushing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the frontiers. And so I'm not silencing them. I'm trying to report what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I think I see, and it's up to them domestically to find their own &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;voices.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Milli. Thank you very much for the question. I have personally &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;huge respect for everything that Isa Gambar did, for all the struggle &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that Ali Karimli has shown in the last years. They have inspired and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;led ten thousands of people into struggle all these years under the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;worst conditions that anyone can imagine. But I think in the new &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;generation of activists and the new generation of people who want to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;change Azerbaijan, they have quite different ideas about the tactics, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;strategy, methods of how this change can be achieved and what this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;change should look like.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Again, with all my due respect for all these leaders of opposition &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Azerbaijan which have been in charge for the last two decades in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;leading this fight, I think it's very important--the best thing that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these leaders can do now is actually support all of the young people in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;groups, within their parties and outside of their parties, and give a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;message to people of Azerbaijan that their struggle is not personal--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it's not personally about Isa Gambar, it's not personally about Ali &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Karimli--because, unfortunately, if you talk about problems, we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shouldn't just target the government--we should talk also about the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;opposition. There is also cult of personality in certain political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;parties.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And this is not something that the new generation accepts. Everyone &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;should be the leader. This should be the message of any political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;activist, any political leader emerging in Azerbaijan. Anyone who comes &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and says, look, I'm so great, I'm fantastic, and I will lead you into &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the new life--like, this is not something that people of Azerbaijan are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;buying. And you can see it by the views and numbers of people that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people are reaching.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And if people don't come to these protests in Azerbaijan that are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;monthly, routinely organized, maybe people doubt the tactics. Maybe &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they think that this is not effective. Maybe they don't see the point &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to come show up so government spies film them and then pressure them &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and their families. I think millions of people in Azerbaijan are ready &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to stand up and come and fight for freedom, but they are trying to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understand how we can do it in one day, all of us together--one day to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;come on the street, finish this, and then go home and do our routine &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;life.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And this leader should be ready that people are questioning it and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they need to think about how they work with social media, how they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;communicate with people, what their attitudes are toward tactics, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;strategy and communication with the people. So when there are new &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;political activists, political leaders or groups emerge and suggest &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;something alternative, I think it's a process of national selection.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And you cannot say to someone, why do you do this or why you don't &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do this--it's a natural process. And time and history will show what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can lead and who can change Azerbaijan and what this change will look &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;like. But there are certainly, again, hundreds of people who are maybe &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not even on the surface now, but they are ready to lead the government, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;various ministers. They are experts. They are very successful abroad, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all inside of the country in their own specific field, and they are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just waiting for this moment that Azerbaijan will change, and then we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;will all see that we are hundreds, thousands of people who can make &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ministries, bureaucracy, political parties and new civic groups.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. I think we have time for one more question. I'm going to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;take the woman in the back, please.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Hi, I'm Cathy Cosman. I used to work at the U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission on International Religious Freedom.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you so much, Maran, for bringing up the issue of religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prisoners, the majority, as they are, in all post-Soviet states. And I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want to point out that the vast majority of political prisoners, or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious prisoners--however you want to call them--prisoners of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conscience, who by definition have not used violence or advocated for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it, are independent Muslims. And both human rights groups, civil &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;society, government groups, with the exception of the organization &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;where I used to work, do not pay attention to Muslims. And I really &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think this is not only a flaw from the point of view of human rights, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;but it's also a huge strategic error, because then by ignoring the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;problems of Muslims, be they still living under onerous and unfair &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;legislation, or all the more so if they're imprisoned for their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;independent religious views and activities, as Muslims, they of course &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;will be alienated from the West. And I think that's something that none &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of us want, I hope.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would also just comment that Congressman Smith's H. Res. 537 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;calls for the U.S. administration to pursue potential International &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Religious Freedom sanctions, which are travel bans against the worst &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;violators of that fundamental freedom within Azerbaijan. So there's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;definitely an intention to that on the part of Congressman Smith's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resolution.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Emin, if you'd like to say a last word, and then I think we'll wrap &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;up.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Milli. We have very courageous religious activists like Taleh &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Bagirzade, for example, who's languishing in jail in Azerbaijan. And I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want you to know that he has quite tolerant and quite embracive views &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about the relationship between government and society.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I think that Islam and religion in Azerbaijan has been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;historically quite different from many times. I mean, it's not for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nothing that Azerbaijan was the first democratic country in the Muslim &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;world, that created parliamentary republic, that gave rights to women &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to vote. And this is another propaganda of government, when they try to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;present situation in Azerbaijan as such, if Aliyev goes, there is this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bunch of Muslim leaders and activists and Azerbaijan will turn into &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;another Iran or Saudi Arabia. This is just not true. Anyone who &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;traveled in Azerbaijan, anyone who lived in Azerbaijan, people when &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they come here, they're actually a bit surprised that the level of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;secularism in Azerbaijan, it goes beyond what this government thinks &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about this or can do about it, you know? It is just in the DNA of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;history of Azerbaijan--and let's say tomorrow Aliyev is gone and we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have a parliamentary republic, I'm sure there will be Islamist party &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and they will have probably 10-20 percent in parliament.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    People understand very well the importance of the separation of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;state and religion. And I think a lot of people in Azerbaijan &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understand themselves as Muslims, and this is their constitutional &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;right. But when it comes to practice, the majority of Azerbaijanis are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not practicing Islam in the way, for example, that people in Saudi &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Arabia or Iran are practicing Islam. I'm absolutely sure that, as Maran &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also said, people who are practicing Islam in a way that it is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;practiced, for example, in Iran or other Muslim countries, they have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;major grievances. It's about injustice. It's about how government &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;treats its own citizens regardless of them being Muslims or not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Muslims.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And as long as this problem exists, this helps the radicalization &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of this minority, and it doesn't help the development of Azerbaijan. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;The situation is not as the government tries to present it, especially &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;here in the West, in the U.S., in Europe. And just one trip to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan would be enough to understand what kind of society is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan. So this government, it stops Muslims, everyone in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Azerbaijan from the next stage of development, unfortunately.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Price. I'm extremely grateful to our panelists, all of whom &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;traveled fair distances to be here with us today. I'm especially &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;grateful to Emin Milli. I think one of the great opportunities that we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have with these briefings is to feature people who have been on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ground doing the difficult work of defending freedom and spreading free &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;information, and at a very high personal cost oftentimes. So I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;grateful for your presence and the presence of the other Azeri &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;activists who have spoken here today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I thank you all for your attendance here and for all those who &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have watched live on Facebook Live. The briefing is hereby adjourned.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    [Whereupon, at 12:05 p.m., the briefing ended.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            This is an official publication of the Commission on&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                    Security and Cooperation in Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  This publication is intended to document&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  developments and trends in participating&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  States of the Organization for Security&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                     and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE).&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;           All Commission publications may be freely reproduced,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            in any form, with appropriate credit. The Commission&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            encourages the widest possible dissemination of its&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               publications.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      www.csce.gov       @HelsinkiComm&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 The Commission's Web site provides access&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 to the latest press releases and reports,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                as well as hearings and briefings. Using the&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;         Commission's electronic subscription service, readers are&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            able to receive press releases, articles, and other&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          materials by topic or countries of particular interest.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                          Please subscribe today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;&amp;lt;/pre&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
</intro>
</Hearing>
