<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="25868">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                        [H.A.S.C. No. 115-46]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                HEARING&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                   ON&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                          FOR FISCAL YEAR 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                  AND&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;              OVERSIGHT OF PREVIOUSLY AUTHORIZED PROGRAMS&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               BEFORE THE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;committee_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES&lt;/committee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
&lt;/option&gt;
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON STRATEGIC FORCES HEARING&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                                   ON
                    FISCAL YEAR 2018 PRIORITIES AND
                    POSTURE OF THE NATIONAL SECURITY
                            SPACE ENTERPRISE
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                              MAY 19, 2017
                                  ______
                         U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE 
25-868                         WASHINGTON : 2017 
-----------------------------------------------------------------------
  For sale by the Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Publishing 
  Office Internet: bookstore.gpo.gov Phone: toll free (866) 512-1800; 
         DC area (202) 512-1800 Fax: (202) 512-2104 Mail: Stop IDCC, 
                          Washington, DC 20402-0001
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON STRATEGIC FORCES&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                     MIKE ROGERS, Alabama, Chairman
TRENT FRANKS, Arizona, Vice Chair    JIM COOPER, Tennessee
DOUG LAMBORN, Colorado               SUSAN A. DAVIS, California
DUNCAN HUNTER, California            RICK LARSEN, Washington
MO BROOKS, Alabama                   JOHN GARAMENDI, California
JIM BRIDENSTINE, Oklahoma            BETO O'ROURKE, Texas
MICHAEL R. TURNER, Ohio              DONALD NORCROSS, New Jersey
MIKE COFFMAN, Colorado               COLLEEN HANABUSA, Hawaii
BRADLEY BYRNE, Alabama               RO KHANNA, California
SAM GRAVES, Missouri
                 Steve Kitay, Professional Staff Member
                         Leonor Tomero, Counsel
                           Mike Gancio, Clerk
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <Directory>
    &lt;table-of-content&gt;C O N T E N T S&lt;/table-of-content&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS&lt;/Speakers&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;Hon Jim Cooper&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative from Tennessee Ranking Member&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
</Directory>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;Subcommittee on Strategic Forces...............................     1&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Hon Mike Rogers&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative from Alabama Chairman&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;witnesses&gt;WITNESSES&lt;/witnesses&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Lt Gen David J USAF Buck&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Commander Joint Functional Component Command for Space&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Robert Cardillo&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Director National GeospatialIntelligence Agency&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;John D Hill&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Performing the Duties of Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Space Policy Office of the Under Secretary of Defense for Policy Raymond&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;APPENDIX&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;Prepared Statements:&lt;/Speakers&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;Lt Gen David J Cardillo Buck&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Robert Hill John D Raymond&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Subcommittee on Strategic Forces,&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                              Washington, DC, Friday, May 19, 2017.
    The subcommittee met, pursuant to call, at 7:59 a.m., in 
room 2118, Rayburn House Office Building, Hon. Mike Rogers 
(chairman of the subcommittee) presiding.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;      ALABAMA, CHAIRMAN, SUBCOMMITTEE ON STRATEGIC FORCES
    Mr. Rogers. Good morning, and welcome to the Strategic 
Forces Subcommittee hearing, ``Fiscal Year 2018 Priorities and 
Posture of the National Security Space Enterprise.'' We are 
honored to have a panel of expert witnesses who are leaders in 
our national security space program to join us here today. And 
before I introduce them, though, I want to take a moment to 
acknowledge that, while I can't imagine there being a better 
place to work than for the Strategic Forces Subcommittee on the 
House Armed Services Committee, apparently, somebody thinks 
there is a better job in Washington, DC. This will be the last 
hearing that Steve Kitay will be in his current position. He is 
leaving us to go work for the Secretary of Defense, he will be 
the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Space Policy. And our 
loss is the Secretary's gain. So we are going to miss him. He 
has been with as long time and does a great job. But I know he 
will do a great job for our country in his new capacity as 
well. So good luck, buddy.
    Today we have some witnesses that are very familiar to this 
committee, and do a great job for our country: General John 
``Jay'' Raymond, Commander, Air Force Space Command; Lieutenant 
General David Buck, Commander, Joint Functional Component 
Command for Space [JFCC Space]; Ms. Betty Sapp, Director of 
National Reconnaissance Office; Robert Cardillo, Director of 
National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency; and Mr. John Hill, 
Acting Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Space Policy.
    After we finish this unclassified testimony and questions 
and answers, we will adjourn to a closed session to continue 
our oversight in an appropriately secure fashion.
    In Secretary Mattis' confirmation hearing in front of 
Senate earlier this year, his official testimony stated, quote, 
``While our military maintains capable air, land, and sea 
forces, the cyber and space domains now demand an increasing 
share of attention and investment,'' close quote. And I fully 
agree with the Secretary's statement.
    Our military and intelligence leaders have been clear in 
their warnings, some going back many years, that our use of 
space could be taken away from us in the next military 
conflict. However, we have not moved with the conviction and 
urgency to respond to these warnings. And this has left us with 
a growing crisis to confront in outer space.
    While I have the full faith and confidence in each of our 
expert witnesses here today, I do not have faith in the tangled 
bureaucratic structure they must work with. Meanwhile, China, 
for example, is advancing rapidly in space and counterspace and 
has established a new military organization to focus its space, 
cyber, and electronic warfare capabilities. Dr. John Hamre, 
former Deputy Secretary of Defense, eloquently stated in an 
earlier hearing to this subcommittee, quote, ``We are not well 
organized to deal with the new challenges we face in space. The 
old structure may have been sufficient when space was an 
uncontested area of operations. That time has passed.'' Again, 
I couldn't agree more.
    Ladies and gentlemen, now is the least capable our 
adversaries will be in space. And now is the time for reform, 
even if it is disruptive today.
    With that, I look forward to hearing all your perspectives 
on space priorities and posture. I thank all of you for being 
here and working with us on this important topic.
    I now recognize my friend and colleague from Tennessee, the 
ranking member, Mr. Jim Cooper.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Appendix on page 29.]
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;        RANKING MEMBER, SUBCOMMITTEE ON STRATEGIC FORCES
    Mr. Cooper. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I would like to add my 
note of congratulations to Steve, well done. And I thank you 
for this hearing, Mr. Chairman. I appreciate especially your 
focus on strengthening America's space capabilities. There is 
no more important goal.
    There are many issues before us and before the Air Force in 
particular, but I am glad we are addressing them in a 
bipartisan, joint, and substantive fashion. I look forward to 
the testimony of the witnesses.
    Mr. Rogers. Great. I now recognize our witnesses. The 
witnesses were asked to summarize. Their prepared statements 
will be submitted for the record. Without objection, so 
ordered. If you could take your statements and keep them to 5 
minutes or less so we can get to questions, that would be 
awesome.
    General Raymond, you are recognized.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                         SPACE COMMAND
    General Raymond. Thank you, Chairman Rogers, Ranking Member 
Cooper. Let me also pile on and say congratulations to Steve 
Kitay. We look forward to having you sitting here next to us 
next year.
    Distinguished members of the subcommittee, thank you for 
the opportunity to appear before you as the commander of Air 
Force Space Command. It is my distinct privilege to lead and 
represent nearly 36,000 professional and dedicated airmen 
providing resilient and affordable space and cyberspace 
capabilities for the joint force and our Nation. It is also a 
distinct privilege to testify with my friends and panel of 
experts and close partners.
    This is a very exciting year for both the Air Force and the 
Air Force Space Command. In 2017, September of 2017, our Air 
Force celebrates our 70th birthday, and Air Force Space Command 
celebrates a 35th birthday, although, as an Air Force, we have 
been involved in space since 1954 and since the beginning.
    We have come a long way and done a remarkable job 
integrating space capabilities into joint warfighting. Today, 
there is nothing we do, and I repeat, nothing we do as a joint 
force that isn't enabled by space. Integration has been our 
strength. Nevertheless, we find ourselves at the intersection 
of high reliance and vulnerability in the space domain. Today, 
in no uncertain terms, space is a warfighting domain, just like 
air, land, and sea. Potential adversaries are developing 
capabilities to deny us access to and the benefits of the space 
domain. Let me be very clear, we do not want a conflict that 
extends into space, but one way to keep that from happening is 
to make sure that we are prepared for it and be able to fight 
and win that conflict if it were to occur. I think it shouldn't 
be lost on anybody that our space program is the envy of the 
world.
    My near-term priorities are fourfold. First, in partnership 
with Betty Sapp, is to operationalize the National Space 
Defense Center, and provide them with command and control 
capability necessary to operate in a contested domain.
    Secondly, we must improve space situational awareness, 
transforming from a cataloging focus to a warfighting focus 
required of this domain.
    Third, we need to transition our space architecture into a 
defendable space architecture to provide resilient and 
defendable capabilities for the current strategic environment 
that we face.
    And finally, we need to continue to professionally develop 
Air Force Space Command airmen.
    I thank you for your support, I thank you for your active 
leadership, and look forward to continuing to work closely with 
you in the years ahead. I also look forward to your questions.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;the Appendix on page 31.]
    Mr. Rogers. General Buck.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt; FUNCTIONAL COMPONENT COMMAND FOR SPACE, U.S. STRATEGIC COMMAND
    General Buck. Chairman Rogers, Ranking Member Cooper, and 
members of the subcommittee, thank you for your steadfast 
support of our men and women in uniform, the space enterprise, 
and this Nation.
    As this committee is well aware, we have turned an 
educational corner of sorts. It is now widely acknowledged that 
space is critical to our way of life. This, coupled with an 
understanding of the compelling and compounding threats to our 
freedom of action in space is the burning platform to evolve 
our national security space enterprise.
    We don't need a clean-slate approach, but certainly, an 
overhaul is necessary to guarantee our freedoms in, through, 
and from space.
    This is a challenge, because our national security space 
architecture and processes were largely conceived to provide 
services, or commodities, during an era when our most 
significant co-orbital threat was debris. Given the emerging 
threats, we no longer approach space with simply a service 
provider mentality. Our foremost responsibility is to gain and 
maintain space superiority. This is a prerequisite to 
protecting and defending the space joint operating area, and 
for providing space force combat engagement with the joint 
forces across the globe.
    Over the past year, we have made substantial progress, 
especially with respect to all-domain operations and our 
ability to protect and defend the national security space 
enterprise. We are better warfighters. There are, however, 
areas that require continued focus and vigilance. We must 
continue to normalize operations across the enterprise. This 
includes space situational awareness, as well as improving 
foundational intelligence, and the ability to provide robust 
indications and warning. We also must continue the full-court 
press to deliver a next generation battle space awareness and 
command and control capability. At the same time, we must 
review and update the associated authorities and rules of 
engagement for operations in space. And we must continue, we 
must continue to push on fielding required capabilities on 
operationally relevant timelines.
    Looking forward, we are focused on maintaining freedom of 
action in space. It is an imperative of our joint force. As a 
learning organization, we will continue to review and mature 
our approaches and organizational structures. We can accept no 
less, because the speed and complexity of future fights demands 
operationally agile organizations.
    Every challenge is an opportunity, and we have many 
opportunities in space. Freedom of action in space is not a 
birthright; it must be secured, and it must be preserved. This 
requires constant vigilance, strong partnerships, and active 
participation. I thank the committee for your leadership and 
for your advocacy. I look forward to our continued partnership.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Appendix on page 50.]
    Mr. Rogers. I thank you, General Buck. Ms. Sapp you are 
recognized for 5 minutes.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                             OFFICE
    Ms. Sapp. Thank you, Chairman Rogers, Ranking Member 
Cooper, and distinguished members of the subcommittee. Thank 
you for the opportunity to be here on behalf of the National 
Reconnaissance Office, or NRO. The NRO is responsible for 
developing, acquiring, launching, and operating the Nation's 
overhead intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance 
architecture. We are the foundation of the U.S. global 
situational awareness. We contribute to global intelligence, 
military and homeland security operations, while simultaneously 
assisting with the formation of national policy, and achieving 
diplomatic goals. We provide direct support to U.S. 
warfighters, help protect U.S. borders, and contribute 
significantly to the fight against ISIS [Islamic State of Iraq 
and Syria] and other counterterrorism operations worldwide.
    The foundation of NRO mission capabilities and 
contributions are our people. Our people are behind every 
mission success, and enable the direct support we provide to 
the combatant commands, their service and functional 
components, and deployed tactical units. The NRO workforce is 
not just dedicated to mission, but talented and empowered to 
innovate.
    We instill a culture of innovation and risk tolerance in 
everything we do. NRO innovation comes in many forms to include 
using existing capabilities differently, developing new apps 
for our space and ground systems, and developing the new 
capabilities critical to closing intelligence gaps.
    We are also working with our mission partners to ensure we 
fully leverage commercial products, services, and capabilities. 
The NRO is a small, flat, end-to-end organization, fully 
capable of successfully delivering an increasingly capable, 
integrated, resilient, and affordable architecture.
    We have control of every function required, from the R&amp;amp;D 
[research and development] that enables us to stay ahead of 
targets and threats, to the acquisition of new space and ground 
capability, to the operations required to use, adapt, and 
upgrade those capabilities to respond to new and changing 
mission imperatives in the field.
    We are performing extremely well. All 15 of our major 
system acquisitions are ``green,'' meaning they are meeting or 
exceeding cost, schedule, and performance metrics. This year, 
we received our eighth consecutive clean financial management 
audit, demonstrating our ability to properly manage all 
resources entrusted to us. And we continue to improve our 
collection capabilities and the resiliency to stay ahead of 
targets and threats. But staying ahead of the adversaries who 
threaten our space capabilities is a challenge. Those 
adversaries are making space a priority, investing heavily and 
accepting the risk necessary for rapid progress.
    The U.S. has not been keeping pace. I believe we have not 
made the investment that would indicate space is a priority or 
fundamental to the U.S. Our requirements budget and acquisition 
processes are disconnected, and none of them moves quickly. 
Failure is not well-tolerated, even in the research and 
development activities required to keep our space capabilities 
relevant and vital, or to improve their resiliency.
    National security space is a team sport, and everyone on 
the team, those in the executive branch, and in the Congress, 
must do all they can to advance its capabilities and improve 
its resilience to threats. We must have processes that are 
integrated, that move faster, and that demonstrate greater risk 
tolerance. We must recommit to space as a national priority and 
imperative.
    This committee has been out in front trying to drive the 
changes required. The NRO is inspired by this committee's 
efforts to address the barriers to change and the pace of 
change required to advance national security space. The NRO, 
and the broader national space community, have people with the 
talent, commitment, and passion necessary to take us forward. 
We only need to empower and enable them to succeed.
    Mr. Chairman and members of the subcommittee, thank you for 
your continued support of the National Reconnaissance Office, 
its people, and its mission.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Appendix on page 63.]
    Mr. Rogers. Thank you, Ms. Sapp. The chair now recognizes 
Mr. Cardillo for 5 minutes.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                      INTELLIGENCE AGENCY
    Mr. Cardillo. Thank you, Chairman Rogers, Ranking Member 
Cooper, and members of the committee. I, too, am pleased to 
testify before you today with my distinguished colleagues as a 
member of the team of national security professionals.
    NGA is the primary provider of geospatial intelligence, or 
GEOINT, for the Department of Defense and the intelligence 
community. Our support to military services, combatant 
commands, and warfighters includes safety in navigation, 
precise targeting, disaster recovery, and tailored intelligence 
support, just to name a few. I also have the job of being the 
Functional Manager for the National System of Geospatial 
Intelligence. And I strengthen the overall enterprise by 
ensuring that those combatant command needs are met through 
future overhead architectures. More specifically, the GEOINT 
enterprise capability document which serves as a framework to 
translate those needs into the key enterprise functions and 
capabilities that our analysts require to resolve our most 
vexing intelligence challenges.
    Now, global persistent GEOINT provides an architecture to 
monitor these intelligence challenges, enables NGA to provide 
national and tactical leaders the intelligence and early 
warning needed for decision advantage. It leverages the 
exquisite capabilities of the National Reconnaissance Office to 
allow the combatant commands to hold strategic targets at risk. 
It also integrates the capabilities of our international 
partners to fill gaps in our enterprise.
    Now, the explosion of data has driven the GEOINT discipline 
beyond the limits of human interpretation and explanation. By 
combining all of the data now available to us, and with the use 
of algorithms, automated processing, machine-to-machine 
learning, and artificial intelligence, we believe we can 
automate as much as 75 percent or more of the rote tasks we 
perform today. This will free our analysts to spend more time 
and focus on those hard intelligence problems. Getting to that 
point will require significant investments in our IT 
[information technology] architecture, as well as in our 
research and development.
    Not only is that data exploding, conservative estimates 
over the next 10 years predict that over 9,000 commercial 
satellites will be launched compared to fewer than 1,500 in the 
last 10 years. Accordingly, NGA will partner with the NRO to 
engage with and access the most mature of these new space via 
the commercial GEOINT activity. Through it, we will identify 
and evaluate emerging commercial GEOINT data and services 
against those needs that we capture and maintain.
    In closing, the national security space enterprise is vital 
to NGA's ability to provide advantage to warfighter commanders 
and policymakers, to give them the decision space and the 
operational time they need to do their job. Timely, relevant, 
and accurate GEOINT is only possible through the combined 
efforts of the IC [intelligence community], the Department of 
Defense, emerging industry, and allied partners.
    I am happy to address any questions you might have and I am 
pleased to be here. Thank you.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Appendix on page 70.]
    Mr. Rogers. Thank you, Mr. Cardillo. Mr. Hill, you are 
recognized for 5 minutes.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;ASSISTANT SECRETARY OF DEFENSE FOR SPACE POLICY, OFFICE OF THE 
             UNDER SECRETARY OF DEFENSE FOR POLICY
    Mr. Hill. Thank you, Chairman Rogers, Ranking Member 
Cooper, and distinguished members of the committee, thank you 
for the opportunity to testify today here with my distinguished 
colleagues.
    In the months ahead, understanding and addressing the 
implications of the growing threats in space is critical as 
this administration prepares the President's new national 
security strategy, and the national defense strategy, and as 
Congress carries out its responsibilities for oversight and 
funding of the programs and activities necessary to realize 
those strategies.
    No less important, strategic success requires increased 
resources, an end to defense budget caps, an end to the years-
long pattern of extended continuing resolutions, and a return 
to strategy-focused resourcing. Today, we consider space 
security in an era when Russia and China present anti-access/
area denial [A2/AD] strategies intended to prevent or counter 
U.S. intervention in crises or conflicts, and to undercut our 
ability to secure our interests.
    Diplomatic solutions remain our preferred option to 
settling the differences that divide nations. But American 
diplomatic influence rests on the credibility and capability of 
our military power, which is fundamental to deterrence and to 
the confidence of our allies in knowing that they do not have 
to submit to the coercive pressures of large and powerful 
neighbors.
    America's space posture underwrites deterrence by enabling 
the U.S. military to project power globally, respond to crises 
rapidly, strike swiftly and precisely, and command forces in 
multiple theaters simultaneously. Potential adversaries know 
well our reliance on space systems that many perceive as 
vulnerable, leading to an unstable situation in which some have 
concluded that in times of conflict, attacking U.S. military 
space systems may make an irresistible and most tempting 
choice.
    Disabusing them of such misguided notions is a strategic 
priority. That is why, in the Department of Defense, we are 
making such a concerted effort to strengthen the mission 
assurance of our space capabilities, and to deny aggressors the 
benefits of attacks in space. We are changing our investments 
and operations, and increasing our partnering with commercial 
entities and allies. More importantly, we are changing 
attitudes by recognizing that space is a warfighting domain and 
preparing ourselves to deter conflict in space and prevail if 
deterrence fails.
    Finally, I want to recognize this committee's priority on 
strengthening national security space organization, management, 
and leadership. This question has the attention of the 
Secretary and Deputy Secretary of Defense. They expect to be 
presented with sound analysis and a full range of options, and 
they mean for us to meet the deadline of reporting to Congress 
this June.
    In conclusion, I want to thank this committee for keeping 
the challenges of securing space before the public. I look 
forward to working together to ensure that we have the right 
strategy and resources, and the necessary programs, posture, 
and organizational structures to sustain deterrence, to prevail 
if deterrence fails, and to increase the incentives nations 
have to settling their differences by peaceful means. Thank 
you.
    And I would add, as the person acting in the job that Mr. 
Kitay will be doing, nobody is happier to have him come in than 
I am. Thank you.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Appendix on page 79.]
    Mr. Rogers. I hear you. Thank you, Mr. Hill.
    I recognize myself first for questions. This will be a 
question for anybody who is willing to swing at it. We passed a 
law about 10 years ago that directed how the Operationally 
Responsive Space [ORS] Office would be run. And I have heard 
instead of being streamlined, ORS options are still forced to 
go through the traditional Pentagon processes, including the 
Defense Space Council [DSC]. So rather than a small number of 
decisionmakers focused on moving fast with respect to 
operationally responsive requirements and acquisition, the 
recent decision meeting of the ORS program included over 60 
attendees, with 54 more than we had envisioned. To me, this 
example is indicative of the extremely fragmented space 
organization and bureaucratic kudzu--my word--you have got to 
be from the south to know what kudzu is--that comes in and 
strangles out the life of the DOD space programs. It is a 
situation where everyone can say ``no,'' but no one can say 
``yes.''
    So how do we fix that? General Raymond, swing first.
    General Raymond. I will swing first. I am familiar with 
kudzu.
    Mr. Rogers. You are recognized.
    General Raymond. Chairman, thanks for the question. Sixty 
people were not involved in that decision. As you stated, the 
ORS EXCOM [executive committee] law is pretty clear. There are 
six ORS EXCOM members by law. The PDSA [Principal DOD Space 
Advisor] has the ability to designate others that are critical 
to that decision.
    In this case, I wasn't in the room, but my understanding is 
that those six were the voting members, plus two or three 
others, that was it. It is under the framework of a larger DSC, 
but the decisionmakers were the eight- or nine-person level, 
those were the voting members and the decision actually went 
pretty quick.
    Mr. Rogers. Well, I understand that there were six voting 
members, but weren't there 60 people in the room?
    General Raymond. Yes, there were 60 people in the room, but 
there is also some goodness in transparency of having others 
there. They didn't vote, they didn't influence the decision, 
they were there. I will tell you, after those folks make that 
decision, a lot of those folks then have to be the ones that go 
execute that decision to make sure they have a common 
understanding. So it was a very small number of folks that was 
consistent with the legislation that was passed for a small, 
tight decision-making process for ORS EXCOM. And I am pretty 
comfortable that it was a pretty rapid decision.
    Mr. Rogers. So six people were the decisionmakers?
    General Raymond. As I mentioned to you, there were six that 
were by law, and then there was a couple others that added by 
the----
    Mr. Rogers. So there were eight people?
    General Raymond. I wasn't in the room, but it was small 
numbers.
    Mr. Rogers. Okay. Six to eight people?
    Betty Sapp, do you have to have six to eight people to make 
decisions on acquisition process programs with your 
organization?
    Ms. Sapp. I have at least two people to make decisions, one 
on the IC side and one on the DOD side. There are a lot of 
people, as you mentioned, who review the package of 
documentation for sufficiency before it gets to those 
decisionmakers. And, again, there is a whole lot of staff on 
the IC side, there is a whole lot of staff on the DOD side. So 
a lot of people look at it before it even gets on the calendar 
for the decisionmakers.
    Mr. Rogers. The people that look at it, do they have the 
authority to stop it or say no?
    Ms. Sapp. Yeah, the authority to stall it.
    Mr. Rogers. Is that the case with the ORS, General Raymond? 
Those other people, can they slow it down or stop it?
    General Raymond. My understanding is they do not have a 
vote in that process. They have the--as by law, the----
    Mr. Rogers. How about the lead-up process to get to that 
room, before it gets to that room for decisionmaking.
    General Raymond. The PDSA schedules the Defense Space 
Council, and it is done relatively routinely, and it was done 
pretty quickly in this process. I didn't sense a slowdown on 
this.
    Mr. Rogers. Anybody else want a swing at it? All right.
    Mr. Hill. Chairman, I will give you a comment as one of 
those nonvoting people who was in the room.
    Mr. Rogers. Okay.
    Mr. Hill. What the Principal DOD Space Advisor also did 
was, she used that to tee up a decision that is also necessary, 
which is the long-term solution for weather--so ORS is an 
important gap in the ORS program that was before us. An 
important gap [inaudible] that General Hyten had put forward 
and had been brought in the Air Force. That went pretty 
quickly. The discussion also then said to everybody are we also 
moving on the requirements process for the longer term, which 
she used that effectively in that respect.
    Mr. Rogers. Great. In the testimony to the SASC [Senate 
Armed Services Committee] earlier this week, General Goldfein 
talked about the need to integrate space. The Joint Staff is 
who is responsible for overall space integration forces. On 
that Joint Staff, there are 11 Air Force general officers. Of 
those 11 general officers, how many space professionals are 
included? Anybody want to guess? It would be zero. Do you know 
how many are pilots? That would be nine. If we look at the 
specific combatant command, according to EUCOM [U.S. European 
Command] there are over 28,000 Air Force personnel supporting 
EUCOM. And how many of those 28,000 are dedicated to work space 
issues? That would be two.
    We do need to integrate space. I completely agree with 
General Goldfein on that with the air, and our land and sea, 
and cyber obligations. It is what combatant commanders do. But 
they are also designed to fight and win wars in a joint manner.
    So General Buck, how do we integrate space capabilities 
better into our war plans and combatant commands? To me, that 
starts with people, and I am interested in your perspective.
    General Buck. Thank you. I agree with you. I would like to 
get more space officers, general officers on the Joint Staff. 
But the chief's very focused on developing joint officers, and 
I think that is a focus area for us as well. When we look 
across the enterprise, you look at United States Strategic 
Command, we have two space officers working in joint jobs at 
U.S. Strategic Command. I am in a joint billet myself as 
commander of JFCC Space.
    The way we--I serve as--my JSpOC [Joint Space] Operations 
Center at Vandenberg, serves as space coordinating authority 
for the combatant command, so they have reach-back authority 
back to get those space effects out to theater.
    As far as developing joint operations, General Raymond, I 
think we are doing a pretty good job, and that is a focus area 
as we go forward.
    General Raymond. I would say, Chairman Rogers, you bring up 
a great point. The challenges that we face as a Nation today 
are transregional, if not global, multidomain and 
multifunctional. They are not confined to a line on the map. It 
is not just one geographic commander's responsibility; it is 
pretty much all the combatant commanders' responsibility. Each 
combatant commander has what is called a coordinating authority 
for space. Each of those combatant commanders has delegated 
that authority down to the CFACCs [combined force air component 
commanders], or the air component of that. In the air 
components around the globe, we probably have a senior space 
officer called the director of space forces. We have--and 
General Goldfein testified to this. He was the space 
coordinating authority at CENTCOM [U.S. Central Command] at the 
time. We have a senior space officer called the director of 
space forces. He has a staff of about five. And then in every 
single division in the AOC [air operations center], we have 
space professionals embedded in those divisions.
    So what we have done is prioritized putting the weight of 
effort in those AOCs where the combatant commander has 
designated that authority, too. And that is where we do that 
multidomain integration work, that is the hub of that 
multidomain integration work.
    Mr. Rogers. You mentioned that General Goldfein, at one 
time, was the space advisor?
    General Raymond. No, sir, he was the CFACC, the Air Force's 
component commander for CENTCOM. And in that role, the CENTCOM 
commander delegates to him the authority called the space 
coordinating authority. And his AOC, where he operated out of, 
is that multidomain center that integrates air, space, and 
cyber into that fight, and that is where we focus a significant 
portion of our space operations.
    Mr. Rogers. General Buck, you were going to say something.
    General Buck. I am sorry to interrupt. I will say that 
probably in CENTCOM, we have the preponderance of space 
officers in CENTCOM right now. That is our weight of effort.
    And if you look at CENTCOM right now, in the director of 
space force office we probably have 8, maybe 10 space officers 
in the director of space force offices there. But what is a 
real win for us, when not just we have a director of space 
force office there, but when we embed space officers in ISRD 
[intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance division] and 
COD [combat operations division] and CPD [combat planning 
division], that is a win; when we start not being an add-on, 
but we are baked into the processes over there. And I think we 
are doing better. Our focus right now is on CENTCOM, but I will 
tell you, sir, we are getting better in PACOM [U.S. Pacific 
Command] and EUCOM across the board.
    Mr. Rogers. Great. The chair recognizes the ranking member 
for any questions he may have.
    Mr. Cooper. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I would like to focus 
in my questioning on how crowded space is and how it is going 
to get a lot more crowded. Mr. Cardillo mentioned in his 
testimony on page 5 that in the last 10 years, we saw something 
like 1,500 satellites go up, but in the next 10 years, 
something like 9,000. That is 2\1/2\ satellites a day going up 
in space. That is amazing. But we have seen launches like in 
India recently that they put up 100 sats [satellites] just in 
one launch. So as space gets more crowded, it gets more 
treacherous. General Buck mentioned in his testimony, it used 
to be that the main threat we faced was debris; now we face 
traffic, we may face threats. So I am particularly interested 
in this idea of the nonmilitary space traffic management. 
Again, I understand, General Raymond, you embarked on a pilot 
program with the FAA [Federal Aviation Administration] on that?
    General Raymond. Thank you, Ranking Member Cooper. We have. 
As I testified before to this panel, I share your concern; 
space is clearly congested and contested, but in this case, on 
the congested side. General Buck and his team track 23,000 
objects a day, take about 400,000 observations a day to keep 
track of all that, act as the space traffic control for the 
world and keeps the domain safe for all.
    It is very important, and I think General Buck will agree 
with me, I will pass it to him here, but it is very important, 
for national security purposes, that we have the ability to 
have radars, to task those radars, to collect the data for 
those radars, to be able to maintain the awareness that we need 
for that domain. However, I don't think we need to be the 
organization that makes the notifications around the world and 
acts as the traffic cop.
    So I have met with the FAA administrator a couple months 
ago, and asked if he would join us in developing a pilot 
program, if you will, to see if we could inform this going 
forward. General Buck has the lead on pulling that together. 
And, David, if you want to give an update on where we are.
    General Buck. Thank you, General Raymond.
    I am really proud of the team and how far we have come with 
the FAA. I have talked to Dr. Nield directly, and we have 
agreed jointly to begin that pilot program. I expect that pilot 
program to begin this summer, probably August timeframe.
    I do agree with General Raymond, there are some aspects of 
the space traffic management that are not military, inherently 
military. And we could load-shed them to a civil agency. 
Things--safety of flight, debris management, norms of behavior. 
I don't think those are inherently military. I think it is 
important to make a distinction, too, between what is space 
traffic management and what is space situational awareness. For 
me, as a warfighter, I need space situational awareness; I need 
to know what an object is, where it is going, what its 
capabilities are, what its vulnerabilities are, those types of 
things.
    What I don't need to be doing, I don't think, are things 
like notifications for conjunction assessment and norms of 
behavior. And I think that is better suited for a civil agency, 
and I think that is where we are going, sir.
    Mr. Cooper. Let me add some color to your remarks. General 
Raymond said in a very calm fashion, we keep space safe, or 
something like that. We are protecting other countries' $1 
billion satellites from a piece of shrapnel that might be 
traveling at 33,000 miles an hour, but could destroy the 
machine, and for that, we get not even a thank-you note. You 
know, it is kind of amazing that we provide this magnificent 
worldwide service and little appreciation. Plus, as you said, 
when we consider load-shedding, it is a burden on our folks 
that doesn't necessarily need to be borne by them.
    General Raymond. Other people--not all countries--some 
countries do send us thank-you notes, do talk a lot more to us, 
others don't. We are really doing it because we want to keep 
the space domain safe for all to use, including us. And so that 
is the emphasis behind that. We need to be able to operate in 
space, and it is our way of helping to make sure that we can do 
that.
    Mr. Cooper. But it is also an essential truth-telling 
function. Like, if you look at the downing of the Malaysian 
airliner over the Ukraine, there was worldwide debate and 
dispute over what caused that plane to crash. And even though 
we have excellent air traffic control in most parts of the 
world, there was still a significant dispute. And when it comes 
to separating news from fake news and propaganda, you know, I 
think in the space domain, it would be nice if we established a 
sort of gold standard of truth so we would know if it was 
debris, we would know if it was something less benign than 
that. So I am worried that while I hope the pilot program gets 
off to a good start this summer, I hope it will soon be able to 
establish a standard, but even with air traffic, we are having 
difficulty isolating causes when it should be, with all of our 
plane radars and things like that, an easier thing to prove 
than it is in space. So I hope we will get on that task.
    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
    Mr. Rogers. The chair now recognizes Mr. Lamborn for any 
questions he may have.
    Mr. Lamborn. I thank you, Mr. Chairman. And thank you all 
for the great service that you provide for our country. And 
General Raymond, I am going to follow up on a question we 
touched on in our conversation yesterday. With BMC2 [battle 
management command and control], I remain concerned about the 
prospect of repeating the same mistakes we made with JMS [Joint 
Space Operations Center Mission System], whereby lab prototypes 
and custom government development efforts were prioritized over 
utilizing proven commercial capabilities, which, unfortunately, 
led to huge scheduling and cost overruns. Can I get your 
commitment that you will prioritize the utilization of 
commercial capabilities to the maximum extent practicable 
first, and then fill in with government development for the 
truly unique military requirements that don't reside in the 
commercial marketplace?
    General Raymond. I am a big proponent of commercial data. I 
have said for many years in front of this committee that we 
need all sources of data. We need data from commercial, all the 
way up to the high-end intelligence data. And on what our 
strategy going forward on the battle management command and 
control system that you reference is to do just that, is to use 
commercial companies in a consortium to help us develop those 
requirements.
    It is analogous to the iPhone. You've got the iPhone and 
then you have apps. And we want to have open standards and open 
consortium so all players can play in feeding us that data and 
to do so quickly. We have to get it on the floor. We have to 
get it in the National Space Defense Center as quick as we 
possibly can.
    Therefore, what we did was, we switched the program, and I 
gave that to the Air Force Rapid Capabilities Office, who has 
already done this. They have already taken the capability, 
built an open-architected system, has a consortium approach, 
and it has worked very well. So we are fast-forwarding this 
capability by giving it to the folks that can move rapidly, 
that have already done it in another capability in the air 
domain. And what this will allow us to do is also get at that 
multidomain integration.
    So the whole purpose of this program going forward is to 
enable a lot of commercial data and other source data to be 
integrated to give General Buck the data that he needs to have 
to do the mission that he is responsible for.
    General Buck. If I could just make a comment along the same 
lines. Ranking Member Cooper stressed the importance of domain 
awareness. It is really important that we ingest non-
traditional data into our space surveillance network as well. 
That is a hard thing to do, but we are making progress. And I 
think this summer some time, we are going to bring out a 
capability called the non-traditional data preprocessor that 
will begin to allow ingestion of commercial data into our space 
surveillance network. So I think that is a move in the right 
direction for domain awareness and non-traditional ingestion, 
like commercial sensors, if you will.
    Mr. Lamborn. Thank you both.
    Changing gears, I have heard some rumors about insufficient 
funding for GPS [Global Positioning System] III in the fiscal 
year 2018 request. What are we doing to keep this important 
program on track?
    General Raymond. So Congressman, we have not submitted the 
2018 budget going forward. We have, in my opinion, a pretty 
healthy GPS constellation in that we have got 31 operational 
satellites on orbit. We actually have 37 on orbit, 31 are 
operational. We are moving forward with the [GPS] OCX [Next 
Generation Operational Control System] program. Although that, 
as many folks have testified previously, would not be the model 
program that we would hold up as the standard. And we are 
clearly not out of the woods yet. And I won't be comfortable 
until that capability is operational on the OPS [operations] 
floor for General Buck's team to be able to operate.
    So I am pretty comfortable where we are with a relatively 
healthy GPS constellation that is on orbit and progress being 
made on the ground control----
    Mr. Lamborn. What does that mean for the budget for next 
year?
    General Raymond. The budget is going to be released next 
week. And so, I would prefer not to speculate on what might be 
released in the budget until that gets released.
    Mr. Lamborn. Okay. Ms. Sapp, in 40 seconds, I am going to 
give you a huge question, but you referred to how we don't have 
the commitment we need for space going forward. What can we do 
better as a country to show that commitment and that resolve?
    Ms. Sapp. I think we really need help on the budget side, 
not just investment in space, but the ability to use the 
investment. As we are fielding new things to improve our 
resiliency, it was very hard to move ahead with new things 
under our continuing resolution. It is not allowed. So that is 
just slowing the pace of progress, even after we get it out of 
the executive branch, which is no mean feat. So you could help 
a lot on that front.
    Mr. Lamborn. Thank you so much.
    General Raymond. I would echo that as well on behalf of Air 
Force Space Command.
    Mr. Lamborn. Thank you.
    Mr. Rogers. The chair now recognizes the gentleman from 
California, Mr. Garamendi, for any questions he may have.
    Mr. Garamendi. I am going to forego the usual GPS backup. I 
assume that is moving along, and if not, there will be a piece 
of legislation that will move it along perhaps even faster.
    Not exactly sure how far to go with this. I represent Beale 
Air Force Base. There are certain activities going on, I am not 
sure we should be talking about them here. But I would like to 
take that up, because I think it integrates with most of what 
is being discussed here.
    Just in general, the integration of information from a 
variety of sources, I think this is something that is happening 
just in general. Your views on that progress?
    General Raymond. In general, I think it is going really 
well. And in fact, as largely the model that I use to make the 
decision to go with the approach that we talked about in the 
battle management command and control conversation we just had 
with Congressman Lamborn. I would be more than happy to talk 
more in the closed session with you.
    Mr. Garamendi. I think I will let it go at that point. Oh, 
no, I have one more. We picked this up yesterday in going on--a 
plan for the next decade of critical assets that need to be 
developed and deployed, and the approximate cost of those. I 
think we need to have a long-term vision here about where we 
are going to deploy perhaps the most essential asset of all, 
which is our financial resources. I have not seen such a 
display of those things that we--that you, the military in 
general, and certainly the Air Force specifically in the space 
area, need, want, must have. I think it is really essential 
that we look at that. There will be insufficient money for 
everything, particularly if the tax cuts are real.
    And, so, we are going to need to make some tough decisions 
about prioritization, and that means the long view, 10 years 
minimum, so that we can say, Okay, these things will be funded, 
those are not, or we are going to fund all of it and not fund 
something else. So Mr. Chairman, if we could move in that 
direction so we can have that long-term vision.
    General Raymond. Could I--I would welcome an opportunity to 
come back to you and walk you through the Space Enterprise 
Vision. That is our longer-term vision for space. It is done in 
very close partnership, it is an integrated vision with the 
NRO. I want to take a moment--I do this every time I can, and I 
am not saying it because Betty Sapp is here--Betty Sapp is a 
huge partner for us.
    Mr. Garamendi. Two minutes, eight seconds. Go for it.
    General Raymond. But I would be more than welcome to come 
back and walk you through that vision, walk you through the 
priorities as we see them and inform you on that.
    Mr. Garamendi. We heard some of this yesterday from General 
Goldfein about different directions, or at least a different 
set of priorities for the future. Much of it involved your 
work, so I wanted to get a fix on that and other things that we 
may not, but is a priority. Thank you for that.
    I didn't mean to cut you off, I really meant you had 2 
minutes and 8 seconds to answer.
    General Raymond. No, I didn't want to take your time. I 
wanted to see if you had more questions.
    Mr. Garamendi. Thank you.
    Mr. Rogers. The chair recognizes Mr. Bridenstine for 5 
minutes.
    Mr. Bridenstine. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. When you think 
about the consortium, General Raymond, that you talked about 
for the BMC2 piece of the National Space Defense Center. That 
consortium, of course, is trying to rapidly develop a 
capability where we are currently maybe lagging behind. And, of 
course, I think everybody on this committee fully supports that 
effort.
    In the meantime, is there an SSA [space situational 
awareness] gap that needs to be filled that could be--
commercial could help with? And maybe General Buck, if you 
would like to answer that as well.
    General Buck. Well, thank you, sir. Good seeing you again.
    Mr. Bridenstine. Always.
    General Buck. I mentioned a non-traditional data 
preprocessor. I think that is a step in the right direction. I 
think you will agree with me, the ability to ingest some of 
those non-tradi--that helps. What also we have is, we have SBSS 
[Space Based Space Surveillance] that is online--on orbit right 
now, that is being extended. The life on that is extended past 
its--I think the dates are classified, but that is going to be 
extended, and plus ORS-5 [Operationally Responsive Space 5] 
gives us, provides us that gap-filler capability as well. So I 
think those three things together give us the capability to 
fulfill that gap.
    General Raymond. Just as a general statement, more data is 
better, from a South Carolina kudzu guy. More data is better. 
We need data across the full spectrum, and we do get that 
across the full spectrum. The other thing that we have done is 
develop partnerships, and we have got--don't quote me on the 
numbers--over 50 or 60 SSA sharing agreements with partners. It 
is largely one-way sharing, but there are two-way sharing 
pieces. I would like to make that stronger. When we get the new 
JMS system up with more capacity and more ability to ingest 
that data, that will take off. But more is better.
    Mr. Bridenstine. More is better. I would like to maybe 
continue on what Ranking Member Cooper was talking about, this 
effort to create a partnership with the FAA for space 
situational awareness specifically. Can you share with us how 
that is being funded? And is it coming out of your budget? Is 
it coming out of their budget? Is there something Congress 
should do here to help?
    General Buck. My understanding is there is going to be a 
fiscal year 2018 budget request coming out of the FAA. But I am 
hesitant to say that because I am getting in the FAA's lane a 
little bit. But I think there is a funding request for 2018 
that is coming out of the FAA, sir, but I don't have the 
specifics on that.
    Mr. Bridenstine. That is good to hear. Again, I know that 
is not your lane. I don't want to get you in trouble, but I 
think this committee would be very supportive of that 
partnership. Right now, we have heard testimony over and over 
again how we are providing free situational awareness to the 
entire world, and to all the commercial partners, and at the 
same time, the tasking that it has imposed on our warfighters 
at the JSpOC has been problematic, to the extent I hear this 
from other Members of Congress that they want to--and I heard 
you use the word ``load-shed''--they want to load-shed the 
mission, but they do not want to load-shed the funding. And I 
want everybody on this committee to know, the Air Force was 
never funded to provide space situational awareness to the 
entire world and commercial operators for free. That has not 
ever been in your mission description. And yet, that is what 
you are doing by default out of goodness of your hearts. I say 
the goodness out of your hearts, but the reality is we need to 
protect our own assets, and we all know that.
    So I just want to reiterate the fact that if we can create 
a space situational awareness environment that can be led by a 
civilian agency and free your manpower to actually be focused 
on fighting and winning wars, I think everybody on this panel 
would fully support that effort. And if we need to do an 
appropriation, I think that that is something we should be 
advocating for. So with that--go ahead.
    General Raymond. I agree with everything you said. I just 
also want to make sure that we state the criticality that the 
national security space mission needs to make sure that they 
have the space situational awareness.
    Mr. Bridenstine. Absolutely.
    General Raymond. So I agree with you that there is a role 
here for others, but it is critical to our national security 
that we also maintain the capability to have that awareness.
    Mr. Bridenstine. One hundred percent, Air Force must and 
will always do space situational awareness, and, of course, 
space defense; I 100 percent agree with that. It is the--not 
just the conjunctional analysis, but it is the warning that 
takes a lot of the manpower away from your----
    General Raymond. I am with you.
    Mr. Bridenstine. Okay. All right. With that, Mr. Chairman, 
I yield back.
    Mr. Rogers. I thank the gentleman. The chair now recognizes 
the gentleman from Washington State, Mr. Larsen, for 5 minutes.
    Mr. Larsen. Thanks, Mr. Chairman. I was going to jump in on 
this, but given that I am the ranking member of the Aviation 
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
</Hearing>
