<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="32261">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;115th Congress }                            Printed for the use of the             &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;2nd Session    }      Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe                       &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;======================================================================&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	                     Free-Trade Zones: Productive&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	                           or Destructive?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         SEPTEMBER 12, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                           Briefing of the&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         Washington: 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;         Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  234 Ford House Office Building                                               &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   Washington, DC 20515&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      202-225-1901&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      csce@mail.house.gov&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      http://www.csce.gov&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         @HelsinkiComm                    &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  Legislative Branch Commissioners&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;              HOUSE				SENATE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;CHRISTOPHER H. SMITH, New Jersey 	ROGER WICKER, Mississippi,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Co-Chairman			  Chairman&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ALCEE L. HASTINGS, Florida		BENJAMIN L. CARDIN. Maryland&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ROBERT B. ADERHOLT, Alabama		JOHN BOOZMAN, Arkansas&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;MICHAEL C. BURGESS, Texas		CORY GARDNER, Colorado&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;STEVE COHEN, Tennessee			MARCO RUBIO, Florida&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;RICHARD HUDSON, North Carolina		JEANNE SHAHEEN, New Hampshire&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;RANDY HULTGREN, Illinois		THOM TILLIS, North Carolina&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;SHEILA JACKSON LEE, Texas		TOM UDALL, New Mexico&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;GWEN MOORE, Wisconsin			SHELDON WHITEHOUSE, Rhode Island&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;               Executive Branch Commissioners&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                    DEPARTMENT OF STATE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  DEPARTMENT OF COMMERCE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                            [II]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Helsinki process, formally titled the Conference on Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe, traces its origin to the signing of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Helsinki Final Act in Finland on August 1, 1975, by the leaders of 33 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European countries, the United States and Canada. As of January 1, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;1995, the Helsinki process was renamed the Organization for Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE). The membership of the OSCE has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;expanded to 56 participating States, reflecting the breakup of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Soviet Union, Czechoslovakia, and Yugoslavia.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The OSCE Secretariat is in Vienna, Austria, where weekly meetings &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the participating States' permanent representatives are held. In &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;addition, specialized seminars and meetings are convened in various &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;locations. Periodic consultations are held among Senior Officials, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Ministers and Heads of State or Government.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Although the OSCE continues to engage in standard setting in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fields of military security, economic and environmental cooperation, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and human rights and humanitarian concerns, the Organization is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;primarily focused on initiatives designed to prevent, manage and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resolve conflict within and among the participating States. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Organization deploys numerous missions and field activities located in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Southeastern and Eastern Europe, the Caucasus, and Central Asia. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;website of the OSCE is: &amp;lt;www.osce.org&amp;gt;.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, also known as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Helsinki Commission, is a U.S. Government agency created in 1976 to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;monitor and encourage compliance by the participating States with their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;OSCE commitments, with a particular emphasis on human rights.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission consists of nine members from the United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Senate, nine members from the House of Representatives, and one member &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;each from the Departments of State, Defense and Commerce. The positions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Chair and Co-Chair rotate between the Senate and House every two &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years, when a new Congress convenes. A professional staff assists the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commissioners in their work.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In fulfilling its mandate, the Commission gathers and disseminates &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relevant information to the U.S. Congress and the public by convening &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hearings, issuing reports that reflect the views of Members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission and/or its staff, and providing details about the activities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the Helsinki process and developments in OSCE participating States.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission also contributes to the formulation and execution of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.S. policy regarding the OSCE, including through Member and staff &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participation on U.S. Delegations to OSCE meetings. Members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission have regular contact with parliamentarians, government &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;officials, representatives of non-governmental organizations, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;private individuals from participating States. The website of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission is: &amp;lt;www.csce.gov&amp;gt;.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            Free-Trade Zones: Productive or Destructive?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                           September 12, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                                                   Page&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              PARTICIPANTS&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Paul Massaro, Policy Advisor, Commission on Security and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Cooperation in Europe...................................................1&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Clay Fuller, Jeane Kirkpatrick Fellow, American Enterprise &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Institute...............................................................2&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Jack Radisch, Senior Project Manager, OECD High Level Risk Forum....5&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Stephane Jacobzone, Deputy Head, Division of Public Governance, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD)...........5&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Pedro Assares Rodrigues, Representative, Europol Liaison Bureau.....7&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Free-Trade Zones: Productive or Destructive?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              ----------                              &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                           September 12, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The briefing was held at 3:00 p.m. in Room 2220, Rayburn Senate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Office Building, Washington, DC, Paul Massaro, Policy Advisor, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, presiding.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Panelists present: Paul Massaro, Policy Advisor, Commission on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Security and Cooperation in Europe; Clay Fuller, Jeane Kirkpatrick &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Fellow, American Enterprise Institute; Jack Radisch, Senior Project &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Manager, OECD High Level Risk Forum; Stephane Jacobzone, Deputy Head, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Division of Public Governance, Organisation for Economic Co-operation &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Development (OECD); and Pedro Assares Rodrigues, Representative, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol Liaison Bureau.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Okay. Good afternoon and welcome to this briefing of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the U.S. Helsinki Commission.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The commission is mandated to monitor compliance with international &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rules and standards across Europe, which include military affairs, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economic and environmental issues, and human rights and democracy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My name is Paul Massaro and I am the policy advisor responsible for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economic and environmental issues, including illicit trade.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would like to welcome you today on behalf of our bipartisan and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bicameral leadership to discuss an underexamined threat to the national &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;security of the United States: free-trade zones, or FTZs. FTZs are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;duty-free areas within a country's borders designed to encourage &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economic development by allowing goods to be imported and exported &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;under less restrictive conditions than are present elsewhere in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;country.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In many places, these zones generate jobs and wealth. However, they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are also hospitable to illicit trade and money laundering. In the worst &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cases, law enforcement fails and FTZs become global hubs of criminal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;activity, black holes that enable corruption.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    For all the prosperity that globalization has generated, corruption &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is consuming an ever-greater share of these gains. In order to enrich &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;themselves, transnational criminal networks have found innovative ways &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to exploit otherwise productive technologies and governance frameworks &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to flout international rules and standards. This has led to a flood of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;dangerous counterfeits and contraband into U.S. and European markets, a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;spike in wealth inequality as ill-gotten gains are distributed among a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;handful of bosses, and a besiegement of the rule of law as authorities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;struggle to keep up.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    As these criminals have become more sophisticated, their political &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;influence has increased. In many cases, transnational criminal networks &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have become so effective at manipulating globalization that they have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fused with the government, capturing the state and turning it to their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;devious ends. This brand of authoritarianism based on globalized &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;corruption, or kleptocracy as we've come to call it, poses a major &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;national security threat to the United States as the country finds &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;itself economically entangled with autocratic powers that have no &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;intention of playing by the rules.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    These powers have wasted no time weaponizing corruption and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;deploying it as their primary tool of foreign policy. By strategically &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;placing authoritarian capital, kleptocracies are able to, one, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;influence operations, engage in reputation laundering, and gain access &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to and leverage over elites. While many of the vulnerabilities that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;enable this weaponization of corruption have become a focus of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Washington policy community, in particular the national security threat &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;posed by anonymous shell companies, others have remained out of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;limelight. Free-trade zones fall squarely into this category.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We have a truly distinguished panel here today to help us &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understand the role of FTZs, how they are being exploited by criminal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;actors, and what action can be taken. Speaking first we have Dr. Clay &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Fuller to my left, the American Enterprise Institute Jeane Kirkpatrick &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fellow. He is a leading light in understanding the corruption &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;authoritarianism nexus and will set the stage by providing us his &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;insights.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Fuller, thank you so much for joining us today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Fuller. Do you want me to go?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Not just yet. [Chuckles.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We will then hear from Jack Radisch, senior project manager with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development, or OECD, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;High-Level Risk Forum. Jack is here all the way from Paris to discuss &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all the good work the OECD's Task Force on Countering Illicit Trade has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been doing on FTZs.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I also want to welcome Stephane Jacobzone, who we've got at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;front table with us today. He is the deputy head of the Division of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Public Governance at the OECD, so also from Paris.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you so much for joining us, Stephane.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So glad that you both could be here.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Finally, we will hear from Pedro Assares Rodrigues, Europol's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;representative here in Washington. As the EU's police cooperation body, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol is well aware of the complexities regarding transnational &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;criminal networks in the 21st century. Pedro will speak to Europol's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;efforts to combat illicit trade, including through FTZs, and the need &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for transatlantic cooperation to take on globalized corruption.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Pedro, thanks so much for joining us.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    With that, I will hand it over to Dr. Fuller.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thanks so much. The floor is yours.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Fuller. All right. Thank you very much, Paul.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So thank you to the Commission on Security and Cooperation in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europe for inviting me here today to provide a few comments on the use &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of foreign trade zones in this superbly named briefing, ``Free-Trade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Zones: Productive or Destructive?''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I have given my comments a clever name as well: ``More Data on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;FTZs, Please?'' [Laughter.] My British and Panamanian friends would &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;know that I like to say SOPs for the FTZs also, but I'm going to talk &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;here about a more nuanced and objective way of thinking about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transparency. And there's two points that I'm going to make about this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the context of the FTZs.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So there needs to be more and better aggregate data on free-trade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;zones around the world. Private and public sector actors that use and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;study free-trade zones can be instrumental in pushing governments to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;report more standardized and higher-quality data on zones.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We've known for years that things like corruption, illicit trade, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;illicit finance are huge issues within free-trade zones around the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;world. The law enforcement community, large multinational corporations, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;environmental protection groups, journalists and labor rights &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organizations are keenly aware of the issues, but they seem to be stuck &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;without a way to move forward. So thanks to the hard work of the OECD, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we now have some preliminary empirical evidence that free-trade zones &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do play a significant role in the trafficking of counterfeit goods &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;specifically, but further research and better data are needed.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    During the last year at the American Enterprise Institute, I have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;written extensively on issues of kleptocracy, authoritarianism, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;corruption, illicit trade and illicit finance. As I emphasized at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;last Helsinki Commission meeting on illicit trade specifically, I want &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to reiterate the idea that in all anticorruption efforts, including &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fighting illicit trade and illicit finance, groups interested in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reforming FTZs would do well to define not just what they are fighting &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;against, but what it is they are fighting for.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So if we define corruption as the abuse of entrusted power for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;private gain, then its natural opposite, or in other words what we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;should be fighting for, is the use of earned power for public gain. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;This begs the question, how do we fight for the use of earned power for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public gain? Well, the answer is transparency. But not in the classic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sunlight, disinfectant, investigative or activist sense that we usually &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think of the term ``transparency'' in.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Transparency can be thought of very simply as the credible &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reporting of aggregate economic data to the public. So think about the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;important roles of aggregate data, like job growth numbers, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;unemployment and GDP growth--transparency defined objectively as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;credible aggregate economic data is a crucial public good that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governments are best suited to provide, but crucially requires help &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;from the private sector in order to collect and define the concepts &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;needed to measure it.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Similar to how a lighthouse provides data to incoming ships in a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;storm or polling and elections provide signals of grievances and policy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shifts, credible aggregate FTZ data can act as a coordination good &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;amongst a host of public and private actors, including businesses, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;financial institutions and law enforcement agencies.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The U.S. Government is currently one of the best in the world when &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it comes to reporting aggregate data. But in my opinion, it utterly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fails when it comes to its own FTZs. For example, I cannot find a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;credible number of how many active FTZs we have in the United States. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;My best guess at this point is that it's somewhere between 176 and 250. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;So in fact, the entire world utterly fails at publishing these data. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;The number of FTZs globally is typically estimated by experts to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;somewhere between 3,000 and 5,000. I think we can do much better than &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that. So the first point of problems in reporting data, problems with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;FTZ data stem from the simple measurement issues that are made &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inordinately complex due to a lack of standardization around the world. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;The most basic problem that we can get to is in simply counting zones.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So no definitive number of zones exists because they are called &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different things in different places. In China, in Dubai, they are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;often called special economic zones. In the United States, they are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;called foreign-trade zones. And elsewhere, they are called free-trade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;zones or export-processing zones or industrial parks or a host of other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;names. Furthermore, there's even more questions. Should we count things &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;like subzones and operators? Should we count the number of firms? &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Should we count the number of employees, square kilometers or the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;volumes of trade? Or should we categorize zones by the economic sectors &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that they service?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My point is that while complex questions exist, these are far from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;insurmountable and they can be easily overcome by the national &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governments that write these zones into laws and with the help of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;firms that operate within them, through simple standardization and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reporting mechanisms.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    To date, other than the data I have personally collected and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;analyzed on trade zones around the world, only the World Bank and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;OECD have attempted systematic global studies of the effects of these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;zones. These are great and informative studies, but what I'm saying is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that to make these studies better there needs to be better and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;standardized national-level data.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So the last point--pushing for better data. Credible reporting of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;aggregate economic data is transparency. Transparency in this objective &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sense is good for both economic growth and the rule of law. For the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;private sector, it's the term ``aggregate'' that's key, right, because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;private firms are rightly jealous of their privacy. Without it, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;competitors and bad actors will find ways to use and abuse their data &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to gain an unfair advantage and perpetuate further criminal activities. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;But there's no harm done in asking national governments to clearly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;define, count and report basic aggregate information on zones to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public. There are a host of ways in which this can be done while still &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;protecting the privacy of firms located within the zones.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, for governments and law enforcement agencies, the term &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;``credible'' is key here. In order for transparency to work as a public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;good, it has to be credible. To use my previous examples, a lighthouse &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is only as valuable as it is dependable, a poll is only as reliable as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it is scientific and an election is only as valuable as it is free and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fair. But governments around the world are currently facing credibility &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;issues across the board, and I would argue that this is partly due to a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;lack of transparency in this objective sense.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Foreign-trade zones, I think, are a great place to start building &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;back trust between the private and public sector because, one, they are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relatively small; two, they are geographically delineated to specific &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;areas; and three, because of these previous two points they are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;theoretically more easily monitored jointly by public and private &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;entities.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In the almost 10 years of studying and following the use of FTZs &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;worldwide, it's become my view that there is no more pragmatic way to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;promote lasting economic growth free of the corruption that feeds &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economic inequality, organized crime, illegal immigration and a host of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;other complex issues than to report more credible aggregate economic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;data on foreign-trade zones.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So the work of the OECD is an important first step and it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;establishes a solid baseline for understanding and working around these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;issues concerning FTZs. However, improving transparency of foreign-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;trade zones will require bottom-up, private/public pressure on national &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governments to publish better data. Then once leading national &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governments develop these aggregate data, it is up to them to persuade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their trading partners to standardize and share these aggregate data &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with each other to act as a coordinated public good.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ultimately, without a clearer picture of how the world free-trade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;zones work and their effects, public and private sector initiatives to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;minimize their subversion by criminal elements will remain futile.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you for your time and I look forward to any questions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Thank you very much, Dr. Fuller. I'm so happy you also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;were impressed with the OECD's work on free-trade zones. That's why we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;invited them here today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So with that, I'd like to hand the floor to Jack and Stephane to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;talk about that very work.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Radisch. Thank you very much, Paul.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And thank you very much to the Helsinki Commission for this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;invitation to present some of the OECD's findings related to free-trade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;zones.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'd like first to just contextualize that research that we're doing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on free-trade zones. It's not to look at the economic benefits, which &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are undoubtable in many cases. Our research is focusing on the role of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;free-trade zones pertaining to illicit trade. And that's the topic of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our panel today, and so that drives very much the approach we take and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the information that we gather and analyze with regard to free-trade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;zones.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Task Force on Countering Illicit Trade at the OECD was set up &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to study, to map, to quantify different sectors of illicit trade. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;some of you might be familiar with the work that we've done on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;counterfeit trade. That's an area where we actually have a high level &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of confidence in our estimates of the quantity and the flows of that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sector of illicit trade. The OECD estimated that up to $461 billion is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conducted in trade in fakes based on the years that we studied. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we'll continue that research next year with updated years of data so we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can begin to compare and see if there's any trends that emerge. For &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;now, we have pictures over a couple of different years successively. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;But $461 billion in trade in fakes is a lot of money. And where does &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that money go, but oftentimes recycling into the criminal hands behind &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these criminal enterprises.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And we analyzed through trade data and seizure data the flows of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that trade in fakes. And we noticed that oftentimes it's going through &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;free-trade zones. So that led us on to another line of inquiry to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;analyze the correlation between free-trade zones and the trade in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;global fakes.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So I'd like to ask my colleague Stephane to say about a few of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;findings on the economic impacts and correlations in that report.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And also, we have more recent reports on the conditions that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;attract the trade in fakes.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Stephane.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Jacobzone. Yes, thank you very much, Jack.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I just wanted to say that the OECD is an economic cooperation set &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;up after World War II to promote economic cooperation among nations. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;It's part of the George Marshall Plan, is heavily committed to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transparency.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And the work we are presenting today is part of our work to step up &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;global anticorruption efforts that we do in partnership with the U.K.--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I see some of our colleagues here--with the U.S. and also this work on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;free-trade zones in partnership with the European Union Intellectual &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Property Office.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So what are we looking at? We are in fact looking at governance &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;gaps. These are the sort of grease of globalizations because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;globalization is meant to be good for everyone. But there are people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who can see the gaps who make enormous profits above this sort of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;benign neglect, or blind-eyes policy, where people can let things go &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just as they are so that you can maximize profits.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    What we found--and you are very right, Dr. Fuller, to say that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there is no standardized data on the free-trade zones, because to do &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our work we had to rely on some academic databases--because academics' &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;interest in the topic have had armies of students and people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;researching the facts, that gave us a database of nearly 3,000 free-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;trade zones. It may not be exhaustive, but sufficient to get good &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;statistical results. And that's how we built our results.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And when we did our analysis, we did find that for nearly each &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;additional free-trade zone in the country, I think the propensity to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;export free goods in that country would jump by, let's say, 5 or 6 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;percent. So that was a statistical, proven link between the increasing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;numbers of free-trade zones and the propensity to export fake goods. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And that's part of a general analysis where we look at governance gaps.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And we see that countries where there are, let's say, sufficient &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;production capacities, logistics capacities, the ability to facilitate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shipments and trade flows, but which at the same time do not have the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;same governance standards as, let's say, a country such as the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States, have become the hubs of the dark economy globally and can be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;used by traffickers to shape counterfeit products.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We have another related publication on why do countries export fake &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;goods.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And then you would say, what do you do with that? You have to do &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;something. You have to get some form of a joint effort by nations to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;step up the pressure. And with Jack, we have also been developing some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;form of a guidance which in the future--at least the countries inside &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the OECD to start with, which represents at least still 50 or 60 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;percent of the global economy--would commit to monitor, track and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;publish information on their free-trade zones--answering to your &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;comment--and where we would also invite the free-trade zones to adopt &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;codes of conduct so that free-trade zones means, okay, you are duty &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;free, you don't pay taxes, you have a good environment for business, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;but it doesn't mean that you are not subject to any checks, for example &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;customs check, and so that we can sort of detect any illegal activity &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that would go through you. So that's the sort of effort that we are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pushing through.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Radisch. And if I can follow up on that, because we've &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conducted this empirical work, we've seen that there really is a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;problem going through the free-trade zones. It's not just anecdotes, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it's not just a hunch--we've shown this correlation. And the question &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;really is what to do about it. And yet, many of these economies do &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;depend on free-trade zones for their economic benefits. Not all of them &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have panned out the way they might have anticipated. And the question &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is what to do about the illicit trade that's going through some of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;them. And this is the work that Stephane is referring to.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Through the OECD, we're developing a standard that would be helpful &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to law enforcement around the world to have a better idea of what's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;going on inside particular zones at any given time. So talking about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;information requirements, this is not focused on the, say, the economic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;benefits or the employment gains, but rather what merchandise, what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;consignments are coming in and going out, who owns the merchandise, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;where is it going.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The idea is to have a situational awareness of what's present &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inside a free-trade zone at any given moment so that when there's an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;investigation on the premises, it can really make a difference. This &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;doesn't add up on what the audit trail points, that there is a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;discrepancy on what the inventory says. And this is the type of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;information that the law enforcement community and customs need in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;order to fight this scourge.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Thanks so much, Jack and Stephane. And thank you for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all the data you've been collecting, your good work, and also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;specifically for highlighting the work you've been doing on developing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;guidance. I think at the end of the day when we're looking at results &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and policy, that's going to be extremely helpful. And you mention that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that would be very helpful to law enforcement.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Well, it just so happens we have a law enforcement representative &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at the table, so I'd like to hand it over to Pedro now to speak to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Rodrigues. Thanks so much, Paul, for the floor. And thank you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also to the Helsinki Commission for the invitation addressed to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So, indeed, my name is Pedro Assares. I'm one of Europol's liaison &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;officers here to Washington, and just to tell you a little bit about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol, to provide you some context on what we do and who we are, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol was created in 1992 as a European drugs unit, and since then we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have evolved into dealing with serious and organized crime, terrorism, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and all other forms of criminality that affect the European Union's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;interests. And within these interests, obviously, we include fraud, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;counterfeiting, money laundering--so all the criminal activities that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;basically are connected, as we have heard before, to free-trade zones.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Europol's main role is actually to support its member states, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;member states in the European Union and other partners we work with, in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;preventing and combating crime, and we do it by basically acting as a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;central information hub. We host a large database of criminal entities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of various different natures, and we also provide our partners with an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;information exchange platform. We have one system which is called SIENA &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that is basically connecting all the 28 European member states plus all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the countries and international organizations that we have agreements &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with. Obviously the U.S. is also included in this group of partners. We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also provide analytical and operational support, and we have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;specialized teams that deal with this type of criminality.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And to mention the last very particular characteristic of Europol &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which makes us, I would say, unique, is our network of liaison &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;officers. So we have between 220 and 230 liaison officers in house, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;based in The Hague, where Europol is headquartered. And basically this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;network of liaison officers allows all the countries and organizations &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;represented at Europol to interact directly in real time. So if I have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;an issue on counterfeiting, and it's involving my own country and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;another country across the world--the U.S., for example--I can just go &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;up one floor or go down one floor, knock on the door of that specific &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;liaison officer and basically ask a question.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The majority of times liaison officers have direct access to their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;databases--national databases, so it can just be a matter of asking a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;question and getting an immediate answer. Other times they just need to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;basically relay the questions back home, and it will be dealt with by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;law enforcement agencies in this case, or by customs authorities also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in what relates to this conference today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Just to give you an idea of our interaction with the U.S., we have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;around 25 U.S. liaison officers based permanently in The Hague, within &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the building, and we have them from 10 different Federal agencies, so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just to name a few--I have a list because there are quite a few. So &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ATF, CBP with direct intervention in free-trade zones, DEA, Defense &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Security Service, FBI, FDA, ICE, IRS, the Secret Service, TSA, and also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the NYPD is represented at Europol.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Cooperation with the U.S. began in 2001 with the signature of a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;strategic agreement, and the year after, in 2002, we signed an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;operational agreement with the U.S. and with its agencies that allows &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol basically to exchange information and to allow for a platform &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for member states to exchange information with the U.S. as well, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also to provide mutual support for each other's high-priority &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;investigations in this case.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I can say that the cooperation between the U.S. and the EU is a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;success story; it has been increasing ever since it began. In recent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years, for unfortunate reasons--so as a result of the terrorist attacks &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the EU, there has been more and more information exchanged, and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;core criminal areas where Europol actually interacts with the U.S. are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;counterterrorism, citizen organized crime, cybercrime, and also illegal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;immigration since 2015 with the advent of the migration crisis that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;existed in Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would also call attention to the TFTP program. Free-trade zones--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;although I'm not an expert in the matter; my area of expertise is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different, but I've done some reading, and there are suspicions that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;free-trade zones could act as a platform for financing terrorism. So &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there is a big component of cooperation between the U.S. and the EU on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;financing of terrorism. We have a terrorist financing tracking program &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in place which basically keeps the liaison bureau here in the U.S., &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;actually, and we occupy it as part of our daily business to exchange &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;information on this kind of topic.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I made mention to SIENA, the Secure Information Exchange Network &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Application--so the information exchange system that Europol has in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;place is also connected here to the U.S., and this has been a major &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;advantage. It allows law enforcement agencies to interact with U.S. law &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;enforcement agencies very directly, securely, without even the need to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;involve Europol, for example. So if there is a need to reach out to any &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;state, local, national law enforcement, customs authorities as well, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this channel can be used directly to exchange information.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Going into a bit more specifically on free-trade zones, basically &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they are being described as an environment with few inspections and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;large cargo coming in and out, and as such, fertile ground for criminal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;activity, for organized crime groups to take advantage of these relaxed &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;procedures, I would say, or controlled procedures to basically just &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;make profits and, again, take advantage of some measures that were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;meant to boost economic growth. As any other low-risk and high-reward &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;situation, it's easily identified by organized crime groups, and they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;will obviously take advantage of it and try to make their own profits &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;out of it. So Europol's response to this type of criminality is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;basically delivered by three main clusters: the fraud cluster, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;counterfeiting cluster, and the financial intelligence cluster.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We do have one operations department which has five different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;subunits, so we have one information central hub which is the gateway &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for all the information that reaches Europol. We have a serious and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organized crime center, we have a cybercrime center, we have a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;counterterrorism center, and we have horizontal operational support &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;where financial intelligence is included. The other two, fraud and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;counterfeiting, are part of the serious and organized crime unit, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there are two specific teams within the fraud cluster which are of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relevance for today's discussion, which are Apate, which is dealing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with fraud, and in this case with special relevance in fake invoice &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fraud. Then we have Smoke, which as the name suggests, deals with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cigarette smuggling. Then we have another team called Copy within the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;counterfeiting cluster, and basically they deal directly with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;counterfeiting, and then a team called Sustrans--that's short for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;suspicious transactions. Colleagues there deal with money laundering &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and trying to detect and disrupt criminal cash flows which are linked &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to organized crime.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    To know more on Europol's take on free-trade zones, I would invite &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you to read a joint report between Europol and the European Union &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Intellectual Property Office that was drafted in 2017. \1\ It's a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;situation report on counterfeiting and piracy in the EU, and it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;basically contains a section which is topic-specific to free-trade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;zones, and it highlights that this remains a threat in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;counterfeiting landscape in the EU, mainly for the reasons that were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;highlighted by the previous panelists, but also highlights that this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;type of criminality is linked with other forms of organized crime such &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as drugs trafficking, excise fraud, human trafficking and human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;smuggling, document fraud, corruption, and so on.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;---------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;\1\  https://www.europol.europa.eu/publications-documents/2017-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;situation-report-counterfeiting-and-piracy-in-european-union&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;---------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So what is being done at the European level that Europol is either &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participating in or trying to show some initiative in? In 2016, in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;July, Europol launched--together again with the European Union &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Intellectual Property Office--the Intellectual Property Crime &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Coordinated Coalition--which is a really long name and acronym--and has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a sister organization based in the U.S. But mainly the intention was to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;provide operational and technical support to law enforcement agencies &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;within the European Union on cross-border investigations in regard to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;counterfeiting, but it also served the purpose of monitoring new trends &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and emerging criminal--or modus operandi in relation to counterfeiting &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and piracy as well.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    There is also something else to highlight: The existence of an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;enforcement database, which is integrated with Europol and with the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European Anti-Fraud Office, and because it is built on existing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European databases on trademark information and registered designs, it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;allows customs authorities and national police authorities basically to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;access information or to view information on products' details, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;actually makes it easier to spot counterfeits and to take the necessary &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and subsequent action.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would finally just also mention Europol hosts an online platform &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for experts which has a number of different sub-platforms on different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;types of criminality, and one of those is called Customs Enforcement, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and it's basically just an online secure platform where customs &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;authorities and other types of law enforcement can apply for membership &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and discuss or exchange non-operational information on this platform at &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different levels--at the national level, at the Customs Cooperation &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Working Party level, or at the World Customs Organization level. So &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;basically it's a restrictive online group that can be accessible by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;request. It allows for sharing knowledge, sharing best practices, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;information, statistics, if necessary--so it's an interesting platform &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for information exchange.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And this basically concludes my intervention, and I'm happy to take &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;any questions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Thank you very much, Pedro, for the insights into how &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol is approaching this problem.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'll say I think everybody in this room and everybody at the table, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we want to make sure that law enforcement has the tools it needs and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the data it needs to take this problem on, so having you at the table &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is really meaningful. Thanks for coming today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So we'll go ahead and move into the Q&amp;amp;A session, so go ahead and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think of your questions. I'm going to ask a couple, and then we'll open &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it up to the public.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My first one is for OECD, Jack and Stephane. I was hoping you might &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be able to speak a little bit to the kinds of items you find in free-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;trade zones--what kind of goods are trafficked and how that impacts the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States and the transatlantic sphere.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Radisch. Sure.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Thanks.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Radisch. I'll say a few words about what kinds of goods, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;then maybe Stefane--if you could say how it impacts the U.S. economy, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;if you have that data stored away up here, but otherwise you'll find &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    First of all, when it comes to counterfeits, anything that can be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;counterfeited and that you can make a profit on, you're going to find &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it. It really spans the full range of harmonized system [HS] codes. But &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I think an important point here to make today is, it's not just trade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in counterfeits in free-trade zones. Now that's where we are data rich. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And of course the OECD is an organization where we want to give advice &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to governments that is evidence based; it is data driven.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We have hundreds of thousands of data points on counterfeits. Now &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that doesn't mean there isn't other types of illegal goods going &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;through these free-trade zones. It just means we have a lot less &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;evidence and data on it because really they are based on cases, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;investigations, anecdotes, our interviews, but that's not the kind of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;information that is gathered in trade data. But for example, wildlife, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;arms, money laundering operations, I think--not just in goods, but the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;illegal services going on inside the free-trade zones we have to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;aware of as well. So money laundering through illegal offshore sports &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;betting is a big area, and securities fraud--and the main point to bear &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in mind is that a free-trade zone was never supposed to be an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;``anything goes'' zone, and that is what has happened in some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;jurisdictions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    For example, a recent case in the Philippines of securities fraud &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;by--I won't mention the nationality, but they weren't from the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Philippines--had set up a boiler room inside a free-trade zone to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;commit securities fraud, defrauded many hundreds of millions--maybe I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;exaggerating--it was over a hundred million from investors in South &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Africa. And this was a group that came from a country that had already &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been investigated and arrested for securities fraud in their home &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;country. So they find a place somewhere else in the world where they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can set up shop with lax oversight and start conducting securities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fraud. So you get an idea that it's not just goods, but also services, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and that's why it's important, as our colleague from Europol mentioned, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to have different work streams to address these.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Jacobzone. We don't have information specifically on the impact &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of free-trade zones on the U.S. economy. This is something that we want &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to do in the future, which is to look at the specific impacts of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;illicit trade on the U.S. economy, both through the impact on the U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;retail market, but also the global impact on U.S. bonds.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    What is clear is that we know that as soon as the country has more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economic free-trade zones, then there is more likelihood to export &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fakes, and there are all sorts of correlations about this. So I'm bit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sorry that--you know, I would be happy to make the data I speak more--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We also have evidence that there should be some financial flows and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;illicit financial flows that are associated with free-trade zones. This &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is in the jurisdictions of another body which is not in OECD, but is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hosted also in our organization called the FATF, the Financial Action &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Task Force. So I wish they could also shed light on this point.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would also say that, from what we understand, the complexity of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the topic from a policy perspective is the fact that what many people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;call free-trade zones--it's an aggregate that covers a number of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;things. And in fact, I guess there is an Association of Free Trade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Zones in the United States. I think we met some of their people, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;many of these zones that operate within the United States, I think, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would be quite keen to undergo some controls or would be ready to not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be labeled as misuse of free-trade zones. And there are a number of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;jurisdictions around the globe which I guess would have an incentive to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not be seen as dark havens or as being singled out for conducting all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this sort of, let's say, more dirty business.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So the task ahead in the future, I think, would also be to connect &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the real trade flows and some of the illicit financial flows, which is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;something where the information is a bit patchy, to look at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;specific impact on countries and also ensure a process whereby some of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the information can be gathered.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But the report on free-trade zones, which I am happy to send--and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just had it in front of me on the screen--it takes quite a bit of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;econometrics and sophisticated data modeling to get to some of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;policy results that we have in front of you today. And as was mentioned &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;by Jack, there is also evidence that not only does this show in our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;statistics and econometrics, but this is corroborated by the experience &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of law enforcement officers whether at Europol, Interpol, our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;colleagues also at the World Customs Organization. So there is also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;qualitative evidence that is consistent with some of the empirical &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;findings that we found.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Radisch. We could say, Paul--just a last word about that--on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the basis of our reports, we know that U.S. brands are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disproportionately affected. We know that, as I mentioned--to be more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;specific, the full range of HS code goods can be found transiting, so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it's not just high-end, luxury brands--Louis Vuitton, Chanel; but those &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are definitely affected--but it's also pharmaceuticals, it's also &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;automobile parts. So do you really want to be driving around in a car &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with counterfeit parts?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    There's real public health concerns here when we're talking about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;counterfeit medicines, we're talking about counterfeit makeup that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;doesn't go through the same testing that the normal brands do and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;legitimate goods do. Even parts that are going into our critical &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;infrastructure--so everything across the spectrum can be counterfeited &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and is going to make its way through free-trade zones because--well, in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;certain respects, because of the lack of oversight.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So it's a very important gap that we need to get our minds around &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in this age of globalization that has ramped up in a way that really &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wasn't anticipated.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Jacobzone. To complement what Jack said and something that is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;quite topical for the U.S. economy today is this issue of public health &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and pharmaceuticals, I think, is a bit more acute in the United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;than in other countries. And you have also seen the opioid crisis, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there are also a range of illicit trade factors that are also at play &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in this complex. And of course free-trade zones is one of the factors &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that fuel illicit trade; not the only one, but one of the factors.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Well, could I just actually follow up on that real &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;quick with maybe just a short question, short answer, and that's, if &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the FTZs want it, and the impact is very big in the United States, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the United States is clearly strongly affected by this issue, are there &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;barriers to completing a report? Do you intend to do a report? Or are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there not resources, money, time?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Jacobzone. I don't feel we have any barriers in terms of no one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is preventing us from conducting the work. I think we have some of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;best data available. We are very grateful we are able to draw on all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the U.S. custom seizures data, all the European custom seizures data. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;The World Customs Organizations has many people, friends who have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;helped us along the way, so I think we have all the data that is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;needed. I think in that context that's helpful.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Resources are a bit of an issue because this is not such a huge &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;theme, and on the day-to-day basis this can be a bit of an issue. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;guess in order to go further in this area, what we need is the adoption &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of these guidelines and the possibility to get some teeth in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;process because once you have some teeth in the process, once you are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;able to get a process through which free-trade zones will have to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;self-certified, would have to undergo some transparency measures &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;through which countries would engage in some peer review mechanism, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;then you are going to sort of drive results and exert some pressure. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And for that we will need some form of political buy-in and support--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and I'd be happy to come back in the U.S. sometime next year once the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;guidance is adopted as a way to launch it and help set up some forces &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;behind it--because if the guidance is just a piece of paper produced by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the OECD, so what? But if on the basis of guidance there is clear &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;action by nations and by countries, and let's have measures by customs &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to target certain products or certain free-trade zones, and concerted &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;action, not just by the U.S. but also U.S. and Europe of the main &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;importance in the globe, then they will feel the pressure.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. And just to clarify, that guidance would have to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;adopted by consensus by the ambassadors of the OECD?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Jacobzone. The OECD is an international, intergovernmental &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organization, so the guidance, in our language our recommendation is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;adopted by the OECD Council, which means the ambassadors of the members &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the 34, 35 members of the OECD.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Great. Thanks so much. So I'm going to ask one more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;question, and then we'll open it to the floor.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    This one's for Dr. Fuller, and I hope I don't set you off too bad. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I was just hoping you could speak maybe a little bit to how do FTZs &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;play into authoritarian economics? How do authorization regimes view &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;FTZs, or abuse them, or use them within the context of keeping the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regime alive, pushing authoritarian influence in the world, et cetera, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;et cetera?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Fuller. Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I obviously take a more sort of academic approach to all this than &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;an enforcement or a regulatory one. But there's this great research out &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there right now that looks at world development indicators and missing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;data as data. So it looks at when countries around the world from 1980 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to 2011 did report data or didn't report aggregate data, like GDP, or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;literacy rates, and stuff like that. And it looks at it and it finds &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this difference between authoritarian and democratic countries. No &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;matter how you want to divide it up, between democracies and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;autocracies, democracies are just more transparent in the sense that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they just report more aggregate, credible economic data. And it's this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;clear trend across the board. And so knowing that research, reading &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it--this is based on formal theory, backed up by empirical evidence--it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;finds this sort of danger zone trap for authoritarian governments where &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;when they report more, this can trigger coups and all sorts of other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;things that can be bad for business and supply chains that are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;increasingly becoming more complex all over the world, which is why I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sort of look toward this promoting of looking inward at our own &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;programs and democracies around the world.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I don't have much concern about U.S.-EU cooperation. I think &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they're doing great. I mean, I'm a big fan of law enforcement--don't &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;get me wrong--but I became an academic because I don't like authority. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;So I get into this thinking of it in the fact that we don't need more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and more enforcement necessarily. What we need is to grow these zone &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;programs and to make them shining examples on the hill for the rest of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the world. So if we get more aggregate economic data for these things, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it can act as a coordination good in democracies where you have a free &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;press, free media, academics who are going to study and report on this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;stuff. This allows private actors to better shop for what zone fits &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their needs better, to locate to them, to know which ones are--because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;everybody uses this risk-based analysis for everything, in trade, in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;finance and everything. And so if there's more data out there for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;private companies and the private sector to use in making their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;decisions, this allows them to make more efficient decisions on where &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to locate, what's available to them, where to go, which in turn grows &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the economy. It grows the zone. It makes the zone more successful. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Which then, once you have that, then you can turn to the rest of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;world, in places with these dangerous zones, or zones with more bad &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;things going on into them, and then you can say, hey, look at what we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;did here, you should try it, too.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And then from a position of having these shining programs that are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;clear and transparent in the sense that they report aggregate, credible &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economic data, then you can talk to them from a better position of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;saying, well, look at what we did, and then they can do it, because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it's going to be different in every single country. Every single &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;country has different levels and different types of democracy and rule &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of law and different--other things that are going to need different--I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mean, this is the beauty of the private sector and capitalism and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;democratic capitalism that built this country and made it so powerful &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and great. And so it needs to be sort of enhanced in that way.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And these aggregate indicators are a coordination good between the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public and private sector that I feel is a great place to start, again &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because these zones are specifically geographically delineated, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;therefore, theoretically, then can be monitored by both law enforcement &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and by both the private sector as well. And so I think that's a great &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;place to start. While I think the recommendations are great and I think &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they should be adopted and that's a good start in changing norms around &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;foreign trade zones around the world, I think the more pragmatic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;approach that's going to have the biggest effect, and that's in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;national security interests of the United States and in every country &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that wants to do it, is to look at their own zone programs and look at &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ways to report better data on them.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Thanks so much, Dr. Fuller.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So first things first, let's get our own house in order, right?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Fuller. Yes.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Okay.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So just a real quick clarification question on the guidance. If the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;guidance passed, would something like FTZ guidance, where you can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;unanimously vote a country has suspicious activity, or something like &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that? And could you say a country's out of line with the guidance, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;therefore that's the teeth of FTZ, really, is the ability to issue &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these suspicious activities reports?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Radisch. At this point, the countries have to decide how they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want to follow up on what to put in place, whether it's going to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;through a process of peer reviewing, which is a standard OECD tool for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;compliance, or measuring up to what one has agreed to do. That's one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;option.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Another option is a certification regime, having firms that are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;professional in auditing going through these free-trade zones--there's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;so many of them--to see whether they are complying with a code of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conduct along the terms that have been set up--and then having that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;transparently posted, for example, on the OECD website so everyone can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;see and countries can adjust their treatment of noncompliance the way &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they think is best fit, or whether there will be some commonality &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;across the countries about what that might entail in terms of how they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;treat noncomplying jurisdictions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So those are still some of the fine points that need to be decided &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at this stage of the development of this guidance. That's on course for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a discussion over the next several months, but it's a fair point to ask &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about and it's one that the countries are debating.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Jacobzone. Jack, you were asking before why these countries set &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;up free-trade zones. And I think the fact is that if you look at many &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries that let's say do not have democratic regimes and at many &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;semi-emerging economies--they have regulatory frameworks that are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;stifling business activity, you can't get a license, you can't get your &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;business up. It's all very bad.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And so many of these countries, instead of reforming their whole &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economy in a positive way, are just taking a short cut by saying we're &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not going to change the whole thing, it's too hard, too difficult, we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want to keep control. But we just created this small island, this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thing, and there people can just do what they want so that it will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;create jobs and growth, and then we can have revenues for the State and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we don't necessarily need to make change to the rest of the economy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And generally the OECD advising--we're engaging with a number of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these emerging economies--is to help them to adapt their whole &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regulatory framework, to adapt their economy as a whole so that it can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;benefit from globalization and be improved, and not necessarily try to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;take this sort of dual approach where you don't touch the big thing and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you just allow everything in that small three things--because that's, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think, the approach that many countries have been doing as they see &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these ones as this is where you can quickly create a lot of jobs in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;some sort of an island of prosperity in economies that otherwise do not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;develop so well. I mean, I'm talking a bit generally here, but I think &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there is an aspect to this in the conversations.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And on the powers, the OECD's not FATF. So we have to be very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;clear. FATF is a very special organization that is distinct of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;OECD. Even if there are close relationships between the two &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organizations, and at the sense of OECD work, there is mutual learning &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and peer pressure, what we call the process of peer review, whereby &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries come together, discuss, and put things in the open. And as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Jack mentioned, a lot of this we are serving as a secretariat to this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organization and a lot of these decisions still have to be taken by the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;member nations.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Fuller. So I agree with that. I see that too. These are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;laboratories of experimentation in these authoritarian or, as we call &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;them, developing economies. They use these zones as a way to experiment &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with liberal policies, and we have for a long time looked at them with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the hope that somehow these authoritarian governments are going to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;magically liberalize their entire economy and their entire country.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I think we're coming to a point right now--what I've been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;writing about a lot--is to where we're starting to recognize that's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just not going to happen. They're getting the benefits out of these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;zones and out of these experiments with liberalization, and they're &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;using it to survive longer in power, to get rid of term limits, to stay &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in office power, to strengthen their own regimes--and then in some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cases, in the case of North Korea's free trades zones--threaten the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States back with the goods that they've been able to use to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;survive on.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So I would say this is where I get back to the better strategy, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think, in my opinion, while I totally respect and think what the OECD &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is doing is noble and a good cause, in my opinion I would think a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;better sort of foreign policy for the United States would be to sort of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;start disentangling with these zones and authoritarian regimes around &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the world and start focusing on the ones in more democratic countries &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that are better, again, at reporting aggregate, credible, economic data &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to their publics.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Thank you, Dr. Fuller.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And with that, we'll take some questions from the audience. Have we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;got any questions in this audience? Just raise your hand. Don't be shy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Yes, please, David. Do we have any microphones? Oh, do you mind &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;walking up to the mic, David?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    If you'd like to ask a question next, you can go ahead and walk up.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Thank you very much, Paul, and thank you, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;presenters, for their excellent briefings this afternoon.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And just building on some of the comments that we just heard on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;importance of resources, I very much also agree with Dr. Fuller. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think it is important that we build up some of the more problematic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;free-trade zones by perhaps exploring pilots with them to provide the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;type of capacities, the capabilities. And I hope that after the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;guidelines are approved by the ministers--and that's a big if--but if &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they are approved, I think as we shift toward the implementation phase, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that we begin to work within the OECD and other partners to develop the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;type of resources that I think are critical to work with our partners, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;including in Panama and others who I think are facing tremendous &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;challenges--not only on the illicit trade across the various &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;commodities that Jack mentioned, but on issues related to corruption as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;well--the issue of illicit financial flows is a critical part of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;challenge in many free-trade zones today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So the question to the OECD is, how are you working right now with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;free-trade zones in trying to enhance those type of capacities, those &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;type of capabilities? And is there any plan to develop some pilots, as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Dr. Fuller was mentioning, to support those who are committed toward &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;more transparency through greater enforcement in free-trade zones?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Please go ahead. Jack or Stephane?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Radisch. Sure. The short answer is that, David, we have invited &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;some of the well-known free-trade zones of ill repute to our meetings. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And we will continue to do so. We want to have them at the table. We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want to work closely with them in precisely the basis that you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;described. That's the most constructive way. And it's only as a second &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;order that countries would have as part of their discussion what to do &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;if that fails and what kind of pressure can be exerted to make these &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;jurisdictions, well, change their ways, change their behavior.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And there's a game plan for that as well in the OECD history, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that's the work on tax havens. So there are many ways of going about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;working with countries to effect the change that's needed, and the most &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;constructive one would definitely be working with the countries that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you mentioned yourself on a constructive basis. How can we improve upon &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the capacity to know better what's going on inside the zones and to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;weed out the criminal elements? Because everyone wants to benefit from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;trade, and the idea is that if some of these problematic jurisdictions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can clean up their ways so that will make them--really they are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;championing a different way of doing business. And that will put &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pressure on the others who are not cleaning up their act, because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;eventually, if there is pressure brought to bear from OECD countries, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;then that will affect the businesses' decisions to actually use those &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;free-trade zones or not.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Great. Okay, thanks.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Can we get another question from the public? Thanks so much.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Hi. Joe McKellen [ph] with Congressman Donovan's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;office.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    With the unfortunate departure of the U.K. from the European Union, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;do you all kind of envision any difficulties in cracking down on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;illicit trade going to and from that country?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Jacobzone. I would say to the country because the U.K.'s still &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a member of the OECD. And in fact, if the U.K. is not any more a full &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;member of the European Union, this will step up the incentives for our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.K. colleagues to achieve cooperation with other countries through the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;OECD. And we have some U.K. colleagues inside the room, and I think &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that there is a global anti-corruption effort at the OECD that is under &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the leadership of the U.K. or benefits a lot from the U.K.'s influence, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and the U.K. is strongly engaged and committed on all these fronts and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;working closely inside the OECD.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Yes, please, Dr. Fuller, yes. I mean, we have the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;British Embassy here today, so we will also have them perhaps say &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;something. And I also want to let Dr. Fuller speak, but I also want to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ask Pedro to say something, because I know a big piece of the Brexit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;debate and the international law enforcement debate is exactly how the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.K. will work with Europol following Brexit. So it's an interesting &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;question,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But, please.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Fuller. Okay, so the U.K. has actually been leading the fight &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;really on this in other ways. I don't want to speak to Brexit or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;anything like that. I want to speak to U.K.'s leadership, especially in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the area of things like beneficial ownership transparency, where they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have been sort of leading the fight on this. While I sort of disagree &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with the public reporting of private data, I do find groups that are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;analyzing the data here have come up with very useful insights that are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;good examples of this transparency and credible aggregate data that I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;talking about. For example, they've analyzed it and looked through and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;found that there's approximately 1.2 owners per business--that's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;incorporated--and that there's a certain percentage that aren't able to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;identify their number. These are good examples of aggregate data that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;allow private and public actors to coordinate their actions together, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and which spurs economic growth, because, again, this is what it's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about, in my view. There's the question of right, so, what am I talking &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about that's going to fight illicit trade? And the answer is not much. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I'm talking about drowning out illicit trade by growing licit trade. So &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it's a perceptions thing. If you grow the amount of the legal economy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;happening, then the impacts and the effects of the illicit economy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shrink relative to the size of the legal economy. And so that's what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I'm trying to make an argument for growing the legal economy and taking &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;steps toward that in order to shrink the impact of the illicit economy. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Because you're never going to get rid of bad actors. They're always &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;going to be there.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Even if they--[inaudible].&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Fuller. Exactly.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Could we hear real quick from Pedro? And then, John, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;if I could force you to the mic, if you don't mind?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Kay. Yes, sure.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Yes. [Laughs.] Okay, good.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Rodrigues. Okay, so Brexit-related questions are very frequent &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;nowadays. And, well, short answer: It remains to be seen. The U.K. is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;one of the largest, if not the largest contributor of information to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol. It's a leading force in many different crime areas, many &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different platforms. And I don't think that will change too much.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    That said, there's a couple of rules which are deeply enshrined in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol's regulation, and one of those which is very important is that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for Europol to be able to provide the full extent of support that we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;provide to our partners, the investigation in question needs to have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the involvement of at least two EU member states. So if in the past we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;could support full investigation between the U.K. and France, for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;example, now we would need the U.K., France, possibly, if negotiations &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;don't--I'm pretty sure that the U.K. will negotiate its own terms with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol. It's in everyone's best interest that the U.K. remains close &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to Europol, and I'm pretty sure that an operational agreement will be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;signed and in place. But one of the possibilities or one of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;discussions is that, for example, the U.K. would actually need two &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;additional member states in this case to be able to bring an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;investigation to Europol so it could be supported as a high priority &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;case, which means that we can devote a full range of services and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;support.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. John.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Kay. Okay, thank you for the--[inaudible]. [Laughter.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My name's John Kay. I work out of the British Embassy here in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Washington, but I'm a career U.K. customs officer. My current employer &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is HM Revenue--Her Majesty's Revenue &amp;amp; Customs. So I'm here as actually &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;one of the U.K. law enforcement liaison officers based in Washington &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;working with our partner agencies in the U.S. and other nearby &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    To echo my friend from Europol, Pedro, we do have an international &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;network of liaison officers not just in the globe but in particular in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Europol, and that will continue. The U.K. is seeking to remain a member &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Europol and will continue to have a number of agents from police, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;National Crime Agency, and HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs based in Europol.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And again, answering the question in particular, this is not a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;political question, and it's certainly not something I'm answering on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;behalf of the ambassador here for the U.K. in the U.S. But speaking as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;an HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs officer, we do value international &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;collaboration. We work bilaterally with all our colleagues in a number &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of law enforcement agencies--not just in the U.S., but globally. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the fact that we may be moving toward an EU exit next March, in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;forthcoming year, doesn't mean that we won't continue to collaborate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with law enforcement.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And especially when it comes to illicit trade, counterfeit trade, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the U.K. is absolutely committed to a level playing field for economic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prosperity for everyone. And one thing I would emphasize is just &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because the U.K. may be leaving the European Union doesn't mean that we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;don't want to take our ball home with us and go to bed. We literally do &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;want to continue to be a full member of the international economic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;community for economic prosperity, both across the globe, in Europe, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;but obviously important for the U.K. as well. And that means leveling &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that playing field, encouraging private sort of enterprise to move &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;economic goods across international boundaries. And where free-trade &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;zones are used to help prosper internationally, they should be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;obviously subject to some sort of support by domestic revenue and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;customs authorities to enable that to happen in the correct way.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Thank you very much, John.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    KAY: And finally, the only thing I would say is thank you to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;OECD for their work on this, and the U.K. continues to support your &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;activity in this regard.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Excellent. Thanks very much.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Do we have more questions from the audience? Step right up. Get &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;your exercise.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Okay. Well, I'm going to ask one more question. If there's any &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;last-minute questions after that, we can take them. Okay?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So my final question for OECD is, have you highlighted any of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;worst offenders, the worst FTZs? Can you speak to anything like that? &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[Laughs.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Jacobzone. I would say we're economists. We're not law &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;enforcement officials, so we're not treating individual cases. We are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;treating aggregated sets of data. So I think this sort of question &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;should be more directed to our colleagues in law enforcement, our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;colleague from the U.K. or from Europol, than to the OECD as an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organization, I'm afraid.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Radisch. At this point in time.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Massaro. Got it. Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Okay. If there aren't any more questions, anybody want to say &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;anything else on the panel? Then we will close the briefing.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you so much. [Applause.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    [Whereupon, at 4:07 p.m., the briefing ended.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            This is an official publication of the Commission on&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                    Security and Cooperation in Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  This publication is intended to document&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  developments and trends in participating&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  States of the Organization for Security&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                     and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE).&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;           All Commission publications may be freely reproduced,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            in any form, with appropriate credit. The Commission&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            encourages the widest possible dissemination of its&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               publications.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      www.csce.gov       @HelsinkiComm&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 The Commission's Web site provides access&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 to the latest press releases and reports,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                as well as hearings and briefings. Using the&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;         Commission's electronic subscription service, readers are&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            able to receive press releases, articles, and other&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          materials by topic or countries of particular interest.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                          Please subscribe today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;&amp;lt;/pre&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
</intro>
</Hearing>
