<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="25837">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         [H.A.S.C. No. 115-44]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                HEARING&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                   ON&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                          FOR FISCAL YEAR 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                  AND&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;              OVERSIGHT OF PREVIOUSLY AUTHORIZED PROGRAMS&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               BEFORE THE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;committee_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES&lt;/committee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             FIRST SESSION
                               __________
&lt;/option&gt;
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON MILITARY PERSONNEL HEARING&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                                   ON
              MILITARY PERSONNEL POSTURE: FISCAL YEAR 2018
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                              MAY 17, 2017
                               _________ 
                     U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
 25-837                       WASHINGTON : 2018      
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON MILITARY PERSONNEL&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                    MIKE COFFMAN, Colorado, Chairman
WALTER B. JONES, North Carolina      JACKIE SPEIER, California
BRAD R. WENSTRUP, Ohio, Vice Chair   ROBERT A. BRADY, Pennsylvania
STEVE RUSSELL, Oklahoma              NIKI TSONGAS, Massachusetts
DON BACON, Nebraska                  RUBEN GALLEGO, Arizona
MARTHA McSALLY, Arizona              CAROL SHEA-PORTER, New Hampshire
RALPH LEE ABRAHAM, Louisiana         JACKY ROSEN, Nevada
TRENT KELLY, Mississippi
               Dave Giachetti, Professional Staff Member
                Craig Greene, Professional Staff Member
                         Danielle Steitz, Clerk
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <Directory>
    &lt;table-of-content&gt;C O N T E N T S&lt;/table-of-content&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS&lt;/Speakers&gt;
</Directory>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;Subcommittee on Military Personnel.............................     1&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;Chairman&gt;
        &lt;Cname&gt;Speier&lt;/Cname&gt;
        &lt;Clocation&gt; Ranking &lt;/Clocation&gt;
    &lt;/Chairman&gt;
    &lt;people&gt;
        &lt;Pname&gt;Member&lt;/Pname&gt;
        &lt;Plocation&gt; Subcommittee on Military Personnel.....................&lt;/Plocation&gt;
    &lt;/people&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Hon Mike Coffman&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative from Colorado Chairman&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;witnesses&gt;WITNESSES&lt;/witnesses&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;LtGen Mark A Brilakis&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;USMC Deputy Commandant for Manpower and Reserve Affairs&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;VADM Robert P Burke&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;USN Chief of Naval Personnel&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Lt Gen Gina M Grosso&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;USAF Deputy Chief of Staff for Manpower&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;LTG James C McConville&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;USA Deputy Chief of Staff&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;APPENDIX&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;Prepared Statements:&lt;/Speakers&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;LtGen Mark A Burke Brilakis&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;VADM Robert P Coffman Hon Mike Grosso&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Subcommittee on Military Personnel,&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                           Washington, DC, Wednesday, May 17, 2017.
    The subcommittee met, pursuant to call, at 3:30 p.m., in 
room 2118, Rayburn House Office Building, Hon. Mike Coffman 
(chairman of the subcommittee) presiding.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;     COLORADO, CHAIRMAN, SUBCOMMITTEE ON MILITARY PERSONNEL
    Mr. Coffman. Please be seated. I want to welcome everyone 
to the Military Personnel Subcommittee's hearing on the state 
of the military service personnel systems as we enter the 
fiscal year 2018 budget season.
    Our panel of the service personnel chiefs is here to 
address each of their services' personnel postures, including 
personnel policies for recruiting and retention, family 
programs, and/or address budget and legislative requests for 
fiscal year 2018 to the extent that they can.
    Today's focus is on the personnel policies the services 
currently have to sustain and create efficiencies, which 
includes promotion policy, bonus and incentive policies, and 
end-strength changes that still need to be examined in light of 
proposed increases, and the ensuing challenges.
    I am especially interested in your plans for retention of 
the right service members that are central to your mission, in 
what may develop into difficult recruiting and retention--into 
a difficult recruiting and retention environment in the coming 
years. We would like to understand the policies and programs 
that will be used to maintain and increase personnel end 
strengths.
    Before I introduce our panel, let me offer Congresswoman 
Speier an opportunity to make any opening remarks.
    Ms. Speier.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Appendix on page 33.]
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt; CALIFORNIA, RANKING MEMBER, SUBCOMMITTEE ON MILITARY PERSONNEL
    Ms. Speier. Mr. Chairman, thank you. And thank you to all 
of our witnesses who are here today. This is a critical time to 
hear from you. The services have spent the past several years 
implementing end-strength reductions. Before we commit to 
growing the force again, we need to take a very good look 
beyond just the numbers, because for each and every new service 
member that commits to military service, we are signing the 
government up for a lifelong commitment to them as well, a 
commitment that will come with a significant cost.
    I am interested in hearing how the services are going to 
compete in an increasingly competitive labor market and retain 
the skilled individuals they invest in, while still operating 
in a constrained budget environment. In the past, recruiting 
challenges have been addressed by lowering standards, a tactic 
I do not support and presume you do not as well.
    But simply adding manpower will not address the personnel 
challenges of today and tomorrow. We also need to focus on 
retention, quality of life, and fostering the culture of 
respect for all service members. These are areas in which I 
believe current efforts are insufficient. Skilled women and men 
are abandoning the military in response to a persistent plague 
of harassment, assault, and degradation. Further cuts to family 
programs and housing allowances run counter to trends in the 
private sector, providing even more enticement to leave.
    We also need to think creatively about how the services 
manage people. I am interested in hearing how the services are 
going to transform their personnel management policies to 
better manage and retain talent. There have been many proposals 
over the past few years, and many of these initiatives can be 
accomplished internally without changes in law but will most 
likely require a cultural shift, which has always seemed to be 
the biggest challenge.
    I understand that this may be General McConville's last 
hearing as the Army's personnel chief and that he may be moving 
up. Thank you for all you have done as Army's G-1.
    And thank you, Mr. Chairman. I look forward to hearing from 
our witnesses.
    Mr. Coffman. Thank you, Ranking Member Speier.
    Let me welcome our panel:
    Lieutenant General James McConville, Deputy Chief of Staff, 
G-1, United States Army. Additionally, I would like to also 
congratulate General McConville on his nomination to be the 
United States Army Vice Chief of Staff.
    Vice Admiral Robert Burke, Chief of Naval Personnel, United 
States Navy.
    Lieutenant General Mark Brilakis, Deputy Chief of Staff for 
Manpower--I am sorry. Deputy Commandant for Manpower and 
Reserve Affairs, United States Marine Corps.
    Lieutenant General Gina Grosso, Deputy Chief of Staff for 
Manpower, Personnel and Services, United States Air Force.
    General McConville, you are now recognized for 5 minutes.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                 STAFF, G-1, UNITED STATES ARMY
    General McConville. Thank you, sir.
    Chairman Coffman, Ranking Member Speier, distinguished 
members of the committee. I would like to thank you for the 
opportunity to appear before you on behalf of the United States 
Army. I have submitted a statement for the record, but I would 
like to highlight a couple of points.
    The Army's people--our soldiers, our civilians, our 
retirees, veterans, and families--are our greatest asset. They 
are our greatest weapons system, and there is a continued need 
for a ready force, one that is fully manned, fully equipped, 
and trained, as evidenced daily by the international events. 
Predictable and timely funding are key to manning the Army and 
accomplishing our missions. We thank you for the increase in 
end strength of 28,000. That will improve our readiness and 
ensure that the Army has better manned formations.
    I want to thank you for all you have done. And as we move 
into the future--you asked about talent management--we are 
moving from a personnel management system to a modern talent 
management system that will allow us to more effectively manage 
all three components of the Army.
    Diversity is important to the Army. Through our outreach 
and marketing efforts, we are increasing the diversity of our 
force in underrepresented branches and occupations. We are 
committed to giving all soldiers the opportunity to serve in 
whatever military occupation they can meet the standards of. 
Currently, all military occupations are open to women, and 
women serve in every battalion in the Active Army.
    We remain focused on personal resiliency and suicide 
prevention with world-class programs for our soldiers, 
civilians, and families, and are aggressively working to 
decrease the stigma with seeking behavior health care.
    Sexual assault and sexual harassment have no place in our 
ranks and diminish our readiness. Our recently published 
Workplace and Gender Relations Survey of Active Duty Members 
shows a decrease in prevalence and increase in reporting, but 
there is much work to be done.
    At the end of the day, the Army's people, the men and women 
who serve our country today, along with their families, and all 
those are vital to the security of our Nation.
    I thank you for your continued support of the All-Volunteer 
Army and look forward to your questions.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;in the Appendix on page 34.]
    Mr. Coffman. Vice Admiral Burke.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                 PERSONNEL, UNITED STATES NAVY
    Admiral Burke. Chairman Coffman, Ranking Member Speier, and 
distinguished members of this committee, thank you for the 
opportunity to appear before you to discuss Navy manpower, 
personnel, training, education, and family support programs.
    I am honored to represent the men and women of the United 
States Navy. For 240 years, the Navy has been a cornerstone of 
American security and prosperity. Now more than ever, the Navy 
is important to national security and so are its people. As 
Chief of Naval Personnel, I am responsible for ensuring our 
ships, squadrons, submarines, and stations are fully manned 
with sailors who are ready to undertake the many jobs and tasks 
we ask of them. This responsibility includes finding and 
recruiting talented individuals as well as executing training 
pipelines that transform sailors into highly skilled maritime 
warriors.
    While the Navy has healthy recruiting, retention, and 
manning today, it is vital we update policies that position us 
to deal with challenges before we are confronted with a crisis. 
As with the weapons systems we use, we must continue to refresh 
our personnel system to keep pace with the rapidly changing 
world, and we must do so with a sense of urgency. Our workforce 
must be poised to adapt quickly to new and evolving threats as 
we continue to work to attract and retain the very best sailors 
in an increasingly competitive talent market.
    We will continue to evaluate our policies, practices, 
delivery systems, and when appropriate, we will pursue 
additional avenues, with your help, to improve readiness and 
also to provide sailors choice and flexibility.
    Sailor 2025 is an effort we began a few years ago and is a 
roadmap to help us do just that. Today it consists of about 45 
different initiatives aimed at modernizing our personnel 
management and training systems to more effectively recruit, 
train, and manage our force while also improving the Navy's 
warfighting readiness. At the foundation of these initiatives 
is an effort to streamline and optimize our organizational 
processes. Today, our success greatly depends upon the 
extraordinary efforts of sailors and Navy civilians working 
tirelessly to overcome an aging personnel business model in a 
noncoherent and manually intensive family of 55 personnel IT 
[information technology] systems. That is why we are 
transforming the way we operate, leveraging modern commercial 
IT capabilities and practices that will help us improve fleet 
readiness and customer service to our sailors, reducing 
operating costs and helping us to manage our organizational 
data and programs.
    Ultimately, this transformation is intended to holistically 
improve the way we manage sailors' careers and deliver 
personnel readiness to our Navy.
    I look forward to working with you as we build the Navy of 
tomorrow together, and I look forward to your questions. Thank 
you.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;the Appendix on page 47.]
    Mr. Coffman. General Brilakis.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;  FOR MANPOWER AND RESERVE AFFAIRS, UNITED STATES MARINE CORPS
    General Brilakis. Thank you.
    Chairman Coffman, Ranking Member Speier, distinguished 
members of the subcommittee, it is my privilege to appear 
before you to discuss your Marine Corps.
    Marines are the foundation of the Corps. They are the 
services' most critical resource and always will be. Your 
Marines are recruited, educated, trained, and retained to win 
our Nation's battles. Everything we do in the Marine Corps must 
contribute to their readiness and their ability to win in 
battle.
    Overall, Marine Corps recruiting and retention remains 
strong. Our recruiters continue to find high-quality men and 
women of character who want to take up the challenge to be 
United States Marines. We will make our recruiting mission this 
year, and we will have a start pool for next year above 50 
percent. Over 99 percent of those who we will ship will be tier 
1 traditional high school graduates or the equivalent.
    We thank you for the increased end-strength authorization 
in last year's NDAA [National Defense Authorization Act] that 
takes us to 185,000 in the Active Component. This increase 
serves to enable our retaining critical warfighting 
capabilities while improving information-related capabilities 
and capacities necessary in an increasingly dynamic operating 
environment.
    Along with the other services, the Marine Corps is 
diligently preparing for the new Blended Retirement System 
[BRS] that goes into effect on January 1st. This new system 
represents the most significant change in military compensation 
in many years. So the financial education of each Marine is a 
priority. To this end, we have implemented an integrated 
communications plan to increase awareness. I have personally 
discussed the BRS at major installations with our leaders and 
recently spoke to our prospective commanders course about the 
challenge of preparing over 184,000 Marines in both the Active 
and the Reserve Component for this important opt-in decision 
during 2018. We must get this right. Thereafter, we will 
closely be monitoring the BRS for any unintended consequences, 
including those affecting retention.
    Your Marines are proud of what they do. They are proud of 
the Eagle, Globe, and Anchor, and what it and each Marine 
represents to our Nation. With your continued support, a 
vibrant Marine Corps will be ready to meet our Nation's call.
    Thank you again for the opportunity to present this 
testimony, and I look forward to your questions.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;the Appendix on page 60.]
    Mr. Coffman. General Grosso.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt; FOR MANPOWER, PERSONNEL AND SERVICES, UNITED STATES AIR FORCE
    General Grosso. Chairman Coffman, Ranking Member Speier, 
and distinguished members of the subcommittee, thank you for 
the opportunity to appear before you today to deliver the Air 
Force personnel posture for fiscal year 2018.
    America's Air Force is always there, providing global 
vigilance, global reach, and global power to combatant 
commanders around the world. However, being always there comes 
at a cost to equipment, infrastructure, and, most importantly, 
our airmen. Sustained global commitments and continued 
budgetary uncertainty have diminished our ability to 
successfully balance capability, capacity, and readiness. 
Simultaneously, the Air Force experienced increased demand in 
enduring missions and growth in new mission sets such as cyber, 
remotely piloted aircraft, information surveillance and 
reconnaissance, and special operations.
    The Air Force is currently facing three distinct personnel 
challenges: first, the need for increased end strength to 
support current mission requirements; second, the national 
pilot crisis; and, finally, meeting the quality-of-life and 
quality-of-service needs of our airmen and their families.
    Our first challenge is obtaining the end strength the Air 
Force needs to support current mission requirements. We are 
grateful for the congressional support to increase fiscal year 
2017 Active Duty end-strength levels to 321,000 airmen. Even 
with this increase, Air Force readiness depends on responsible 
growth in fiscal year 2018 to a requested total force end-
strength level of 675,000 airmen. This growth is necessary to 
support current operations.
    Our second challenge is the national pilot crisis. As you 
are aware, we discussed the pilot shortage at length in our 
March 29 hearing. I would just add to that discussion that we 
are meeting with several airline senior executives tomorrow to 
seek ways to collaboratively address the national pilot 
shortage.
    The third challenge to note today is ensuring we meet the 
quality-of-life and quality-of-service needs of our airmen and 
their families. Our force readiness depends on a strong, 
resilient force. We are increasing resiliency skills programs 
by adding installation resilience trainers, evaluating military 
family needs, and ensuring airmen exposed to combat and 
traumatic events receive needed care. Unfortunately, working 
against our resiliency efforts is any form of interpersonal or 
self-directed violence, to include sexual assault and suicide. 
Any number of incidents is one too many.
    Additionally, violence is not always physical, as forms of 
violence have bled into social media. Since my testimony to 
this committee on the Air Force's social media policies, the 
chief of staff chartered a working group to evaluate the 
policies in place for appropriate conduct online and via social 
media.
    New guidance is currently in coordination. This guidance 
will be punitive and will be completed and issued in the next 
60 days.
    As we move beyond our immediate challenges, we are planning 
and preparing for the future. To do this, the Air Force 
established a comprehensive human capital strategy across six 
lines of effort to address talent planning, talent acquisition, 
talent development and utilization, talent evaluation, 
compensation and retention, and, finally, transition. Our 
talent management strategy focuses on how to best leverage the 
abilities of our total force airmen, maximize efficiencies, and 
increase human performance to produce warfighters and leaders 
for the Air Force and joint force.
    To further our status, we established a Talent Management 
Innovation Cell to rapidly identify and deploy initiatives 
within existing authorities. As this team produces policies and 
programs to better attract and retain talent, we will work with 
our service partners and the Office of the Secretary of Defense 
to present options to Congress to modify or add authorities as 
needed.
    Our talent strategy would not be possible without the 
support and authorities Congress has already given us. For 
example, we are using the Career Intermission Program authority 
to provide career flexibility to our airmen and their families. 
Additionally, the Air Force is grateful for congressional 
support in continuation of direct hire authorities to hire 
talented civilian airmen directly from our universities, expand 
the access of professionals for our depots, and increase hiring 
speed to bolster our cyber mission forces.
    We also appreciate the authority granted for expanded 
parental leave and the first aviation bonus increase in 18 
years. The increased bonus will help alleviate our pilot crisis 
by retaining more pilots after their initial Active Duty 
service commitments.
    Thank you for allowing me to cover our current personnel 
challenges today and share with you how we are preparing for 
the future. I look forward to your questions.
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
</Hearing>
