<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="33109">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;115th Congress }                            Printed for the use of the             &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;2nd Session    }      Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe                       &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;======================================================================&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	              Beyond Tolerance: Faith in&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	                the Public Square&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[GRAPHIC NOT AVAILABLE IN TIFF FORMAT]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         October 29, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                           Briefing of the&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         Washington: 2019&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;      Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  234 Ford House Office Building                                           &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   Washington, DC 20515&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      202-225-1901&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      csce@mail.house.gov&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      http://www.csce.gov&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         @HelsinkiComm&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            Legislative Branch Commissioners&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;              HOUSE				SENATE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;CHRISTOPHER H. SMITH, New Jersey 	ROGER WICKER, Mississippi,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          Co-Chairman			  Chairman&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ALCEE L. HASTINGS, Florida		BENJAMIN L. CARDIN. Maryland&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ROBERT B. ADERHOLT, Alabama		JOHN BOOZMAN, Arkansas&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;MICHAEL C. BURGESS, Texas		CORY GARDNER, Colorado&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;STEVE COHEN, Tennessee			MARCO RUBIO, Florida&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;RICHARD HUDSON, North Carolina		JEANNE SHAHEEN, New Hampshire&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;RANDY HULTGREN, Illinois		THOM TILLIS, North Carolina&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;SHEILA JACKSON LEE, Texas		TOM UDALL, New Mexico&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;GWEN MOORE, Wisconsin			SHELDON WHITEHOUSE, Rhode Island&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                Executive Branch Commissioners&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                     DEPARTMENT OF STATE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	            DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   DEPARTMENT OF COMMERCE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                           [II]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ABOUT THE ORGANIZATION FOR SECURITY AND COOPERATION IN EUROPE  &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Helsinki process, formally titled the Conference on Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe, traces its origin to the signing of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Helsinki Final Act in Finland on August 1, 1975, by the leaders of 33 &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European countries, the United States and Canada. As of January 1, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;1995, the Helsinki process was renamed the Organization for Security &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE. The membership of the OSCE has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;expanded to 56 participating States, reflecting the breakup of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Soviet Union, Czechoslovakia, and Yugoslavia.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The OSCE Secretariat is in Vienna, Austria, where weekly meetings &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the participating States' permanent representatives are held. In &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;addition, specialized seminars and meetings are convened in various &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;locations. Periodic consultations are held among Senior Officials, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Ministers and Heads of State or Government.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Although the OSCE continues to engage in standard setting in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fields of military security, economic and environmental cooperation, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and human rights and humanitarian concerns, the Organization is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;primarily focused on initiatives designed to prevent, manage and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;resolve conflict within and among the participating States. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Organization deploys numerous missions and field activities located in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Southeastern and Eastern Europe, the Caucasus, and Central Asia. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;website of the OSCE is: &amp;lt;www.osce.org&amp;gt;.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ABOUT THE COMMISSION ON SECURITY AND COOPERATION IN EUROPE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, also known as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Helsinki Commission, is a U.S. Government agency created in 1976 to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;monitor and encourage compliance by the participating States with their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;OSCE commitments, with a particular emphasis on human rights.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission consists of nine members from the United States &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Senate, nine members from the House of Representatives, and one member &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;each from the Departments of State, Defense and Commerce. The positions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Chair and Co-Chair rotate between the Senate and House every two &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;years, when a new Congress convenes. A professional staff assists the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commissioners in their work.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In fulfilling its mandate, the Commission gathers and disseminates &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relevant information to the U.S. Congress and the public by convening &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hearings, issuing reports that reflect the views of Members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission and/or its staff, and providing details about the activities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the Helsinki process and developments in OSCE participating States.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The Commission also contributes to the formulation and execution of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;U.S. policy regarding the OSCE, including through Member and staff &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participation on U.S. Delegations to OSCE meetings. Members of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission have regular contact with parliamentarians, government &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;officials, representatives of non-governmental organizations, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;private individuals from participating States. The website of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission is: &amp;lt;www.csce.gov&amp;gt;.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                [III]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                     Beyond Tolerance: Faith in&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	              the Public Square&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;		             ----------                              &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;		          October 29, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                                                  Page&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              PARTICIPANTS&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Nathaniel Hurd, Senior Policy Advisor, Commission for Security and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Cooperation in Europe................................................1&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Eric Treene, Special Counsel for Religious Discrimination, Civil &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Rights Division, U.S. Department of Justice..........................3&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Rev. Dr. Andrew Bennett, Director, Cardus Religious Freedom &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Institute, and Canada's Ambassador for Religious Freedom (2013-2016)&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;(via videoconference)................................................5&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Sophie van Bijsterveld, Senator, Dutch Parliament, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Professor of Religion, Law, and Society, Radboud University (via &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;videoconference).....................................................6&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                     Beyond Tolerance: Faith in&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;	                the Public Square&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                              ----------                              &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                            October 29, 2018&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The briefing was held at 2:30 p.m. in Room 188, Russell Senate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Office Building, Washington, DC, Nathaniel Hurd, Senior Policy Advisor, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission for Security and Cooperation in Europe, presiding.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Panelists present: Nathaniel Hurd, Senior Policy Advisor, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission for Security and Cooperation in Europe; Eric Treene, Special &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Counsel for Religious Discrimination, Civil Rights Division, U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Department of Justice; Rev. Dr. Andrew Bennett, Director, Cardus &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Religious Freedom Institute, and Canada's Ambassador for Religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Freedom (2013-2016) (via videoconference); and Dr. Sophie van &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Bijsterveld, Senator, Dutch Parliament, and Professor of Religion, Law, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Society, Radboud University (via videoconference).&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Good afternoon. On behalf of the chairman of the Helsinki &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission, Senator Roger Wicker, and our co-chairman, Congressman &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Chris Smith, welcome to this briefing on ``Beyond Tolerance: Faith in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Public Square.'' I'll be your moderator for today. My name is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Nathaniel Hurd, and I'm a senior policy advisor at the Helsinki &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Commission.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    This is a briefing on faith in the public square as a good in and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of itself, as a public good, and as the fruit of religious freedom. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Jewish communities have been part of the square of what is now the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States at least since the 1650s. This past Saturday, a man &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;targeted and killed 11 of our Jewish brothers and sisters in the Tree &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Life Synagogue in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Last night, on National &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Public Radio, the executive editor of the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;David Shribman, remarked, ``I sometimes say that this is the only &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;community I've ever lived in in which the people who aren't Jews &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;actually pronounce the Yiddish words correctly.'' Such fraternity &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reflects one of the most important exhortations in American history.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    On August 18th, 1790, George Washington visited the Touro Synagogue &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Newport, Rhode Island. Later that day, he wrote a letter to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;congregants entitled, ``To the Hebrew congregation in Newport, Rhode &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Island.'' He ended his letter with these words: ``May the children of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Stock of Abraham, who dwell in this land, continue to merit and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;enjoy the good will of the other inhabitants; while everyone shall sit &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in safety under his own vine and fig tree, and there shall be none to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;make him afraid. May the father of all mercies scatter light and not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;darkness in our paths, and make us all in our several vocations useful &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;here, and in his own due time and way everlastingly happy.'' Words that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I hope will guide us as a country, including the local community of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Pittsburgh, in the coming weeks and months.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I will now introduce our panelists in the order in which they will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;speak. Eric Treene, to my left, is special counsel for religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;discrimination at the U.S. Department of Justice's Civil Rights &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Division. He oversees the Civil Rights Division's religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;discrimination enforcement, outreach, and policy efforts. Mr. Treene &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also coordinates outreach to religious communities and the department's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;outreach efforts to the Muslim, Arab, Sikh, and South Asian communities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regarding post-9/11 discrimination and hate crimes. Before joining the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Department of Justice in 2002, he was director of litigation at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Becket Fund for Religious Liberty, where he represented Christians, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Muslims, Jews, Sikhs, Buddhists, and Native Americans in a wide range &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of discrimination cases. Mr. Treene received his Bachelor of Arts in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;political science from Amherst College and his law degree from Harvard &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Law School. He was a law clerk to Judge John Walker, Jr. of the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit. Mr. Treene is the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;author of a number of articles and a contributor to two books on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;constitutional law and civil rights.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Welcome.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. The Reverend Dr. Andrew Bennett is program director for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Cardus Law. He is an ordained deacon in the Ukrainian Greek Catholic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Church in the Eparchy, or diocese, of Toronto and eastern Canada. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Father Deacon Andrew served as Canada's first Ambassador for Religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Freedom and head of the Office of Religious Freedom from 2013-2016. He &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;simultaneously served as Canada's head of delegation to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;International Holocaust Remembrance Alliance, a 31-country body which &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;leads international efforts in Holocaust education, research, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;remembrance. Father Deacon Andrew holds degrees in history from McGill &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Dalhousie Universities. He received his Ph.D. in politics from the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;University of Edinburgh. And on a personal note, he and I have actually &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;known each other since 1997, when he was a precocious Ph.D. student and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I was a study-abroad student and actually had hair. [Laughter.] So this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is in many respects a continuation of the conversation that we were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;having even back then.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Welcome, Father Deacon.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Sophie van Bijsterveld joins us from the Netherlands to reflect &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on the subject in a Western European context. She graduated in law from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the University of Utrecht and received a doctorate in law from Tilburg &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;University. Since September 2014, she has been professor of religion, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;law, and society at Radboud University. Dr. van Bijsterveld has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;lectured and published extensively in the fields of international human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rights protection, religious liberty, constitutional law, and hybrid &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governance. Her books include ``The Empty Throne: Democracy and the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Rule of Law in Transition.'' Her latest book is ``State and Religion: &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Reassessing a Mutual Relationship.'' Since 2007, she has been a senator &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the Dutch upper house of Parliament for the Christian Democratic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Party. From 2008 to 2015, Dr. von Bijsterveld was a member of the board &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the scientific institute for the Christian Democratic Party. She was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also a founding editor of the Dutch Journal of Religion, Law and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Policy. I should note that there's a 6-hour time difference between us &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and the Netherlands, so she's joining us at 8:30 at night. We're &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;especially grateful that she's with us.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Senior Counsel Treene.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Well, thank you very much. Like Americans everywhere &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and people around the world, I am grieving today the horrific killing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at the Tree of Life Synagogue. And my thoughts and prayers are with the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;victims and their families. And 11 killed, six injured. And the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Department of Justice--the attorney general spoke about, quite &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;forcefully, hatred and violence on the basis of religion could have no &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;place in our society. And he said every American has the right to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;attend their house of worship in safety. We are saddened by this. We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are also resolute to pursue this hate crime. And charges have been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;brought. We've been very active in religious hate crimes against all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Two weeks ago we had a man sentenced to 24 \1/2\ years in prison &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for--a Texas man--for arson in a mosque in Victoria, Texas. We've been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very aggressive. And the attorney general has been quite forthright &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about the importance of prosecuting hate crimes as part of religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;liberty.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Normally we think of religious liberty as the right of people as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;against the state. You're free from infringement by the state. But the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;attorney general, speaking to the Union of Orthodox Jewish &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Congregations of America back in June said religious freedom means not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;only freedom from government intrusion, but also freedom from violence. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;The first civil right is the right to be safe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The idea that we have religious freedom is one of our greatest &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;treasures in America. We speak of it as our first freedom. It's the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;first right listed in the Bill of Rights. It's foundational to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;right of conscience and our other freedoms. But I think the attorney &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;general is acknowledging that this right will mean very little if we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;don't have the right to be safe in our places of worship, to worship as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we see fit, to walk down the street without fear of attack because of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;what we believe and how we express that. So we stand with the people of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Tree of Life Synagogue and all Americans.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Religious freedom is the first freedom, as I mentioned. Nathaniel &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mentioned the letter to the Touro Synagogue, which was a community of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Jews developed there in the late 1600s to bring their faith, to do what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;many Christian sects were doing, to see in a new land a place where &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they could worship freely. President Washington in his letter--I want &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to use it as a framework of what I want to talk about--he said, ``It is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;now no more that toleration is spoken of, as if it were the indulgence &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of one class of people, that another enjoyed the exercise of their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inherent natural rights. For happily the Government of the United &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;States, which gives to bigotry no sanction, to persecution no &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;assistance requires only that they who live under its protection should &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;demean themselves as good citizens . . . ''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    This letter was pivotal for two reasons. One, it was the nature of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the right that it was inalienable, it was an inherent right. It wasn't &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a gift from the government to the people. It was something that the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Jews of Newport, of the Baptists of Virginia, that they had as an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inherent right. The second part is that it was a principle applied to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;everybody--to not only the Christian sects that were multiplying in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States at the time, but people of all faiths. President Trump &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has followed other recent presidents in proclaiming January 16th as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Religious Freedom Day. It's a day we celebrate at the national level &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and a kind of obscure event. It's the passage of the Virginia Statute &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Religious Freedom.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Why is a state statute so important? One, it was penned by Thomas &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Jefferson, who wrote the Declaration of Independence. But it also is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;important because it lays out the framework in three ways for religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;liberty in America, that President Washington also touched on in his &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;letter to the Hebrew congregation in Newport. First, the preamble. He &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;says, ``God has created the mind free.'' And therefore, any &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;interference with freedom, and with conscience, is not only something &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that is, as he said, meanness and hypocrisy for the government to try &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to punish such things, but it is an affront to the natural order.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Second, Jefferson said in the Virginia statute that ``no man shall &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be compelled to frequent or support any religious worship, place, or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ministry,'' nor ``suffer on account of his religious opinions or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;belief.'' So it has a duality to it. You can't be forced against your &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conscience to support a faith. That's what we are familiar with as the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;establishment clause of the Constitution. But also, you can't suffer on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;account of your opinion and belief under your conscience. And that's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;free exercise.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And Jefferson had a third section saying that we know we're just &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;passing a statute, but if some future legislature were to take it away, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they could. They have the right. But they would be wrong in doing so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because this is an inherent right that no one should be taking away. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And looking back on this, someone said, oh, wasn't this wonderful? &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Thomas Jefferson, you created freedom for the Christians of Virginia. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And he said, no, no, this wasn't about Christians. And he specifically &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mentions Hindus, Muslims, and Jews as all enjoying the protection. So &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there are two key takeaways. One is religious liberty is a fundamental &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;right, not a gift from the state. Second, the protection of conscience &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is at the very core of this right. And, third, that it applies to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;everybody.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, when you look out in the world, there are three different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;approaches to religious--this is very, very rough--but the way I see &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it, it breaks into sort of three categories. There's theocracy. It can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be sort of rigid where, you know, religion controls everything. It can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be the milder theocracy of Britain in the 1700s, where you could be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;punished for working on the Sabbath and you had to worship at certain &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;times and so forth, sort of a milder theocracy. But that's a theocratic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;view. There's sort of a secularism that governments should ensure a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;secular public order. That's what you see in France, where laicite is a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;high value.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And then there's a third vision, which I think Jefferson was laying &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;out, which is a pluralistic vision, where religion is something the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government will stay out. It will not become overbearing in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious sphere and endorse one religion at the expense of others. But &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at the same time, the government will create room for religion, will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;make space for religion to flourish. So in schools, you don't have the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;teacher leading the class in prayer, but on the other hand you protect &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;students' rights to gather. And we brought a case in the Department of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Justice where kids were not allowed to gather for prayers at lunchtime &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in a small group.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So this is sort of the model. We're trying to keep introductions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;brief, but I'll get into as we go along with your questions how we're &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;implementing this through the civil rights laws that we enforce--the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hate crime laws, but also the law to allow places of worship to build &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;students' rights of religious expression, people's ability in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;workplace to have their religion accommodated so they don't have to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;choose between their livelihood and their faith. With that, I look &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;forward to what our other panelists have to say.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Father Deacon Andrew.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Rev. Bennett. Thank you very much. I'd like to focus my talk on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;related rights of freedom of religion and conscience and view them from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;my perspective as Canada's first Ambassador for Religious Freedom &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;between 2013 and 2016, and now as Director of Cardus Religious Freedom &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Institute, which seeks to educate and advocate for religious freedom &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and conscience rights. And I also understand these rights as a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Catholic, and so view it through the lens of the Catholic tradition, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rooted in incarnational anthropology.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We find in section two of the Canadian Charter of Rights and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Freedoms embedded in the Constitutional Act of 1982 enumeration of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fundamental freedoms, the equivalent of the inalienable rights of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;American Bill of Rights. It's neither whimsy nor accidental that the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;first fundamental freedom is freedom of conscience and religion. We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bind them together in the Canadian Charter. If we're to share a common &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;life in Canada, or anywhere else for that matter, robust freedom of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religion and conscience must be affirmed and upheld. It is the freedom &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that enables us to live fully as we are, and as we are called to do.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Freedom of religion bears witness to the truth that human beings &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;desire to make sense of our world and to encounter the divine. Unlike &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the freedoms that relate to public action--such as freedom of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;expression, freedom of association, freedom of assembly--to which it is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bound, freedom of conscience and religion addresses what Professor &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Rabbi David Novak of the University of Toronto has referred to as the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;``metaphysical need of the human person.'' In this sense, religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;freedom can perhaps be more fully defined beyond international human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rights covenants, beyond simply the Bill of Rights or the Canadian &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Charter of Rights as having the initial freedom to contemplate the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;metaphysical and--[audio break]--just who am I? Who am I in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relationship to you? Who am I in relationship to the world in which I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;live? And who am I in relationship to God to a particular philosophy to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which I elect to subscribe and follow?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thought necessarily precedes action. In a religious way, freedom of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conscience does not necessarily relate to theological or creedal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;statements, but rather to the inherent human freedom to believe and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;assert certain truths. For example, that medical-assisted suicide is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wrong, a belief that is not necessarily dependent on confessing a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;particular religious faith. It can come from a humanistic view. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;frequent and mistaken post-modern assumption gaining currency in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;certain quarters, including in Canada, is that freedom of religion or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conscience can be relegated in favor of upholding a broader freedom of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;expression of association. To diminish the defense of religious freedom &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conscience rights this way, I would argue, is a symptom of an amnesia--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;an amnesia that is increasingly forgetful of who we are as human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;beings, forgetful of our deepest longings, and of our true dignity.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The ability to freely, publicly and privately act upon this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;metaphysical need that I talked about is foundational to our democracy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and foundational to our common life together. Without the guarantee of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this freedom, we are no less free in our interior life, but when &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;freedom of conscience and religion is threatened or ignored, our public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;common living out of our lives of faith can be undermined, sometimes &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;gravely. So in a truly pluralist democracy, acceptance of difference &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;must include the right to hold different theological and different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ethical and moral positions, even when they go against the prevailing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;spirit of our age. So long as these views are held and advanced &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;peacefully and do not advocate physical violence that would violate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;human dignity, they must be allowed to inhabit the public space.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We must reject what I would label an ``illiberal totalitarianism'' &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the public square that seeks to establish socially correct and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;acceptable beliefs, treating any peacefully contrary view as deviant &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and something to be silenced. There must be no totalitarianism of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;accepted belief or accepted opinion in a pluralistic democracy such as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Canada or the United States. A true pluralism must embrace and enable &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;difference, but not simply a subset of differences that may be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;permitted at a moment by a given set of beliefs at a given moment in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our history. This, I would argue, is illiberal pluralism that embraces &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a cultish secularism where the state imposes values and dictates what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious beliefs are publicly permissible. The freedom to practice &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;one's deeply held religious faith and hold positions of conscience in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the public square is a freedom that implicitly advances and supports &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;true pluralism.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    To champion religious freedom, and also conscience rights, is to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also implicitly accept that there are those in our common life who will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hold beliefs, theological and philosophical and moral, that many of us &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;will vehemently reject. And that's okay. If people in our society, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;whether they be Muslims, Christians, Sikhs, or Jews, or people of no &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious faith, are constrained in their faith through practice and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;how that faith informs their conscience, and profoundly shapes their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understanding of the human person, they will become increasingly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;marginalized and our society increasingly atomized.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    In building our common life and maintaining the public square, we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;must champion human flourishing as the common good so that our fellow &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;human beings may flourish and be able to live their lives of faith &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fully--both privately and publicly. Increasingly in Canada, there are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;growing and persistent challenges to the inherent freedom of conscience &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and religion. These challenges come from our secular institutions--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;legislative, administrative, and judicial--from the overstepping and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;infringing on Canadians' freedom in this regard. Again, a freedom that, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as our first presenter noted, is not the gift of the state, but rather &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a freedom that we bear in virtue of being human beings.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So in conclusion, in recent years there have been encroachments by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a self-proclaimed ``neutral secular order'' to advance a rival secular &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;democracy, intolerant of genuine diversity. There have also been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;statutory and regulatory actions taken to constrain freedom of religion &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and conscience at both the federal and municipal levels. Some of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;most notable cases include the 2018 Canada Summer Jobs Attestation, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;2018 Supreme Court of Canada decisions in the Trinity Western Law &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;School case, and the Wall case, the bubble zone legislation in Ontario, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and the violation of conscience rights by the College of Physicians and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Surgeons of Ontario. And I am happy to speak to some of these cases in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;greater detail in response to questions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Thank you, Father Deacon.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. van Bijsterveld.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. van Bijsterveld. Thank you very much. It is a great honor to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participate in this meeting. And I thank the Helsinki Commission very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;much for inviting me.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My presentation focuses on Western European developments, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;certainly religious freedom and the place of religion in the public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;square. And I will approach this topic first by outlining some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;characteristics of the debates and, second, I will sketch some public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;responses toward the current challenges. I will start with some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;preliminary remarks and I will close with a few personal observations.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Three preliminary remarks. The first: 57 countries, including the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States, Canada, and all the countries of Europe, are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participating states of the Organization for Security and Cooperation &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in Europe (OSCE). The relations between state, society, and religion &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;differ from country to country. This is also true for the part of this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;region that is formed by Western Europe. Over the centuries, different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;political realities, differences in religious makeup of the society, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;differences in interrelation between secular and ecclesiastical &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;authorities and historical facts all have had an impact on what we now &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;call the place of religion in the public square.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My second remark--in the OSCE context, the notions of ``respect'' &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and ``tolerance'' are often featured. However positive these notions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;appear, their meaning is not always clear or even defined. Where &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;``respect'' is concerned, the distinction must be made, in my view, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;between persons on the one hand and views and actions on the other. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;person deserves respect as a person. But views and actions, not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;necessarily so. And as of ``tolerance,'' I prefer to speak in terms of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;liberty and restrictions to liberty when possible. Either persons enjoy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;liberty or they do not, in which case there must be valid reasons to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;legitimize restrictions. Alternatively, one could speak in terms of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;equal treatment or non-discrimination.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My third remark--the word ``secularism'' often features in debates &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on religion in the public square. And this word can have different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;meanings as various authors also realize. In the words of the former &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Archbishop of Canterbury, Rowan Williams, it can refer to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;``programmatic secularism'' or ``procedural secularism.'' In this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;realm, programmatic secularism stands for fending off manifestations of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religion in the public square and procedural secularism is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fundamentally open to manifestations of religion--the state, itself, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;being secular. In a given context, it's important the use of secularism &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is clear.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, for my preliminary remarks: I now come to the general &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;characteristics of the debates. Three general characteristics mark the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;current debates. The first is the nature of the issues. In the roughly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;200 years of modern debates on religion in the public square and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;freedom of religion in Western European countries, various periods can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be discerned. In previous periods, the focus was of institutional &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;competences between church and state, or accommodation of religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;social activities in the framework of the emerging welfare state. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;current issues of contention mostly concern values--which values are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;being expressed or promoted through religion, and how much liberty do &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they deserve?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Second, there is a transnational dimension of many issues &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;concerning religion. During the 20th century, religious issues were by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and large purely domestic issues. Currently, these issues are often &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;connected to controversial societal contexts as immigration, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;integration, foreign influencing, and radicalization. And as a result, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the debates are often conducted in terms of limitations of liberty &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rather than liberty.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Third, over the last decades, religion has increasingly become &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;experienced as a purely private matter, and religious liberty as an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;individual personal liberty. The current issues of controversy, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;however, have once again fostered an awareness of the societal and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public dimensions of religion. This rediscovery also has positive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sides. In many Western European countries, functional welfare states &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have felt overburdened and religion is retreating somewhat from the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;social domain, notably financially. And this goes hand-in-hand with the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;renewed positive valuation of the social functions of religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organizations. New forms of contact, and cooperation, and coordination &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;between such organizations and, notably, local authorities take place.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I now come to my next point--public responses toward current &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;challenges. And, again, I make three observations.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    First, Americans scholars or academics observe a trend that legal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;issues concerning religion are seen through the lens of equal treatment &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rather than religious liberty. Insofar as individuals are concerned, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this resonates with experiences in Western Europe for the same reasons &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as have been mentioned. And for institutional liberty basis, it is less &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;self-evident.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Second, legal and political responses to religious diversification &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;may rely on basic instincts of traditional church-state systems. Thus, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;France continues to bar visible signs of religion in the public sphere, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;whereas, for example, in Italy Catholicism may function as a symbolic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;focal point, the crucifix in the public classroom being an example. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;other countries experience more of a dilemma.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Third, the European Court of Human Rights tends to leave national &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;states some room for maneuver in finding a right balance with regard to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;these issues. Although the Court is sometimes criticized for this, one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;must realize--especially in the United States--that this is a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;supranational court that deals with countries with a variety of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different starting points where the place of religion in the public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;domain is concerned. And there are many issues that are controversial &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the various states as well.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Finally, a few personal observations. First, it is unavoidable that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious issues tend to be assessed through the lens of equality &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rather than liberty. However, the one should not replace the other. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Furthermore, equal treatment applies in equal circumstances. And equal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;treatment therefore is not necessarily identical treatment. Second, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;restrictions to religious liberty may be necessary. However, applying &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;general solutions to a specific problem must be avoided. Legislation, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;therefore, is not always the most fruitful response to an issue.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And third, and last, the development of a relaxed attitude of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public authorities toward religion begins with a basic familiarity with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;concrete religious traditions and denominations. For both public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;authorities and religious communities, it is important to get to know &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;each other, if they do not already. Thank you for your attention.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Thank you. We'll now have a period of sort of a moderated &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Q&amp;amp;A. So I'll be asking the panelists some questions. Once that's done, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we'll open it up to questions from you who are here in the room, as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;well as those of you that are watching online on Facebook. For those of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you in the room, if you could use the standing microphone and identify &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;yourself when it's time for that Q&amp;amp;A period.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Just a note about the context of my questions: A lot of the debates &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and discussions about this topic often are mostly restricted to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;questions about law and public policy. And unfortunately, there aren't &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;enough discussions about people's first principles, about their basic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;assumptions, about distinctions between different kind of categories &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and words, et cetera. So a lot of my questions are intended to tease &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that out of our panelists.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My first line of questions is going to focus on philosophy. I think &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;philosophy can be one of those subjects that's easy to have a go at. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Seems to be somewhat impractical. But the fact is that all of us have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;existential questions, metaphysical questions that tug on the human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;heart. And Father Deacon Andrew highlighted some of them.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Philosophy actually helps us to seek and receive answers to some of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;those questions. I think it's also worth noting that how we view the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;world, our ideas-in this modern, contemporary setting--are often not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;entirely new. They have roots in earlier times and in earlier ages. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;philosophy can help us trace back those roots.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    A lot of the discussions and debates about faith in the public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;square intersect with broader debates about the very nature of truth. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Does truth exist? Is it objective? Does it exist outside of us? Is it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;something that we can know and access, or is it something that we at &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the individual level just sort of generate and create, or is it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;something that we can actually receive? What we're discussing now &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reflects in many respects philosophical shifts. In particular, from the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Medieval period to the period of the Renaissance, and then forthgoing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the period of the Enlightenment and its sort of philosophical &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;successors. In particular, I'm thinking of Descartes.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And so my first set of questions are in particular for Father &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Deacon Andrew and Dr. van Bijsterveld. What is the philosophical &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;lineage about some of the contemporary skepticism that we see about &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;truth as something that's objective, as existing outside of us, as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;something that is accessible and knowable, evidenced in ordinary human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;experience, and received rather than self-created?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And then for Mr. Treene, if you could say a word or two about the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;philosophical lineage of faith in the public square and the religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;freedom that enables it, that we can see in the founding documents in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the United States? And then I'll ask you to go into a more provocative &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;area, which is as you look at faith in the public square now, basic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;discussions about religious freedom, and reflect on our founding &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;documents, do you think that there were any philosophical presumptions &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that the founders made, perhaps unintentionally, that have sort of led &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to some of the challenges that we see today?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We'll start with Father Deacon Andrew and Dr. van Bijsterveld.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Rev. Bennett. Well, thank you very much. That's certainly a very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;big question about, theological--[inaudible]--traditional &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understandings of truth as being objective and universal. Our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understanding of fundamental freedoms--such as freedom of religion, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;freedom of conscience--certainly in Western democracies derives &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;directly from the Judeo-Christian understanding of the human being, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;human person, and the human person's relationship to an existential &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reality, metaphysical reality, their relationship to God.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So this understanding of truth is definitely something that exists &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in and of itself. It is something that exists in and of itself, and it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is beyond us in a certain sense, but also accessible by us because we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;believe that certainly as Christians, and as Jews, and some other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;faiths as well, that truth is revealed to us. So we have a particular &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understanding of revelation and that core understanding of revealed &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;truth as objective and universal. Certainly from the Christian &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;perspective, we understand that truth is not a particular philosophy or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a particular abstraction but rather it's a person. It's the person of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Jesus Christ. And so we have that understanding as Christians that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;truth is a person with whom you have a relationship. And you have a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relationship with, and that grows as you enter more fully into that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;truth.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So that understanding of truth certainly is implicit within our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understanding of fundamental freedoms, because there's this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understanding that we have these freedoms by virtue of being human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;beings. And because we are human beings, created in the image and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;likeness of God, there is a certain dignity that we have. Now, it's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;important, I think, in these days to sort of unpack what we mean by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;human dignity, because human dignity now often has a very different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;meaning or is construed in different ways--as are other terms such as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;compassion and even truth itself. But from my perspective, that would &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be how I would respond to your question, Nathaniel.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. And Dr. van Bijsterveld?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. van Bijsterveld. Yes. Thank you. Well, I find your basic first &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;question quite hard to answer. What I could say is this: At a time when &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Western European countries' freedom of religion was first incorporated &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the constitutions, we see that in a context of societies that are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;thoroughly Christian, whatever sort of divisions or predominance of a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;particular religion there may be. What we see, of course, now is that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;freedom of religion functions in a much more secularized context, and a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;context where diversity has gained a different meaning. And it's clear &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that those differences over time may also influence the interpretation &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of religious freedom, or at least can understand that there will be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;debate about what religious freedom actually means.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Yes. And to respond to something that Dr. van &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Bijsterveld said in her opening remarks, where she mentioned in U.S. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;law things have moved from religious liberty more toward equal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;treatment, I would say in some respects that I would agree with that. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;But both of these have roots with the founders. The founders, as I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mentioned, looked at equal treatment of all persons regardless of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religion, as well as this idea of conscience being precedent to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;demands of the state. And if you look at the law, there have been a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;number of decisions that have moved the ball in religious liberty by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;using equal treatment paradigms. Most recently Trinity Lutheran, saying &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;if you have a program giving playground equipment--here, it was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;actually the rubber surface so that the kids don't get injured on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;playground--you had to treat churches equally. Same thing with the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;school choice decisions. If you give out a scholarship to parents you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;can't discriminate. Parents are able to use those at the school of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their choice. Same thing in free speech cases. If there's a forum for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;speech, you can't exclude religious speech.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, the law has moved in that direction, but all of those have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been five-four decisions, six-three decisions on our Supreme Court. I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think it's worth nothing that if you look at the unanimous decisions in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the religious liberty space, they've all been pure religious liberty &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cases. Most recently Hosanna-Tabor case, where a church wanted to hire &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ministers, even where that conflicted with non-discrimination laws, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;state had to keep its hands off, that there was something precious and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different about religious liberty, that a church must be allowed to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;decide who its leaders will be. That was a unanimous decision.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Then we have decisions interpreting some statutes, like the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Religious Freedom and Restoration Act. Unanimously, the Supreme Court &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;held you can't prosecute somebody who has a sincere belief in using a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;hallucinogenic tea, in the Gonzales case. And then you have the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prisoner case involving a Muslim prisoner under a statute here we have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that protects prisoner and religious rights, that a prisoner had a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;right to wear a beard, even though it wasn't an equality argument. It &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was a pure conscience versus the state argument. So I just think it's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;interesting that those three pure religious liberty cases were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;unanimous Supreme Court decisions, and the equality cases--while there &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are more of them and they have been moving in that equality direction, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;were more split in the court.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. There have been several references today to the subject &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of secularism. Father Deacon Andrew, you referred to a ``self-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;proclaimed neutral secular order'' that has limited conscience rights &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the medical and legal profession in order to advance a prevailing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;secular orthodoxy, intolerant in genuine diversity. So just two quick &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;questions for you, and then after you've answered----&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Hope. Nathaniel, we've lost them.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Ah.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Hope. They'll be back, but you may want to----&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Let me move then onto the intersection between faith in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the public square and social change movements--something of great &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;significance here in the United States. Just an observation first. Many &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;champions of the abolition of slavery, suffrage for women, and civil &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rights for African Americans were explicitly animated by their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious faith. It is rare to encounter contemporary criticisms of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;faith in the public square in these specific contexts. General organs &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as well as legal, policy, and cultural challenges against faith in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public square most often seem to arise when people of faith are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;advocating for something specific with which the critic disagrees. I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wondering if you might be able to say a few words maybe elaborating a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bit on the intersection between social change movements, the role that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;faith played in those, and then these discussions and debates that we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have more broadly about faith in the public square, and whether or not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;you would concur that there may be a bit of inconsistency about the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;criticism.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Well, I would say that coming from the civil rights &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;division, where we just celebrated our anniversary--we were founded in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;1958, so we had our 60th anniversary. We focused on our history, and we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;looked at Martin Luther King, who, A, was animated by faith. And I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think that's what you're getting at. But also, he was imprisoned. His &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;supporters had charges filed against them for disturbing the peace. He &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;had a vision that conflicted with some of the mores and standards of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the time and it was jarring. I'm always struck to look back, when we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ask this question of just how critical his faith was to his movement, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and also how much resistance he got. In retrospect Bill Nye said, Oh, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;yes, Martin Luther King, that's the paradigm of faith in the public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;square. But it was tumultuous at the time. And you can't get around &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Looking at some of the debates and discussions today &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about a whole range of questions, ranging from immigration, to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;abortion, and everything in between, again this impression that some of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;us have that when people of faith bring their faith to the public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;square in a way that, when it comes to questions of law or policy, you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;happen to agree with, that often seems to be welcome, whereas where &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there's a point of disagreement, there's a bit of a pushback. Would you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;say that's a fair characterization?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Yes. And I think the Martin Luther King example &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;exemplifies that. I'd be curious to see what Dr. van Bijsterveld sees &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as the Dutch--is she still on, or is just us?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. It's just us.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. It's just us. [Laughter.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Ms. Hope. We're trying to get them back.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. About just over a year ago there was an article published &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the online publication Public Discourse. And it was authored by a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;professor, Dr. Margaret McCarthy. She teaches at the John Paul II &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Institute for Studies on Marriage and Family here in Washington at The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Catholic University of America. To sort of summarize her argument, she &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was certainly sympathetic to why advocates for faith in the public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;square, in particular advocates for the religious freedom that enables &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;faith in the public square, were primarily emphasizing and appealing to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their sincerely held beliefs. She made explicit reference to our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;founding documents, to law, et cetera, et cetera.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And you know, a lot of case law that relates to this very much &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;centers on that particular phrase. But her caution was that to people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that may hold a different point of view about faith more generally, or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at least faith in the public square, this may be something that's hard &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for them to understand.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    She said, ``We ought to be aware of the cost we incur by appealing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on such grounds. For reasons pertaining to the kind of religion that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has dominated the American landscape and the narrow and reductive &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;parameters of public reason in the liberal order, whatever we seek to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;defend in virtue of religious freedom [or the rights of conscience] &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;will be invariably consigned to the realm of the private and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;`personal,' which is to say, the utterly irrational. To see this, one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;need only consider what it would mean for science were scientists to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;insist on the `freedom of their science' or to appeal to their &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;`sincerely held beliefs about gravity.' Without diminishing the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;importance of the fight to keep culture-forming institutions open, it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;would be a Pyrrhic victory if success in the legal arena came at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cost of vindicating the view that a person's religion is essentially &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;`nobody else's business.' '' And then she goes on to conclude, `` &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;`Sincerely held beliefs' currently in question are not sincerely held &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;beliefs at all, however much they have been privatized for their own &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;safety. Rather, they are rational judgments about the nature of things, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;things that bear immediately on social and public life.''&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    She's proposing that maybe there's a bit of a tension when one &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;looks in sort of a legal sphere and when one looks more broadly to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public square, the debate, the discussion of ideas, culture, society, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;et cetera. As somebody who has been working on these things for a very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;long time, particularly in the legal space, would you say this is sort &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of a reasonable characterization of a tension? Does this tension exist? &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And what are the implications if there is a desire to ensure that there &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is, in the eyes of the law, a legal space for faith in the public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;square, but at the same time not sort of conceding the privatization of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religion. How do you sort of square that tension, if it does exist?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Well, I guess I would answer it in my role, which is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;someone at the Department of Justice. We're not concerned with what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;arguments are listened to, right? So it's for the legislators to decide &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;what to listen to. It's for people in the public arena, writers, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all this to hear thoughts and decide what's good and what's not. But &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our role is to protect the fundamental rights. And we do that. We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;brought a case on behalf of a student in Georgia Gwinnett University &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;who was told he could not proselytize on campus. He was confined to a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;narrow free speech zone. That free speech zone actually was between the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;dormitories and the classrooms and the rest of the facilities. This was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;primarily a commuter college. Basically they were saying, you can talk &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to 20 percent of the students, but the rest of them you've got no &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;chance of talking to.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So we're defending their right to put forth their arguments. That's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;what the Constitution provides, various Federal laws provide. And &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that's really our role. As far as which arguments are going to be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;listened to and so forth, I'm going to leave that for other folks.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. One other question before we turn to the audience. I have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a whole line of questions for our other panelists, and hopefully &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they'll be able to rejoin us. You sort of touch briefly on these three &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;models of governance, if you will--theocracy, secularism, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pluralism. I appreciate the fact that you're trying to sort of stay &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;within time, but I'm wondering if you could sort of unpack those a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;little bit more. And in particular, I'm wondering if you could walk us &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;through how you understand the distinction sort of between secularism &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and pluralism.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Right. And I mentioned laicite, which is the French &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;model, which is the public square should be secular. So, for example, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;barring girls from wearing religious clothing, the head scarves, hijab. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;We at Department of Justice went to court to protect a girl's right to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wear a head scarf to school. The idea that the government shouldn't be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the business of making religious choices for people, but the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government on the other hand should protect people's religious choices, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;should make space for them, so that when you go forth into a job, into &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a school, you don't have to leave that facet of your character behind. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;You can bring it with you, without offending the idea that we're going &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to be a country that doesn't establish one religion, that people can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;bring their religions with them, participate in public life, try to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;convince others share their faith with others.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, around a water cooler, if someone says, ``I don't want to hear &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;any more about gun control,'' or whatever, pick your hot issue, you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;respect it, okay. You can step back. The same thing with religion. You &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shouldn't be overbearing with it. But you certainly should be able to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;share it with other people. That's the idea in a pluralistic model.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. While we wait for our other panelists to come back, I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;presuming there are some questions from the audience. As you can see, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there's a standing mic right there. If you have a question, if you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;could please identify yourself by name and by organization as well.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. The monitor's dead.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Yes, I know. [Laughter.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Good afternoon. My name is Joe Ramallo. I'm an intern &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for Congressman Leonard Lance over on the House side.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I had a question today for you, Mr. Treene. Well, thanks for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;being here. But Mr. Hurd had asked a question early on in regard to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;some assumptions that the founding fathers, the framers of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Constitution might have made when writing the Constitution. And you had &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;touched on the idea of inalienable rights. From what my understanding &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of inalienable rights are, that there is an assumption that a belief in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a higher power is essential for the understanding or the belief in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inalienable rights. So, A, my question is, is that an assumption the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;founding fathers had made? Second, more broadly, with that assumption &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;then does the First Amendment not protect freedom from religion?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. No, certainly not. The founders certainly based this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;right on natural law, the idea of a creator endowing people with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;inalienable rights. But then look at the Constitution. Even before we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have the Bill of Rights we have the Constitution, which says there &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;shall be no religious test for public office. Right from the get-go I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think this comes down into this idea of the pluralistic model. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pluralistic model doesn't push out religion from public life. You can &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;say, yes, the founders had a vision that religious liberty came from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;God. But at the same time, that religious liberty applies to everybody, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;believer and nonbeliever alike.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Any other questions? Well, I have one more.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Okay. [Laughter.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. I do wonder sometimes whether the friction between people &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of religious faith and people who may not have religious faith may &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sometimes partially be rooted in a real or perceived lack of advocacy &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on behalf of another, that is, the perception on the one hand is that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people of religious faith are not sort of robust enough in advocating &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for the freedom of belief and conscience of the people who don't have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious faith, and vice versa. I'm wondering, as you look back &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;through American law and public policy, some of the sort of laws and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;statutes and sort of policies that we've seen, the public writings, et &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cetera, from some of our founding fathers, were they just confined and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;constrained to people of religious faith, or did they in fact cover &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people who might not have religious faith?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Well, let me answer it this way: The Supreme Court's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been pretty clear on conscientious objector decisions that our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tradition of giving conscientious objection, which dates back to the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Civil War and the Quakers, nonetheless applies broadly to anyone with a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;belief in the immorality of fighting a war that is general as opposed &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to specific and opposed to a particular war. But anything, as they say, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that occupies the same space as traditional religious faith. So that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was a broad statement. It wouldn't cover everything, right? So any sort &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of moral conclusion you came to that this was an unjust war. If &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;somebody has a deep-seated belief that war was wrong, it's as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;comprehensive as to occupy the same space as religious faith, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Supreme Court said that will suffice.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And it's the same thing when we look at free exercise of religion. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;They look at what is sincerely held. Not does your belief kind of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reflect one of the major religions or even one of the minor religions. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;There is a famous case involving Jehovah's Witnesses, and one said she &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;could not make tank turrets. And the employer said, wait a minute, this &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;other Jehovah's Witness who works for me makes tank turrets. Point to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;me in the Jehovah's Witness documents where this violates your faith. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And the Supreme Court said, no. You can be a religion of one to have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that deep faith that we are going to protect. So I think that--mostly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it's just a question--we'll leave it to the philosophers to answer the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;rest of it.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. And maybe just to tease something out about it, is the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understanding you just mentioned--is that in large part because there &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;has been a long-held deference to the rights of individuals and groups &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to understand their own faith as they see fit, as opposed to having to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sort of demonstrate or prove something correct?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Yes. It goes back to Madison, right? Sort of conscience &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is king, right? It would be very strange indeed if we said we're going &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to define conscience according to how the government wants to define &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conscience. But, no, rather they give it a broad reading, looking from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the standpoint of the person claiming the right of conscience.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Any other questions from the audience?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I've actually been told that we're trying to get a bit of a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;technical fix. So maybe if we could take maybe a 5-minute break, and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;then we'll see if we can reconvene. Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    [Break.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Great. With our panelists in Canada and Europe rejoining &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;us, we'll get back to some of the questions that I had intended to ask. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;And again, we'll open it up again.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. So I get a break now? I can, like, go get coffee and--&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[inaudible]? [Laughter.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. There were several references that you made to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;secularism.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And Father Deacon Andrew, you referred to a quote, ``Self-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;proclaimed neutral secular order that has limited conscience rights in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the medical and legal professions in order to advance a prevailing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;secular orthodoxy, intolerant of genuine diversity.'' If this type of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;secularism is not neutral, what is it? A second question would be, is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there such a thing as neutral secularism?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I'm also wondering if you think that debates in the public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;square suffer to a certain extent from the lack of a self-awareness and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;openness about one's first principles? My impression from your comment &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about neutral secularism was that there is a perception of neutrality &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that doesn't actually reflect the reality.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So if you could answer those three and then, Dr. Van Bijsterveld, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I'll have some questions for you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Rev. Bennett. Sure. Well, I have a certain knowledge, adding onto &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Professor Van Bijesterveld's arguments about there being a secularism, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that there are various meanings of secularism. Charles Taylor has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;really charted those quite nicely in ``A Secular Age,'' that the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understanding of secularism has evolved. Now I would say, certainly in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Canada and maybe also in other Western democracies, there is a premise &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that secularism is neutral, that it appears at a neutral space where &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people of different beliefs can exist. But in fact, certainly in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Canadian case, what we're seeing is not that type of what I would call &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;open secularism, but rather a secular position that itself is a value &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;proposition and it has a particular faith, it has particular practices.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would say, in Canada certainly, the types of secularism we're &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;seeing in our institutions is a type of secularism that tolerates &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;diversity, but it's a prescribed diversity. As long as you're the sort &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of diversity that we like and fits with our definition of a diverse &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;society, then you're fine. However, if you hold beliefs or views that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;contravene or are different from that identified diversity, then you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are going to be on the outs within society. I think there's the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;possibility for the state to be neutral.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'm glad that in Canada we have a secular state. I wouldn't want a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;particular religious community being bound together with the state. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;That secular model is very good, but it needs to be, in Charles &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Taylor's way of expressing it, an open secularism where the state &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ensures that people of different religious beliefs, different belief &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;systems generally, are able to flourish within the body politic. A &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;closed secularism is where the state would dictate that there could be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;no public displays of religion.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think in Canada right now, a lot of communities, but I would say &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in particularly in my own Christian community, certainly Catholics and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;also Protestants of different traditions, I would say in many ways have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;accepted implicitly the privatization of public faith, that there has &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been a willingness to back away from the public square in order to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;embrace this desire for tolerance, a desire to have a neutrality. In &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fact in backing away of the public square and into the comfortable pew, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;let's say, where religious practice is simply something for the place &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of worship or for the home, that public square then is a vacuum, it's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;vacated by people of religious belief and there's a vacuum created, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which will be filled. When you have that vacant space, it means that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public debate is not being enriched by those particular religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;traditions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think a genuine pluralism is a very deep pluralism where you have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people of many different beliefs, many different philosophical &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;perspectives who are able to meet in the public square and engage with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;one another. I think that's what we should be striving for and that, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think, is at the heart of religious freedom in democracies.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Thank you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Van Bijsterveld, you spoke of at least two terms, programmatic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;secularism and procedural secularism, defining programmatic secularism &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as one that stands for fending off manifestations of religion in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public square and procedural secularism that is, as you put it, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fundamentally open to manifestations of religion in the public square, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the state itself being the secular. Are programmatic and procedural &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;secularisms limited to law, policy and regulation or do they extend &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;into other spheres, like culture?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. van Bijsterveld. Well, yes. First of all, I think it's very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;helpful, and the distinction is not my own, I derived it from the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;former archbishop of Canterbury. He says this procedural secularism, in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;which he defines a state as a community of communities where various &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;voices may ring, is where the state itself has an ideal where fills to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public domains. What you would see is that in Western European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries, the French laicite, the French system of church-state, in my &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;view, comes very close to that programmatic secularism. Whereas other &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries, for instance my own country, but also other European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries, are much more, in the sense, procedural secularism.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    He also talked about the word ``neutrality'' of the state and finds &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the word ``neutrality'' very complicated and also very confusing and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fuzzy because neutrality of the state does not mean you're value &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;neutral, states are not value neutral, states in its policies is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;continuously involved with all sorts of values. It's not value neutral.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But what could it mean? In my view, it would mean that the state &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;does not identify with one particular faith tradition. That seems to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;say it's neutral, it doesn't identify with one particular faith &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tradition. It can also mean that the state has a fundamental openness &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for all religions.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'm not so much in favor of using the words because it can mean so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;many things, ``neutrality.'' If you use it, you should be very clear in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;how you use it. In my sense, it certainly would mean that the state &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;does not identify with one particular tradition. Don't let us think &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that the state is value neutral, because the state isn't.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Mr. Treene, it's very striking in looking at the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;establishment clause, that is that the state will not establish a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religion or favor any particular religion, that it seems to stand &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;somewhat in contrast with what we saw from some of the earliest &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European settlers to the United States. I'm wondering, as someone who's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a bit of a historian when it comes to religious freedom and our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;founding documents, the Founders, of course, were bearing in mind the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;European experience where there was a very strong intermingling of sort &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of temporal power and faith and religion in a very sort of explicit and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;official way. Then, of course, they also were bearing in mind the early &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;American experience as well. Can you, to the extent that we sort of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have a sense of reflections on our own history here and that sort of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;early pre-United States period--was that something that they very much &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;were thinking about?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Sure. The presumption in Europe was that this is the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;1600s, 1700s and earlier was that, a godly king would make sure that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people within their kingdom followed the faith. That was not seen as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;controversial. As I said, it was sort of a milder theocracy that you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;saw in England where people were tolerated, but be taxed for support of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Anglican Church, you could not work on the Sabbath and heresy was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;punishable.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    When they passed the Virginia Statute on Religious Freedom, though, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that swept all that away and it was sort of a two-part thing. It was &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the defeat of a bill that would have supported clergy in the State of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Virginia, there would only be a few chosen sects that would have been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;supported, so it essentially established the Anglican Church as the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;main church and then a few others as well. And they struck down that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;law.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Then the statute banned any heresy laws, laws barring people who &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;were atheists from serving as executors of wills and a whole range of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;laws that were swept away to preserve that fundamental--again, that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;duality of we're not going to establish religion, but at the same time &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we're going to let people exercise their religion as their conscience &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;leads them and we will not tolerate any civil burdens or punishments.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. The next basket of questions has to do with the subjects &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of friendship and civic engagement.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. Van Bijsterveld had said that, ``for both public authorities &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and religious communities, it is important to get to know each other, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;if they do not already.'' One could argue that this could actually be &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;extended to sort of the full range of persons and relationships in a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;society.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    There's a very interesting and compelling book written by a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;political scientist--he's now at Brown, he was at Michigan when he &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;wrote it--named Ashutosh Varshney. It's called ``Ethnic Conflict and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Civic Life: Hindus and Muslims in India.'' He and his team looked at &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this massive dataset, focusing on violence between Hindus and Muslims &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the Indian context. A lot of the research that had been done to that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;point had focused on where violence had happened and why it had &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;happened. He was more interested in why it didn't happen in particular &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;places. You might have the same rumor, the same spark that had sort of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;prompted violence in another place, and yet in this other location, we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;didn't see it. So the question was, why?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    His thesis basically is that in these areas where the violence &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;didn't happen, there was very strong civic life. And what he meant by &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that very specifically was you had Hindus and Muslims who came together &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for cricket clubs or for book clubs or they had gotten tired of the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;local sanitation not working and had decided it was time to come &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;together and do something about it. So they got to know each other in a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;way where they weren't just sitting around and sort of having what we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;might traditionally think of as interreligious dialog. These were &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people who just kind of got to know each other and said as human &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;persons they had a common interest, maybe a common objective. Because &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;they got to know each other in an organizational context, when there &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was conflict they were able to organize each other, they were able to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organize very, very quickly.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So, Father Deacon and Dr. Van Bijsterveld, with that in mind, what &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is the role of friendship and working together on common interests or &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;working together on a common good specifically between people of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious faith and people of no religious faith to sort of engage in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the enterprise, as Father Deacon put it, building our common life so &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that our fellow human beings may flourish?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. van Bijsterveld. Are you asking me?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. I'm asking both of you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. van Bijsterveld. Okay. Well, thank you. Well, I think it is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very important indeed. Of course, friendship is maybe a lot to ask, but &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;at least it's important that people need each other and that they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;engage in professional relationships or other civic relationships &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;concerning civic activities. Because if you don't know each other, it's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very difficult to form a good understanding of the other. So, yes, I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think it is very important.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think it is also especially important also in the law. If you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;look at the history of church-state relationships in the Netherlands, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for example, we often think that they have evolved because the lawyers &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;got better understanding of the law and of religious freedom, and it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was implemented in a better way. Of course, that is true to a large &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;extent. In retrospect, we could also see these developments of more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relaxation of church-state relationships in the function of a societal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;element where different new religious organizations got to know each &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;other and got to know the state and the other way around. I think that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;is very important now where in Western Europe we have a large presence &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of Islam, but Islam is still very much unknown to us, and so are the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different groups. So my answer is yes.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Father Deacon?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Rev. Bennett. I would say I think there is, in the case of Canada, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and certainly I would hazard to guess it would be the same for the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States, we are a country that has, for most of our history, been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very diverse. You can walk down any street in this country and you just &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;see that diversity is a demographic reality. This is a very diverse &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;country. Friendship between people of different faiths and different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;beliefs is essential for that flourishing that I mentioned, for that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;flourishing to build a common life together.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now, if the official narrative or the narrative that is coming out &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of our institutions is that somehow, implicitly, religion can be a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;source of potential conflict and so, therefore, we can't have public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;expressions of religion because that emphasizes maybe too much &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;difference and, therefore, we're not going to be able to build some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;sort of perceived or false neutral society--if that's the case, then &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it's going to be very hard for us to encounter one another and to share &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our different faiths.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think this is particularly true in the university, in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;workplace, in the factory, wherever it might be. So often we are told &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;or we are conditioned socially to leave our religious faith at home. We &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have a little box on our table as we exit the house and we open the box &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;each morning, we drop our religious faith in there only to pick it up &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;when we come back home in the evening. When we're in the public space, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;when we're at the university, when we're in our office, God forbid we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;talk about our religious beliefs because it might offend someone or it &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;might lead to some sort of conflict. I think that is a very unfortunate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and very misguided approach.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Rather, we should be allowed to be our entire selves. Certainly, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this is a narrative that is dominant on a whole range of different &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;identities, whether we're talking--[inaudible]--certainly of a strength &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about allowing people to be themselves. That's the same for the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious self. We have to be able to live our lives, our religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;lives, publicly.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Historically throughout human history, our religious lives have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been lived publicly and that needs to be encouraged. Because when we &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;encounter one another and we encounter one another not in some sort of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;relativistic, mushy middle where there's some sort of false consensus, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;when we encounter one another and we can say ``I profoundly disagree &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;with your religious beliefs or I profoundly disagree with your moral &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;perspective, but I still recognize in you my neighbor and I still &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;recognize in you that you have a dignity as a human being and I am &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;called to be in a relationship with you so that we can build a society &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;together.'' That needs to be the narrative, rather than pushing &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious belief into the dark places, because that is not healthy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Yes, just to respond to that, I agree, there's a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;temptation to think that the more we allow for religious expression and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious liberty, we're going to end up with more religious conflict &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as people knock against each other in the public square. Actually, the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;data suggests otherwise.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Tim Shah at Georgetown University, a sociologist, has done a lot of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;work on this. If you plot out the levels of religious conflict in a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;country and you also looked at the level of religious liberty, what you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;actually find is, in general, there are a few outliers--but the more &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;freedom you have, the less social conflict you have between religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;groups. It's those countries that try to tamp down on religious freedom &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that end up having the greatest interreligious conflict.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. I know that one of the legal questions that has come up &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the last decade, 15-plus years in particular, has been this question &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of federal grants going to faith-based entities, particularly faith-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;based organizations. And the charge has been that this is a violation &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of the establishment clause, that the government is essentially &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;weighing in.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Is it that? Or is it ensuring that faith-based entities are able to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;compete for grants just as any other entity, whether secular or not?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Well, to go back to something that Dr. Van Bijsterveld &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;said at the beginning, we said tension between religious equality &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;arguments and religious autonomy, this one involves both: The idea that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a religious group shouldn't have to compromise its beliefs and, say, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;set up a secular parallel organization to carry out social works, that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it can integrate those. That's the autonomy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    But also, the equality argument is, if they're offering a secular &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;service--a homeless shelter, a jobs program--shouldn't the religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organization be equal in coming forward with a plan that they think is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;effective? And can't the government, if it's a secular program, fund &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;it, even if it's run by a religious group? That's something that the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Bush administration, the Obama administration, the Trump administration &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have all embraced. This initiative has continued through all three of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;those administrations.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    And I'd be very curious to see how that's handled in Canada and in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the Netherlands. My take is that, generally, other countries aren't as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;cautious about government funding in those situations.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Yes. If the two of you would like to respond to that, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that would be great.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Rev. Bennett. Well, certainly in the Canadian case, separation of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;church and state is not a constitutional principle in Canada. We don't &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;have the non-establishment clause or the free-exercise clause. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Certainly, freedom of religion or conscience in the Charter of Rights &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and Freedoms would be sort of rough equivalency of the free-exercise &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;clause. But in Canada you will have provincial governments, municipal &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;governments, the Federal Government providing support to a variety of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;faith-based institutions. Certainly in the province of Ontario, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;taxpayer dollars are used to support a very wide and large network of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;publicly funded Catholic schools in the province. That's been there for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a considerable period of time.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I would say that there's a fairly well-established series of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;programs for federal funding and provincial funding where faith-based &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;groups can obtain funding to support, in many cases, explicitly faith-&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;based activities. We certainly have, as in the United States, a wide &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;array of public holidays that are oriented to the Christian calendar. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;People are being paid to not be at work those days. That's another &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;example that I think often gets overlooked in the United States.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. And Dr. Van Bijsterveld, any reflections on the European &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;context?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. van Bijsterveld. Yes. If I may take that situation as an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;example, it's a fairly highly developed social welfare state where the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;state, of course, plays a very strong role in the redistribution of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;finances for public goals. The basic rule is that if the state gives &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;subsidies for carrying out the activities that it wants to promote, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;then faith-based organizations should not be excluded on the basis of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;their faith, only when it compounds very specific differences, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;functional differences, then a difference may be made. But not on the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;basis of faith.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Maybe for an American audience, it's also interesting to say that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;our whole organization of our educational system shows this basic &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;understanding very much. We have a dual system where state education &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and public education exists next to private education and private &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;education is practically 100 percent also conventional education. The &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;states raise funds for public education, public schools, but also for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;those private conventional schools. Of course, those private &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conventional schools are subject to most regulations that the state &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;schools are subject to as well, of course with the exception of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;respectful religious identity.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Now what we've seen with the retreat of the social welfare state &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;somewhat in the financial domain, they have these cooperation &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;arrangements also exist. We even see new forms of cooperation between &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;states and the church exist also on a financial level.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Rev. Bennett. I think just to add to that, in the immediate case, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;we have seen increasing tensions around the role that particularly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;provincial funding for Catholic education and especially there have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;been some fault lines that have been drawn over the last little while.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Also, with private schools that receive virtually no state funding, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there was a very famous case that went up to the supreme court of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Canada involving an independent Catholic high school, Jesuit high &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;school, in Montreal, Loyola High School. The provincial government in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Quebec brought in a new curriculum on teaching basically values and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;ethics that was very--again, to use the word--neutral in that you could &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not approach it from a particular faith perspective. This curriculum &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;was imposed on all schools across the province. Loyola said ``we will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;not teach this according to the model that you've put forward, we will &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;teach it from a Catholic perspective, we're not going to teach that all &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;faiths are equal, we believe that there is a preeminence for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Catholicism because that's what we confess.'' The province took them to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;court. In the end, the supreme court of Canada found in favor of Loyola &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;High School and said that as an independent Catholic school they had a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;right to teach their students about their particular Catholic faith, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;regardless of what the province had to say about it.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    There are, even in a very strong social welfare state like Canada &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;or the Netherlands, there are some fault lines emerging, and certainly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;here in Canada.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Just on the subject of federal funding, we have a bit of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;a different legal regime in the United States. There is, both for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;funding purposes, for development, and also for activities in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;United States, there is an explicit prohibition on the use of those for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious purposes, correct?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. We don't want to get into all the legal niceties, but &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;there's a difference we have between direct aid, which is the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government giving money to an organization directly, choosing a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;provider, like saying you have a good homeless shelter, I'm going to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fund you. If that's the case, it has to be a purely secular program.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    If, however, it's an indirect aid, like we say we're going to give &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people job training scholarships or a piece of paper that lets them get &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;job training and they want to take that to any job training that they &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;choose. Salvation Army has a program that integrates ministry and drug &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;treatment and job training and so forth, that's fine as long as it's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the person's choice to take that and indirectly give it to a religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;purpose. That's getting into the niceties of American law.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. We have a question from the audience.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. I was just wondering, all three of you have spoken &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;about the importance of, one way or the other of whether we like &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;neutrality or not, the government not taking sides in religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;controversies--you know, not writing prayers for schools and so on. I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just looking in this pamphlet of the 68 countries listed among the OSCE &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;participating States and their partners. I don't know about a lot of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;them, but I have in my head at least 26 of them don't at all fit that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;model. So I was just wondering--and even if you go back as recently as, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;say, when President Reagan was saying that Engel v. Vitale was wrongly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;decided and that there should be still prayers allowed in American &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public schools. Most of our own history in this country doesn't seem to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;reflect that, a lot of these other countries don't.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I was just wondering, for the three of you, from the point of view &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of international religious freedom as promoted by the Helsinki Accords, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;how important, even if you think that it's better to have a government &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that doesn't take sides in these discussions, how important do you &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;think it is for the human right of religious freedom that the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government not takes sides in religious questions? Or is it licit for a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government to hold one particular religious tradition or set of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;traditions in a public place of honor and give it place over others?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. And if you could--your name and affiliation?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Sorry. Dan Burns, Catholic University of America.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Rev. Bennett. Sure. That's a very good question. As was raised &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;earlier on, there are various types of state systems in relation &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;between religion and the state.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I think, certainly as a Canadian, we come out of the British &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;tradition very strongly. In the United Kingdom right now, there are two &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;established churches--there's the Church of England and the Church of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Scotland. They're both established, and so there's a precedence for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;them, particularly the Church of England, with bishops sitting as &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;spiritual peers and as lords. There's a particular preeminence for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Church of England schools and so forth.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    The United Kingdom over its history has been able to fairly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;successfully evolve into a state where you have an established church, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;yet there is a very strong pluralism and respect for religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;difference. I think that model is acceptable as long as there is that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;respect for pluralism and the state is, while being tied to a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;particular church or a particular faith, it does respect the rights of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;all of its citizens to live out their faith freely, both privately in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;terms of worship and their practices at home, but also publicly, to act &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;on that faith in the public square.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    When you look at it sort of through history, very often, certainly &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in the case of the church, when the church and the state have been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;fused, it's usually in the end not been that good for the church, but &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the state certainly hasn't suffered. I would argue, from my own &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;perspective, from the perspective of the Canadian experience, that it's &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;good not to have a particular established religion, but rather that the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;state should be very broad in its understanding of religious freedom &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;and should be very respectful to those citizens who do want to have &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religion playing a central role in their lives, again, publicly and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;privately.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    There needs to be greater breadth than there is currently for a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;state such as Canada. There needs to be a much broader understanding of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;religious freedom rather than a narrowing as we're seeing.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Treene. Yes, I would say in the U.S. context, the Founders in &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;this respect, like in so many other respects, were both idealistic and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;pragmatic. The idealistic vision is conscience, protection of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conscience, and they decided, looking back at history, established &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;churches tended to infringe conscience. I don't think it's the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;establishment clause itself is a fundamental principle the way that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;conscience is, but it's seen by the Founders as that which will lead to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the protection of conscience the same way many of our liberties are, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;how they designed the United States, the Government, and divided the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;powers. There's nothing in principle about division of three branches &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;of government that leads to liberty, but the ultimate goal was the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;preservation of liberty and true democracy.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Dr. Van Bijsterveld?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Dr. van Bijsterveld. Yes. In Europe, of course, our situation is &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;quite different from the United States. In many countries, there are &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;stratified systems of a church-state relationship. And the ultimate &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;example is, of course, a country where there is an established church. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;We have various countries like that in Europe. England has been &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;mentioned as an example, but also Denmark or Greece. Among them, those &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;countries are quite different. For instance, in England the state and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;church are really two different entities--the state and the Anglican &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Church--but there are a number of connections between them, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;institutionalized connections. In Denmark, for instance, it's very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;difficult to distinguish the established church from the state as an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;organization. In Greece, it's different altogether.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Apart from those state churches, there are also stratified systems &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;in which the states cooperate with particular churches or give some &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;churches a more elevated status. Usually, that is a system that is open &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;for all churches who fit the particular requirements.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I agree also with Andrew when it says that the issue is not so much &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;if there is a stratified system or whether there is an established &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;church. The basic issue is, given the system, is there real religious &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;freedom and also equality regardless of religion?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. Thank you. We'll have one last call for questions from &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the audience and then we'll wrap after that.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Hi. I have a question for Mr. Bennett, although, as far &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as I understand, he's looking at my back. So that's really rude of me, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I'm really sorry. [Laughs.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    My name is Ann Sineva. I am working on government affairs and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;public policy here in D.C. with the Church of Scientology National &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Affairs Office.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    It's good to see you, Mr. Bennett, again in your new capacity.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Rev. Bennett. Nice to see you.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Questioner. Yes, I have a question about mostly civil society &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;because there was a lot said tonight about church versus the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;government. I want to challenge you on something you said earlier &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;today. Actually, I would be very honored if other panelists commented &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;as well, but the reason why I'm singling out Mr. Bennett is because he &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;said something earlier, which I'm paraphrasing slightly, but you said &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that in a truly diverse, pluralistic society, people would live with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different theological and ethical views. I wanted to challenge you on &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the point about ethical and see if you had more to say on that and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;could elaborate. Because I believe that if we had a society built with &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;people that had completely different ethical views and no agreed-upon &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;moral code, then it would no longer be a community, a society.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    So, obviously, the Supreme Court takes cases concerning ethical &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;matters and Mr. Treene deals with that constantly in his work. I'm &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;curious to see your perspective as a religious leader, what do you tell &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;your congregation? Where is the common-sense ground there between our &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;differences, but also ethical points that we could survive on together?&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Rev. Bennett. Yes, very good question. Thank you for the point. &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Just by stating that, obviously, I'm a Catholic, I'm a deacon in the &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church, and so I believe that what I hold to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be true, both in terms of my theology, in terms of my ethical view and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;my moral views that stem from that theology and from a Christian &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;anthropology, I believe that to be true. I believe it to be true not &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;just for me, but I believe it to be true for all of you. It's a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;universal and objective truth, ethics and so forth. I think that as a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;society, we should strive to have a common ethic and a common set of &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;moral beliefs that champion the whole dignity of the human person.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I'm also part of a society. There are going to be people who &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;disagree with me. So then, how do we go on? I think we have, again, an &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;open public square where I have the ability as a Catholic to try and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;convince others of the truth of my belief. If, however, the public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;square becomes tightened and if it's constrained to me and I can no &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;longer do that, then I'm going to be frustrated in my citizenship and &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I'm going to probably begin to retreat.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    It's not that I have a relativistic approach to ethics. I believe &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that the ethic that I profess and try to live as a Christian, as a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Catholic, is true. I believe it's objectively and universally true, but &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;I need the ability in the public square to express that. And when I &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;come up against people that have different moral, ethical, theological, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;philosophical beliefs, I need to be able to dialog with them. I need to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be able to engage with them. And I need to see in them a common &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;humanity with me.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    We need common humanity and we need to be able to build a society &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;based on that common humanity, but also recognizing that there are very &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;different belief systems out there and a lot of us are going to claim &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;that our belief systems are true. That's the nature of society--it's a &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;very messy business, but there has to be that space in the public &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;square to engage with one another and to have the ability to convince &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;the other.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Mr. Hurd. I want to thank our panelists.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    I want to thank those of you who came here today, those of you that &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;are watching online, and also a special thanks to my colleagues, to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;Jordan, our hearing coordinator, to Stacy, our communications director, &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;to Cade and Thea, our fellows, and Alexa and Cecilia, our interns, for &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;helping put this together.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    This was certainly not intended to be comprehensive--impossible to &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;be so in so short a period of time--but hopefully it has added &lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;something to the conversations that are happening off the Hill.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Thank you. [Applause.]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;    Whereupon, at 4:16 p.m., the briefing ended.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                          [all]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            This is an official publication of the Commission on&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                    Security and Cooperation in Europe.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  This publication is intended to document&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  developments and trends in participating&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  States of the Organization for Security&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                     and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE).&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;           All Commission publications may be freely reproduced,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            in any form, with appropriate credit. The Commission&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            encourages the widest possible dissemination of its&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               publications.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                  &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;SUP&amp;gt;&amp;lt; &amp;lt;/SUP&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                      www.csce.gov       @HelsinkiComm&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 The Commission's Web site provides access&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                 to the latest press releases and reports,&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                as well as hearings and briefings. Using the&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;         Commission's electronic subscription service, readers are&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;            able to receive press releases, articles, and other&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;          materials by topic or countries of particular interest.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                          Please subscribe today.&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;&amp;lt;/pre&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/info&gt;
</intro>
</Hearing>
