<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<Hearing HearingID="29492">
    <intro>    &lt;info&gt;[House Hearing, 115 Congress]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;[From the U.S. Government Publishing Office]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                         [H.A.S.C. No. 115-88]&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                     ____________________________&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                HEARING&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                   ON&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                   NATIONAL DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                          FOR FISCAL YEAR 2019&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                                  AND&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;              OVERSIGHT OF PREVIOUSLY AUTHORIZED PROGRAMS&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;info&gt;                               BEFORE THE&lt;/info&gt;
    &lt;committee_name&gt;COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES&lt;/committee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                        HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
                     ONE HUNDRED FIFTEENTH CONGRESS
                             SECOND SESSION
                               __________
&lt;/option&gt;
</intro>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON STRATEGIC FORCES HEARING&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                                   ON
  FISCAL YEAR 2019 BUDGET REQUEST FOR NATIONAL SECURITY SPACE PROGRAMS
                               __________
                              HEARING HELD
                             MARCH 15, 2018
                           _________ 
                U.S. GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING OFFICE
29-492                    WASHINGTON : 2019     
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;SUBCOMMITTEE ON STRATEGIC FORCES&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                     MIKE ROGERS, Alabama, Chairman
DOUG LAMBORN, Colorado               JIM COOPER, Tennessee
DUNCAN HUNTER, California            SUSAN A. DAVIS, California
MO BROOKS, Alabama                   RICK LARSEN, Washington
JIM BRIDENSTINE, Oklahoma            JOHN GARAMENDI, California
MICHAEL R. TURNER, Ohio              BETO O'ROURKE, Texas
MIKE COFFMAN, Colorado               DONALD NORCROSS, New Jersey
BRADLEY BYRNE, Alabama               COLLEEN HANABUSA, Hawaii
SAM GRAVES, Missouri                 RO KHANNA, California
JODY B. HICE, Georgia
                Sarah Mineiro, Professional Staff Member
                         Leonor Tomero, Counsel
                           Mike Gancio, Clerk
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
    <Directory>
    &lt;table-of-content&gt;C O N T E N T S&lt;/table-of-content&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;STATEMENTS PRESENTED BY MEMBERS OF CONGRESS&lt;/Speakers&gt;
</Directory>
    <subcomitteeComposition>
    &lt;subcomittee_name&gt;Subcommittee on Strategic Forces...............................     1&lt;/subcomittee_name&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Hon Mike Rogers&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;a Representative from Alabama Chairman&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;witnesses&gt;WITNESSES&lt;/witnesses&gt;
    &lt;Witness&gt;Hon Kenneth P Rapuano&lt;/Witness&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Assistant Secretary of Defense for Homeland Defense and Global Security Department of Defense Raymond&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;APPENDIX&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;Speakers&gt;Prepared Statements:&lt;/Speakers&gt;
    &lt;peopleSpeaker&gt;Hon Kenneth P Raymond Rapuano&lt;/peopleSpeaker&gt;
    &lt;peopleinfo&gt;Gen John W Rogers Hon Mike Sapp&lt;/peopleinfo&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Subcommittee on Strategic Forces,&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                          Washington, DC, Thursday, March 15, 2018.
    The subcommittee met, pursuant to call, at 4:30 p.m., in 
room 2118, Rayburn House Office Building, Hon. Mike Rogers 
(chairman of the subcommittee) presiding.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;      ALABAMA, CHAIRMAN, SUBCOMMITTEE ON STRATEGIC FORCES
    Mr. Rogers. Good afternoon. I want to welcome everybody to 
this hearing of the Subcommittee on Strategic Forces and our 
hearing on the 2019 budget request for national security space 
programs.
    Unfortunately, as everybody in the room now knows, we were 
interrupted by votes, and we are an hour behind starting off. 
So for the sake of not keeping you all here all night, I am 
going to submit my opening statement for the record, and the 
ranking member has told me that he is going to submit his 
opening statement for the record, too.
    So we will go straight to your opening statements. And I 
would ask that each of you have 5 minutes. Your entire 
statement will be accepted into the record, so if you would 
just summarize it, we will get to questions and answers and 
finish this session and go to the classified section 
immediately after that.
    So, with that, thank you all for being here. I know it 
takes a lot of time and energy to prepare for these things, but 
it really helps us. We really need to hear your thoughts at 
this time of year.
    So, with that, I will recognize General Raymond.
    Well, first let me recognize we have General Raymond with 
us today, Betty Sapp from NRO [National Reconnaissance Office], 
and the Honorable Kenneth Rapuano.
    We will start with General Raymond for your opening 
statement. You are recognized.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Appendix on page 19.]
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                         SPACE COMMAND
    General Raymond. Thank you.
    Chairman Rogers, Ranking Member Cooper, distinguished 
members of the subcommittee, I am honored to appear before this 
committee.
    And this time it is my first time being able to testify in 
front of you in my dual hat as the Air Force Space Command 
commander and as the Joint Forces Space Component commander, a 
component of U.S. Strategic Command. I have the absolute 
distinct privilege of leading and representing both the Air 
Force and joint space personnel, who underpin successful global 
operations for our joint force and our Nation.
    As I have stated previously, I am increasingly convinced 
that we are at a strategic inflection point and that we must 
accelerate our preparations to protect and defend against a 
conflict that begins in, or extends to, space, and that is 
exactly what we are doing.
    Today's space capabilities are the foundation of power 
projection and fuel our joint force lethality. A high-end 
conflict may begin in our domain, which will require us to 
fight for space superiority.
    As a component of United States Strategic Command, I would 
be remiss if I didn't echo the words of my boss, General Hyten, 
to say that our force is fully prepared to deter and, if 
necessary, to respond, and win, if deterrence were to fail.
    As our National Security Strategy states, the United States 
considers unfettered access to and freedom to operate in space 
to be a vital interest. Our National Defense Strategy clearly 
articulates that the central challenge to the United States 
prosperity and security is the reemergence of long-term 
strategic competition.
    Space is a warfighting domain, just like air, land, and 
sea. This budget is aligned with the National Defense Strategy 
to meet our warfighting imperatives necessary to compete, 
deter, and win. This budget marks a bold shift towards an 
increased focus on space superiority in a contested 
environment.
    Specifically, we are enhancing our space situational 
awareness and our ability to command and control. We are 
shifting towards more defendable architectures. We are 
investing in tests and training infrastructure to further 
enhance our readiness. And, finally, we are enhancing our 
partnerships with the intelligence community, our allied 
partners, and the commercial space industry.
    I thank you for your support, and I look forward to working 
with Congress as we continue to focus on our national security 
space posture.
    I am privileged, absolutely privileged, to be here with my 
distinguished colleagues on the panel this afternoon, and I 
look forward to your questions. Thank you.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;the Appendix on page 21.]
    Mr. Rogers. Thank you, General.
    The Chair now recognizes Betty Sapp, Director of the 
National Reconnaissance Office.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;                     RECONNAISSANCE OFFICE
    Ms. Sapp. Thank you, Chairman Rogers, Ranking Member 
Cooper, and distinguished members of the committee. It was a 
great pleasure to host you and your committee members out at 
the NRO, and it is a great honor for me to be here today.
    The NRO has a very clear and a very critical mission for 
the Nation: We provide the space-based ISR [intelligence, 
surveillance, and reconnaissance] capabilities necessary to 
assure the U.S. an information and operational advantage.
    The NRO is structured for success. We are small and 
streamlined with end-to-end mission responsibility. We have 
enjoyed success in all aspects of that end-to-end mission. Our 
research and development team has developed and matured the 
next-generation technology necessary to stay ahead of changing 
targets and threats, fill current mission gaps, and develop new 
partnerships. Our acquisition teams are delivering the 
capabilities our users need on time and within budget.
    In 2017, for the ninth consecutive year, we achieved a 
clean independent audit opinion, demonstrating our ability to 
properly manage and account for the resources entrusted to us. 
We had four successful launches last year, including our first 
on a SpaceX Falcon 9. Finally, and most importantly, we 
continued to deliver critical operational capabilities with a 
better than 99.7 percent reliability.
    Our fiscal year 2019 budget request will build on the 
successful history of delivering innovative overhead 
intelligence systems for national security with the resilience 
required for the threat environment we face. We are 
specifically focused on investments that will deliver and 
assure the space-based capabilities we will need in a future 
fight: more resilience, more capability and capacity, and more 
speed.
    Greater resilience continues to be a top priority. 
Processes and CONOPS [concept of operations] to protect our 
current on-orbit systems are being refined and tested, and our 
people are being trained to use them to full advantage. New 
systems will have resiliency features built in as an inherent 
part of their design.
    In a future conflict, resilient space must backstop and 
work in concert with resilient air assets. Our investments 
focus on achieving the capacity and the capabilities required 
by the IC [intelligence community] and the DOD [Department of 
Defense]. We are increasing persistence in the ``look rate'' 
from space, reducing the gaps currently exploited by our 
adversaries.
    Finally, we require more capacity and capabilities in 
space. They must be combined to deliver that critical 
information directly to warfighters at the tactical edge and in 
the fight, and it must be delivered when they need it. Enabled 
by advances in artificial intelligence, automatic target 
recognition, machine learning, and emerging technology, the NRO 
plans to do exactly that.
    Everyone at the NRO is focused on our mission: delivering 
innovative overhead intelligence systems for national security. 
The current and projected threat environment doesn't change our 
mission, it just makes it more challenging. The men and women 
of the NRO are more than up to that challenge.
    Thank you for your support, and I look forward to your 
questions.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Appendix on page 40.]
    Mr. Rogers. Thank you very much.
    The Chair now recognizes Kenneth Rapuano, Assistant 
Secretary of Defense for Homeland Defense and Global Security.
    You are recognized for 5 minutes. Thank you.
&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;DEFENSE FOR HOMELAND DEFENSE AND GLOBAL SECURITY, DEPARTMENT OF 
                            DEFENSE
    Secretary Rapuano. Thank you, Chairman Rogers, Ranking 
Member Cooper, and distinguished members of the subcommittee. 
It is an honor to appear before you today along with General 
Jay Raymond, Commander of Air Force Space Command and the U.S. 
Strategic Command Joint Force Space Component commander, and 
Ms. Betty Sapp, Director of the National Reconnaissance Office.
    Space is a warfighting domain, and just as in air, land, 
sea, and cyberspace, the Department of Defense must be prepared 
to address any and all threats to our national security. Space 
systems provide our joint force an unmatched ability to project 
power globally, respond to crises rapidly, strike swiftly and 
precisely, and command forces in multiple theaters of operation 
simultaneously.
    Our National Security Strategy and the National Defense 
Strategy prominently recognize the criticality of space and 
acknowledge the potential for conflict to extend into space.
    Our new National Defense Strategy [NDS] charts the course 
for how DOD will contribute to each of the National Security 
Strategy's four national interests. Under the new NDS, long-
term strategic competition with China and Russia are the 
principal priorities for the Department. Addressing the 
challenges posed to our preeminence as a space power is 
fundamental to that effort.
    Today's potential adversaries and competitors have studied 
how the U.S. joint force operates, and they are rapidly 
developing capabilities designed to challenge our freedom of 
action across all domains. Those potential adversaries view 
space as an area where they could weaken our advantage and 
cause cascading impacts on our sea, air, land, and cyber 
systems that rely on our space-based capabilities. Denial of 
U.S. space advantage is a key component of their strategy.
    With this budget, the Department is making critical 
investments in capabilities necessary to protect and defend the 
space domain to ensure the mission to compete, deter, and win 
in the face of growing challenges.
    The fiscal year 2019 budget request prioritizes activities 
to address the space threat and improves on the performance of 
our space systems. Our aim remains to deliver the space effects 
to enable the combat edge our Nation and our warfighters must 
have.
    We also recognize the important need for the Department to 
be organized and structured most effectively to deliver on our 
duty to protect the Nation and its vital interests. The 
Department must accelerate, and is accelerating, its response 
to the changing dynamics of space.
    The Deputy Secretary of Defense has heard Congress' 
concerns, and consistent with the NDAA [National Defense 
Authorization Act] for Fiscal Year 2018 has already taken 
action through interim implementation guidance and looks 
forward to completing the directed studies and changes that may 
be required.
    The Department's partnership with Congress is and will 
remain absolutely critical to our success. To that end, I 
remain grateful for this subcommittee's strong support and 
interest in this vital area and its advocacy to dissuade 
aggression and establish a lethal force with the unmatched 
ability to prevail in, from, and through the ultimate high 
ground of space.
    I look forward to your questions. Thank you.
&lt;/option&gt;
</subcomitteeComposition>
</Hearing>
